<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Ensuring Minimal
               Computing Serves Maximal Connection</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Grant <dhq:family>Wythoff</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-->https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6605-9596</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Princeton University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>gwythoff@princeton.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Grant Wythoff is the Digital Humanities Strategist at Princeton University. His teaching and research areas include media theory, speculative fiction, and community technology. Grant is the co-founder of Philly Community Wireless, the founding editor of Startwords, and author of The Perversity of Things: Hugo Gernsback on Media, Tinkering, and Scientifiction (University of Minnesota Press).</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000596</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->2</idno>
         	<date when="2022-06-25">25 June 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2022-08-02" who="BRG">fixed encoding errors</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>Originally devised as an insult by Richard Wollheim, the term <q>minimalism</q>
               described a 1960s movement that foregrounded the relationship between an art object and
               its museum viewer. Today, minimalism is the guiding ethos for a surprising variety of
               pop cultural phenomena, from belongings that spark joy to
               contemplative practice that increases mindfulness. This article first takes a broader
               view of minimalism to register several problematic echoes of minimal computing among
               digital detoxers and disaster survivalists in intensities ranging from Luddism to
               asceticism. Attention needs to be given to these echoes, especially when valorizing DIY
               infrastructures built out of necessity by Indigenous, poor, or coastal communities and
               out of privilege by doomsday preppers. Second, this article asks what becomes of minimal
               computing now that we have seen the vital importance of maximal connection during the
               COVID-19 pandemic. Do arguments for minimalism still hold in a socially-distant,
               unevenly-connected world? I argue that it will be important to reframe the digital
               minimalist conversations of the 2010s for the demands of digital equity in the 2020s.
               Going forward, we should ask: which of these competing claims to minimalism — as a form
               of attention, mindfulness, and agency — are compatible with maximal connection, with
               maximal choice, with maximal investment in communities and infrastructures? And when we
               hold up minimalism as a virtue, is that virtue a property of particular tools or
               specific techniques for using them? Finally, this article profiles the ways that
               academic conversations on minimal computing have independently taken root outside
               universities through grassroots organizing and activism under the banner of community
               technology. I close by suggesting ways that minimal computing can be led by community
               input, while also playing a role in public scholarship and community partnerships that
               extend existing academic research.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>This article first takes a broader
               view of minimalism to register several problematic echoes of minimal computing among
               digital detoxers and disaster survivalists in intensities ranging from Luddism to
               asceticism.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
     
        <body>
           <div>
        <head></head>
         <p>The question that has been at the heart of minimal computing — <quote rend="inline">What do we need?</quote> — may
            never quite land the same way again.<note> As Alex Gil and Élika Ortega frame minimal
               computing, <quote rend="inline">We prefer to (un-)define minimal computing around the question ‘What do
               we need?’</quote> <ptr target="#gil2016"/>.</note> The summer of 2020 found librarians asking
            researchers about books they needed to access, department chairs surveying faculty for
            their remote teaching needs, undergraduate students sharing leads on summer work after
            paid internships were cancelled, and graduate students turning CVs into resumes as the
            remains of the academic job market all but evaporated. As I write this, academics
            continue to hash out detailed scenario plans at universities whose fates seem to change
            by the day. But these approaches to what we need in academia, these finer-grained
            tactics and forms of exchange, have only now become possible to imagine. Not long ago,
            we found ourselves asking even more fundamental versions of the question: What do we
            need in order to communicate, to eat, to stay healthy, to keep communities intact?</p>
         <p>The same pandemic has affected everyone in remarkably different ways. But no one will
            soon forget the feeling of preparing in March 2020 for a crisis whose shape seemed to
            evolve in real time. I remember standing with my partner in a grocery aisle, wondering
            whether microwaveable or stovetop rice would be a safer bet if infrastructure
            maintainers could no longer report to work. Which utilities would last longer:
            electricity (delivered here in Philadelphia by a private company) or gas (a municipal
            utility)? The next day, I tried to reassure myself that it was just paranoia that led me
            to download PDFs of grocery checklists and CDC preparedness guides in case our Internet
            connection also went down. <quote rend="inline">Who knew what was true,</quote> says the protagonist of <title
               rend="italic">Severance</title> (2018), Ling Ma’s uncannily timed novel of pandemic
            survival in New York City:</p>
         <p><quote rend="block">The sheer density of information and misinformation at the End, encapsulated in news
            articles and message-board theories and clickbait traps that had propagated hysterically
            through retweets and shares, had effectively rendered us more ignorant, more helpless,
            more innocent in our stupidity. <ptr target="#ma2018"/></quote></p>
         <p>The actuality of what communities experienced in the following months — checking on
            neighbors, refreshing news feeds, delivering groceries, shuffling endless Zoom calls —
            was nothing like the dystopian imaginaries that led us to go with the stovetop rice over
            the microwaveable. (Didn’t Snake Plissken cook over an open fire in <title rend="italic"
               >Escape from New York?</title>) Nor did it make the growing number of doomsday <q>prepper</q>
            billionaires — whose minds apparently always work this way — look any less silly
            <ptr target="#oconnell2020"/> <ptr target="#osnos2017"/>. As Laurie Penny writes on these techno-libertarians, who
            for years have been buying underground bunkers, bullets, and meals ready to eat: </p>
         <p><quote rend="block">Shit-hits-the-fan escapism — a big part of the alt-right imaginary — never predicted
            this. I have lurked in countless stagnant ideological Internet back alleys where young
            men excitedly talk about the coming end of civilization, where men can be real men
            again, and women will need protectors. How inconvenient, then, that when this
            world-inverting crisis finally showed up, we weren’t given an enemy we could fight with
            our hands (wash your hands). <ptr target="#penny2020"/></quote></p>
         <p>Instead, the past two years have crystallized the meaning of asking <quote rend="inline">What do we need?</quote>
            both as individuals and as communities, demonstrating how the question surfaces issues
            of connection, solidarity, and belonging (Who are <q>we</q>?) as well as different orders of
            value (Which needs get prioritized?). Countless forms of communal response to this
            crisis have quickly overshadowed the individualistic, doomsday prepper imaginary.<note>
               Hopefully, one legacy of this pandemic will be an understanding of the uselessness of
               preparing alone — preparing based solely on individual needs and isolated experiences
               of crisis — rather than preparing as a community.</note>
         </p>
         <p>Proponents of minimal computing have placed <quote rend="inline">What do we need?</quote> at the center of digital
            humanities practice, beginning with the formation of the Global Outlook::DH Minimal
            Computing Working Group in 2014. In a field often tempted by the discourse of
            innovation, minimal computing instead has pushed digital humanities conversations toward
            issues of technology access, participation, sustainability, stewardship, and equity. In
               <title rend="italic">New Digital Worlds</title>, Roopika Risam describes minimal computing
            as <quote rend="inline">a range of cultural practices that privilege making do with available materials to
            engage in creative problem-solving and innovation. These go by names like <emph>jugaad</emph> in India, <emph>gambiarra</emph> in Brazil, <emph>rebusque</emph> in Colombia, <emph>jus kali</emph> in Kenya,
               and <emph>zizhu chuangxin</emph> in China</quote> <ptr target="#risam2018" loc="43"/>. Risam shows that
            by foregrounding cultural practices rather than tools or platforms, minimal computing
            prioritizes a humanist approach to technology, including questions like: </p>
         <p><quote rend="block">How to repurpose existing technologies to reduce e-waste and engage with obsolescence in
            generative ways; how to conceptualize the difference between choosing to engage with
            minimal computing principles and doing so out of necessity; and how to examine the
            social impacts of computing through postcolonial lenses. <ptr target="#risam2018" loc="43"/></quote> </p>
         <p>Judging from the range of contributions to this issue of <title rend="italic">Digital
               Humanities Quarterly</title>, humanists have experimented with many permutations of
            digital methods and media theory to explore these questions over the past eight years.</p>
         <p>But the idea that I can’t shake — and the place I began when first proposing this essay
            — is that minimal computing often bumps up against problematic echoes of constraint,
            disaster, and isolation that circulate in far more public contexts than digital
            humanities discourse is capable of reaching. Some of these echoes can be found among
            groups animated by imaginaries of collapse, like the aforementioned disaster preppers
            and a recent subgenre of speculative fiction known as <soCalled>solarpunk,</soCalled> committed to far more
            generative stories of <quote rend="inline">ingenuity, generatively, independence, and community</quote> in the face
            of climate change <ptr target="#flynn2014"/> <ptr target="#konstantinou2019"/>. Meanwhile, self-described digital
            minimalists promote screen detoxes, mindfulness retreats, and tech fixes to reclaim
            control of our attention, ultimately advancing an asocial imaginary of disconnection and
            withdrawal. To cite the title of a recent documentary film, <quote rend="inline">offline is the new luxury</quote>
            <ptr target="#vanderhaak2016"/>. </p>
         <p>Still, other echoes can be found in movements that I see running in parallel to minimal
            computing, grassroots movements that bear important lessons for our academic
            conversations. This includes community technology organizations working to ensure
            digital equity in U.S. cities that still, in 2022, see less than fifty percent of
            residents in some areas connected to broadband. And it includes proponents of a
            decentralized web in response to the advance of data surveillance and tech industry
            overreach. </p>
         <p>But the imagination of constraint that generated solarpunk stories of climate resilience
            is not at all the same one that produced an injunction to limit screen time and reclaim
            attention. Nor are the arguments for living out a doomsday scenario in an off-the-grid,
            independent bunker commensurate with arguments for a decentralized, interdependent
            network topology. And yet all of these discourses are animated by competing visions of
            minimalism as a virtue. Across the political spectrum, the idea is in the air.</p>
         <p>How ironic then, that maximal digital connection is all that has kept and will keep so
            many going during this epoch of social distancing, as every happy hour and routine
            healthcare appointment, every first date and kindergarten class moved online. It’s far
            too early to describe this shift accurately, but even in the thick of things it’s clear
            that the pandemic has shuffled all previously settled distinctions between on- and
            offline, distance and proximity, connection and touch. What becomes of minimal computing
            now that we have seen the vital importance of maximal connection? Do arguments for
            minimalism still hold in a socially-distant, unevenly-connected U.S., let alone around
            the world? In order to take some steps toward an answer, I want to understand the
            problematic echoes that have informed the practice and reception of minimal computing.
            At the same time, I’d like to outline some of the emergent ways that I see minimal
            computing growing in this new world.</p></div>
      
     
         <div>
            <head>Community Technology and Mesh Networks</head>
            <p>In the context of COVID-19, asking <quote rend="inline">What do we need</quote> depends largely on the <q>we</q> in
               question. For Black, Indigenous, and people of color (BIPOC) in the U.S., the
               pandemic has exacerbated inequities that have plagued their communities for
               centuries. As Stacey Patton put it, <quote rend="inline">The pathology of American racism is making the
               pathology of the coronavirus worse.</quote> Higher rates of incarceration, homelessness,
               chronic medical conditions, and a lack of access to quality health care all leave
               Black Americans <quote rend="inline">more vulnerable to increased viral transmission, infection and death
                  during a pandemic</quote> <ptr target="#patton2020"/>.<note> Ruha Benjamin’s Pandemic Portal <quote rend="inline">tracks,
                  synthesizes, and situates the data on the racial dimensions of the pandemic within
                  historically and sociologically grounded interpretative frameworks</quote> <ptr target="#benjamin2021"/>.
                  </note> The disproportionate impacts of COVID-19 are seen not only in
               health outcomes, but also in employment — the unemployment rate for Black people rose
               in May 2020 while the employment rate for white people rebounded — as well as in digital inclusion. When schools closed at
               the beginning of the pandemic, roughly half of Philadelphia’s K-12 students lacked an
               Internet connection at home, rendering the Chromebook laptop lending program offered
               by the school district useless <ptr target="#hetrick2020"/>.<note> According to
                  Christian Hetrick and Dylan Purcell, <quote rend="inline">A 2019 survey by the School District of
                  Philadelphia found that only 45% of students in grades three through five accessed
                  the Internet from a computer at home, compared with 56% in grades six through
                  eight, and 58% for high school students</quote> <ptr target="#hetrick2020"/>. </note> And
               according to a March 2020 study by the Federal Reserve Bank of Philadelphia, 80% of
               White residents had broadband subscriptions, compared to only 53% of Black and 44% of
               Latinx residents in the Philadelphia-Camden-Wilmington metropolitan area <ptr target="#sanchez2020"/>.
               Internet accessibility in Philadelphia corresponds so closely with race that a
               map of broadband connection rates by neighborhood is essentially identical to a map
               of the city’s whitest neighborhoods.<note> See, for example, the following two
                  Philadelphia maps based on 2018 data from the US Census Bureau’s <title rend="quotes">American
                  Community Survey</title>: A map of disconnection rates <ptr target="#purcell2021"/> and a map of race
                  and ethnicity <ptr target="#statisticalatlas2018"/>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Unfortunately, Philadelphia is not unique among U.S. cities in this regard. When
               every classroom and doctor’s office moved online, when bearing witness to violence
               and injustice on the Internet became a matter of life and death, the twinned crises
               of global pandemic and state-sponsored, racist violence, symbolized by the murder of
               George Floyd, foregrounded the urgency of finally addressing digital inclusion in the
               U.S., almost a decade after the United Nations declared Internet access a fundamental
               human right <ptr target="#wired2011"/>. But in the absence of a competent policy response at either
               the federal or local levels in the U.S., communities have devised various forms of
               <q>making do</q> to fill the gaps. During the summer of 2020, across the country, groups
               organized to build networked computing infrastructures from scratch, using various
               combinations of hardware, software, policy stopgaps, community ownership, and
               cooperative decision-making <ptr target="#rosen2021"/>.<note> These community technologies respond
                  to the prevailing mode of Internet access in the United States; even though there
                  is broad agreement that the Internet is a <emph>public</emph> good,
                  neoliberal policies have only privileged <emph>private</emph> models of
                  Internet service, financializing the commons and withholding access and ownership
                  from exploited communities.</note>
            </p>
            <p>These projects center on the development of mesh networks. Greta Byrum, Co-Director
               of the Digital Equity Laboratory at The New School, explains:</p>
            <cit><quote rend="block">Instead of requiring a centralized hub to direct network traffic, a mesh operating
               system automatically searches for the best path for data to travel. Devices (even
               computers or phones) can become <q>nodes</q> or connecting points that enable data to hop
               from place to place until it reaches its destination. If a node fails or breaks, the
               network automatically routes around it through other nodes.</quote> <ptr target="#byrum2019"/> </cit>
            <p>In the context of the COVID-19 crisis, many groups have been using community-owned
               and operated mesh networks to share a single Internet connection among a broader
               group of users with comparatively little cost required.<note> See the <title
                     rend="italic">Community Technology Field Guide</title> for an overview of mesh
                  networks. It was co-authored by New America’s Open Technology Institute, The Work
                  Department, Allied Media Projects, and the Detroit Community Technology Project
                  <ptr target="#community2021"/>. </note> In New York, Community Tech NY
               developed DIY instructions for making their Portable Network Kit at home, as the
               in-person workshops they led for years became impossible.<note>See <ref
                     target="http://communitytechny.org/stepping-through-the-portal-ctny-the-pandemic/"
                     >http://communitytechny.org/stepping-through-the-portal-ctny-the-pandemic/.</ref>
               </note> In Baltimore, the Digital Harbor Foundation and Project WAVES worked with the
               public schools to <q>daisy-chain</q> the schools’ Internet backbone to neighboring homes
               with mesh radios <ptr target="#digital2021"/> <ptr target="#project2021"/>. And in several
               cities along the East Coast, bookmobiles, ice cream trucks, and satellite vans were
               repurposed as mobile WiFi hotspots resembling the 1970s Stanford Research Institute
               Packet Radio Vans: the first example of mobile networking. The Kingston Equitable
               Internet Initiative also expanded their network with one of these vehicles.<note>
                 See <ref target="https://keii.network/">https://keii.network/</ref>. For the SRI
                  packet van, see <ptr target="#computerhistorymuseum"/>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Like the <quote rend="inline">cultural practices . . . with available materials</quote> detailed in Risam’s
               description of minimal computing, community technology involves the construction,
               maintenance, and care of technical and community infrastructures alike <ptr target="#risam2018" loc="43"/>.
               Many of these mesh groups have learned from the foundational training curricula
               developed by the Detroit Community Technology Project, founded by Diana Nucera, who
               defines community technology as, <quote rend="inline">A principled approach to technology that is
               grounded in the struggle for a more just digital ecosystem, placing value on equity,
               participation, common ownership and sustainability</quote> <ptr target="#nucera2016" loc="15"/>. From the
               perspective of community technology, building mesh networks means not only
               maintaining the codebase and buildout, but also <quote rend="inline">fostering relationships of trust and
               cooperation among neighbors, who must work together to make decisions about network
               design, services, access protocols, security, and long-term sustainability</quote> <ptr target="#byrum2019"/>.
               Rather than parachuting in shiny new hardware, mesh network groups and
               community technologists host participatory design workshops and technical trainings
               that empower communities to maintain and grow their network connections in
               relationships of care. As Hi‘ilei Julia Kawehipuaakahaopulani Hobart and Tamara
               Kneese write in their introduction to an important new issue of <title rend="italic"
                  >Social Text</title> devoted to <q>Radical Care,</q> such forms of care have historically
               come to the fore<note> In the wake of 2020, I
                  highly recommend this special issue as a roadmap for the ways history can inform
                  collective practice now.</note></p>
            <cit><quote rend="block">when institutions and infrastructures break down, fail, or neglect. Reciprocity and
               attentiveness to the inequitable dynamics that characterize our current social
               landscape represent the kind of care that can radically remake worlds that exceed
               those offered by the neoliberal or postneoliberal state, which has proved inadequate
               in its dispensation of care.</quote> <ptr target="#hobart2020" loc="3"/></cit>
            
            <p>Here in Philadelphia, these conversations flourished among a working group composed
               of community organizers, technologists, academics, public school teachers, and City
               Hall staffers who came together during the early months of the COVID-19 lockdown.
               This Philly Community Wireless (PCW) project has been learning from the efforts of
               mesh groups in other cities, as well as from the history of past community technology
               efforts in Philadelphia. These include Wireless Philadelphia, one of the country’s
               first municipal WiFi providers that unfortunately dissolved soon after it was formed
               in 2004; Prometheus, a collective that built and advocated for independent, low-power
               radio and other wireless technologies throughout the 2000s; and Philly Mesh, an
               experimenter group that worked toward interoperability with mesh networks in other
               cities in the mid-2010s <ptr target="#breitbart2007"/> <ptr target="#dunbarhester2014"/> <ptr target="#phillymesh2021"/>.</p>
            <p>One thing we have learned at PCW by centering our conversations on community
               technology is that not all approaches to <q>minimalism</q> are compatible. For example, two very distinct versions of minimalism have emerged in our
               survey of mesh projects around the country, as well as within our own conversations.
               In the first version, decentralized networks, non-proprietary hardware, and open
               source software are prized for their ability to build truly independent networks. A
               decentralized web (DWeb) could minimize reliance on exploitative Internet service
               providers looking to sell user data, as well as minimize the surveillance harms that
               disproportionately impact BIPOC communities. The second version of minimalism instead
               emphasizes inclusion and access, regardless of the tools used to achieve them. In
               this version, access to the Internet is viewed as a fundamental human right. The
               Alliance for Affordable Internet — a global coalition of organizations working to
               reduce cost barriers to Internet access — further specifies that baseline
               connectivity is not enough and instead emphasizes <q>meaningful connectivity</q> as the
               standard. <q>Meaningful connectivity,</q> according to their definition, involves the
               following four <q>minimal thresholds</q>:</p>
            <list type="unordered">
               <item>Regular Internet use | minimum threshold: daily use</item>
               <item>An appropriate device | minimum threshold: access to a smartphone</item>
               <item>Enough data | minimum threshold: an unlimited broadband connection at home or a
                  place of work or study</item>
               <item>A fast connection | minimum threshold: 4G mobile connectivity <ptr target="#alliance2020"/>.</item>
            </list>
            <p>These debates will continue to evolve alongside the mesh networking technologies that
               animate them. As Rory Solomon details, technologists have only recently developed the
               routing protocols that make mesh networks scalable, in which every radio sends and
               receives packets of information simultaneously, minimizing <q>hops</q> between nodes while
               avoiding interference between all of that delicately interwoven traffic <ptr target="#solomon2020" loc="2–3"/>.<note> 
                  As Rory Solomon notes: <cit><quote rend="block">This process of relaying messages through
                  intermediaries is called routing, and a crucial part of building mesh networks is
                  the development and deployment of routing algorithms that optimize network
                  efficiency in terms of several possible variables, including: minimizing number of
                  intermediate steps or ’hops’ [between network nodes], minimizing time or cost of
                  message delivery, maximizing the quantity of overall throughput in the network,
                  performing well in the presence of high levels of message traffic or noise, and
                  perhaps most importantly, maximizing network resiliency, meaning the capacity of
                  messages to be successfully routed from sender to receiver even in the event of
                  lost intermediate links.</quote> <ptr target="#solomon2020" loc="2–3"/></cit></note> And so the kinds of political
               ideas emerging from mesh praxis — ideas about justice, equity, and privacy — will
               only become clearer as more communities in cities around the country begin to map
               their lines of sight and thread themselves together, node-by-node. It will be
               interesting to see whether the <q>minimal thresholds</q> of meaningful connectivity can be
               achieved through complex, experimental hardware, and whether that highly specialized
               hardware can be made responsive to community input and ownership.</p>
            <p>For now, the problem is that the non-proprietary hardware prized by one crowd
               presents yet another barrier to access in the eyes of the other, who prefers tools
               that easily connect people right out-of-the-box. And so the pursuit of
               decentralization on the one hand and meaningful connectivity on the other is a
               tension that seems present in many mesh communities. But the debate plays out
               differently depending on its context. In some cases, one form of tech activism
               gradually transforms into another when arguments for network independence and racial
               justice are found to be complimentary. In others, a mesh group splinters and factions
               end up pursuing different goals. This outcome is more likely to be the case when the
               group’s membership consists largely of tech and telecom employees volunteering their
               time to build experimental infrastructures without much input from the
                  community.<note> As many of us learned when building Philly Community Wireless
                  beginning in the summer of 2020, not all scholarship happens in the space of
                  publication and peer review. I am grateful to many people for conversations,
                  instruction, and advice on community technology praxis that informed this section,
                  including Adam Longwill, Addie Barron, Andrew Coy, David Johnson, Devren
                  Washington, Erica Kermani, Franca Muller Paz, Greta Byrum, Hannah Sassaman,
                  Heather Lewis-Weber, Helyx Horwitz, Houman Saberi, Jennifer Oxenford, Jonathan
                  Latko, Juliet Fink-Yates, Kate Goodman, Mark Steckel, Michael Major, Monique Tate,
                  Raul Enriquez, Rory Solomon, Sascha Meinrath, Stasia Monteiro, Tejas Gupta, and
                  Tithi Chattopadhyay. </note>
            </p>
            <p>What do we need? Clearly, it depends.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Minimalism as Austerity Chic</head>
            <p>Community technologists and advocates of the decentralized web each stake competing
               claims to <q>minimalism</q>: one draws attention to the minimal requirements necessary for
               human flourishing, while the other seeks to minimize the influence of corporations
               that extract profitable data from everyday life.<note> For examples of these two
                  different schools of thought, see the Community Technology Collective (<ref
                     target="https://www.ctcollective.org/">https://www.ctcollective.org/</ref>)
                  and Tim Berners-Lee’s new open source software project Solid (<ref target="https://inrupt.com/solid"
                     >https://inrupt.com/solid</ref>), in which <quote rend="inline">pods store
                  user data in an interoperable format and provide users with permissioning
                  controls.</quote></note> Working with members of both groups
               over the past year, I’ve found myself wondering what the concept and practice of
               minimal computing might offer these evolving debates. Does minimal computing offer
               its own competing school of thought? Or is it more of an umbrella descriptor for
               these interrelated approaches to tech justice?<note> My understanding of <q>tech
                  justice</q> is informed by the work of the Philly Tech Justice coalition, which
                  pushes back <quote rend="inline">against intrusive data collection and unnecessary camera
                     surveillance, and digital illiteracy and lack of technology access</quote> <ptr target="#phillytech2021"/>. </note>
            </p>
            <p>At the moment, it’s difficult to say. <q>Minimalism</q> is an incredibly diffuse idea
               circulating in so many different contexts that it’s often tricky to parse the weight
               that <q>minimal</q> holds when someone says <q>minimal computing.</q> Today, minimalism is the
               guiding ethos for a surprising variety of pop cultural phenomena, spanning everything
               from belongings that spark joy to contemplative practice that increases mindfulness
               <ptr target="#kondo2014"/> <ptr target="#crawford2016"/>. A minimalism of paring back and throwing things away can
               be found on Instagram and Pinterest: in mid-century modern furniture and lone potted
               plants against clean white subway tile backdrops, in sans serif fonts on bright,
               monochrome backgrounds with slogans reading <quote rend="inline">Own less stuff. Find more purpose</quote> and
               <quote rend="inline">The more you throw away, the more you’ll find.</quote> <note> For examples of this brand of
                  minimalism, see the Netflix film <title rend="italic">Minimalism: A Documentary About
                     the Important Things</title> (2016) and Instagram accounts like @minimalismlife.
                  For critiques of the self-help industry tied to this minimalist ethos, see
                  <ptr target="#brinkmann2017"/> and <ptr target="#cederstrom2015"/>.</note> But this aestheticized
               minimalism — a choice to pare back made by people who have everything they need — is
               a stark departure from the minimalism of necessity highlighted by practitioners of
               minimal computing. Taking a broader view of minimalism registers several problematic
               echoes of minimal computing among digital detoxers and disaster survivalists in
               intensities ranging from Luddism to asceticism. Attention needs to be given to these
               echoes, especially when valorizing DIY infrastructures built out of necessity by
               Indigenous, poor, or coastal communities and out of privilege by doomsday
               preppers.</p>
            <p>Minimalism was originally the name for an avant garde movement in 1960s art that
               foregrounded the relationship between an art object and its museum viewer. With
               techniques like prioritizing shape and scale over representation, artists associated
               with minimalism sought to project little more than objecthood from their sculptures
               and paintings. <quote rend="inline">What is at stake . . . is whether the paintings or objects in
               question are experienced as paintings or as objects,</quote> wrote Michael Fried, who
               preferred the term <q>literalist</q> to describe these conceptual works, in 1967. <quote rend="inline">Like
               the shape of the object, the materials do not represent, signify, or allude to
               anything: they are what they are and nothing more</quote> <ptr target="#fried1998" loc="151"/>. In the case of
               a minimalist sculpture, brushed aluminum is just brushed aluminum. Think of Donald
               Judd’s repeating cubes of identical size, Anne Truitt’s pillars broken by contrasting
               bands of color, Dan Flavin’s sculptural arrangements of fluorescent light fixtures,
               and Richard Serra’s massive, curved steel structures. At first, critics and artists
               alike applied a variety of terms to these works: literalist, cool, ABC, receptive,
               primary. But eventually, <q>minimalist</q> stuck.</p>
            <p>Critics writing about this cadre of 1960s artists emphasized the theatrical qualities
               of the museum goer’s experience in the presence of their works. The sculptor Robert
               Morris described <quote rend="inline">one’s awareness of oneself existing in the same space as the work .
               . . as he [<emph>sic</emph>] apprehends the object from various positions and under varying
               conditions of light and spatial context</quote> <ptr target="#fried1998" loc="153–154"/>. Minimalist sculptures
               tend to be either massive or scaled to the size of the human body. When massive,
               viewers have to back up and circle around the sculptures, participating in space and
               time as they take in the objects from multiple angles. When they are
               anthropomorphically scaled, like Tony Smith’s six-by-six-by-six foot cube <title
                  rend="italic">Die</title>, the sculptures possess an eerie presence: coming across
               one in an empty room feels like being surprised by someone you didn’t expect to be
               there.</p>
            <p>If minimalist art amounted to <quote rend="inline">a new genre of theater,</quote> as Fried wrote, it was a
               profoundly atomizing form of theater in which the viewer is confronted, distanced,
               and isolated: </p>
            <p><quote rend="block">That the beholder is confronted by literalist work within a situation that he [<emph>sic</emph>]
               experiences as his means that there is an important sense in which the work in
               question exists for him alone, even if he is not actually alone with the work at the
               time. . . . Someone has merely to enter the room in which a literalist work has been
               placed to become that beholder, that audience of one — almost as though the work in
               question has been waiting for him. <ptr target="#fried1998" loc="163"/> </quote></p>
            <p>This asocial theatricality couldn’t be farther from the communal experience of
               theater that Bertolt Brecht or Antonin Artaud advocated for, a theater that
               transformed its heterogeneous audience into a collective whole. For Michael Fried, if
               minimalism is a form of theater, it only admits an audience of one.</p>
            <p>The ubiquity of minimalist sensibilities today makes a lot more sense when seen in
               light of its roots in this 1960s conceptual art movement, with its sculptures that
               provoked atomization and isolation. For Kyle Chayka, minimalism today is <quote rend="inline">an
               inevitable societal and cultural shift responding to the experience of living through
               the 2000s,</quote> from the impossibility of owning a home and paying down debt to the
               vanishing likelihood of ever being paid a fair wage in a job that is secure. During a
               time when crises fade only as the next one begins, <quote rend="inline">flexibility and mobility now feel
               safer than being static, another reason that owning less looks more and more
               attractive. . . . It makes sense that millennials embrace minimalism. My generation
               has never had a healthy relationship with material stability</quote> <ptr target="#chayka2020" loc="14"/>.
               <note> As Chayka notes, <quote rend="inline">I began thinking of this universal feeling as the
                  longing for less. It’s an abstract, almost nostalgic desire, a pull toward a
                  different, simpler world. Not past nor future, neither utopian nor dystopian, this
                  more authentic world is always just beyond our current existence in a place we can
                  never quite reach. Maybe the longing for less is the constant shadow of humanity’s
                  self-doubt: What if we were better off without everything we’ve gained in modern
                  society?</quote> <ptr target="#chayka2020" loc="14"/>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The architect Pier Vittorio Aureli is less charitable in his description of
               minimalism as a form of <q>austerity chic.</q> In <title rend="italic">Less is Enough</title>,
               Aureli argues that the endless romanticization of minimalism in the 21st century is
               the result of the inhumane demands that capitalism has made of people since the
               industrial age:</p>
            <p><quote rend="block">Within the history of capitalism, <q>less is more</q> defines the advantages of reducing
               the costs of production. Capitalists have always tried to obtain <emph
                  >more</emph> with <emph>less</emph>. Capitalism is not just a process of
               accumulation but also, and especially, the incessant optimisation of the productive
               process towards a situation in which <emph>less</emph> capital investment
               equals more capital accumulation. Technological innovation has always been driven by
               the imperative to reduce the costs of production, the need for wage earners. The very
               notion of <emph>industry</emph> is based on this idea: to be <emph>industrious</emph> means being able to obtain the best results with
               fewer means. <ptr target="#aureli2014" loc="3"/></quote></p>
            <p>Because capitalism constantly demands that we do more with less, minimalism could
               serve as an invitation to ask why: why we should be content with austerity, where
               this injunction comes from, and what might be possible with more. Unfortunately,
               minimalism is instead broadly seen as a self-apparent virtue, a celebration of
               isolated individuals paring back the boundaries of their otherwise shared
               experiences.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>From Digital Minimalism to Digital Equity</head>
            <p>Digital minimalism has recently emerged as an offshoot of the broader minimalist
               imaginary in order to cope with ever-intensifying forms of precarity that affect our
               ability to maintain not just livable wages, but also uninterrupted trains of thought.
               Digital minimalists seek to reinforce the permeable membrane of their attention
               through mindfulness exercises, software settings, productivity apps, and other forms
               of tech fixes. Approaches in this area fall into a few different categories. First
               are the books that seek to identify and change the habits that lead users to
               constantly seek refuge in their phones. Proponents in this camp offer prompts like
               <q>spend time alone</q> and <q>hold conversation hours.</q><note> See also  <ptr target="#brabazon2013"/>, <ptr target="#clear2018"/>, <ptr target="#levy2017"/>, <ptr target="#newport2019"/>, <ptr target="#otto2016"/>, <ptr target="#perlow2012"/>, and
                  Stanford’s Ritual Design Lab <ptr target="#ozenc2021"/>. </note> A related group
               consists of tech industry employees and insiders who have seen the light and devoted
               themselves to fixing the social harms their algorithms have created. Former Google
               engineer Tristan Harris, for example, founded the nonprofit Center for Humane
               Technology to draw attention to the ways recommendation algorithms manipulate our
               cognitive biases in order to keep us scrolling. The group has begun a laudable
               campaign that pressures tech companies to pivot from business models built on
               cognitive exploitation by <quote rend="inline">creat[ing] market conditions for humane tech,</quote> albeit
               without a real road map for doing so <ptr target="#center2021"/>.</p>
            <p>A second category tries to solve surveillance capitalism with tech fixes. For their
               part, tech companies now allow users to seemingly calibrate their attention through
               options recently added to the system preferences of all major mobile platforms. These
               features are known as <q>Digital Wellbeing</q> in Android, <q>Screen Time</q> in iOS, and <q>Zen
               Mode</q> on OxygenOS. A digital minimalist might be further outfitted with gadgets like
               IRL Glasses with polarized lenses that block the images on screens and slabs of solid
               plastic called NoPhones that act as pacifiers for smartphone addicts. Digital
               minimalists can also choose from the Google Paper Phone, a paper printout folded like
               a zine containing all of the information you’ll need for the day and the Light Phone,
               an app-less device with an e-ink display that only calls and texts. If minimalism has
               become synonymous with the capitalist injunction to do more with less, it also
               promises that buying more will allow us to do less.</p>
            <p>A third group of digital minimalists draws from the medicalized discourse of screen
               detoxes and tech fixes used by both groups above. But they go one step further by
               attributing the 21st-century crisis of attention not only to overreach by the tech
               industry and its powerful algorithms but also to a certain moral failure on the part
               of users. Public philosophers James Williams and Matthew Crawford both describe
               attention as a battleground for human agency. And both seem almost nostalgic for an
               earlier era when humanity could rely on an <quote rend="inline">off-the-shelf package of religious and
                  cultural constraints</quote> to regulate our attention, agency, and values <ptr target="#williams2018" loc="21"/>.
               Williams writes, <quote rend="inline">In the twentieth century the rise of secularism and modernism
               in the West occasioned the collapse — if not the jettisoning — of many of these
               off-the-shelf packages of constraints in the cause of the liberation of the
               individual.</quote> Users of digital devices are now faced with <quote rend="inline">the self-regulatory cost of
                  bringing your own boundaries</quote> to attention <ptr target="#williams2018" loc="21–22"/>.<note> Williams
                  continues: <quote rend="inline">In many cases, this rejection occurred on the basis of philosophical
                  or cosmological disagreements with the old packages. This has, of course, had many
                  great benefits. Yet by rejecting entire packages of constraint, we’ve also
                  rejected those constraints that were actually useful for our purposes. When you
                  dismantle existing boundaries in your environment, it frees you from their
                  limitations, but it requires you to bring your own boundaries where you didn’t
                  have to before. Sometimes, taking on this additional self-regulatory burden is
                  totally worth it. Other times, though, the cost is too high</quote> <ptr target="#williams2018" loc="21–22"/>.</note> 
               For Crawford, <quote rend="inline">The left’s project of liberation led us to dismantle
               inherited cultural jigs that once imposed a certain coherence (for better and worse)
               on individual lives</quote> <ptr target="#crawford2016" loc="41"/>.<note> Crawford continues: <quote rend="inline">This created a
                  vacuum of cultural authority that has been filled, opportunistically, with
                  attentional landscapes that get installed by whatever ’choice architect’ brings
                  the most energy to the task — usually because it sees the profit potential</quote>
                  <ptr target="#crawford2016" loc="41"/>. </note> Both writers retreat into the Western philosophical
               canon for guidance amid our present <quote rend="inline">vacuum of cultural authority</quote> <ptr target="#crawford2016" loc="41"/>.</p>
            <p>Digital minimalism has emerged at a moment when the tech industry continues to invent
               new methods for transforming our habits and desires into profitable data. But most
               researchers understand this transformation not in terms of the absence of religion,
               but the presence of capitalism. These are the terms that Soshana Zuboff has
               persuasively developed in her work on <quote rend="inline">surveillance capitalism</quote> <ptr target="#zuboff2019"/>. Others
               describe the tech industry’s co-opting of our everyday behavior into new forms of
               value as a colonial process. Nick Couldry and Ulises A. Mejias see this digital
               extraction as an expansion of the ways colonialism has appropriated human life for
               centuries: <quote rend="inline">Colonialism’s sites of exploitation today include the very same West that
               historically imposed colonialism on the rest of the world. . . . What if the armory
               of colonialism is expanding? What if new ways of appropriating human life, and the
               freedoms on which it depends, are emerging?</quote> <ptr target="#couldry2019" loc="x"/>.
               Unfortunately, the self-help nature of digital minimalism is disconnected from a
               broader accounting of the tech industry’s collective, social impacts. Instead, much
               like the isolated, atomized viewer of a minimalist sculpture, digital minimalists
               emphasize the sanctity of an idealized, individual human experience without ever
               thinking to address the stratification of those experiences.<note> Laura
                  Portwood-Stacer argues that <quote rend="inline">individuals who consciously choose to abstain from
                  participation on the ubiquitous Facebook platform</quote> end up <quote rend="inline">framing refusal as a
                  performance of elitism, which may work against observers interpreting
                  conscientious refusal as a persuasive and emulable practice of critique.</quote> She
                  refers to this stance as <q>conspicuous non-consumption</q> <ptr target="#portwoodstacer2013" loc="1041"/>. See also <ptr target="#karppi2018"/>. </note>
            </p>
            <p>While some manuals are better conceptualized than others — especially Jenny Odell’s
               wonderful <title rend="italic">How to Do Nothing</title>, in many ways a parody of the
               genre <ptr target="#odell2019"/> — digital minimalism is largely an argument against technology
               that forecloses collective action. Digital minimalists often fashion themselves as
               21st-century Luddites. But as Megan Ward has argued, Luddism was originally an
               economic argument, not a self-help motto or personal virtue: <quote rend="inline">Refusing to be
               ceaselessly on-call may increasingly become the province of the wealthy and powerful,
               a return to an era when recreational time was a luxury of the elites rather than a
               social right for the masses</quote> <ptr target="#ward2017"/>.<note> On the post-WWII afterlives of
                  nineteenth-century Luddism, see <ptr target="#tierney2019"/>. </note> Unplugging or digitally
               detoxing doesn’t absolve us of any ethical entanglements at a time when gig workers
               don’t have the privilege to put their devices away, or when Black and Brown
               communities don’t have a say in whether they will be surveilled by facial recognition
               systems and disproportionately imprisoned by pretrial sentencing algorithms <ptr target="#ticona2015"/>.<note> 
                  Ticona conducts a comparative study of how workers in different
                  sectors manage the <quote rend="inline">entrance of mobile phones into the workplace . . . within a
                  marketplace where jobs are increasingly uncertain and insecure.</quote> She finds that
                  <quote rend="inline">service workers deployed strategies of everyday resistance in concert with their
                  ICTs to gain a feeling of autonomy within the power structures of their
                  workplaces. The knowledge workers deployed strategies of inaccessibility to resist
                  the work-extending affordances of their devices and decouple from work which
                  threatened to colonize too much of their lives. Both service and knowledge workers
                  deploy strategies that may obscure the institutional sources of their problems by
                  overindividualizing risk and responsibility</quote> <ptr target="#ticona2015" loc="509"/>. On pretrial
                  sentencing, see especially the Mapping Pretrial Injustice Project, a collaboration
                  between the Movement Alliance Project and MediaJustice, at <ref
                     target="https://pretrialrisk.com/">https://pretrialrisk.com/</ref>.</note> Ruha
               Benjamin, who details these and other forms of digital inequity in <title rend="italic"
                  >Race After Technology: Abolitionist Tools for the New Jim Code</title>, writes
               of</p>
            <cit><quote rend="block">Silicon Valley parents requiring nannies to sign <q>no-phone contracts</q> and opting to
               send their children to schools in which devices are banned or introduced slowly, in
               favor of <quote rend="inline">pencils, paper, blackboards, and craft materials.</quote> All the while I attend
               education conferences around the country in which vendors fill massive expo halls to
               sell educators the latest products couched in a concern that all students deserve
               access — yet the most privileged <emph>refuse</emph> it? . . . Social
               theorist Karl Marx might call tech personalization our era’s opium of the masses and
               encourage us to <q>just say no,</q> though he might also point out that not everyone is in
               an equal position to refuse, owing to existing forms of stratification.</quote> <ptr target="#benjamin2019" loc="15–16, 17"/> </cit>
            <p>Read in this light, <quote rend="inline">offline is the new luxury</quote> seems to be less a celebration of
               leisure and mindfulness than an accurate diagnosis of digital inequity <ptr target="#vanderhaak2016"/>.</p>
            <p>Of course, all these terms have been scrambled amid a pandemic, when broadband
               connectivity could mean the difference between going out of business and creating an
               online storefront, or going without healthcare and scheduling a virtual appointment.
               The writings of the digital minimalists seem almost quaint now that so much of social
               existence has become filtered through screens. For some time, maximal digital
               connection will be all we have. It’s difficult to say how much of this new maximalist
               sensibility will survive the pandemic. But it will be important to reframe the
               digital minimalist conversations of the 2010s for the demands of digital equity in
               the 2020s. Going forward, we should ask: which of these competing claims to
               minimalism — as a form of attention, mindfulness, and agency — are compatible with
               maximal connection, with maximal choice, with maximal investment in communities and
               infrastructures?</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Minimal Computing, Maximal Connection</head>
            <p>It’s almost impossible to talk about minimal computing without reference to these
               free-floating cultural imaginaries of minimalism as a <q>solution</q> to the problems of
               technology today, from doing more with less to surviving off the grid. Before we
               deploy minimal computing in digital humanities pedagogy and practice, these
               problematic echoes of minimal computing need to be examined. At a moment when
               minimalism in pop culture commodifies asceticism and romanticizes disconnection,
               practitioners of minimal computing should use the term carefully. When digital
               humanists use the phrase, what does <q>minimal</q> mean? And when we hold up minimalism as
               a virtue, is that virtue a property of particular tools or specific techniques for
               using them?</p>
            <p>In 2014, Dennis Tenen and I published a tutorial that showed how academic writers
               could step outside <quote rend="inline">proprietary word processing software and fragile file formats</quote>
               like Microsoft Word and Google Docs. The values guiding that piece included an
               emphasis on the fundamentals of computation, legibility of the many layers of
               mediation involved in word processing, and above all, sustainability of the media on
               which we record our ideas <ptr target="#tenen2014"/> <ptr target="#gil2015"/>.
               The tools we used to achieve those goals are now closely associated with <soCalled>minimal
               computing</soCalled>: markdown and the document conversion software Pandoc, as well as static
               site generators. But I now wonder whether we were prioritizing the values embedded in
               the tools (as do the proponents of a decentralized web who advance non-proprietary
               hardware) or the values that informed our selection and use of those tools (like the
               community technologists who advocate for meaningful connectivity for all). When it
               comes to Pandoc and static sites, do these artifacts have politics, as Langdon Winner
               famously asked? Can particular technologies have either inherently democratic or
               inherently authoritarian tendencies, <quote rend="inline">embody[ing] specific forms of power and
                  authority?</quote> <ptr target="#winner1980" loc="121"/>.</p>
            <p>The answer is of course a resounding yes. Pandoc prevents information from being
               endangered or locked into proprietary ecosystems, while static sites enable the
               democratization and rapid deployment of humanist praxis, which Alex Gil and Élika
               Ortega usefully describe as <quote rend="inline">the renewal, dissemination, and preservation of the
                  scholarly record</quote> <ptr target="#gil2016" loc="29"/>. However, I would caution against an easy
               equivocation between tools and their attendant politics. Too often, digital humanists
               attribute democratic tendencies to some tools while overlooking the authoritarian
               tendencies of others. I’m thinking in particular about the number of digital
               humanities studies that use
               facial recognition technologies in studies of film and television without once
               mentioning the racist ways those tools are deployed in the world<note> There is
                  growing public awareness of the discriminatory effects of these technologies. For
                  example, IBM, Microsoft, and Amazon have all banned the sale of their
                  facial-recognition systems to police departments <ptr target="#greene2020"/>. See also the Safe
                  Face Pledge, <quote rend="inline">an opportunity for organizations to make public commitments towards
                     mitigating the abuse of facial analysis technology</quote> <ptr target="#algorithmicjusticeleague"/>.
               </note> — or work in cultural analytics that sidestep questions about machine
               learning’s amplification of existing inequities with the briefest of preambles before
               moving on to the value-neutral application of those tools.<note> These automated
                  systems introduce <quote rend="inline">subtler forms of discrimination that give the illusion of
                  progress and neutrality, even as coded inequity makes it easier and faster to
                  produce racist outcomes</quote> <ptr target="#benjamin2019" loc="22"/>.</note> If we simply borrow a data
               science tool in the humanities and apply it to a corpus of photographs or novels
               without questioning the assumptions baked into that tool or the harmful ways that
               tool is deployed in the world today, that is a missed opportunity for dialogue and
               advocacy.</p>
            <p>A better approach might be to invert Langdon Winner’s question, as Christina
               Dunbar-Hester does in her book <title rend="italic">Low Power to the People:</title> <quote rend="inline">Do
               politics have artifacts?</quote> This is a much more difficult question, asking how we can
               identify which tools best exemplify a particular political argument. Dunbar-Hester’s
               book is an ethnography of community technologists working with radio and WiFi in the
               early 2000s who negotiated <quote rend="inline">the construction and implementation of specific beliefs
               about what technology can do, what technology should do, or what artifact is most
               appropriate to enact a set of politics</quote> <ptr target="#dunbarhester2014"/>. Winner explores the
               existence of <quote rend="inline">artifactual politics,</quote> rightly concluding that all artifacts entail
               some form of political argument or effect. His approach to artifactual politics would
               describe minimal computing as an assemblage of particular tools and platforms —
               Jekyll, Hugo, Pandoc, Markdown — that afford a particular form of politics, an
               argument about the role of technology in daily life. Dunbar-Hester asks instead how
               to identify and describe <quote rend="inline">political artifacts,</quote> or the artifacts that embody
               particular arguments. If the politics of minimal computing are access, participation,
               sustainability, and equity, then what tools are best suited to achieve those goals?
               The benefit of Dunbar-Hester’s approach is that there is never just one right answer,
               and it ensures that we lead with a fluid conversation about values rather than
               locking those values into the affordances of a particular tool.</p>
            <p>For example, while the tools currently associated with minimal computing are more
               sustainable, they can be less equitable in terms of participation (considering the
               steep learning curve of starting from scratch) or bandwidth (given their pared back,
               lower-definition, lesser-than resources). Jentery Sayers warned of this early on, in
               2016: <quote rend="inline">It’s easy to become preoccupied with technical details and specialization,
                  which often ostracize people or inhibit participation</quote> <ptr target="#sayers2016"/>. Since then,
               minimal computing has become near synonymous with static sites in particular, but
               static sites are often at odds with some of minimal computing’s core values of access
               and participation. The Executive Council of the Association for Computers and the
               Humanities, for example, recently decided against migrating their website from
               WordPress to a static site generator due in part to learning-curve concerns. The
               Council worried that the command line, markdown, and Git may have presented too great
               a barrier to entry for new contributors to the site.<note> The details on this
                  decision were relayed to me by Executive Council member Rebecca Sutton
                  Koeser.</note> While static site generators are remarkable tools — I’m a known fan
               — they have become too easily conflated with minimal computing. An artifactual
               politics approach has welded a value (rapid deployment) to a tool (static site
               generators) at the expense of sustainable community partnerships and equitable
               participation.</p>
            <p>Values guiding the theory and practice of minimal computing include access,
               participation, sustainability, stewardship, and equity. When placed alongside each
               other — as we’ve seen — these values often produce rich contradictions that can be
               difficult to appreciate if particular tools elevate some values at the expense of
               others. I find that this has been especially difficult to remember during the
               pandemic, amid a rush to throw tools and platforms at every activity under the sun in
               a desperate attempt to recreate the way things felt before social distancing. But the
               contribution of minimal computing has always been the way it foregrounds — instead of
               particular tools — what Roopika Risam calls <quote rend="inline">cultural practices,</quote> what German media
               theorists call <term>Kulturtechniken</term>, and what we can simply refer
               to here as technique, or the way we do things <ptr target="#risam2018" loc="43"/> <ptr target="#siegart2015"/>. If
               minimal computing is to continue asking <quote rend="inline">What do we need?</quote> in order to define the
               <q>we</q> in question and elevate the values held in common by that <q>we,</q> then it will
               have to find new ways to center its principles on the way we do things rather than
               the tools we use to do them. I offer three suggestions in closing for how to surface
               such techniques in the unsettled months and years to come.</p>
            <p>First, minimal computing should be led by community input. For the community
               technologist, maximal connection doesn’t necessarily mean more tools. Instead, it
               means increased accountability, tangibility, and locality to the ways we connect with
               one another. In building social and technical infrastructures alongside one another,
               community technologists advocate not only for access, but also for the legibility of
               unseen, surveillant infrastructures. As Rory Solomon writes: </p>
            <p><quote rend="block">Mesh networks are more like students passing notes in class. . . . Even though social
               media and meme culture are often referred to as peer-to-peer, they remain
               intermediated by vast agglomerations of actors — corporations, institutions,
               platforms, infrastructures, workers — that we don’t know and maybe can’t fully know
               or see. <ptr target="#solomon2020" loc="3"/></quote> </p>
            <p>For Greta Byrum, mesh is <quote rend="inline">a tool of resilience and mutual aid . . . a way to resist
               autocratic control of communications systems</quote> <ptr target="#byrum2019"/>. As we’ve seen, minimalism
               is relative. But the version of minimal computing offered by community technologists
               is a minimalism of paring back to make visible, of participation and equity. At the
               same time, it is a minimalism that remains tool-agnostic and responsive to the values
               of a community. Community technology connects the individual user to her shared
               social bonds — and the impacts of technology on both — by advancing a form of
               minimalism that is rich with social connection.</p>
            <p>Second, minimal computing should be responsive to the underlying contradictions and
               concerns that have inspired flawed responses to the tech industry like digital
               minimalism and disaster survivalism. Both of these ideas advocate for inward retreat
               and isolation. But their imaginaries of constraint also offer lessons for the future
               of minimal computing as it is practiced in digital humanities scholarship, pedagogy,
               and praxis. Clearly, the romance with the tech industry is over and the public is
               hungry for new ways to think about the role of invasive technologies in daily life.
               And so minimal computing should incorporate the bare minimum literacies needed today
               in order to understand what data is captured about our habits and desires, as well as
               the impacts that collection will have. It should also incorporate tactics for data
               literacy and the obfuscation of surveillance (also known as <q>sousveillance</q>), instead
               of retreats into mindfulness.<note> A regular workshop series on Obfuscation
                  showcases and debates <quote rend="inline">creative ways to evade surveillance, protect privacy, and
                  improve security by adding and modifying data instead of concealing it, making it
                  more ambiguous and difficult to exploit</quote> <ptr target="#workshop2021"/>. The workshop
                  grew out of the book by Finn Brunton and Helen Nissenbaum, <title rend="italic"
                     >Obfuscation: A User’s Guide for Privacy and Protest</title> <ptr target="#brunton2016"/>. 
                  For a grassroots parallel to this academic initiative, see <title
                     rend="italic">Our Data Bodies: Digital Defense Playbook</title>, authored by the
                  Detroit Community Technology Project <ptr target="#lewis2018"/>. </note> Minimal
               computing can offer self-determination rather than self-help, an ethics of connection
               rather than an injunction to detox, and forms of solidarity rather than
               appropriation.</p>
            <p>And finally, given this broad hunger for more responsible technology, minimal
               computing can play a role in public scholarship and community partnerships that
               extend existing academic research.<note> Here, we might think of earlier calls among
                  digital humanists to ground their theories in community practice, or more
                  specifically, by rethinking what constitutes scholarly community. Rita Raley,
                  providing the examples of DHCommons and the HASTAC Scholars program, writes:
                  <quote rend="inline">Tactical activities are increasingly framed in terms of community and
                  infrastructural investment, and the result has been a proliferation of community
                  labs and gardens and alternative systems of exchange. To take a tactical,
                  media-informed approach to the digital humanities is thus to renew one’s
                  commitments to the sharing of knowledge — not simply references and links but,
                  more important, ideas</quote> <ptr target="#raley2014"/>. More recently, Matthew Applegate has written
                  on <quote rend="inline">politicized modes of DH praxis</quote> that have <quote rend="inline">proven to be a conduit for
                  centering marginalized voices, creating space for many who are excluded from
                  academic advancement, and rethinking how humanistic inquiry is practiced</quote>
                  <ptr target="#applegate2019"/>. </note> Minimal computing has largely grown in digital
               humanities contexts by emphasizing the preservation of the scholarly and cultural
               record. But the use of minimal computing tools and techniques in digital humanities
               research can also provide a model for the understanding, critique, and application of
               those tools in the broader world. What academics call minimal computing has
               independently taken root outside universities through grassroots organizing,
               activism, and advocacy on technology. Two groups of people are having the same
               conversation in two different contexts: for every Maryland Institute for Technology
               in the Humanities there’s a Detroit Equitable Internet Initiative, for every Harvard
               MetaLab, a Pittsburgh MetaMesh. It’s especially important to recognize these existing
               parallels as many expect the makeup of academia to change dramatically from the
               coronavirus’s irreparable damage to already-misguided university budgets. Asking
               <quote rend="inline">What do we need?</quote> in minimal computing now means defining the <q>we</q> that will
               constitute researchers, scholars, and archivists as graduate programs contract and
               the professoriate is hollowed out. If we can’t count on institutional support, what
               comes next?</p>
            <p>While the pandemic has widened fault lines that long predate the current crisis,
               academics can now triangulate a new <q>we</q> as the common ground shifts beneath our
               feet. If universities fail, digital humanities praxis will continue elsewhere. The
               pandemic provides the occasion for community technologists and digital humanists to
               join efforts, and for academics to contribute their energies to support the voices
               and vision of community-based organizations.</p></div>
            
            <div>
               <head>Acknowledgments</head>
               <p>This essay was written with a sense of urgency in May and June 2020,
               during collective reckonings with a global pandemic and state-sponsored, racist
               violence: twinned crises that have lasted longer than any crisis, by definition,
               should. I’m grateful to Rebecca Sutton Koeser, Zoe LeBlanc, Jessa Lingel, Rory Solomon, Sara J. Grossman, Alex Wermer-Colan, and two anonymous reviewers for their input, to Roopika Risam and Alex Gil for the uncommon lengths they went in order to make this special issue stand as a well-designed, consistent whole, to Lydia Guterman for engaging these ideas so thoroughly during copyedits, and for my friends at Philly Community Wireless.
            </p></div>
            
        </body>
            
         
         
      
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="algorithmicjusticeleague" label="Algorithmic Justice League 2021"> Algorithmic Justice League. <title rend="quotes">Overview - Inactive.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Safe Face Pledge</title>. Accessed October 19, 2021. <ref target="https://www.safefacepledge.org/">https://www.safefacepledge.org/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="alliance2020" label="Alliance for Affordable Internet 2020"> Alliance for Affordable Internet (A4AI).
               <title rend="quotes">Meaningful Connectivity: A New Target to Raise the Bar for Internet Access.</title> <title
                  rend="italic">Alliance for Affordable Internet. </title>Accessed October 13, 2021.
               <ref target="https://a4ai.org/meaningful-connectivity/"
                  >https://a4ai.org/meaningful-connectivity/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="applegate2019" label="Applegate 2019"> Applegate, Matthew. <title rend="italic">Guerrilla Theory: Political
               Concepts, Critical Digital Humanities.</title> Evanston, IL: Northwestern
               University Press, 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="aureli2014" label="Aureli 2014"> Aureli, Pier Vittorio. <title rend="italic">Less Is Enough: On
               Architecture and Asceticism</title>. Moscow: Strelka Press, 2014.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="benjamin2021" label="Benjamin 2021"> Benjamin, Ruha. <title rend="quotes">About Pandemic Portal.</title> <title rend="italic">The Just
               Data Lab. </title>Accessed October 19, 2021. <ref
                  target="https://www.thejustdatalab.com/">https://www.thejustdatalab.com/</ref>.
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="benjamin2019" label="Benjamin 2019"> Benjamin, Ruha. <title rend="italic">Race After Technology: Abolitionist
               Tools for the New Jim Code</title>. Medford, MA: Polity, 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brabazon2013" label="Brabazon 2013"> Brabazon, Tara. <title rend="italic">Digital Dieting: From Information
               Obesity to Intellectual Fitness</title>. London, UK: Routledge, 2013.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="breitbart2007" label="Breitbart, Lakshmipathy, and Meinrath 2007"> Breitbart, Joshua, Naveen Lakshmipathy,
               and Sascha D. Meinrath. <title rend="italic">The Philadelphia Story: Learning from a
                  Municipal Wireless Pioneer</title>. Washington D.C.: New America Foundation, 2007. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brinkmann2017" label="Brinkmann 2017"> Brinkmann, Svend. <title rend="italic">Stand Firm: Resisting the
               Self-Improvement Craze</title>. Malden, MA: Polity, 2017.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brunton2016" label="Brunton and Nissenbaum 2016"> Brunton, Finn and Helen Nissenbaum. <title rend="italic">Obfuscation: A
               User’s Guide for Privacy and Protest.</title> Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2016. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="byrum2019" label="Byrum 2019"> Byrum, Greta. <title rend="quotes">Building the People’s Internet.</title> <title rend="italic">Urban
               Omnibus</title>, October 2, 2019. <ref
                  target="https://urbanomnibus.net/2019/10/building-the-peoples-internet/"
                  >https://urbanomnibus.net/2019/10/building-the-peoples-internet/</ref>.
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cederstrom2015" label="Cederström and Spicer 2015"> Cederström, Carl and André Spicer. <title rend="italic">The
               Wellness Syndrome</title>. Malden, MA: Polity, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="center2021" label="Center for Humane Technology 2021"> <title rend="quotes">For Technologists: Review Our Principles.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Center for Humane Technology</title>. Accessed October 19, 2021. <ref
                  target="https://www.humanetech.com/technologists#principles"
                  >https://www.humanetech.com/technologists#principles</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chayka2020" label="Chayka 2020"> Chayka, Kyle. <title rend="italic">The Longing for Less: Living with
               Minimalism</title>. NY: Bloomsbury Publishing, 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="clear2018" label="Clear 2018"> Clear, James. <title rend="italic">Atomic Habits: An Easy &amp; Proven Way
               to Build Good Habits &amp; Break Bad Ones</title>. NY: Avery, 2018. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="community2021" label="Community Technology Field Guide 2021"> Open Technology Institute, New America, 
               The Work Department, 
               Allied Media Projects, and Detroit
               Community Technology Project. <title rend="quotes">Neighborhood Network Construction Kit: Introduction to
               Mesh.</title> <title rend="italic">Community Technology Field Guide</title>. Accessed October 19, 2021. <ref
                  target="https://communitytechnology.github.io/docs/cck/networking/intro-to-mesh/"
                  >https://communitytechnology.github.io/docs/cck/networking/intro-to-mesh/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="computerhistorymuseum" label="Computer History Museum 2021"> <title rend="quotes">SRI Mobile Van.</title> <title rend="italic">Computer History Museum</title>. Accessed
               October 19, 2021. <ref
                  target="https://www.computerhistory.org/collections/catalog/X1590.99"
                  >https://www.computerhistory.org/collections/catalog/X1590.99</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="couldry2019" label="Couldry and Mejias 2019"> Couldry, Nick and Ulises A. Mejias. <title rend="italic">The
               Costs of Connection: How Data Is Colonizing Human Life and Appropriating It for
               Capitalism</title>. Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press, 2019. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crawford2016" label="Crawford 2016"> Crawford, Matthew B. <title rend="italic">The World Beyond Your Head: On
               Becoming an Individual in an Age of Distraction</title>. NY: Farrar, Straus
               and Giroux, 2016.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="digital2021" label="Digital Harbor Foundation 2021"> <title rend="quotes">About.</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Harbor Foundation</title>. Accessed October
               19, 2021. <ref target="https://www.digitalharbor.org/about/"
                  >https://www.digitalharbor.org/about/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dunbarhester2014" label="Dunbar-Hester 2014"> Dunbar-Hester, Christina. <title rend="italic">Low Power to the
               People: Pirates, Protest, and Politics in FM Radio Activism</title>. Cambridge, MA:
               MIT Press, 2014.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="flynn2014" label="Flynn 2014"> Flynn, Adam. <title rend="quotes">Solarpunk: Notes toward a manifesto.</title> <title rend="italic">Hieroglyph</title>,
               September 4, 2014.
               <ref target="https://hieroglyph.asu.edu/2014/09/solarpunk-notes-toward-a-manifesto/">https://hieroglyph.asu.edu/2014/09/solarpunk-notes-toward-a-manifesto/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fried1998" label="Fried 1998"> Fried, Michael. <title rend="italic">Art and Objecthood: Essays and
               Reviews</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1998. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gil2015" label="Gil 2015"> Gil, Alex. <title rend="quotes">The User, the Learner and the Machines We Make.</title> <title
               rend="italic">Minimal Computing</title>, May 21, 2015. <ref
                  target="https://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2015/05/21/user-vs-learner/"
                  >https://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2015/05/21/user-vs-learner/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gil2016" label="Gil and Ortega 2016"> Gil, Alex and Élika Ortega. <title rend="quotes">Global Outlooks in Digital
               Humanities: Multilingual Practices and Minimal Computing.</title> In <title rend="italic">Doing
                  Digital Humanities: Practice, Training, Research</title>, edited by Constance
               Crompton, Richard J. Lane, and Ray Siemens, 22–34. Abingdon, UK: Routledge, 2016. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.4324/9781315707860-12"
                  >10.4324/9781315707860-12</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="greene2020" label="Greene 2020"> Greene, Jay. <title rend="quotes">Microsoft Won’t Sell Police Its Facial-Recognition
               Technology, Following Similar Moves by Amazon and IBM.</title> <title rend="italic">The Washington Post</title>, June 11,
               2020.
               <ref target="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2020/06/11/microsoft-facial-recognition/">https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2020/06/11/microsoft-facial-recognition/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hetrick2020" label="Hetrick and Purcell 2020"> Hetrick, Christian and Dylan Purcell. <title rend="quotes">Thousands of Philly
               Students Are Stuck at Home with No Computer or Internet After Coronavirus Closed
               Schools.</title> <title rend="italic">The Philadelphia Inquirer</title>, April 3, 2020. <ref
                  target="https://www.inquirer.com/education/coronavirus-students-digital-divide-philadelphia-comcast-20200403.html"
                  >https://www.inquirer.com/education/coronavirus-students-digital-divide-philadelphia-comcast-20200403.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hobart2020" label="Hobart and Kneese 2020"> Hobart, Hi‘ilei Julia Kawehipuaakahaopulani Hobart and
               Tamara Kneese. <title rend="quotes">Radical Care: Survival Strategies for Uncertain Times.</title> <title
                  rend="italic">Social Text</title> vol. 38.1 (March 2020): 1–16, doi:<ref
                     target="https://doi.org/10.1215/01642472-7971067"
                     >10.1215/01642472-7971067</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="karppi2018" label="Karppi 2018"> Karppi, Tero. <title rend="italic">Disconnect: Facebook’s Affective
               Bonds</title>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kondo2014" label="Kondō 2014"> Kondō, Marie. <title rend="italic">The Life-Changing Magic of Tidying up:
               The Japanese Art of Decluttering and Organizing</title>. Berkeley, CA: Ten Speed
               Press, 2014. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="konstantinou2019" label="Konstantinou 2019"> Konstantinou, Lee. <title rend="quotes">Our Sci-Fi Is Broken, and Hopepunk — Whatever
               That Is — Can’t Fix It.</title> <title rend="italic">Slate Magazine</title>, January 15, 2019.
               <ref
                  target="https://slate.com/technology/2019/01/hopepunk-cyberpunk-solarpunk-science-fiction-broken.html"
                  >https://slate.com/technology/2019/01/hopepunk-cyberpunk-solarpunk-science-fiction-broken.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="levy2017" label="Levy 2017"> Levy, David M. <title rend="italic">Mindful Tech: How to Bring Balance to
               Our Digital Lives</title>. New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 2017. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lewis2018" label="Lewis et al. 2018"> Lewis, Tamika, Seeta Peña Gangadharan, Mariella Saba, and Tawana Petty. <title rend="quotes">Digital Defense Playbook: Community Power Tools for Reclaiming Data.</title> <title rend="italic">Our Data Bodies</title>. Accessed March 15, 2022. <ref target="https://www.odbproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/ODB_DDP_HighRes_Spreads.pdf">https://www.odbproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/ODB_DDP_HighRes_Spreads.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ma2018" label="Ma 2018"> Ma, Ling. <title rend="italic">Severance</title>. New York: Farrar, Straus and
               Giroux, 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mapping2021" label="Movement Alliance Project and MediaJustice"> Movement Alliance Project and MediaJustice.
               <title rend="quotes">About.</title> Mapping Pretrial Injustice Project. Accessed October 19, 2021.
               <ref target="https://pretrialrisk.com/our-research/about/">https://pretrialrisk.com/our-research/about/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="newport2019" label="Newport 2019"> Newport, Cal. <title rend="italic">Digital Minimalism: Choosing a Focused
               Life in a Noisy World</title>. NY: Portfolio, 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nucera2016" label="Nucera 2016"> Nucera, Diana J. <title rend="quotes">Teaching Community Technology Handbook.</title> <title rend="italic">Detroit Community Technology Project</title>. Accessed March 15, 2022. <ref target="https://detroitcommunitytech.org/sites/default/files/librarypdfs/TeachingCommunityTech.pdf">https://detroitcommunitytech.org/sites/default/files/librarypdfs/TeachingCommunityTech.pdf</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oconnell2020" label="O’Connell 2020"> O’Connell, Mark. <title rend="italic">Notes from an Apocalypse: A
               Personal Journey to the End of the World and Back</title>. London: Granta
               Publications, 2020. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="odell2019" label="Odell 2019"> Odell, Jenny. <title rend="italic">How to Do Nothing: Resisting the
               Attention Economy</title>. Brooklyn: Melville House, 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="osnos2017" label="Osnos 2017"> Osnos, Evan. <title rend="quotes">Doomsday Prep for the Super-Rich.</title> <title rend="italic">The
               New Yorker</title>, January 30, 2017.
               <ref target="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/01/30/doomsday-prep-for-the-super-rich">https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/01/30/doomsday-prep-for-the-super-rich</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="otto2016" label="Otto and Westhagen 2016"> Otto, Daniela and Florian Westhagen. <title rend="italic"
               >Digital Detox: Wie Sie entspannt mit Handy &amp; Co. leben</title>. Berlin:
               Springer, 2018. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ozenc2021" label="Ozenc and Hagan 2021"> Ozenc, F. Kursat, and Margaret Hagan. <title rend="quotes">About.</title> <title rend="italic">Ritual Design
               Lab</title>. Accessed October 19, 2021. <ref target="https://www.ritualdesignlab.org/about/"
                  >https://www.ritualdesignlab.org/about/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="patton2020" label="Patton 2020"> Patton, Stacey. <title rend="quotes">Black America Is Suffering from the Coronavirus.</title> <title
               rend="italic">The Washington Post</title>, April 11, 2020. <ref
                  target="https://www.washingtonpost.com/outlook/2020/04/11/coronavirus-black-america-racism/"
                  >https://www.washingtonpost.com/outlook/2020/04/11/coronavirus-black-america-racism/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="penny2020" label="Penny 2020"> Penny, Laurie. <title rend="quotes">This Is Not the Apocalypse You Were Looking For.</title> <title
               rend="italic">Wired</title>, March 30, 2020.
               <ref target="https://www.wired.com/story/coronavirus-apocalypse-myths/">https://www.wired.com/story/coronavirus-apocalypse-myths/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="perlow2012" label="Perlow 2012"> Perlow, Leslie A. <title rend="italic">Sleeping With Your Smartphone: How
               to Break the 24/7 Habit and Change the Way You Work</title>. Boston: Harvard Business
               Review Press, 2012. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="phillymesh2021" label="Philly Mesh 2021"> <title rend="quotes">Home.</title> <title rend="italic">Philly Mesh.</title> Accessed
               October 13, 2021.
               <ref target="https://phillymesh.net/">https://phillymesh.net/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="phillytech2021" label="Philly Tech Justice 2021"> <title rend="quotes">About.</title> <title rend="italic">Philly Tech Justice.
            </title>Accessed October 19, 2021. <ref target="https://phillytechjustice.org/about/"
               >https://phillytechjustice.org/about/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="portwoodstacer2013" label="Portwood-Stacer 2013"> Portwood-Stacer, Laura. <title rend="quotes">Media Refusal and Conspicuous
               Non-Consumption: The Performative and Political Dimensions of Facebook Abstention.</title>
               <title rend="italic">New Media &amp; Society</title> vol. 15.7, (November 2013): 1041–1057.
               doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1461444812465139"
                  >10.1177/1461444812465139</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="project2021" label="Project Waves 2021"> <title rend="quotes">About.</title> Project Waves. Accessed October 19, 2021. <ref
               target="https://www.projectwaves.net/about"
               >https://www.projectwaves.net/about</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="purcell2021" label="Purcell 2021"> Purcell, Dylan. <title rend="quotes">Broadband Internet Access Lags in Many Philadelphia
               Neighborhoods.</title> <title rend="italic">Datawrapper. </title>Accessed October 19, 2021. <ref
                  target="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/Ce3Cz/3/"
                  >https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/Ce3Cz/3/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="raley2014" label="Raley 2014"> Raley, Rita. <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities for the Next Five Minutes.</title> <title
               rend="italic">Differences</title> vol. 25.1 (January 2014): 26–45.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="risam2018" label="Risam 2018"> Risam, Roopika. <title rend="italic">New Digital Worlds: Postcolonial
               Digital Humanities in Theory, Praxis, and Pedagogy</title>. Evanston, IL:
               Northwestern University Press, 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rosen2021" label="Rosen 2021"> Rosen, David. <title rend="quotes">Cities Struggle to End the Urban Digital Divide.</title> <title
               rend="italic">The Progressive Magazine</title>. Accessed October 24, 2021.
               <ref target="https://progressive.org/latest/urban-digital-divide-rosen-210916/">https://progressive.org/latest/urban-digital-divide-rosen-210916/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sanchez2020" label="Sanchez 2020"> Sanchez, Alvaro. <title rend="italic">Toward Digital Inclusion: Broadband
               Access in the Third Federal Reserve District. </title>Federal Reserve Bank of
               Philadelphia, March 2020. <ref
                  target="https://www.philadelphiafed.org/-/media/frbp/assets/community-development/reports/toward-digital-inclusion-broadband-access-in-the-third-federal-reserve-district.pdf"
                  >https://www.philadelphiafed.org/-/media/frbp/assets/community-development/reports/toward-digital-inclusion-broadband-access-in-the-third-federal-reserve-district.pdf</ref>.
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sayers2016" label="Sayers 2016"> Sayers, Jentery. <title rend="quotes">Minimal Definitions-Minimal Computing.</title> <title
               rend="italic">Minimal Computing: A Working Group of GO::DH</title>, October 2, 2016.
               <ref
                  target="http://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2016/10/02/minimal-definitions/"
                  >http://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2016/10/02/minimal-definitions/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="siegart2015" label="Siegert 2015"> Siegert, Bernhard. <title rend="italic">Cultural Techniques: Grids,
               Doors, Filters, and Other Articulations of the Real</title>. Oxford: Oxford
               University Press, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="solomon2020" label="Solomon 2020"> Solomon, Rory. <title rend="quotes">Meshiness: Mesh Networks and the Politics of
               Connectivity.</title> PhD dissertation, 2020. New York University. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="statisticalatlas2018" label="Statistical Atlas 2018"> <title rend="quotes">Race and Ethnicity in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Statistical Atlas</title>, September 10, 2018. <ref
                  target="https://statisticalatlas.com/place/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia/Race-and-Ethnicity#data-map/neighborhood/white"
                  >https://statisticalatlas.com/place/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia/Race-and-Ethnicity#data-map/neighborhood/white</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tenen2014" label="Tenen and Wythoff 2014"> Tenen, Dennis and Grant Wythoff. <title rend="quotes">Sustainable Authorship in
               Plain Text using Pandoc and Markdown.</title> <title rend="italic">The Programming
                  Historian</title> 3, 2014. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.46430/phen0041"
                     >https://doi.org/10.46430/phen0041</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ticona2015" label="Ticona 2015"> Ticona, Julia. <title rend="quotes">Strategies of Control: Workers’ Use of ICTs to Shape
               Knowledge and Service Work.</title> <title rend="italic">Information, Communication &amp; Society</title> vol. 18.5 (May
               2015): 509–523. doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/1369118X.2015.1012531"
                  >10.1080/1369118X.2015.1012531</ref>.
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tierney2019" label="Tierney 2019"> Tierney, Matt. <title rend="italic">Dismantlings: Words Against Machines in the American
               Long Seventies.</title> Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vanderhaak2016" label="Van der Haak 2016"> van der Haak, Bregtje, dir. <title rend="italic">Offline Is the New
               Luxury. </title>Hilversum, Netherlands: VPRO Backlight, 2016. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ward2017" label="Ward 2017"> Ward, Megan. <title rend="quotes">Your Digital Detox Isn’t as Radical as You Think.</title> <title
               rend="italic">The Washington Post</title>, July 30, 2017. <ref
                  target="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/made-by-history/wp/2017/07/30/your-digital-detox-isnt-as-radical-as-you-think/"
                  >https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/made-by-history/wp/2017/07/30/your-digital-detox-isnt-as-radical-as-you-think/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="williams2018" label="Williams 2018"> Williams, James. <title rend="italic">Stand Out of Our Light: Freedom
               and Resistance in the Attention Economy</title>. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University
               Press, 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="winner1980" label="Winner 1980"> Winner, Langdon. <title rend="quotes">Do Artifacts Have Politics?</title> <title rend="italic"
               >Daedalus</title> vol. 109.1 (1980): 121–136.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wired2011" label="Wired 2011"> <title rend="quotes">U.N. Report Declares Internet Access a Human Right.</title> <title rend="italic"
               >Wired Magazine</title>, June 6, 2011. <ref
                  target="https://www.wired.com/2011/06/internet-a-human-right/"
                  >https://www.wired.com/2011/06/internet-a-human-right/</ref>.
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="workshop2021" label="Workshop on Obfuscation 2021"> <title rend="quotes">About.</title> Workshop on Obfuscation. Accessed October 19,
               2021. <ref target="https://www.obfuscationworkshop.org/"
                  >https://www.obfuscationworkshop.org/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zuboff2019" label="Zuboff 2019"> Zuboff, Shoshana. <title rend="italic">The Age of Surveillance Capitalism:
               The Fight for a Human Future at the New Frontier of Power</title>. NY:
               PublicAffairs, 2019.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
