<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt><!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">A Named Entity Recognition Model for Medieval Latin Charters<!--article title in English--></title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo><!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Pierre <dhq:family>Chastang</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>UVSQ-Université Paris-Saclay</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>pierre.chastang@uvsq.fr</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Pierre Chastang is a full professor of medieval history at UVSQ-Université Paris-Saclay. 
                     His main fields of research are the culture of writing and written heritage in the Middle Ages. 
                     For the past ten years, he has been developing interdisciplinary research projects involving history,
                     physical-chemical analysis of ancient materials, and text mining concerning medieval pragmatic writing.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo><!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Sergio <dhq:family>Torres Aguilar</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>UVSQ-Université Paris-Saclay</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>regester3@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Sergio Torres Aguilar is a postdoctoral research fellow at the École nationale des Chartes in Paris. 
                     He received the doctoral degree on history in 2019 from Paris-Saclay university. His research focuses on machine
                     learning methods applied to historical sources, natural languages processing to ancient languages and handwritten 
                     text recognition for medieval manuscripts.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo><!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Xavier <dhq:family>Tannier</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Sorbonne Université</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>xavier.tannier@sorbonne-universite.fr</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Xavier Tannier is a full professor of computer science at Sorbonne University, Paris. He conducts his research in the 
                     laboratory for medical informatics and knowledge engineering for e-health (LIMICS). His main research topics concern 
                     natural language processing and information retrieval and extraction.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000574</idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->015</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->4</idno>
            <date when="2021-11-12">November 12, 2021</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords"><!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords"><!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc><!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2022-08-01" who="BRG">revised to pass encoding validation</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract><!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>Named entity recognition is an advantageous technique with an increasing presence in
               digital humanities. In theory, automatic detection and recovery of named entities can provide new ways 
               of looking up unedited information in edited sources and can allow the parsing of a massive amount of 
               data in a short time for supporting historical hypotheses. In this paper, we detail the implementation
               of a model for automatic named entity recognition in medieval Latin sources and we test its robustness
               on different datasets. Different models were trained on a vast dataset of Burgundian diplomatic charters
               from the 9th to 14th centuries and validated by using general and century <term>ad hoc</term> models tested on short
               sets of Parisian, English, Italian and Spanish charters. We present the results of cross-validation in each
               case and we discuss the implications of these results for the history of medieval place-names and personal names.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser><!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>In this paper, we detail the implementation
               of a model for automatic named entity recognition in medieval Latin sources and we test its robustness
               on different datasets.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            
         <head>1. Introduction</head>

         <p>In this paper, we introduce a new model for the automatic recognition of named
                entities in medieval Latin charters. The named entity concept involves all physical
                and real objects which can be designated with a specific name. A named entity
                recognition (NER) model detects entities in the text and classifies them (e.g., a
                person's name, a location name, an organization's name, a date). It becomes
                possible, then, to index the resulting information units and to extract
                relationships between them. In that sense, automatic NER systems can help to improve
                current information systems by building a knowledge base of all the spatial, social
                and personal entities in a set of documents; this enables a searchable and quotable
                corpus matrix using actors and places as dynamic keywords which help to provide
                meaningful answers to questions asked on a large textual database.</p>
         <p>In recent years, some projects have entailed the production of structured data
                through manual tagging of named entities in thousand-item historical corpora. This
                manual operation takes years for an entire team and can obviously not be scaled up
                to the almost 500,000 (and increasing) medieval digitized documents. This lengthy
                process can be completed only with massive acceleration through a computational
                operation of converting automatically thousands of documents in raw data format into
                structured data in a short time. </p>
         <p>In the present project we use one of these hand-annotated corpora as our dataset: the
                CBMA (<title rend="italic">Corpus Burgundiae Medii Aevi</title>), which contains a
                collection of medieval charters and cartularies produced in Burgundy. From the 11th century on, many ecclesiastical institutions started
                to compose cartularies in which they transcribed their own documents, especially
                titles relating to their property and their land rights, in order to better preserve
                written deeds and keep legal proof of ecclesiastical possessions and social
                relationships. Today, these registers stand as one of the major sources for medieval
                studies. Among the texts collected in the CBMA we isolated a set of 5300-items (1,2
                million words), which correspond mostly to cartularies from Cluny. This large
                sub-set contains mainly donations, exchanges and sales, that is, written records
                dealing with the transfer of lands, goods and rights between ecclesiastical
                institutions and between private and public actors. While these documents are
                relatively formulaic, with only limited vocabulary and a relatively small number of
                turns of phrase, their geographical provenance is as diverse (more than one hundred
                different places) as the chronological scope of their production is wide (from the
                early 10th century to the middle of the 13th century). Moreover, they include many different kinds
                of documents: charters, notices, bulls, diplomas, letters, lawsuits, etc.</p>
         <p>As we will show, developing a model able to achieve entity recognition for this
                corpus presents several challenges. The need to choose a single corpus for stability
                and coherence can affect the ability of the model to be generalized to a wide range
                of documents, because it reduces the variety of samples and can hide more specific
                phenomena. Constructing a robust model requires finding a technical and intellectual
                compromise between collecting sufficiently varied data and avoiding extreme training
                on some similar structures <ptr target="#plank2016"/>. This issue becomes even more complicated if
                we consider the particular characteristics of our main corpora: on the one hand,
                diplomatic charters combine formulaic structure and variable lists of named entities
            <ptr target="#zimmermann2003"/>, which can be an advantage regarding iteration in training. But it
                also means fitting problems of recognition over other corpora, because there are
                many formulaic traditions, different models in according to juridical actions and
                regional redactional dependencies. On the other hand, because Latin is a
                low-resource language in natural language processing, the work must be conducted
                using tools and vocabularies not initially developed for Latin or developed for
                classical Latin literature <ptr target="#eger2015"/>; not to mention the technical
                adaptations required for the specificities of medieval Latin due to several
                linguistics alterations. Above all, less technical but more extended, pre-processing
                must be completed, such as the normalization of textual spelling, the manual
                validation of much inflected language arbitrariness, and the listing of difficulties
                due to overlapping and to textual ambiguities. </p>
         <p>The construction of a proper validation environment, proving the robustness of our
                model, has led us to build several corpora and sub-corpora variations and to
                annotate manually other smaller corpora. We finally developed a validation protocol
                with an extensive set of evaluations in order to show that our model can be applied
                to a wide range of unannotated charters with different typologies and belonging to
                different scriptural traditions and regional origins.</p>
         <p>This paper describes, first, the historical nature of our corpus and the features of
                our gold-standard corpus. It explains the method adopted in generating the model
                with a machine-learning approach based on conditional random fields (CRF). We detail
                the construction of the model and sub-models, as well as the results obtained by the
                application of our general model and by the different experiments using
                cross-validation. In the discussion, we try to develop a broader argument for
                results by referring to current onomastic studies, historical and scriptural usages,
                and language variations, thus offering a contextualized explanation that can help to
                clarify, from a non-technical and humanistic perspective, matches and errors
                obtained in the application of the model. The constitutive models of this project
                have been deployed in a web-based application adapted to expert and non-expert users
                located at <ref target="https://entities-recognition.irht.cnrs.fr/">https://entities-recognition.irht.cnrs.fr</ref>.
                An automatic and accessible web-based annotation workflow, based on models developed
                in this project, has been deployed at <ref target="https://entities-recognition.irht.cnrs.fr/">https://entities-recognition.irht.cnrs.fr</ref>. Finally, we propose
                some suggestions for the fruitful application of these models in the wider context
                of digital humanities.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
         <head>2. Academic Background</head>
         <p>Named entity recognition (NER) is one of the most promising technical tools in the
                digital humanities field. Some classical digital humanities projects have been
                conducted with NER, thereby opening new ways to explore and query large databases.
                Actively used in the medical, biological and journalistic domains <ptr target="#abacha2011"/> 
            <ptr target="#eltyeb2014"/>, named entities prove to be meaningful pieces of
                information intimately connected to the main issues addressed by humanistic studies.
                NER techniques are an excellent way to provide an overview of a corpus. On the one
                hand, they help to classify data into pre-defined categories, which is primordial to
                indexing and describing data and eventually to building structured databases. On the
                other hand, they can activate data exploration at different scope levels. For
                example, NER techniques can be used to identify core concepts and cluster them into
                vocabularies, ontologies, and actor's attributes on documentary series They are also
                indispensable in the pre-treatment of texts since they provide pieces of information
                that do not appear in the language dictionaries. Alternatively, at a corpora level,
                NER techniques can serve to build thick social, spatial and semantic relationship
                networks using named entities as nodes. </p>
         <p>NER work in the digital humanities community consists of two subtasks: (i) detection
                and classification of named entities in classical and modern language texts and (ii)
                entity linking towards already existing knowledge databases. Concerning the first
                task, experiments have proven that supervised approaches are more suitable for
                large-scale databases than rule-based or unsupervised ones <ptr target="#nadeau2007"/>. In
                these supervised methods, especially statistics-sequential methods, algorithms use
                labelled data and meta-information obtained by different types of syntactical
                analysis, such as POS tagging, parsing, chunking, from word-based to sentence-based
                levels. The system then builds a statistical model based on these labelled data and
                suggests the best labels for a new, unlabelled sequence of words. Some digital
                humanities projects in recent years <ptr target="#curran2003"/> <ptr target="#won2018"/> <ptr target="#rayson2017"/>
            produce supervised models exceeding 80% on the F-measure (harmonic mean
                of precision and recall).</p>
         <p>Nevertheless, because of the lack of annotated data, rule-based or dictionary-based
                models are still very popular, despite the fact that they generally achieve a low
                recall ratio (for the former) or a low precision ratio (for the latter). Training a
                dictionary-based recognition model against a list of names can lead to a high ratio
                of recognition for a particular corpus, but the model is often not robust when
                applied to unseen texts or different types of data. On the other hand, rule-based
                models trained using rule definitions and descriptions to categorize entities show a
                valid global recall, but a slight tendency to poor precision-ratio on unseen texts.
                In spite of that, these methods have proven very useful for rapid textual annotation
                of small corpora or more standardized corpora like those from literature and
                journals <ptr target="#grover2008"/> <ptr target="#mosallam2014"/> <ptr target="#ehrmann2016"/>. </p>
         <p>Recent years have seen an increasing popularity of hybrid, semi-supervised
                approaches. Bootstrapping techniques use a small set of annotated data in order to
                obtain automatically tagged data by taking advantage of specific repetitive and
                contextual patterns. Some work on this topic has introduced interesting propositions
                with excellent results <ptr target="#brooke2016"/> <ptr target="#neelakantan2015"/> <ptr target="#klein2014"/>.</p>
         <p>Both unsupervised and supervised methods need annotated corpora in order to build
                better linguistic analyzers and evaluation tools. This problem has motivated, in
                recent years, different actions in the digital humanities community. The main one is
                the production of handcrafted corpora with one or more fully annotated attributes,
                such as morphological features, semantical descriptions, syntactic relationships,
                named entities, etc. The medieval corpora made available by <ref
                   target="http://www.cbma-project.eu/">CBMA,</ref> <ref target="http://cdlm.unipv.it/">CDLM,</ref> and <ref target="http://srcmf.org/">SRCMF</ref>
            projects are among these, as well as
                examples of well-constructed lists of authorities, gazetteers and treebanks such as
                proposed by <ref target="http://commons.pelagios.org/">Pelagios</ref>,
            <ref target="http://web.philo.ulg.ac.be/lasla/">LASLA,</ref> and <ref target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu">Perseus,</ref> which are used in many
                projects to improve semi-supervised methods specially addressed to classical and
                medieval literature. In addition, the growing number of platforms created to
                facilitate morphological analysis of new corpora, like <ref target="http://outils.biblissima.fr/fr/collatinus-web/">Collatinus</ref>
            <ref target="http://www.lemlat3.eu/">Lemlat,</ref> or <ref target="https://gutentag.sdsu.edu/">GutenTag</ref>,
            is remarkable; these
                platforms offer a gateway to rapid extraction of a full range of linguistic
                attributes. </p>
         <p>All these efforts are complemented by an increasing availability of programming
                packages including easy access to classical techniques like POS tagging, parsing,
                chunking and named entity resolution in combination with annotating tools based on
                treebanks-training such as TreeTagger and Lapos. They are contributing to the
                incorporation of NER in mid-range projects. <ref target="https://stanfordnlp.github.io/CoreNLP/">Stanford CoreNLP</ref>,
            <ref target="http://nlp.lsi.upc.edu/freeling/node/1">Freeling,</ref>, <ref target="https://www.nltk.org/">Natural Language
               Toolkit</ref> and <ref target="http://scikit-learn.org/stable/">Scikit-learn</ref> are among the most used
                set of tools and libraries.</p>
         <p>Concerning the task of disambiguation (entity linking), projects are close to
                semantic Web and linked open data principles, based on interoperability and
                machine-readable data. Natural languages are ambiguous by definition, and retrieved
                entity mentions must be clearly identified. There are several propositions,
                especially from library domains, calling to use lists of authors and authoritative
                databases to link recovered entities with unique referents stocked in big databases
                like DBpedia <ptr target="#lehmann2013"/>, Freebase <ptr target="#bollacker2008"/>, or Yago
            <ptr target="#hoffart2013"/> using URI’s (Uniform Resource Identifier) <ptr target="#nouvel2016"/>
            <ptr target="#rizzo2011"/>. Some very interesting works based on small-size corpora have
            been taking this direction, especially studies by literary scholars <ptr target="#frontini2016"/>
            <ptr target="#elson2010"/>. However, they are limited to databases containing
                knowledge about relevant people or mapping modern texts. For instance, these works
                are tightly focused on geographical disambiguation, because places do not show a
                high number of possibilities. </p> 
         <p>To address both problems, automatic entity detection and entity disambiguation, it is
                necessary to have large, hand-made annotated corpora whose production is highly
                time-consuming work. For instance, computer acceleration is the most promising
                solution for dealing with the large and growing number of available digital
                historical documents. Algorithm-based techniques can do intelligent tasks and
                provide a very valuable result. However, experience shows that high context
                dependency at different levels compels the combination of the automatic result with
                an academic methodology to define correct heuristics tasks and to incorporate the
                most adequate epistemological rules.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>3. Corpora and Model</head>

        <div> <head>3.1. CBMA corpus description</head>
         <p>The main corpus we use comes from a database of medieval Burgundian charters provided
            by the CBMA group.<note> The entire
                            corpus is freely available in multiple formats on the website of the
                            CBMA project: <ref target="http://www.cbma-project.eu/bdds2/2014-07-10-14-27-56.html">http://www.cbma-project.eu/bdds2/2014-07-10-14-27-56.html</ref>
                        </note> The size of the complete database is about 29,000 documents
                stocked in cartularies and collections of originals, among which a sub-corpus of
                5,300 items has been annotated with both person and location entities by the CBMA
                scientific team. The document set is mainly comprised of private charters produced
                between the 10th and 14th centuries in Cluniac abbeys, and a small part in
                Cistercian abbeys. The items come from almost 100 small places in Burgundy, and they
                are stored in ten different cartularies (mainly in four: Cartulary A and B from the
                abbey of Cluny, the cartulary of St Vincent of Maçon, the cartulary of the priory of
                Jully-les-Nonnains, and the cartulary from the Cistercian abbey of Vauluisant).<note> Bernard,
                            Auguste &amp; A.Bruel. Recueil des chartes de l'abbaye de Cluny.
                            Imprimerie nationale, 1876; Petit, Ernest. Cartulaire du prieuré de
                            Jully-les-Nonnains. Imprimerie de Georges Rouillé, 1881; Ragut, Camille;
                            Chavot, Th. Cartulaire de Saint-Vincent de Mâcon: connu sous le nom de
                            Livre enchaîné. Impr. d'É. Protat, 1864.</note> These
                cartularies were edited, during the 19th and 20th centuries, with different
                diplomatic and philological editorial standards. (Figure 1 shows how these acts
                spread over time.) </p>
         <p>Typewritten texts digitized in modern editions are the primary source of available
                textual corpora, where elements such as capitalization, punctuation, and development
                of abbreviations have been added, therefore modernizing original sources for easier
                reading. Plain text has been stored in a database, and a team of historical and
                philological experts has manually annotated named entities. Due to lack of time and
                resources, personal and geographical entities have been tagged, but not juridical
                and institutional entities.</p>
         <p>Our gold-standard corpus composed by the CBMA team is mainly distributed through five
                main types of acts: diplomas, charters, bulls, notices, and census lists forming a
                corpus of 5,300 items with 1.2 million words and almost 85,000 named entities. </p>
            <figure>
               <head>Chronological distribution and legal act classification in the CBMA annotated corpus</head>
            	<figDesc>Line graph displaying distribution and legal act classification in the CBMA corpus</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image1.jpeg" style="height: 450px;"/>
               
            </figure>

         <p>The importance of cartularies in medieval history is well known, for they gather
                transcriptions of original records and copies from various kinds of acts: royal
                deeds, privileges, judgments, private business, donations, etc. Such sources prove
                to be formal documents written by following formulaic patterns, which provide them
                with a more or less stereotyped structure. In these discourses, the names of people,
                places, ecclesiastical or other organizations, dates, titles, etc., are specific
                elements connected to the particular context of writing. All the documents are
                written in medieval variants of Latin, which uses special rules and vocabularies,
                and presents much more linguistic variation than classical Latin.</p>
         <p>An example here of these documents may be enlightening. Dated between 994 and 1007 A.
                    D,<note>
                            BERNARD A., BRUEL A., <hi rend="italic">op.cit</hi>, tome 3 : 987-1027, p. 245, n° 2039
                                (Collection de documents inédits sur l'histoire de France. Première
                                série, Histoire politique).</note> this donation act
                to the Cluny abbey begins with a short protocol followed immediately by the
                dispositive indicating the object and purpose of the donation and the participants
                in the act:</p>
         <p>
            <foreign xml:lang="la"><quote rend="block"><emph>In nomine Verbi incarnati. Cuncti noverint populi, quod ego
                    Adalguis dono Domino Deo et sanctis apostolis ejus Petro et Paulo, ad loco
                    Cluniaco, ubi domnus et reverentissimus Odilo abbas magis videtur preesse quam
                    prodesse, pro redemptione omnium peccatorum meorum, ut Dominus dignetur
                    auxiliare in extremi diem judicii.</emph></quote></foreign>
            <note> « In the name of the Incarnate Word. Let
                            all the people know that I, Adalgis, donate to the Lord God and to his
                            holy apostles, Peter and Paul, in the place of Cluny, where the master
                            and most venerable abbot Odilon seems to rule more than to benefit, for
                            the redemption of all of my sins, and for the Lord to assist me in the
                            last day of judgment.There are, then, these
                            things in the county of Macon, in the villa of Tasiaco: that is, in the
                            first place, one <term><foreign xml:lang="la">curtilus</foreign></term> (small estate) with a
                            house and vine and field; and it has boundaries from three sides, from
                            one Rodulfus' land, from another Seguinus' land, from the third Franks'
                            land and from the forth the public road.Another field in other place; it has boundaries from four sides, from a
                            side Rodulfus' land, from another Fulchardus' land and last one the
                            public road. And two small pieces of meadow land; they have boundaries
                            from three sides, from one side Sanctus Quintinus' land, from another
                            Sanctus Martinus' land and from the other the public road. The rectors of Cluny can do whatever they want, from
                            today on, with this donation. However, if any person would want any
                            legal dispute to stand against this donation, let God's wrath fall on
                            him, and let him be submerged alive in hell if he doesn’t return to
                            amendment.Sign(Signum) Adalgis’, woman, who
                            ordered this act to be made and asked to validate it. S(ignum)
                            Ingelelmi, S. Arlei, S. another Arlei. S. Bernardi. S.
                        Ebrardi. »</note>
         </p>
         <p>Coming up next is a detailed description and location of lands and properties that
                are the object of exchange in the donation act. The descriptions always involve
                nominal reference (metonymy) and they follow a hierarchy in land organization, in
                this case, <foreign xml:lang="la"><term>comitum, villa, terra</term></foreign>, inside which we can find
                the land properties classified in specialized parcels, here <term><foreign xml:lang="la">campum, vinea, curtilus, pratum</foreign>,</term> etc.: </p>
         <p>
            <quote rend="block"><foreign xml:lang="la"><emph>Sunt ergo ipsas res in comitatu Matisconensi, in villa Tasiaco: hoc est in primis unum curtile cum domo
               et vinea, et campum; et habet fines de tres partes, de una terra Rodulfo, de alia Seguini, de tertia terra francorum, 
               de quarta via publica. In alio loco alium campum; habet fines de quattuor partes, de una parte terra Rodulfo, de alia
               terra Fulchardo, de tertia via publica. Et in aliis duobus locis duabus peciolas de prato; habent fines de tres partes, 
               de una parte terra Sancti Quintini, de alia Sancti Martini, de alia via publica. </emph></foreign></quote>
         </p>
         <p>Closing the dispositive is a <term><foreign xml:lang="la">sanctio</foreign></term> containing penal clauses
                designed to reinforce and guarantee legal action:</p>
         <p>
            <quote rend="block"><emph><foreign xml:lang="la">De hanc donationem faciunt rectores de Cluniaco quicquid facere
                    voluerint ab hodierno die. Si quis vero ullus homo donationem hanc contrariare
                    voluerit aliquam litem, ira Dei incurrat super illum, et sit demersus in
                    infernum vivus, si ad emendationem non venerit.</foreign></emph></quote>
         </p>
         <p>Finally, there is a two-fold eschatocol with the subscriptions of the donor and of
                witnesses, containing their names and an “S.” for
                <term><foreign xml:lang="la">signum</foreign></term>(signature): </p>
         <p>
            <emph><foreign xml:lang="la"><quote rend="block">S. Adalguis femina, qui hanc cartam fieri jussit et firmare
                    rogavit. S. Ingelelmi. S. Arlei. S. item Arlei. S. Bernardi. S.
                Ebrardi.</quote></foreign></emph>
         </p>
         <p>The writing style, the size and purpose of acts continuously vary, but they are
                follow a similar formulaic pattern. Except in long preambles – part of the
                protocol – where the writers of acts can express ideological motivations of actions
                by using quotation of authority texts, the acts do not include personal or narrative
                details. That gives the impression that we are facing a repetitive and modularly
                constructed source. This <emph>dryness</emph> is a
                necessity in documents that aim to become proofs of rights. The formulary pattern
                shapes the notarial written expression, and it is the named entity that specifies
                and individualizes the document. As we can notice in the above example, conventional
                structures also include hierarchical and referential elements and provide support
                for a dynamic use of named entities in each part of the charter. Indeed, the
                recovery of one named entity can involve the recovery of one piece of a complex
                regional landscape, the name of one tenant of a shared property, one node of a
                familiar or communal network, or one named participant in a long series of
                ecclesiastical transactions. Put together, these pieces can help to rebuild
                topographical indices and villas layouts, to propose social, juridical and economic
                frameworks established around land possession, or to describe a more detailed image
                of economic life in abbeys. From this, we can easily imagine the power of detection
                and recovery of named entities to quickly and extensively examine large databases of
                medieval documentation.</p>
         <p>Conducting research using NER with historical corpora is not
                more complicated than working with Newswire or literature. Indeed, the different
                degrees of difficulty to complete a recognition model in any of these three areas
                comes from the varying degrees of observation necessary to detect main phenomena
                affecting the extraction of linguistic features. Historical literature about Cluniac
                cartularies is not lacking, and a bibliographical inspection can prevent some major
                problems affecting the collection of named entity occurrences. Four main highlights
                must be reported.</p>
         <p>In the first place, because corpus goes from the late 9th century to the mid-13th
                century, we span the process of anthroponymic revolution in western Europe that
                begins in the early 10th century and extends until the
                13th century. This is a process very well described by recent studies <ptr target="#bourin1996"/>. 
            Roughly speaking, the single
                name denomination, a reduction of the Roman format used since early medieval times,
                was replaced around the late 10th century by a new
                tradition using the bi-name with two or more components (usually fathers’ names and
                locatives), and this new tradition was consolidated throughout the 11th and 12th centuries. From
                the mid-12th century on, this formulaic denomination
                adopted more complex modes using periphrasis, familiar references, professions,
                regional origin, even surnames, to form personal names with three to six components.
                The increasing irregularity of names represents one significant challenge to our
                model.</p>
         <p>In the second place, we are often faced with overlapping and ambiguous series of
                entities which arise from three main documentary issues: </p>
         <p>(1) the rise of the <term><foreign xml:lang="la">donatio pro anima</foreign></term> formulary model around
                the beginning of the 10th century. This charter model
                testifying to a property donation to the church takes place within the alms-giving
                doctrine <ptr target="#magnani2002"/>. Because cartularies gather together ecclesiastical property
                documents, a substantial part of our corpora follows this model. With the donation,
                the donor gives a property to a saint, who acts as an intermediary, and not directly
                to the church, and this property becomes part of lands under a saint’s <term><foreign xml:lang="la">dominium</foreign></term>, which is managed by a monastery or an abbey acting
                as a juridical person. In this panorama, charters contain extensive lists of named
                entities mixing personal, geographical and institutional functions under one name
                (ex. <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">rebus Sancti Vincentii Matiscensis, terra de Sancta Maria de
                    Optimo Monte</foreign></emph>, <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">in honore Sancti Petri constructam</foreign></emph>,
                etc.). These nested entities, classified as place names rather than as names of
                persons, introduce a substantial bias factor to the model (See figure 2).</p>
         <p>(2) a significant number of toponyms, starting from the 11th century, occurring as part of the bi-name personal denomination (acting
                as a locative complement). The overlapped entities usually have two or three
                components (ex. <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">Lambertus de Malliaco, Stephano de Cave
                Rupe</foreign></emph>), but in the 13th century it is not rare to
                find entities with four or five components (ex. <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">Guillelmus de
                    Sancti Stephano de Ponte</foreign></emph>). This is a difficult technical problem, because
                disambiguation needs an advanced model able to classify one occurrence into two or
                more classes, and that is not always possible. If we take into account only the
                largest entity (in these cases, a personal name), we could lose thousands of
                associated micro-toponyms.</p>
         <p>(3) the rapid extension of a common vocabulary in cartularies to describe lands,
                properties, and goods, which tended to fix spatial descriptions inside a
                stereotypical textual model. The textual environment uses and reuses concepts, <term><foreign xml:lang="la">formulae</foreign></term>, and word associations arranged in a discourse
                containing parts usually well distinguished (formulary). This can be an essential
                factor of recognition, but it can also become a source of overfitting and
                overgeneralized training on co-occurrences. </p>
         <p>In the third place, the production of the charters covers at least three periods of
                change linked to profound transformations in territorial reality, in the
                organization of writing, and in the legality of acts. Charters from the 10th century, which almost entirely concern ecclesiastical
                patrimony, are very close to the formulary; personal changes and adaptations are
                almost absent. They present long preambles and very precise and descriptive <term><foreign xml:lang="la">dispositio</foreign></term>. In the early 11th
                century, even if the topics of charters do not change, they are partly replaced by
                    <term>notices</term>, which are summaries of the charters drawn up
                more freely. Over the course of this century, numerous transformations in written
                vocabulary relate to profound changes in the spatial and legal structures affecting
                the redaction of charters [Bange 1984]. The broad nature of these changes in Western
                Europe, linked to feudalism, fuelled in 90’s a historiographical debate concerning
                the <term><foreign xml:lang="la">mutatio</foreign></term> of the year 1000 <ptr target="#barthelemy1997"/>. </p>
         <p>In the fourth and last place, documents present a particular state of the language.
                Our four single-century corpora show linguistic features with a high degree of
                heterogeneity, because the documents were written during the course of a
                vernacularization process with progressive emancipation from the rules of classical
                Latin <ptr target="#brunner2009"/>. Much of the inconsistency and arbitrariness encountered during
                construction of an automatic model comes from this issue. The task is even more
                complicated if we consider that scarce NLP resources for Latin are adapted to
                literary texts based on classical Latin and devoted to the extraction of literary or
                philological features <ptr target="#passarotti2014"/>. In fact, the model proposed in this article
                tries to fill a major gap in this NLP research.</p></div>
         <div><head>3.2. Corpus Modification and Extension</head>
         <p>Modifications and adaptations of the CBMA corpus were motivated by questions related
                to the representativeness and robustness of our models. We aim to develop a model
                based on a regional corpus and to investigate whether it can be applied to another
                corpus created in different circumstances or belonging to different areas and
                traditions of writing. </p>
         <p>There are three reasons why we created multiple sub-corpora in our study: </p>
         <p>(i) First, <term><foreign xml:lang="la">scriptoria</foreign></term> are localized in the Burgundy region,
                where Cluniac and Cistercian abbeys were founded, and where they developed their
                influence during the 10th, 11th and 12th centuries. </p>
         <p>(ii) Secondly, the chronological distribution of the corpus is concentrated on the
                10th and 11th centuries, which are the period of the most substantial Cluniac
                production <ptr target="#iognaprat2013"/>. In our corpus, the documentation before the
                10th century is very scarce, and Latin is no longer the common language after
                ca. 1260. </p>
         <p>(iii) Third, the charters have been obtained from ten different editions and twelve
                different cartularies concerning legal transactions from almost 100 small areas. </p>
         <p>In other words, we are confronting a problem that is double in scope: on the one
                hand, we have a central institution (Cluny) that is the recipient of the documents
                and that applies certain corrections and alterations to them when making copies.
                Because the documents come from different areas with different scriptural traditions
                and preferences, the differences are largely authorized, and not the result of
                error. On the other hand, the over-representation of Cluniac and Cistercian charters
                can hide minor stylistic variations coming from smaller institutions.</p>
         <p>In order to study the impact of all of these issues on the quality of our model, we
                performed different cross-validation and evaluation experiments; each one focused on
                a single, isolated aspect: corpus size, temporal variations, and regional
                variations.</p>
         <div><head>3.2.2. Generating sub-corpora </head>
         <p>Several sub-corpora were produced during the course of our experimentations by
                modifying the number of documents and the temporal distribution:</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>The reduction of the size of the training dataset generally affects the
                    accuracy of the model when used upon new data. We tested different sizes of
                    training corpus to estimate the minimal amount of training data that is
                    necessary to obtain good results. With our 5300-document corpus, we experimented
                    with different sizes of training corpus: 4000, 2500, 1500, 1000 and 500
                    documents (we reserved a fifth of the documents in each set to use as a test
                    corpus), and we applied the same training protocols in all cases. These
                    experiments are important not only to the constitution of an extensible model,
                    but also to the formation of a lighter model requiring lower computational
                    resources. </item>
            <item>On the other hand, the purpose of temporal variations
                    is to build a cross-validation environment for testing the robustness of the
                    model on different chronological units, and then validating, or not, the
                    application of the model to a wider temporal range. For this reason, we built
                    century models, that is, learning models using only documents from the same
                    century. The accuracy of this experiment may be questioned because, in many
                    cases, the date of a document’s creation is not certain, and the document is
                    dated, then, using a time interval. This problem was corrected by building
                    sub-corpora, considering a charter inside two corpora if its estimated date was
                    near a transition period. For example, a charter dated around 980-1020 was
                    considered to be in both the 10th- and 11th-century
                    models. Thus, we obtained a biased result in contiguous model comparison due to
                    the portion of shared charters, but, in compensation, we obtained sub-corpora
                    that were more representative of each century, since changes of style or
                    scriptural practices do not follow rigid chronological divisions. The
                    distribution of all these corpora and sub-corpora can be observed in our Table
                    1. </item>
         </list></div>
        <div> <head>3.2.3. Manual annotation of extra corpora </head>
         <p>Nevertheless, both types of the previously mentioned experiments decrease the variety
                in the training corpus, and the features provided to the model can hide specific
                scriptural phenomena. To investigate this issue, an extra corpus of 400 items
                extracted from unlabelled data was tagged, with named entities covering the grey
                chronological areas of the 9th, 12th and 13th centuries. By adding this additional
                corpus to our sub-corpora, we expected to assure a chronological variety of smaller
                corpora and to avoid the loss of scriptural varieties. For that reason, documents
                were chosen in the decades that were the least represented in the original corpus.
                This supplementary corpus was also divided by centuries and each part was added as
                an auxiliary group to the century corpora.</p>
         <p>Taking it even further, corpora and sub-corpora models were trained using charters
                from the same corpus. The robustness of these models had to be compared using
                non-Burgundian charters. To accomplish this task, four new small-sized corpora were
                annotated by hand. These documents were extracted from Parisian, English, Lombard
                and Castilian charters from four regions with an intense charter production
                displaying different scriptural models. They are part of four of the most complete
                medieval charter corpora available online: the Ile-de-France cartulary
                (12th -13th centuries) published by the <ref target="http://elec.enc.sorbonne.fr/cartulaires/">École des Chartes</ref>;
            the <ref target="https://deeds.library.utoronto.ca/cartularies">DEEDS
                    corpus</ref> (10th-13th centuries); the
            <ref target="http://www.lombardiabeniculturali.it/cdlm/">CDML</ref>
            (<title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la">Codice diplomatico della Lombardie Medievale</foreign></title>, 11th-12th centuries) 
            containing ecclesiastical and chancery charters; and the
            <ref target="http://corpuscodea.es/corpus/consultas.php">CODEA (CHARTA)</ref>
             corpus (10th-18th centuries)
                containing documents to map the rise of medieval Spanish. </p>
         <p>The limited size of these sub-corpora (from 70 to 100 charters) made sub-corpora
                formation by century impossible in these cases, but we tried to balance them
                chronologically and to include not only cartulary documents but also some diplomas,
                bulls and administrative acts to increase heterogeneity.</p>
         <table>
            <head>Table
               1: Nº of charters for each century and global features in gold-standard corpus and external corpora</head>
            <row role="label">
               <cell role="label">
                 Century/Corpora
               </cell>
               <cell role="label">ENG-LAND</cell>
               <cell role="label">CASTILE</cell>
               <cell role="label">ILEFRANCE</cell>
               <cell role="label">LOMBARDY</cell>
               <cell role="label">Original
                        Corpus</cell>
               <cell role="label">Modified
                        Corpus</cell>
               <cell role="label">400_Set</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>10th</cell>
               <cell>10</cell>
               <cell>7</cell>
               <cell>9</cell>
               <cell>8</cell>
               <cell>2292</cell>
               <cell>3230</cell>
               <cell>12</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>11th</cell>
               <cell>24</cell>
               <cell>13</cell>
               <cell>23</cell>
               <cell>17</cell>
               <cell>1510</cell>
               <cell>2050</cell>
               <cell>27</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>12th</cell>
               <cell>24</cell>
               <cell>16</cell>
               <cell>54</cell>
               <cell>23</cell>
               <cell>816</cell>
               <cell>860</cell>
               <cell>182</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>13th</cell>
               <cell>12</cell>
               <cell>14</cell>
               <cell>63</cell>
               <cell>2</cell>
               <cell>638</cell>
               <cell>730</cell>
               <cell>149</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Nº Tokens</cell>
               <cell>11110</cell>
               <cell>15616</cell>
               <cell>41608</cell>
               <cell>12441</cell>
               <cell>1096095</cell>
               <cell>1096095</cell>
               <cell>104330</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Nº
                        Entities</cell>
               <cell>1326</cell>
               <cell>1841</cell>
               <cell>3594</cell>
               <cell>1222</cell>
               <cell>84752</cell>
               <cell>84752</cell>
               <cell>8263</cell>
            </row>
         </table></div>
         </div>
        
         <div>

         <head>3.3. CRF modeling</head>
         <div><head>3.3.1. Normalization and segmentation</head>
         <p>This section describes the pre-processing steps applied to all our corpora. First, we
                did a manual validation of doubtful items in the training data, mostly for detecting
                nested, overlapping entities and ill-formed annotations. For example, the
                description of territorial boundaries with abuse of possessive genitive (or
                nominative) forms leads to overlapping entities, but also to entities with unclear
                boundaries, and is due to a much freer order in the phrase and use of declensions
                than in classical Latin (see examples in Table 5). Overlapping entities are usually
                connected to names serving different functions, frequently saints’ names. They can
                refer to a personal name or the name of an abbey, a piece of land, a feudal
                territory, or even a festivity date. On the other hand, the texts from philological
                and diplomatic editions can contain paratextual data such as special characters,
                glosses, titles, etc., that can introduce noise into the model. A process of
                normalization in textual spelling is completed through scripts. This normalization
                decreases error rate and makes the transformation of the original format corpus
                easier.</p>
         <p>We then split the main corpus into three sets necessary for the creation of the
                model, i.e., training set, development set, and test set. We randomly selected a
                training corpus of 4,000 documents (<code>&gt;</code>one million words), a test corpus of 1,000
                documents, a development corpus of 300 documents forming the development set, used
                to avoid overfitting, i.e. a model that is too close to the test set and thus not
                robust to new data. To ensure the chronological presence of documents in each
                sub-corpus, we also tested semi-random distribution by creating clusters of
                documents every 25 years, but this approach did not show significant differences in
                the results. That is why we preferred the random method in order to maintain the
                original distribution of data. The temporal distribution of the three datasets turns
                out to be very similar to the distribution of the entire corpus.</p></div>
         <div><head>3.3.2. Model</head>
         <p>We see our NER problem as a problem of traditional sequence classification, and we
                use the well-known BIO format to represent the data. In this format, each token (in
                our case, each word) is assigned to a BIO class: B-entity, I-entity, and O-entity,
                respectively, representing the beginning (B), continuation (I as <q>inside</q>), or
                absence (O as <q>outside</q>) of named entities (See Table 2). We then apply Conditional
                Random Fields <ptr target="#lafferty2001"/>, one of the most popular methods for this
                category of problems. To apply this supervised machine-learning approach, each word
                in a sentence must be regarded as a token. The entire corpus was converted into a
                tabular format, providing lexical, syntactical, and morphological information at a
                token-level. Each word was represented by the following:</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>TOKEN (original word)</item>
            <item>POS (part-of-speech category)</item>
            <item>LEMMA</item>
            <item>CASE (whether the first letter is in upper or lower case)</item>
            <item>SUFFIX (last three letters of the surface form)</item>
         </list>
         <p>The first three features (TOKEN, POS and LEMMA) were obtained from a version of the
            tool <ref target="http://www.cis.uni-muenchen.de/~schmid/tools/TreeTagger/">TreeTagger</ref>
            adapted to Medio Latin, created by the <ref target="http://www.glossaria.eu/treetagger/">OMNIA</ref> group in
                2013. These three features help the model to consider the grammatical and
                morphological information from the text. The next two columns (CASE and SUFFIX) help
                the classifier to exploit capitalization and the inflected nature of Latin, in which
                the end of the word determines its grammatical function. </p>
         <p>We considered the problem as a two-step classification: the first step extracts the
                personal names, while the second step extracts location names. A single classifier
                extracting personal and location names jointly could not be implemented, as the
                corpus contains a lot of overlapping entities. That is why the last columns of
                Figure 2 list the classes in BIO format. </p>
         
            <figure>
               <head>Example of two and three nested levels of overlapped entities</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image2.jpeg" style="height: 150px;"/>
               <figDesc>Screenshot of a set of rows and columns</figDesc>
            </figure>
         

         <p>The CRF method operates by forming a discriminative model and finding the best state
                assignment from a set of training corpora containing tagged features. That is, given
                a series of labelled observations it constructs an interpretation and from there it
                determines probabilistically the most approximate label for a new unseen sequence
                <ptr target="#wallach2004"/>. As explained above, the corpus has been divided into three different
                sections: training set, validation (development) set, and test set. After each
                iteration on the training set, the learned model is applied to the validation set,
                and the process is stopped when the validation result does not improve anymore
                (<soCalled>early stopping</soCalled>). The test set was reserved to evaluate the performance of the
                model with data that did not participate in the learning phase, thus avoiding any
                bias. </p>
         <p>The features used by the CRF model are specified by a list of patterns determining
                the observation rules for each element (word) of the sequence (document). A token
                feature can be one of the seven columns on the token row, the rows before or after,
                or a combination of these. This allows using the immediate context of each word. The
                pattern that we have written combines unigrams and bigrams in an extended sequence
                of grams (i.e., regarding words one by one or two at a time), combining two forward
                and two backward token-line positions. An efficient feature selection and induction
                by the L-BFGS algorithm was provided by Wapiti <ptr target="#lavergne2010"/> in a
                sequence-labelling toolkit developed at LIMSI-CNRS.</p>
         <table>
            <head>Table 2: Training sample for the sequence “Quod ego Hugo de Berziaco perpendens.” The gray zone indicates
               one single observation (i.e., the word de) combining features from all columns in a window of five tokens 
               (from two tokens before to two tokens after the observed token).</head>
            <row role="label">
               <cell role="label">TOKEN</cell>
               <cell role="label">POS</cell>
               <cell role="label">LEMMA</cell>
               <cell role="label">CASE</cell>
               <cell role="label">SUFFIX</cell>
               <cell role="label">ENTITY</cell>
               <cell role="label">ENTITY</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Quod</cell>
               <cell>CON</cell>
               <cell>Quod</cell>
               <cell>UPPER</cell>
               <cell>Uod</cell>
               <cell>O</cell>
               <cell>O</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>ego <emph>[2,0]</emph>
               </cell>
               <cell>PRO</cell>
               <cell>Ego</cell>
               <cell>LOWER</cell>
               <cell>Ego</cell>
               <cell>O</cell>
               <cell>O</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Hugo
                        <emph>[1,0]</emph>
               </cell>
               <cell>NAM</cell>
               <cell>-</cell>
               <cell>UPPER</cell>
               <cell>ugo</cell>
               <cell>B-PERS</cell>
               <cell>O</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>de <emph>[0,0]</emph>
               </cell>
               <cell>PRE <emph>[0,1]</emph>
               </cell>
               <cell>de <emph>[0,2]</emph>
               </cell>
               <cell>LOWER <emph>[0,3]</emph>
               </cell>
               <cell>de <emph>[0,4]</emph>
               </cell>
               <cell>I-PERS <emph>[0,5]</emph>
               </cell>
               <cell>O <emph>[0,6]</emph>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Berziaco [-1,0]
                    </cell>
               <cell>NAM</cell>
               <cell>-</cell>
               <cell>UPPER</cell>
               <cell>aco</cell>
               <cell>I-PERS</cell>
               <cell>B-LOC</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>perpendens [-2,0]
                    </cell>
               <cell>VBE</cell>
               <cell>Perpendeo</cell>
               <cell>LOWER</cell>
               <cell>ens</cell>
               <cell>O</cell>
               <cell>O</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>,</cell>
               <cell>PON</cell>
               <cell>,</cell>
               <cell>LOWER</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
            </row>
         </table></div>
         </div>
         </div>
         <div>
        
           <head>4. Evaluation</head>
<div>
         <head>4.1. Model experimentations</head>
         <p>All models were evaluated with traditional precision, by recall and F1-measure with
            two different configurations, as implemented in the tool <ref target="https://bitbucket.org/nicta_biomed/brateval">BratEval</ref>: <q>exact
                match</q> counts a true positive if an extracted named entity has the correct type
                (person or location) and if the boundaries of the extracted entity match perfectly
                with the gold standard. On the other hand, <q>partial match</q> counts a true positive
                even if the extracted entity shares only a partial overlap with the gold standard. </p>
        <div> <head>4.1.1. General model</head>
         <p>We first ran our model trained with the entire training and development CBMA set,
                regardless of its temporal and geographical characteristics. This model achieves an
                exact match F1-measure of 0.95 and a partial match of 0.96 on test data for people’s
                names; it achieves an exact match of 0.91 and a partial match of 0.92 for location
                names. All experiments show a similar result in precision and recall parameters. The
                difference between exact and partial results is not more than two points, confirming
                that boundary detection is not very problematic, although it is often a hard task in
                NER.</p>
           <table>
            <head>Table 3: Best current ratio recognition expressed in BIO-tag ratio of recognition and number of occurrences according 
               to Brateval tool which provides a pairwise comparison of annotation sets in Brat format. The tool displays two results: 
               Exact match (EM)when entities agree in type and extension, and 
               Partial match (PM) when entities agree in type but not in extension.  True positive (TP), False Positive 
               (FP), False negative (FN), Recall (Rc), Precision (Pr) and F1-measure</head>
            <row role="label">
               <cell role="label">Personal
                        name</cell>
               <cell role="label">PR</cell>
               <cell role="label">RC</cell>
               <cell role="label">F1</cell>
               <cell role="label">TP</cell>
               <cell role="label">FP</cell>
               <cell role="label">FN</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>B-PERS</cell>
               <cell>0.95</cell>
               <cell>0.96</cell>
               <cell>0.96</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>I-PERS</cell>
               <cell>0.88</cell>
               <cell>0.92</cell>
               <cell>0.90</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Partial
                        match</cell>
               <cell>0.95</cell>
               <cell>0.97</cell>
               <cell>0.96</cell>
               <cell>12965</cell>
               <cell>615</cell>
               <cell>291</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Exact
                        match</cell>
               <cell>0.93</cell>
               <cell>0.96</cell>
               <cell>0.95</cell>
               <cell>12729</cell>
               <cell>851</cell>
               <cell>529</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Location
                        name</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>B-LOC</cell>
               <cell>0.91</cell>
               <cell>0.93</cell>
               <cell>0.92</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>I-LOC</cell>
               <cell>0.81</cell>
               <cell>0.80</cell>
               <cell>0.80</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Partial
                        match</cell>
               <cell>0.92</cell>
               <cell>0.92</cell>
               <cell>0.92</cell>
               <cell>7171</cell>
               <cell>590</cell>
               <cell>550</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Exact
                        match</cell>
               <cell>0.90</cell>
               <cell>0.91</cell>
               <cell>0.91</cell>
               <cell>7035</cell>
               <cell>726</cell>
               <cell>681</cell>
            </row>
         </table></div>

         <div><head>4.1.2. Century models</head>
         <p>Tables 4 (personal names) and 5 (location names) show the result of our
                cross-validation experiments on century models. For each one of the four considered
                centuries (from the 10th to the
                13th centuries), we applied a model
                trained on one century to another century set. Cross-results did not show a
                considerable heterogeneity, and the results are very close to those obtained with
                big-sized models. The main differences are detected while evaluating datasets and
                models formed on the basis of charters from the 10th and 13th centuries. Here there
                are three highlights: first, the 10th-century model
                constructed from the largest dataset gives us the worst results when applied to the
                other charters, especially to the 12th- and 13th-century datasets; second, the application of the
                    10th-, 11th-, and 12th-century models to the 13th-century dataset offers the lowest compared performance; third, the
                worst individual performance is obtained by crossing the 10th-century model with the dataset of the 13th-century charters.</p>
         <p>All this suggests two major observations: (i) there are no significant gaps in the
                variety of features of corpora modelled on four centuries of charters, thus
                maintaining a regular detection of naming phenomena that produces results similar to
                those of single-century models; (ii) in consequence, detection problems are
                concentrated at a feature-level in irregular denominations and in severe changes in
                the name's composition (or in its textual disposition) that have taken place in the
                    13th but not in the 10th
                century or vice versa.</p></div>
         <div><head>4.1.3. European charters </head>
         <p>Tables 6 and 7 (corresponding to names of persons and locations) show the results
                obtained by the application of our different models to the <soCalled>foreign</soCalled> corpora
                described in section 3.2. We apply to these regional corpora the models trained with
                the general CBMA datasets (two models with different sizes) and the four,
                single-century sub-corpora trained from the same dataset. The six results obtained
                show great proximity among them. General models provide better coverage, normally
                around 3%-5% superior to the century models, and again, we can see that the model
                trained on 1,500 charters shows a small decrease in performance (1-2 points)
                compared to the full model. The use of a smaller set of annotated documents could be
                acceptable. </p>
         <p>The performance of general model is quite appropriate: PERS partial-match recognition
                is between 94% and 93%, and exact-match recognition shows results between 87% and
                81% for the four regional corpora. In the case of LOC entities, the partial-match
                recognition reaches results between 85% and 82%, and exact-match recognition is
                between 81% and 73%. Analysing only the numerical results from single-century
                models, we noticed many similarities to the results obtained in previous century
                model evaluations: (i) the best performance models are the central models from the
                11th and 12th centuries; (ii) boundary models (from the 10th and 13th centuries) are less adequate for
                recognition, especially of compound entities; and (iii) the model from the 10th
                century, trained with the largest number of documents, offers the lowest efficiency
                on foreign corpora recognition. </p>
         <p>We also noticed a correlation between single-century models and regional corpora. For
                example, the Parisian corpus, composed mostly of later medieval charters, offered
                slightly higher numbers when evaluated with the 12th-
                and 13th-century models; the Lombard corpus,
                concentrated in the 11th and 12th centuries without any 13th-century
                charters, showed lower performance when evaluated by 13th century model, while the English and Hispanic corpora, with the most
                balanced chronology (the Hispanic corpus is not really an organic corpus), presented
                greater distance between partial and exact matches when evaluated with all four of
                the century models. </p>
         <p>To summarize, the similar results obtained from the six models help to reinforce the
                hypothesis about the results of century model evaluations: (i) there are long series
                of features in documents that resist changes in the chronology, size and origin of
                the charters, features that are better treated by an iterative model based on the
                formulary and on established scriptural traditions, assuring thereby an initially
                acceptable ratio of recognition; (ii) there are more discrete sets of features,
                added to previously mentioned ones, determined by local specificities, document
                changes and highly specific phenomena, which become the primary source of errors. In
                addition to these, the set of particularities from the four external corpora were
                treated without a considerable decrease in the general performance, suggesting that
                there are global similarities in the composition of the name that are much stronger
                than differences suggested by each regional tradition.</p>
         
            <figure>
               <head>Table
                  4: Accuracy scores obtained on cross evaluation for names of persons and places using century and general models on European and century set test.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image3.png"/>
               <figDesc>Screenshot of a table</figDesc>
            </figure></div>
</div>
         
         <div><head>4.2. Match and error analysis</head>
         <p>High performance on a partial match means that the model detects the presence of
                named entities no matter what size they are. In the case of single-named entities,
                there is only one single target element, and we can assume that the results in the
                detection are almost the same as the classification of the entity. In the case of
                complex entities (two or more components), complete classification is less efficient
                than detection by around 5-10 points (the difference between partial and exact
                matching), but there is still high performance at the task of recognition. </p>
         <p>These results can become more meaningful if we remark three significant situations
                detected concerning named entities in our corpus and in evaluated corpora:</p>
         <p>(1) As we mentioned above (section 3.1), the most widely diffused type of complex
                name is formed by the association of two or three single entities. In fact, around
                86% of the compound personal names in the CBMA corpus have between two and three
                parts. This denomination format is generally composed of
                <emph>name + de + toponym</emph> (ex. <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">Bertrannus de Verziaco</foreign></emph>). But in other cases, this double name
                format can be produced though declension, syntagmatic or periphrastic denominations,
                or even adding a second component using a genitive or nominative. There is a
                juxtaposition of two single names in the <emph>name + name</emph> (or <emph>noun</emph>) or <emph>name + nexus + name</emph>
                (or <emph>noun</emph>) formats (ex. <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">Rudericus Didaci, Bellonus Mangacii, Gariardus de loco
                    Antimiano</foreign></emph>). </p>
         <p>(2) From the 11th century on, more than half of the geographical entities detected
                form part of a personal name. The <emph>name + de + toponym</emph> format
                enjoyed great success until the 13th century. In this format, we generally consider
                the last name as a location indicator (usually a micro-toponym or hagio-toponym),
                which means that well-performed boundary detection for a double name involves full
                geographical entity detection (that is a B-PERS + <emph>de</emph> + B-LOC
                pattern).</p>
         <p>(3) Complex and single personal and geographic entities are closely related to an
                extensive and precise vocabulary of co-occurring words. This is a necessity in legal
                texts about properties where donors must be clearly identified, properties must be
                well-described, and signatures and signs of validations must be included. Lands and
                people are identified by using terms and titles of presentation expressed in a
                common vocabulary that responds to a spatial and social reality, but also to the
                uses signified by the formulary.</p>
         <p>According to the evaluation results, the model can detect the apparition of entities
                with up to 95% efficiency and classify them with an accuracy of up to 90% in the
                case of single entities as well as in the case of the most extended forms of
                composed entities: the double locative name and the double name using the <emph>de</emph> particle, the genitive, or any other single nexus. </p>
         <p>In this respect, we can confirm a model able, on the one hand, to classify with high
                performance both the single names used almost exclusively until the 10th century and
                the most widely diffused name format in medieval times since the 11th century: the
                double name in all its variations. We can also confirm a model able, on the other
                hand, to recognize the non-complex entities associated with a large, social, and
                professional vocabulary. (See Table 4.)</p>
         <p>Furthermore, as long as the double name maintains a two- or three-part compound
                format, the model has a high level of efficiency (90% or more) due to limited
                variations and not very complex n-gram observations. Providing information related
                to lemma and termination (or declension), capital letters and grammar features is
                usually enough for the model to accomplish named entity recognition on compound
                names. </p>
         <p>Taking that into account, the most frequent errors in recognition must necessarily be
                linked to long, complex denominations and specific phenomena such as grammatical
                forms in the Latin phrases or to changes in underlying textual structures. In Table
                5, we can see displayed some examples of frequent errors made by the system. For
                example, in Lombard texts the prevalence of periphrastic denominations produces a
                lower ratio for the recovery of inside parts of named entities because of the high
                frequency of non-entity words between names (see examples 1 and 2). In 11th- and 12th-century
                charters, the increasing use of the genitive in naming entities produces a large
                group of entities without particles. In addition, the coexistence in medieval Latin
                of the inflectional rules of classical Latin, the expansion in the use of
                prepositions, and the gradual extinction of Latin cases can all lead the model to
                some confusions (see example 4). </p>
         <p>It is especially hard to handle the apparition and rapid expansion of institutional
                names under saints’ avocations in diplomatic donation models in the
                10th century due to overlapping
                between personal, institutional, and place names (examples 6 and 8). The model does
                not work well with overlapped entities because most machine learning classifiers are
                not designed to attribute more than one class to each instance. In that sense, the
                confusion between place names and personal names must be solved by designating one
                class for each entity. </p>
         <p>The overgeneralization of very common particles (such as
                <emph>de</emph> in compound entities), as well as of
                location trigger words (such as <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">terra, serum, pars, domus, manus,
                    apud</foreign></emph>) and also of personal co-occurrent words (such as
                <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">episcopus, beatus, dominus, sacerdos, miles</foreign></emph>, etc.)
                can lead to false positives when the model finds an entity different than that
                expected, as illustrated by examples 5 and 7. On the other hand, because of the more
                flexible nature of the phrase order in Latin, the system can classify as inside
                entity (I-PERS, I-LOC) those nouns that are single-named entities or non-name
                entities.</p>
         <p>Finally, in the course of all these experiments, we detected an important number of
                errors related to the original format of the documents. These texts are not raw
                data, and they contain many added features characteristic of a philological,
                palaeographical, or diplomatic edition, such as special characters, textual gaps,
                abbreviations, headlines, and orthographic redundancy (example 9). Not all this
                information is relevant to the model, and this can produce an important amount of
                noisy training data. Automatic and manual cleaning can resolve a significant part of
                this problem.</p>
         
            <figure>
               <head>Table
                  5: Examples of frequent errors made by the system on European charters. The first column of each example shows the text excerpt;
                  the second and third column shows the gold standard for location and person names, and the last column shows the system automatic classification.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image4.jpeg"/>
               <figDesc>Screenshot of a table</figDesc>
            </figure></div>
         </div>
         
         <div>

            <head>5. Discussion</head>

         <p>In this work, we use different types of information to build a model for automatic
                named entity recognition: grammatical categories, lemma, case, entity categorization
                and n-gram observations. A model based on a probabilistic CRF-approach that extracts
                correlations dependencies between this information and observations leads us to high
                performance in the process of categorizing entities. High percentages in the
                results, after having tested the model on corpora of different geographical origins
                and different periods, demonstrate that the linguistic and statistical algorithmic
                approach has proven to be robust. In fact, the results are quite conclusive, but the
                evaluation process involves an important level of heterogeneity needing an
                explanation that exceeds the most technical level and requires the use of humanistic
                knowledge. We need to answer why a model created from a regional corpus can obtain a
                high recognition rate on medieval documents from other regions, chronologies and
                even traditions. </p>
         <p>Thus, references to the historical background, social usages and scriptural
                variations can provide a more meaningful explanatory context, enriching the evidence
                obtained by machine-learning methods. Reviewing the literature about historical
                names is a good first step. Anthroponymic studies suggest a double movement in
                Western Europe after the 10th century: first, a
                reduction of name stock and consequently a reduction of the variety of common names;
                and second, an extension of double names in variable forms: <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">nomen
                    paternum</foreign></emph> (name + name of father), locatives (name + place-name) and
                nicknames (name + profession, qualities or titles). In fact, the nature of the
                second element in bi-names distinguishes several naming traditions in Europe. In
                France, the meridional tradition incorporated the <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">nomen
                   paternum</foreign></emph> quickly, that is, the hereditary second name coming from the
                father, but central and northern regions (like Burgundy and Île-de-France) developed
                a preference for locatives and periphrastic forms <ptr target="#bourin1996"/>. </p>
         <p>Single-name forms disappeared in the 12th century, and traditional and local names
                were replaced by the universal Christian or princely names. At the same time, in the
                northern Hispanic regions and Castile, the tradition promoted an incorporation of
            <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">nomen
               paternum</foreign></emph>, formed with the declension in the
                original name of the father (v.g. <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">Gundisaluo Roderici, Rodericus
                    Ferrandi</foreign></emph>) and, later, a composition of three names in association with
                locatives and nicknames (v.g <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">Ferrando Sanchiz de Fenosa</foreign></emph>)
                <ptr target="#sopena1996"/>. Norman traditions heavily influenced the central and southern regions
            of England, which adopted double locative or triple names and <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">nomen
               paternum</foreign></emph> formed by the second name of the father (v.g <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">Guidonis Nerioli de Buxiaco, Aimo de Monte Pauonis</foreign></emph>) 
            <ptr target="#billy1995"/>. The tradition operating in the Lombardy region presents the same phenomena of
                duplication in anthroponymic elements during the 11th century, but prefers a system
                that promotes a more broadly referential second name (v.g. <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">Otonnis
                    qui dicitur de Suso, Grioulum filium Lafranci Caipeni</foreign></emph>) which takes the form
                of a periphrastic composition promoting surnames, geographical origin, and
                ancestor’s filiations <ptr target="#corrarati1994"/>. </p>
         <p>Concerning geographical names, we must make a distinction between landscape entities
                and nominal entities. The first are used to describe or to locate a property,
                whereas the second appear as a locative complement of a compound name. Indeed, a
                large proportion of geographical entities is linked to the rise of double names
                between the 11th and 13th
                centuries, when the locative complement became a form of familial or personal social
                distinction. The expansion and precise definition in Europe of the <emph>name + locative</emph> combination through use of the <emph>de</emph>
                particle (genitive or nominative without preposition) produced a very strong
                increase in binomial name entities combining personal and geographical components.
                This is a process that quickly produces great variety by proposing the origin,
                residence, feudal, or ethnic place as locative complement (v.g. <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">Iohannes Allemanus</foreign></emph>) 
            completing the information about an individual person.
                In fact, all these locatives are generally real places, but they are usually defined
                as hagio-toponyms, old toponyms, and micro-toponyms hardly connected with real
                spaces on a map.</p>
         <p>Nevertheless, most of the geographical entities are not associated with a personal
                name but correspond to the first above-mentioned type: landscape and territorial
                names. They are the names of a <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">terra</foreign></emph>, a 
            <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">villa</foreign></emph>, a <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">pagus</foreign></emph>, an <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">ager</foreign></emph>, a
                river, a building, a church, a monastery, a so-called place, etc. Names and master
                words or co-occurrences are closely related in charters (see Table 5) because
                cartularies produce, by classifying records geographically and transcribing them in
                a codex, a spatial knowledge of ecclesiastical estates which uses many of the same
                global geographical entities <ptr target="#chastang2007"/>. The first effect of this is the
                constant reference in formulary charters to a well-delineated territorial space, a
                cadastral order that today is almost impossible to reconstruct due to numerous
                information gaps <ptr target="#bange1984"/>. </p>
         <table>
            <head>Table
               5: Co-occurrences or presenting words (appositional, periphrastic and attributive nouns) of personal and geographical named entities. This table corresponds in the broadest sense to a jurisdictional and social vocabulary of personal and geographic categorization.
            </head>
            <row role="label">
               <cell role="label">Personal
                            entities</cell>
               <cell role="label">Geographical
                            entities</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Professions and social activities:
                        <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">camerarius, cantor, magister,
                            miles, monachus, notarius, sacerdos</foreign></emph>
               </cell>
               <cell>
                  <p>Landform spaces:
                            <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">boscus, fluvius, locus, mons,
                                nemus, pratus, rivus, silva</foreign></emph>
                  </p>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Secular and religious titles:
                        <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">abbas, beatus, comes, domnus,
                            dominus, dux, episcopus, papa, presbyter, princeps, rex</foreign></emph>
               </cell>
               <cell>Seigniorial and ecclesiastical division of sedentary lands:
                        <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">ager, conventus, curtilus, domus,
                            feudus, grangia, mansus, pagus, vicus</foreign></emph>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Dignities and Nicknames:
                        <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">benedictus, brunus, grossus,
                            humilis, largus, normandus, paganus, servus, venerabilis</foreign></emph>
               </cell>
               <cell>Legal and jurisdictional division:
                        <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">area, castrum, civitas, diocesis,
                            ecclesia, provincia, sedes, terra, villa</foreign></emph>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Periphrastic nexus:
                        <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">appelatus, cognomen, dictus, nomen,
                            vocatus</foreign></emph>
               </cell>
               <cell>Landmarks and micro-spaces:
                        <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">altar, atrium, capella, capitulum,
                            castellum, cenobium, domus, ecclesia, hospital, monasterium</foreign></emph>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Words with nominal value:
                        <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">alius, ego, filius, frater, idem, nepos,
                            signum (S.), uxor</foreign></emph>
               </cell>
               <cell>Prepositions, adverbs or global locative value terms:
                        <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">ad, apud, fines, inter, manus,
                            meridies, pars, pro, supra, vocabulum</foreign></emph>
               </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
                    <p>According to the evaluation of our general model, the results obtained in B-LOC
                recognition (geographical Begin-entity) are just five points below (90% compared to
                95%) the best performance obtained in B-PERS (personal Begin-entity). That means
                that performance on detection of geographical entities and the classification of
                single entities is almost as excellent as obtained on personal names. Geographical
                entities usually appear in less complex forms than the entities of the name, which
                raises the percentage of this first result. But performance decreases almost ten
                points if inside entities (I-PERS and I-LOC) are compared (90% and 80%), which
                indicates that elements involved in composed geographical entities are harder to
                model. This proportionality is more or less maintained in evaluating foreign corpora
                (see Tables 6 and 7). All results are, on average, acceptable, but, once more, the
                problems are concentrated on inside-entities, as is shown when comparing partial and
                exhaustive Brateval results. </p>
         <p>The most common format for complex entities is the double name (bi-name), but as we
                have seen, our model can handle well the recognition of this prolific format and its
                variants, which suggests that we need to examine more complex forms of composed
                entities. Thus, regarding the apparition of complex geographical entities, we notice
                different situations depending on regional traditions. Concerning personal names,
                Castile and Southern England are regions where the triple name expansion takes place
                one century before it does in Central France. Both regions form bi-names with two
                nominal components, and the incorporation of locatives entails triple or quadruple
                names (v.g. <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">Guilielmi de Sancto Satiro</foreign></emph>, <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">Martinus Garciez de Stallaia</foreign></emph>). 
            In Lombardy, the formation of complex names
                never takes root, but the addition of periphrastic composition (through <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">dicitur, nominatur, filius, de loco</foreign></emph>, etc.) 
            creates some long
                entities impossible to dissolve. Almost the same thing happens in central French
                regions where representative quantities in triple names are not present before the
                    13th century. But the use of locatives and
                periphrastic forms since the 11th century contributes to
                the apparition of complex entities of up to five elements (v.g. <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">Adalbertus de vico Camonaco filii Iohanni</foreign></emph>).</p>
         <p>Nonetheless, the most complex entity format is related to overlapped and nested
                entities (see Section 4.2). Personal entities, acting as possessive genitive or
                nominative, can be found fulfilling the function of a geographical entity in the
                land and boundary land descriptions in donations, purchases, inheritances, or legal
                disputes (v.g <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">a mane terra Bertrannus; sub domi ipsius
                    Ansaldi</foreign></emph>). Furthermore, since the 10th century,
                saints and ecclesiastical institutions were currently present in the <term><foreign xml:lang="la">formulae</foreign></term> of the
                <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">donationes pro anima</foreign></emph>, where they
                performed the function of intermediate receptors and defenders of properties. Their
                presence in charters contributes to creating complex entities with four or more
                elements taking, associating, or superimposing a saint’s name, an institutional
                name, and a geographical name.</p>
         <p>In part, this complexity is, even more, a result of medieval variants of the Latin
                language. The gradual expansion of use of the genitive since the 11th century
                created large groups of entities without intermediate particles; at the same time,
                there was an increase in prepositions and the extinction of many Latin case endings,
                all of which lead the model, in many instances, to recognize the words of
                non-entities as named entities. Latin phrase order is irregular, and exceptions in
                medieval variants are almost infinite; consequently, training taking into account
                grammatical rules, co-occurrences, and context can generate many false positives
                even with an approach that is not rule-based.</p>
         <p>The difficulty in recognizing entities involved in these complex phenomena lies not
                so much in their quantity as in their extensive consequences. The percentage of
                complex entities (more than three elements) does not exceed 11% of the total in our
                corpora, but the statistical impact on results due to bad recognition of such
                entities is more elevated when they are composed of more than four elements: B-PERS
                + (3) I-PERS (that means three inside-entity errors for each non-recovered entity).
                Moreover, the impact of these phenomena is increased if we consider that the
                original mark-up of our database, in which non-physical personal names and juridical
                actors are classified as place-names, can elevate the number of false positives in
                automatic recognition of complex place-names.</p>
         <p>The influence of these circumstances is more evident in the different tests of
                temporal variability that we have performed. On one hand, the results of century
                models applied to European charters are very stable, which confirms, first, the
                presence of important homogeneous structures in name compositions and formulaic
                patterns and, second, the presence of a larger stock of name compositions than we
                would have expected in the Burgundy region in each century, which provides more
                variety in the training process. On the other hand, in all cases, the model
                developed with charters from the 10th century, when the
                double name was not yet established, is less adequate for recognition in other
                centuries; at the same time, the models from the 10th,
                    11th, and 12th centuries
                are less efficient when used on 13th century charters,
                because larger and more complex compositions increased in this century. </p>
         <p>Finally, the excellent statistical results in spite of temporal variability also show
                that there is a high degree of iteration in late medieval formulaic discourse. This
                characteristic helped us to form a valid model starting from an incomplete and not
                very structured corpus. We obtained an acceptable ratio of recognition when we
                tested the model on charters representing different legal acts: donations,
                transactions, royal orders, deeds and notarial actions from four European regions.
                That leads us to assume a vast radius of application for our model on Western
                European legal acts of various types. In addition, single-century models do not show
                substantial improvements compared to the results of general models when applied to
                documents from each century, which confirms that our general model can provide the
                best ratios of recognition along a temporal line of at least four centuries, from
                the 10th to the
                13th century.</p>
         </div>
         <div>

            <head>6. Conclusion </head>
         
         <p>We present a named entities recognition model applied to medieval Latin charters, and
                we implement an adequate evaluation environment. The model produced from long data
                sets of Burgundian medieval charters is able to accomplish a high ratio of
                recognition of the personal and geographical names of medieval Latin documentary
                sources, especially from the 10th to the 13th century. The evaluation is focused on
                demonstration of the robustness of the model in diverse situations. We performed
                different cross-validation experiments modifying size, chronology, typology, and
                regional origin in several sub-corpora, obtaining a very acceptable ratio of
                recognition in each case, which confirms that our model has a wide range of
                applications with respect to medieval documentary sources. By crossing results, we
                can confirm that the model supports an accurate semi-automatization of named
                entities recognition and, in consequence, that it can provide a primordial level of
                structuration of data, saving many human efforts.</p>
         <p>Validation and cross-experiments also show us that questions about representativeness
                in the learning model do not generate insurmountable issues. Our discussion tries to
                confirm that the most significant problems in recognition are an expression of the
                intense dependency of data on complex historical, social and scriptural conditions,
                and not only on linguistic or statistical concerns. Several historical and
                philological conclusions helped us to refine and normalize algorithmic approaches
                and to understand numerical results provided by the machine. This also led to
                corrections of the original dataset and to complement it by the integration of the
                new annotated datasets that we have produced during this project.</p>
         <p>The use of this NER model can be fruitful in different fields of research in the
                Humanities, including, in particular, recovery information systems, automatic
                indexing and distant reading. Since named entities are not subject to a lot of
                variation, they can be used as keywords and meaningful terms improving internal
                workflows of search engines. A NER model which can automatically spot these keywords
                within a large dataset, becomes a useful tool to speed up, classify and refine
                requests on ancient documents that are available in plain text editions. The
                recovery of entities, acting as nodes of action, can serve as a first step in the
                production of historical GIS-maps, and the reconstruction of event timelines or
                social networks. These widely used forms of data visualization can benefit from
                automatic tagging while automatic tagging can also help to solve questions
                concerning the production or the dating of ancient texts by providing data that
                scholars have traditionally used in their textual or manuscripts studies – mention
                of persons, places, words or formulas. Since it enriches datasets with specific
                linguistic and semantic features, our NER model can even be integrated into a
                pipeline of tasks, such as topic classification of ancient texts, automatic
                handwriting recognition or word sense disambiguation.</p>
         <p>* This project is supported by the "IDI 2016" project
                    funded by the IDEX Paris-Saclay, ANR-11-IDEX-0003-02</p>
         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="abacha2011" label="Abacha et al. 2011">
               Abacha, A. B, Zweigenbaum, Pierre. (2011).
               <title rend="quotes">Medical entity recognition: A comparison of semantic and statistical methods.</title> In
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of BioNLP</title> 2011 Workshop. Association for Computational Linguistics, p.
               56-64.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bange1984" label="Bange 1984">
               Bange, F. (1984). <title rend="quotes">L'ager et la villa : structures du
               paysage et du peuplement dans la région mâconnaise à la fin du Haut Moyen Age
               (IXe-XIe siècles).</title> Annales. Economies, sociétés, civilisations, 39(03),
               pp.529-569.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="barthelemy1997" label="Barthélemy 1997">
               Barthélemy, D. (1997). <title rend="quotes"> La mutation de l'an mil,
               a-t-elle eu lieu ?</title> <title rend="italic">En Annales. Histoire, Sciences Sociales.</title> Cambridge University
               Press, p. 767-777.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="billy1995" label="Billy 1995">
               Billy, P. (1995). <title rend="quotes">Nommer en Basse-Normandie aux
               Xle-XVe siècles.</title> <title rend="italic">Cahier des Annales de Normandie</title>, 26(1), pp.223-232. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bollacker2008" label="Bollacker at al. 2008">
               Bollacker, K., Evans, C., Paritosh, P.,
               Sturge, T. and Taylor, J. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Freebase: A Collaboratively Created Graph Database
               for Structuring Human Knowledge.</title> <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2008 ACM SIGMOD International
               Conference on Management of Data</title>, ACM, pp. 1247-1250.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bourin1996" label="Bourin 1996">
               Bourin, Monique. (1996). <title rend="quotes">France du Midi et France du
               Nord : deux systèmes anthroponymiques? L’anthroponymie document de l’histoire
               sociale des mondes méditerranéens médiévaux.</title> <title rend="italic">Publications de l'École française de
               Rome</title>, 226(1), pp.179-202. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brooke2016" label="Brooke et al. 2016">
               Brooke, J., Hammond, A., Baldwin, T. (2016).
               <title rend="quotes">Bootstrapped text-level named entity recognition for literature.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
               the 54th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</title> (Volume 2:
               Short Papers), pp. 344-350.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brunner2009" label="Brunner 2009">Brunner, T. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Le passage aux langues vernaculaires dans les actes de la pratique en Occident.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Le Moyen Age</title>, vol.
               115, no 1, pp. 29-72.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="budassi2016" label="Budassi et al. 2016">BUDASSI, M., PASSAROTTI, M. (2016). 
               <title rend="quotes">Nomen Omen. Enhancing the Latin Morphological Analyser Lemlat with an Onomasticon.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 10th SIGHUM Workshop on Language
               Technology for Cultural Heritage, Social Sciences, and Humanities</title>. pp. 90-94.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chastang2007" label="Chastang 2007">
               Chastang, P. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Du locus
               au territorium. Quelques remarques sur l’évolution des catégories en usage dans le
               classement des cartulaires méridionaux au XIIe siècle.</title> In <title rend="italic">Annales du Midi : revue
               archéologique, historique et philologique de la France méridionale</title>, Tome 119, N°260,
               pp. 457-474.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cohen2004" label="Cohen et al. 2004">
               Cohen, W. W., and Sarawagi, S. (2004). <title rend="quotes">Exploiting
               dictionaries in named entity extraction: combining semi-markov extraction
               processes and data integration methods.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the tenth ACM SIGKDD
               international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining</title>, pp.
               89-98.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="corrarati1994" label="Corrarati 1994">
               Corrarati, P. (1994). <title rend="quotes">Nomi, individui, famiglie a
               Milano nel secolo XI. Mélanges de l'Ecole française de Rome.</title> <title rend="italic">Moyen-Age</title>, 106(2),
               pp. 459-474.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="curran2003" label="Curran et al. 2003">
               Curran, J. R., Clark, S. (2003). <title rend="quotes">Language
               independent NER using a maximum entropy tagger.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the seventh
               conference on Natural language learning</title> at HLT-NAACL 2003-Volume 4. Association for
               Computational Linguistics, p. 164-167.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="duby1953" label="Duby 1953">
               Duby, Georges (1953). <title rend="quotes">La société aux XIe et XIIe
               siècles dans la région mâconnaise.</title> <title rend="italic">Bibliothèque Générale de l’Ecole Pratique des
               Hautes Etudes</title>, 6e section, Paris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="durrell2007" label="Durrell 2007">
               Durrell, M. (2007). <title rend="quotes">GerManC: a historical corpus of
               German 1650-1800: Full Research Report.</title> <title rend="italic">ESRC End of Award Report</title>,
               RES-000-22-1609.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eger2015" label="Eger et al. 2015">
               Eger, S., Vor der Brück, T., Mehler, A. (2015).
               <title rend="quotes">Lexicon-assisted tagging and lemmatization in Latin: A comparison of six taggers and
               two lemmatization methods.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 9th SIGHUM Workshop on Language
               Technology for Cultural Heritage, Social Sciences, and Humanities</title> (LaTeCH 2015), pp.
               105-113.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ehrmann2016" label="Ehrmann et al. 2016">
               Ehrmann, Maud, et al. (2016). Diachronic
               <title rend="quotes">Evaluation of NER Systems on Old Newspapers.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 13th Conference
               on Natural Language Processing</title> (KONVENS 2016)). <title rend="quotes">Bochumer Linguistische
               Arbeitsberichte</title>, p. 97-107.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="elson2010" label="Elson et al. 2010">
               Elson, D. K., Dames, N., McKeown, K. R.
               (2010). <title rend="quotes">Extracting social networks from literary fiction.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 48th
               annual meeting of the association for computational linguistics</title>. Association for
               Computational Linguistics, p. 138-147.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eltyeb2014" label="Eltyeb et al. 2014">
               Eltyeb, S. and Salim, N. (2014). <title rend="quotes">Chemical
               named entities recognition: a review on approaches and applications.</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of
               cheminformatics</title>, vol. 6, no 1, p. 17.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="erdmann2016" label="Erdmann et al. 2016">
               Erdmann, A., Brown, C., Joseph, B., Janse,
               M., Ajaka, P., Elsner, M., and de Marneffe, M. C. (2016). <title rend="quotes">Challenges and Solutions
               for Latin Named Entity Recognition.</title> <title rend="italic">LT4DH 2016</title>, 85.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="frontini2016" label="Frontini et al. 2016">
               Frontini, F., Brando, C., Riguet, M., Jacquot, C., and Jolivet, V.  (2016). <title rend="quotes">Annotation of Toponyms in TEI Digital Literary 
               Editions and Linking to the Web of Data,</title> <title rend="italic">MATLIT: Materialidades da Literatura</title>, 4(2), pp. 49-75.  </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="grover2008" label="Grover et al. 2008">
               Grover, C., Givon, S., Tobin, R., and Ball, J. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Named Entity Recognition for Digitised Historical Texts.</title> In <title rend="italic">LREC</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="guyotjeannin1997" label="Guyotjeannin 1997">
               Guyotjeannin, Olivier (1997). <title rend="quotes"><q>Penuria
               scriptorum</q> : le mythe de l’anarchie documentaire dans la France du Nord
               (Xe-première moitié du XIe siècle),</title> <title rend="italic">Bibliothèque de l'école des chartes</title>. Tome 155,
               livraison 1, pp. 11-44.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hoffart2013" label="Hoffart et al. 2013">
               Hoffart, J., Suchanek, F. M., Berberich, K.
               and Weikum, G. (2013). <title rend="quotes">YAGO2: A Spatially and Temporally Enhanced Knowledge Base
               from Wikipedia Artificial Intelligence,</title> special issue on Wikipedia and
               Semi-Structured Resources.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="iognaprat2013" label="Iogna-Prat et al. 2013">
               Iogna-Prat, D., et al. (2013), <title rend="italic">Cluny :
               les moines et la société au premier âge féodal.</title> Presses universitaires de Rennes.
               Collection « Art et Société ».</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="klein2014" label="Klein et al. 2014">
               Klein, E., Alex, B., Clifford, J. (2014).
               <title rend="quotes">Bootstrapping a historical commodities lexicon with SKOS and DBpedia.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings
               of the 8th Workshop on Language Technology for Cultural Heritage, Social Sciences,
               and Humanities</title> (LaTeCH), pp. 13-21.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lafferty2001" label="Lafferty et al. 2001">
               Lafferty, J., McCallum, A., and Pereira, F.
               (2001). <title rend="quotes">Conditional random fields: Probabilistic models for segmenting and labeling
               sequence data.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the eighteenth international conference on machine
               learning</title>, ICML, Vol. 1, pp. 282-289.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lavergne2010" label="Lavergne et al. 2010">
               Lavergne, T., Cappé, O., and Yvon, F. (2010), <title rend="quotes">Practical very large scale CRFs.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 48th Annual 
               Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, Association for Computational Linguistics</title>, pp. 504-513. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lehmann2013" label="Lehmann et al. 2013">
               Lehmann, J.; Isele, R.; Jakob, M.; Jentzsch,
               A.; Kontokostas, D.; Mendes, P. N.; Hellmann, S.; Morsey, M.; van Kleef, P.; Auer,
               Sö. &amp; Bizer, C. <title rend="quotes">DBpedia - A Large-scale, Multilingual Knowledge Base Extracted</title>
               from <title rend="italic">Wikipedia Semantic Web Journal</title>, 2013</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="li2016" label="Li et al. 2016">
               Li, H., and Shi, J. (2016). <title rend="quotes">Linking Named Entity in a Question with DBpedia Knowledge Base.</title> In <title rend="italic">Joint 
               International Semantic Technology Conference</title>, Springer International Publishing, pp. 263-270. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="magnani2002" label="Magnani 2002">
               Magnani, Eliana. (2002). <title rend="quotes">Le don au moyen âge.</title> <title rend="italic">Revue
               du MAUSS</title>, no 1, pp. 309-322.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mosallam2014" label="Mosallam et al. 2014">
               Mosallam, Y., Abi-Haidar, A., Ganascia, J.
               (2014). <title rend="quotes">Unsupervised named entity recognition and disambiguation: an application to
               old French journals.</title> In <title rend="italic">Industrial Conference on Data Mining.</title> Springer, Cham, pp.
               12-23.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nadeau2007" label="Nadeau et al. 2007">
               Nadeau, D., Sekine, S. (2007). <title rend="quotes">A survey of
               named entity recognition and classification.</title> <title rend="italic">Lingvisticae Investigationes</title>, vol. 30,
               no 1, pp. 3-26.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="neelakantan2015" label="Neelakantan et al. 2015">
               Neelakantan, A., Collins, M. (2015).
               <title rend="italic">Learning dictionaries for named entity recognition using minimal supervision.</title> arXiv
               preprint arXiv:1504.06650.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nouvel2016" label="Nouvel et al. 2016">
               Nouvel, D., Ehrmann, M., Rosset, S. (2016).
               <title rend="italic">Named Entities for Computational Linguistics.</title> ISTE, cognitive science series.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="passarotti2014" label="Passarotti 2014">
               Passarotti, Marco. (2014). <title rend="quotes">From Syntax to Semantics. First
               Steps Towards Tectogrammatical Annotation of Latin.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 8th Workshop on Language
               Technology for Cultural Heritage, Social Sciences, and Humanities</title>
               (LaTeCH). pp. 100-109.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="plank2016" label="Plank 2016">
               Plank, B. (2016). <title rend="italic">What to do about non-standard (or
               non-canonical) language in NLP.</title> arXiv preprint arXiv:1608.07836.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pochampally2016" label="Pochampally et al. 2016">
               Pochampally, Y., Karlapalem, K.,
               Yarrabelly, N. (2016), <title rend="quotes">Semi-Supervised Automatic Generation of Wikipedia Articles
               for Named Entities.</title> In Wiki@ ICWSM.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rayson2017" label="Rayson et al. 2017">
               Rayson, P., et al. (2017). <title rend="quotes">A deeply annotated
               testbed for geographical text analysis: The Corpus of Lake District Writing.</title> In
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 1st ACM SIGSPATIAL Workshop on Geospatial Humanities</title>. ACM, pp.
               9-15.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rizzo2011" label="Rizzo et al. 2011">
               Rizzo, G., Troncy, R. (2011). <title rend="quotes">Nerd: evaluating
               named entity recognition tools in the web of data.</title> In <title rend="italic">Workshop on Web Scale
               Knowledge Extraction</title> (WEKEX’11).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rose2007" label="Rosé 2007">Rosé, I. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Panorama de l’écrit diplomatique en Bourgogne : autour des cartulaires (XIe-XVIIIe siècles).</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Bulletin du centre d’études médiévales d’Auxerre</title>, BUCEMA, (11).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sopena1996" label="Sopena 1996">
               Sopena, P. M. (1996). <title rend="quotes">L'anthroponymie de l'Espagne
               chrétienne entre le IXe et le XIIe siècle.</title> <title rend="italic">L’anthroponymie document de l’histoire
               sociale des mondes méditerranéens médiévaux, Publications de l'École française de
               Rome</title>, 226(1), pp. 63-85.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wallach2004" label="Wallach 2004">Wallach, H. M. (2004), <title rend="quotes">Conditional random fields: An introduction.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Technical Reports</title> (CIS), pp. 22.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="won2018" label="Won et al. 2018">
               Won, M., Murrieta-Flores, P. and Martins, B.
               (2018) <title rend="quotes">Ensemble Named Entity Recognition (NER): Evaluating NER Tools in the
               Identification of Place Names in Historical Corpora.</title> Front. <title rend="italic">Digit. Humanit.</title> 5 :2.
               doi: 10.3389/fdigh.2018.00002</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zimmermann2003" label="Zimmermann 2003">
               <hi rend="bold">Zimmermann 2003</hi> Zimmermann, M. (2003), <title rend="italic">Écrire et lire en
               Catalogne : IXe-XIIe siècle (Vol. 1).</title> Casa de Velázquez, Madrid, pp.251-284.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
