<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Somewhere Nearby is Colossal Cave: Examining Will Crowther's Original <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> in Code and in Kentucky </title>
            <author>Dennis G. Jerz</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
			            <dhq:author_name>Dennis G. <dhq:family>Jerz</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
			            <dhq:affiliation>Seton Hill University</dhq:affiliation>
			            <email>jerz@setonhill.edu</email>
			            <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Dennis G. Jerz is Associate Professor of English — New Media
				Journalism at Seton Hill University, in southwestern Pennsylvania. He holds a Ph.D. in
				English from the University of Toronto, and an M.A. and B.A. in English from the
				University of Virginia. His publications include <title rend="quotes">An Annotated Bibliography of
				Interactive Fiction Scholarship</title> (Text/Technology, 2002), Technology in
				American Drama, 1920-1950: Soul and Society in the Age of the Machine (Greenwood Press,
				2003), a simulation of the motion of wagons in a medieval pageant in York, England
				(ReSoundings, 1997), and articles about blogging, memes, and education. Since 1999, he
				has maintained Jerz's Literacy Weblog (<ref target="http://jerz.setonhill.edu/weblog/">
					http://jerz.setonhill.edu/weblog/</ref>), where he explores his interests in new
				media, literature, journalism, and writing.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
		          </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000009</idno>
            <idno type="volume">001</idno>
            <idno type="issue">2</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2007-09-12">12 September 2007</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace" rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2009-03-05" who="CRB">Added bio from bios.xml</change>
         <change when="2008-06-16" who="Ashwini">Updated revisionDesc format, added
					publicationStmt, changed xref to ref, changed file attribute of graphic element
					to url attribute, added "#" to target attribute of internal ref and ptr for
					validation with new schema</change>
         <change when="2007-08-30" who="Ashwini Athavale">commented out the repeating header</change>
         <change when="2007-08-29" who="Julia Flanders">Added teaser</change>
         <change when="2007-08-06" who="Ashwini Athavale">Removed # from links and changed
					tags from ref to xref for external links</change>
         <change when="2007-08-06" who="Ashwini Athavale">Removed # from links and changed
					tags from ref to xref for external links</change>
         <change when="2007-07-07" who="Julia Flanders">Encoded article</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>Because so little primary historical work has been done on the classic text computer
				game <title rend="quotes">Colossal Cave Adventure</title>, academic and popular
				references to it frequently perpetuate inaccuracies. <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> was the first in a series of text-based games
					(<q>interactive fiction</q>) that emphasize exploring, puzzles, and
				story, typically in a fantasy setting; these games had a significant cultural impact
				in the late 1970s and a significant commercial presence in the early 1980s. Will
				Crowther based his program on a real cave in Kentucky; Don Woods expanded this
				version significantly. The expanded work has been examined as an occasion for
				narrative encounters <ptr target="#buckles1985"/> and as an aesthetic masterpiece of
				logic and utility <ptr target="#knuth1998"/>; however, previous attempts to assess
				the significance of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> remain incomplete without
				access to Crowther's original source code and Crowther's original source cave.
				Accordingly, this paper analyzes previously unpublished files recovered from a
				backup of Woods's student account at Stanford, and documents an excursion to the
				real Colossal Cave in Kentucky in 2005. In addition, new interviews with Crowther,
				Woods, and their associates (particularly members of Crowther's family) provide new
				insights on the precise nature of Woods's significant contributions. Real locations
				in the cave and several artifacts (such as an iron rod and an axe head) correspond
				to their representation in Crowther's version; however, by May of 1977, Woods had
				expanded the game to include numerous locations that he invented, along with
				significant technical innovations (such as scorekeeping and a player inventory).
				Sources that incorrectly date Crowther's original to 1972 or 1974, or that identify
				it as a cartographic data file with no game or fantasy elements, are sourced thinly
				if at all. The new evidence establishes that Crowther wrote the game during the
				1975-76 academic year and probably abandoned it in early 1976. The original game
				employed magic, humor, simple combat, and basic puzzles, all of which Woods greatly
				expanded. While Crowther remained largely faithful to the geography of the real
				cave, his original did introduce subtle changes to the environment in order to
				improve the gameplay.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>The true history of <title rend="quotes">Colossal Cave Adventure</title>.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="section01">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Will Crowther's <title rend="quotes">Colossal Cave Adventure</title> was neither the
				first computer game nor the first program to emulate conversation<note>
                  <ref target="#montfort2003">Montfort (2003)</ref> aptly traces the precursors to
						<title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>, such as <title rend="quotes">ELIZA</title>, <title rend="quotes">SHURDLU</title>, and <title rend="quotes">Hunt the Wumpus</title> (the latter of which was also set in a
				cave).</note>; nevertheless, <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> — an interactive
				textual simulation of a caving expedition, augmented by fantasy-themed puzzles –
				inspired a generation of hackers. Playing <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>
				involves reading prose descriptions of the setting, and typing brief commands (i.e.
					<q>light lamp</q>) in order to solve puzzles and collect
				treasure. Similar text games representing environments defined both by story and
				rules were extremely popular during the 80s and (with the addition of graphics)
				through the 90s. Text-adventures, also known as <q>interactive fiction</q>
					(IF),<note>The term <term>interactive fiction</term> has also been applied to
					hypertext literature <ptr target="#howell1990"/>, AI-based character simulations
						<ptr target="#anderson1990"/>, and, sporadically, as a synonym for
						<q>alternate reality</q> or <q>viral marketing</q> games
						<ptr target="#mcgonigal2008" loc="6"/> and <ref target="http://www.immersivegaming.com">http://www.immersivegaming.com</ref>); however, in this paper,
						<q>interactive fiction</q> applies only to the genre of
					command-line text games patterned after <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>.</note> attracted modest scholarly attention as an emerging
				literary form in the 80s;<note>See <ref target="#jerz2002">Jerz 2002</ref>, and
					particularly the note on Packard, E. <title rend="quotes">Interactive Fiction
						for Children: Boon or Bane?</title>, <title rend="italic">School Library
						Journal</title> 34 (1987): 40-1.</note> yet <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth1997">[m]ost commentators and critics of the adventure game
						genre… fail to mention the original <title rend="italic">Adventure</title>
						at all, and those who do usually date it far off the mark… and often neglect
						to mention its creators</quote>
                  <ptr target="#aarseth1997" loc="107"/>
               </cit>. The resulting vacuum has attracted memes, some so firmly lodged in our
				inventory of digital lore that they regularly appear without citation. In order to
				map out the groundwork for a more accurate assessment of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>, its innovations, and its legacy, this study draws on two
				crucial resources previously unexamined by digital scholars: Crowther’s original
				source code and Kentucky’s original source cave.</p>
            <p>Levy observes that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#levy1984">like any significant program, Adventure was expressive of
						the personality and environment of the authors</quote>
                  <ptr loc="133" target="#levy1984"/>
               </cit>. Due to Crowther's personal choice to keep a low profile,<note>Crowther's
					older daughter Sandy Lawrence (2002) ponders
					her father's fame: <quote rend="inline" source="#lawrence2002">It’s funny thinking of him as the J. D.
						Salinger of interactive fiction… to me, he’s just my dad.</quote>
               </note>
				analysis of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>
               <note>While some scholars use
					italics for titles of computer games, and while the popular gaming press often
					does not mark game titles in any way, this study will format the title of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> as if it were a short story.</note> must
				rely more heavily on the environment — both professional and natural. We know
				Crowther's coding environment was collaborative and highly technical,<note>For an
					analysis of computer programming culture during this time period, see <ref target="#kidder1981">Kidder, 1981</ref>; <ref target="#levy1984">Levy,
					1984</ref>; and <ref target="#hafner1996">Hafner and Lyon, 1996</ref>.</note>
				but so far we have only known Crowther's <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>
				indirectly, through a version greatly expanded by Don Woods. <ref target="#section02">Section 2</ref> of this article is a formal examination of
				Crowther's original source code files, offering, for the first time, a clear
				understanding of Crowther's innovative blend of simulation and fantasy, as well as a
				better appreciation of the creative contributions of Woods. <ref target="#section03">Section 3</ref> compares the game to maps of the cave site, presents
				photographs of an excursion to Colossal Cave, and offers testimony from experienced
				cavers. These key sources — the code and the cave, analyzed here for the first time
				– establish that Crowther's original was not only faithful to the geography of the
				real Colossal Cave, but was also a fantasy remediation of that site. <ref target="#section04">Section 4</ref> offers a revision of the <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> timeline in an attempt to correct common
				misconceptions and encourage further scholarship, and a brief <ref target="#section05">conclusion</ref> compiles the major formalist observations,
				as a gesture towards encouraging further research.</p>
            <div>
               <head>Taking Inventory of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>
               </head>
               <p>While today's young computer professionals may have only passing familiarity with
						<title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>, the game had a tremendous effect on
					an earlier generation of programmers. Lines from <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>, such as <q>You are in a maze of twisty
						little passages, all alike</q> and the magic word <q>XYZZY</q>, quickly entered hacker culture. <title rend="italic">The New
						Hacker Dictionary</title>
                  <note>
                     <title rend="italic">The New Hacker's
							Dictionary</title>
						               <ptr target="#raymond1996"/> repurposes the entry <ref target="http://www.catb.org/~esr/jargon/html/v/vadding.html">http://www.catb.org/~esr/jargon/html/V/vadding.html</ref> from <title rend="quotes">The Jargon File</title>, an older compilation of computer
                  	culture, at one point edited by Don Woods.</note> includes the term <quote rend="inline" source="#raymond1996">vadding</quote> (<quote rend="inline" source="#raymond1996">from VAD, a permutation
						of ADV (i.e., ADVENT), used to avoid a particular admin's continual
						search-and-destroy sweeps for the game</quote>), defining it as a <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#raymond1996">leisure-time activity of certain hackers involving the
							covert exploration of the <q>secret</q> parts of large
							buildings</quote>
                     <ptr target="#raymond1996" loc="465"/>
                  </cit>. </p>
               <figure xml:id="figure01">
                  <head>Tourist Caves as Graphical User Interface. In a tourist cave, clean and orderly routes shunt visitors along
							carefully defined paths that emphasize visual impact. Some sites offer
							access ramps, elevators, and conveniences such as underground bathrooms,
							carefully isolating visitors from the potential for uncertainty or
							discomfort. The managed environment serves non-specialists who are
							unlikely to explore undeveloped caves.
						               Photo illustration by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005.
							Reproduced by permission. </head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_001.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of a tourist cave showing photo of cave with Microsoft
						Office-style help window reading "It looks like you are trying to visit
						Mammoth Cave National Park. Would you like to: Take the stairs up to the
						parking lot; Take the stairs down to the entrance; Find the elevator; Don't
						show me this tip again."</figDesc>
                  
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="figure02">
                  <head>Wild Caves as Command Line Interface. Visitors hiking to the Bedquilt Entrance of Colossal Cave are likely to
							get tired, get ticks, and get lost. The benefit for a serious caver who
							actually makes it inside is the ability to choose destination and route,
							perhaps linking up known routes in new ways, or seeking unknown passages
							to <q>virgin cave</q>. Photo illustration by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by permission.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_002.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of a "wild cave" showing photo of the author pointing into a dark
						cave tunnel with command-line style words "ENTER CAVE" and "OK" superimposed</figDesc>
                 
               </figure>
               <p>Successors to <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> were among the best-selling
					computer games of the 1980s. Even after the commercial market faded, hobbyists
					continued to play, review, and create interactive fiction. Indeed, the
					post-commercial IF community<note>The Usenet groups rec.games.int-fiction (for
						players) and rec.arts.int-fiction (for authors and theorists) remain
						important community forces, along with the annual Interactive Fiction
						Competition (for short games) and the XYZZY Awards. IF authors who regularly
						post relevant critical, theoretical, review, or how-to essays include
						Stephen Granade (<ref target="http://brasslantern.org">http://brasslantern.org</ref>) and Emily Short (<ref target="http://emshort.wordpress.com">http://emshort.wordpress.com</ref>). Since 1994, the e-zine <title rend="quotes">SPAG</title> has published reviews and interviews
						(currently at <ref target="http://sparkynet.com/spag/">http://sparkynet.com/spag/</ref>). A wealth of other community
						resources are available at <ref target="http://ifwiki.org">http://ifwiki.org</ref>, including a FAQ resource for those who are new to
						the genre.</note> was producing valuable analysis and theory<note>See <title rend="quotes">Archives and Meta-resources</title>
						               <ptr target="#jerz2002"/>.</note> long before games began to emerge as an
					academic subject. </p>
               <p>Within the computer science field, <ref target="#knuth1998">Knuth (1998)</ref>
					used <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> as his sole example in a 107-page
					tutorial on <q>literate programming</q> — coding for human readers as
					well as machines. His text carefully translates the Crowther/Woods FORTRAN code
					to CWEB, prefacing each section of code with a discussion of how the rules
					defined in each section of code affect the gameplay. </p>
               <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#knuth1998">You get to wander around until you've located all fifteen
						treasures, although you need not have taken them yet. After that, you enter
						a new level of complexity: A global variable called <hi rend="italic">clock1</hi> starts ticking downwards, every time you take a turn inside the
						cave. When it hits zero, we start closing the cave; then we sit back and
						wait for you to try to get out, letting <hi rend="italic">clock2</hi> do the
						ticking.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#knuth1998" loc="80"/>
               </cit>
               <p>Knuth expects his reader to have played <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>
					multiple times, but offers his close reading of the code as the proper way to
					experience the work. His approach is the mirror image of <ref target="#buckles1985">Buckles (1985)</ref>, whose dissertation on <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> employs literary formalism to examine what
					she calls a <quote rend="inline" source="#buckles1985">storygame</quote> in terms of established
					genres such as the riddle and the folktale. Where Knuth’s procedural formalism
					argues <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#knuth1998">you cannot fully appreciate the astonishing brilliance
							of its design until you have seen all of the surprises that have been
							built in [the code]</quote>
                     <ptr loc="1" target="#knuth1998"/>
                  </cit>, Buckles explores the narratives that her volunteer players generated as
					they attempted (often unsuccessfully) to make sense of their partial exposure to
					the simulated world. While Knuth and Buckles could hardly approach their subject
					more differently, both studies take <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> as a
					given, without examining the cultural context in which Crowther and Woods
					created the text, or the context in which its first players interpreted it.
						<title rend="italic">Twisty Little Passages</title>
					             <ptr target="#montfort2003"/>, which takes its title from an infamous maze in
						<title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>, presents a detailed analysis of the
					cultural origins and significance of <title rend="quotes">Zork</title>, a
					similar game that was inspired by <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>
					             <ptr target="#anderson1985"/>. While Montfort offers an excellent overview of
					canonical knowledge about <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> and later
					developments in the genre of interactive fiction, much basic scholarly work on
						<title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> has remained.<note>The published
						evidence on <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> is not always reliable.
						In a rare interview, Crowther warned that his <quote rend="inline" source="#oneill1990">grasp of
							times and history and such is pretty fuzzy</quote>
						               <ptr target="#oneill1990" loc="3"/>. </note>
               </p>
               <p>Despite the historical importance of text adventures (they created the first
					market for home computer games), IF has only rarely attracted serious attention
					from digital scholars. Notable exceptions include Aarseth's reading <ptr target="#aarseth1997"/> of Marc Blank's 1982 <title rend="quotes">Deadline</title>, and, of course, Montfort's ongoing work.<note>The depth of
						Montfort's inquiry into interactive fiction is suggested by <title rend="quotes">Interactive Fiction as <q>Story</q>,
								<q>Game</q>, <q>Storygame</q>,
							<q>Novel</q>, <q>World</q>,
							<q>Literature</q>, <q>Puzzle</q>,
							<q>Problem</q>, <q>Riddle</q>, and
							<q>Machine</q>
                     </title> (in <title rend="italic">First Person:
							New Media as Story, Performance, and Game</title>, MIT, 2004) and <title rend="quotes">Face It, Tiger, You Just Hit the Jackpot: Reading and
							Playing Cadre’s <title rend="italic">Varicella</title>
                     </title>,
						(co-authored with Stuart Moulthrop, in <title rend="italic">Fineart
						Forum</title> 17:8, Aug 2003).</note> Nevertheless, Aarseth's complaint
					about authors who overlook <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> remains valid.
					Murray mentions <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> only in an end note,
					describing Crowther's original as a 1972 map and attributing the fantasy
					elements entirely to Woods <ptr target="#murray1997" loc="290"/>. Douglass uses
					the more accurate date of 1975, but re-affirms a stubborn meme when he describes
						<title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> as a <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#douglass2007">spelunking simulation… expanded by Don Woods into a
							Tolkein-esque fantasy</quote>
                     <ptr loc="129" target="#douglass2007"/>
                  </cit>. A recent article in the <title rend="italic">New York Times</title>
					completely overlooks <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>, stating <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#chaplin2007">Zork introduced the world to the adventure game</quote>
                     <ptr target="#chaplin2007"/>
                  </cit>. Yet Costikyan is too scrupulous, using <title rend="italic">Colossal
						Cave</title> to refer to the Crowther original and <title rend="italic">Adventure</title> to refer to the Woods expansion, representing them as two
					different examples of interactive fiction <ptr target="#costikyan2007" loc="5"/>. While other scholarship focusing on more recent works of interactive fiction
					includes Douglass's analysis of Plotkin's 2000 <title rend="quotes">Shade</title> and brief author notes by Montfort, Meretzky and Short <ptr target="#harrington2007"/>, and Keller's ethnographic <title rend="quotes">Gaming, Identity and Literacy</title>
					             <ptr target="#selfe2007"/>, the historical and cultural role of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> itself remains under-examined. </p>
               <p>In the realm of journalism, <ref target="#dibbell2002">Dibbell (2002)</ref>
					revisits and summarizes canonical sources on <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>, drawing on sources such as <ref target="#nelson2001">Nelson
						(2001)</ref> and <ref target="#aarseth1997">Aarseth (1997)</ref>, but the
					article, written for a general reader, contributes no new knowledge. <ref target="#douglass2006">Douglass (2006)</ref> lists <quote rend="inline" source="#douglass2006">a
						fairly constrained set of talking points</quote> that gaming and mainstream
					articles about interactive fiction typically follow: for instance, works of IF
						<quote rend="inline" source="#douglass2006">started the computer game industry</quote>, <quote rend="inline" source="#douglass2006">were killed by graphics cards</quote>, and <quote rend="inline" source="#douglass2006">are still being made!</quote> The formulaic nature of these
					stories is due in part to the journalist's obligation to introduce readers to an
					unfamiliar genre; regrettably, such boilerplate coverage can perpetuate faulty
					assertions. A March 2002 <title rend="italic">GameSpy</title> article is a
					typical example of the resilience of various memes that have entered the realm
					of common knowledge: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#gamespy2002">The year was 1972. Crowther, an amateur spelunker
							distraught over a recent divorce, wanted to create a game that he and
							his kids could play on the computer together. He whipped up a computer
							text simulation of the Mammoth Caves in Kentucky... Of course there were
							no puzzles in Crowther's version, just a mighty underground realm to
							explore. Enter Don Woods, who found a copy of the game on the primitive
							Internet. He asked permission to play with the source code and the
							result was Adventure (sometimes called <title rend="italic">Colossal
								Caves</title>). He added treasures to collect, monsters, traps,
							puzzles, and more. </quote>
                     <ptr target="#gamespy2002"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Little evidence has been available to challenge many of these assumptions, as
					well as others (such as the claim that Crowther based his game not on Colossal
					Cave but a nearby cave named Bedquilt, or that Don Woods hacked his way into
					Crowther's account). New interviews with Crowther, his family members, and his
					associates (see <ref target="#section04">Section 4</ref>) establish that
					Crowther <emph>did</emph> present his game as a post-divorce activity for his
					children (although he also shared it with his Dungeons and Dragons friends);
					Crowther <emph>was</emph> a caver (but <quote rend="inline" source="#oneill1990">In those days, the
						thing I cared most about was rock climbing,</quote>
					             <ptr target="#oneill1990" loc="5"/>); the game <emph>was</emph> based on one
					section of the Mammoth Cave system in southwestern Kentucky, which contains
					Colossal Cave (a sub-network with many entrances, of which Crowther featured one
					named Bedquilt); and Stanford University graduate student Don Woods
					<emph>did</emph> find Crowther's abandoned program (not by hacking, but simply
					by playing a copy that someone else had placed on a computer at the Stanford
					medical school; see <ref target="#cordella2001">Cordella [2001]</ref>). Woods
					had previously estimated a March or April 1976 release date <ptr target="#cordella2001"/>, but now he agrees with the 1977 claim made by the
					present study <ptr target="#woods2007"/>.</p>
               <p>Crowther's original source code,<note>Dalenberg gives the tag CROW0000 to this
						original version, in a genealogy of early <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> files <ptr target="#dalenberg2004"/>, and a <title rend="quotes">Family Tree</title>
						               <ptr target="#dalenberg2006"/> with links to various downloadable
					versions.</note> which had been presumed lost for decades, was recovered in 2005
					from a backup of Don Woods's student account at the Stanford Artificial
					Intelligence Lab (SAIL).<note>In response to my request, Les Earnest (SAIL
						executive officer, 1965-1980), Bruce Baumgart (former Stanford Ph.D.
						student, now an employee of the Internet Archive) and Martin Frost (systems
						manager of Stanford's CS department) kindly gave Don Woods web-based access
						to a tape backup of his Stanford student account. Woods chose five files
						from that backup tape, which he identified as components of Crowther's
						original FORTRAN 4 source code, and made them available for scholarly study
						(see <ref target="#crowther1977">Crowther and Woods, <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>
                     </ref>). The two oldest files (a pair representing
						the data and the code) are dated March 11, 1977. According to Woods, these
						files represent Crowther's original work. The archive includes three more
						files from late March, showing some of the first changes Woods made in both
						the data and the code. For an analysis, see part 2 of this article, <ref target="#section02">Exploring Colossal Cave in Code</ref>.</note> The
					recovered files, dated March 1977, and bearing the in-game message <q>WELCOME TO ADVENTURE!!</q>, confirm that Crowther's
					original was in fact a game, with puzzles (such as a sequence that involves
					interactions between a rusty rod, an empty birdcage, a bird, and a snake),
					subtle humor (such as the surprising way that the bird helps the player get past
					the snake), and fantasy (including a magical crystal bridge, magic words, and
					combat with axe-wielding dwarves). Yet Crowther's adventures in Colossal Cave
					began earlier, via the Cave Research Foundation (CRF). Several caving resources
					shed light on the pre-history of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>,
					including Crowther’s 1975 map of the Bedquilt region of Colossal Cave (sometimes
					confused with Crowther's original game), and a manual describing recreational
					caving as the CRF practiced it in the mid 70s. Insights gained from a recent CRF
					expedition to Colossal Cave — together with an analysis of the recovered source
					code and new feedback from Crowther, Woods, and others with knowledge of the
					original <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> — clarify our understanding of
					an important digital artifact.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Cultural and Commercial Impact</head>
               <p>When <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> reached MIT in the spring of 1977,
					one group of players reacted by creating <title rend="quotes">Zork</title> and
					the company Infocom, whose text-adventure titles were best-sellers during the
					80s. Other entrepreneurs inspired by <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>
					included Scott Adams (founder of Adventure International), who published the
					lean but accessible <title rend="quotes">Adventureland</title> in 1978, and Ken
					and Roberta Williams (co-founders of Sierra On-Line), who produced the first
					graphic adventure game (<title rend="quotes">Mystery House,</title> 1980) after
					Roberta got hooked on <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>
					             <ptr target="#levy1984" loc="294–295"/>. In 1978, Atari employee Warren Robinett
					reworked the general exploration-and-treasure premise into a 2D graphic game,
					also called <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>, which sold a million units
						<ptr target="#robinett2000"/>. During the late 70s, text-based computer
					games had tactical advantages over games using the slow, blocky, and expensive
					graphics that were then cutting-edge. </p>
               <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#bennahum1998">The day I discovered Dungeon [the mainframe, pre-commercial
						version of Zork] I decided the computer room was the best place at
						school….We had no color monitors, no videogames to play. Everything here was
						text, blocky white letters on black screens. Yet the words were seductive
						because they revealed a hidden order behind everything...</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bennahum1998" loc="106, 108"/>
               </cit>
               <p>Last year's graphic games dated quickly due to rapid hardware advances, while
					last year's text games still appealed to this year's text gamers, which helped
					sales. Text games were also easily portable to multiple platforms, thereby
					increasing sales potential in a crowded market. When the PC and Mac emerged as
					the dominant hardware platforms in the late 80s, both the aesthetic and economic
					advantages of text adventures evaporated. </p>
               <p>Nevertheless, many things that <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> players
					enjoyed — logic and resource-management puzzles and the exploration of a complex
					virtual topography within the context of a framing story — remain staples in
					adventure, role-playing, and multiplayer game genres. Further, many elements
					that <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> did not implement — complex
					non-player characters, believable AI, dynamic branching plots — still elude
					today’s game designers. Former Infocom supervisor Dan Horn, reflecting on
					Infocom's failure to secure a foothold in the emerging multiplayer, real-time
					role-playing genre, blames his company's <quote rend="inline" source="#briceno2000">bad business
						decisions. Imagine if you will [Infocom's] Sorceror, Planetfall, and
						Deadline with the EverQuest [graphical] engine, amazing... but lost forever</quote>
					             <ptr target="#briceno2000" loc="44"/>. In a review of Electronic Entertainment
					Expo 2000, <ref target="#au2000">Au (2000)</ref> describes the action-centered
					blockbuster mentality that tends to obscure the importance of innovative niche
					titles: <quote rend="inline" source="#au2000">Lured by the siren song of ever-improving graphics
						power, terrified by the risks involved with truly unique ideas in gaming,
						the industry is collectively stumbling along a path well-worn by
					Hollywood,</quote> which uses non-stop action and visual spectacle to compete
					against itself for the quickest path to the consumer's dollar. A 2002 column in
					the <title rend="italic">New York Times</title> suggested that the commercial
					gaming industry's quest for graphic realism is misguided, and perhaps even at
					odds with the elemental pleasure of identifying and mastering a set of rules:
						<quote rend="inline" source="#rothstein2002">One of the major goals of video game systems has been
						to simulate the real, to create images so lifelike, and movements so natural
						that there is no sense of artifice,</quote> yet paradoxically, <quote rend="inline" source="#rothstein2002">the technology is put in service to creating a world that
						could very well do without it</quote>
					             <ptr target="#rothstein2002"/>. Because interactive fiction authors can draw on
					an existing body of narrative techniques, as well as emergent code-based
					interaction techniques, the medium (free from the corporate pressures associated
					with team-based development) is well-suited to individual experimentation and
					innovation.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Story, Rules, and Interactive Fiction</head>
               <p>Observing the joint activities of Hollywood and Silicon Valley, Poole speaks
					optimistically of a <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#poole2000">new pragmatism among video game designers: concentrating
							on what they alone can provide, rather than chasing the fashionable
							dream of interactive narrative, or uncritically seeking convergence with
							the cinema. Instead, especially in their concentration on character,
							videogames are carefully strip-mining our conventional notions of
							narrative and storytelling for what can be usefully simulated in their
							own, utterly different, medium.</quote>
                     <ptr loc="111" target="#poole2000"/>
                  </cit> According to Poole, narrative-driven games that aim to model personality
					are advancing an effort begun by text-adventures, which were, during the 80s, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#poole2000">the most promising avenue for success in this field</quote>
                     <ptr target="#poole2000" loc="106"/>
                  </cit>. Poole's intimate knowledge of contemporary gaming culture offers more
					first-person acuity than the influential <title rend="italic">Hamlet on the
						Holodeck</title>
					             <ptr target="#murray1997"/>, which draws more insight from gamer narratives (and
					analyses of game-like experiences in <title rend="italic">Star Trek</title>)
					than from the games themselves. Eskelinen is, however, too harsh <ptr target="#eskelinen2001"/> when he takes Murray to task for interpreting the
					Russian <title rend="quotes">Tetris</title> as a commentary on disorder in the
               	overly-scheduled American lifestyle. To Eskelinen, Murray commits <quote rend="inline" source="#eskelinen2001">interpretive violence</quote> by ignoring <quote rend="inline" source="#eskelinen2001">the actual game</quote> and instead trying <quote rend="inline" source="#eskelinen2001">to
						interpret its supposed content, or better yet, project her favourite content
						on it.</quote> Murray's approach fails, according to Eskelinen, because
						<quote rend="inline" source="#eskelinen2001">consequently we don't learn anything of the features
						that make <title rend="italic">Tetris</title> a game</quote>. By dismissing
					the value of examining his subject through any critical lens other than strict
					digital formalism, Eskelinen cleaves exclusively to one side of an unnecessary
					fissure between rules-based (ludological) and story-based (narratological) modes
					of games scholarship.<note>
                     <ref target="#juul2005">Juul (2005)</ref> admirably
						attempts to heal the rift between the rules-based and narrative-based
						approaches to games scholarship. </note> This apparent opposition
					illustrates the postmodern assertion that, owing to the socially-constructed
					nature of <q>meaning,</q> different readers will
					inevitably find different meanings in a given text. For example, <ref target="#buckles1985">Buckles (1985)</ref> investigates the unique
					narratives that <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> players constructed,
					examining how these stories helped players construct a working understanding of
					the game's puzzles. Such an approach privileges the perspective of a payer
					without access to the source code, yielding insights that differ from those
					achieved through Knuth’s code-based approach, which does not examine the role
					imagination plays in retaining (or losing) the player’s interest when the rules
					seem impenetrable. When discussing the postmodern emphasis on the reader's
					interpretive act rather than the writer's authorial power, <ref target="#hutcheon1988">Hutcheon (1988)</ref> offers the textual variability
					of interactive fiction as <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#hutcheon1988">the most extreme example I can think of</quote>
                     <ptr target="#hutcheon1988" loc="77"/>
                  </cit>. A binary approach to digital formalism does not mesh well with the
					axiom, familiar to literary critics, that seeking out diverse and indeed
					conflicting interpretations of a bounded text is a normal component of the
					acquisition of knowledge (so long as these interpretations are supported by
					evidence, thereby anchoring the interpretation on the safe side of the slippery
					slope).</p>
               <p>Hutcheon's observation highlights Aarseth's distinction between the infinite
					variable <emph>interpretations</emph> of any traditional text and the
					constrained variable content of a cybertext (1997, p. 3). Even after accepting
					that variable <emph>content</emph> is a defining principle of a cybertext, we
					are still free to recognize that variable content is as open to variable
						<emph>interpretation</emph> as any fixed text. For example, to a generation
					raised on <title rend="italic">Star Trek</title> or to scientists familiar with
					the latest chatterbots, Weizenbaum's <title rend="quotes">ELIZA</title> (1966)
					seems unimpressive as an implementation of artificial intelligence; yet when
					examined as a controlled expression of the angst that many in the general public
					felt about contemporary technology, or when taken as a withering parody of a
					touchy-feely 1960s psychiatrist, the same program gains new relevance. Poole
					quotes Richard Darling (a developer with the British company Codemasters)
					regarding the <title rend="quotes">ELIZA</title>-as-game: <quote rend="inline" source="#poole2000">I
						think, that in the games world, [artificial intelligence] hasn't to me
						actually exceeded that excitement level</quote>
					             <ptr loc="107" target="#poole2000"/>. In fact, because it had such a big impact
					on non-specialists who had previously seen nothing like it, <title rend="quotes">ELIZA</title> may be more <emph>culturally</emph> significant than the more
					sophisticated chatterbots that followed it. But perhaps even more fundamental is
					the observation that humans reach for anthropomorphic images when confronted
					with computer behavior that they do not understand; the name given to this
					tendency — the <q>ELIZA effect</q> — is one example of the
					program's cultural legacy. <title rend="quotes">Tetris</title> has its own
					cultural legacy; Murray presumably encountered the game within the context of
					her own overscheduled American lifestyle. The marketing emphasized the game's
					Soviet origins, capitalizing on the American consumer's interest, during the
					last years of the Soviet Empire, in participating — at least symbolically — in
						<foreign>glasnost </foreign>and <foreign>perestroika</foreign>, therefore
					giving casual gamers a reason to try a title that might not otherwise have
					appealed to them. The <quote rend="inline" source="#eskelinen2001">actual game,</quote> then, is not
					only the set of abstracted rules that interests Eskelinen, but also a cultural
					artifact upon which humans (from marketers to players to games scholars) project
					their own concept of meaning according to their own unique values.<note>Consider
							<title rend="quotes">Freefall</title>
						               <ptr target="#plotkin1995"/>, a remediation of <title rend="quotes">Tetris</title>. This text game, created as a joke, begins with the
						following words: <quote rend="inline" source="#plotkin1995">You wake up. You have no memory of who
							you are, or where you are, or what you have been doing. A peculiarly
							vibrating, tinny music pours from an invisible source. Then you see the
							tremendous chunk of stone falling towards you…. </quote>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>The first comprehensive assessment of the cultural history of interactive fiction
					is found in Nelson's <title rend="italic">Inform Designer's Manual</title> 4th
					ed. <ptr target="#nelson2001"/> (an encyclopedic reference for one of several
					highly-advanced programming languages used by the interactive fiction hobbyist
					community). An appendix offers an overview of the genre, beginning with the
					story of Stephen Bishop, a cave explorer, cartographer, and former slave, who
					worked as a tour guide in Colossal Cave in the hopes of buying freedom for his
					wife and children. <quote rend="inline" source="#nelson2001">It's hard not to feel a certain sadness
						that the first adventure game was shaped by those two lost souls, Bishop and
						Crowther, each like Orpheus unable to draw his wife out of the underworld</quote>
					             <ptr target="#nelson2001" loc="344"/>. While the comparison of a cave beloved by
					both men to slavery, divorce, and death may seem melodramatic, Nelson aptly
					identifies the pathos which contextualizes the adventures Bishop and Crowther
					experienced in Colossal Cave. For Crowther's children, Sandy <ptr target="#lawrence2002"/> and Laura <ptr target="#carter2002"/>, playing
					computer games (including their father's original game, and later the version
					Woods expanded) was always part of visiting their father after the divorce. One
					of Crowther's former caving companions recalled CRF culture in the early 70s in
					utopian terms, describing the breakup of the Crowthers' marriage as a
					catastrophic event; this mutual friend was himself clearly suffering 30 years
					later. Another caver who was with the Crowthers on an expedition in the summer
					of 1975 reports that one glance at <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> was
					enough to identify it immediately as a cathartic exercise, an attempt by Will to
					memorialize a lost experience. </p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> was written for fun and shared for free;
					it was the cultural product of an educated, puzzle-loving, and fundamentally
					altruistic geek culture. Had it been better suited to the expectations of the
					non-technical public, it would likely have been less interesting to the
					community of computer specialists and entrepreneurs who responded by creating
					their own variations. In his editorial in the first issue of <title rend="italic">Game Studies</title>, <ref target="#aarseth2001">Aarseth
						(2001)</ref> sketches a game studies manifesto urging scholars to examine
					not only the huge industrial players, but also the activities of the <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth2001">world-wide, non-commercial, collective games movement.</quote>
					Writing of the game modding community, <ref target="#au2002">Au (2002)</ref>
					observed that mods (amateur variations upon and expansions for commercial
					products) <quote rend="inline" source="#au2002">represent the most visible success of the free
						software movement on the larger culture. For the millions who play computer
						games, the same ethos of volunteerism and shared ownership that
						characterizes free software has helped utterly transform the gaming
						experience and the $8 billion-plus gaming industry.</quote> In a similar
					vein, <ref target="#ryan2001">Ryan (2001)</ref> articulates a vision of what
					might happen <quote rend="inline" source="#ryan2001">if computer games could emancipate themselves
						from the tyranny of the market,</quote> which, as is the case in Hollywood,
					forces developers to appeal to the broadest audience. Contrasting the high
					overhead of games with the low cost of producing literature, Ryan posits that <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#ryan2001">if games could enjoy a comparable freedom of
							expression, we might see hybrids of literature and games which would
							place greater aesthetic emphasis on the plot</quote>
                     <ref target="#ryan2001">fn. 9</ref>
                  </cit>. There are, of course, computer games that succeed without compelling
					plots; however, by nature, interactive fiction invites and rewards a
					narratological approach more readily than other gaming sub-genres.</p>
               <p>Poole observes that a generation ago, cinema and jazz studies occupied only
					marginal spaces in academia; yet they are today considered respectable subjects
					for examination (13). A close relation of the adventure game, the MUD, has
					already drawn considerable academic attention.<note>MUD-related scholarship is
						far too detailed to catalog here, but see <ref target="#turkle1995">Turkle
							(1995)</ref>.</note> The rhetorical connections between contemporary IF
					and MUDs have not been fully explored, even though the first MUD was a hacked
					version of a text adventure game. Arguing against the received notion that
					advances in computer technology have made IF irrelevant, <ref target="#cadre2004">Cadre (2004?)</ref> introduces his own collection of
					avant-garde IF titles by claiming <quote rend="inline" source="#cadre2004">the <emph>medium</emph>
						of interactive fiction is no more a relic of the 1980s than the novel is a
						relic of the 17th century</quote>. With three decades of history but with so
					little basic research published, the text adventure genre remains a promising
					subject for digital humanities research.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="section02">
            <head>Exploring Colossal Cave in Code</head>
            <p>His daughter Sandy quotes Will Crowther as saying, <quote rend="inline" source="#lawrence2002">You know I've
					done all sorts of wonderful things in my career, it's funny that the one thing
					I'm remembered for is <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>
               </quote>
				           <ptr target="#lawrence2002"/>. Before he coded his legendary game, Crowther had
				helped map the complex network of caverns on which the game is based; and before
					<emph>that</emph>, he had already secured a place in history due to his
				contributions to a different network. As a member of the team of programmers at
				Bolt, Beranek and Newman (BBN), he helped create the ARPANET, the immediate
				forerunner to the internet. </p>
            <div>
               <head>Historical and Cultural Context</head>
               <p>While BBN was actively researching artificial intelligence at the time Crowther
					was building <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>, the game <quote rend="inline" source="#kraley2004">was just some rather simplistic logic and a small table of
						known words — of course backed up by some very clever thinking,</quote>
					according to <ref target="#kraley2004">Kraley (2004)</ref>, whose office was
					across from Crowther's. Kraley joined Crowther in a months-long Dungeons and
					Dragons campaign (led by Eric Roberts and including future Infocom co-founder
					Dave Lebling among the core of about eight participants). <quote rend="inline" source="#kraley2004">[O]ne day, a few of us wandered into [Crowther's] office so he could show
						off his program. It was very crude in many respects — Will was always
						parsimonious of memory — but surprisingly sophisticated. We all had a blast
						playing it, offering suggestions, finding bugs, and so forth.</quote>
					Crowther's original Adventure impressed his colleagues. <quote rend="inline" source="#kraley2004">Will was very proud - or more accurately amused - of how well he could fool
						people into thinking that there was some very complex AI behind the
					game,</quote> according to Kraley. Nevertheless, <quote rend="inline" source="#kraley2004">once it
						was working, Will wasn't very interested in perfecting or expanding
					it.</quote>
               </p>
               <p>Crowther has described himself putting a copy of the game on his BBN computer,
					leaving for a month's vacation, and returning to find the game being played all
					over the internet <ptr target="#hafner1994"/>. Among those who found the game at
					this stage were two Stanford graduate students, Don Woods and John Gilbert.
					According to <ref target="#gilbert2005">Gilbert (2005)</ref>, someone (possibly
					the instructor, Bob Floyd) mentioned the game in their CS204 class (a <quote rend="inline" source="#gilbert2005">programming and problem-solving seminar</quote>) — after which
					Gilbert and Woods <quote rend="inline" source="#gilbert2005">stayed up all night at the AI lab playing
						the game and mapping the cave, including scanning the binary code for
						character strings in order to guess what the possibilities were.</quote>
					After contacting Crowther and requesting the source code, Woods greatly
					increased the game's size, complexity, and polish. <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#anderson1985">In early 1977…. [w]hen <title rend="italic">Adventure</title> arrived at MIT, the reaction was typical: after
							everybody spent a lot of time doing nothing but solving the game (it's
							estimated that <title rend="italic">Adventure</title> set the entire
							computer industry back two weeks), the true lunatics began to think
							about how they could do it better</quote>
                     <ptr target="#anderson1985"/>
                  </cit>. During this time, Tom Van Vleck was a managing engineer at Honeywell. He
					describes <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> as just another fad. <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#vanvleck2001">[S]ome staff members spent many hours at it. Others
							played it once or twice, showed it to relatives and friends, and lost
							interest. Gaming was not a source of interest in computing, or a way of
							recruiting people to the field: it was something we could do with the
							machine that was comprehensible to non-computer folks, who were often
							baffled about what a computer was and what we did</quote>
                     <ptr target="#vanvleck2001"/>
                  </cit>. But at MIT, a group of hackers was sufficiently captivated by <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> that they developed a similar game, <title rend="quotes">Zork,</title> along with a company, Infocom, to market it <ptr target="#anderson1985"/>; <ptr target="#briceno2000"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Analysis of Crowther’s Source Code</head>
               <p>The earliest source code for Crowther's PDP-10 <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> game <ptr target="#crowther1976"/>, exists in two FORTRAN
					files — one for data, and one for code, dated 11 Mar 1977. According to <ref target="#woods2007">Woods (2007)</ref>, these files show the program as
					Crowther left it, before Woods began debugging and expanding the code. The data
					file comprises six separate tables that contain most of the game's text: 1) long
					descriptions, 2) short room labels, 3) map data, 4) grouped vocabulary keywords,
					5) static game states, and 6) hints and events. Embedded in the code file are
					the static components of variable strings, such as <q> I SEE
						NO <q>,A5,</q> HERE.</q> (where <q>A5</q> represents the name of an object). All text was
					written in all-caps due to the limitations of the PDP-10.</p>
               <div>
                  <head>Table 1 [Long Descriptions]</head>
               	<quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>1 YOU ARE STANDING AT THE END OF A ROAD BEFORE A SMALL BRICK</item>
                        <item>1 BUILDING. AROUND YOU IS A FOREST. A SMALL</item>
                        <item>1 STREAM FLOWS OUT OF THE BUILDING AND DOWN A GULLY.</item>
                        <item>2 YOU HAVE WALKED UP A HILL, STILL IN THE FOREST</item>
                        <item>2 THE ROAD NOW SLOPES BACK DOWN THE OTHER SIDE OF THE HILL.</item>
                        <item>2 THERE IS A BUILDING IN THE DISTANCE.</item>
                        <item>3 YOU ARE INSIDE A BUILDING, A WELL HOUSE FOR A LARGE
							SPRING.</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
                  <p>The first line in the data file is not the first text displayed when the game
						starts, or the first instruction executed by the computer; rather, it is
						simply the first row in a table that stores long descriptions of game
						locations. Its 149 lines present 78 separate items numbered from 1-79
						(omitting number 26). Items 42-58 include ten locations with the identical
						description <q>YOU ARE IN A MAZE OF TWISTY LITTLE
							PASSAGES, ALL ALIKE,</q> representing locations in a challenging
						three-dimensional maze. (Woods added a separate maze, with rooms that are
							<q>ALL DIFFERENT.</q>) Typically, the items in
						this table are displayed when the player has changed location, but some
						describe an unexpected game state.</p>
               	<quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>20 YOU ARE AT THE BOTTOM OF THE PIT WITH A BROKEN NECK.</item>
                        <item>21 YOU DIDN'T MAKE IT</item>
                        <item>22 THE DOME IS UNCLIMBABLE</item>
                        <item>23 YOU CAN'T GO IN THROUGH A LOCKED STEEL GRATE!</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Table 2 [Short Room Labels]</head>
               	<quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>1 YOU'RE AT END OF ROAD AGAIN.</item>
                        <item>2 YOU'RE AT HILL IN ROAD.</item>
                        <item>3 YOU'RE INSIDE BUILDING.</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
                  <p>Table 2 holds 27 one-line items, numbered from 1-68, with many gaps. The
						entries in Table 1 that report failed attempts to move to the requested
						location, such as items 20-23 above, have no corresponding labels in Table
						2. Rooms with short descriptions, such as #29 (<q>YOU ARE
							IN THE SOUTH SIDE CHAMBER.</q>) and most maze locations, also have
						no corresponding Table 2 entry.</p>
               	<quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>18 YOU'RE IN NUGGET OF GOLD ROOM.</item>
                        <item>19 YOU'RE IN HALL OF MT KING.</item>
                        <item>33 YOU'RE AT Y2</item>
                        <item>35 YOU'RE AT WINDOW ON PIT</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
                  <p>Slightly more than half of the lines end with periods; the rest are
						unpunctuated. </p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Table 3 [Map Data]</head>
               	<quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">
						               <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                           <cell>44</cell>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>3</cell>
                           <cell>3</cell>
                           <cell>12</cell>
                           <cell>19</cell>
                           <cell>43</cell>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>4</cell>
                           <cell>4</cell>
                           <cell>5</cell>
                           <cell>13</cell>
                           <cell>14</cell>
                           <cell>46</cell>
                           <cell>30</cell>
                           <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>5</cell>
                           <cell>6</cell>
                           <cell>45</cell>
                           <cell>43</cell>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>8</cell>
                           <cell>49</cell>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>8</cell>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                           <cell>12</cell>
                           <cell>7</cell>
                           <cell>43</cell>
                           <cell>45</cell>
                           <cell>30</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                           <cell>5</cell>
                           <cell>6</cell>
                           <cell>45</cell>
                           <cell>46</cell>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>3</cell>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>3</cell>
                           <cell>11</cell>
                           <cell>32</cell>
                           <cell>44</cell>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>3</cell>
                           <cell>11</cell>
                           <cell>48</cell>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>3</cell>
                           <cell>33</cell>
                           <cell>65</cell>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>3</cell>
                           <cell>79</cell>
                           <cell>5</cell>
                           <cell>14</cell>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                        </row>
                     </table>
					             </quote>
                  <p>Table 3 links map locations with vocabulary word groups. Experienced coders
						are invited to spelunk the FORTRAN source directly <ptr target="#crowther1976"/>; those who are unfamiliar with the language may
						appreciate a brief guided tour on how this table handles player navigation.
						The line <q>1 2 2 44</q>, when interpreted by the
						code, means <q>When in room 1 (<q>YOU'RE
								AT END OF ROAD AGAIN</q>), print out the strings in Table 1
							marked with value 2 ('YOU HAVE WALKED UP A HILL, STILL IN THE FOREST /
							THE ROAD NOW SLOPES BACK DOWN THE OTHER SIDE OF THE HILL. / THERE IS A
							BUILDING IN THE DISTANCE.') in response to the player typing keyword 2
								(<q>ROAD</q>) or a keyword from group 44
								(<q>WEST</q> or <q>W</q>). Then, move the player to room 2, <q>HILL
								IN ROAD</q>.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>The line <q>3 1 3 11 32 44</q> represents several ways
						to get from room 3 (<q>YOU'RE INSIDE BUILDING</q>) to
						room 1 (<q>YOU'RE AT END OF ROAD AGAIN</q>). These
						include several words (<q>ENTER</q>, <q>DOOR</q> and <q>GATE</q>) that
						Table 4 lists with a value of 3; another set (<q>OUT</q>, <q>OUTSI</q>, <q>EXIT</q>, and <q>LEAVE</q>) with a value of 11;
						the word <q>OUTDO[ORS]</q> (which has a value of 32)
						and <q>WEST</q> and <q>W</q>
						(which we have already seen carry the value of 44).</p>
                  <p>The table handles some special events very efficiently. For instance, the
						Table 3 [Map Data] line <q>3 79 5 14</q> defines what
						happens when the player is in room 3 (<q>YOU'RE INSIDE
							BUILDING</q>) and types <q>DOWNS</q> or <q>STREAM</q> — a reasonable request, but one that the
						game does not permit. The game prints out the strings from Table 1 marked
						with value 79, or <q>THE STREAM FLOWS OUT THROUGH A PAIR
							OF 1 FOOT DIAMETER SEWER / PIPES. IT WOULD BE ADVISABLE TO USE THE
						DOOR.</q> Since the game has refused the requested action, the player
						should not end this turn in room number 79 (which does not exist), but
						rather should stay in room 3. The Table 3 [Map Data] entry for value 79 is
							<q>79 3 1</q>, which we may translate as <q>When temporarily in fake room 79, move the player to room
							3 if the player has entered vocabulary keyword group 1.</q> But
						there is no vocabulary keyword group 1; the vocabulary word groups start
						with a value of 2. Just as room 79 is a room the player cannot visit,
						vocabulary group 1 represents a keyword that the player can never type. The
						code is set up to respond to these values by delivering a customized
						rejection message and returning the player to the room where the turn
						started.</p>
                  <p>The line <q>3 11 48</q> will move the player from
						inside the building (3) to <q>YOU'RE IN DEBRIS
						ROOM</q> when the player types the keyword 48 — the famous magic word
							<q>XYZZY</q>. Likewise, <q>3 33
							65</q> describes how the player moves from inside the building to
							<q>YOU'RE AT Y2</q> (room 33) after invoking the
						magic word <q>PLUGH</q> (65).</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Table 4 [Grouped Vocabulary Keywords]</head>
                  <p>This long table (193 items) represents every word the game recognizes, though
						all input is truncated to the first 5 characters. The first group of 93
						lines stores strings that the game recognizes as attempts to move. These are
						numbered from 2-70 with some omissions and many duplicates. </p>
               	<quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>2 ROAD</item>
                        <item>3 ENTER</item>
                        <item>3 DOOR</item>
                        <item>3 GATE</item>
                        <item>4 UPSTR</item>
                        <item>5 DOWNS</item>
                        <item>6 FORES</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
                  <p>The numbering identifies the typed commands <q>ENTER</q>, <q>DOOR</q> and <q>GATE</q> with a value of 3, marking them as synonyms. The last item
						in this section, numbered 70, is <q>BEDQU[ILT]</q>.
						Most of these words are the names of specific locations, but words for
						general motion (<q>BACK</q>, <q>RETUR[N]</q> and <q>RETRE[AT]</q>) are also
						on the list.<note>According to Crowther's help text, <quote rend="inline" source="#crowther1976">MOST OF MY VOCABULARY DESCRIBES PLACES AND IS USED TO MOVE YOU
								THERE.</quote> (<ref target="#crowther1976">Excerpt from Item 51 in
								Table 6.</ref>)</note> While Adventure lore commonly reports that
						Crowther created the game for his young daughters, the keyword table
						suggests Crowther also had adult players in mind. The last keyword is an
						expletive.</p>
                  <p>While navigation by compass directions is perhaps one of the most
						recognizable features of the text-adventure genre, the compass directions
						seem to have been added relatively late to the vocabulary data table. Thus,
						dozens of names for locations from the initial above-ground sequence (<q>HOUSE</q>, <q>GATE</q>, <q>FORES[T]</q>) and words associated with a more linear
						navigation style (<q>FORWA[RD]</q>, <q>BACK</q>, <q>ENTER</q> and
							<q>EXIT</q>) are numbered 2-26, with synonyms such
						as <q>NULL</q> and <q>NOWHE[RE]</q> sharing numbers. Terms for the concepts <q>UP</q> and <q>DOWN</q> and
						several synonyms appear at numbers 29 and 30, respectively, while the four
						cardinal compass directions appear in numbers 43-46, and the diagonals at 60
						and 62-64. William F. Mann, a caver who <quote rend="inline" source="#mann2003">helped a bit
							with the mapping of the Bedquilt area</quote> depicted in the game,
						recalls playing <quote rend="inline" source="#mann2003">several versions of ADVENTURE as they
							were being developed</quote>
						               <ptr target="#mann2003"/>. According to Mann, the game had always included
						compass directions; he suggests that the late appearance of the compass
						directions in the vocabulary table indicates that Crowther moved that
						feature from the code file to the data file at that stage of development.
						Further evidence that supports the assertion that compass directions were
						always an important way of navigating in the game is found in Table 6, in
						which items 10, 11 and 14 are displayed variously when the player is having
						trouble navigating. Each of these first suggests navigation by compass
						points, then via place names (e.g. item 10: <q>I AM UNSURE
							HOW YOU ARE FACING. USE COMPASS POINTS OR NEARBY OBJECTS.</q>).</p>
                  <p> A second group of 35 items, numbered from 1001-1023 with some omissions and
						duplication, represents objects, including props that can be picked up (e.g.
						the keys and various treasures), scenery items that affect the player's
						motion (e.g. the rough stone steps and the fissure in the Hall of Mists),
						and adversaries (the snake and the dwarves). </p>
               	<quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>1001 KEYS</item>
                        <item>1001 KEY</item>
                        <item>1002 LAMP</item>
                        <item>1002 HEADL</item>
                        <item>1003 GRATE</item>
                        <item>1004 CAGE</item>
                        <item>1005 ROD</item>
                        <item>1006 STEPS</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
                  <p>Item 1018 and item 1022 are both given as <q>KNIFE</q>,
						but only item 1018 is set up to accept the synonym <q>KNIVE[S]</q>. Note that <q>HEADL[AMP]</q> is
						given as a synonym for <q>LAMP,</q> reflecting the
						caving practice of keeping the hands free by mounting the light source on
						one's head. (Don Woods added the synonym <q>LANTE</q>
						and referred to the light source as a <q>LANTERN.</q>) </p>
                  <p>A third group of 53 lines covers 16 more commands, including 12 synonyms for
							<q>TAKE</q>, five for <q>RELEA[SE]</q>, and nine for <q>WALK</q>.</p>
                  <p>An examination of this table reveals several insights. Crowther's original
						version contains no vocabulary words to represent commands for saving a
						game, reporting the score, or taking inventory of possessions; all these
						elements were added by Woods. One of the most versatile objects in the
						Crowther/Woods collaboration, the bottle — which can be empty or full, and
						refilled with water or oil — exists in a greatly simplified form in the
						Crowther original. The word <q>BOTTL[E]</q> and the
						word <q>WATER</q> both have the number 1020,
						indicating that the container and its contents were treated by Crowther as
						the same object. There are table entries for <q>POUR</q> and <q>DRINK,</q> both of which will set
						a flag that indicates the bottle is empty; yet there are no commands for
						refilling the bottle. Since the last prop in this list is 1023, the
						numbering suggests Crowther added the bottle at a late stage in the game's
						development. </p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Table 5 [Static Game States]</head>
               	<quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>201 THERE ARE SOME KEYS ON THE GROUND HERE.</item>
                        <item>202 THERE IS A SHINY BRASS LAMP NEARBY.</item>
                        <item>3 THE GRATE IS LOCKED</item>
                        <item>103 THE GRATE IS OPEN.</item>
                        <item>204 THERE IS A SMALL WICKER CAGE DISCARDED NEARBY.</item>
                        <item>205 A THREE FOOT BLACK ROD WITH A RUSTY STAR ON AN END LIES
							NEARBY</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
                  <p>This short table (24 items) includes descriptions of game states that
						represent lasting changes to the environment. For example, if the player
						drops the keys in a room, then every time the player returns to the room, a
						message will indicate the presence of the keys. Some of these table entries
						describe obstacles, and others describe room features. Exclamation points
						emphasize the importance of valuable items, threats, and unexpected
						consequences.</p>
               	<quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>209 ROUGH STONE STEPS LEAD UP THE DOME.</item>
                        <item>210 THERE IS A LARGE SPARKLING NUGGET OF GOLD HERE!</item>
                        <item>11 A HUGE GREEN FIERCE SNAKE BARS THE WAY!</item>
                        <item>112 A CRYSTAL BRIDGE NOW SPANS THE FISSURE.</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
                  <p>The numbering here is not sequential, because the hundreds digit is used to
						indicate an alternate state — e.g. item 3 defines the locked grate, and item
						103 defines the unlocked grate. </p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Table 6 [Hints and Events]</head>
                  <p>The final table in the data file, 132 lines long, contains 80 numbered groups
						of lines that offer hints and descriptions of one-time game events (rather
						than enduring state changes, such as Table 5 contains).</p>
               	<quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>1 SOMEWHERE NEARBY IS COLOSSAL CAVE, WHERE OTHERS HAVE FOUND</item>
                        <item>1 FORTUNES IN TREASURE AND GOLD, THOUGH IT IS RUMORED</item>
                        <item>1 THAT SOME WHO ENTER ARE NEVER SEEN AGAIN. MAGIC IS SAID</item>
                        <item>1 TO WORK IN THE CAVE. I WILL BE YOUR EYES AND HANDS. DIRECT</item>
                        <item>1 ME WITH COMMANDS OF 1 OR 2 WORDS.</item>
                        <item>1 (ERRORS, SUGGESTIONS, COMPLAINTS TO CROWTHER)</item>
                        <item>1 (IF STUCK TYPE HELP FOR SOME HINTS)</item>
                        <item>2 A LITTLE DWARF WITH A BIG KNIFE BLOCKS YOUR WAY.</item>
                        <item>3 A LITTLE DWARF JUST WALKED AROUND A CORNER,SAW YOU, THREW</item>
                        <item>3 A LITTLE AXE AT YOU WHICH MISSED, CURSED, AND RAN AWAY.</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
                  <p>Crowther's prose was lean and condensed, as we see in item 3. The subject
							<q>DWARF</q> is followed by a tight array of six
						verbs, of which the first three (<q>WALKED,</q>
						               <q>SAW</q> and <q>THREW</q>)
						pertain to the subject, the next (<q>MISSED</q>)
						pertains to the direct object (<q>AXE</q>), and the
						final two (<q>CURSED</q> and <q>RAN</q>) pertain to the subject. The compressed structure leads to an
						amusing ambiguity, suggesting that the axe not only missed, but also cursed
						and ran away. </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Notes on the Woods Expansion</head>
               <p>Mann's assessment of the Crowther/Woods collaboration offers an apt summary:
						<quote rend="inline" source="#mann2004">Crowther was interested in using the cave as a setting
						for a game, with magic, puzzles, conflict, and humor. Woods carried that
						forward, but without the feel for being in an actual cave, and with a need
						to limit the use of the machine to off hours. He added mostly policy,
						puzzles and humor</quote> <ptr target="#mann2004"/>. Crowther supplied the original text-parser
					and established the basic principles of gameplay, leaving Woods free to
					concentrate on expansion, creative variation, and real-world resource management
					(such as a system for resuming a suspended game and a password-protected method
					of restricting access to the game during working hours). Woods retained the
					general structure of the code when he expanded the game, typically adding on to
					the end of the existing tables, and squeezing creative variations out of his own
					imagination and out of possibilities he found in Crowther's original material.
					For example, Crowther's original responds to the command <q>BLAST</q> with the message <q>BLASTING REQUIRES
						DYNAMITE,</q> but none exists in his game. Woods, however, incorporates
						<q>BLAST</q> into the finale. </p>
               <p>Woods added several rooms to Crowther's existing <q>ALL
					ALIKE</q> maze (making the maze more challenging to navigate), and created
					his own maze, where the passages were <q>ALL
					DIFFERENT.</q> He also created a randomly-moving pirate who steals the
					player's treasures. Crowther supplied the humorous solution to the snake
					obstacle, but when the player tries to unleash the same feathered fury on
					Woods’s dragon, the results are comically disastrous. While Crowther's bottle of
					water can only be emptied, Woods adds complexity by making it refillable and
					capable of carrying water or oil. Woods also supplied puzzles for Crowther's
					consumable items (the food and the water). In a variation on the crystal bridge
					that can appear, Woods adds a bridge that can collapse. </p>
               <p>Where Crowther was an efficient minimalist, Woods was comparatively lavish with
					scenery. Crowther did not create corpse objects for vanquished opponents; once
					defeated, the snake and the dwarves simply vanish. Woods, on the other hand,
					implements separate functional and destroyed objects for the dragon, the bear,
					and the troll bridge. He also created a plant that exists in three states –
					thirsty and small, thirsty and large, and sated and climbable. Because Woods
					added objects with complex behavior, his code had to deal with an even greater
					number of potential events. (For example, what happens when a wandering dwarf
					encounters the bear or the dragon?)</p>
               <p>Woods edited for standard usage, and occasionally for clarity. Upon starting
						<title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>, the player's first choice is whether
					to ask for instructions (see <ref target="#example01">Example 1</ref>, below). </p>
               <dhq:example xml:id="example01">
                  <head>Comparison of Instructions Text</head>
                  <p>
						               <ref target="#crowther1975">Crowther, 1975-76</ref>
					             </p>
               	<quote rend="block" source="#crowther1977">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>1 SOMEWHERE NEARBY IS COLOSSAL CAVE, WHERE OTHERS HAVE FOUND</item>
                        <item>1 FORTUNES IN TREASURE AND GOLD, THOUGH IT IS RUMORED</item>
                        <item>1 THAT SOME WHO ENTER ARE NEVER SEEN AGAIN. MAGIC IS SAID</item>
                        <item>1 TO WORK IN THE CAVE. I WILL BE YOUR EYES AND HANDS. DIRECT</item>
                        <item>1 ME WITH COMMANDS OF 1 OR 2 WORDS.</item>
                        <item>1 (ERRORS, SUGGESTIONS, COMPLAINTS TO CROWTHER)</item>
                        <item>1 (IF STUCK TYPE HELP FOR SOME HINTS)</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
                  <p>
						               <ref target="#crowther1977">Crowther and Woods, 1977</ref>
					             </p>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1997">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>1 SOMEWHERE NEARBY IS COLOSSAL CAVE, WHERE OTHERS HAVE FOUND
								FORTUNES IN</item>
                        <item>1 TREASURE AND GOLD, THOUGH IT IS RUMORED THAT SOME WHO ENTER ARE
								NEVER</item>
                        <item>1 SEEN AGAIN. MAGIC IS SAID TO WORK IN THE CAVE. I WILL BE YOUR
								EYES</item>
                        <item>1 AND HANDS. DIRECT ME WITH COMMANDS OF 1 OR 2 WORDS. I SHOULD
								WARN</item>
                        <item>1 YOU THAT I LOOK AT ONLY THE FIRST FIVE LETTERS OF EACH WORD, SO
								YOU'LL</item>
                        <item>1 HAVE TO ENTER <q>NORTHEAST</q> AS <q>NE</q> TO DISTINGUISH IT FROM <q>NORTH</q>.</item>
                        <item>1 (SHOULD YOU GET STUCK, TYPE <q>HELP</q>
								FOR SOME GENERAL HINTS. FOR INFOR-</item>
                        <item>1 MATION ON HOW TO END YOUR ADVENTURE, ETC., TYPE <q>INFO</q>.)</item>
                        <item>1 - - -</item>
                        <item>1 THIS PROGRAM WAS ORIGINALLY DEVELOPED BY WILLIE CROWTHER. MOST
								OF THE</item>
                        <item>1 FEATURES OF THE CURRENT PROGRAM WERE ADDED BY DON WOODS (DON @
								SU-AI).</item>
                        <item>1 CONTACT DON IF YOU HAVE ANY QUESTIONS, COMMENTS, ETC.</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
               </dhq:example>
               <p>Woods retained the purely aesthetic portion of Crowther's instructions (offering
					a motivation for the player's actions and introducing the fantasy element), but
					added details pertaining to the text parser, session mechanics, and authorship.
					While Crowther ended his instructions with a no-nonsense, <q>IF STUCK TYPE HELP FOR HINTS,</q> Woods expanded, qualified, and
					punctuated the statement thus: <q>SHOULD YOU GET STUCK, TYPE
							<q>HELP</q> FOR SOME GENERAL HINTS</q>. Woods
					also added a note about the parser's inability to tell the difference between
						<q>NORTH</q> and <q>NORTHEAST,</q> illustrating the attention he paid to improving the playing
					experience.</p>
               <p>Both versions offer hints accessible by typing <q>HELP</q>
					(see <ref target="#example02">Example 2</ref>, below). To Crowther's original
						<q>HELP</q> text, Woods added a reference to the new
					verb <q>INVENTORY,</q> and clarified a passage referring
					to manipulating objects. </p>
               <dhq:example xml:id="example02">
                  <head>Comparison of Hint Text</head>
                  <p>
						               <ref target="#crowther1976">Crowther, 1975-76</ref>
					             </p>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>51 I KNOW OF PLACES, ACTIONS, AND THINGS. MOST OF MY VOCABULARY</item>
                        <item>51 DESCRIBES PLACES AND IS USED TO MOVE YOU THERE. TO MOVE TRY</item>
                        <item>51 WORDS LIKE FOREST, BUILDING, DOWNSTREAM, ENTER, EAST, WEST</item>
                        <item>51 NORTH, SOUTH, UP, OR DOWN. I KNOW ABOUT A FEW SPECIAL OBJECTS,</item>
                        <item>51 LIKE A BLACK ROD HIDDEN IN THE CAVE. THESE OBJECTS CAN BE</item>
                        <item>51 MANIPULATED USING ONE OF THE ACTION WORDS THAT I KNOW. USUALLY </item>
                        <item>51 YOU WILL NEED TO GIVE BOTH THE OBJECT AND ACTION WORDS</item>
                        <item>51 (IN EITHER ORDER), BUT SOMETIMES I CAN INFER THE OBJECT FROM</item>
                        <item>51 THE VERB ALONE. THE OBJECTS HAVE SIDE EFFECTS - FOR</item>
                        <item>51 INSTANCE, THE ROD SCARES THE BIRD.</item>
                        <item>51 USUALLY PEOPLE HAVING TROUBLE MOVING JUST NEED TO TRY A FEW</item>
                        <item>51 MORE WORDS. USUALLY PEOPLE TRYING TO MANIPULATE AN</item>
                        <item>51 OBJECT ARE ATTEMPTING SOMETHING BEYOND THEIR (OR MY!)</item>
                        <item>51 CAPABILITIES AND SHOULD TRY A COMPLETELY DIFFERENT TACK.</item>
                        <item>51 TO SPEED THE GAME YOU CAN SOMETIMES MOVE LONG DISTANCES</item>
                        <item>51 WITH A SINGLE WORD. FOR EXAMPLE, <q>BUILDING</q> USUALLY GETS</item>
                        <item>51 YOU TO THE BUILDING FROM ANYWHERE ABOVE GROUND EXCEPT WHEN</item>
                        <item>51 LOST IN THE FOREST. ALSO, NOTE THAT CAVE PASSAGES TURN A</item>
                        <item>51 LOT, AND THAT LEAVING A ROOM TO THE NORTH DOES NOT GUARANTEE</item>
                        <item>51 ENTERING THE NEXT FROM THE SOUTH. GOOD LUCK!</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
                  <p>
						               <ref target="#crowther1977">Crowther and Woods, 1977</ref>
					             </p>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1977">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>51 I KNOW OF PLACES, ACTIONS, AND THINGS. MOST OF MY VOCABULARY</item>
                        <item>51 DESCRIBES PLACES AND IS USED TO MOVE YOU THERE. TO MOVE, TRY
								WORDS</item>
                        <item>51 LIKE FOREST, BUILDING, DOWNSTREAM, ENTER, EAST, WEST, NORTH,
								SOUTH,</item>
                        <item>51 UP, OR DOWN. I KNOW ABOUT A FEW SPECIAL OBJECTS, LIKE A BLACK
								ROD</item>
                        <item>51 HIDDEN IN THE CAVE. THESE OBJECTS CAN BE MANIPULATED USING SOME
								OF</item>
                        <item>51 THE ACTION WORDS THAT I KNOW. USUALLY YOU WILL NEED TO GIVE
								BOTH THE</item>
                        <item>51 OBJECT AND ACTION WORDS (IN EITHER ORDER), BUT SOMETIMES I CAN
								INFER</item>
                        <item>51 THE OBJECT FROM THE VERB ALONE. SOME OBJECTS ALSO IMPLY VERBS;
								IN</item>
                        <item>51 PARTICULAR, <q>INVENTORY</q> IMPLIES
									<q>TAKE INVENTORY</q>, WHICH CAUSES ME TO</item>
                        <item>51 GIVE YOU A LIST OF WHAT YOU'RE CARRYING. THE OBJECTS HAVE SIDE</item>
                        <item>51 EFFECTS; FOR INSTANCE, THE ROD SCARES THE BIRD. USUALLY PEOPLE
								HAVING</item>
                        <item>51 TROUBLE MOVING JUST NEED TO TRY A FEW MORE WORDS. USUALLY
								PEOPLE</item>
                        <item>51 TRYING UNSUCCESSFULLY TO MANIPULATE AN OBJECT ARE ATTEMPTING
								SOMETHING</item>
                        <item>51 BEYOND THEIR (OR MY!) CAPABILITIES AND SHOULD TRY A COMPLETELY</item>
                        <item>51 DIFFERENT TACK. TO SPEED THE GAME YOU CAN SOMETIMES MOVE LONG</item>
                        <item>51 DISTANCES WITH A SINGLE WORD. FOR EXAMPLE, <q>BUILDING</q> USUALLY GETS</item>
                        <item>51 YOU TO THE BUILDING FROM ANYWHERE ABOVE GROUND EXCEPT WHEN LOST
								IN THE</item>
                        <item>51 FOREST. ALSO, NOTE THAT CAVE PASSAGES TURN A LOT, AND THAT
								LEAVING A</item>
                        <item>51 ROOM TO THE NORTH DOES NOT GUARANTEE ENTERING THE NEXT FROM THE
								SOUTH.</item>
                        <item>51 GOOD LUCK!</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
               </dhq:example>
               <p>Crowther had written <q>USUALLY PEOPLE TRYING TO MANIPULATE AN
						OBJECT ARE ATTEMPTING SOMETHING BEYOND THEIR (OR MY!) CAPABILITIES…</q>
					Because players see this passage only after typing <q>HELP,</q> the context suggests that this passage refers to a player having
					difficulty manipulating an object; yet a novice player who encounters that
					passage very early in the game might conclude that the game does not permit any
					manipulation at all. Woods's revision refers more precisely to <q>TRYING <emph>UNSUCCESSFULLY</emph> TO MANIPULATE AN
					OBJECT</q> (emphasis added). Likewise, where Crowther referred to
					manipulating objects using <q>ONE OF THE ACTION WORDS THAT I
						KNOW</q>, Woods avoided giving the impression that an object can be
					manipulated with <emph>only</emph> one action word, so that his passage refers
					instead to <q>
                     <emph>SOME</emph> OF THE ACTION WORDS</q>
					(emphasis added).</p>
               <p>Crowther's potent writing features in Room 13, <q>…A SPLENDID
						CHAMBER THIRTY FEET HIGH. THE WALLS ARE FROZEN RIVERS OF ORANGE STONE. AN
						AWKWARD CANYON AND A GOOD PASSAGE EXIT FROM EAST AND WEST SIDES OF THE
						CHAMBER.</q> A forthcoming study of caves as computer game environments
					assesses this passage as follows: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#jerz2005">While the player is informed that the chamber is <q>splendid,</q> the text does not explicitly state
							what emotional effect the height of the chamber or the proximity of the
								<q>frozen rivers of orange stone</q> is
							supposed to have. Rather, we see this location through seasoned,
							critical eyes, duly noting the presence of geological wonders, but then
							immediately evaluating the next possible move, as one must do when
							exploring in a real cave. As it happens, the <q>awkward</q> exit from the Orange River Room is the way back to
							the surface, and the <q>good passage</q> leads
							deeper into the cave. Without clumsily announcing something like, <q>The west exit looks so intriguing that you can hardly
								wait to explore it,</q> the text subtly discourages the player's
							premature exit, and reinforces the exploratory premise of classic text
							adventures. </quote>
                     <ptr target="#jerz2005"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> succeeds in large part due to the depth
					and realism of the scenery, which is rendered in concise prose that calls
					interesting details to the reader's attention, yet leaves much to the
					imagination. The <quote rend="inline" source="#crowther1977">Breath-Taking View</quote> (<ref target="#crowther1977">Crowther and Woods, Room 126</ref>) is an exception;
					co-authored by Gilbert, the graduate student who played Crowther's version of
						<title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> with Woods late into the night, its
					effusive language not only tells what the room looks like, but also informs the
					reader what emotions the scene is supposed to invoke (cf. the gorge <q>FILLED WITH A BIZARRE CHAOS OF TORTURED ROCK WHICH SEEMS TO
						HAVE BEEN CRAFTED BY THE DEVIL HIMSELF</q>). When Nelson analyzes the
					tension between Crowther's austere fantasy vision and the often comical set
					pieces supplied by Woods, he finds the stylistic conflict an agreeable part of
					the game's charm. <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#nelson2001">Stretching a point, you could say that there is a
							Crowther and a Woods in every designer, the one intent on recreating an
							experienced world, the other with a really neat puzzle which ought to
							fit <emph>somewhere</emph>
                     </quote>
                     <ptr target="#nelson2001" loc="345"/>
                  </cit>. Notable tension is evident in changes to the cave environment that occur
					in the Woods expansion, such as 1) the underground volcano, 2) the
					battery-dispensing vending machine, and 3) announcements from a public address
					system warning that the cave is closing. Lacking firsthand experience of caves,
					Woods had to rely upon his own imagination. Yet even these details logically
					extend, respectively, Crowther's use of 1) intriguing geography, 2) treasure
					items, and 3) magic words. Some of Woods's additions, such as the Soft Room and
					the Oriental Room, seem completely out of place when considered separately; but
					once it becomes clear that objects found in these two locations work together to
					solve an inventory puzzle, these two incongruities make perfect sense as gaming
					elements. </p>
               <p>In 1994, Crowther reflected on the success of the game: <quote rend="inline" source="#hafner1994">And
						why did people enjoy it? Because it's exactly the kind of thing that
						computer programmers do. They're struggling with an obstinate system that
						can do what you want but only if you can figure out the right thing to say
						to it</quote>
					             <ptr target="#hafner1994" loc="2–3"/>. Crowther's children both recall instances
					in which their father deflected their frustration with <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> by noting that they were stuck on one of Woods’s details
					(see <ref target="#section04">Section 4</ref>). According to <ref target="#crowther2001">Crowther (2001)</ref>, <quote rend="inline" source="#crowther2001">My intent
						was that the deeper you went into the cave, the more fantasy appeared. Don
						made it appear faster than ever I would have, which in retrospect was
					good</quote>. </p>
               <p>Woods's most striking diversions from Crowther's initial realism occur on the far
					side of the troll bridge, yet this region is only accessible after the player
					has encountered Crowther's earlier scenery, which involves capturing a strangely
					passive little bird, watching the improbable defeat of a fierce snake, conjuring
					up a magical crystal bridge, teleporting via magic words, and fighting with
					dwarves whose corpses vanish. Given this context, the fairy-tale elements that
					Woods supplied (including a dragon, a troll, a beanstalk, more magic words, and
					a friendly bear) seem perfectly in keeping with Crowther's fantasy premise. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="section03">
            <head>Exploring Colossal Cave in Kentucky</head>
            <p> Woods's 1977 expansion of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> features <q>RECENT ISSUES OF <title rend="quotes">SPELUNKER TODAY</title>
					MAGAZINE,</q> and sources often describe Crowther as a <q>spelunker.</q> Yet <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#cahill2001">[c]avers haven't called themselves spelunkers for almost 40
						years now. They may belong to the National Speleological Society, but they
						don't spelunk. They cave.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#cahill2001"/>
               </cit>
               <note>A bumper sticker and T-shirt slogan often seen in cave country reads
						<q>Cavers rescue spelunkers</q>.</note> Resources from
				caving culture, including an expedition to Colossal Cave, offer various insights on
				Crowther's <title rend="quotes">Adventure.</title>
			         </p>
            <div>
               <head>Bedquilt Entrance, Colossal Cave</head>
               <figure xml:id="figure03">
                  <head>Flint Mammoth Cave System / Bedquilt Section, Colossal Cave. The title box of the survey map Will and Pat Crowther completed for the
							Cave Research Foundation represents Bedquilt as a section of Colossal
							Cave, rather than a separate nearby cave, as it has often been
							misunderstood.  Photo by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by permission. </head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_003.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of the title box of the survey map for the Bedquilt Cave section
						of Colossal Cave</figDesc>
                  
               </figure>
               <p> In his popular online tribute to <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>, Adams
					(2001c) correctly identifies Colossal as part of the Mammoth system, but
					perpetuates a misunderstanding when he writes <quote rend="inline" source="#adams2001c">the game is
						not actually based on that cave, but is instead a remarkably faithful
						reproduction of nearby Bedquilt Cave.</quote> In fact, Bedquilt is <q>nearby</q> Colossal Cave only in the sense that your back
					door is <q>nearby</q> your house. </p>
               <figure xml:id="figure04">
                  <head>Bedquilt Entrance Label.  Another detail from the same 1975 map of Colossal Cave. The boxed X
							indicates the horizontal grate leading into the cave. 
						               Photo by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
							permission.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_004.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of a detail from the survey map of Colossal Cave</figDesc>
                  
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Crowther's Map and Game</head>
               <p>Crowther's frequent caving and mapping collaborator was his wife Pat, who in 1972
					had distinguished herself in the caving community by making the final connection
					– that is, physically squeezing through a tiny hole — between two sprawling
					networks of caverns which had up to that point been considered separate
					entities. For years, using a compass and a measuring tape, survey teams from the
					Cave Research Foundation had recorded the coordinates of a sinewy array of 3D
					points. The Crowthers used the raw data to form a computer model. According to a
					Feb 6 1990 alt.folklore.computers posting written by the former Patricia
					Crowther <ptr target="#wilcox1990"/>: <quote rend="inline" source="#wilcox1990">We typed in all that
						survey data from muddy little books on a 110-baud teletype to a PDP-1…. Then
						generated plotting commands on huge rolls of paper tape, which we carried
						over and plotted using a salvaged Calcomp drum plotter attached to a
						Honeywell 316 that was destined to become an ARPAnet IMP.</quote>
				           </p>
               <figure xml:id="figure05">
                  <head>Cave Survey Line Plot. Did Will Crowther create a map-like cave simulation that was later turned
							into a fantasy role-playing game that we know as <title rend="quotes">Colossal Cave Adventure</title>? 
						               While both the graphical map and the textual game represent Crowther's
							creative efforts to use computer technology to sort and communicate his
							intimate knowledge of this particular cave system, the two intellectual
							efforts were otherwise unrelated. In 1974, Crowther, a volunteer cartographer with the Cave Research
							Foundation, participated in an intense summer-long survey of the
							Bedquilt region of Colossal Cave. This line plot was published as an
							example of mapped survey data in Brucker and Watson's 1975 <title rend="italic">The Longest Cave</title> (32).</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_005.gif"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of a cave survey line plot</figDesc>
                  
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="figure06">
                  <head>Line Plot and Sketches.   Illustration: Using information taken down in sketchbooks by survey
							teams, Crowther, as volunteer cartographer for the Cave Research
							Foundation, helped flesh out the line plot maps (left) into more
							detailed environmental maps (right). 
						               These images, which represent the Bedquilt Entrance to Colossal Cave,
							appear without identification on page 32 of Brucker and Watson's <title rend="italic">The Longest Cave</title> (see <ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref> above, for comparison).</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_006.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of line plots and sketches of the Bequilt section of Colossal
						Cave</figDesc>
                  
               </figure>
               <p>Mapping the Bedquilt region of Colossal Cave involved using the line plots as the
					framework for hand-drawn details gleaned from sketches and notes taken during
					survey expeditions. While the resulting map can be understood as a technical and
					creative embellishment that makes the stark 3D dataset more accessible and more
					aesthetically appealing, it is a mistake to conflate either the 3D dataset or
					the 2D hand-drawn map with Crowther's text-based game.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Woods's Co-Authorship</head>
               <dhq:example xml:id="example03">
                  <head>Gillogly-Schwartz Transcript 1</head>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#gillogly1977">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>host% <emph>/usr/games/Adventure</emph>
                        </item>
                        <item>Welcome to Adventure!! Would you like instructions?</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>yes</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>Somewhere nearby is Colossal Cave, where others have found
								fortunes in treasure and gold, though it is rumored that some who
								enter are never seen again. Magic is said to work in the cave. I
								will be your eyes and hands. Direct me with commands of 1 or 2
								words. I should warn you that I look at only the first five letters
								of each word, so you'll have to enter <q>northeast</q> as <q>ne</q> to distinguish
								it from <q>north</q>. (Should you get stuck,
								type <q>help</q> for some general hints. For
								information on how to end your adventure, etc., type <q>info</q>.)</item>
                        <item>This program was originally developed by Will Crowther. Most of
								the features of the current program were added by Don Woods. Address
								complaints about the UNIX version to Jim Gillogly (jim@rand.org).</item>
                        <item>You are standing at the end of a road before a small brick
								building. Around you is a forest. A small stream flows out of the
								building and down a gully.</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>enter</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>You are inside a building, a well house for a large spring. There
								are some keys on the ground here. There is a shiny brass lamp
								nearby. There is food here. There is a bottle of water here.</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>get keys</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>OK</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>get lamp</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>OK</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>exit</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>You're at end of road again.</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
                  <p>This transcript of Gillogly's early (July 1977) translation of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> from the Crowther and Woods FORTRAN code
						to C, shows the help text and the first few moves. Italicized passages
						represent the player's contributions. </p>
               </dhq:example>
               <p>When Don Woods published his expansion, he added the following note to the
					in-game help text: <q>THIS PROGRAM WAS ORIGINALLY DEVELOPED BY
						WILLIE CROWTHER. MOST OF THE FEATURES OF THE CURRENT PROGRAM WERE ADDED BY
						DON WOODS (DON @ SU-AI).</q> Gillogly's translation of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> from FORTRAN to C preserves that line
					(editing it to change uppercase letters to lowercase when appropriate; see
					Example 3, above). Gillogly's source code <ptr target="#gillogly1977"/> also
					includes a brief technical note (in <q>hdr.h</q>) that
					states, in part, <quote rend="inline" source="#gillogly1977">This program is a re-write of ADVENT,
						written in FORTRAN mostly by Don Woods of SAIL.</quote> While Woods's
					original note claims authorship of <q>MOST OF THE FEATURES OF
						THE CURRENT PROGRAM,</q> the reference to the <emph>current</emph>
					version seems to imply that Woods was writing for an audience that had access to
					Crowther's original source code. Yet Gillogly's note describes the program
					generally as written <quote rend="inline" source="#gillogly1977">mostly by Don Woods,</quote> which
					seems to intensify Woods's authorial claims, or at least implies a different
					understanding of the term <q>features.</q> In interviews,
					on his website, and in his source code, Woods has always given co-authorship
					credit to Crowther. Gillogly's phrasing may have contributed to the
					commonly-reported meme that Crowther's original version was a realistic map, and
					that all the game and fantasy elements are Woods's. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Comparative Sample: Words, Code, Map, and Images</head>
               <p>The following exercise in multimedia intertextuality compares the first few rooms
					of the cave, as represented via text from a session with Gillogly’s <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>, Crowther's source data, his CRF map, and
					site photographs. Crowther’s CRF map and his original game are completely
					different entities.</p>
               <dhq:example xml:id="example04">
                  <head>Gillogly-Schwartz Transcript 2</head>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#schwartz1999">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>You are in a 20-foot depression floored with bare dirt. Set into
								the dirt is a strong steel grate mounted in concrete. A dry
								streambed leads into the depression. The grate is locked.</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>open grate</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>The grate is now unlocked.</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>down</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>You are in a small chamber beneath a 3x3 steel grate to the
								surface. A low crawl over cobbles leads inward to the west. The
								grate is open.</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>west</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>You are crawling over cobbles in a low passage. There is a dim
								light at the east end of the passage. There is a small wicker cage
								discarded nearby.</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>west</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>It is now pitch dark. If you proceed you will likely fall into a
								pit.</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>lamp on</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>Your lamp is now on. You are in a debris room filled with stuff
								washed in from the surface. A low wide passage with cobbles becomes
								plugged with mud and debris here, but an awkward canyon leads upward
								and west. A note on the wall says <q>Magic word
									XYZZY</q>. A three foot black rod with a rusty star on an
								end lies nearby.</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>east</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>You are crawling over cobbles in a low passage. There is a dim
								light at the east end of the passage. There is a small wicker cage
								discarded nearby.</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>get cage</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>OK</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>west</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>You're in Debris Room. A three foot black rod with a rusty star on
								an end lies nearby.</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>get rod</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>OK</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>west</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>You are in an awkward sloping east/west canyon.</item>
                        <item>
								                   <emph>west</emph>
							                 </item>
                        <item>You are in a splendid chamber thirty feet high. The walls are
								frozen rivers of orange stone. An awkward canyon and a good passage
								exit from east and west sides of the chamber. A cheerful little bird
								is sitting here singing.</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
                  <p>Illustration: This transcript from <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>
						(compiled from <ptr target="#schwartz1999"/>, which records a session with
						the Gillogly UNIX/C version), shows the player entering Colossal Cave via
						Bedquilt. </p>
               </dhq:example>
               <dhq:example xml:id="example05">
                  <head>Crowther -- Bedquilt Entrance to Colossal Cave</head>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1977">
						               <list type="simple">
                        <item>9 YOU ARE IN A SMALL CHAMBER BENEATH A 3X3 STEEL GRATE TO THE</item>
                        <item>9 SURFACE. A LOW CRAWL OVER COBBLES LEADS INWARD TO THE WEST.</item>
                        <item>10 YOU ARE CRAWLING OVER COBBLES IN A LOW PASSAGE. THERE IS A</item>
                        <item>10 DIM LIGHT AT THE EAST END OF THE PASSAGE.</item>
                        <item>11 YOU ARE IN A DEBRIS ROOM, FILLED WITH STUFF WASHED IN FROM</item>
                        <item>11 THE SURFACE. A LOW WIDE PASSAGE WITH COBBLES BECOMES</item>
                        <item>11 PLUGGED WITH MUD AND DEBRIS HERE,BUT AN AWKWARD CANYON</item>
                        <item>11 LEADS UPWARD AND WEST.</item>
                        <item>11 A NOTE ON THE WALL SAYS <q>MAGIC WORD
								XYZZY</q>.</item>
                        <item>12 YOU ARE IN AN AWKWARD SLOPING EAST/WEST CANYON.</item>
                        <item>13 YOU ARE IN A SPLENDID CHAMBER THIRTY FEET HIGH. THE WALLS</item>
                        <item>13 ARE FROZEN RIVERS OF ORANGE STONE. AN AWKWARD CANYON AND A</item>
                        <item>13 GOOD PASSAGE EXIT FROM EAST AND WEST SIDES OF THE
							CHAMBER.</item>
                     </list>
					             </quote>
                  <p>Illustration: Excerpt from the data file for Will Crowther's original
						cave-exploration game. These lines represent locations the player encounters
						near the Bedquilt entrance of Colossal Cave. <ref target="#example04">Example 4</ref> shows these descriptions at work in Giloogly's 1977
						port of the Crowther/Woods source code.</p>
               </dhq:example>
               <p>Don Woods added rich layers of complexity and polish that turned Crowther's code
					from a brilliant idea into a finished game, but Crowther's humor, fantasy,
					combat and puzzles had already set a tone that would define the genre. In
					addition to the <q>Magic Word XYZZY</q> (see <ref target="#example05">Example 5</ref>), players of Crowther's original game
					encountered belligerent dwarves, a surprisingly resourceful bird, a rusty metal
					rod with magical powers, and help text that announces <q>MAGIC
						IS SAID TO WORK IN THE CAVES.</q> Since Woods never visited Colossal
					Cave, the new rooms and scenic elements he created (such as the underground
					volcano and the battery-dispensing vending machine) obviously reflect his own
					imagination, rather than the real subterranean landscape. </p>
               <figure xml:id="figure07">
                  <head>Cave Map <ptr target="#crowther1975"/> compared to Toomey’s Game Map <ptr target="#toomey1990"/>.  How well does the geography of the real Colossal Cave (part of the
							Mammoth Cave System in southwestern Kentucky) match up with the map for
							Crowther's <title rend="quotes">Colossal Cave Adventure</title>? 
						               
                        <q>Cave Map</q> (top) shows a detail from the Cave
							Research Foundation's map of the Bedquilt entrance to Colossal Cave.
							While Crowther simplified the layout for the game, reducing northwest
							zigs and southwest zags, and thus permitting the player to progress
							straight west from the entrance grate (marked with a boxed <q>X</q> in the lower right corner of the <q>CAVE MAP</q>), approximately the first half of the
							game is essentially faithful to the real cave. </head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_007.gif"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of a cave map</figDesc>
                  
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="figure08">
                  <head>CRF-Toomey-Crowther Mashup. <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">
							                 <list type="simple">
                           <item>9 YOU ARE IN A SMALL CHAMBER BENEATH A 3X3 STEEL GRATE TO THE</item>
                           <item>9 SURFACE. A LOW CRAWL OVER COBBLES LEADS INWARD TO THE WEST.</item>
                           <item>10 YOU ARE CRAWLING OVER COBBLES IN A LOW PASSAGE. THERE IS A</item>
                           <item>10 DIM LIGHT AT THE EAST END OF THE PASSAGE.</item>
                           <item>11 YOU ARE IN A DEBRIS ROOM, FILLED WITH STUFF WASHED IN FROM</item>
                           <item>11 THE SURFACE. A LOW WIDE PASSAGE WITH COBBLES BECOMES</item>
                           <item>11 PLUGGED WITH MUD AND DEBRIS HERE,BUT AN AWKWARD CANYON</item>
                           <item>11 LEADS UPWARD AND WEST.</item>
                           <item>11 A NOTE ON THE WALL SAYS <q>MAGIC WORD
										XYZZY</q>.</item>
                           <item>12 YOU ARE IN AN AWKWARD SLOPING EAST/WEST CANYON.</item>
                           <item>13 YOU ARE IN A SPLENDID CHAMBER THIRTY FEET HIGH. THE WALLS</item>
                           <item>13 ARE FROZEN RIVERS OF ORANGE STONE. AN AWKWARD CANYON AND A</item>
                           <item>13 GOOD PASSAGE EXIT FROM EAST AND WEST SIDES OF THE
								CHAMBER.</item>
                        </list>
						               </quote>
						               Illustration: Crowther and Crowther’s 1975 map of the Bedquilt region of
							Colossal cave, overlaid by elements from Toomey’s game map (199x), above
							an excerpt from Table 1 of Crowther’s FORTRAN source files (1976).</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_008.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of a cave map with accompanying text from Adventure</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Photographic Walkthrough</head>
               <p>Like the benevolent omniscient narrator of Victorian fiction, the narrator of
						<title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> — the <q>I</q> who answers
					the player's request for help — chooses to divulge certain details and withhold
					others. This characteristic of the game reflects the values of an experienced
					caver, who is typically reluctant to tell outsiders exactly where the entrances
					are: <quote rend="inline" source="#cahill2001">They'll take a flashlight and a clothesline and one or
						the other will break or malfunction and then they'll die or have to be
						rescued, and you'll be responsible</quote>
					             <ptr target="#cahill2001"/>. For good reason, then, CRF members and National
					Park Service employees are reluctant to publicize the location of any
					undeveloped cave entrance.</p>
               <div>
                  <head>The Bedquilt Rinky-Dink (Building and Forest)</head>
                  <p>Using a publicly-available map, the following details of the region were
						determined in 2004 by Mann: <cit><quote rend="block" source="#mann2004">The (closed) road from the
							Collins House and the Austin house (now torn down) runs south about one
							mile to a public road. The Pumphouse was at the end of another closed
							road (not shown on my map) on the other side of that public road about
							one-half mile southwest at the Adwell Spring. The Bedquilt entrance is
							about another one-half mile southwest, downstream. The Colossal entrance
							is about one-half mile westnorthwest of the Bedquilt entrance, over the
							ridge.</quote><ptr target="#mann2004"/></cit>
                  </p>
                  <p>Via MapQuest's <q>Place Name</q> feature, Adwell Spring
						is easily located as a site within Mammoth Cave National Park.</p>
                  <p>Of the small brick building (which Crowther <ptr target="#crowther1976"/>
						describes as <quote rend="inline" source="#crowther1976">A WELL HOUSE FOR A LARGE SPRING</quote>)
						built by the U.S. Park Service to house a pump that supplied water for
						visitors, only the foundation remains. While the Cave Research Foundation
						did not store supplies there, the <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>
						player finds a bottle, a shiny brass lamp, tasty food, and keys inside. </p>
                  <figure xml:id="figure09">
                     <head>Foundation of the Building Featured in <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>. Cave Research Foundation members in Mammoth Cave National Park,
								Kentucky visit the remnants of the small brick building featured in
								the opening of <title rend="quotes">Colossal Cave Adventure.</title>
								Dennis G. Jerz displays a water bottle, shiny brass lamp, and tasty
								food — items Crowther put there in the game. A fourth item — the key
								to the entrance gate -- is safely around the neck of party leader
								Dave West (seated in the background). <ref target="#crowther1976">(Room 2, <q>AT HILL IN ROAD</q>)</ref>
							                 
							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.
                     </head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_009.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of a scene in Mammoth Cave National Park</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <p>According to the <title rend="italic">Cave Research Foundation Personnel
							Manual</title>
						               <ptr target="#freeman1975"/>, the U.S. Park Service usually locks entrances
						to caves in Mammoth Cave National Park, and keys are issued to each small
						party of cavers <ptr target="#freeman1975" loc="33"/>. The other items found
						in the building also hold a special significance within caving culture. </p>
                  <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#jerz2005">In the chapter entitled <q>Caving
								Equipment,</q> the handbook [<title rend="italic">Cave Research
								Foundation Personnel Manual</title>] lists, among other items,
								<q>Food</q> (because cavers typically eat one
							or two meals on an expedition), a <q>Container for
								lamp water,</q> and <q>Metal carbide
							lamp.</q> Carbide is a substance that reacts with water to produce a
							flammable gas. Crowther supplied the game with a lamp, a bottle, and a
							source of water — but no carbide. Cave Research Foundation member Tom
							Brucker, who worked with the Crowthers on their intensive 1974 survey of
							Bedquilt, recalls that when he first played the game, he assumed the
							brass lantern would run out of carbide fuel, and assumed that winning
							the game would require finding a fresh supply….(It was Woods who
							supplied the <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> lamp with a timer
							that warns the player that the lantern's power is running out, and who
							also added an underground vending machine — the source of fresh
							batteries.) Other items that are not implemented as objects in the game,
							but whose presence is implied, include a pack and a compass. The CRF
							manual offers a thoughtful soliloquy on the ideal proportions and strap
							configuration for a cave pack (26), and a whole chapter explains the
							proper use of a compass during a map-making survey.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#jerz2005"/>
                  </cit>
                  <p>Obviously enough, cavers use a bottle as a source of drinking water. Less
						obvious: cavers also use a bottle to carry their own waste water out of the
						cave.</p>
                  <p>Difficulty in finding the cave entrance is often a significant part of a real
						visit to the Bedquilt region of Colossal Cave. According to a CRF trip
						report dated 30 Jun 1974, leader Richard Zopf and party members Pat and Will
						Crowther <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#brucker2005">had trouble following the road in and cut down the
								valley early to find the entrance which was cleverly hidden by mud.
								Pat and Will scratched their heads and the sand alternately, and
								soon our shovel scratched the gate, about 1.5 feet down. It is, as
								one faces the hill, directly opposite the higher hole and next to
								the left bank. We cleaned the gate and got the old lock to open. The
								lock should be replaced with a Park service lock next trip. The new
								lock should be well-oiled. We relocked the gate, ascended the hill,
								and followed the road all the way back. The ticks were minimal.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#brucker2005"/>
                     </cit>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the game, the player can reach the entrance simply by going south from the
						pumphouse. But among cavers, an unsuccessful excursion to the Bedquilt
						entrance is a common experience known as <q>The Bedquilt
							Rinky-Dink.</q>
					             </p>
                  <figure xml:id="figure10">
                     <head>Somewhere Nearby is Colossal Cave. <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">YOU ARE IN OPEN FOREST NEAR BOTH A VALLEY AND A
									ROAD. </quote>
                           <ptr loc="Room 6" target="#crowther1976"/>
                        </cit>
							                 <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">THE TREES OF THE FOREST ARE LARGE HARDWOOD OAK
									AND MAPLE, WITH AN OCCASIONAL GROVE OF PINE OR SPRUCE. THERE IS
									QUITE A BIT OF UNDERGROWTH, LARGELY BIRCH AND ASH SAPLINGS PLUS
									NONDESCRITPT BUSHES OF VARIOUS SORTS. THIS TIME OF YEAR
									VISIBILITY IS QUITE RESTRICTED BY ALL THE LEAVES, BUT TRAVEL IS
									QUITE EASY IF YOU DETOUR AROUND THE SPRUCE AND BERRY BUSHES.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Table 6, Item 64</ref>
                        </cit>
							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.
							                 The first CRF expedition to Colossal Cave in July of 2005 failed to
								locate the entrance. When asked, <q>What am I
									going to tell everyone when they ask me why we aren't just
									following the creek bed south from the pumphouse?</q>, party
								members said the creek bed was too overgrown for easy travel. The
								next day, CRF cartographer Dave West led a successful trip.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_010.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of forest scene with accompanying text from Adventure</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Bedquilt Entrance</head>
                  <figure xml:id="figure11">
                     <head>Colossal Cave Key. <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">YOU ARE IN A 20 FOOT DEPRESSION FLOORED WITH
									BARE DIRT. SET INTO THE DIRT IS A STRONG STEEL GRATE MOUNTED IN
									CONCRETE. A DRY STREAMBED LEADS INTO THE DEPRESSION.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Room 8, <q>YOU'RE
										OUTSIDE GRATE</q>
                           </ref>
                        </cit>

							                 The horizontal gate no longer exists. This key opens the new vertical
								gate, which has been set up several hundred feet inside the cave
								entrance.
							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_011.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of the author holding the cave key</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure12">
                     <head>Bedquilt Entrance, 1994. <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">YOU ARE IN A SMALL CHAMBER BENEATH A 3X3 STEEL
									GRATE TO THE SURFACE. A LOW CRAWL OVER COBBLES LEADS INWARD TO
									THE WEST.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Room 9, <q>YOU'RE
										BELOW THE GRATE</q>
                           </ref>
                        </cit>

							                 In 1994, cavers cleared out the remnants of the concrete structure
								and the steel grate <ptr target="#nss1994"/>. 
							                 Photo by Larry Matiz, 1994. Reproduced by permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_012.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of the entrance to the Bedquilt section of Colossal Cave</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <p>The old horizontal gate and the concrete structure in which it was set were
						removed in 1994, according to the National Speleological Society. <q>Friday the entire Field Camp crew went to the Bedquilt
							Entrance to remove the debris from that project. This consisted of the
							old gate, a steel monster that took four people to haul up the hill, the
							broken concrete from the former gate base and the tools used on the
							project. We formed a chain gang part of the way up the hill and passed
							the broken concrete from person to person…. The debris was loaded into a
							waiting trailer and removed from the area. </q>
					             </p>
                  <figure xml:id="figure13">
                     <head>Using the Bedquilt Entrance. In 2005, the Bedquilt entrance to Colossal Cave was a tight squeeze. 
							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_013.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of the author looking out from the Bedquilt entrance to
							Colossal Cave</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure14">
                     <head>Looking Out the Bedquilt Entrance to Colossal Cave. Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_014.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of the cave entrance looking out from within</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Cobble Crawl to Debris Room</head>
                  <figure xml:id="figure15">
                     <head>Low Crawl over Cobbles. <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">YOU ARE CRAWLING OVER COBBLES IN A LOW PASSAGE.
									THERE IS A DIM LIGHT AT THE EAST END OF THE PASSAGE.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Room 10, <q>YOU'RE IN
										COBBLE CRAWL.</q>
                           </ref>
                        </cit>

							                 This passage stretches northwest for hundreds of feet, often with
								less than a foot of clearance. It is possible to push the cobbles
								aside in order to make more headroom, so the real site is not quite
								as claustrophobic as the photo might appear. In the game, progress
								beyond this point is impossible without the lamp. 
							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_015.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of a low-ceilinged cave passage</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure16">
                     <head>
							                 <q>MAGIC WORD XYZZY</q>. <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">YOU ARE IN A DEBRIS ROOM, FILLED WITH STUFF
									WASHED IN FROM THE SURFACE…. A NOTE ON THE WALL SAYS <q>MAGIC WORD XYZZY</q>. </quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Room 11, <q>YOU'RE IN
										DEBRIS ROOM.</q>
                           </ref>
                        </cit>

							                 Cave Research Foundation members Lynn Brucker and Roger Brucker
								crouch beside the wall that many cavers believe Will Crowther was
								thinking of when he put the <q>XYZZY</q>
								message into <title rend="quotes">Adventure.</title>
							                 
							                 Photo by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced
								by permission.
						               </head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_016.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of two cavers in a cave room</figDesc>
                    
                  </figure>
                  <p>In a telephone interview, Crowther's sister Betty Bloom, who was one of the
						original play-testers of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>, shared an
						anecdote: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#bloom2002">I was bored having to go through all the steps
								every time, and I said, <q>I want to go directly into the game.</q>
									[<hi rend="italic">Dramatic pause</hi>.]
									<q>Ecks-why-zee-zee-why!</q>
                        </quote>
                        <ptr target="#bloom2002"/>
                     </cit>. Crowther confirmed this detail about the word, which teleports the
						player to and from the small building: <quote rend="inline" source="#bloom2002">Betty was
							correct that I created it for her - she is an impatient sort, and wanted
							a shortcut. I figured why not, there are lots of impatient people out
							there who would appreciate a shortcut</quote>
						               <ptr target="#bloom2002"/>. According to Bloom, <quote rend="inline" source="#crowther2007">XYZZY</quote> was a family password. <quote rend="inline" source="#crowther2007">If the kids ever
							got lost in an airport, and they ever had to verify who they were, we
							would just ask them for a magic word, and it would be XYZZY.</quote>
						While Crowther states that <quote rend="inline" source="#crowther2007">XYZZY was not a family
							password - I made it up out of whole cloth just for the game,</quote> we
						may imagine that <emph>other</emph> family members used it as a password,
							<emph>after</emph> Crowther invented it for the game. In telephone
						interviews, Bloom and Crowther's daughters all spelled out the letters in
						the word, but they report that Crowther himself pronounced it
						<q>zizzy.</q> According to Crowther
							(2007), <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#crowther2007">Magic words should look queer, and
							yet somehow be pronounceable - XYZZY seemed pretty good that way. I was
							considering working for XEROX at the time, which probably suggested
							starting with an X.</quote><ptr target="#crowther2007"/></cit> Asked about Hunsinger's observation that
						XYZZY is <quote rend="inline" source="#adams2007b">a mnemonic device to remember how to do cross
							products</quote>
						               <ptr target="#adams2007b"/>, Crowther replied, <quote rend="inline" source="#adams2007b">I've
							never heard that math mnemonic.</quote>
                  </p>
                  <figure xml:id="figure17">
                     <head>Silt-filled Canyon. <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">YOU ARE IN AN AWKWARD SLOPING EAST/WEST CANYON.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Room 12.</ref>
                        </cit>
							                 In caver terminology, a <q>canyon</q> is any passage that
								is taller than it is wide. This passage still slopes, but has silted
								up considerably since Crowther knew it. 
							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_017.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of the author in a silt-filled canyon</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure18">
                     <head>New Vertical Gate. <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">THE GRATE IS NOW UNLOCKED.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Table 6, Item 37</ref>
                        </cit>
							                 Instead of the horizontal 3x3 horizontal grate described in <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>, the Bedquilt entrance to
								Colossal Cave is now protected by a vertical gate, which in this
								photograph lies open on the ground (away from the camera). A spray
								can of oil is stored on a rock nearby. 
							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_018.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of the author looking out from behind a metal gate</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Bird Chamber to Hall of Mists</head>
                  <figure xml:id="figure19">
                     <head>Cave Formations. <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">YOU ARE IN A SPLENDID CHAMBER THIRTY FEET HIGH.
									THE WALLS ARE FROZEN RIVERS OF ORANGE STONE. AN AWKWARD CANYON
									AND A GOOD PASSAGE EXIT FROM EAST AND WEST SIDES OF THE CHAMBER.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Room 13, <q>YOU'RE IN
										BIRD CHAMBER.</q>
                           </ref>
                        </cit>

							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_019.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of the author in a high-ceilinged cave room hung with
							stalactites</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <p>While Woods retained the name <q>Bird Chamber,</q> many
						later versions of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> present this room
						as <q>Orange River Chamber.</q> No birds are likely to
						be found singing this deep in the cave, but the cave formations here do
						resemble a certain prop associated with the bird. </p>
                  <figure xml:id="figure20">
                     <head>Birdcage? <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">A CHEERFUL LITTLE BIRD IS SITTING HERE SINGING</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Table 5, Item 7</ref>
                        </cit>

							                 <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">THERE IS A SMALL WICKER CAGE DISCARDED NEARBY.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Table 5, Item 204</ref>
                        </cit>
							                 Could this formation in the <q>Bird Chamber</q>
								(where the player encounters a cheerful, and eventually helpful,
								bird) have given Will Crowther the idea to include a birdcage (which
								the player finds nearby in the Cobble Crawl)? 
							                 Photo by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced
								by permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_020.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of a caver standing next to a rock formation with a regular
							vertical pattern</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure21">
                     <head><cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">A THREE FOOT BLACK ROD WITH A RUSTY STAR ON AN
									END LIES NEARBY</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Table 5, Item 205</ref>
                        </cit>
							                 It is not quite three feet long, there is no sign of the star, and
								when this photo was taken it was in <q>Top of
									Small Pit</q> rather than the <q>Debris
									Room</q> where Crowther placed it. But there is a rusty rod
								in the real Colossal Cave. A star-less <q>THREE
									FOOT BLACK ROD WITH A RUSTY MARK ON AN END</q> was added by
								Woods. 
							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_021.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of the author pointing to an iron bar set in an alcove of the
							cave</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure22">
                     <head>Looking down from <q>Top of Small Pit</q>. <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">AT YOUR FEET IS A SMALL PIT BREATHING TRACES OF
									WHITE MIST. AN EAST PASSAGE ENDS HERE EXCEPT FOR A SMALL CRACK
									LEADING ON. </quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Room 14, <q>YOU'RE AT
										TOP OF SMALL PIT</q>
                           </ref>
                        </cit>

							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.
                     </head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_022.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo from above of two cavers descending into a vertical pit</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure23">
                     <head>In the <q>Hall of Mists,</q> looking up towards
								<q>Top of Small Pit.</q>  Coming down is much easier than going up. <ref target="#park1994">Park (1994)</ref> describes the passage as <quote rend="inline" source="#park1994">more difficult than just typing <q>up</q>
									or <q>down</q> at your computer terminal.
									At the top of it, you are stretched all the way out, pressing
									against the other wall with outstretched legs, while fervently
									searching for a place to put your butt or back in order to
									support your weight.</quote>
							                 
							                 Photo by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced
								by permission.
                     </head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_023.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo from below of cavers descending a vertical pit</figDesc>
                    
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure24">
                     <head>Hall of Mists. <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">YOU ARE AT ONE END OF A VAST HALL STRETCHING
									FORWARD OUT OF SIGHT TO THE WEST. THERE ARE OPENINGS TO EITHER
									SIDE. NEARBY, A WIDE STONE STAIRCASE LEADS DOWNWARD. THE HALL IS
									FILLED WITH WISPS OF WHITE MIST SWAYING TO AND FRO ALMOST AS IF
									ALIVE. A COLD WIND BLOWS UP THE STAIRCASE. THERE IS A PASSAGE AT
									THE TOP OF A DOME BEHIND YOU.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Room 15, <q>IN HALL
										OF MISTS</q>
                           </ref>
                        </cit>

							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission. </head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_024.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of a large cave room</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure25">
                  	<head><cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">YOU ARE ON THE EAST BANK OF A FISSURE SLICING
									CLEAR ACROSS THE HALL. THE MIST IS QUITE THICK HERE, AND THE
									FISSURE IS TOO WIDE TO JUMP.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Room 17, <q>ON EAST
										BANK OF FISSURE.</q>
                           </ref>
                        </cit>

							                 <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">A CRYSTAL BRIDGE NOW SPANS THE FISSURE.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Table 5, Item 112</ref>
                        </cit>
							                 Crowther invented a fissure which blocks the player's progress. The
								magical appearance of the crystal bridge is one of Crowther's
								departures from reality, and further evidence that his original
								version of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> was a game with
								fantasy elements, even before Don Woods expanded, polished, and
								re-released it. If these long stone slabs were not in the real cave,
								it would still be possible to traverse the hall by walking across
								rubble; but passage would be much slower. The magic crystal bridge
								likewise speeds the player’s progress through the game, even though
								it is possible to get to the other side of the hall without
								conjuring up the bridge.
							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission. </head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_025.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of the author seated on a large rock formation within a cave
							room</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure26">
                  	<head><cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">THIS IS A LOW ROOM WITH A CRUDE NOTE ON THE
									WALL. IT SAYS <q>YOU WON'T GET IT UP THE
									STEPS</q>.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Room 18, <q>YOU'RE IN
										NUGGET OF GOLD ROOM.</q>
                           </ref>
                        </cit>
							                 <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">THERE IS A LARGE SPARKLING NUGGET OF GOLD HERE!</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Table 5, Item 210</ref>
                        </cit>

							                 A thorough search of a small room south of the Hall of Mists yielded
								neither note nor nugget, but perhaps that was due to a sputtering
								headlamp. 
							                  Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced
								by permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_026.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of the author looking up out of an aperture</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure27">
                     <head>YOU HAVE NO SOURCE OF LIGHT. <ref target="#crowther1976">Table 6,
								Item 38</ref>. Battery-powered lights were cumbersome and inefficient in the 1970s.
								The brass lamps that were the favored light source contain water in
								the upper chamber, which drips slowly into a lower chamber filled
								with calcium carbide. The resulting chemical reaction produces
								acetylene gas, which burns with a very clean flame. 
							                 While some modern cavers prefer battery-powered LEDs, carbide lamps
								remain popular among traditionalists — in part because caves are
								chilly and the open flame is a convenient source of warmth.
								Aesthetically, the brass reflector makes the orange flame seem even
								warmer; but more important, the brass fixtures will not interfere
								with a delicate compass needle. 
							                 Photo by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced
								by permission.
                     </head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_027.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of a caver refilling a lamp from a small bottle</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure28">
                  	<head> There are in fact some old discarded batteries in the Hall of Mists.
								While modern cavers are expected to bring all of their own trash
								with them, these items are considered historical artifacts. 
							                 Woods added a timer to the headlamp, and a vending machine to
								dispense fresh batteries. While Crowther wrote his game at a time
								when carbide lanterns were more reliable than battery-powered
								lights, his original source code does include the command <q>RUB,</q> which yields the response <q>RUBBING THE ELECTRIC LAMP IS NOT PARTICULARLY
									REWARDING. ANYWAY, NOTHING EXCITING HAPPENS.</q> Thus, Woods
								was following Crowther's lead when he implemented the light source
								as electric. 
							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_028.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of rusted batteries on the cave floor, with a hand for scale</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure29">
                     <head>THERE IS A LITTLE AXE HERE (Table 5, Item 221). <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">A LITTLE DWARF JUST WALKED AROUND A CORNER, SAW
									YOU, THREW A LITTLE AXE AT YOU WHICH MISSED, CURSED, AND RAN
									AWAY.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Table 6, Item 3</ref>
                        </cit>
							                 A diminutive cave dweller examines an old axe head, located in the
								Hall of Mists.
							                 Photo by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced
								by permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_029.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of a rusted axe head resting on a rock formation, with a
							cricket at lower left</figDesc>
                    
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure30">
                     <head>Stopping for a leisurely lunch in the Hall of Mists. <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">THERE IS FOOD HERE.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Table 5, Item 221</ref>
                        </cit>

							                 The temperature in Colossal Cave is about 53 degrees, so a hot meal
								is welcome. Lynn Brucker has eaten a can of fruit, poured a
								microwaveable container of noodles into the fruit can, and is now
								heating the noodles over the flame of a tiny stove. Plastic baggies
								keep dirt away from napkins, utensils, and camera lenses. 
							                 Photo by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced
								by permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_030.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of a caver seated on the ground eating from a can</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure31">
                     <head>Wide Stone Staircase. <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">NEARBY, A WIDE STONE STAIRCASE LEADS DOWNWARD.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Room 15, <q>YOU'RE IN
										HALL OF MISTS</q>
                           </ref>
                        </cit>

							                 Caver terminology often employs architectural metaphors. For instance
								a <q>room</q> is any discrete space, no matter the shape;
								a <q>hall</q> is any long space, a
								<q>chimney</q> is a pit when seen from below, and a
									<q>dome</q> is the roof of a pit. There really is a
								wide staircase (pictured here) leading down from the Hall of Mists
								to the Hall of the Mountain King. There are also <q>ROUGH STONE STEPS</q> leading down from <q>At Top of Pit,</q> and they are now very rough
								indeed (see <ref target="#figure23">Figure 23</ref>). According to
								CRF members, the steps date from a time before the Park Service took
								over the site, when a private owner was developing it for tourism. 
							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_031.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of two cavers descending a wide stone staircase</figDesc>
                    
                  </figure>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>A Maze of Twisty Little Passages, All Alike</head>
                  <figure xml:id="figure32">
                     <head><cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">YOU ARE AT THE WEST END OF HALL OF MISTS. A LOW
									WIDE CRAWL CONTINUES WEST AND ANOTHER GOES NORTH. TO THE SOUTH
									IS A LITTLE PASSAGE 6 FEET OFF THE FLOOR.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Room 41, <q>YOU'RE AT
										WEST END OF HALL OF MISTS.</q>
                           </ref>
                        </cit>

							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_032.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo from below of two cavers ascending a passage</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure33">
                     <head><cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">YOU ARE IN A MAZE OF TWISTY LITTLE PASSAGES, ALL
									ALIKE.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Rooms 42, 43, 44, 45, 49, 50, 51, 52,
									53, and 55.</ref>
                        </cit>
							                 Party leader Dave West points out one of several potential ways to
								get lost in the location that inspired the most infamous of all game
								mazes. 
							                 Photo by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced
								by permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_033.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of a caver pointing into a large tunnel</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure34">
                     <head>Text Adventures in Colossal Cave.  Serious modern cavers frown on permanently defacing cave features
								with graffiti, but some cavers do document and learn from these
								testaments to the achievements of previous cavers. 
							                 Among the forms of annotation often spotted during this trip were
								painted survey dots (see the bright orange stripe, visible on a rock
								on the lower right of <ref target="#figure19">Figure 19</ref>),
								sooty marks made with burning lamp tips, and small cards bearing
								directional information (one is visible in <ref target="#figure21">Figure 21</ref>, near the base of the rod). 
							                 Photo by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced
								by permission. </head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_034.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of graffiti carved into the cave wall</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure35">
                     <head><cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">THE LITTLE BIRD IS NOW DEAD. ITS BODY
									DISAPPEARS.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Table 6, Item 45</ref>
                        </cit>
							                 A rock cairn marks the skeleton of a small visitor defeated by the
								maze of twisty little passages.
							                 Photo by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced
								by permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_035.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of a bird skeleton on the cave floor with inset detail</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>You're At Y2... A Hollow Voice Says <q>PLUGH</q>
                  </head>
                  <figure xml:id="figure36">
                     <head><cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">YOU ARE IN A LARGE ROOM, WITH A PASSAGE TO THE
									SOUTH, A PASSAGE TO THE WEST, AND A WALL OF BROKEN ROCK TO THE
									EAST. THERE IS A LARGE <q>Y2</q> ON A ROCK
									IN ROOMS CENTER.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Room 33, <q>YOU'RE AT
										Y2</q>
                           </ref>
                        </cit>

							                 <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">A HOLLOW VOICE SAYS <q>PLUGH</q>
								                   </quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Table 6, Item 8</ref>
                        </cit>

							                 In <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>, entering the command
									<q>PLUGH</q> from this location transports
								the player to the small building. <ref target="resources/audio/y2.mp3">Click here for
								audio</ref> <!-- <media mimeType="audio/mp3 url="resources/audio/y2.mpeg3"><desc>Audio file of the command "PLUGH"</desc></media> -->
                        
							                 <hi rend="bold">Jerz:</hi> <said>All right, well here I am underground with Dave West, Roger
								Brucker and Lynn Brucker at Y2. Dave, what would you say we're
								supposed to say at this point?</said>
							                 <hi rend="bold">West:</hi> <said>Well… I've tried many ways to pronounce it. Plug, ploog, ploof,
								pluh. And I'm still here.</said>
							                 <hi rend="bold">R. Brucker:</hi> <said><q>PLUGH!!</q></said>
                        
							                 <hi rend="bold">Jerz:</hi> <said>That didn't sound too hollow. It sounded… something. </said>

							                 Photos by Lynn Brucker and Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation
								2005. Reproduced by permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_036.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Two photos of cavers seated in a cave</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <p>Another of the commonly-repeated memes about Colossal Cave describes Y2 as
							<quote rend="inline" source="#adams2007a">a common notation on maps denoting a secondary
							entrance</quote>
						               <ptr target="#adams2007a"/>. CRF members say that it is merely a label given
						to a survey station, the second in a series of points along a survey route
						that happened to use the letter Y. A CRF trip report dated November 1974
						indicates that Crowther led a team that began the Y survey in the Bedquilt
						area of Colossal Cave <ptr target="#brucker2005"/>. While there are other
						entrances to Colossal Cave, there is no such entrance near <q>YOU'RE IN Y2.</q> While Y2 is the only survey code
						mentioned in the game, in the real cave, similar alphanumerical marks are
						often spotted (see <ref target="#figure25">Figure 25</ref>, on one of the
						slabs occupying the space where Crowther put the crystal bridge).</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>At Window on Pit</head>
                  <figure xml:id="figure37">
                     <head>A Caving Theorist Contemplates Applied Speleology. <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">…OTHERS HAVE FOUND FORTUNES IN TREASURE AND
									GOLD, THOUGH IT IS RUMORED THAT SOME WHO ENTER ARE NEVER SEEN
									AGAIN.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Table 6, Item 1</ref>
                        </cit>
							                 Photo by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced
								by permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_037.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of the author pointing into a dark cave passage</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>The party's computer game specialist must have seemed reasonably competent
						during his first attempt at applied caving. After bringing the party to the
						Y2 junction, leader Dave West pointed to a tiny opening five feet off the
						ground — about a foot high and two feet wide — and said, <q>Go that way.</q>
					             </p>
                  <p>It is one thing to squirm through a tight passage when one can always see
						several people ahead, silhouetted against the lighted walls. It is a much
						more stressful experience to plunge ahead towards the darkness that lurks,
						grue-like, beyond the flickering edges of sight. The roof of the narrow
						passage opened up before long, and then the bottom dropped away. The
						destination turned out to be what Crowther called Room 35, <q>Window on Pit</q> (see <ref target="#figure38">Figure
							38</ref>), <q>WHICH GOES UP AND DOWN OUT OF
						SIGHT.</q> (Figures <ref target="#figure39">39</ref>, <ref target="#figure40">40</ref>). Woods created a second room (#110) with
						the same name, and also created a shadowy figure who waves back at you from
						a lighted window on the other side of the pit. While the bottom of the pit
						is only implied in Crowther's game, Woods implemented it as follows: <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1977">SUSPENDED FROM SOME UNSEEN POINT FAR ABOVE YOU, AN ENORMOUS
							TWO-SIDED MIRROR IS HANGING PARALLEL TO AND MIDWAY BETWEEN THE CANYON
							WALLS. (THE MIRROR IS OBVIOUSLY PROVIDED FOR THE USE OF THE DWARVES, WHO
							AS YOU KNOW, ARE EXTREMELY VAIN.) A SMALL WINDOW CAN BE SEEN IN EITHER
							WALL, SOME FIFTY FEET UP.</quote>
						               <ref target="#crowther1977">(Woods's Room 109, <q>YOU'RE
								IN MIRROR CANYON.</q>)</ref> This riff on Crowther's original
						geography, and the off-beat approach to the setting, is a typical example of
						Woods's tendency to introduce a comic tension within the spirit of
						Crowther's original.</p>
                  <figure xml:id="figure38">
                     <head>
							                 <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">YOU ARE AT A WINDOW ON A HUGE PIT, WHICH GOES UP
									AND DOWN OUT OF SIGHT. A FLOOR IS INDISTINCTLY VISIBLE OVER 50
									FEET BELOW. DIRECTLY OPPOSITE YOU AND 25 FEET AWAY THERE IS A
									SIMILAR WINDOW.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Room 35, <q>YOU'RE AT
										WINDOW ON PIT</q>
                           </ref>
                        </cit>

							                 In caving terminology, a horizontal passage makes a
								<q>window</q> when it intersects with a larger vertical
								shaft. 
							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.
						               </head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_038.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of the author crouching next to the entrance to a cave
							passage</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure39">
                     <head>Composite photo showing the view across pit. A composite view of the <q>window</q> across the shaft, as
								seen from the vantage point of the window in <ref target="#figure38">Figure 38</ref>. <ref target="#crowther1976">(Room 35, <q>YOU'RE AT WINDOW ON PIT</q>.)</ref>
							                 
							                 Photo by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced
								by permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_039.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo looking across a large cave shaft, showing a tall vertical
							rock face with a tunnel entrance near the top</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure40">
                     <head>Looking down from <q>Window on Pit</q>.  A ledge visible in the upper right of this image is the same ledge
								seen in the bottom center of <ref target="#figure39">Figure
								39</ref>. 
							                 Photo by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced
								by permission. 
                     </head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_040.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo showing the view from the tunnel entrance looking down into
							the cave shaft of the previous image</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>At Brink of Climbable Pit</head>
                  <figure xml:id="figure41">
                     <head>Mist at the Brink of Climbable Pit. 
                           <cit><quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">YOU ARE ON THE BRINK OF A SMALL CLEAN CLIMBABLE
									PIT. A CRAWL LEADS WEST.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Room 37</ref></cit>
                        

							                 <cit>
                           <quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">MIST IS A WHITE VAPOR, USUALLY WATER, SEEN FROM
									TIME TO TIME IN CAVERNS. IT CAN BE FOUND ANYWHERE BUT IS
									FREQUENTLY A SIGN OF A DEEP PIT LEADING DOWN TO WATER.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Table 6, Item 69</ref>
                        </cit>

							                 Photo by Lynn Brucker, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced by
								permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_041.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of cavers descending into a cave pit</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="figure42">
                     <head>Telling stories at Brink of Climbable Pit before the return trip. 
                           <cit><quote rend="block" source="#crowther1976">SORRY, BUT I AM NOT ALLOWED TO GIVE MORE DETAIL.
									I WILL REPEAT THE LONG DESCRIPTION OF YOUR LOCATION.</quote>
                           <ref target="#crowther1976">Table 6, Item 15</ref></cit>.
                        

							                 Photo by Dennis G. Jerz, © Cave Research Foundation 2005. Reproduced
								by permission.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jerz2007_042.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>Photo of a group of cavers seated in a cave</figDesc>
                     
                  </figure>
                  <p>Cavers have a wry sense of humor and an easy communal nature. While mountain
						climbers who pause to rest before making the return trip can focus on the
						view, the CRF members faced each other and swapped stories at <q>AT BRINK OF CLIMBABLE PIT.</q> When it was time to go,
						West turned to the newest member of the party — a caving theorist who often
						has trouble finding his car in the faculty parking lot — and said, <q>You're
							going to lead us out.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And he was serious.<note>
							                 <cit>
                           <quote rend="inline" source="#jerz2005">Before long, team leader Dave West hesitated at
									a junction. <q>You’ll notice I’m not following you anymore</q>,
									he said, prompting Jerz to backtrack and choose another route.
									After a few more similar false starts, Jerz finally realized
									that the proper direction from that junction was <emph>straight
										up</emph>…</quote>
                           <ptr target="#jerz2005"/>
                        </cit>
						               </note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Cavers Reflect on <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>
               </head>
               <p>Crowther's ex-wife Patricia Wilcox did not play or even know about the original
					version of the game. She recalls a CRF meeting in <quote rend="inline" source="#wilcox2002">1976 or
						77</quote> in which many members who had ostensibly come to Boston for a
					weekend of mapping instead spent hours playing the Crowther/Woods <title rend="quotes">Adventure.</title> She described the geography of the game as
						<quote rend="inline" source="#wilcox2002">Completely different from the real cave. It used names
						that we made up,</quote> though her assessment is likely influenced by the
					sections added by Woods. According to <ref target="#crowther2001">Crowther
						(2001)</ref>, <quote rend="inline" source="#crowther2001">the geometry [of the game] was lifted
						directly from Bedquilt Cave.</quote>
               </p>
               <p>Other cavers have reported that the geography of the game closely matches the
					geography of the cave. For example, <ref target="#park1994">Park (1994)</ref>
					reports that an <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> fan and novice caver, Bev
					Schwartz, knew the game so well that, on her first trip into the real cave,
						<quote rend="inline" source="#park1994">We would be at a junction and she would ask compass
						directions and then begin to tell us what was down this passage or the other
						– all correctly!</quote> Park also offers an anecdote of a party's encounter
					with a real snake while climbing up into the Bird Chamber (see Figures <ref target="#figure21">21</ref>, <ref target="#figure22">22</ref>, <ref target="#figure23">23</ref>): <q>[O]ne party member, Roger,
						noticed to his horror a copperhead snake (was it THE SNAKE?) on the ledge
						next to his right hand…. Confronted by the snake, Roger was so beside
						himself that all he could do was yell <q>Strike, strike</q> as the
						copperhead proceeded to do just that. Tom, the party leader, had already
						made the climb up (and not seen the snake). Looking around for something to
						do, he found a stick (was it the MAGIC WAND?), in the Bird Chamber (the room
						with the rivers of orange stone, actually a beautiful column of orange
						travertine). Wand in hand, he moved the snake away.</q>
				           </p>
               <p>Park's references to a snake and rod illustrate the general opinion among cavers
					that Crowther's cave and game are very closely connected. Nevertheless, Crowther
					did make certain deliberate changes when he created the game. For instance, he
					invented the fissure that blocks the player's progress at the Hall of Mists. Tom
					Brucker, who caved with the Crowthers while they were mapping the site, reports
					that in order to create the crystal bridge puzzle,<note>It is possible to get to
						the other side of the fissure without conjuring up the crystal bridge, but
						the presence of the bridge, like the uttering of the magic words, permits
						the player to navigate more efficiently.</note> Crowther edited out a
					passage that would have enabled an easy bypass.</p>
               <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#brucker2005a">Will never liked that passage, even though it loops back to
						the Hall of the Mountain King.….Will based the game on what we purposely
						called <q>The Bad map of Bedquilt</q> … a very quick,
						[albeit] elegant, map that challenged us during the Bedquilt project to fill
						in the missing parts. There were plenty of parts missing.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#brucker2005a"/>
               </cit>
               <p> When asked what elements of Crowther's personality he finds in the game, Brucker
					stated that Crowther is the sort of person who would say, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#brucker2005a">You want to see how clever I am? I took your 300 lines
							of code, and I reduced it by 47%. He didn’t set out to <emph>be</emph>
							clever. [He would say] Let’s set out to make some puzzle and see if
							someone can solve it. It really reflects his nature…. I think he’s that
							little dwarf, throwing the axe at you. He won’t leave you alone. Whoosh!
							Come on. Figure it out!</quote>
                     <ptr target="#brucker2005a"/>
                  </cit>
				           </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="section04">
            <head>Adjusting the <title rend="italic">Adventure</title> Timeline</head>
            <p>Numerous timelines of computer and gaming history and multiple sources report that
				Crowther's original game was abandoned as early as 1972, and that Woods released his
				updated version in 1976. Both dates are incorrect. </p>
            <p>The false date of 1972 has attracted many compilers of timelines and internet
				histories, possibly because it is the date the former Patricia Crowther traversed a
				tight passage between two networks of caves previously thought to have been
				unconnected — an event that marks the climax of Brucker and Watson's <title rend="italic">The Longest Cave</title> (1976). Interviews with Crowther and his
				family members (sister, two children, and ex-wife) all confirm that the game was
				created shortly after the divorce, which they all say happened in mid-1975 <ptr target="#crowther2001"/>; <ptr target="#bloom2002"/>; <ptr target="#carter2002"/>; <ptr target="#lawrence2002"/>; <ptr target="#wilcox2002"/>. Betty Bloom,
				Crowther's sister, recalls spending her sabbatical with Crowther during the time he
				created the game, and was a regular playtester. According to Bloom's records, that
				sabbatical took place during the academic year of 75-76. In separate telephone
				interviews, Crowther's children Sandy (born in 1967) and Laura (born in 1970) recall
				being eight and <q>less than six,</q> respectively, when they
				first played the game, during a school vacation when they were staying with their
				father. <ref target="#crowther2001">Crowther (2001)</ref> recalls creating <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> over a period of several weekends; likewise, his
				daughters recall watching the game develop across a span of several different school
				vacations. None of the family members remembers which school vacations were
				involved. Bloom and Sandy both indicate Laura had already turned six, which would
				place the creation of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> after Laura's sixth
				birthday (in January of 1976). According to Laura: <quote rend="inline" source="#carter2002">I think 1972
					is early -- I would have been two.</quote>
			         </p>
            <p>When asked what her father thought of Woods's expansion, Laura (who became a
				middle-school science teacher) said, <quote rend="inline" source="#carter2002">I remember being extremely
					irritated by things like the pirate, and Dad saying not to blame
					<emph>him</emph>, it wasn't his fault!</quote> Sandy (who became a Sun Solaris
				administrator) has vivid memories of being <quote rend="inline" source="#lawrence2002">addicted</quote> to
				playing the Crowther/Woods version when she was older; as a child, she remembers
				mostly being frustrated by her father’s version. When asked about her father's
				reaction to Woods's expansions, she recalled: <quote rend="inline" source="#lawrence2002">I got stuck with,
						<q>Kill dragon.</q>
					             <q>What with, your bare hands?</q> You have to say, <q>yes.</q> I remember my father saying, <q>That was Don Woods.</q>
               </quote>
			         </p>
            <p>All Crowther family testimony is consistent with the 1975-76 date range. Responding
				to a direct request via e-mail, <ref target="#crowther2001">Crowther (2001)</ref>
				dated his original <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> to 1975, <quote rend="inline" source="#crowther2007">give or take a year.</quote> Certainly Crowther had stopped
				working on the game by the time Woods contacted him (by sending an e-mail to <q>crowther</q> at every domain name in existence at the time).
				Woods, in early interviews, gave March or April of 1976 as the date he released his
				expansion; but after examining backup files from his Stanford student account, he
				now says <ref target="#crowther2007">(2007)</ref> his estimate was off by a year,
				because the oldest relevant files in Woods’s student account (likely representing
				when Woods started on the code, not when Crowther stopped) bear the date March 11,
				1977. Gilbert (one of Woods's Stanford classmates) had written <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#gilbert2005">I'm pretty certain it was between October and December 1975
						when Don and I first ran across it</quote>
                  <ptr target="#gilbert2005"/>
               </cit>, which supports Laura’s memory of being <quote rend="inline" source="#carter2002">less than
				six</quote> and thus makes a plausible case for 1975; nevertheless, when informed
				that Woods now uses the 1977 figure, Gilbert also suggested that 1975 may be <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#gilbert2007">off by a year</quote>
                  <ptr target="#gilbert2007"/>
               </cit>. The most likely timeline places Crowther ceasing work on his original game
				in early 1976. </p>
            <p>This new timeline results in an even faster trajectory for key events in the advance
				of the new genre. Crowther's memory <ptr target="#hafner1994"/> of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> having gained a following a month after he put
				the program on his BBN account and left for a vacation is supported by the fact that
				one of these early fans brought it to a Stanford computer, where Woods encountered
				it. Some time before March 11, 1977, Woods contacted Crowther, who gave him access
				to the source code. By March 23, we see in Woods’s records a version with some 20
				additional lines of code — a low-level subroutine that Woods supplied in order to
				get the source to compile. The March 31 set of files again show only minor tweaks.
				The evidence demonstrates Woods was working on Crowther's source code during March,
				but during that month we see no evidence of Woods's creative expansions.</p>
            <p>Woods must have been very busy during April. By mid-May, hackers at MIT had noticed
				the game. After they solved it, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#anderson1985">the true lunatics began to think about how they could do it
						better</quote>
                  <ptr target="#anderson1985"/>
               </cit>, and by June, <title rend="quotes">Zork</title> had already taken
				recognizable form. When one considers that this pioneering work on text adventure
				games was happening during a time span which includes the May 25 release of <title rend="italic">Star Wars</title> and the June 5 sale of the first Apple
				computers, it is not likely that any other similar time span has encompassed so many
				seminal events in geek culture. </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="section05">
            <head>Conclusions</head>
            <p>The research expedition to the real Colossal Cave in Mammoth Cave National Park
				confirms that the map of Will Crowther's original <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> closely follows the geography of the real cave, but with fantasy
				and puzzle elements. The original source code shows that Crowther selectively
				deviated from realism; the tension between the altered geography and the mostly
				naturalistic text illustrates Crowther’s respectful intimacy with the natural
				wonders of Colossal Cave. Woods added complexity and polish, with a careful eye for
				improving the user’s experience (and, occasionally, proofreading). His contributions
				more than doubled the size of the original data file (from 728 lines to 1809) and
				more than quadrupled the size of the code file (from 709 lines to 2949). When
				expanding the geography, Woods improvised freely, yet his additions form an
				agreeable tension with Crowther’s naturalistic setting.</p>
            <p>Relevant details from caving culture which offer insights into <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> include artifacts in the real <title rend="quotes">Colossal
					Cave,</title> such as an axe head and a rusty iron rod; human alterations to the
				natural cave, such as carved stone steps and a locked iron gate; natural geographic
				features, such as the striking formations of orange rock and the huge stone slabs
				occupying the space where a magical bridge appears in the game; and newly-assembled
				evidence of Crowther's activities in Colossal Cave, including Cave Research
				Foundation maps and trip reports. This evidence demonstrates the extent to which
				Crowther's familiarity with the real cave provided inspiration for a genre-defining
				new form of artistic expression. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>This article was made possible in its present form by a travel grant from Seton Hill
				University; as well as the cooperation of the Cave Research Foundation (most notably
				the Brucker family); the professionalism of the Digital Humanities Quarterly
				editorial staff; the willingness of many, many correspondents who scrounged through
				their filing cabinets, attics, and memories for forgotten treasures; and the bemused
				consent of my wife. Particular thanks are due to the cooperation of Will Crowther,
				his family and associates; and to Don Woods, who offered gracious notes on an
				advanced draft. Mistakes or omissions are my own. — DGJ</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="aarseth1997" label="Aarseth 1997" key="aarseth1997">
			            <author>Aarseth, Espen J.</author>
			            <title rend="italic">Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic Literature</title>.
				<pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>: <publisher>Johns Hopkins UP</publisher>,
				<date>1997</date></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="aarseth2001" label="Aarseth 2001" key="aarseth2001">
			            <author>Aarseth, E.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Game Studies, Year One</title>, <title rend="italic">Game Studies
				1.1</title> (<date>2001</date>). <ref target="http://www.gamestudies.org/0101/editorial.html">http://www.gamestudies.org/0101/editorial.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="adams2007c" label="Adams 2007c" key="adams2007c">
			            <author>Adams, R.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">A History of <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>
               </title>, <title rend="italic">The Colossal Cave Adventure Page (2001-2007)</title>. <ref target="http://www.rickadams.org/adventure/a_history.html">http://www.rickadams.org/adventure/a_history.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="adams2007a" label="Adams 2007a" key="adams2007a">
			            <author>Adams, R.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Magic word <q>XYZZY</q>
               </title>, <title rend="italic">The Colossal Cave Adventure Page (2001-2007)</title>. <ref target="http://www.rickadams.org/adventure/c_xyzzy.html">http://www.rickadams.org/adventure/c_xyzzy.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="adams2007b" label="Adams 2007b" key="adams2007b">
			            <author>Adams, R.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">The Real Colossal Cave</title>, <title rend="italic">The Colossal
				Cave Adventure Page (2001-2007)</title>. <ref target="http://www.rickadams.org/adventure/b_cave.html">http://www.rickadams.org/adventure/b_cave.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="anderson1985" label="Anderson 1985" key="anderson1985">
			            <author>Anderson, T.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">The History of Zork [Part 1].</title>
			            <title rend="italic">New Zork Times [Infocom newsletter]</title>
			            4.1. (<date>1985</date>). <ref target="http://www.ifarchive.org/if-archive/infocom/nzt+tsl/nzt41.pdf">http://www.ifarchive.org/if-archive/infocom/NZT+TSL/NZT41.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="anderson1990" label="Anderson and Holmqvist 1990" key="anderson1990">
			            <author>Anderson, Peter Bogh</author> and <author>Holmqvist, Berit</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Interactive Fiction: Artificial Intelligence as a Mode of Sign
				Production</title>, <title rend="italic">AI and Society</title>, 4:
				291-313.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="au2000" label="Au 2000" key="au2000">
			            <author>Au, Wagner James</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Will you tell me a story — please?</title>, <title rend="italic">Salon</title>, <date>16 May 2000</date>. <ref target="http://www.salon.com/tech/log/2000/05/16/e3/">http://www.salon.com/tech/log/2000/05/16/e3/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="au2002" label="Au 2002" key="au2002">
			            <author>Au, Wagner James</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Triumph of the Mod</title>, <title rend="italic">Salon</title>,
				<date>16 Apr 2002</date>. <ref target="http://www.salon.com/tech/feature/2002/04/16/modding">http://www.salon.com/tech/feature/2002/04/16/modding</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bennahum1998" label="Bennahum 1998" key="bennahum1998">
			            <author>Bennahum, D.</author>
			            <title rend="italic">Extra Life: The Coming of Age in Cyberspace</title>. <pubPlace>New
				York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Basic Books</publisher>, <date>1998</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bloom2002" label="Bloom 2002" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Bloom, B.</author> Telephone interview, <date>01 July 2002</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="briceno2000" label="Briceno et al. 2000" key="briceno2000">
			            <author>Briceno, H.</author>, <author>Chao, W.</author>, <author>Glenn, A.</author>,
				<author>Hu, S.</author>, <author>Krishnamurthy, A.</author>, and <author>Tsuchida,
				B.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Down from the Top of Its Game: The Story of Infocom, Inc.</title>
			[undergraduate class project, <title rend="quotes">6.933J/STS.420J: The Structure of
				Engineering Revolutions</title>], MIT, <date>December 2000</date>. <ref target="http://web.mit.edu/6.933/www/fall2000/infocom/infocom-paper.pdf">http://web.mit.edu/6.933/www/Fall2000/infocom/infocom-paper.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brucker2005" label="Brucker, L. 2005" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Brucker, L.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Work in Colossal with Will Crowther's time (1974 - 1975)</title>.
			Excerpts from Cave Research Foundation trip report database. E-mail to the author,
				<date>03 Apr 2005</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brucker1976" label="Brucker and Watson 1976" key="brucker1976">
			            <author>Brucker, Roger W.</author> and <author>Richard A. Watson</author>. <title rend="italic">The Longest Cave</title>. <pubPlace>Carbondale</pubPlace>:
				<publisher>Southern Illinois UP</publisher>, <date>1976</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brucker2005a" label="Brucker, T. 2005a" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Brucker, T.</author> E-mail to the author <date>04 Apr 2005</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brucker2005b" label="Brucker, T. 2005b" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Brucker, T.</author> Personal interview, CRF Hamilton Valley Facility, Kentucky,
				<date>08 July, 2005</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="buckles1985" label="Buckles 1985" key="buckles1985">
			            <author>Buckles, M. A.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Interactive Fiction: The Computer Storygame <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>
               </title>. Ph.D. Thesis. U. Cal at San Diego,
			<date>1985</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cadre2004" label="Cadre 2004?" key="cadre2004">
			            <author>Cadre, A.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Interactive Fiction.</title> adamcadre.ac [personal website],
				<date>c2004</date>. <ref target="http://adamcadre.ac/if.html">http://adamcadre.ac/if.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cahill2001" label="Cahill 2001" key="cahill2001">
			            <author>Cahill, T.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">A Rudiment for Cavers.</title> In <author>Taylor, R.</author>,
				<title rend="italic">Caves: Exploring Hidden Realms</title>. <pubPlace>Washington,
				D.C.</pubPlace>: <publisher>National Geographic</publisher>, <date>2001</date>:
				187. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="carter2002" label="Carter 2002" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Carter, L.</author> Telephone interview, <date>01 July 2002</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chaplin2007" label="Chaplin 2007" key="chaplin2007">
			            <author>Chaplin, H.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Is That Just Some Game? No, It’s a Cultural Artifact</title>,
				<title rend="italic">New York Times</title>, <date>21 Mar 2007</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cordella2001" label="Cordella 2001" key="cordella2001">
			
			            <author>Cordella, F.</author>
			            <author>Cordella, Francesco</author>. <title rend="quotes">Interactive Fiction? I prefer
					<title rend="none">Adventure</title>
               </title>, in <title>L'avventura è
				l'avventura</title>, <date>2001</date>. <ref target="http://www.avventuretestuali.com/interviste/woods-eng/">http://www.avventuretestuali.com/interviste/woods-eng/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="costikyan2007" label="Costikyan 2007" key="costikyan2007">
			            <author>Costikyan, G.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Games, Storytelling and Breaking the String.</title> In Harrington,
			P. and Wardruip-Fruin, N. (eds.), <title rend="italic">Second Person: Role-Playing and
				Story in Games and Playable Media</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>:
				<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>, <date>2007</date>, 5-13.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crowther1976" label="Crowther 1976" key="crowther1975a">
			            <author>Crowther, W.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title> [aka <title rend="quotes">ADVENT</title> and
				<title rend="quotes">Colossal Cave</title>; FORTRAN source code],
			<date>c1975-76</date>. <ref target="http://www.icynic.com/~don/jerz/">http://www.icynic.com/~don/jerz/</ref> and <ref target="http://jerz.setonhill.edu/if/crowther/">http://jerz.setonhill.edu/if/crowther/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crowther2001" label="Crowther 2001" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Crowther, W.</author> E-mail to the author, <date>15 Jun 2001</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crowther2007" label="Crowther 2007" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Crowther, W.</author> E-mail to the author, <date>26 March 2007</date>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crowther1975" label="Crowther and Crowther 1975" key="crowther1975b">
			            <author>Crowther, W.</author> and <author>Crowther, P</author>. <title rend="quotes">Flint Mammoth Cave System: Bedquilt Section, Colossal Cave.</title> Survey map.
				<publisher>Cave Research Foundation</publisher>, <date>1975</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crowther1977" label="Crowther and Woods 1977" key="crowther1977">
			            <author>Crowther, W.</author> and <author>Woods, D.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>. [aka <title rend="quotes">ADVENT</title> and
				<title rend="quotes">Colossal Cave</title>] FORTRAN source code. <date>1977</date>.
			Accessed 01 Jun 2007. <ref target="http://mirror.ifarchive.org/if-archive/games/source/adv350-pdp10.tar.gz">http://mirror.ifarchive.org/if-archive/games/source/adv350-pdp10.tar.gz</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dalenberg2004" label="Dalenberg 2004" key="dalenberg2004">
			            <author>Dalenberg, R.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">
                  <title rend="none">Adventure</title> Family Tree</title>, Russel
			Dalenberg’s Home Page [personal web site], <date>2004</date>. <ref target="http://www.io.com/~ged/www/family.html">http://www.io.com/~ged/www/family.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dalenberg2006" label="Dalenberg 2006" key="dalenberg2006">
			            <author>Dalenberg, R.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Versions and Ports of <title rend="none">Adventure</title> known to
				exist</title> v.2.6.7 Russel Dalenberg’s Home Page [personal web site],
			<date>2006</date>. <ref target="http://www.io.com/~ged/www/advelist.html">http://www.io.com/~ged/www/advelist.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dibbell2002" label="Dibbell 2002" key="dibbell2002">
			            <author>Dibbell, J.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">A Marketable Wonder: Spelunking the American Imagination</title>,
				<title rend="italic">Topic Magazine</title>, 2. <ref target="http://www.webdelsol.com/topic/articles/02/dibbell.html">http://www.webdelsol.com/Topic/articles/02/dibbell.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="douglass2006" label="Douglass 2006" key="douglass2006">
			            <author>Douglass, J.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">IF is History! Interactive Fiction in the News</title> Weblog
			entry. WRT: Writer Response Theory, <date>18 Jan 2006</date>. <ref target="http://writerresponsetheory.org/wordpress/2006/01/18/if-is-history/">http://writerresponsetheory.org/wordpress/2006/01/18/if-is-history/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="douglass2007" label="Douglass 2007" key="douglass2007">
			            <author>Douglass, J.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Enlightening Interactive Fiction: Andrew Plotkin's Shade.</title>
			In Harrington, P. and Wardruip-Fruin, N. (eds.), <title rend="italic">Second Person:
				Role-Playing and Story in Games and Playable Media</title>.
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>, <date>2007</date>,
				129-136.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eskelinen2001" label="Eskelinen 2001" key="eskelinen2001">
			            <author>Eskelinen, M.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">The Gaming Situation</title>, <title rend="italic">Game
			Studies</title>, 1:1 (<date>2001</date>). <ref target="http://www.gamestudies.org/0101/eskelinen/">http://www.gamestudies.org/0101/eskelinen/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="freeman1975" label="Freeman 1975" key="freeman1975">
			            <editor>Freeman, J.</editor>
			            <title rend="italic">CRF Personnel Manual: Central Kentucky Karst Area</title>, 2nd
			edition. <pubPlace>Columbus, Ohio</pubPlace>: <publisher>Cave Research
			Foundation</publisher>, <date>1975</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gamespy2002" label="Gamespy 2002" key="gamespy2002">
			            <title>GameSpy's 30 Most Influential People in Gaming #24: Will Crowther and Don
			Woods</title>. <title>GameSpy.com</title>. <ref target="http://archive.gamespy.com/articles/march02/top30/2419/index.shtm">http://archive.gamespy.com/articles/march02/top30/2419/index.shtm</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gilbert2005" label="Gilbert 2005" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Gilbert, J.</author> E-mail to the author, <date>13 Apr 2005</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gilbert2007" label="Gilbert 2007" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Gilbert, J.</author> E-mail to the author, <date>08 Jun 2007</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gillogly1977" label="Gillogly 1977" key="gillogly1977"> Gillogly, J. (translator). <title rend="quotes">Adventure</title>. <date>1977</date>. C translation of <ref target="#crowther1977">Crowther and Woods 1977</ref>. Additional modifications
				(<date>1991-95</date>) © <publisher>The Regents of the University of
				California</publisher>. <ref target="http://www.ifarchive.org/ifarchive/games/source/adv350jg.zip">http://www.ifarchive.org/ifarchive/games/source/adv350jg.zip</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hafner1994" label="Hafner 1994" key="hafner1994">
			            <author>Hafner, K.</author> (compiler). <title rend="quotes">Will Crowther</title>,
				<title rend="italic">The Internet Archive</title>. <date>1994</date>. <ref target="http://www.archive.org/details/willcrowtherinterview">http://www.archive.org/details/WillCrowtherInterview</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hafner1996" label="Hafner and Lyon 1996" key="hafner1996">
			            <author>Hafner, K.</author> and <author>Lyon, M.</author>
			            <title rend="italic">When Wizards Stay Up Late: the Origins of the Internet</title>.
				<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Simon and Schuster</publisher>,
			<date>1996</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="harrington2007" label="Harrington and Wardruip-Fruin 2007" key="harrington2007"> Harrington, P.
			and Wardruip-Fruin, N. (eds.), <title rend="italic">Second Person: Role-Playing and
				Story in Games and Playable Media</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>:
				<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>, <date>2007</date>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="herz1997" label="Herz 1997" key="herz1997">
			            <author>Herz, J. C.</author>
			            <title rend="italic">Joystick Nation: How Computer Games Ate Our Quarters, Won Our
				Hearts and Rewired Our Minds</title>. <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>:
			<publisher>Little</publisher>, Brown, <date>1997</date>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="howell1990" label="Howell and Douglas 1990" key="howell1990">
			            <author>Howell, G.</author> and <author>Douglas, J. Y.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">The Evolution of Interactive Fiction</title>, <title rend="italic">Computer Assisted Learning: An International Journal</title>, 2:
				93-109.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hutcheon1988" label="Hutcheon 1988" key="hutcheon1988">
			            <author>Hutcheon, L.</author>
			            <title rend="italic">A Poetics of Postmodernism</title>. <pubPlace>New York and
			London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Routledge</publisher>, <date>1988</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jerz2000" label="Jerz 2000" key="jerz2000a">
			            <author>Jerz, D</author>. <title rend="quotes">Colossal Cave Adventure (c. 1976)</title>
			[instructional website]. <date>2000</date>. <ref target="http://jerz.setonhill.edu/if/canon/adventure.htm">http://jerz.setonhill.edu/if/canon/Adventure.htm</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jerz2002" label="Jerz 2002" key="jerz2002">
			            <author>Jerz, D.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">An Annotated Bibliography of Interactive Fiction
			Scholarship</title>, <title rend="italic">Text Technology</title>
			            11.2: 97-172. <ref target="http://jerz.setonhill.edu/if/bibliography/">http://jerz.setonhill.edu/if/bibliography/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jerz2005" label="Jerz and Thomas 2005" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Jerz, D.</author> and <author>Thomas, D</author>. <title rend="quotes">Cave Gave
				Game: The Subterranean as Game</title>. <date>2005</date>. Unpublished.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="juul2001" label="Juul 2001" key="juul2001">
			            <author>Juul, J.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Games Telling Stories?</title>, <title rend="italic">Game Studies</title>
			            1:1 (<date>2001</date>). <ref target="http://www.gamestudies.org/0101/juul-gts/">http://www.gamestudies.org/0101/juul-gts/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="juul2005" label="Juul 2005" key="juul2005">
			            <author>Juul, J.</author>
			            <title rend="italic">Half-Real: Video Games between Real Rules and Fictional Worlds.</title>
			            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>, <date>2005</date>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="keller2007" label="Keller 2007" key="keller2007">
			            <author>Keller, D.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Gaming, Identity and Literacy.</title> In Selfe, C. and Hawisher,
			G. (eds.). <title rend="italic">Gaming Lives in the Twenty-first Century</title>.
				<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher>,
			<date>2007</date>, 71-87.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kidder1981" label="Kidder 1981" key="kidder1981">
			            <author>Kidder, T.</author>
			            <title rend="italic">The Soul of a New Machine</title>. <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>:
				<publisher>Little Brown</publisher>, <date>1981</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kraley2004" label="Kraley 2004" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Kraley, M</author>. E-mail to the author, <date>27 Feb 2004</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="knuth1998" label="Knuth 1998" key="knuth1998">
			            <author>Knuth, D.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Adventure.</title>
			            <title rend="italic">CWEB Tutorial</title>. <date>1998</date>. <ref target="http://www.literateprogramming.com/adventure.pdf">http://www.literateprogramming.com/adventure.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lawrence2002" label="Lawrence 2002" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Lawrence, S</author>. Telephone interview, <date>01 July 2002</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="levy1984" label="Levy 1984" key="levy1984">
			            <author>Levy, S.</author>
			            <title rend="italic">Hackers: Heroes of the Computer Revolution.</title>
			            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Anchor Press</publisher>, <date>1984</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mann2003" label="Mann 2003" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Mann, W.</author> E-mail to the author, <date>30 Jul 2003</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mann2004" label="Mann 2004" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Mann, W.</author> E-mail to the author, <date>27 Feb 2004</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcgonigal2008" label="McGonigal 2008" key="mcgonigal2008">
			            <author>McGonigal, J.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Why I Love Bees: A Case Study in Collective Intelligence
			Gaming</title>, preprint of article forthcoming in Salen, K. (ed), <title rend="italic">Ecologies of Play</title>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="montfort2003" label="Montfort 2003" key="montfort2003">
			            <author>Montfort, Nick</author>. <title rend="italic">Twisty Little Passages</title>.
				<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>, <date>2003</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="murray1997" label="Murray 1997" key="murray1997">
			            <author>Murray, J.</author>
			            <title rend="italic">Hamlet on the Holodeck: The Future of Narrative in
			Cyberspace</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Free Press</publisher>,
				<date>1997</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nss1994" label="NSS 1994" key="nss1994">
			            <title rend="quotes">Mammoth Cave Restoration Field Camp 1994</title>. National
			Speleological Society, <date>1994</date>. <ref target="http://www.caves.org/io/mcrg/camp_reports/1994.htm">http://www.caves.org/io/mcrg/Camp_Reports/1994.htm</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nelson2001" label="Nelson 2001" key="nelson2001">
			            <author>Nelson, G.</author>
			            <title rend="italic">Inform Designer's Manual</title>, 4th ed. <pubPlace>St. Charles,
				Illinois</pubPlace>: <publisher>The Interactive Fiction Library</publisher>,
				<date>2001</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oneill1990" label="O'Neill 1990" key="oneill1990">
			            <author>O'Neill, J.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Oral history interview with William Crowther</title>. Charles
			Babbage Institute, <date>1990</date>. <ref target="http://www.cbi.umn.edu/oh/pdf.phtml?id=97">http://www.cbi.umn.edu/oh/pdf.phtml?id=97</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="park1994" label="Park 1994" key="park1994">
			            <author>Park, M.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Colossal Cave Revisited</title>, <title rend="italic">TidBITS</title>, 8 (<date>1994</date>). <ref target="http://www.tidbits.com/tb-issues/tidbits-229.html#lnk4">http://www.tidbits.com/tb-issues/TidBITS-229.html#lnk4</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="plotkin1995" label="Plotkin 1995" key="plotkin1995">
			            <author>Plotkin, A.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Freefall</title>, freeware. <date>1995</date>. Several versions
			available from <ref target="http://www.wurb.com/if/game/94">http://www.wurb.com/if/game/94</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="poole2000" label="Poole 2000" key="poole2000">
			            <author>Poole, S.</author>
			            <title rend="italic">Trigger Happy</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
				<publisher>Arcade Publishing</publisher>, <date>2000</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="raymond1996" label="Raymond 1996" key="raymond1996"> Raymond, E. (ed). <title rend="italic">The New Hacker's Dictionary</title>, 3rd ed. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>:
				<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>, <date>1996</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="robinett2000" label="Robinett 2000" key="robinett2000">
			            <author>Robinett, W.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Design of the First Action-Adventure Video Game: <title rend="none">Adventure</title> for the Atari 2600</title>, Lecture, University of North
			Carolina Chapel Hill, <date>2000?</date>. <ref target="http://www.warrenrobinett.com/adventure/adventure_lecture.ppt">http://www.warrenrobinett.com/adventure/adventure_lecture.ppt</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rothstein2002" label="Rothstein 2002" key="rothstein2002">
			            <author>Rothstein, E.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Realism May Be Taking the Fun Out of Games</title>, <title rend="italic">New York Times</title>, <date>06 Apr 2002</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ryan2001b" label="Ryan 2001b" key="ryan2001b">
			            <author>Ryan, M.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Beyond Myth and Metaphor: The Case of Narrative in Digital
			Media</title>, <title rend="italic">Game Studies</title>, 1:1
			(<date>2001</date>). <ref target="http://www.gamestudies.org/0101/ryan/">http://www.gamestudies.org/0101/ryan/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="selfe2007" label="Selfe and Hawisher 2007" key="selfe2007"> Selfe, G. and Hawisher (eds.).
				<title rend="italic">Gaming Lives in the Twenty-first Century</title>. <pubPlace>New
				York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher>, <date>2007</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schwartz1999" label="Schwartz 1999" key="schwartz1999">
			            <author>Schwartz, B.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Everything You've Ever Wanted to Know About <title rend="none">Adventure</title>!</title> Personal web page. <date>1999?</date>. <ref target="http://www.ir.bbn.com/~bschwart/adventure.html">http://www.ir.bbn.com/~bschwart/adventure.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="toomey1990" label="Toomey 1990" key="toomey1990">
			            <author>Toomey, W.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">
                  <title rend="none">Adventure</title> Map 2</title>. <date>Early
				1990s</date>. <ref target="http://www.rickadams.org/adventure/maps/advent2.gif">http://www.rickadams.org/adventure/maps/advent2.gif</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="turkle1995" label="Turkle 1995" key="turkle1995">
			            <author>Turkle, S.</author>
			            <title rend="italic">Life on the Screen: Identity in the Age of the Internet</title>.
				<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Simon and Schuster</publisher>,
			<date>1995</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vanvleck2001" label="Van Vleck 2001" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Van Vleck, T.</author> E-mail to the author, <date>01 Feb 2001</date>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wilcox1990" label="Wilcox 1990" key="wilcox1990">
			            <author>Wilcox, P.</author> Re: XYZZY. alt.folklore.computers posting, <date>06 Feb
			1990</date>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wilcox2002" label="Wilcox 2002" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Wilcox, P.</author> Telephone interview, <date>24 May 2002</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="woods2006" label="Woods 2006" key="woods2006">
			            <author>Woods, D.</author>
			            <title rend="quotes">Don Woods's Home Page.</title> Personal web page,
			<date>1998-2006</date>. 08 Jun 2007. <ref target="http://www.icynic.com/~don/">http://www.icynic.com/~don/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="woods2007" label="Woods 2007" key="[unlisted]">
			            <author>Woods, D.</author> E-mail to the author, <date>11 Mar 2007</date>.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>