<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Structure over Style: Collaborative Authorship and the Revival
                    of Literary Capitalism</title>

                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Simon <dhq:family>Fuller</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>National University of Ireland, Maynooth</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>simonfuller9@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Simon Fuller is a former post-graduate student in Computer Science at the
                            National University of Ireland, Maynooth. He holds an M.A. in Philosophy
                            and Literature, and is currently working in machine learning and data
                            science.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>James <dhq:family>O'Sullivan</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Sheffield</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>j.c.osullivan@sheffield.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>James O’Sullivan is the Digital Humanities Research Associate at the
                            University of Sheffield’s Humanities Research Institute. James holds a
                            Ph.D. in Digital Arts &amp; Humanities, as well as advanced degrees in
                            computing, literary, and cultural studies. He recently co-edited <title
                                rend="italic">Reading Modernism with Machines</title> (Palgrave
                            Macmillan, 2016) alongside Shawna Ross. For more, see <ref
                                target="http://josullivan.org/">josullivan.org</ref>.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>


            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000286</idno>
                <idno type="volume">011</idno>
                <idno type="issue">1</idno>
                <date when="2017-02-14">14 February 2017</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>stylometry</item>
                        <item>popular literature</item>
                        <item>text analysis</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="JDF" when="2017-01-30">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>James Patterson is the world’s best-selling living author, but his approach to
                    writing is heavily criticised for being too commercially driven — in many
                    respects, he is considered the master of the airport novel, a highly-productive
                    source of commuter fiction. A former marketing professional, Patterson uses his
                    business acumen to drive sales of his novels, which are largely written in
                    conjunction with lesser-known co-authors. Using stylometry, this paper analyses
                    the extent to which Patterson actually contributes to the writing of his novels,
                    situating his process within the context of literary capitalism and the novel as
                    a force of modernity. </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Stylometric analysis of collaboration in James Patterson's novels</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>James Patterson is among the world’s best-selling living authors, but his
                    approach to literature is often derided. Patrick Anderson of <title
                        rend="italic">The Washington Post</title> labels his work as <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#mahler2010">sick, sexist, sadistic and subliterate</quote>,
                    while Stephen King describes Patterson, quite frankly, as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mahler2010">a terrible writer</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mahler2010"/>
                    </cit>. Patterson’s background is in marketing, and indeed he makes unapologetic
                    use of advertising techniques to increase sales. His writing style is largely
                    considered to be simplistic; his subject matter excessively emotive. Moreover,
                    he hires collaborators, who, according to our analysis, complete much of the
                    actual writing. However, as we will describe in this paper, it is in such a
                    context that we can situate Patterson as working within structures of literary
                    production indissociable from the capitalist forces which drive most literary
                    production. His re-discovery and refinement of the novel’s popular traditions is
                    accompanied by a choice of style and subject matter that make his works
                    exemplary of the experience of leisure-time in late capitalism. Patterson’s
                    particular achievement is to be both author and producer; creator, brand, and
                    corporation. Patterson is, in many respects, as much a trademark as he is a
                    writer. His name is a stamp of approval. What does this mean for our
                    constructions of <q>the author</q>? Does Patterson’s name on the cover mean that
                    a particular novel is written <emph>by</emph> Patterson, or that it has been
                        <emph>approved</emph> by Patterson? Is his name an indicator of the style of
                    a novel, or a gesture towards its structure and content? In our stylometric
                    analyses, we examine the extent to which Patterson actively collaborates on the
                    writing of his novels, exploring his approach in the context of the wider
                    culture industry and its capitalist modes of literary production. Patterson
                    appropriates and manipulates the economic, social, and industrial forces which
                    have shaped the form and content of the novel since its ascent in the
                    eighteenth-century. Informing our discussion with computer-assisted analyses,
                    the focus of which is Patterson, we problematise the relationship between the
                    novel and style.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Defining the Novel</head>
                <p>There is disagreement on the precise origins of the novel, with some suggesting
                    its roots be traced back some two thousand years <ptr target="#doody1997"/>.
                    Typically, however, scholars accept Ian Watt’s assertion that the novel is an
                    eighteenth-century literary form, emerging as a response to romantic prose. It
                    is worth noting that while much of the literature we reference focuses on the
                    evolution of the British novel, wherein other scholars discuss the form as a
                    more global genre, we see little distinction, in the context of this study,
                    between the novels of American writers like Patterson and those of French
                    authors such as Dumas. Watt connects the rise of the novel to the forces of
                    modernity, particularly the emergence of the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#watt2001">commercial and industrial
                            classes</quote>
                        <ptr target="#watt2001" loc="61"/>
                    </cit>, as well as an increase in secular thinking and individualism. John
                    Richetti agrees, commenting in <title rend="italic">The English Novel in
                        History</title>, that early fiction marks <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#richetti1999">an important stage in the
                            fashioning and a key tool for the understanding of this evolving entity,
                            the socially constructed self</quote>
                        <ptr target="#richetti1999" loc="4"/>
                    </cit>. Richetti further notes that the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#richetti2002">expectations for narrative that
                            came to dominate the minds of readers in those years, as well as the
                            popularity of such narratives, may be related to larger intellectual and
                            social changes</quote>
                        <ptr target="#richetti2002" loc="2"/>
                    </cit>. J. Paul Hunter presents early readers of the novel as being young, a
                    product of most novels being <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hunter2002">about young people on the verge of
                            making important life decisions about love or career or both</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hunter2002" loc="20"/>
                    </cit>. Crucial to this study, Hunter outlines how <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hunter2002">novelists repeatedly set
                            themselves the task of addressing situations in which large numbers of
                            readers had a vital interest</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hunter2002" loc="20"/>
                    </cit>. A dominant caricature was present at the time, Samuel Johnson describing
                    readers of the form as young, ignorant, idle time wasters <ptr
                        target="#hunter2002" loc="20–21"/>, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hunter2002">not traditionally educated</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hunter2002" loc="20"/>
                    </cit>, a contention that Hunter refutes: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hunter2002">The time to read had to be stolen
                            from somewhere when life was lived under such difficult and precarious
                            conditions</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hunter2002" loc="21"/>
                    </cit>. This tendency reverberates in the popular contemporary novel, where the
                    primary objective for authors is often the provision of entertainment. Hunter
                    attributes the eighteenth-century rise of the novel to readers’ need for <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#hunter2002">pleasure</quote>: <quote rend="block"
                        source="#hunter2002">… the joy of escape from drudgery or routine; the
                        pleasure of a story well told and a plot carefully built; satisfaction in
                        seeing outcomes (and even solutions) in the recognizable situations of daily
                        life; identification with characters who faced (and often mastered)
                        difficult situations; and, perhaps, the recognition of a part of oneself in
                        a fictional other who might take a different course or come to a different
                        end — as well as the more traditional pleasures (carried over from romances)
                        of compensatory fantasy in contemplating people quite unlike oneself. <ptr
                            target="#hunter2002" loc="22"/></quote></p>
                <p>The power of this fantasy emanates from the <quote rend="inline" source="#watt2001"
                        >combination of romance and formal realism</quote>, a feat which the novel
                    accomplished <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#watt2001">more insidiously than any previous
                            fiction</quote>
                        <ptr target="#watt2001" loc="205"/>
                    </cit>. Further growth in commerce led to an increased market for print, but by
                    the same token, enhanced capacity for production: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#richetti2002">Instead of a luxury affordable
                            only by the privileged and educated few, books and especially novels
                            were part of the revolution in the availability of consumer goods that
                            changed the nature of daily life for a large part of the population in
                            Britain as the eighteenth century progressed</quote>
                        <ptr target="#richetti2002" loc="6"/>
                    </cit>. While access to the form has increased exponentially, its core traits
                    have remained intact: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#frye2006">the popular demand in fiction is
                            always for a mixed form, a romantic novel just romantic enough for the
                            reader to project his libido on the hero and his anima on the heroine,
                            and just novel enough to keep these projections in a familiar
                            world</quote>
                        <ptr target="#frye2006" loc="99"/>
                    </cit>. As the novel became increasingly saturated by theory, and influenced by
                    social movements, each generation saw varying transformations to the form. As
                    Marthe Robert aptly notes, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#robert2000">its boundaries fluctuate in all
                            directions</quote>
                        <ptr target="#robert2000" loc="58"/>
                    </cit>. What has remained a constant throughout is the continued democratisation
                    of reading, a movement which has often been connected to a perceived
                    deterioration in literary quality. This is where one of the primary concerns of
                    our examination takes hold, upon the tension between plot and style, and whether
                    or not, in such a context, style tells us little more than who completed the
                    actual writing, as opposed to who devised the narrative framework into which
                    such words are poured. It is difficult to argue which activity is more essential
                    without falling into the largely unhelpful binary of <q>substance over
                    style</q>. Saying this, and adages aside, the novel has always been about plot,
                    about reader-driven content designed to obscure social realities under romantic
                    elements and sensational details. Privileging style is the exception, not the
                    rule, and is limited to specific literary epochs, such as high modernism.
                    Patterson, as we will see, takes the contrary position to the stylists — not
                    only do his novels privilege fast-paced plot over character and situational
                    development, but his writing method seems to have been reduced down to providing
                    an overview of the plot which someone else, to whatever little extent, then
                    fleshes out. The relationship between plot and style has undergone increased
                    strain as a product of contemporary writing practices, more susceptible to
                    capitalist modes of production than ever before.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Brand-managed authors</head>
                <p>The main subject of this study is James Patterson. At the time of writing, he is
                    the world’s most successful living author, outselling J. K. Rowling, Dan Brown,
                    and John Grisham combined <ptr target="#wood2009"/>. Between 2006 and 2010, one
                    in every seventeen novels sold in the United States was authored by Patterson
                        <ptr target="#mahler2010"/>. He has achieved this feat by publishing copious
                    numbers of reasonably successful novels rather than a select few blockbusters.
                    His most successful release, 1993’s <title rend="italic">Along Came A
                        Spider</title>, only reached number two on the bestseller charts. Its five
                    million print-run is small compared to that of say, Dan Brown’s <title
                        rend="italic">The Da Vinci Code</title>; however, by 2014 he had published
                    in excess of 100 novels. </p>
                <p>Patterson wrote his first thriller in 1976, but before the 1990s his main
                    employment and source of income lay in marketing. He worked at J. Walter
                    Thompson, where he became its youngest ever creative director and eventually
                    chief executive of North American operations <ptr target="#mahler2010"/>. His
                    marketing continues to inform his approach to promotion and writing. In fact,
                    the two processes, Patterson’s writing and his marketing, are somewhat
                    indistinguishable. For <title rend="italic">Along Came A Spider</title>, he took
                    the unusual step of using television advertising <ptr target="#wroe2013"/>,
                    paying for it out of his own pocket <ptr target="#deighton2006" loc="8"/>. Since
                    then, he has taken control of his own marketing from his publisher, Little,
                    Brown and Co., a division of Hachette <ptr target="#mahler2010"/>. Two editors
                    and three full-time Hachette employees, plus assistants, work exclusively for
                    Patterson. According to Michael Pietsch, his editor and publisher, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#deighton2006">Jim is at the very least
                            co-publisher of his own books</quote>
                        <ptr target="#deighton2006" loc="5"/>
                    </cit>. Patterson, in this sense, is bigger than his publisher. In outranking
                    his publisher, he differs significantly from many forms of commercial fiction.
                    Mills and Boon, for instance, employ writers to create romance novels that
                    conform to a limited horizon of reader expectation. Watt describes how in the
                    eighteenth-century, the bookseller-publishers of Grub street used to employ
                    writers, often paying by the word, to churn out novels and translate works from
                    French <ptr target="#watt2001" loc="55"/>. Commercial fiction has always been
                    driven by the demands of its readership. What makes Patterson different, is that
                    he exerts personal control over the publishing apparatus which seek to match
                    literary content to the market. Patterson brings a new level of rigour to
                    marketing within the publishing industry. This is acknowledged by Larry
                    Kirschbaum, former head of Little, Brown: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mahler2010">Until the last 15 years or so, the
                            thought that you could mass-merchandise authors had always been
                            resisted… Jim was at the forefront of changing that</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mahler2010"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>What Patterson shares with the writers of Mills and Boon novels, the forgotten
                    eighteenth-century hack pieces, and the dime novels and penny dreadfuls of the
                    nineteenth-century, is that he writes simple, populistic works with no
                    pretensions of academic literary quality, designed to sell. But, like the
                    publishers of Grub Street, he has a greater number and variety of books to sell
                    than most authors can produce. As we will discuss, he achieves this in part by
                    hiring collaborators. Patterson therefore has properties of the traditional
                    popular author, properties of the publishing house, as well as those of the
                    modern marketing executive. If the development of the form and content of
                    popular fiction is explainable to a large extent by the socio-economic factors
                    that drive its production,<note><soCalled>High art</soCalled> — though we resist
                        certain facets of the dichotomy this term suggests — is somewhat different
                        in that it tends to engage with the literary and metaphysical tradition, and
                        is therefore less reducible to local socio-economic factors.</note> then
                    Patterson is in the unusual position of possessing an overview of these factors,
                    and writing and commissioning fiction accordingly. As such, economic forces do
                    not simply shape his work externally or deterministically, but are put to play
                    by him from the outset to determine a written product that will be popular,
                    marketable, and replicable. It is said of Dumas, père, to whom we will return,
                    that he <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#lucasdubreton">did not exist at all, he was
                            only a myth, a trademark invented by a syndicate of editors to dupe the
                            public</quote>
                        <ptr target="#lucasdubreton"/>
                    </cit>. As already noted, Patterson is himself a trademark, a stamp of approval
                    that is more indicative of a novel’s structure than it is its style.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Reader-Driven Content</head>
                <p>In an effort to broaden his following, Patterson has commissioned his own studies
                    into the demographics of his audience <ptr target="#deighton2006" loc="5"/>.
                    Such research has even directly influenced the content of his work — in one
                    case, in order to make up for a lag of sales on the West coast of the United
                    States, where John Grisham was the dominant author, he decided to locate his
                    second thriller series, <title rend="italic">The Women’s Murder Club</title>, in
                    San Francisco <ptr target="#mahler2010"/>. In a generally complimentary
                    assessment, Jonathan Mahler says of Patterson’s TV campaign for his breakthrough
                    work, <title rend="italic">Along Came A Spider</title>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mahler2010">It’s entirely possible, even quite
                            likely, that without those ads, <title rend="italic">Along Came a
                                Spider</title> never would have made the bestseller list, and that
                            James Patterson would now be just another thriller writer</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mahler2010"/>
                    </cit>. The problem with such an appraisal is not that it ascribes Patterson’s
                    success to his marketing alone, but that it considers Patterson’s literary work
                    and the surrounding marketing as separate in the first place. Rather, the
                    literary and commercial facets of his work reinforce each other to the point
                    where, as in the case of his choice of location for <title rend="italic">The
                        Women’s Murder Club</title> series, they are indistinct.</p>
                <p>When producing a novel, Patterson uses about a dozen readers as a soundboard for
                    the work in progress, making alterations as they point to the <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#deighton2006">weaker</quote> elements of a story
                        <ptr target="#deighton2006" loc="5"/>. His writing is designed to arrest
                    readers’ attention, and to encourage them to buy into a series of novels,
                    typically based around a primary, re-occurring character or characters. As
                    Nicholas Wroe explains: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#wroe2013">His prose is doggedly functional
                            with short sentences and chapters relentlessly working to propel the
                            plot</quote>
                        <ptr target="#wroe2013"/>
                    </cit>. His use of short chapters, says Mahler, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mahler2010">creates a lot of half-blank pages;
                            his books are, in a very literal sense, page-turners</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mahler2010"/>
                    </cit>. The development of this approach is premeditated. Patterson himself
                    describes how, after his earlier, less successful works, he is <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mahler2010">less interested in sentences now
                            and more interested in stories</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mahler2010"/>
                    </cit>. Of his first work, <title rend="italic">The Thomas Berryman
                        Number</title>, he says that he <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#wood2009">couldn't have supported [himself] on that kind of
                        book</quote>, and that his writing is now <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#wood2009">very self-consciously
                            commercial</quote>
                        <ptr target="#wood2009"/>
                    </cit>. In developing a formula that has seen him become the world’s most
                    successful writer, Patterson’s new releases often do not receive press reviews,
                    but they attract a large number of reader reviews across online media. Here, it
                    is quickly apparent that his works are praised by readers for the qualities he
                    has intentionally fostered. An excerpt from an Amazon review for <title
                        rend="italic">I, Alex Cross</title> reads: <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#undocumented">This is well written — using Patterson's usual
                        quick and easy chapters,</quote> evidently equating brevity with quality.
                    Another review for the same work concludes: <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#undocumented">The thriller is written in short chapters, which I
                        like, and the font is large enough to make reading enjoyable. The prose is
                        clear, succinct, and paints a picture of full-blown evil and terror. A fast
                        read.</quote><note>These reviews taken from Amazon.com’s page for <title
                            rend="italic">I, Alex Cross</title>, where they were both posted on
                        November 16, 2009. They are attributed to <q>Tina</q> and <q>B. Davis</q>.
                        Accessed on July 2, 2014.</note></p>
                <p>That Patterson should let the reader instruct the form and content of his work is
                    not a perversion of the proper order of literary creation. Rather, it seems to
                    be constitutive of the rise to prominence of the novel in the modern era. For
                    Watt, the relative democratisation of readership in the eighteenth-century
                    encouraged writers to write <quote rend="inline" source="#watt2001">very
                        explicitly and even tautologically</quote> for the audience, while also, as
                    we will see with Patterson, writing quickly in order to increase business
                    throughput <ptr target="#watt2001" loc="56"/>. Thus, a simplification of writing
                    form was a defining characteristic of the development of the modern, popular
                    novel. Patterson also seems to be drawing from contemporary cinema and
                    television. The cinematic narrative is constructed in the editor’s lab out of a
                    patchwork of sounds and images; for Walter Benjamin, the screen actor’s
                    performance, and her experience of it, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2002c">is assembled from many
                            individual performances</quote>
                        <ptr target="#benjamin2002c" loc="112"/>
                    </cit>. This mosaic-like structure is echoed in Patterson’s short paragraphs and
                    chapters which lurch the protagonist from crisis to crisis. As such, he has
                    further simplified the reading process by bringing its narrative presentation
                    into line with a reader whose attention is shaped by film and television, and
                    the truncated and informal writing style of the Internet.</p>
                <p>In a short early article on a genre of German nineteenth-century literature,
                    Benjamin asks: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2005">Chambermaid’s romances? Since
                            when are works of art categorized according to the class which consumes
                            them? Unfortunately, they are not, or all too seldom</quote>
                        <ptr target="#benjamin2005" loc="225"/>
                    </cit>. Rather than being classified otherwise, such works have generally not
                    received any attention at all: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2005">this entire body of literature
                            has been despised for as long as the superstitious belief in ‘absolute
                            art’ has existed</quote>
                        <ptr target="#benjamin2005" loc="225"/>
                    </cit>. For Watt, appraising perhaps the first modern instance of the novel’s
                    dominance in eighteenth-century England, this profession, which <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#watt2001">in the eighteenth century probably
                            constituted the largest single occupational group</quote>
                        <ptr target="#watt2001" loc="47"/>
                    </cit>, also shaped the content of the contemporaneous literature, most famously
                    in the eponymous heroine of <title rend="italic">Pamela</title>. Indeed, he goes
                    on to argue, the long dominant, and still prescient, themes of courtship, and
                    marrying above class, have their origin in the preponderance of women readers of
                    the novel, particularly from the lower, middle, and servant classes <ptr
                        target="#watt2001" loc="148–149, 154, 163–164"/>. Patterson’s novels, also
                    with a predominantly female readership <ptr target="#deighton2006" loc="5"/>,
                    span many genres, but largely consist of a standard thriller formula, for
                    instance serial-killers and their opposing crime fighters, the latter juggling,
                    usually successfully, their work with their family commitments, weaving
                    contemporary problems of conflicting work-family demands with wider social fears
                    about terror and criminality — for an example, see <title rend="italic">Along
                        Came a Spider</title>.</p>
                <p>The <emph>form</emph> of his novels also appears to be moulded by contemporary
                    experience. In particular, his work is perhaps best described as <q>commuter
                        fiction</q>. Nicholas Paumgarten describes how the average time for a
                    commute has significantly increased <ptr target="#paumgarten2007"/>. As a
                    result, reading has increasingly become one of those pursuits that can pass the
                    time of a commute. For example, a truck driver describes how <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mahler2010">he had never read any of
                            Patterson’s books but that he had listened to every single one of them
                            on the road</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mahler2010"/>
                    </cit>. A number of online reader reviews also describe Patterson’s writing in
                    terms of their commutes. One such reviewer of Patterson’s <title rend="italic"
                        >The Postcard Killers </title>directly relates the writing style to the
                    realities of modern transitional life: <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#undocumented">As a consequence of such short chapters I whizzed
                        through this book in under two hours and it was a fairly decent thriller and
                        a good way to spend time commuting to work.</quote><note>This review was
                        posted on Amazon.co.uk by <q>Nicola F</q>, December 2011. Access on July 2,
                        2014.</note> With large print, and chapters of two or three pages,
                    Patterson’s works are constructed to fit between the stops on a metro line.</p>
                <p>We believe that, here, Patterson again exemplifies traits characteristic of the
                    rise of the novel. Disposable, leisurely art is, for Benjamin, the dominant
                    aesthetic form of late modernity: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2002d">Just as the art of the Greeks
                            was geared toward lasting, so the art of the present is geared toward
                            being worn out</quote>
                        <ptr target="#benjamin2002d" loc="142"/>
                    </cit>. To greatly summarise Benjamin’s position regarding the novel, this
                    disposability has its origins in the isolation of the subject, who no longer has
                    access to the continuity of communal experience. The novelist and reader are
                    exemplary for Benjamin of the crisis in experience that is symptomatic of late
                    modernity. The novelist, for their part, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2002b">... has secluded himself. The
                            birthplace of the novel is the individual in isolation ...</quote>
                        <ptr target="#benjamin2002b" loc="146"/>
                    </cit>. The reader of the novel is also <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2002d">isolated, more so than any
                            other reader … In this solitude of his … he destroys, swallows up the
                            material as a fire devours a log in a fireplace</quote>
                        <ptr target="#benjamin2002d" loc="156"/>
                    </cit>. Benjamin suggests that this reflects a wholesale <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#benjamin2003a">change in the structure of their
                        experience</quote>, as evidenced in the experience of navigating a city,
                    which he directly describes in terms of Marx’s theory of alienation of the
                    worker in industrial production <ptr target="#benjamin2003a" loc="314"/>. The
                    pedestrian navigates through the city <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#benjamin2003a">in a series of shocks and collisions</quote>,
                    corresponding their movements to the dictates of cars and traffic lights. They
                    are thus subjected by technology to <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2003a">a complex kind of
                            training</quote>
                        <ptr target="#benjamin2003a" loc="328"/>
                    </cit>. Modern subjects have <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2003a"
                        >adapted themselves to machines</quote> to the extent that their experience
                    is primarily that of <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2003a">a reaction to shocks</quote>
                        <ptr target="#benjamin2003a" loc="329"/>
                    </cit>. Traversing the city, the subject is isolated from others, as well as
                    alienated from herself. Benjamin cites George Simmel on public transport: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2003b">Before the development of
                            buses, railroads, and trams in the nineteenth century, people had never
                            been in situations where they had to look at one another for long
                            minutes or even hours without speaking to one another</quote>
                        <ptr target="#benjamin2003b" loc="20"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>In advanced technological society, shared, enduring experience (<foreign
                        xml:lang="de">Erfahrung</foreign>) gives way to <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#benjamin2002c">shock experience</quote>, whether that of the
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2002c">passerby in the
                    crowd</quote>, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2003a">the isolated ‘experiences’ of
                            the worker at his machine</quote>
                        <ptr target="#benjamin2003a" loc="329"/>
                    </cit>, or the film actor, whose performance is split <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#benjamin2002c">into a series of episodes capable of being
                        assembled</quote> in the editing room <ptr target="#benjamin2002c" loc="113"
                    />. Film is thus seen as giving modernity aesthetic form: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2003a">in film, perception conditioned
                            by shock was established as a formal principle</quote>
                        <ptr target="#benjamin2003a" loc="328"/>
                    </cit>. We have discussed how Patterson aligns his work to the aesthetic
                    expectations of the subject in the age of television and cinema. But Patterson’s
                    work also responds directly to the shock experience of modernity which was
                    formalised in cinema. In their short segments, his books are shaped to the
                    disruptive punctuations of urban passage which they reflect and constitute.</p>
                <p>By understanding the pervading social forces of occidental late capitalism, and
                    by anticipating the nature of everyday human experience within this network of
                    systems, Patterson produces novels which have the phantasms of modern life
                    inscribed upon their pages, and the fractured reality of modern experience
                    carved out as their form.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Collaboration &amp; the Absence of Style</head>
                <p>A much-noted aspect of Patterson’s approach is his use of collaborators for his
                    novels. In 2000 he published three books, all of which were successful, and this
                    prompted him to focus upon collaboration in order to dominate the market <ptr
                        target="#wroe2013"/>. As a result of this process, he produced 13 distinct
                    publications in 2012 and the same number in 2013. The co-authors are directly
                    employed by Patterson, assigned to a particular genre or series, and paid out of
                    Patterson’s own pocket <ptr target="#mahler2010"/> at what is rumoured to be a
                    flat rate with bonuses and no royalties <ptr target="#wood2009"/>. For many,
                    such as Gross and De Jonge who feature in our stylometric analysis, it has
                    provided a launching pad for their solo careers. While Patterson does not like
                    the term <q>boss</q>, he concedes that he is the senior figure in any
                    collaboration, and defends his position by way of employee satisfaction: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#beard2012">nobody quits</quote>
                        <ptr target="#beard2012"/>
                    </cit>, and <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#blum2012">nobody asks for a raise</quote>
                        <ptr target="#blum2012"/>
                    </cit>. Indeed, he primarily assumes a managerial role in the creative process
                    itself: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#blum2012">I write an outline for a book. The
                            outlines are very specific about what each scene is supposed to
                            accomplish. I get pages from [the collaborator] every two weeks, and
                            then I re-write them. That’s the way everything works. Sometimes I’ll
                            just give notes…</quote>
                        <ptr target="#blum2012"/>
                    </cit>. Patterson appears to be part creator, part editor, and also part
                    guarantor of satisfaction — a sort of <title rend="italic">Alfred Hitchcock
                        Presents</title> stamp of quality. In his own words: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#deighton2006">my name on the cover is the
                            assurance of a good read</quote>
                        <ptr target="#deighton2006" loc="2"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>Defending his process, Patterson points out that collaboration has also been used
                    in other creative outlets, such as television <ptr target="#wroe2013"/>,
                    newspapers, cinema, and even the masonic guilds behind the medieval cathedrals
                        <ptr target="#beard2012"/>. In employing collaborative methods, Patterson
                    has in fact aligned novel writing with the creative norm in contemporary
                    culture. As Hobsbawm says of the late twentieth-century: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hobsbawm1994">Creation was now essentially
                            cooperative rather than individual, technological rather than
                            manual</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hobsbawm1994" loc="519"/>
                    </cit>. A crucial juncture in the establishment of this modern paradigm, and of
                    its rise in the field of professional writing, was the introduction of the
                    producer system in early Hollywood cinema, wherein the producer takes precedence
                    over the director, overseeing a process in which labour is divided along lines
                    established in heavy industry, with the same goals of increased efficiency and
                    profit. The task of screenwriting is further sub-divided along these lines: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#thomson1993">By the early teens, American
                            studios not only had writing departments but also sub-specialties within
                            those departments</quote>
                        <ptr target="#thomson1993" loc="387"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>Some commentators have described Patterson’s successful application of these
                    methods to novel writing as unprecedented. Mahler, for instance, states: <quote
                        rend="block" source="#mahler2010">Books, at least in their traditional
                        conception, are the product of one person’s imagination and sensibility,
                        rendered in a singular, unreproducible style and voice. Some novelists have
                        tried using co-authors, usually with limited success. Certainly none have
                        taken collaboration to the level Patterson has… <ptr target="#mahler2010"
                        /></quote></p>
                <p>But Patterson’s approach is not as new as Mahler claims. Division of labour was
                    in fact adopted in literature from at least the mid-nineteenth-century. Benjamin
                    frequently discusses the growing application of industrial methods on
                    nineteenth-century French literature as the commercial returns for literature
                    increased. As such, the French novel, for Benjamin, appears to build upon the
                    commercial origin of the British novel, industrializing the already commercial
                    form. The most commercially successful writers of the era included Sue, Scribe,
                    and Dumas, each of which employed collaborators in order to increase output <ptr
                        target="#benjamin2003c" loc="14–15"/>. Benjamin cites Kreysig, who describes
                    the playwright Eugene Scribe in terms which mirror accounts of Patterson’s
                    method: <quote rend="block" source="#benjamin2003b">...he transferred the
                        principle of division of labour from the workshops of tailors, cabinet
                        makers, and manufacturers of pen nibs to the ateliers of the dramatic
                        artists… Scribe chose the subject, sketched out the main lines of the plot
                        ... and his apprentices would compose the appropriate dialogue or verses.
                        ...their name would appear on the title page (next to that of the firm) as a
                        just recompense, until the best would break away and begin turning out
                        dramatical works of their own invention, perhaps also in their turn
                        recruiting new assistants. <ptr target="#benjamin2003b" loc="671–672"
                        /></quote></p>
                <p>Dumas took simultaneous contracts for serialised novels from different journals
                        <ptr target="#benjamin2003b" loc="585"/>, once occupying <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2003b">almost simultaneously, with
                            three of his novels, the feuilleton sections of <title rend="italic">La
                                Presse, Le Constitutionnel</title>, and <title rend="italic">Le
                                Journal des debats</title></quote>
                        <ptr target="#benjamin2003b" loc="760"/>
                    </cit>. He designated the writing task to others in order to keep up with
                    demand. As a caricature puts it: <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2003b"
                        >It was said that Dumas employed a whole army of poor writers in his
                        cellars</quote> while he drank champagne with actresses <ptr
                        target="#benjamin2003b" loc="15"/>. He was accused by de Mirecourt of
                    running <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2003c">a factory of
                        novels</quote> and the <hi rend="italic">Revue des Mondes </hi>questioned
                    whether he even knew the names of all the titles published in his name <ptr
                        target="#benjamin2003c" loc="15"/>. De Mirecourt writes: <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#lucasdubreton">his novels are by Maquet,
                        Fiorention, Meurice, Malefille, or Paul Lacroix … [he] dares, monster that
                        he is, to sign his name alone.</quote> As a consequence of this criticism,
                    Dumas was obliged to publicly recognise Maquet and others as collaborators <ptr
                        target="#lucasdubreton"/>. In his defence, Dumas sought credit for providing
                    so much employment: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#benjamin2002a">In twenty years, he said, he
                            had written 400 novels and 35 plays. He had created jobs for 8160 people
                            — proofreaders, typesetters, machinists, wardrobe mistresses</quote>
                        <ptr target="#benjamin2002a" loc="276"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>Marx and Engels, in a certain sense, approved of Dumas and Scribe, in that they
                    saw their adoption of industry techniques as formally aligning popular culture
                    with the modes of production. In <title rend="italic">The German
                        Ideology</title>, they favourably compare French popular fiction to the
                    German, paying particular attention to the latter’s appropriation of the
                    division of labour: <quote rend="block" source="#marx2001">In proclaiming the
                        uniqueness of work in science and art, Stirner adopts a position far
                        inferior to that of the bourgeoisie. At the present time it has already been
                        found necessary to organize this ‘unique’ activity. Horace Vernet would not
                        have had time to paint even a tenth of his pictures if he regarded them as
                        works which ‘only this Unique person is capable of producing’. In Paris, the
                        great demand for vaudevilles and novels brought about the organization of
                        work for their production, organisation which at any rate yields something
                        better than its ‘unique’ competitors in Germany. <ptr target="#marx2001"
                            loc="108"/></quote></p>
                <p>Thus, by employing collaborators and dividing the writing process in order to
                    increase profit, Patterson re-establishes techniques which dominated popular
                    fiction in nineteenth-century Paris. While these writers were often derided for
                    this, Marx and Engels perceived that, by employing the principles of division of
                    labour which defined working existence, the collaborative approach generated
                    mass entertainment that was pleasurable, disposable, and efficient to create.
                    The culturally dominant forms of mass entertainment were thence increasingly
                    those which adopted the principle of division of labour: in cinema, and then
                    television, in the publisher-brand Mills and Boon novels in which the individual
                    authors were expendable and interchangeable, and then in Patterson, who has
                    become one of the world’s most commercially successful authors by using
                    hierarchical collaboration to launch multiple bestsellers each year. By drawing
                    on established cinematic archetypes of plot to write the kind of suspense which
                    people expect, and by employing a simple, punchy format, Patterson has devised a
                    commodity which is amenable to replication. As such, he displays the primary
                    motivation which has driven the production of the novel since the
                    eighteenth-century Grub Street booksellers began employing writers to fashion
                        <title rend="italic">Pamela-</title>esque romances — the drive to meet
                    commercial demand <ptr target="#watt2001" loc="47"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Stylometric Analysis</head>
                <p>Gaby Wood comments in <title rend="italic">The Guardian</title> that the
                    sentences in Patterson’s novel <quote rend="inline" source="#wood2009">are not
                        designed to be lingered over</quote>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#wood2009">they are more or less all
                    plot</quote>, she argues <ptr target="#wood2009"/>. To his credit, Patterson has
                    been very open in describing how his novels are produced. This paper seeks to
                    further elaborate on this process, using computational stylistics to produce
                    statistically valid indicators of the amount of actual writing that Patterson
                    contributes before deeming a novel worthy of his brand. This information will
                    allow us to better understand the role of brand-managed authors like Patterson
                    in the creative process, and indeed, how they are situated within the context of
                    the novel as a form of literary capitalism. </p>
                <p>We evaluate the relative contributions of Patterson and two of his collaborators
                    using versions of Burrow’s Delta, a widely-used lexical measure for English
                    texts <ptr target="#burrows2002"/>. We selected the collaborators Peter de Jonge
                    and Andrew Gross for this investigation, largely as a consequence of access to
                    appropriate single-author samples. Patterson, by his own accounts, allocates
                    most of the actual writing to his junior partners. We formed the working
                    hypothesis that the collaborative novels would be stylometrically more similar
                    to texts written primarily by Patterson’s co-authors, rather than to any of the
                    novels attributed to Patterson alone. This study is based on the premise that
                    the lexical features we have selected are effective in distinguishing the
                    sentence writer over the architect of the plot. This correlates with much of the
                    field’s existing research. Patrick Juola, for instance, demonstrates that in
                    attempted forgeries, the lexical signature of the forger overrides the semantic
                    content which might associate it with the impersonated party <ptr
                        target="#juola2013"/>. Our second hypothesis was that Patterson’s
                    contribution would be strongest at critical moments in the text. Given the
                    plot-driven genre, we believed that these would typically be present at the
                    beginning and end of the novels.</p>
                <p>To test our first hypothesis, we employ a <q>Bootstrap Consensus Tree</q> cluster
                    analysis over maximum frequency words ranging from 100 to 1000, in intervals of
                    100, with the Burrow’s Delta metric, using the <title rend="italic"
                        >Stylo</title> package for <title rend="italic">R</title>
                    <ptr target="#eder-rybicki2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#eder-kestemont2013"/>. We use a consensus strength of 0.5, meaning
                    that we formed a tree showing proximity wherever this occurred in 50% or more of
                    the 10 maximum frequency clusterings described <ptr target="#wilkinson1996"/>.
                    For our second hypothesis, we use the Rolling Delta technique <ptr
                        target="#rybicki2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#vandalen2007"/>
                    <ptr target="#hoover2011"/>. To provide a general intuitive description of this
                    method, Burrow’s Delta distances are measured between the collaborative text and
                    single-author texts for each participating author. However, distances are
                    measured to <q>windows</q> of the collaborative text, allowing for estimation as
                    to which sections carry the stylistic fingerprint of one contributor over
                    another. Sample single-author tests are then plotted over the baseline of the
                    collaborative text, where greater proximity to the baseline indicates greater
                    stylistic similarity, as defined by the Delta distance metric.</p>
                <p>A more robust study of this topic would need to assess Patterson’s contribution
                    to the abstract entity which is the plot of the works we have examined. We did
                    make an attempt at this, computationally measuring the frequency of action verbs
                    across a text.<note>With thanks to Geoffrey Rockwell for his suggestions on this
                        topic during discussions at the annual gathering of the Canadian Society for
                        Digital Humanities / Société canadienne des humanités numériques, May
                        2014.</note> The expectation was, considering the genre, that there would be
                    significant spikes at particular points in the novel. Our hope was there would
                    be some noticeable trends, which did occur, across some of the Patterson only
                    novels, as opposed to the co-authored texts, which presented far more variation.
                    This would suggest that there is something significant in our results, yet, we
                    are not in a position to reasonably conclude that we are detecting an authorial
                    fingerprint, rather than just structures common to this particular genre. It
                    would be interesting, however, to return to this aspect of our analysis at a
                    further point with a more conclusive methodology.</p>
                <p>In this paper, we examine the following collaborative texts:</p>
                <p>Patterson &amp; De Jonge: <list type="simple">
                        <item><title rend="italic">Beach House </title>(2003)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">Beach Road </title>(2006)</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Patterson &amp; Gross: <list type="simple">
                        <item><title rend="italic">2nd Chance </title>(2002)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">3rd Degree </title>(2004)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">Judge and Jury </title>(2006)</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Patterson &amp; Karp: <list type="simple">
                        <item><title rend="italic">Kill Me If You Can </title>(2011)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">NYPD Red </title>(2012)</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Our solo texts, by author, are as follows:</p>
                <p>DeJonge: <list type="simple">
                        <item><title rend="italic">Shadows Still Remain</title> (2009)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">Buried On Avenue B</title> (2012)</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Gross: <list type="simple">
                        <item><title rend="italic">The Dark Tide</title> (2008)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">Don't Look Twice</title> (2009)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">Killing Hour </title>(2011)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">15 Seconds</title> (2012)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">No Way Back</title> 2013)</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>For Patterson, we used this fixed set of nine solo works: <list type="simple">
                        <item><title rend="italic">First to Die </title>(2001)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">Four Blind Mice </title>(2002)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">The Lake House </title>(2003)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">London Bridges </title>(2004)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">Maximum Ride: The Angel Experiment
                            </title>(2005)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">Maximum Ride: Saving The World And Other Extreme
                                Sports </title>(2007)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">I, Alex Cross</title> (2009)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">Fang </title>(2010)</item>
                        <item><title rend="italic">Nevermore </title>(2012)</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>The following visualisation displays our bootstrap consensus tree over the entire
                    dataset:</p>

                <figure>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>


                <p>As predicted, the collaborative works all cluster with the respective junior
                    writer. Within both the De Jonge and Gross clusters, the collaborative works
                    form a distinct sub-cluster. Within the Patterson cluster, the <title
                        rend="italic">Maximum Ride</title> series of novels are separated from
                    another cluster consisting of Alex Cross novels and the Patterson novel, <title
                        rend="italic">The Lake House</title>. One surprise result is that <title
                        rend="italic">First to Die</title>, a solo Patterson text, is clustered with
                    the subsequent works in <title rend="italic">The Women’s Murder Club
                    </title>series, which he wrote with Andrew Gross. This could simply represent a
                    limitation of the Delta metric over these texts, or alternatively, it could
                    indicate that Gross was so influenced by the particular style that Patterson
                    manifested in this work that he imitated it more exactly than Patterson managed
                    in any of the other works under examination. A third possibility is that the new
                    collaborative series, <title rend="italic">The Women’s Murder Club</title>,
                    opened with a purported solo Patterson work, when it was in fact a co-authored
                    novel.</p>
                <p>Our full study comprised Rolling Deltas for all collaborative texts, under a
                    number of different settings. For the purpose of this abstract we include just
                    two Rolling Delta studies, <title rend="italic">First to Die</title> and its
                    sequel in the series, <title rend="italic">Second Chance</title>:</p>


                <figure>

                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                </figure>


                <figure>

                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                </figure>

                <p>For <title rend="italic">Second Chance</title>, Gross’ texts are closest
                    throughout, apart from <title rend="italic">First to Die</title>, which, as we
                    have already discussed, is attributed solely to Patterson. <title rend="italic"
                        >First to Die</title>'s model is more interesting, as the work presents
                    itself as we would expect a true collaboration in which the authors have shared
                    the task of writing passages or sentences with Patterson intervening at critical
                    junctures. This seems to add plausibility to the conjecture that the work might
                    in fact have been written by Gross and Patterson, rather than Patterson alone,
                    as is officially stated. One might ultimately discount such a possibility, and
                    explain this anomaly as an artifact caused by the limitations of stylometric
                    analysis in its current stage of development. However, were we to accept these
                    results at face value, they might indicate an interesting situation in
                    commercial fiction: namely, a junior writer, Andrew Gross, having his name
                    erased from a book he co-wrote in order to increase the commercial value and
                    status of that book as a product. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusions</head>
                <p>The quantitative data suggests that Patterson’s collaborators perform the vast
                    majority of the actual writing. Our results demonstrate that Patterson, like
                    Dumas, has commodified his reputation as an author and met demand through
                    delegation. However, it appears that Patterson has generally been transparent
                    regarding his collaborative process, and has offered sufficient accreditation,
                    tutelage, opportunity, and financial reward to those with whom he works.</p>
                <p>The novel has always been a commercial form. Its rise was a product of the rise
                    of the bourgeoisie. But Patterson has perhaps brought the novel to its logical
                    conclusion. In a certain sense, Patterson’s works are not reducible to their
                    socio-economic context. Rather, wresting marketing control from his publisher,
                    hiring his own soundboard readers, and employing subsidiary writers, Patterson
                    generates pulp far more concentratedly than the vagaries of traditional
                    historical materialism would generally allow. While we might see <soCalled>high
                        literature</soCalled> as irreducible to its immediate socio-economic context
                    because the author is in a kind of dialogue with the whole literary and even
                    metaphysical canon, Patterson’s work is irreducible in the sense that he creates
                    his fiction in accordance with his own manipulations of its economic base.</p>
                <p>As Patterson says: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#deighton2006">above all my brand stands for
                            story. I became successful when I stopped writing sentences and started
                            writing stories. Editors think it's about style. It's not. It's all
                            story</quote>
                        <ptr target="#deighton2006" loc="5"/>
                    </cit>. On the one hand, we note that for Patterson, this is just as well, as
                    our analysis shows that his stylometric fingerprint is sometimes weak, even in
                    his solo works. To keep things in perspective, we recall Aristotle's assertion
                    that plot (<ref
                        target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/morph?l=su%2Fstasis&amp;la=greek&amp;can=su%2Fstasis0&amp;prior=pragma/twn"
                            ><foreign xml:lang="grc">μῦθος</foreign></ref>) is the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#aristotle1932">arrangement of the incidents
                                (<ref
                                target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/morph?l=h(&amp;la=greek&amp;can=h(2&amp;prior=e)sti\n"
                                    ><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἡ</foreign></ref>
                            <ref
                                target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/morph?l=tw%3Dn&amp;la=greek&amp;can=tw%3Dn2&amp;prior=h("
                                    ><foreign xml:lang="grc">τῶν</foreign></ref>
                            <ref
                                target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/morph?l=pragma%2Ftwn&amp;la=greek&amp;can=pragma%2Ftwn1&amp;prior=tw=n"
                                    ><foreign xml:lang="grc">πραγμάτων</foreign></ref>
                            <ref
                                target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/morph?l=su%2Fstasis&amp;la=greek&amp;can=su%2Fstasis0&amp;prior=pragma/twn"
                                    ><foreign xml:lang="grc">σύστασις</foreign></ref>)</quote>
                        <ptr target="#aristotle1932"/>
                    </cit>. Is plot, then, what makes an author? These findings demonstrate how
                    style is very much privileged across particular literary aesthetics, and that it
                    is, in many respects, relegated to an afterthought within contemporary popular
                    fiction. Style remains a powerful measurement in experiments of this kind, but
                    as a literary device, it is not always present within a form that has long held
                    strong ties with the forces of late capitalism. When we see the name Patterson,
                    Dumas, or Hitchcock, is that an indication of reliability rather than
                    authenticity; substance rather than style?</p>
            </div>
            <div>


                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>Part of this research was generously funded by the Higher Education Authority,
                    under the Programme for Research in Third Level Institutions, Cycle 5, and under
                    the Irish Research Council’s EMBARK Initiative.</p>
                <p>Earlier incarnations of this study have been presented at the following
                    conferences: </p>
                <p>Fuller, Simon, and James O’Sullivan. “‘More or less all plot’: A Rolling Delta
                    Analysis of the Commodification of Collaboration.” <hi rend="italic">Canadian
                        Society for Digital Humanities Annual Conference</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Congress of the Humanities and Social Sciences</hi>, Brock University,
                    Saint Catharine’s, 26 May 2014.</p>
                <p>Fuller, Simon, and James O’Sullivan. “Beyond Style: Literary Capitalism and the
                    Publishing Industry.” <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities</hi>, Lausanne, 10
                    July 2014.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl/>

                <bibl label="Aristotle 1932" xml:id="aristotle1932">Aristotle. <title rend="italic"
                        >Poetics</title>. [Online]. Cambridge, Massachusetts; London, Harvard
                    University Press; William Heinemann. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu">www.perseus.tufts.edu</ref> (1932)
                    [Accessed: 16 October 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Beard 2012" xml:id="beard2012">Beard, A. <title rend="quotes">Life’s
                        Work: James Patterson</title>. <title rend="italic">Harvard Business Review
                        Magazine</title>. [Online]. Available from: <ref
                        target="https://hbr.org/product/lifes-work-james-patterson/R1203T-PDF-ENG"
                        >https://hbr.org/product/lifes-work-james-patterson/R1203T-PDF-ENG</ref>
                    (2012) [Accessed: 1 July 2014].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Benjamin 2005" xml:id="benjamin2005">Benjamin, W. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Chambermaid’s Romances of the Past Century</title>. In: Howard Eiland &amp;
                    Michael W. Jennings, and Gary Smith (eds.). <title rend="italic">Walter Benjamin
                        Selected Writings: Volume 2, part 1, 1927-1930</title>. Cambridge,
                    Massachusetts, and London, The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press (2205):
                    225-231. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Benjamin 2002a" xml:id="benjamin2002a">Benjamin, W. <title
                        rend="quotes">Edward Fuchs, Collector and Historian</title>. In: Howard
                    Eiland &amp; Michael W. Jennings (eds.). <title rend="italic">Walter Benjamin
                        Selected Writings: Volume 3, 1935-1938</title>. Cambridge, Massachusetts,
                    and London, The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press (2002a):
                    260–302.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Benjamin 2003a" xml:id="benjamin2003a">Benjamin, W. <title
                        rend="quotes">On Some Motifs in Baudelaire</title>. In: Howard Eiland &amp;
                    Michael W. Jennings (eds.). <title rend="italic">Walter Benjamin Selected
                        Writings: Volume 4, 1938-1940</title>. Cambridge, Massachusetts, and London,
                    The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press (2003a): 313–354.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Benjamin 2003b" xml:id="benjamin2003b">Benjamin, W. <title
                        rend="italic">The Arcades Project</title>. Trans. Howard Eiland &amp; Kevin
                    McLaughlin. Cambridge, Massachusetts and London, The Belknap Press of Harvard
                    University Press (2003b).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Benjamin 2003c" xml:id="benjamin2003c">Benjamin, W. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Paris of the Second Empire in Baudelaire</title>. In:
                    Howard Eiland &amp; Michael W. Jennings (eds.). <title rend="italic">Walter
                        Benjamin Selected Writings: Volume 4, 1938-1940</title>. Cambridge,
                    Massachusetts, and London, The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press
                    (2003c): 3–92.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Benjamin 2002b" xml:id="benjamin2002b">Benjamin, W. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Storyteller: Observations on the Works of Nikolai
                        Leskov</title>. In: Howard Eiland &amp; Michael W. Jennings (eds.). <title
                        rend="italic">Walter Benjamin Selected Writings: Volume 3,
                    1935-1938</title>. Cambridge, Massachusetts, and London, The Belknap Press of
                    Harvard University Press (2002b): 143–166.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Benjamin 2002c" xml:id="benjamin2002c">Benjamin, W. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Work of Art in the Age of Its Technological
                        Reproducibility</title>. In: Howard Eiland &amp; Michael W. Jennings (eds.).
                        <title rend="italic">Walter Benjamin Selected Writings: Volume 3,
                        1935-1938</title>. Cambridge, Massachusetts, and London, The Belknap Press
                    of Harvard University Press (2002c): 101–133.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Benjamin 2002d" xml:id="benjamin2002d">Benjamin, W. <title
                        rend="quotes">Theory of Distraction</title>. In: Howard Eiland &amp; Michael
                    W. Jennings (eds.). <title rend="italic">Walter Benjamin Selected Writings:
                        Volume 3, 1935-1938</title>. Cambridge, Massachusetts, and London, The
                    Belknap Press of Harvard University Press (2002d): 141–142.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Blum 2012" xml:id="blum2012">Blum, L.S. <title rend="quotes">James
                        Patterson Explains Why His Books Sell Like Crazy</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Wall Street Journal</title>. [Online]. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://blogs.wsj.com/speakeasy/2012/03/30/james-patterson-explains-his-why-his-books-sell-like-crazy"
                        >http://blogs.wsj.com/speakeasy/2012/03/30/james-patterson-explains-his-why-his-books-sell-like-crazy/</ref>
                    (2012) [Accessed: 23 January 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Burrows 2002" xml:id="burrows2002">Burrows, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >‘Delta’: A Measure of Stylistic Difference and a Guide to Likely
                        Authorship</title>. <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic
                        Computing</title>. 17.3 (2002): 267–287.</bibl>
                <bibl label="van Dalen-Oskam &amp; van Zundert 2007" xml:id="vandalen2007">van
                    Dalen-Oskam, K. &amp; Zundert, J. van. <title rend="quotes">Delta for Middle
                        Dutch — Author and Copyist Distinction in Walewein</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>. 22.3 (2007):
                    345–362.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Deighton 2006" xml:id="deighton2006">Deighton, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Marketing James Patterson</title>. <title rend="italic">Harvard Business
                        Review</title>. [Online]. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://hbr.org/product/a/an/505029-PDF-ENG?cm_sp=doi-_-case-_-505029-PDF-ENG&amp;referral=00103"
                        >http://hbr.org/product/a/an/505029-PDF-ENG?cm_sp=doi-_-case-_-505029-PDF-ENG&amp;referral=00103</ref>
                    (2006) [Accessed: 24 August 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Doody 1997" xml:id="doody1997">Doody, M.A. <title rend="italic">The
                        True Story of the Novel</title>. New Brunswick, Rutgers University Press
                    (1997).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Eder, Kestemont, &amp; Rybicki 2013" xml:id="eder-kestemont2013">Eder,
                    M., Kestemont, M. &amp; Rybicki, J. <title rend="quotes">Stylometry with R: a
                        suite of tools</title>. In: <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2013:
                        Conference Abstracts</title>. University of Nebraska–Lincoln (2013):
                    487–489.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Eder &amp; Rybicki 2013" xml:id="eder-rybicki2013">Eder, M. &amp;
                    Rybicki, J. <title rend="quotes">Do birds of a feather really flock together, or
                        how to choose training samples for authorship attribution</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>. 28.2 (2013):
                    229–236.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Frye 2006" xml:id="frye2006">Frye, N. <title rend="quotes">Anatomy of
                        Criticism</title>. In: Dorothy J. Hale (ed.). <title rend="italic">The
                        Novel: An Anthology of Criticism and Theory 1900-2000</title>. Malden,
                    Massachusetts, Blackwell Publishing (2006): 97-106.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Hobsbawm 1994" xml:id="hobsbawm1994">Hobsbawm, E. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Age of Extremes: The Short 20th Century</title>. London, Abacus
                    (1994).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Hoover 2011" xml:id="hoover2011">Hoover, D. L. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Tutor’s Story: a case study of mixed authorship</title>. In: <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2011: Conference Abstracts</title>.
                    Stanford (2011): 149–151.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Hunter 2002" xml:id="hunter2002">Hunter, J. P. <title rend="quotes">The
                        novel and social/cultural history</title>. In: John Richetti (ed.). <title
                        rend="italic">The Cambridge Companion to the Eighteenth-Century
                        Novel</title>. Cambridge, Cambridge University Press (2002): 9-40.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Juola 2013" xml:id="juola2013">Juola, P. <title rend="italic"
                        >Stylometric Report - Heartland Institute Memo</title>. [Online]. Available
                    from: <ref
                        target="https://wattsupwiththat.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/memoreport.pdf"
                        >https://wattsupwiththat.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/memoreport.pdf</ref>
                    (2013) [Accessed: 23 January 2017].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Lucas-Dubreton n.d." xml:id="lucasdubreton">Lucas-Dubreton, J. <title
                        rend="italic">The Fourth Musketeer: The Life of Alexander Dumas</title>.
                    [Online]. Le site web Alexandre Dumas père / The Alexandre Dumas père Web Site.
                    Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.cadytech.com/dumas/related/fourth_musketeer.php"
                        >http://www.cadytech.com/dumas/related/fourth_musketeer.php</ref> (n.d.)
                    [Accessed: 24 October 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Mahler 2010" xml:id="mahler2010">Mahler, J. <title rend="quotes">James
                        Patterson Inc</title>. <title rend="italic">The New York Times
                        Magazine</title>. [Online] 24 January 2010. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/24/magazine/24patterson-t.html"
                        >http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/24/magazine/24patterson-t.html</ref>
                    [Accessed: 14 August 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Marx &amp; Engels 2001" xml:id="marx2001">Marx, K. &amp; Engels, F.
                        <title rend="italic">German Ideology, Part 1 and Selections from Parts 2 and
                        3</title>. Christopher John Arthur (ed.). New York, International Publishers
                    (2001).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Paumgarten 2007" xml:id="paumgarten2007">Paumgarten, N. <title
                        rend="quotes">There and Back Again: The Soul of the Commuter</title>.
                    [Online]. 16 April 2007. <title rend="italic">The New Yorker</title>. Available
                    from: <ref
                        target="http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2007/04/16/there-and-back-again"
                        >http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2007/04/16/there-and-back-again</ref>
                    [Accessed: 1 July 2014].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Richetti 2002" xml:id="richetti2002">Richetti, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Introduction</title>. In: John Richetti (ed.). <title rend="italic">The
                        Cambridge Companion to the Eighteenth-Century Novel</title>. Cambridge,
                    Cambridge University Press (2002): 1–8.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Richetti 1999" xml:id="richetti1999">Richetti, J. <title rend="italic"
                        >The English Novel in History 1700-1780</title>. London, Routledge
                    (1999).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Robert 2000" xml:id="robert2000">Robert, M. <title rend="quotes">From
                        Origins of the Novel</title>. In: Michael McKeon (ed.). <title rend="italic"
                        >Theory of the Novel: A Historical Approach</title>. Baltimore, The Johns
                    Hopkins University Press (2000): 57–69.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Rybicki, Kestemont, &amp; Hoover 2013" xml:id="rybicki2013">Rybicki,
                    J., Kestemont, M. &amp; Hoover, D.L. <title rend="quotes">Collaborative
                        authorship: Conrad, Ford and rolling delta</title>. In: <title rend="italic"
                        >Digital Humanities 2013: Conference Abstracts</title>. University of
                    Nebraska–Lincoln (2013): 368–371.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Thompson 1993" xml:id="thomson1993">Thompson, K. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Early Alternatives to the Hollywood Mode of Production: Implications for
                        Europe’s Avant-Gardes</title>. <title rend="italic">Film History</title>.
                    5.4 (1993): 386–404.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Watt 2001" xml:id="watt2001">Watt, I. <title rend="italic">The Rise of
                        the Novel</title>. Berkeley and Los Angeles, University of California Press
                    (2001).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Wilkinson 1996" xml:id="wilkinson1996">Wilkinson, M. <title
                        rend="quotes">Majority-rule reduced consensus trees and their use in
                        bootstrapping</title>. <title rend="italic">Molecular Biology and
                        Evolution</title>. 13.3 (1996): 437–444.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Wood 2009" xml:id="wood2009">Wood, G. <title rend="quotes">The world’s
                        no 1 bestseller</title>. [Online]. 5 April 2009. <title rend="italic">The
                        Guardian</title>. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.theguardian.com/books/2009/apr/05/james-patterson-author-bestseller"
                        >http://www.theguardian.com/books/2009/apr/05/james-patterson-author-bestseller</ref>
                    [Accessed: 17 August 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Wroe 2013" xml:id="wroe2013">Wroe, N. <title rend="quotes">James
                        Patterson: a life in writing</title>. [Online]. 11 May 2013. <title
                        rend="italic">The Guardian</title>. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.theguardian.com/culture/2013/may/11/james-patterson-life-in-writing"
                        >http://www.theguardian.com/culture/2013/may/11/james-patterson-life-in-writing</ref>
                    [Accessed: 19 August 2013].</bibl>

            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
