<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Unveiling the Critical Nexus of Data Preprocessing and Transparent Documentation for Result Quality and Reproducibility in Digital History</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Clodomir <dhq:family>Santana</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7869-7184</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Tadeusz Manteuffel Institute of History, Polish Academy of Sciences, Poland</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>clodomir@ieee.org</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                      <p>Clodomir Santana received the bachelor's degree in computer engineering from the Polytechnic School, University of Pernambuco, the master's degree in systems engineering from the University of Pernambuco, in 2019, and the Ph.D. degree in computer science from the University of Exeter, U.K. Currently he is with Tadeusz Manteuffel Institute of History, Polish Academy of Sciences. His master's dissertation received an honourable mention from the University of Pernambuco. During the bachelor's degree, he was awarded a scholarship from the Brazilian Coordination of Superior Level Staff Improvement (CAPES) to be a visiting student with the Faculty of Engineering and Applied Science, Memorial University, Canada, for 16 months. His research interests include digital history, metaheuristics, network science, human dynamics, and natural language processing.
                      </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Demival <dhq:family>Vasques Filho</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4552-0427</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Centre for Contemporary and Digital History, University of Luxembourg, Luxembourg</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>demival.vasques@uni.lu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                      <p>Demival Vasques Filho is a Research Scientist at the Centre for Contemporary and Digital History (C²DH) of the University of Luxembourg. He holds a PhD in Physics, specializing in the broad area of Complexity and Network Science. His research interests focus on developing new methods and expanding the application of complex systems concepts in the study of social sciences and humanities.
                      </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Michał <dhq:family>Bojanowski</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7503-852X</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Department of Quantitative Methods and Information Technology, Kozminski University, Poland</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>mbojanowski@kozminski.edu.pl</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                      <p>Michał Bojanowski is an assistant professor at the Department of Quantitative Methods and Information Technology at Kozminski University and a researcher at the COALESCE Lab at the Autonomous University of Barcelona. He holds a PhD in sociology (2012, ICS / Utrecht University) and his research focuses on conflict, cooperation and other relational aspects of social cohesion. He specializes in modeling social network data, especially those collected with non-sociocentric designs, as well as in assembling complex social network datasets from non-obvious sources (such as historical archives) using often technically-advanced procedures. Michał is an R developer with over 20 years of experience and a member of Statnet Development Team - creators and maintainers of a suite of R packages for statistical network analysis.
                      </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Agata <dhq:family>Błoch</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2070-2750</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Tadeusz Manteuffel Institute of History, Polish Academy of Sciences, Poland</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>EMAIL</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                      <p>Agata Błoch is an Assistant Professor at the Institute of History of the Polish Academy of Sciences in the Department of Historical Atlases in the Section of Digital History. She is the principal investigator of <title rend="italic">Imperial Commoners in Brazil and West Africa (1640–1822): A Global History from a Correspondence Network Perspective</title>, funded by the National Science Center of Poland, 2022/45/B/HS3/00473, 2023-2027. The project combines digital humanities and history by drawing on a unique dataset of official correspondence between Lisbon and its Atlantic colonies, comprising nearly 170,000 letters, to view the empire as a dynamic space based on networks and created through grassroots communication. Project website: <ref target="www.projectmape.org">www.projectmape.org</ref>. Her publications include <title rend="italic">Networks from Archives: Reconstructing networks of official correspondence in the early modern Portuguese empire</title> in Social Networks and The <title rend="italic">Miserable Vassals of the Empire: The Androgynous Codes of Behaviour of Black and Indigenous Peoples in Late Colonial Brazil (1775–1808)</title> in Journal of History, among others.
                      </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">XXX</idno>
                <idno type="volume">XXX</idno>
                <idno type="issue">XXX</idno>
                <date when="2024-04-15">15 April 2024</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            	<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
            		<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
            	</taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <term corresp="#data_modeling"/>
                    <term corresp="#machine_learning"/>
                    <term corresp="#nlp"/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                  <list type="simple">
                    <item>Preprocessing</item>
                    <item>Topic Modelling</item>
                    <item>Documentation</item>
                    <item>Digital History</item>
                  </list>
                </keywords>
            	<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
            		<list type="simple">
            			<item></item>
            		</list>
            	</keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
        	<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000717/000717.xml">GitHub</ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>This study underscores the importance of adequate data preprocessing, transparency, and documentation in digital history research, showcasing how these often overlooked practices impact research quality and reproducibility. We present a topic modelling case study involving over 160,000 records of official correspondence of the Atlantic Portuguese Empire from 1640 to 1822 to illustrate how these practices, associated with standardised formats and metadata conventions, facilitate the sharing and reproduction of experiments. First, we evaluate the impact of data cleaning and preprocessing on model performance. Second, concerning model selection, we compare the performance of latent Dirichlet allocation (LDA), latent semantic indexing (LSI), and Gibbs sampling algorithm for a Dirichlet mixture model (GSDMM). Besides stressing the underestimated significance of data preprocessing and transparent documentation to strengthen research robustness and contribute to a reproducibility culture, we also demonstrate the potential of topic modelling in digital historical studies, specifically in the context of the Atlantic Portuguese Empire.
                </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
              <p>The study presents promising outcomes with proper preprocessing, model selection, and parameterisation. Our findings encourage further exploration and refinement of the methodology employed.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
<body>

<head>1. Introduction: Bringing Preprocessing and Documentation to the Spotlight</head>

<p>
The tools of digital humanities have considerably broadened the perspectives of historical scholarship. However, new opportunities do not come without challenges. Along this paper, we debate one of these new challenges historians are facing: dealing with huge amounts of data that require methodological practices previously unfamiliar to these scholars.
</p>
<p>
Up to the 1970s and 1980s, we have the so-called “pre-digital” quantitative historical research. The term “pre-digital” encompasses two important aspects within historical studies: firstly, it refers to the period before the widespread introduction of computer software for quantitative data analysis. Secondly, it represents a time before the increasing accessibility of digitised archival collections and their storage in machine-readable formats <ptr target="#Burrows2023"/>; <ptr target="#Kesner1982 Burrows2023"/>. One of the first widely known experiments of digital analysis of historical data can be found in the pioneering work of William O. Aydelotte in 1963<ptr target="#Aydelotte1963"/>. Yet, digital (automated) data extraction and preprocessing took much longer to become part of the digital historian toolbox, doing so only in the 21st century <ptr target="#Pettersson2016"/> .
</p>
<p>
For instance, Padgett and Ansell’s study on the rise of the Medici family in 15th century Florence performed network analysis which involved the creation of a basic dataset through the manual extraction of data from various published and unpublished sources <ptr target="#Padgett1993"/>. Different types of relationships were manually coded, from kinship and patronage to personal and financial ties. Wetherell, Andrejs and Barry also used manual extraction of historical data for network analysis <ptr target="#Wetherell1994"/>. The primary data source came from nominal censuses covering the period from 1795 to 1850, whose extraction was crucial in defining both the extent and structure of the personal communities of peasants residing in Pinkenhof in the Russian Baltic Province of Livland. Timothy Brook’s approach was similar to the previously discussed manual data extraction methods <ptr target="#Brook1981"/>. In researching Chinese trade networks during the 16th century under the Ming dynasty, he extracted and listed relevant information to create a table of place names and the corresponding administrative level and modern Chinese nomenclature.
</p>
<p>
With the growing interest in open access archives, many libraries in the Western hemisphere have introduced complex methods such as Optical Character Recognition (OCR) to digitise their collections <ptr target="#Salmi2020"/>. This trend started with the initiative of governments and private companies in the 1980s who wanted to make their documentation more accessible <ptr target="#Kesner1982"/>. An important observation that Richard Kesner made at the time was that, unlike librarians, archivists could never agree on standardising metadata because it was impossible to use a uniform format for different archival sources <ptr target="#Kesner1982"/>. The lack of a standardised format for historical records is a key reason why this article highlights the importance of appropriate preprocessing in digital history.
</p>
<p>
When considering the profound impact that digital tools have on data-driven historical research, two different approaches can be identified: the traditional method of manual extraction followed by computer analysis, and the fully digital approach, where computational tools are used from the outset. When dealing with network analysis, for instance, a significant number of historians opt, on the one hand, for manual extraction and then use tools such as Python, Gephi or Nodegoat to map data, visualise relationships and construct their arguments <ptr target="#Haggerty2011"/> ; <ptr target="#Verbruggen2020"/> ; <ptr target="#Antunes2021"/>  ; <ptr target="#Ye2022"/>. On the other hand, automated extraction can be performed from either digital databases and repositories with previously carefully prepared metadata <ptr target="#Wittek2011"/> ; <ptr target="#Petz2021"/>  ; <ptr target="#Geraerts2023"/>, born-digital sources <ptr target="#Linkevicius2022"/>, or using Natural Language Processing (NLP) methods to extract entities directly from traditional historical sources <ptr target="#Elwert2020"/> ; <ptr target="#Zbíral2022"/>.
</p>
<p>
Having a paper document and creating a dataset with proper metadata are challenging tasks that require several steps. For instance, Elo describes how he processed the documents with OCR software and then used a Python programme to extract data such as institutions, parties and individuals <ptr target="#Elo2020"/>. In another example, using data made available in Extensible Markup Language (XML) transcriptions of baptisms and marriages, Geraerts and Vasques Filho investigated religious choice in the 18th century <ptr target="#Geraerts2023"/>. With Python scripts, they extracted the content of interest from the transcriptions and organised it in comma-separated values (CSV) files. These data were then ingested into a specifically designed graph database — modelled to connect people, events, and places — in such a way to facilitate quantitative e qualitative network analysis.
</p>
<p>
Computer-assisted historical research thus offers a wide range of possibilities for the analysis of manually or automatically extracted data. These methods include social network analysis <ptr target="#Antunes2021"/>;<ptr target="#Petz2021"/>; <ptr target="#Ye2022"/>; <ptr target="#Geraerts2023"/>; <ptr target="#Linkevicius2022"/>, quantitative analysis <ptr target="#Haggerty2011"/>, semantic text modelling <ptr target="#Zbíral2022"/>,  topic modelling and random indexing <ptr target="#Wittek2011"/> ; <ptr target="#Brauer2013"/> ; <ptr target="#Ravenek2017"/>, spatial methods <ptr target="#Verbruggen2020"/> , or even a mix of them <ptr target="#Ravenek2017"/> ; <ptr target="#Curran2018"/> ; <ptr target="#Elwert2020"/>. However, collected data is never ready to direct processing during the data analysis stage of the research – preprocessing is required in between. Jentsch and Porada illustrated the steps of digital research, showing the pipeline from unstructured text to structured data, that begins with data collection, moving to the OCR process, NLP methods, data access, and ends with data interpretation <ptr target="#Jentsch2021"/>. 
</p>
<p>
The lack of standardised metadata for historical and archival sources makes the preprocessing stage (with its proper documentation) even more relevant in historical research: as mentioned, this is one of the driving forces behind this discussion. However, scholars in the field of digital history seem to prioritise data collection and its interpretation and visualisation, the latter being an attractive component of digital history. The majority of studies focus on identifying relevant historical sources and then discussing the results, paying little attention to the intermediate steps. Based on the illustrative workflow in Figure 1, showing the conventional process in digital historical research, we observe that steps 1 and 2 (experimental design and data collection) and steps 4 and 5 (data analysis and interpretation of results) are disproportionately emphasised. In contrast, step 3, the preprocessing phase, is often not reported with comparable detail. Our earlier works also share that characteristic and not gave a lot of attention to the importance and analyzed the impact of the data preparatory decisions <ptr target="#Bloch2021"/> ; <ptr target="#Bloch2022"/>;<ptr target="#Bloch2024"/> . 
</p>

<figure xml:id="figure1">
 	<head> A typical workflow in digital history.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure1.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>
Thus, our goal is, in the first step, to review the preprocessing stage of a typical digital history project: discuss it’s elements, their relevance and provide examples of decisions made in the literature. In the second step we illustrate the impact of preprocessing decisions on the substantive quality of results with a case study of a topic model for classification of a corpus of 160’000 historical documents. In particular, how different choices of text preparation (filtering) and model selection affect the number of composition of identified document clusters (topics). 
</p>
<p>
To this end the remainder of the article is structured as follows. In section 2 we review the stages of the typical workflow of digital history and the place the preprocessing takes in it – types of preprocessing decisions usually made, their impact illustrated with examples. In section 3 we discuss motivations, approaches and solutions regarding the proper documentation as well as metadata creation and standardisation. Section 4 describes the case study in which we show how substantively impactful the preprocessing decisions can be. Finally, the paper is concluded with a discussion in section 5.
</p>

<head>2. Data Preprocessing as the Foundation for High-Quality Results</head>

<p>
Preprocessing is an iterative process that includes activities related to data preparation, such as cleaning and normalising data, spelling corrections, reducing imperfections, solving problems with missing data and, in the case of textual data, also lemmatising/stemming and sometimes even removing stop words or tags <ptr target="#Kunilovskaya2021"/>; <ptr target="#Garcia2016"/>. This particular stage is of great importance, even if it is not very fascinating and takes up a lot of time. Kunilovskaya and Plum claim that this stage is believed to take up to 80% of the entire research process. However, they also refer to a report based on a survey in which the average time spent by 2,300 respondents worldwide in this critical phase was 45% <ptr target="#Kunilovskaya2021"/>. It is also worth noting that this is an iterative process due to the eventual need to perform some steps more than once. For example, after executing the preprocessing pipeline and analysing the processed data, we noticed that our data cleaning was not removing some terms that were not foreseen. In this case, we modified this step to include these terms and performed the cleaning again.
</p>
<p>
Preprocessing in digital historical research is essential, but also very complex due to the discrepancies between historical sources, archival practices and the nature of the documents in question. Determining whether the documents are digitised or physical, their linguistic diversity and their categorisation (e.g., administrative, religious or private) is crucial <ptr target="#Matthew2020"/>; <ptr target="#Broadwell2020"/>. Each of these elements requires different approaches and an accurate assessment of the advantages and disadvantages of dealing with historical data.
</p>
<p>
Thus, effective documentation of the preprocessing phase – including detailed explanation of the nature and characteristics of the sources (raw data) – is essential to improve result quality and reproducibility. Regarding the latter, the objective is to enable other researchers who follow the described methodology to arrive at similar conclusions, or build upon previous results, when working with the same data. When it comes to results quality, as preprocessing is an iterative process, researchers can improve the results by optimising the approaches performed in this phase by maintaining a good documentation. If the preprocessing steps are insufficiently described, each iteration can generate more difficulties and uncertainties to digital historians.
</p>
<p>
The preprocessing pipeline (Figure 2) is employed to enhance the quality of the raw data <ptr target="#Lee2017"/>;<ptr target="#Fan2021"/> ;<ptr target="#Engel2013"/>, after data acquisition (or collection). It usually involves multiple steps addressing issues such as scattering, baseline changes, peak shifts, noise, missing values, and various other artefacts <ptr target="#Mishra2020"/>. This process is the foundation for robust and valid data analysis. The preprocessing pipeline should take into account the specificities of the data and the requirements of the data analysis models, help unveil relevant underlying structures and, when necessary, accurately predict properties of interest <ptr target="#Mishra2020"/>; <ptr target="#Engel2013"/>.
</p>
<p>
Extensive research has yielded a variety of preprocessing techniques <ptr target="#Mishra2020"/>; <ptr target="#Fan2021"/>. Within the spectrum of these proposed methodologies, some are tailored towards the automated identification of preprocessing strategies <ptr target="#Mishra2019"/>;<ptr target="#Mishra2020"/>, while others address specific tasks, such as data transformations and standardisation <ptr target="#Cao1999"/>;<ptr target="#Baxter1995"/> ; <ptr target="#Shanker1996"/> . Synergistically employing multiple preprocessing techniques can effectively mitigate artefacts that persist when relying solely on a singular technique. Figure 2 depicts an example of a preprocessing pipeline.
</p>
<p>
Usually, cleaning is the first preprocessing step. It aims to transform raw data into a clean, consistent, and reliable dataset that is accurate, amenable to subsequent analyses, modelling, and interpretation <ptr target="#Rahm2000"/>. In this step, we address issues such as identifying and treating missing values, outliers, duplicates, and any inconsistencies in the data.
</p>
<p>
Next, one might require data reduction and scaling depending on the data characteristics (e.g., highdimensional data) or problem tackled (e.g., classification and regression tasks). Data reduction aims to reduce the volume of data without losing important information <ptr target="#Lelewer1987"/>. It focuses on relevant data and eliminating noise or redundancy. In contrast, data scaling involves transforming the features of a dataset so that they fall within a similar scale or range <ptr target="#Cao2016"/>;<ptr target="#Alshdaifat2021"/>. Scaling the data can mitigate the risk of, for example, feature dominance due to their larger magnitudes.
</p>

<figure xml:id="figure2">
 	<head>Example of typical steps in a preprocessing pipeline. Note that some of the depicted steps are optional in some cases. The section of the steps performed depends on the data characteristics and the goal of the analysis. Also, the dashed arrows go in both directions to indicate the iterative nature of the preprocessing.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure2.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>
Lastly, data transformation procedures might be necessary to ensure the compatibility of the data with the methods used for modelling and analysis <ptr target="#Fan2021"/>. For example, some methods struggle to handle categorical data, so an encoding strategy would ensure compatibility, leading to better and more reliable results.
</p>
<p>
As mentioned, the preprocessing pipeline might include other steps depending on the problem at hand, methods employed and analysis goals. Here, we intend to provide an example of typical steps in a pipeline and their intended outcome. We stress the importance of maintaining a record of all the changes made during the data preprocessing. This documentation will be valuable for reproducibility and explaining any data preprocessing steps in research or reports.
</p>
<p>
Furthermore, it is good practice to perform exploratory data analysis (EDA) <ptr target="#Tukey1977"/> after performing the preprocessing steps or even between them. With the EDA, we check summary statistics, distributions, and relationships among variables to ensure the data look as expected. Lastly, let us highlight again that preprocessing is not a one-time task. As new data become available or the data collection process evolves, it is recommended to revisit and update the pipeline.
</p>

<head>2.1. Benefits of Preprocessing</head>

<p>
The notion of data preprocessing affecting the outcome of tools such as machine learning models is widely known and accepted <ptr target="#Alshdaifat2021"/>; <ptr target="#Zelaya2019"/>.  Despite the challenges of assessing this effect, research from several domains has shown the positive impact of proper selection and application of preprocessing tools on the quality of the results <ptr target="#Zhu2016"/>;<ptr target="#Rinnan2009"/>;<ptr target="#Lee2017"/>; <ptr target="#Joo2000"/>;<ptr target="#Alshdaifat2021"/>. The magnitude of these gains depends on several factors <ptr target="#Zhu2016"/>, such as the dataset characteristics (e.g. size, dimensionality, and missing values) and the problem tackled (e.g. classification, regression, and clustering), but we can find examples of 25% improvement when comparing the model results of an optimal preprocessing pipeline to the global model <ptr target="#Rinnan2009"/>.  Also, enhancements in the learning rate and terminal error were reported for neural network models when using adequate preprocessing <ptr target="#Joo2000"/>. 
</p>
<p>
Besides the benefits on the analysis performance, preprocessing contributes to a lower risk of analysis errors and biased results <ptr target="#Kamiran2012"/>;<ptr target="#Zelaya2019"/>. Both data reduction (either by size or dimensionality) and scaling (with clarified model coefficients) enhance interpretation and facilitates understanding, especially for non-experts <ptr target="#Bazjanac2007"/>. These tasks simplify the dataset, making it more manageable and accessible, and allow analysts to focus on relevant patterns, trends, or insights <ptr target="#Monroe2013"/>.
</p>
<p>
Finally, depending on the dataset size and the computational resources available, an adequate preprocessing pipeline can contribute to better computational efficiency. Data reduction techniques allow algorithms to run faster, making the overall process more efficient, and help cut storage costs by minimising the volume of data that must be stored.
</p>

<head>2.2. Challenges of Preprocessing</head>

<p>
Several approaches to identifying the highest performance methods and their optimal combination were also developed to overcome issues due to inappropriate preprocessing <ptr target="#Xu2013"/>;<ptr target="#Zelaya2019"/>; <ptr target="#Zhu2016"/>. However, selecting an optimal preprocessing method is not trivial since it depends on different aspects related to the properties of the data, goals of the analysis and tools employed to achieve these goals <ptr target="#Engel2013"/>.
</p>
<p>
Furthermore, distinct preprocessing methodologies may mitigate specific artefacts while leaving some other effects behind <ptr target="#Rinnan2009"/>. Hence, achieving optimal preprocessing requires integrating multiple techniques <ptr target="#Engel2013"/>. In such scenarios, determining the appropriate combination of methods and the order of their application further augments the intricacy of the problem <ptr target="#Engel2013"/>. 
</p>
<p>
Thus, no preprocessing technique can be considered a gold standard that could be blindly applied to any data, producing satisfactory results irrespective of the data nature <ptr target="#Mishra2020"/>. Despite the efforts toward automating this process and developing more effective tools, method selection is often required to explore the available options <ptr target="#Engel2013"/>. This time-consuming exploration frequently results in a sub-optimal solution, as users can only directly explore a limited set of preprocessing techniques and their combinations <ptr target="#Mishra2020"/>.
</p>
<p>
For these reasons, the field remains open to advancements and novel approaches <ptr target="#Lee2017"/>. It still needs guidelines on the optimal selection and sequencing of preprocessing techniques, including determining when a singular technique suffices and how various techniques can be effectively integrated.
</p>

<head>3. The Role of Comprehensive Documentation in Ensuring Research Reproducibility</head>

<p>
The lack of a golden preprocessing standard amplify the relevance of a proper documentation in the digital humanities; but documentation is not limited to this stage only. Throughout this section, the term “documentation” refers to the systematic recording, detailing, and archiving of all aspects related to the research process. This process includes documenting the research design, methodologies, procedures, data collection techniques, analytical methods, results, interpretations, and conclusions. The primary purpose of documentation is to ensure transparency and reproducibility of the research findings <ptr target="#Gorgolewski2016"/>. It provides a comprehensive record that allows other researchers to understand, evaluate, replicate, and build upon the study.
</p>
<p>
From the reproducibility perspective, the meticulous documentation of every step in data preprocessing is paramount since they transform the raw data into a format suitable for analysis <ptr target="#Gibert2016"/>; each step can significantly impact the outcomes and conclusions of the research. Moreover, detailing the parameters and configurations of the methods employed in the study is another crucial element for improving reproducibility and transparency <ptr target="#Haibe-Kains2020"/>. Parameters such as scaling factors, normalisation methods, missing data imputation techniques, and feature selection criteria can profoundly impact the data characteristics and the subsequent analytical results. By documenting these parameters and the rationale for their selection, researchers also provide insights into the preprocessing decisions, justify the chosen methodologies, and enable critical evaluation and validation of the research process.
</p>
<p>
Besides the parameters and configurations of the methods used, it is also essential to document the software used. Different software packages may have distinct algorithms, functionalities, and default settings that can influence the preprocessing outcomes <ptr target="#Chirigati2016"/>. Through the specification of the software version, modules, and any custom scripts or plugins, researchers enable others to replicate the research, ensuring consistency across studies. Moreover, by leveraging these documents, researchers can identify and address sources of bias, ensure consistency in data handling, and mitigate the risk of errors.
</p>
<p>
Although the documentation process is often associated with the procedures related to the experimental setup, it is far beyond that. It should be conducted since the first steps of the research workflow (i.e., experimental design, as seen in Figure 1). For example, creating well-documented research data and methodologies during the experimental design enhances research reproducibility and helps experts evaluate the research methodology, data quality, interpretations, and limitations. Also, it allows researchers from different disciplines to better understand and build upon existing data and findings.
</p>
<p>
Well-documented research is a valuable educational resource for training the next generation of scientists, researchers, and professionals. It provides examples of best practices in research methodology, data analysis, and reporting. Clear documentation enables educators to incorporate real-world examples, case studies, and research findings into curricula, fostering critical thinking, research skills, and academic excellence.
</p>
<p>
In the literature, we can find examples of works addressing the standardisation of the documentation process. For example, the guiding FAIR (Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, Reusable) <ptr target="#Jacobsen2020"/> data principles are designed to enhance the management, sharing, and reuse of research data and digital resources. Developed by the scientific community, these principles aim to address challenges related to data discovery, accessibility, documentation, integration, and sustainability across diverse disciplines and data infrastructures <ptr target="#Lamprecht2020"/>. The FAIR principles can be summarised as follows:
</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item>Findable: Data and resources should be easy to find for humans and machines. This result can be achieved by assigning persistent identifiers (such as DOIs or URLs), using standardised metadata, providing comprehensive documentation, and ensuring that data is indexed and searchable through relevant repositories, catalogues, or platforms</item>
<item>Accessible: Once located, data and resources can be retrieved and accessed with minimal impediments. Accessibility concerns providing open access, ensuring appropriate authentication and authorisation mechanisms, and offering data in standardised, machine-readable formats. Accessibility ensures that data is available for analysis, validation, and reuse.</item>
<item>Interoperable: Data and resources should be interoperable, meaning they can be integrated, combined, and analysed across different systems, platforms, and disciplines. Interoperability involves using standardised formats, terminologies, ontologies, and protocols and adhering to established data models and conventions. This principle enables researchers to combine data from multiple sources, perform cross-disciplinary analyses, and derive new insights.</item>
<item>Reusable: Data and resources should be reusable, which can be used for various purposes beyond their initial context or research objectives. The steps related to this principle include providing clear licensing, rights, and usage permissions, ensuring data quality and provenance, and offering comprehensive documentation, methodologies, and code. Reusability encourages transparency, reproducibility, and collaboration, allowing researchers to validate findings, build upon existing knowledge, and contribute to collective scientific progress. </item>
</list>

<p>
There are also some domain-specific approaches, such as the data documentation initiative (DDI) <ptr target="#Rasmussen2007"/>. DDI is an international standard for documenting social, behavioural, economic, and health science data. The DDI specification provides a comprehensive framework for describing the various aspects of data, including its collection, processing, distribution, and use <ptr target="#Rasmussen2007"/>. It aims to facilitate the interoperability, preservation, and sharing of research data by promoting standardised metadata documentation. This standard can be beneficial when describing and documenting data sources from the conceptualisation to the archival stages <ptr target="#Rasmussen2007"/>.
</p>
<p>
The DDI has facilitated the development of various tools and resources designed to support the implementation, management, and use of its metadata standards. These range from metadata editors and converters to validation tools and repositories  <ptr target="#Blank2004"/>. For example, the DDI Codebook <ptr target="#Initiative2024b"/> is an XML-based structured documentation format that facilitates the creation of codebooks, data dictionaries, and questionnaires using the metadata standards. It enables researchers to document survey instruments, variables, question text, response categories, and other relevant information in a standardised format. The DDI covers all major content areas but is generally limited to descriptive narrative.
</p>
<p>
Another example of a tool for documenting DDI metadata is the DDI Lifecycle <ptr target="#Initiative2024a"/>. The latter is a comprehensive metadata standard that supports the documentation of the entire research data lifecycle, from conceptualisation and data collection to data processing, analysis, dissemination, and archiving. The DDI Lifecycle provides a structured framework for capturing detailed metadata about data variables, attributes, methodologies, and documentation.
</p>
<p>
Besides these two examples, various metadata editors and tools have been developed to facilitate the creation, editing, validation, and management of DDI metadata. These tools provide graphical user interfaces, templates, wizards, and validation checks to assist researchers, data professionals, and organisations implement DDI standards effectively. Some tools enable metadata transformation, conversion, and interoperability between different formats and standards. Tools such as structured data transformation language (SDTL) and extended knowledge organisation system (XKOS) support the conversion of metadata to and from DDI XML, DDI Codebook, SDMX, RDF, and other relevant formats, ensuring compatibility and consistency across data systems and platforms <ptr target="#DDI2024c"/>.
</p>
<p>
The DDI also complies with FAIR principles. The DDI Alliance and other organisations offer training, workshops, webinars, and educational resources to support the adoption, implementation, and best practices of DDI standards. These resources provide guidance, tutorials, case studies, and examples to assist users in understanding and applying DDI metadata standards effectively.
</p>
<p>
Lastly, local initiatives, such as the European Open Science Cloud (EOSC) <ptr target="#Budroni2019"/> and the German National Research Data Infrastructure (NFDI) <ptr target="#Klingner2023"/>, are proposed to create a unified and accessible ecosystem for research data and digital resources. Both projects aim to accelerate the transition towards open science by providing researchers and institutions access to a wide range of research data, tools, services, and infrastructures.
</p>

<head>4. Case Study: Unveiling Historical Narratives through Topic Modelling</head>

<p>
After advocating the relevance of preprocessing and proper documentation to research, particularly digital history, we present a case study. We apply topic modelling methodologies to unravel latent themes and subjects inherent to an extensive corpus comprising over 160,000 official correspondence of the Atlantic Portuguese Empire. The dataset was sourced from the Historical Overseas Archives of Lisbon between 1640 and 1822.
</p>
<p>
We divide our study into two main phases. First, we explore the impact of data cleaning on the model’s performance and other preprocessing steps. Among these models, we assessed latent Dirichlet allocation (LDA) <ptr target="#Blei2003"/>, latent semantic indexing (LSI) <ptr target="#Rosario2000"/>, and Gibbs sampling algorithm for a Dirichlet mixture model (GSDMM) <ptr target="#Yin2014"/>. Next, we discuss the importance of understanding the characteristics of the data to select a suitable model. We also comment on issues with metrics used to assess the model’s performance and determine the appropriate number of topics.
</p>
<p>
We selected Python version 3.11.5 to build our experimental setup and analysis, and the experiments we performed in a 12th Gen Intel(R) Core(TM) i7-12700H 2.30 GHz computer with 40.0 GB of RAM, HD of 1TB, NVIDIA GeForce RTX 3050, running Windows 11 Pro version 22H2. The supplementary material details the code, the results generated, and the libraries’ specifications. To facilitate reproducibility, besides the code, we also specify the versions of each external library used.
</p>
<p>
Listing these specifications and using open-source multiplatform tools allows us to improve FLAIR’s findability and interoperability principles. To be fully compliant with FLAIR, we intend to target also accessibility and reusability by releasing a version of our dataset on our project website. Together with the code and documentation provided, this dataset will allow researchers to test, replicate and validate our methodology, and that data can be used for other research related to the Atlantic Portuguese Empire.
</p>

<head>4.1. Impact of Preprocessing</head>

<p>
Although we aim to automatically leverage topic modelling models to extract significant themes from the corpus, we must first preprocess the dataset before applying these models to achieve better results. Our preprocessing pipeline consists of data cleaning and transformation, while data scaling and reduction were unnecessary. We “use data cleaning,” referring to a series of procedures to remove unnecessary text elements. These elements include special characters, parentheses and brackets, location and people’s names, and dates.
</p>
<p>
First, we remove the text’s initial and last part of the text in each record, as it only contains metadata
(date, original location of the letter, and archival information) which is useful for other types of analysis but not for topic modelling — metadata do not contain semantic information relevant for our purposes. To illustrate our point, we can take the word Lisbon as an example. Several documents are sent from/to Lisbon; due to the high frequency of this work, the models could create a topic grouping all documents referencing it. In this scenario, the matter discussed in those documents could be related to military, religious, administrative or any other subject. Hence, the group based on the location is not helpful. Figure 3 shows an example text with the removed parts highlighted in yellow.
</p>
<p>
Next, we employ regular expressions to remove special characters such as quotation marks, brackets, parentheses, and a string of white space characters. We also leverage a Named Entity Recognition (NER) model <ptr target="#Nadeau2007"/>;<ptr target="#Bloch2022"/> to remove names of people and locations present in the body of the text. As we explained before, grouping the documents by location is irrelevant to knowing the actual topic discussed in them. Analogously, we remove people’s names as, besides the lack of meaningful information, grouping by names could lead to misinterpretations due to homonyms (e.g., grouping all documents referencing “Maria" would aggregate both commoners and a queen).
</p>

<figure xml:id="figure3">
 	<head>Example of the text highlighting the filtered parts containing dates, locations, and the document archival information. The text can be translated as “216. 1655, April, 24, Lisbon CONSULTATION of the Overseas Council to King D. João IV on the appointment of people to the position of governor of São Tomé, at the end of the three-year term of Cristóvão de Barros Rego, with candidates being Carlos de Nápoles, Inácio Gago da Câmara, and António da Fonseca de Ornelas. AHU-São Tomé, cx. 2, doc. 115. AHU_CU_070, Box 2, D. 216”.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure3.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>
Together with the NER model, we could employ other methods to identify and remove people and locations from the text. For instance, we could filter the text by creating a list of location names from Portugal and the colonies and using libraries available on the web that provide a list of people’s common names per location and language. The main drawback of this approach is the continuous effort of feeding these lists with locations and people not previously captured. Thus, we opted for the NER model as instead of searching for specific words characterised as location names, the model learns from examples of the patterns in the text that indicate that a noun is a location name. The model’s performance depends on the quantity and quality of the examples provided during its training phase.
</p>
<p>
Several NER libraries and pre-trained models are available for our use, provided they work with texts in Portuguese. As we are using Python and due to the availability of resources, we chose to experiment with the spaCy library <ptr target="#Srinivasa-Desikan2018"/> and its pretrained models. Figure 4 shows an example of entities recognised in one sample of our dataset by the pre-trained NER Portuguese model <ptr target="#spaCy2024"/>.
</p>
<p>
Although this model can reach accuracy levels up to 89% because it was trained using news sources of modern Portuguese, the accuracy in our data can be much lower for documents from the 17th until the beginning of the 19th century <ptr target="#Bloch2022"/>. As seen in Figure 4, one of the problems of this model is the long names that are identified as multiple entities. Another drawback of using a pre-trained model is the limitation of the type of entities it can recognise. We can see in Figure 4 that titles and occupations (e.g., king, prince, queen, viceroy, duke, general) were not tagged as this model was not trained to identify them.
</p>
<p>
Due to these entity identification issues related to the specificities of our data, we trained a custom model by providing examples from our corpus. The training process is described in our previous work <ptr target="#Bloch2022"/>, and this new model achieved an overall accuracy of 93,1%. The main drawback of a custom NER model is the time required to select, annotate and train it. However, compared to general pre-trained models, it has several advantages, such as enhanced performance in the problem tackled and the definition of additional entities we wish to identify. For example, besides identifying locations, our custom model can distinguish between masculine and feminine names and identify titles, occupations and different types of organisations (e.g., military and religious).
</p>
<p>
Figure 5 presents the entities recognised in the text shown in Figure 4. We can see in Figure 5 a better identification of people’s names when compared to the pre-trained model. We can also observe that titles and occupations were tagged in the model trained in our data.
Omitting the usage of NER to clean the text or even not disclosing the usage of a custom model impacts the results that can be achieved in the topic modelling stage. Figure 6 shows examples of the impact of not using NER models to filter out irrelevant text elements on the LDA performance. We can see in Figure 6(B) the presence of location names such as “baía”, “espírito_santo” and “maranhao”. Not all documents in those groups are from this location, which can lead to a false interpretation that the other keywords in those groups are related to those places.
</p>

<figure xml:id="figure4">
 	<head>Example of entities tagged by the pre-trained model. The text can be translated as “1777, September 25, Rio de Janeiro OFFICIAL LETTER of the [Viceroy of the State of Brazil], Marquis of Lavradio, [D. Luís de Almeida Portugal Soares de Alarcão Eça e Melo Silva e Mascarenhas], to the [secretary of state for the Navy and Overseas], Martinho de Melo e Castro, about the arrival of the officers from Santa Catarina Island, mentioning his indignation at having submitted to General D. Pedro de Cevallos, although many did not even know what they were signing, because it was not declared to them, unlike what happened in the Colony of Sacramento, in which the governor of the captaincy forced the officers to obey the orders of the Castilians.” We can see in this example that the Marquis of Lavradio’s name was recognised as two different entities.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure4.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<figure xml:id="figure5">
 	<head>Example of entities tagged by the custom-trained model. The text can be translated as “1777, September 25, Rio de Janeiro OFFICIAL LETTER of the [Viceroy of the State of Brazil], Marquis of
Lavradio, [D. Luís de Almeida Portugal Soares de Alarcão Eça e Melo Silva e Mascarenhas], to the [secretary of state for the Navy and Overseas], Martinho de Melo e Castro, about the arrival of the officers from Santa Catarina Island, mentioning his indignation at having submitted to General D. Pedro de Cevallos, although many did not even know what they were signing, because it was not declared to them, unlike what happened in the Colony of Sacramento, in which the governor of the captaincy forced the officers to obey the orders of the Castilians." Note the correct identification of people’s names and recognition of more categories: gender, title, and occupation.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure5.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<figure xml:id="figure6">
 	<head>Examples of the impact of using NER to filter specific entities on the LDA’s performance. (A) results with entities removed and (B) results without removing them. Note in (B) the presence of words irrelevant to characterise the topic, such as “baía”, “maranhao” and “espírito_santo” which refers to locations.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure6.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>
In the last step of our cleaning procedure, we remove stopwords, which are common words often excluded from text-processing applications, such as search engines and NLP tasks. These words are excluded because they typically do not contribute much to a text’s overall meaning or interpretation. They appear so frequently in texts that they do not provide value when analysing or understanding topics’ content. The complete list of stopwords is in the supplementary material. Among the words in this list, we have weekdays, months, interjects, adverbs, and other words not filtered in the previous steps.
</p>
<p>
Figure 7 illustrates a few examples of the topics identified by the LDA model when the stopwords are removed (A) and when they are not (B). We can see in Figure 7 that examples of topics obtained without removing stopwords are dominated by these words that do not add much to the understanding of the main subjective of the groups.
</p>
<p>
As mentioned, a few steps in our preprocessing pipeline are classified as data transformation. These procedures transform the original data into other structures or change the word form. For example, we apply lemmatisation to group the different inflected forms of a word, reducing them to their base or root form — called the lemma <ptr target="#Korenius2004"/>.  — to normalise and simplify the text for analysis and understanding.
 </p>

<figure xml:id="figure7">
 	<head>Examples of the impact of filtering stopwords on the LDA’s performance. (A) results with stopwords removed and (B) results without removing them. Note in (B) the presence of words irrelevant to characterise the topic, such as “letter”, “attachment”, and “confirmation”.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure7.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>
Another example of data transformation applied is the creation of n-grams <ptr target="#Sidorov2014"/>. These are chunks of n consecutive items, such as words, in a sequence of text or speech. They help analyse and model the structure and patterns within language, facilitating tasks like prediction, text generation, and information retrieval. In this work, we leverage the Gensim library <ptr target="#Srinivasa-Desikan2018"/> to generate the set of unigrams and bigrams. The creation of n-grams and lemmatisation can sometimes be classified as feature extraction or feature engineering, depending on the research (Poulston et al., 2015). Regardless of the classification, it is well-established that topic models can benefit from these procedures <ptr target="#Nikolenko2017"/>;<ptr target="#Skorkovska2012"/>;<ptr target="#Poulston2015"/>.
</p>
<p>
The main benefits of the usage of n-grams are related to capturing collocations and improving topic coherence. N-grams, especially bigrams and trigrams, allow the model to identify and group together frequently appearing phrases. Also, single words might have multiple meanings, and by employing n-grams, the model can differentiate between these meanings and create more focused topics. This representation can be particularly valuable if your topics are defined by specific terminology, such as “Espírito Santo" or“Rio de Janeiro", both location names. However, without using n-grams, the model would interpret these terms isolated, leading to inaccurate evaluations of their meaning. For example, “Espírito" and “Santo" (i.e., from Portuguese “Holly" and “Spirit”) could be linked to documents discussing religious matters. While “Rio" and “Janeiro" (i.e. from Portuguese “River" and “January”) could be interpreted as a location and a date.
</p>
<p>
Our pipeline’s last data transformation method is TF-IDF (term frequency-inverse document frequency)— a technique for weighing the importance of words in a document collection. As the name suggests, it comprises two main components: term frequency (TF) and inverse document frequency (IDF). The first gauges how often a word appears in a document relative to its total word count. Words that appear frequently are more important for that particular document. In contrast, IDF estimates how often a word appears across all documents in the collection. The idea behind IDF is that words appearing in many documents are less informative because they don’t distinguish the specific content of a document.
</p>
<p>
By combining these factors, TF-IDF gives higher weights to frequent words within a document but rare across the entire collection. This weighting scheme helps identify the keywords that best characterise the specific topics covered in that document. TF-IDF helps further filter out irrelevant words and emphasise the most informative terms to uncover the underlying themes, leading to more accurate and meaningful topic discovery.
</p>
<p>
We must stress that the adopted preprocessing pipeline was designed to meet the needs of our data, tools, and project goals. Hence, we are not presenting it as a standard process for any topic modelling task on the historical corpus. Instead, by introducing this case study, we aim to provide examples of the preprocessing pipelines, modelling decisions and the impact of each step on the model’s result.
 </p>
<p>
Besides preprocessing, other factors such as model selection and parametrisation also strongly impact results. In the next section, we will explore how we selected the models and parameters, and assessed their performance. 
</p>

<head>4.2. Model Selection, Parametrisation, and Evaluation</head>

<p>
Model selection is challenging since it depends on the characteristics of the data, the problem’s needs, and the resources available. For instance, the length of the text is an important aspect that should be considered while selecting a topic model. Traditional approaches, such as the LDA model, might perform poorly in a corpus of short texts compared to techniques developed specifically for these texts.
</p>
<p>
Figure 8 depicts the distribution of text lengths in our corpus. The original distribution is long-tailed, but for visualisation purposes, we limited the range of the x−axis to the interval [0,200] in (A) and [0,1250] in (B). The truncated data still represent more than 95% of the dataset’s entries. We can see that the average text size in our dataset is 59 words or 361 characters, comparable to datasets of Twitter messages.
</p>

<figure xml:id="figure8">
 	<head>Distribution of the text size in the dataset by number of words (A) and number of characters(B). The average text size in the data is 59 words or 361 characters, comparable to the traditional 280-character limit size of a tweet.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure8.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>
Because our texts are short on average, they were ready for topic modelling right after the preprocessing stage mentioned before. However, for a corpus of long texts, such as book chapters, it can be required to split the text into chunks that will feed the models separately. The primary reasons behind this practice are twofold. First, topic modelling algorithms can be computationally expensive with long texts, and splitting the text into smaller chunks helps decrease the computational complexity of processing the texts. Second, reducing the text size can positively impact the topic coherence (i.e., how well the words within a topic relate to each other semantically). This impact is linked to the possible jumps between different ideas or themes in long texts.
</p>
<p>
However, it is necessary to note that the solution to the text length problem is more complex than splitting the text into the smallest chunk size possible, and there is no one-size-fits-all convention. Using very small chunks of text might not provide enough context for accurate topic identification. Hence, when dealing with corpora of lengthy texts, it is fundamental to perform preliminary results to assess the impact of the text chunk sizes on the topic modelling performance.
</p>
<p>
In our case, this assessment was unnecessary due to the short nature of our text sizes. However, to test the hypotheses that text size can impact the model’s performance and that traditional approaches, such as LDA and LSI, might not perform as well as other models developed to work with short texts, such as the GSDMM, we will perform experiments comparing the performance of these three models on our data using the same preprocessing pipeline. Before presenting the results, we will discuss the model’s evaluation methods.
</p>
<p>
Different approaches to evaluating the quality of the solutions generated can be based on analysing the relevant terms in each topic, distance maps, and metrics. Figure 9 shows examples of these three categories. So far, we have presented examples of topics using word clouds (i.e. representing the most relevant terms in each topic) and visually analysing them. In this approach, we can employ two primary quality evaluation criteria: the number of words overlapping in different groups and the possibility to identify a group’s dominant subject. Hence, good solutions are described as well-defined groups with little to no overlapping terms.
</p>
<p>
Examples of results for LSI, GSDMM, and LDA can be seen, respectively, in Figures 10, 11, and 12. We defined that the models should return 20 groups to assess their capabilities of splitting the corpus into a relatively high number of topics. This approach aimed to obtain several groups with more specific topics rather than a few groups with broader topics. Note that we also investigated the relationship between the number of topics and the quality of the results, which we will discuss later.
</p>

<figure xml:id="figure9">
 	<head>Common forms of assessing the topic modelling results. (A) top relevant terms in each topic, (B) distance map, and (C) metrics. Here, we present the word cloud to represent the most relevant works in a topic, (B) depicts the plot of a distance map based on multidimensional scaling, and (C) shows an example of the Coherence metrics being applied to assess the results of LDA for a different number of topics.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure9.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>
Utilising our evaluation criteria for the word clouds, we can see in Figure 10 that LSI results were the only model that failed to meet both conditions. There are a large number of overlapping terms across groups, such as “catalogue”, “confirmation”, “bay”, “patent”, and “consultation”. Also, it is difficult to determine the relationship between the terms inside each group. However, Figure 11 shows that the GSDMM presented the best results with minimal overlapping relevant words and relatively cohesive topics, while the LDA model had the second-best groups. Though a few terms overlap between different groups in the LDA’s results, Figure 12 indicates that the main issue is the difficulty of interpreting each group’s main topic.
</p>
<p>
Another approach is to use metrics to quantify the performance of the models. The literature offers various metrics to evaluate and support the model selection process <ptr target="#Meaney2023"/>. However, it is essential to notice that a significant percentage of these metrics require a ground truth (i.e., a dataset with the text and their expected groups), which is not always possible. For example, the dataset used in this work does not have the expected topical classification, which restricts the metrics that can be applied.
</p>
<p>
In our experiments, we used the model coherence metric <ptr target="#Meaney2023"/> to measure the interpretability and semantic coherence of the topics produced. This metric outputs values from 0 to 1, in which a higher coherence score typically indicates that words characterising a topic co-occur frequently across the documents in the corpus. Figure 13 shows an application of the coherence metric to evaluate LDA models with different numbers of topics. The idea behind the experiment depicted in Figure 13 is to use the metric to choose the best number of topics. In this approach, the best number of topics will be the one that maximises the metric (e.g., the highest value for the coherence metric). It is also possible to use multiple model evaluation strategies and, for example, combine the use of metrics with the inspections of the top relevant words per topic.
</p>
<p>
Figures 14 and 15 show the characteristics of the groups found for seven (best coherence score) and 20 topics (maximum number tested). We can see in Figure 14 better separations of topics compared to Figure 15. The overlapping of words is also visible in the samples of topics provided in each figure. These samples represent groups in distinct quadrants in the plot; the amount of overlapping of essential words (i.e., large ones) is considerably higher in Figure 15 than in Figure 14.
</p>
<p>
As seen in Figure 13, these model evaluation metrics can also be employed to select the best parametrisation for a given model. In this case, an exhaustive or heuristic search algorithm can find the best or near-best parameters to optimise a given metric. For example, a hyperparameter tunning approach based on a simple exhaustive search can be used to find the best configuration that maximises the model coherence score.
</p>
<figure xml:id="figure10">
 	<head>Example of six groups returned by the LSI algorithm. The complete list is available in the supplementary information. Observe the amount of overlap between different groups, which is a sign of improper splitting.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<figure xml:id="figure11">
 	<head>Example of six groups returned by the GSDMM algorithm. The complete list is available in the supplementary information. Here, we can see a low overlapping between words in different groups, and it is easier to interpret most groups’ general meaning. For example, group 2 seems to have religious topics, group 4 is connected to military issues, and 15 has words related to commerce and trading.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure11.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<figure xml:id="figure12">
 	<head>Example of six groups returned by the LDA algorithm. The complete list is available in the supplementary information. Although there is not much overlap between the words in these groups, extracting the general meaning of the groups is still difficult.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure12.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<figure xml:id="figure13">
 	<head>Example of application of the coherence metric to evaluate the performance of the LDA with different parametrisation. In this case, we analysed the impact of the number of topics on the model performance. According to this metric, the best performance was achieved for seven topics with a coherence score of 0.280.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure13.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>
It is worth noting, however, that this approach has potential issues. First, some metrics do not have a limited range for their output value, so interpreting and comparing the results to other research can be challenging. Second, the interpretation of the metric results is challenging even when it is restricted to an interval. For example, a 0.5 coherence score might be good for one dataset and not enough for another. Lastly, different models have different optimal numbers of topics that maximise the coherence score, as shown in Figure 16. For all these reasons, it is not recommended to rely on a single method for model evaluation.
</p>
<figure xml:id="figure14">
 	<head>Intertopic Distance Map (IDM) for the LDA model with seven groups (maximum coherence score). The word clouds depict examples of the most prominent words in two topics distant from each other in the IDM plot.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure14.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<figure xml:id="figure15">
 	<head>Intertopic Distance Map (IDM) for the LDA model with twenty groups (maximum number tested). The word clouds depict examples of the most prominent words in two topics distant from each other in the IDM plot. Note the high number of cluster overlaps in the IMD and words in the word clouds.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure15.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<figure xml:id="figure16">
 	<head> Best coherence score for the LDA, LSI, and GSDMM. Note the difference not only in the metric value but also in their corresponding number of topics.</head>
<graphic url="resources/images/figure16.png"/>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<head>5. Conclusion: Reproducibility Challenges in Digital History</head>

<p>
In this paper, we have explored the critical role preprocessing and proper documentation have in digital humanities research, using topic modelling as a case study. These often neglected tasks compose the pipeline of digital research, profoundly affecting its reproducibility and transparency: Through our experiments with several topic models, we have demonstrated how variations in preprocessing techniques and the absence of comprehensive documentation can impair the reliability of research outcomes.
</p>
<p>
Reproducibility is a fundamental benchmark in various disciplines and fosters extensive debate. Scholars emphasise the importance of conducting research that others can replicate or validate to ensure its credibility <ptr target="#Peng2011"/>. While this practise is becoming increasingly important <ptr target="#Stodden2014"/>;<ptr target="#Peng2021"/>, the field of digital history presents a particular challenge. As previously mentioned, digital historians often prioritise data collection and visualisation over adequate documentation of the preprocessing stage required for reproducibility.
</p>
<p>
We advocated the necessity for researchers in the digital humanities to carefully consider and document all the preprocessing steps, including the rationale behind each decision, the specific tools, libraries and parameters used, and any modifications made to the original data. Clear and comprehensive documentation enables other researchers to understand, critique, and build upon one’s work. The lack of a golden standard turn these tasks even more valuable – distinct datasets and research goals have their own peculiarities and must be approached in different ways.
</p>
<p>
Referring to the early example of computational analysis of voting data in the House of Commons, Aydelotte summarised the preprocessing stage with a single statement: “I am confident that the information currently stored on my cards is largely accurate” <ptr target="#Aydette1963"/>. However, repeating this experiment or adapting it to our needs seems to be an arduous task or even impossible. Reproducibility involves much more than just repetition and verification, but also an understanding of the meticulous steps that digital historians take to arrive at their results. In examining Padgett and Ansell’s exploration of the rise of the Medici family, to take yet another example, questions naturally arise about the methods they use to organise both published and unpublished sources, as well as their approach to standardising data. These concerns exist not only in cases where the data was extracted manually, but also in automated processes. What lessons can we learn from these experiences and experiments in the field of digital quantitative analysis?
</p>
<p>
Thorough documentation of the preprocessing phase significantly increases data quality and fosters reproducibility. It is important that researchers provide insights into best practises for the manual extraction of data from both unprinted <ptr target="#Antunes2021"/> and printed materials <ptr target="#Ye2022"/>, including analyses of small and large corpora <ptr target="#Elo2020"/>;<ptr target="#Elwert2020"/>. In addition, sharing methods for standardising and cleaning data from existing databases and digital sources <ptr target="#Petz2021"/>. ; <ptr target="#Garaerts2023"/> together with identifying the most useful metadata for specific research purposes <ptr target="#Zbiral2022"/>; <ptr target="#Ravenek2022"/> is a promising way to advance the field of digital history. The question of how researchers engage with sources in different non-English languages <ptr target="#Wittek2011"/>;<ptr target="#Bloch2022"/> can also provide important insights for the broader community of digital historians focusing on non-mainstream materials and incorporating more marginalised archival collections. Collaborative knowledge sharing on these aspects can make an important contribution to digital history methodologies and promote their reproducibility.
</p>
<p>
An exemplary guide to solid preprocessing documentation designed to ensure reproducibility under an open access license can be found in the work done by JiménezBadillo et al. <ptr target="#Jiménez-Badillo2020"/>. The authors meticulously explain their methodology, focusing in particular on geographical text analysis, and describing in detail the individual steps and the challenges encountered in the process. It also provides knowledge about digital research and bridges the gap between data collection and data analysis by explaining what should be done in between.
</p>
<p>
At a time when large amounts of historical data are increasingly being digitised, the quality and reliability of the results depend on the detailed preprocessing of this digital information. From archival records to datasets of digitised manuscripts, best practises of careful data preparation to produce optimal historical analyses are critical. In digital historical research, the effectiveness of subsequent analyses and interpretations is closely linked to the careful preparation and refinement of historical data, making data preprocessing an indispensable foundation for high-quality results in digital historical research.
</p>




<div>
    <head>Data Availability</head>
    <p>
    The paper contains all the necessary information to assess its conclusions. The dataset used is currently being prepared for public release. However, early access can be provided by the authors upon request.
    </p>
</div>

<div>
    <head>Code Availability</head>
    <p>
    Scripts and Notebooks in Python with our analyses and to reproduce the results in this paper will be archived with Zenodo as supplemental material.
    </p>
</div>

<div>
    <head>Acknowledgements</head>
    <p>
    This research is supported by the Polish National Science Centre (Narodowe Centrum Nauki - NCN) grant number 2022/45/B/HS3/00473, project: "Imperial Commoners of Brazil and West Africa (16401822):global history from a correspondence network perspective". The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or manuscript preparation.
    </p>
</div>

<div>
    <head>9	Author Contributions Statement</head>
    <p>
    CS performed the analysis. MB, DVF and AB gathered the data. CS, MB, DVF and AB designed the analysis. All authors discussed the results and contributed to the final manuscript.
    </p>
</div>

<div>
    <head>Competing Interests Statement</head>
    <p>
    The authors declare no competing interests.
    </p>
</div>

</body>
    <back>
      <listBibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Blei2003" label="Blei, David M and Ng, Andrew Y and Jordan, Michael I 2003">
        Blei, David M and Ng, Andrew Y and Jordan, Michael I (2003) 
        <title rend="quotes">Latent dirichlet allocation</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Journal of machine Learning research</title>,
       .Available at:<ref target="https://www.jmlr.org/papers/volume3/blei03a/blei03a.pdf"> https://www.jmlr.org/papers/volume3/blei03a/blei03a.pdf</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Rosario2000" label="Rosario, Barbara 2000">
        Rosario, Barbara (2000) 
        <title rend="quotes">Latent semantic indexing: An overview</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Techn. rep. INFOSYS</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://cs-web.bu.edu/faculty/gkollios/ada17/LectNotes/LSI.PDF"> https://cs-web.bu.edu/faculty/gkollios/ada17/LectNotes/LSI.PDF</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Jianhua2014" label="Jianhua Yin and Jianyong Wang 2014">
        Jianhua Yin and Jianyong Wang (2014) 
        <title rend="quotes">A dirichlet multinomial mixture model-based approach for short text clustering</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 20th ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/2623330.2623715"> https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/2623330.2623715</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Barde2017" label="Barde, Bhagyashree Vyankatrao and Bainwad, Anant Madhavrao 2017">
        Barde, Bhagyashree Vyankatrao and Bainwad, Anant Madhavrao (2017) 
        <title rend="quotes">An overview of topic modeling methods and tools</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">2017 International Conference on Intelligent Computing and Control Systems (ICICCS)</title>,
        745-750.Available at:<ref target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/8250563"> https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/8250563</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Srinivasa-Desikan2018" label="Srinivasa-Desikan, Bhargav 2018">
        Srinivasa-Desikan, Bhargav (2018) 
        <title rend="quotes">Natural Language Processing and Computational Linguistics: A practical guide to text analysis with Python, Gensim, spaCy, and Keras</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Packt Publishing Ltd</title>,
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Mishra2020" label="Mishra, Puneet and Biancolillo, Alessandra and Roger, Jean Michel and Marini, Federico and Rutledge, Douglas N 2020">
        Mishra, Puneet and Biancolillo, Alessandra and Roger, Jean Michel and Marini, Federico and Rutledge, Douglas N (2020) 
        <title rend="quotes">New data preprocessing trends based on ensemble of multiple preprocessing techniques</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">TrAC Trends in Analytical Chemistry</title>,
        132.Available at:<ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0165993620302740"> https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0165993620302740</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Engel2013" label="Engel, Jasper and Gerretzen, Jan and Szymanska, Ewa and Jansen, Jeroen J and Downey, Gerard and Blanchet, Lionel and Buydens, Lutgarde MC 2013">
        Engel, Jasper and Gerretzen, Jan and Szymanska, Ewa and Jansen, Jeroen J and Downey, Gerard and Blanchet, Lionel and Buydens, Lutgarde MC (2013) 
        <title rend="quotes">Breaking with trends in pre-processing?</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">TrAC Trends in Analytical Chemistry</title>,
        50.Available at:<ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0165993613001465"> https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0165993613001465</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Fan2021" label="Fan, Cheng and Chen, Meiling and Wang, Xinghua and Wang, Jiayuan and Huang, Bufu 2021">
        Fan, Cheng and Chen, Meiling and Wang, Xinghua and Wang, Jiayuan and Huang, Bufu (2021) 
        <title rend="quotes">A review on data preprocessing techniques toward efficient and reliable knowledge discovery from building operational data</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Frontiers in Energy Research</title>,
        9.Available at:<ref target="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fenrg.2021.652801/full"> https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fenrg.2021.652801/full</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Rinnan2009" label="Rinnan, Asmund and Van Den Berg, Frans and Engelsen, Soren Balling 2009">
        Rinnan, Asmund and Van Den Berg, Frans and Engelsen, Soren Balling (2009) 
        <title rend="quotes">Review of the most common pre-processing techniques for near-infrared spectra</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">TrAC Trends in Analytical Chemistry</title>,
        28(10).Available at:<ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0165993609001629"> https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0165993609001629</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Lee2017" label="Lee, Loong Chuen and Liong, Choong-Yeun and Jemain, Abdul Aziz 2017">
        Lee, Loong Chuen and Liong, Choong-Yeun and Jemain, Abdul Aziz (2017) 
        <title rend="quotes">A contemporary review on Data Preprocessing (DP) practice strategy in ATR-FTIR spectrum</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Chemometrics and Intelligent Laboratory Systems</title>,
        163.Available at:<ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0169743916305500"> https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0169743916305500</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Joo2000" label="Joo, Dae-Sung and Choi, Dong-Jin and Park, Heekyung 2000">
        Joo, Dae-Sung and Choi, Dong-Jin and Park, Heekyung (2000) 
        <title rend="quotes">The effects of data preprocessing in the determination of coagulant dosing rate</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Water Research</title>,
        34(13).Available at:<ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0043135400000671"> https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0043135400000671</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Alshdaifat2021" label="Alshdaifat, Esra'a and Alshdaifat, Doa'a and Alsarhan, Ayoub and Hussein, Fairouz and El-Salhi, Subhieh Moh'd Faraj S 2021">
        Alshdaifat, Esra'a and Alshdaifat, Doa'a and Alsarhan, Ayoub and Hussein, Fairouz and El-Salhi, Subhieh Moh'd Faraj S (2021) 
        <title rend="quotes">The effect of preprocessing techniques, applied to numeric features, on classification algorithms' performance</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Data</title>,
        6(2).Available at:<ref target="https://www.mdpi.com/2306-5729/6/2/11">https://www.mdpi.com/2306-5729/6/2/11</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Kamiran2012" label="Kamiran, Faisal and Calders, Toon 2012">
        Kamiran, Faisal and Calders, Toon (2012) 
        <title rend="quotes">Data preprocessing techniques for classification without discrimination</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Knowledge and information systems</title>,
        33(1).Available at:<ref target="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10115-011-0463-8"> https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10115-011-0463-8</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Bazjanac2007" label="Bazjanac, Vladimir and Kiviniemi, Arto 2007">
        Bazjanac, Vladimir and Kiviniemi, Arto (2007) 
        <title rend="quotes">Reduction, simplification, translation and interpretation in the exchange of model data</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Cib w</title>,
        78.Available at:<ref target="https://itc.scix.net/pdfs/w78-2007-024-142-Bazjanac.pdf">https://itc.scix.net/pdfs/w78-2007-024-142-Bazjanac.pdf </ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Monroe2013" label="Monroe, Megan and Lan, Rongjian and Lee, Hanseung and Plaisant, Catherine and Shneiderman, Ben 2013">
        Monroe, Megan and Lan, Rongjian and Lee, Hanseung and Plaisant, Catherine and Shneiderman, Ben (2013) 
        <title rend="quotes">Temporal event sequence simplification</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>,
        19(12).Available at:<ref target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/6634100"> https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/6634100</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Xu2020" label="Xu, Yang and Li, Xinyu and Shaw, Shih-Lung and Lu, Feng and Yin, Ling and Chen, Bi Yu 2020">
        Xu, Yang and Li, Xinyu and Shaw, Shih-Lung and Lu, Feng and Yin, Ling and Chen, Bi Yu (2020) 
        <title rend="quotes">Effects of data preprocessing methods on addressing location uncertainty in mobile signaling data</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Annals of the American Association of Geographers</title>,
        111(2).Available at:<ref target="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/24694452.2020.1773232"> https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/24694452.2020.1773232</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Zelaya2019" label="Zelaya, Carlos Vladimiro Gonzalez 2019">
        Zelaya, Carlos Vladimiro Gonzalez (2019) 
        <title rend="quotes">Towards explaining the effects of data preprocessing on machine learning</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">2019 IEEE 35th international conference on data engineering (ICDE)</title>,
        2086-2090.Available at:<ref target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/8731532"> https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/8731532</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Mishra2019" label="Mishra, Puneet and Karami, Azam and Nordon, Alison and Rutledge, Douglas N and Roger, Jean-Michel 2019">
        Mishra, Puneet and Karami, Azam and Nordon, Alison and Rutledge, Douglas N and Roger, Jean-Michel (2019) 
        <title rend="quotes">Automatic de-noising of close-range hyperspectral images with a wavelength-specific shearlet-based image noise reduction method</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Sensors and Actuators B: Chemical</title>,
        281.Available at:<ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0925400518319889">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0925400518319889 </ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Shanker1996" label="Shanker, Murali and Hu, Michael Y and Hung, Ming S 1996">
        Shanker, Murali and Hu, Michael Y and Hung, Ming S (1996) 
        <title rend="quotes">Effect of data standardization on neural network training</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Omega</title>,
        24(4).Available at:<ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0305048396000102"> https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0305048396000102</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Baxter1995" label="Baxter, Michael J 1995">
        Baxter, Michael J (1995) 
        <title rend="quotes">Standardization and transformation in principal component analysis, with applications to archaeometry</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society Series C: Applied Statistics</title>,
        44(4).Available at:<ref target="https://academic.oup.com/jrsssc/article-abstract/44/4/513/6990497"> https://academic.oup.com/jrsssc/article-abstract/44/4/513/6990497</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Cao1999" label="Cao, Yong and Williams, D Dudley and Williams, Nancy E 1999">
        Cao, Yong and Williams, D Dudley and Williams, Nancy E (1999) 
        <title rend="quotes">Data transformation and standardization in the multivariate analysis of river water quality</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Ecological Applications</title>,
        9(2).Available at:<ref target="https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1890/1051-0761%281999%29009%5B0669%3ADTASIT%5D2.0.CO%3B2"> https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1890/1051-0761%281999%29009%5B0669%3ADTASIT%5D2.0.CO%3B2</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Rahm2000" label="Rahm, Erhard and Do, Hong Hai and others 2000">
        Rahm, Erhard and Do, Hong Hai and others (2000) 
        <title rend="quotes">Data cleaning: Problems and current approaches</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">IEEE Data Eng. Bull.</title>,
        23(4).Available at:<ref target="https://cs.brown.edu/courses/cs227/archives/2017/papers/data-cleaning-IEEE.pdf#page=5"> https://cs.brown.edu/courses/cs227/archives/2017/papers/data-cleaning-IEEE.pdf#page=5</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Lelewer1987" label="Lelewer, Debra A and Hirschberg, Daniel S 1987">
        Lelewer, Debra A and Hirschberg, Daniel S (1987) 
        <title rend="quotes">Data compression</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">ACM Computing Surveys (CSUR)</title>,
        19(3).Available at:<ref target="https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/45072.45074"> https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/45072.45074</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Cao2016" label="Cao, Xi Hang and Stojkovic, Ivan and Obradovic, Zoran 2016">
        Cao, Xi Hang and Stojkovic, Ivan and Obradovic, Zoran (2016) 
        <title rend="quotes">A robust data scaling algorithm to improve classification accuracies in biomedical data</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">BMC bioinformatics</title>,
        17(1).Available at:<ref target="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s12859-016-1236-x">https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s12859-016-1236-x </ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Behrens1997" label="Behrens, John T 1997">
        Behrens, John T (1997) 
        <title rend="quotes">Principles and procedures of exploratory data analysis.</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Psychological methods</title>,
        2(2).Available at:<ref target="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/1997-06270-001">https://psycnet.apa.org/record/1997-06270-001 </ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Zhu2016" label="Zhu, Changming and Gao, Daqi 2016">
        Zhu, Changming and Gao, Daqi (2016) 
        <title rend="quotes">Influence of data preprocessing</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Journal of Computing Science and Engineering</title>,
        10(2).Available at:<ref target="https://koreascience.kr/article/JAKO201621650492423.page"> https://koreascience.kr/article/JAKO201621650492423.page</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Burrows2023" label="Burrows, Toby 2023">
        Burrows, Toby (2023) 
        <title rend="quotes">Reproducibility, verifiability, and computational historical research</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Springer</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s42803-023-00068-9"> https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s42803-023-00068-9</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Kesner1982" label="Kesner, Richard M 1982">
        Kesner, Richard M (1982) 
        <title rend="quotes">Historians in the Information Age: Putting the New Technology to Work</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">The Public Historian</title>,
        4(3).Available at:<ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/3377464">https://www.jstor.org/stable/3377464</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Swierenga1974" label="Swierenga, Robert P 1974">
        Swierenga, Robert P (1974) 
        <title rend="quotes">Computers and comparative history</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">The Journal of Interdisciplinary History</title>,
        5(2).Available at:<ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/202509"> https://www.jstor.org/stable/202509</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Aydelotte1963" label="Aydelotte, William O 1963">
        Aydelotte, William O (1963) 
        <title rend="quotes">Voting Patterns in the British House of Commons in the 1840s</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Comparative Studies in Society and History</title>,
        5(2).Available at:<ref target="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/comparative-studies-in-society-and-history/article/abs/voting-patterns-in-the-british-house-of-commons-in-the-1840s/B20A58ED268EFBB9071C0B87C585132B"> https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/comparative-studies-in-society-and-history/article/abs/voting-patterns-in-the-british-house-of-commons-in-the-1840s/B20A58ED268EFBB9071C0B87C585132B</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Padgett1993" label="Padgett, John F and Ansell, Christopher K 1993">
        Padgett, John F and Ansell, Christopher K (1993) 
        <title rend="quotes">Robust Action and the Rise of the Medici, 1400-1434</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">American journal of sociology</title>,
        98(6).Available at:<ref target="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/230190"> https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/230190</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Wetherell1994" label="Wetherell, Charles and Plakans, Andrejs and Wellman, Barry 1994">
        Wetherell, Charles and Plakans, Andrejs and Wellman, Barry (1994) 
        <title rend="quotes">Social networks, kinship, and community in Eastern Europe</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">The Journal of Interdisciplinary History</title>,
        24(4).Available at:<ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/205629"> https://www.jstor.org/stable/205629</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Brook1981" label="Brook, Timothy 1981">
        Brook, Timothy (1981) 
        <title rend="quotes">The Merchant Network in 16th Century China: A Discussion and Translation of Zhang Han's" On Merchants"</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">JSTOR</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://brill.com/display/book/edcoll/9789047412090/Bej.9789004170605.i-454_007.xml"> https://brill.com/display/book/edcoll/9789047412090/Bej.9789004170605.i-454_007.xml</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Bloch2022" label="Bloch, Agata and Vasques Filho, Demival and Bojanowski, Michal 2022">
        Bloch, Agata and Vasques Filho, Demival and Bojanowski, Michal (2022) 
        <title rend="quotes">Networks from archives: Reconstructing networks of official correspondence in the early modern Portuguese empire</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Social Networks</title>,
        69.Available at:<ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0378873320300769"> https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0378873320300769</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Salmi2020" label="Salmi, Hannu 2020">
        Salmi, Hannu (2020) 
        <title rend="quotes">What is digital history?</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">John Wiley &amp; Sons</title>,
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Haggerty2011" label="Haggerty, John and Haggerty, Sheryllynne 2011">
        Haggerty, John and Haggerty, Sheryllynne (2011) 
        <title rend="quotes">The life cycle of a metropolitan business network: Liverpool 1750-1810</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Explorations in Economic History</title>,
        48(2).Available at:<ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0014498310000586"> https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0014498310000586</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Verbruggen2020" label="Verbruggen, Christophe and Blomme, Hans and D'haeninck, Thomas 2020">
        Verbruggen, Christophe and Blomme, Hans and D'haeninck, Thomas (2020) 
        <title rend="quotes">Mobility and movements in intellectual history: a social network approach</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">The Power of Networks</title>,
        125-150.Available at:<ref target="https://www.taylorfrancis.com/chapters/edit/10.4324/9781315189062-8/mobility-movements-intellectual-history-christophe-verbruggen-hans-blomme-thomas-haeninck">https://www.taylorfrancis.com/chapters/edit/10.4324/9781315189062-8/mobility-movements-intellectual-history-christophe-verbruggen-hans-blomme-thomas-haeninck </ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="ANTUNES2021" label="ANTUNES, Anderson PEREIRA 2021">
        ANTUNES, Anderson PEREIRA (2021) 
        <title rend="quotes">Social Network Analysis in the History of Sciences: Visualising Sociability in Scientific Expeditions with Gephi.</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Asociación Argentina de Humanidades Digitales</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://www.arca.fiocruz.br/handle/icict/62071"> https://www.arca.fiocruz.br/handle/icict/62071</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Ye2022" label="Ye, Michelle Jia 2022">
        Ye, Michelle Jia (2022) 
        <title rend="quotes">A history from below: Translators in the publication network of four magazines issued by the China Book Company, 1913-1923</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Translation Studies</title>,
        15(1).Available at:<ref target="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/14781700.2021.1950043"> https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/14781700.2021.1950043</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Wittek2011" label="Wittek, Peter and Ravenek, Walter 2011">
        Wittek, Peter and Ravenek, Walter (2011) 
        <title rend="quotes">Supporting the Exploration of a Corpus of 17th-Century Scholarly Correspondences by Topic Modeling.</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">SDH 2011 Supporting Digital Humanities: Answering the unaskable</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://www.diva-portal.org/smash/record.jsf?pid=diva2%3A887360&amp;dswid=5843"> https://www.diva-portal.org/smash/record.jsf?pid=diva2%3A887360&amp;dswid=5843</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Elwert2020" label="Elwert, Frederik 2020">
        Elwert, Frederik (2020) 
        <title rend="quotes">Social and semantic network analysis in the study of religions</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">The Power of Networks</title>,
        172-186.Available at:<ref target="https://www.taylorfrancis.com/chapters/edit/10.4324/9781315189062-11/social-semantic-network-analysis-study-religions-frederik-elwert"> https://www.taylorfrancis.com/chapters/edit/10.4324/9781315189062-11/social-semantic-network-analysis-study-religions-frederik-elwert</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Petz2021" label="Petz, Cindarella and Pfeffer, Juergen 2021">
        Petz, Cindarella and Pfeffer, Juergen (2021) 
        <title rend="quotes">Configuration to conviction: Network structures of political judiciary in the Austrian Corporate State</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Social Networks</title>,
        66.Available at:<ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S037887332100023X">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S037887332100023X </ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Zbiral2022" label="Zbiral, David and Shaw, Robert LJ 2022">
        Zbiral, David and Shaw, Robert LJ (2022) 
        <title rend="quotes">Hearing Voices: Reapproaching Medieval Inquisition Records</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Religions</title>,
        13(12).Available at:<ref target="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-1444/13/12/1175"> https://www.mdpi.com/2077-1444/13/12/1175</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Elo2020" label="Elo, Kimmo 2020">
        Elo, Kimmo (2020) 
        <title rend="quotes">Utilizing historical network analysis on meta-data to model East German foreign intelligence cycle in the Baltic Sea Region 1975-89</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">The Power of Networks</title>,
        153-171.Available at:<ref target="https://www.taylorfrancis.com/chapters/edit/10.4324/9781315189062-10/utilizing-historical-network-analysis-meta-data-model-east-german-foreign-intelligence-cycle-baltic-sea-region-1975–89-kimmo-elo"> https://www.taylorfrancis.com/chapters/edit/10.4324/9781315189062-10/utilizing-historical-network-analysis-meta-data-model-east-german-foreign-intelligence-cycle-baltic-sea-region-1975–89-kimmo-elo</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Brauer2013" label="Brauer, Rene and Fridlund, Mats 2013">
        Brauer, Rene and Fridlund, Mats (2013) 
        <title rend="quotes">Historicizing topic models, a distant reading of topic modeling texts within historical studies</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">International Conference on Cultural Research in the context of "Digital Humanities", St. Petersburg: Russian State Herzen University</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://acris.aalto.fi/ws/portalfiles/portal/7085738/PUBL2013brauerfridlundConf_libre.pdf"> https://acris.aalto.fi/ws/portalfiles/portal/7085738/PUBL2013brauerfridlundConf_libre.pdf</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Ravenek2017" label="Ravenek, Walter and van den Heuvel, Charles and Gerritsen, Guido 2017">
        Ravenek, Walter and van den Heuvel, Charles and Gerritsen, Guido (2017) 
        <title rend="quotes">The ePistolarium: origins and techniques</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Ubiquity Press London</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://ubiquitypress.com/site/chapters/10.5334/bbi.26/download/1042/"> https://ubiquitypress.com/site/chapters/10.5334/bbi.26/download/1042/</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Jentsch2021" label="Jentsch, Patrick and Porada, Stephan 2021">
        Jentsch, Patrick and Porada, Stephan (2021) 
        <title rend="quotes">From Text to Data. Digitization, Text Analysis and Corpus Linguistics</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Digital Methods in the Humanities. Challenges, Ideas, Perspectives</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://www.transcript-open.de/doi/10.14361/9783839454190-004?html"> https://www.transcript-open.de/doi/10.14361/9783839454190-004?html</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Kunilovskaya2021" label="Kunilovskaya, Maria and Plum, Alistair 2021">
        Kunilovskaya, Maria and Plum, Alistair (2021) 
        <title rend="quotes">Text preprocessing and its implications in a digital humanities project</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Student Research Workshop Associated with RANLP 2021</title>,
        85-93.Available at:<ref target="https://aclanthology.org/2021.ranlp-srw.13/"> https://aclanthology.org/2021.ranlp-srw.13/</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Garcia2016" label="Garcia, Salvador and Ramirez-Gallego, Sergio and Luengo, Julian and Benitez, Jose Manuel and Herrera, Francisco 2016">
        Garcia, Salvador and Ramirez-Gallego, Sergio and Luengo, Julian and Benitez, Jose Manuel and Herrera, Francisco (2016) 
        <title rend="quotes">Big data preprocessing: methods and prospects</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Big Data Analytics</title>,
        1(1).Available at:<ref target="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s41044-016-0014-0">https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s41044-016-0014-0 </ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Matthew2020" label="Matthew, Laura and Bannister, Michael 2020">
        Matthew, Laura and Bannister, Michael (2020) 
        <title rend="quotes">The Form of the Content: The Digital Archive Nahuatl/Nawat in Central America</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/4/000491/000491.html"> https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/4/000491/000491.html</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Curran2018" label="Curran, Ben and Higham, Kyle and Ortiz, Elisenda and Vasques Filho, Demival 2018">
        Curran, Ben and Higham, Kyle and Ortiz, Elisenda and Vasques Filho, Demival (2018) 
        <title rend="quotes">Look who's talking: Two-mode networks as representations of a topic model of New Zealand parliamentary speeches</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">PloS one</title>,
        13(6).Available at:<ref target="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0199072"> https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0199072</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Broadwell2020" label="Broadwell, George Aaron and Garcia Guzman, Moises and Lillehaugen, Brook Danielle and Lopez, Felipe H and Plumb, May Helena and Zarafonetis, Mike 2020">
        Broadwell, George Aaron and Garcia Guzman, Moises and Lillehaugen, Brook Danielle and Lopez, Felipe H and Plumb, May Helena and Zarafonetis, Mike (2020) 
        <title rend="quotes">Ticha: Collaboration with Indigenous communities to build digital resources on Zapotec language and history.</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1L_NgqepWEHlHDPv3RCX-v71AnMVa_rum/view"> https://drive.google.com/file/d/1L_NgqepWEHlHDPv3RCX-v71AnMVa_rum/view</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Peng2011" label="Peng, Roger D 2011">
        Peng, Roger D (2011) 
        <title rend="quotes">Reproducible research in computational science</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Science</title>,
        334(6060).Available at:<ref target="https://www.science.org/doi/abs/10.1126/science.1213847"> https://www.science.org/doi/abs/10.1126/science.1213847</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Stodden2014" label="Stodden, Victoria and Leisch, Friedrich and Peng, Roger D 2014">
        Stodden, Victoria and Leisch, Friedrich and Peng, Roger D (2014) 
        <title rend="quotes">Implementing reproducible research</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">CRC Press</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://api.taylorfrancis.com/content/books/mono/download?identifierName=doi&amp;identifierValue=10.1201/9781315373461&amp;type=googlepdf"> https://api.taylorfrancis.com/content/books/mono/download?identifierName=doi&amp;identifierValue=10.1201/9781315373461&amp;type=googlepdf</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Peng2021" label="Peng, Roger D and Hicks, Stephanie C 2021">
        Peng, Roger D and Hicks, Stephanie C (2021) 
        <title rend="quotes">Reproducible research: a retrospective</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Annual review of public health</title>,
        42.Available at:<ref target="https://www.annualreviews.org/content/journals/10.1146/annurev-publhealth-012420-105110"> https://www.annualreviews.org/content/journals/10.1146/annurev-publhealth-012420-105110</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Jimenez-Badillo2020" label="Jimenez-Badillo, Diego and Murrieta-Flores, Patricia and Martins, Bruno and Gregory, Ian and Favila-Vazquez, Mariana and Liceras-Garrido, Raquel 2020">
        Jimenez-Badillo, Diego and Murrieta-Flores, Patricia and Martins, Bruno and Gregory, Ian and Favila-Vazquez, Mariana and Liceras-Garrido, Raquel (2020) 
        <title rend="quotes">Developing Geographically Oriented NLP Approaches to Sixteenth-Century Historical Documents: Digging into Early Colonial Mexico</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>,
        14(4).Available at:<ref target="https://www.proquest.com/openview/597bb1a0d1b948254b5afd810b7e58f4/1?pq-origsite=gscholar&amp;cbl=5124193"> https://www.proquest.com/openview/597bb1a0d1b948254b5afd810b7e58f4/1?pq-origsite=gscholar&amp;cbl=5124193</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Nadeau2007" label="Nadeau, David and Sekine, Satoshi 2007">
        Nadeau, David and Sekine, Satoshi (2007) 
        <title rend="quotes">A survey of named entity recognition and classification</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Lingvisticae Investigationes</title>,
        30(1).Available at:<ref target="https://www.jbe-platform.com/content/journals/10.1075/li.30.1.03nad">https://www.jbe-platform.com/content/journals/10.1075/li.30.1.03nad </ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Geraerts2023" label="Geraerts, Jaap and Vasques Filho, Demival 2023">
        Geraerts, Jaap and Vasques Filho, Demival (2023) 
        <title rend="quotes">Networks of confessional affiliation: {R}eligious choice and the schism of {U}trecht</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Journal of Historical Network Research</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://graphentechnologien.hypotheses.org/files/2022/01/Religious_choice_and_the_Schism_of_etc-Geraerts_Filho.pdf"> https://graphentechnologien.hypotheses.org/files/2022/01/Religious_choice_and_the_Schism_of_etc-Geraerts_Filho.pdf</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Bloch2024" label="Bloch, Agata and Santana, Clodomir and Bojanowski, Michal and Vasques Filho, Demival 2024">
        Bloch, Agata and Santana, Clodomir and Bojanowski, Michal and Vasques Filho, Demival (2024) 
        <title rend="quotes">Cracking the historical code:
        {F}rom unstructured correspondence corpora to computational analysis</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Models of data extraction and architecture in relational databases of early modern private political archives</title>,
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Bloch2021" label="Bloch, Agata and Vasques Filho, Demival and Bojanowski, Michal 2021">
        Bloch, Agata and Vasques Filho, Demival and Bojanowski, Michal (2021) 
        <title rend="quotes">Slaves, {F}reedmen, {M}ulattos, {P}ardos, and {I}ndigenous {P}eoples - {T}he {E}arly {M}odern social networks of the population of color in the {A}tlantic {P}ortuguese {E}mpire</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">The Digital Black Atlantic</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://muse.jhu.edu/pub/23/oa_edited_volume/book/84470/pdf#page=176"> https://muse.jhu.edu/pub/23/oa_edited_volume/book/84470/pdf#page=176</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Meaney2023" label="Meaney, Christopher and Stukel, Therese A and Austin, Peter C and Moineddin, Rahim and Greiver, Michelle and Escobar, Michael 2023">
        Meaney, Christopher and Stukel, Therese A and Austin, Peter C and Moineddin, Rahim and Greiver, Michelle and Escobar, Michael (2023) 
        <title rend="quotes">Quality indices for topic model selection and evaluation: a literature review and case study</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making</title>,
        23(1).Available at:<ref target="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s12911-023-02216-1"> https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s12911-023-02216-1</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Korenius2004" label="Korenius, Tuomo and Laurikkala, Jorma and Jarvelin, Kalervo and Juhola, Martti 2004">
        Korenius, Tuomo and Laurikkala, Jorma and Jarvelin, Kalervo and Juhola, Martti (2004) 
        <title rend="quotes">Stemming and lemmatization in the clustering of finnish text documents</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the thirteenth ACM international conference on Information and knowledge management</title>,
        625-633.Available at:<ref target="https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/1031171.1031285"> https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/1031171.1031285</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Sidorov2014" label="Sidorov, Grigori and Velasquez, Francisco and Stamatatos, Efstathios and Gelbukh, Alexander and Chanona-Hernandez, Liliana 2014">
        Sidorov, Grigori and Velasquez, Francisco and Stamatatos, Efstathios and Gelbukh, Alexander and Chanona-Hernandez, Liliana (2014) 
        <title rend="quotes">Syntactic n-grams as machine learning features for natural language processing</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Expert Systems with Applications</title>,
        41(3).Available at:<ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0957417413006271"> https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0957417413006271</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Skorkovska2012" label="Skorkovska, Lucie 2012">
        Skorkovska, Lucie (2012) 
        <title rend="quotes">Application of lemmatization and summarization methods in topic identification module for large scale language modeling data filtering</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Text, Speech and Dialogue: 15th International Conference, TSD 2012, Brno, Czech Republic, September 3-7, 2012. Proceedings 15</title>,
        191-198.Available at:<ref target="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-642-32790-2_23"> https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-642-32790-2_23</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Nikolenko2017" label="Nikolenko, Sergey I and Koltcov, Sergei and Koltsova, Olessia 2017">
        Nikolenko, Sergey I and Koltcov, Sergei and Koltsova, Olessia (2017) 
        <title rend="quotes">Topic modelling for qualitative studies</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Journal of Information Science</title>,
        43(1).Available at:<ref target="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0165551515617393"> https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0165551515617393</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Poulston2015" label="Poulston, Adam and Stevenson, Mark and Bontcheva, Kalina 2015">
        Poulston, Adam and Stevenson, Mark and Bontcheva, Kalina (2015) 
        <title rend="quotes">Topic models and n-gram language models for author profiling</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Proceedings of CLEF</title>,
        1391.Available at:<ref target="https://downloads.webis.de/pan/publications/papers/poulston_2015.pdf"> https://downloads.webis.de/pan/publications/papers/poulston_2015.pdf</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Budroni2019" label="Budroni, Paolo and Claude-Burgelman, Jean and Schouppe, Michel 2019">
        Budroni, Paolo and Claude-Burgelman, Jean and Schouppe, Michel (2019) 
        <title rend="quotes">Architectures of knowledge: the European open science cloud</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">ABI Technik</title>,
        39(2).Available at:<ref target="https://www.degruyter.com/document/doi/10.1515/abitech-2019-2006/html"> https://www.degruyter.com/document/doi/10.1515/abitech-2019-2006/html</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Blank2004" label="Blank, Grant and Rasmussen, Karsten Boye 2004">
        Blank, Grant and Rasmussen, Karsten Boye (2004) 
        <title rend="quotes">The data documentation initiative: the value and significance of a worldwide standard</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Social Science Computer Review</title>,
        22(3).Available at:<ref target="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0894439304263144"> https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0894439304263144</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Rasmussen2007" label="Rasmussen, Karsten Boye and Blank, Grant 2007">
        Rasmussen, Karsten Boye and Blank, Grant (2007) 
        <title rend="quotes">The data documentation initiative: a preservation standard for research</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Archival Science</title>,
        7.Available at:<ref target="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10502-006-9036-0"> https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10502-006-9036-0</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Jacobsen2020" label="Jacobsen, Annika and de Miranda Azevedo, Ricardo and Juty, Nick and Batista, Dominique and Coles, Simon and Cornet, Ronald and Courtot, Melanie and Crosas, Merce and Dumontier, Michel and Evelo, Chris T and others 2020">
        Jacobsen, Annika and de Miranda Azevedo, Ricardo and Juty, Nick and Batista, Dominique and Coles, Simon and Cornet, Ronald and Courtot, Melanie and Crosas, Merce and Dumontier, Michel and Evelo, Chris T and others (2020) 
        <title rend="quotes">FAIR principles: interpretations and implementation considerations</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Data intelligence</title>,
        2(1-2).Available at:<ref target="FAIR principles: interpretations and implementation considerations">FAIR principles: interpretations and implementation considerations </ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Lamprecht2020" label="Lamprecht, Anna-Lena and Garcia, Leyla and Kuzak, Mateusz and Martinez, Carlos and Arcila, Ricardo and Martin Del Pico, Eva and Dominguez Del Angel, Victoria and Van De Sandt, Stephanie and Ison, Jon and Martinez, Paula Andrea and others 2020">
        Lamprecht, Anna-Lena and Garcia, Leyla and Kuzak, Mateusz and Martinez, Carlos and Arcila, Ricardo and Martin Del Pico, Eva and Dominguez Del Angel, Victoria and Van De Sandt, Stephanie and Ison, Jon and Martinez, Paula Andrea and others (2020) 
        <title rend="quotes">Towards FAIR principles for research software</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Data Science</title>,
        3(1).Available at:<ref target="https://content.iospress.com/articles/data-science/ds190026"> https://content.iospress.com/articles/data-science/ds190026</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Gorgolewski2016" label="Gorgolewski, Krzysztof J and Poldrack, Russell A 2016">
        Gorgolewski, Krzysztof J and Poldrack, Russell A (2016) 
        <title rend="quotes">A practical guide for improving transparency and reproducibility in neuroimaging research</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">PLoS biology</title>,
        14(7).Available at:<ref target="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.1002506"> https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.1002506</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Gibert2016" label="Gibert, Karina and Sanchez-Marre, Miquel and Izquierdo, Joaquin 2016">
        Gibert, Karina and Sanchez-Marre, Miquel and Izquierdo, Joaquin (2016) 
        <title rend="quotes">A survey on pre-processing techniques: Relevant issues in the context of environmental data mining</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">AI Communications</title>,
        29(6).Available at:<ref target="https://content.iospress.com/articles/ai-communications/aic710"> https://content.iospress.com/articles/ai-communications/aic710</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Haibe-Kains2020" label="Haibe-Kains, Benjamin and Adam, George Alexandru and Hosny, Ahmed and Khodakarami, Farnoosh and Massive Analysis Quality Control (MAQC) Society Board of Directors Shraddha Thakkar 35 Kusko Rebecca 36 Sansone Susanna-Assunta 37 Tong Weida 35 Wolfinger Russ D. 38 Mason Christopher E. 39 Jones Wendell 40 Dopazo Joaquin 41 Furlanello Cesare 42 and Waldron, Levi and Wang, Bo and McIntosh, Chris and Goldenberg, Anna and Kundaje, Anshul and others 2020">
        Haibe-Kains, Benjamin and Adam, George Alexandru and Hosny, Ahmed and Khodakarami, Farnoosh and Massive Analysis Quality Control (MAQC) Society Board of Directors Shraddha Thakkar 35 Kusko Rebecca 36 Sansone Susanna-Assunta 37 Tong Weida 35 Wolfinger Russ D. 38 Mason Christopher E. 39 Jones Wendell 40 Dopazo Joaquin 41 Furlanello Cesare 42 and Waldron, Levi and Wang, Bo and McIntosh, Chris and Goldenberg, Anna and Kundaje, Anshul and others (2020) 
        <title rend="quotes">Transparency and reproducibility in artificial intelligence</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Nature</title>,
        586(7829).Available at:<ref target="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-020-2766-y">https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-020-2766-y </ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Chirigati2016" label="Chirigati, Fernando and Rampin, Remi and Shasha, Dennis and Freire, Juliana 2016">
        Chirigati, Fernando and Rampin, Remi and Shasha, Dennis and Freire, Juliana (2016) 
        <title rend="quotes">Reprozip: Computational reproducibility with ease</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2016 international conference on management of data</title>,
        2085-2088.Available at:<ref target="https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/2882903.2899401"> https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/2882903.2899401</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Linkevicius2022" label="Linkevicius de Andrade, Daniela and Vasques Filho, Demival 2022">
        Linkevicius de Andrade, Daniela and Vasques Filho, Demival (2022) 
        <title rend="quotes">Moderation and authority-building process: the dynamics of knowledge creation on history subreddits</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Internet Histories</title>,
        6(4).Available at:<ref target="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/24701475.2022.2110564"> https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/24701475.2022.2110564</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Pettersson2016" label="Pettersson, Eva and Lindstrom, Jonas and Jacobsson, Benny and Fiebranz, Rosemarie 2016">
        Pettersson, Eva and Lindstrom, Jonas and Jacobsson, Benny and Fiebranz, Rosemarie (2016) 
        <title rend="quotes">HistSearch-Implementation and Evaluation of a Web-based Tool for Automatic Information Extraction from Historical Text.</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">HistoInformatics@ DH</title>,
        25-36.Available at:<ref target="https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-1632/paper_4.pdf"> https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-1632/paper_4.pdf</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Klingner2023" label="Klingner, Carsten M and Denker, Michael and Grun, Sonja and Hanke, Michael and Oeltze-Jafra, Steffen and Ohl, Frank W and Radny, Janina and Rotter, Stefan and Scherberger, Hansjorg and Stein, Alexandra and others 2023">
        Klingner, Carsten M and Denker, Michael and Grun, Sonja and Hanke, Michael and Oeltze-Jafra, Steffen and Ohl, Frank W and Radny, Janina and Rotter, Stefan and Scherberger, Hansjorg and Stein, Alexandra and others (2023) 
        <title rend="quotes">Research Data Management and Data Sharing for Reproducible Research—Results of a Community Survey of the German National Research Data Infrastructure Initiative Neuroscience</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">eneuro</title>,
        10(2).Available at:<ref target="https://www.eneuro.org/content/10/2/eneuro.0215-22.2023.abstract"> https://www.eneuro.org/content/10/2/eneuro.0215-22.2023.abstract</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="spaCy2024" label="spaCy 2024">
        spaCy (2024) 
        <title rend="quotes">pt_core_news_lg</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Hugging Face</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://huggingface.co/spacy/pt_core_news_lg"> https://huggingface.co/spacy/pt_core_news_lg</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="DDI2024a" label="DDI Initiative 2024">
        DDI Initiative (2024) 
        <title rend="quotes">DDI - Lifecycle</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">DDI</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Lifecycle"> https://ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Lifecycle</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="DDI2024b" label="DDI Initiative 2024">
        DDI Initiative (2024) 
        <title rend="quotes">DDI - Codebook</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">DDI</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Codebook"> https://ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Codebook</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="DDI2024c" label="DDI Initiative 2024">
        DDI Initiative (2024) 
        <title rend="quotes">DDI - Overview of Current Products</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">DDI</title>,
        .Available at:<ref target="https://ddialliance.org/products/overview-of-current-products"> https://ddialliance.org/products/overview-of-current-products</ref>
        .
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="Tukey1977" label="Tukey, John W and others 1977">
        Tukey, John W and others 1977
        <title rend="quotes">Exploratory Data Analysis</title>, 
        <title rend="italic">Addison-Wesley</title>,
        .
        </bibl>
      </listBibl>                  
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
