<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Diachronic trends in Homeric translations</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Yuri <dhq:family>Bizzoni</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Gothenburg</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>yuri.bizzoni@gu.se</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Yuri Bizzoni studied Classical Philology during his Bachelor programme
                            and Computational Linguistics for his Master's. He worked on tools for
                            literary translation alignment and diachronic translation analysis,
                            particularly on Homeric translations in Italian and French. Yuri is
                            currently a CLASP PhD student. His research focuses on figurative
                            language detection and interpretation in NLP, from a probabilistic
                            angle. </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Marianne <dhq:family>Reboul</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Université Paris-Sorbonne</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>marianne.reboul@free.fr</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Marianne Reboul is a PhD candidate in France in Comparative Literature,
                            currently working in Digital Humanities at the Sorbonne. She has a
                            Masters Degree and Agrégation in Classics, and is a self-taught
                            programmer in several languages, such as Java and Python. Her Master's
                            thesis was a dynamic digitized translation and explanation of the IXth
                            book of Homer’s Odyssey, and her PhD is entitled «Automatic comparison
                            of French translations of Homer’s Odyssey, from 1541 to 2008»</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Angelo <dhq:family>Del Grosso</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Institute for Computational Liguistics A.
                        Zampolli</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>angelo.delgrosso@ilc.cnr.it</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Angelo Mario Del Grosso is a computer engineer with a Ph.D. in
                            information engineering. He obtained his degree in 2015 with a thesis
                            entitled “Designing a library of Component for Textual Scholarship” from
                            the University of Pisa. Since 2010, he has been working as a research
                            fellow at the Institute of Computational Linguistics “A. Zampolli” of
                            CNR (ILC-CNR). He has been involved in a number of different national
                            and international Digital Humanities projects. His main research
                            interests encompass: Object-Oriented approaches for modeling Abstract
                            Data Types characterizing, in general, the DH domain and, in particular,
                            the requirements of textual scholarship; Analysis, design and
                            development of software components for linguistic and philological
                            applications to process textual resources of ancient texts, medieval
                            tradition, printed tradition, and to handle modern and contemporary
                            authors.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000297</idno>
                <idno type="volume">011</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2017-05-22">22 May 2017</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2017-04-06" who="JDF">Proofread file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>In this paper we intend to present a tool we developed for translation studies
                    and diachronically compare various French translations of the <title
                        rend="italic">Odyssey</title>. </p>
                <p>This field of study is part of the more general <q>Classical Receptions</q>
                    studies that try to analyse the influence and adaptation of classical texts in
                    modern and contemporary literature, theatre, cinema, and many other artistic
                    fields. While Greek texts have been analysed by scholars for more than two
                    thousand years, research about classical translations is not yet a most renown
                    subject. In recent years this theme has raised a growing interest in the
                    academic community. </p>
                <p>We developed a program that can align textual sequences (defined as groups of
                    words delimited by a specified grammatical pivot, in our case proper nouns),
                    without need of previous training. We obtained alignments for many different
                    kinds of translations<note>Even free translations, a problem that wasn’t
                        generally considered by textual aligners since recent studies</note>. While
                    other programs have an upper bound for one-to-many alignments (for example with
                    a maximum of four translated elements aligned to the same original element) this
                    algorithm allows an indefinite number of alignments, both for the source
                    sequences and the target ones. The aligner is based on an implementation of
                    Needleman-Wunsch algorithm and on a string-based similarity approach to textual
                    segments. The aligner needs to establish proper names as anchor words, as they
                    are a relatively stable feature through different translations and tend to be
                    similar in several languages. </p>
                <p>Thanks to the alignments obtained using the program, we can explore translations
                    in a number of ways. We will illustrate the creation of a graphical interface to
                    visualize French Homeric translations. </p>
                <p>With our tool, it is possible to highlight aligned portions of texts and show
                    their immediate differences or similarities, both in meaning and in syntactic
                    distribution. </p>
                <p>We will show some resulting syntactic analyses carried out on a small sample of
                    texts, taken from a corpus of twenty-seven unabridged French translations of the
                    Odyssey and explore how the study of diachronic translations through algorithms
                    of computational linguistics can produce interesting results for literary and
                    linguistic studies. </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Presenting a tool developed for translation studies</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>

            <div>
                <head>Background</head>
                <p>The <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> can be considered as one of the major
                    pillars of modern literature. It has been translated in all major Indo-European
                    languages for many centuries. We created a digital corpus of fifty French
                    translations from the 16th century to the 20th for a total of 207 translations
                    and reprints. In this paper we shall try to demonstrate how trends and literary
                    movements could be analysed using the immediate statistic results and
                    visualizations that we obtained with our tool. This paper will focus on a sample
                    of the whole corpus. </p>
                <p>This paper focuses on the XIth book. This book is a very well known episode of
                    the <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title>, often called the <foreign
                        xml:lang="el">nekuia</foreign>, containing a dialog with the dead (slightly
                    different, for example, from the <foreign xml:lang="el">katabasis</foreign>, an
                    actual descent into Hell). It is also a key episode for translators. In France,
                    from the 16th to the 20th century, the three most translated books were the Ist,
                    the VIth and the XIth. Throughout our research, we have identified three kinds
                    of translations: translations made for scholastic readers who specialize in
                    Ancient Literature, translations made for school use, for students who need to
                    learn about Greek Literature and translations that appear as a kind of stylistic
                    exercise, and often an echo or an announcement of future works. The XIth book is
                    also interesting because every translator who chose to translate it went on to
                    translate the whole of the <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title>. It often seems
                    to be a trial book, a book to test and improve literary skills and style. As a
                    result, we could sketch the translator’s virtual portrait: every single
                    translator of the XIth book has, sooner or later, devoted himself to defending
                    the literary value of Ancient Literature, and more precisely, every one of them
                    has seen in the Ancient corpus a source for inspiration, a stylistic potential
                    to unravel. That is why this particular book was chosen.</p>
                <p>Concerning the Greek pivot text, it is based on the Greek text established by
                    Allen and Monro <ptr target="#monro1902"/>, as it is the most widely used
                    representation of the Greek text, both before and after the 19th century. Monro
                    and Allen are also most familiar with the whole vulgate around Homer, and
                    include many variants from Eustathius, often considered as the most precious
                    source for reconstructing Homeric epics in Greek (since the
                        <emph>princeps</emph> edition of his commentaries in 1542). </p>
                <p>To analyse trends or literary tendencies, the use of alignment and
                    post-processing algorithms appeared as a novelty. Many works already have been
                    made on aligning translations to their original texts (see for example <ptr
                        target="#dechelotte2007"/>; <ptr target="#brown2003"/>; <ptr
                        target="#gale1991"/>) but they focused on synchronic, non-literary corpora.
                    In literary studies, on the other hand, the necessity of textual alignment
                    appeared for two reasons: scholars wanted to evaluate a translation by
                    considering its source and to create a possible alternative to that translation.
                    As a result, the translation itself as a work of art remained underestimated.
                    Aligning translations gives the art of translation its rightful place: an
                    authentic literary experience, considering the translation itself as an object
                    of art and study. We therefore decided to focus on dividing and aligning each
                    translation, in order to identify possible stylistic trends and possible echoes
                    of the literary world of the translator. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Automatic Alignment Method</head>
                <p>Since segment alignment is widely considered a necessary step in order to proceed
                    toward any kind of word alignment attempt <ptr target="#allauzen2009"/>; <ptr
                        target="#gao2008"/>; <ptr target="#gao2011"/>, using a good global aligner
                    is regarded as an important prerequisite for many studies about automatic
                    translation. </p>
                <p>To align our translations to the original text we wrote a Java implementation of
                    the Needleman-Wunsch algorithm<note>The design of the aligner component
                        emphasizes a number of general software design principles. In particular,
                        two aspects characterize the process of such a design: 1) considering and
                        putting into effect general and proven solutions to recurring design
                        problems (see design patterns, <ptr target="#gamma1995"/>), and 2) taking
                        into account suitable Application Programming Interfaces (APIs) as the
                        actual means to separate services from the implementation details <ptr
                            target="#tulach2008"/>; <ptr target="#henning2009"/>. As a result, the
                        component tries to achieve a high degree of extensibility with a low degree
                        of modification (see Open-Close principle in <ptr target="#robert2000"/>).
                        By doing so, the clients of the aligner module have to work only with the
                        Abstract Data Types (ADTs) which have no part in the implementation
                        mechanisms <ptr target="#gabbrielli2010"/>. Consequently users rely only on
                        well-defined Application Programming Interfaces (APIs) which are exported by
                        the component implementation.</note>. The Needleman-Wunsch algorithm <ptr
                        target="#needleman1970"/> was originally designed to align the amino acid
                    sequences of two proteins. This algorithm is expensive in terms of computational
                    complexity and efficiency of the procedure but remains a tool of the highest
                    quality to perform global alignment. </p>
                <p>There have been several attempts to adapt the Needleman-Wunsch algorithm for use
                    in the field of text processing and digital humanities. To cite some of the most
                    recent cases, it has been used to perform phonetic alignments in historical
                    linguistics (see <ptr target="#list2013"/> for an overview), to perform
                    character-based detection of text similarities <ptr target="#gomaa2013"/>, to
                    validate claims of structural affinity in narrative <ptr target="#reiter2014"/>
                    and to detect similar URLs <ptr target="#germann2016"/>. It is sometimes used in
                    tasks of monolingual text alignment in combination with other systems <ptr
                        target="#nelken2006"/>. Since the algorithm in itself is designed to
                    globally align sequences of any kind, its implementations are different in every
                    case. What changes is usually the tokenization of the sequences, (these can be
                    divided in letters, words, or textual blocks as we see here), and the similarity
                    score used to decide whether two elements should be aligned or not. </p>
                <p>In our case, we re-purposed the Needleman-Wunsch structure to align bilingual
                    portions of text. Through the process described in the following pages we
                    globally aligned the XIth book of the <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> with
                    several translations. Such an alignment allows several types of statistical
                    valuations impossible to perform otherwise: these include an analysis of how far
                    the translations deviate from the original, quantify the cases of lacunary texts
                    and start building word-to-word alignments that might show the variations of
                    preferential translations through time. At the least, such a tool can help a
                    scholar finding quantitative data to support or dispute a translational claim. </p>
                <p>Although applying this algorithm to non-biological sequences is not a novelty, to
                    the best of our knowledge there has been no previous application of the
                    Needleman-Wunsch algorithm to translation alignment and diachronic translation
                    study. </p>
                <p>Simply put, the Needleman-Wunsch algorithm tries to align two sequences of
                    comparable length. Given that each sequence is divided into an arbitrary number
                    of elements, such as words or letters for a sentence, the task of the algorithm
                    is to optimally match the elements of the two sequences. </p>
                <p>To perform this operation the algorithm records each possible match between the
                    elements of the two sequences in a grid-like structure, and assigns a score to
                    each combination. This score is usually computed through a matching rule: for
                    example, two identical words are a better match than two totally different
                    words. The cost of leaving a gap if the system doesn’t find any good matches for
                    a sequence’s element is also taken into consideration. Once this grid is built
                    and filled with scores, the algorithm is able to trace back the optimal (e.g.
                    least expensive) path through it, as can be seen in Figure 1. </p>
                <p>An <q>ideal</q> path would be a perfect diagonal, and the algorithm tries to
                    diverge the least from such a path, given the differences between the sequences
                    and the similarity heuristics it uses. This process results in the optimal
                    global alignment of the sequences. </p>
                <p>Figure 2 shows an example of global alignment of two strings performed through
                    the Needleman-Wunsch. If an element could not be aligned, the algorithm will
                    insert a <emph>gap</emph>. </p>
                <p>Since we study translations of comparable length, this approach seems reasonable.
                    As we will detail later, we pass to the algorithm our texts divided in small
                    blocks and we provide it with an ad hoc similarity function. We perform the
                    alignment twice, so that we are able to refine the similarity function for the
                    second alignment through the results of the first alignment. The result is a
                    sequence of small, aligned blocks in one or two languages that can be used as a
                    basis for in-depth quantitative analysis of translation corpora. </p>
                <!--Here goes Figure [figure01.jpg]-->
                <figure>
                    <head>An example of the Needleman-Wunsch grid and an optimal alignment</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>
                <!--Here goes Figure [figure02.jpg]-->
                <figure>
                    <head>An example of a Needleman-Wunsch alignment of two strings</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                </figure>

                <p>In our case, the main problem was the necessity to align long and non-segmented
                    texts with translations that are often noisy, literary and inaccurate.
                    Furthermore, Homeric poems are not divided on a small scale: rhapsodies are
                    hundreds of lines long and episodes can be undetermined. </p>
                <p>There is a variety of elements that can be used as anchors in a text. The best
                    anchors are high frequency words, when the original and its translation are very
                    similar; or low frequency words such as technical terms, if we are sure they
                    will always be translated in the same way or within a very reduced number of
                    variants. Numbers can also act as anchors if they are always translated in the
                    same way. </p>
                <p>However, in the case of Homeric translations, these pivots are not reliable. We
                    can find many kinds translations of the Homeric text, with many types of
                    periphrasis, interpolation, and stylistic compromises. For example, many
                    translators thought that repetition was a reprehensible stylistic feature and
                    consistently used synonyms or periphrases where the original text had simply the
                    same word repeated twice: so high frequency nouns or verbs could be unreliable.
                    Other translators could do just the opposite, making low frequency words
                    unreliable. </p>
                <p>These variations in translation style made choosing appropriate anchors
                    problematic as traditional approaches were difficult to apply (for more
                    traditional approaches see <ptr target="#gomaa2013"/>; <ptr target="#ma2006"/>;
                        <ptr target="#nelken2006"/>; <ptr target="#och2003"/>; <ptr
                        target="#och1999"/>). </p>
                <p>Also, we didn’t have a <q>training dataset</q>, as often happens in other cases
                    of translation alignment, since there was no existing corpus of aligned Homeric
                    Greek - French texts. Even if such a corpus existed, it would have been
                    unreliable due to the compromises that different authors made while translating
                    the text. Additionally, as this is a diachronic study on literary translations,
                    even a Greek - French dictionary of anchor pairs would have hardly been useful. </p>
                <p>For these reasons, in order to segment our texts and their different translations
                    we chose to use proper nouns as anchor words. Proper nouns are a relatively
                    stable feature in Homeric translations. In fact, even the translations which
                    differ most from the original text tend to maintain the Greek proper nouns. It
                    is possible to look through many different translations and find that proper
                    nouns tend to remain phonetically similar with their Greek source, as can be
                    seen in Figure 3. </p>
                <!--Here goes Table [table01.png]-->
                <figure>
                    <head> A proper name used as anchor: stable element through different
                        translations</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/table01.jpg"/>
                </figure>

                <p>We decided to use proper nouns as pivot for segmenting our text. A source
                    sequence is defined as a list of words beginning with a Greek proper noun
                    stopping at index-1, index being the location of the following Greek proper
                    noun; a target sequence is a list of words beginning with a French (or any
                    target language) proper noun, stopping at index-1. However, proper nouns are not
                    completely reliable: duplications, interpolations, substitutions or unusual
                    translations happen in the onomastic field too. As a result rare proper nouns
                    tend to be more reliable pivots while frequent proper nouns should not be given
                    the same importance for the alignment. Once the sequences have been defined, the
                    alignment can begin. </p>
                <p>We first create a dictionary of anchor words. The Greek nouns are transformed
                    according to historical linguistic rules that produced French modern proper
                    nouns from their source Greek ones. For example, in <foreign xml:lang="el"
                        >Ἀχαιός</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="el">αι</foreign> is reduced to
                        <emph>e</emph>, and <foreign xml:lang="el">χ</foreign> transcribed as
                        <emph>ch</emph><note>For details on phonetic transformer, see code online,
                        PhoneticTransformer class in <ref
                            target="https://github.com/OdysseusPolymetis/OdysseusForMaven"
                            >https://github.com/OdysseusPolymetis/Odysseus</ref>.</note>. Once the
                    Greek noun has been transformed, it is compared to its possible translation
                    considering the edit distance between the two. If the distance is small, the
                    target value is considered as a translation of the source key. A map
                        <code>&lt;String, String []&gt;</code> is therefore created, with a key for
                    the source text and a list of translations for the target texts. The dictionary
                    is cumulative and allows to add every possible value of every possible target
                    text to a single source key. A possible representation of this map could be: </p>
                <p>
                    <dhq:example>
                        <head>To each lemmatized Greek name correspond several potential French
                            values.</head>
                        <p><foreign xml:lang="el">Ἐρέβευς</foreign> – <foreign xml:lang="fr"
                                >Erèbe</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="fr">Erebe</foreign><lb/>
                            <foreign xml:lang="el">Μενελάου</foreign> – <foreign xml:lang="fr"
                                >Ménélas</foreign>
                            <lb/>
                            <foreign xml:lang="el">Μέντορι</foreign> – <foreign xml:lang="fr"
                                >Mentor</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="fr">Mentôr</foreign> .… </p>
                    </dhq:example>
                </p>

                <p>This dictionary will allow us to increase or decrease the potential similarity
                    between two sequences. The alignment process can now begin. </p>
                <p>As we briefly explained at the beginning of the paper, the first step is to
                    create a 2D matrix where all the sequences are stored: the source sequences are
                    stored in the columns (each sequence is stored in each column), the target
                    sequences are stored in the lines (each sequence is stored in a different line).
                    To align the elements of the series, it will be necessary to choose a scoring
                    system. A basic scoring system can be thus summed up: if a source element at
                    index <emph>i</emph> and a target element at index <emph>j</emph> are equal (two
                    identical letters, two similar numbers, etc.) the score stored in the matrix at
                    index <emph>ij</emph> is 1, otherwise 0. </p>
                <p>Our way of establishing scores between sequences is similar, but more selective.
                    We use many similarity metrics already well known that we implemented for our
                    own purposes, such as the Monge Elkan distance, the Levensthein distance, the
                    Jaro-Winkler distance, or the Hamming distance<note>For details see our github
                        repository: <ref
                            target="https://github.com/OdysseusPolymetis/OdysseusForMaven"
                            >https://github.com/OdysseusPolymetis/Odysseus</ref>.</note> on both the
                    transformed Greek and the tags associated with each word (both in French and
                    Greek). The sequences carry their morphological information: each verb in Greek
                    is associated with a VB tag, each noun with a NN tag, etc. and so is the target
                    sequence. It therefore possible to take into account the syntactic similarity
                    between the source and the target. Yet again, this is far from being the only
                    similarity measures we use. The similarity is also determined by the frequency
                    of the proper nouns used both in source and in target sequences. Since the
                    frequency of proper nouns, like that of words in general, follows a Zipfian
                    distribution, we give to proper nouns a similarity score which is inversely
                    proportional to their frequency. If a low-frequency noun appears in Greek, and
                    if its potential translation can be found in its potential matching sequence,
                    the similarity is much stronger. We also take into account the absolute distance
                    between two sequences. If a very short sequence is associated with a very long
                    one, the score between the two is very likely to be low. Finally, another
                    essential similarity measure can only be performed once a first alignment has
                    been produced. In a second alignment, as we will see, we can take into account
                    the distributional semantic similarity between words. </p>
                <p>When this process is done, we have a list of aligned chunks, with gaps when the
                    Needleman-Wunsch found no possible alignment, as in the example in Figure 4. The
                    chunk <foreign xml:lang="el">Μέντωρ , ὅς ῥ '</foreign> hasn’t found a good
                    alignment and was thus paired with a gap. </p>
                <!--Here goes Table [table02.png]-->
                <figure>
                    <head>Example of block alignment with a gap</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/table02.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Three post-processing steps are then performed. First, we remove all the gaps
                    from the source text. For example, if at the same index both the source sequence
                    and the target sequence are gap characters, the index of both lists is removed.
                    If the source sequence is a gap while the target one is not, the source sequence
                    is removed. The target sequence is then associated with either the previous or
                    the next sequence in the source text, based on which of these contains a
                    potential match for the proper noun in the target sequence </p>
                <p>Once this first alignment and rearrangement is done, we proceed to yet another
                    alignment, this time taking into account the similarity between sequences
                    deduced from our distributional semantics method. </p>
                <p>This step is performed through a small variation of a standard distributional
                    semantics model. The distribution of words in the text (both original and
                    translation) is modelled into a vector representing how many times a given word
                    occurs in each aligned original-translation block. In this way, the contextual
                    information which is usually taken into account in semantic spaces is removed
                    and the co-occurrence of bilingual couples in the aligned blocks emerges with
                    clarity. A French word and a Greek word occurring in the same sequence of
                    aligned blocks will have similar vectors. Through this method we manage to
                    automatically retrieve a small dictionary of word-translation pairs. Naturally,
                    the length of this dictionary is modifiable changing the similarity threshold
                    above which two elements are considered a word-translation pair. If the first
                    alignment was very noisy (for example with many gap and large blocks) we will
                    need a higher threshold to establish a meaningful correspondence, while a
                    cleaner first alignment will allow us to relax our acceptability constraints. It
                    also becomes evident if a text tends to use always the same translation for the
                    same set of words, or if it translates them differently in different contexts. </p>
                <p>To this distributional dictionary, we add a specific MGiza dictionary. Once the
                    alignment of the corpus has been done, we use a wordtoword aligner called
                    MGiza++, the most recent version of Giza++. As it is multithreaded, the program
                    is much quicker, uses less memory, and the training process is more supple and
                    modifiable. The word-to-word alignment is done in two steps: first the
                    production of a co-occurrence tab (with the pre-implemented sent2cooc
                    algorithm), and an alignment based on <q>training models</q> (recursively
                    modifiable). MGiza++ uses IBM<note>A source and a target sequence, predicting
                        for each word of the source sequence a word of the target sequence based on
                        the 1:n model of alignment.</note> and HMM<note>The probability of an
                        occurrence is based on the preceding one.</note>
                    <ptr target="#manmatha2006"/> Models. These two models suggest that each word in
                    a corpus has its own non-arbitrary place, forming potential clusters with the
                    others, and that the position of the source and target words is highly dependent
                    on what surrounds them. </p>
                <p>The result is a series of aligned pairs like in Figure 5. </p>
                <!--Here goes Table [table03.png]-->
                <figure>
                    <head>Example of block alignment with a gap</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/table03.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <!--Here goes Figure [figure03.png]-->
                <figure>
                    <head>Alignment in the main frame</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>It is possible to refine textual blocks by recollecting the beginning and end of
                    their opening and closing sentences. This final step creates meaningful blocks
                    that start and end with complete sentences, although this procedure requires
                    some precaution. Figure 6 shows an example of the alignment possibilities of the
                    interface. </p>
                <p>The program was originally conceived with a Java interface. The application was
                    designed to be a purely local tool. However, when the time came to show our
                    results to a wide variety of researchers, we soon found out we needed a web
                    interface, to address the needs of specialists in Digital Humanities and a wider
                    range of literary researchers.<note>Our website is accessible at the following
                        web address: <ref target="https://odysseuspolymetis.github.io/paralogos"
                            >https://odysseuspolymetis.github.io/paralogos</ref>. The whole code is
                        freely available as open-source.</note> The whole code is open-source, on
                    our GitHub repository, and the .jar may be compiled with the .jardesc file. The
                    web interface, although on a different repository, is built for this program.
                    The users input files, as can be seen in the open-source code, can be in several
                    formats, such as .doc, .txt or .xml. During the process, the program will
                    segment integral texts into its main components, such as chapters, parts or
                    books (essentially with the use of regular expressions when the scheme is basic
                    enough). For the <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title>, it is segmented in books.
                    The book-segmented texts are printed in xml files. We then apply our
                        <term>NamesPatternMatcher</term> to create xml files with elements segmented
                    by proper nouns. Each of these elements has its correspondent attribute
                    lemmatized and tagged. When the alignments have been done, the output is printed
                    in xml files with a fixed identification for each sequence, which allows us to
                    associate it with the source, but also with its corresponding targets. </p>
                <p>Statistical comparison (number of occurrences of each term in the whole file,
                    number of occurrences for this precise identification and its correspondents,
                    etc.), phonetic comparison (phonetic similarities between source and target and
                    between different targets) and syntactical comparison (proximity with Greek in
                    the whole file, proximity with Greek for a precise identifier, etc.) allow us to
                    have a clear overview of all the translations at once. The web interface we
                    built for visualization allows us to visualize all the dynamically aligned text
                    simultaneously. One of the features that still remains to be added to the web
                    interface is a personal notebook for each user with the possibility of
                    commenting on chosen aligned sequences and hyper-linking those commentaries to
                    their specific identifiers. </p>
                <p>In other words, the calculation capacity is not comparable to that of a human
                    being. One would not be able to measure, for example, the exact syntactical
                    proximity between the Greek text in regard to 50 different French translations
                    at once. The fact that one is able to analyse multiple translations at once
                    while focusing on extremely precise events in the texts also shows what the
                    whole process of translation studies hints at, that one does not simply read
                    Homer’s text, but only one singular aspect of it from a particular author. </p>
                <p>Complete transparency of translation is not possible, and that is partly what our
                    tool shows. Although many sequences may convey the same general meaning, the way
                    each translator illustrates his perceptions in his own style shows the reader
                    that the <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> is not just one text, but a myriad
                    of interpretations brought to us through translations. To fully understand this
                    variation, close-reading is not sufficient and may easily be faulty. One may be
                    able to make accurate statements on some correspondences between one source text
                    and one target text, but it is highly doubtful that the human brain would be
                    able to compare so many translations at once and get a clear view of all the
                    relevant information. Not only is the human process slower and riskier, but it
                    also does not allow the adjunction of all the metadata our program can take into
                    account, such as the association of unexpected expressions or words found thanks
                    to distributional semantics that help us visualize the evolution of different
                    concepts through time. Finally, some scholars, such as Noémi Hepp <ptr
                        target="#hepp1968"/>, tend to present their own subjective judgements about
                    various translators as objective ones, while analysing the texts through
                    close-reading. The result is that, although Noémi Hepp might be considered as
                    deliberately controversial in this matter, some of her assertions about
                    translators that either she or translation critics of the time disliked are
                    clearly (both statistically and syntactically) unjustified. </p>
                <p>We will show a set of results obtained using the method outlined above to analyse
                    a segment of our corpus of translations of the <title rend="italic"
                        >Odyssey</title>. This analysis focuses on a specific portion of text,
                    extracted from the XIth book of the <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> (v.
                    3444). In this part of the paper, we would like to give an example of what
                    scholars may obtain using the program we made. We should proceed diachronically,
                    and see if we can spot trends and literary tendencies through the centuries.
                    However, every example we chose, though randomly chosen, can be compared, in our
                    program, to the 27 translations we digitalized. Figure 7 shows how a multiple
                    translation alignment looks in the interface and Figure 8 shows how a single
                    translation appears to the user, with different colors highlighting some
                    relevant elements of the text (hapax legomena, high frequency terms and so on). </p>
                <div>
                    <head>Salomon Certon</head>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure04.jpg]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Multiple alignments around Salomon Certon</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.JPG"/>
                    </figure>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure05.jpg]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Salomon Certon's aligned text</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>We first chose to compare Salomon Certon’s translation <ptr
                            target="#certon1604"/> with the others. The immediate post-Renaissance
                        period is a very rich time for Greek and Latin culture. </p>
                    <p>The idea that a cultural regeneration is deeply related to linguistic
                        regeneration flourishes. That is to say that French poets tend to seek their
                        own style within Ancient Epics. The general idea is that the skillful
                        translator should not slavishly imitate the author’s genius, but enrich it
                        by giving it his own skill and language (<foreign xml:lang="la">translatio
                            studii</foreign>). Translating appears therefore to be highly linked
                        with imitation. The same tradition is tangible in Ronsard’s followers’
                        works, such as in Amadis Jamyn’s <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> in
                        hexameters. The <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> had only been partially
                        translated before Salomon Certon, and his attempt is the first ever to
                        translate the entire <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title>. Although Certon
                        translates the <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> at the beginning of the
                        17th century, he is clearly inspired by the methods and traditions of the
                        16th century. He specializes in Latin metrics that he tends to reproduce,
                        and it is clearly visible that he has read Jamyn’s first three and
                        Peletier’s first two books <ptr target="#salel1545"/>, as he tends to
                        imitate them, or even cite them <foreign xml:lang="la">pro verbo</foreign>.
                        Initially he did not want to translate the whole <title rend="italic"
                            >Odyssey</title>, and it was Henri IV himself that asked for the
                        complete translation. But Certon did acknowledge his affiliation with his
                        predecessors, and did not count so much on innovation. Like Jamyn, he is not
                        such a good Hellenist, and is forced to repeatedly use Volterra’s Latin
                        translation, which was not even the latest and most accurate of his time. As
                        a result, many times, when Certon misses parts of the <title rend="italic"
                            >Odyssey</title>, it can be attributed to a Latin omission (while these
                        parts are present in his Greek version). However, his translation, as we
                        will see, seems to be nearer to the Greek than, for example, Jamyn’s. Certon
                        tends to reproduce more proper nouns than Jamyn, and is much nearer to the
                        Greek syntax and phonemes than his predecessor. As a result we could say
                        that his translation is not innovative in his translating habits, but that
                        being the first of its kind in terms of tackling the whole <title
                            rend="italic">Odyssey</title> in French, he had to rely more heavily
                        than his predecessors on both Latin and Greek versions. </p>
                    <p>In this abstract we can see that the necessity of capturing Homer’s verses
                        causes an expansion of the text, leading to the presence of many hapaxes or
                        low frequency terms, that is to say words that are not present in any of the
                        other translations at this point of the text. For example, in <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">Lorsque j’eus par mes
                                voeux &amp; supplications / Apaisé les esprits, fait mes
                                oblations</foreign></q>, the second line is an expansion and
                        cannot be justified by the Greek text. This suggests that Certon privileged
                        maintaining the metre over strict accuracy. </p>
                    <p>Comparing Certon’s translation with the others it is apparent that he
                        translates in <q>alexandrins</q>, and tends to drastically develop the Greek
                        text (his is one of the longest texts in our corpus). The verb <q><foreign
                                xml:lang="grc">λαβὼν</foreign></q> simply disappears. The word
                                <q><foreign xml:lang="grc">κελαινεφές</foreign></q>, literally
                            <q>in black smoke</q>, becomes <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">une rivière grosse et du
                                coup une humeur noirastre distilloit</foreign></q> (<q>an enormous river and from the neck
                            a black liquid ran</q>), which is a clarification and an
                        amplification. Many of Certon’s connotations cannot be deduced from the
                        Greek text, such as souls <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">qui volent</foreign></q>
                            (<q>flying</q>), <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">vaines</foreign></q>
                            (<q>empty</q>) (Christian heritage of the soul’s lightness). Death is
                        personified, which is quite far from the traditional pagan belief of the
                        souls’ peregrination. The tragic connotation is amplified. The <q><foreign
                                xml:lang="grc">Ἐρέβευς</foreign></q>, like in Volterra’s Latin
                        translation <ptr target="#maffei1523"/>, is absent. In fact, in his whole
                        translation, Certon tends to emphasize the gleam and shine of French.
                        Therefore, we may say that, if there is a kind of imitation of the Greek
                        text, it is more the imitation of a spirit rather than servile literal
                        imitation. Certon’s goal, when translating the <title rend="italic"
                            >Odyssey</title> is less a stylistic matter than a moral matter. For
                        Certon, the <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> seems to have a moral
                        function much more than a purely aesthetic one. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Achille de la Valterie, 1681</head>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure06.jpg]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Multiple alignments around Achille de la Valterie</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure07.jpg]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Achille de la Valterie's aligned text</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>On the whole, we know very little about Achille de la Valterie. We know that
                        he was a <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">jésuite</foreign></q>, but that he
                        renounced his vows later on. He is also known to have published a
                        translation of Juvenal’s and Perse’s <title rend="italic">Satires</title>,
                        and that he translated the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> as well as the
                            <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title>. His Homeric translations begin
                        with an <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">épître</foreign></q>, from which we can
                        deduce his way of translating. First, he states that there is no need to
                        know about Homer’s life to translate Homer: <quote rend="block"
                            source="#lavalterie1708"><foreign xml:lang="fr">Quand on ne sait point
                                toutes ces choses, on a du moins l’avantage de n’être point obligé
                                de les oublier, après avoir perdu beaucoup de temps à les
                                apprendre.</foreign><note><cit>
                                    <quote rend="inline" source="#lavalterie1708">When you do not
                                        know all these things, you have at least the advantage not
                                        to have to forget them, once you have lost so much time
                                        learning them</quote>
                                    <ptr target="#lavalterie1708"/>
                                </cit></note></quote></p>
                    <p>There is therefore no documentary value in Homer’s epics. And although he
                        states that strict proximity to the Greek text is one of his
                                goals<note><quote rend="inline" source="#lavalterie1708"><foreign xml:lang="fr"
                                    >Je puis prendre à témoin ceux qui entendent la langue grecque,
                                    que j’ai copié exactement mon original, étant persuadé que la
                                    beauté de mon ouvrage consistait à conserver avec quelque sorte
                                    de religion tous ses traits, et à les exprimer avec une parfaite
                                    fidélité</foreign></quote>, <cit>
                                <quote rend="inline" source="#lavalterie1708">All those who know
                                    Greek can bear witness that I exactly copied the original, and
                                    that I am convinced that what made my work beautiful was that I
                                    religiously preserved all its aspects, and that I expressed them
                                    with perfect accuracy.</quote>
                                <ptr target="#lavalterie1708"/>
                            </cit></note>, he also states that Homer’s epics should not be left
                        unattended and may need consistent changes: <quote rend="block"
                            source="#lavalterie1708"><foreign xml:lang="fr">Pour prévenir (...) le
                                dégoût que la délicatesse du temps aurait peut-être donné de ma
                                traduction, j’ai rapproché les moeurs des Anciens autant qu’il m’a
                                été permis (...) [et] je n’ai osé faire paraître Achille, Patrocle,
                                Ulysse et Ajax dans la cuisine, et dire toutes les choses que le
                                Poète ne fait point de difficulté de représenter (...) je me suis
                                servi de termes généraux dont notre langue s’accomode mieux que de
                                tout ce détail.</foreign><note><cit>
                                    <quote rend="inline" source="#lavalterie1708">To avoid (...)
                                        some reluctance possibly found in our delicate times while
                                        reading this translation, I approximately followed the
                                        Ancients’ customs. I did not dare show Achilles, Patroclus
                                        and Ulysses in the kitchen, and say all the things the Poet
                                        cared to show. I used general words, more appropriate in our
                                        language than those many details.</quote>
                                    <ptr target="#lavalterie1708"/>
                                </cit></note></quote></p>
                    <p>La Valterie has no real philological ambition. Indeed, from what we can get
                        studying his translations, La Valterie is an extremely poor Hellenist (it is
                        almost doubtful that he read any Greek at all) and mainly translated from
                        Latin, but also from existing translations (this is quite visible in our
                        program when you compare La Valterie’s translation <ptr
                            target="#lavalterie1709"/> to Boitel’s <ptr target="#boitel1638"/>, as
                        they have very rare terms in common in the same places and follow the same
                        syntactic structure, almost amounting to plagiarism). </p>
                    <p>Our program does help us to see immediately that La Valterie’s translation is
                        extremely far from the original text, and even contradictory with its
                        supposed source. A frequency study shows that the whole (or at least the
                        majority) of La Valterie’s translation is sewed with hapaxes (it is both far
                        from the Greek text and never used in any of the French translations), which
                        made it the most difficult text to align. We can also see that, although
                        most translators tend to reproduce important syntactic marks in Greek (full
                        stops, etc), La Valterie’s translation is the only one with no resemblance
                        whatsoever to the Greek syntax. This is visible in our example. Sentences
                        are long, there are frequent clarifications, tangible modalisations, and, of
                        course, many mistakes. It is also clear in this example that La Valterie
                        tends to avoid what he considers as trivial words and expressions, which
                        need to be either modernized or deleted. The word <q><foreign xml:lang="fr"
                                >cérémonies</foreign></q> may be justified (though it erases the
                        polysemic <q><foreign xml:lang="grc">εὐχωλῇσι</foreign></q> and
                                <q><foreign xml:lang="grc">λιτῇσί</foreign></q>, both
                        supplications and liturgical prayers), <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">se rebutter des incommodités de leur
                                vieillesse</foreign></q> (<q>grieving about the harshness of old age</q>) is a complex manner of
                        defining a much simpler down to earth single word in Greek, <q><foreign
                                xml:lang="grc">πολύτλητος</foreign></q> (then again this whole
                        expression is an hapax, as no other translator will bother to be so
                        disdainful of a simple practical term). The word <q><foreign xml:lang="fr"
                                >Capitaines</foreign></q> is a condensation of war heroes adapted to
                        the 17th century. </p>
                    <p>Therefore, La Valterie’s translation is both very far from being accurate or
                        even faithful to the Greek. In later critical essays on Homeric
                        translations, especially in Madame Dacier’s work, which is discussed below,
                        La Valterie is seen as someone who has been left behind by the progress of
                        translation. His translation has been edited, reprinted, but there are still
                        no serious critics who say anything positive about it, quite the opposite in
                        fact. A few years late, La Valterie becomes the paragon of a moralist
                        translator; fit to feebly teach some moral values, but clearly unfit to
                        reveal Homer’s beauty. From the 17th century onward, practising translation
                        as a mere imitation is no longer an unquestionable principle. </p>
                    <p>Figures 9 and 10 show an alignment around La Valterie’s text and a small part
                        of the same text tokenized in blocks in the interface. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Anne Dacier, 1716</head>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure08.png]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Multiple alignments around Anne Dacier</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure09.png]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Anne Dacier's aligned </head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Madame Dacier’s note on this part: <quote rend="block" source="#undocumented"><foreign
                                xml:lang="fr">Les six vers qui suivent celuici : Parce,
                                disaient-ils, qu’il n’est pas encore temps que ces Ames viennent,
                                &amp; que d’ailleurs il n’est pas possible que les blessures
                                paraissent sur les Ames. Mais cette critique me parait trèsfausse.
                                Pourquoi n’est-il pas temps que ces Ames viennent, Homere ne dit-il
                                pas que les ombres des morts viennent de tous côtez du fond de
                                l’Erebe ? &amp; ne reçoivent-ils pas ce vers ? Les six qui le
                                suivent n’en font que l’explication. Quant aux blessures, il est
                                bien vrai qu’elles ne peuvent paroître sur la partie spirituelle de
                                l’Ame, aussi n’est-ce pas de celle-là dont Homere parle, puisque
                                les Morts ne l’avaient plus ; il parle du corps subtil de l’Ame,
                                &amp; tout ce qui avait blessé le corps terrestre, avait aussi
                                blessé le corps subtil, &amp; y avait laissé sa marque. Voilà
                                pourquoi il est dit que dans les songes on voit les Ames dans le
                                même état où sont les corps, &amp; voilà aussi d’où vient la
                                difference qu’Ulysse remarque dans ces ombres. Ce qui me parait le
                                plus surprenant ici, c’est ce qu’Ulysse ajoute, que ces Ames avaient
                                encore leurs armes, &amp; que ces armes étaient encore teintes de
                                sang. Comment ces Ames, ces Ombres, qui n’étaient que le corps
                                subtil de l’Ame, pouvaient-elles conserver leurs armes ? Je crois
                                que c’est un point nouveau qu’Ulysse ajoute ici à la Theologie
                                reçue, &amp; qu’il ajoute, parce qu’il parle aux Pheaciens, peuple
                                peu instruit.</foreign></quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>The first turning point in contrast with this tendency seems to appear with
                        Madame Dacier’s translations (from what we gathered from the program,
                        studying the texts diachronically). Anne Lefebvre Dacier (known as <q>Madame
                            Dacier</q>), wrote her translations as a reaction to Homeric imitations.
                        Many translators had followed the same principles as La Vallterie for at
                        least a century. The <title rend="italic">Iliade</title> by La Motte <ptr
                            target="#lamotte1714"/> is one of the many examples of a tendency to
                        transform the epics into an <q>up-to-date</q> version. In this general
                        atmosphere, Madame Dacier is an exception. She was very fond of Greek and
                        Latin from a very young age, and was given the chance to grow up with just
                        as much education as a man thanks to her father. Though small and, above
                        all, a woman, her strong character and her excellent knowledge of Greek
                        forced her peers to acknowledge the quality of her many
                            publications<note>See for example Dacier, Anne. <title rend="italic"
                                >Comédies grecques [d’Aristophane]</title>. G. Gallet, 1692, Dacier,
                            Anne. <title rend="italic">Les poesies d’Anacreon et de Sapho, traduites
                                de grec an françois, avec des remarques</title> chez Paul Marret,
                            1699, Dacier, Anne. <title rend="italic">Dictys Cretensis et Dares
                                Phrygius De bello et excidio Trojae, in usum serenissimi delphini,
                                cum interpretatione Annae Daceriae</title>. apud Georgium Gallet,
                            1702, Dacier, Anne. <title rend="italic">Ilias</title>, 1712, Dacier,
                            Anne. <title rend="italic">Des causes de la corruption du goust</title>.
                            Rigaud, 1714.</note>. She is a paragon of scientific, archaeological and
                        philanthropic knowledge of Homer’s works. As she says herself in her <title
                            rend="italic">Iliade</title>: <quote rend="block" source="#dacier1712"
                                ><foreign xml:lang="fr">Je n’écris pas pour les savants qui lisent
                                Homère en sa langue (...) j’écris pour ceux qui ne le connaissent
                                point, c’est à dire pour le plus grand nombre, à l’égard desquels ce
                                poète est comme mort.</foreign>
                            <ptr target="#dacier1712"/></quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Although she states that her work is not made to be a philological
                        translation, it is clear that the amount of research and stylistic work in
                        her translations is enormous<note>On this matter, see <ptr
                                target="#dacier1717"/>, but also many works about her, such as <ptr
                                target="#garnier2002"/></note>. The <title rend="italic"
                            >Odyssey</title>
                        <ptr target="#dacier1717"/> is heavily annotated (the notes generally take
                        three quarters of a single page). She wants her readers to see Homer as he
                        is, not as he should be in a contemporary world. Therefore, she has to
                        explain many of the incoherences and cultural gaps that would make Homer
                        incompatible with the modern world. She tends to justify shocking
                        descriptions or attitudes in the <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> by
                        saying that those were acceptable because they were different, and justifies
                        her assertions both philologically and archaeologically. She also tends to
                        erase most of Homer’s stylistic specificities, as they have no scientific
                        purpose. </p>
                    <p>Dacier uses common terms for the society she lives in, uses simplified
                        syntax, and above all annotates her text enormously. We included the notes
                        and explanations directly in the text but did not align them. What is most
                        visible in this abstract is that Dacier tends to respect the length and
                        syntax of the Greek text, much more than her predecessors. It is also
                        visible that she initiates this tendency for the following translators such
                        as Bitaubé (for more details on syntactic proximity after Madame Dacier, see
                        our website). She erases the polysemy of the Greek word <q><foreign
                                xml:lang="grc">κελαινεφές</foreign></q>, interpreting it in a
                        logical and clarified way (leaving aside both the smoky effect and its
                        blackness). She just translates the expression <q><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >νεκύων κατατεθνηώτων</foreign></q> by <q><foreign xml:lang="fr"
                                >les ombres</foreign></q>, erasing the redundancy like <q>the dead
                            that have lived</q>. Dacier definitely wants to imitate the Greek
                        syntax, keeping the paratactic <q><foreign xml:lang="grc">τε</foreign></q>:
                        this is quite visible in the important similarity to the Greek throughout
                        the text (see greyer colums). She also chooses to clarify the polysemous
                        word <q><foreign xml:lang="grc">νεοπενθέα</foreign></q>, with the images of
                        both sorrow and flowers. She adapts the deity Ares into Mars who would be
                        more familiar to her audience, and she is one of the rare translators (along
                        with Bitaubé) to use this adaptation. We decided to add the footnote we
                        included, as it shows Dacier’s desire to explain the war heroes’ death in
                        terms of Christian beliefs. There is no phonetic proximity to the Greek
                        whatsoever. She does not simply want to imitate Homer but to make him
                        understandable for her readers and so phonetic imitation, which is seen
                        later in Leconte de Lisle, would be counter-productive. It is also
                        noticeable that this abstract contains a large amount of green words, while
                        earlier translations do not.This means that many of the words she uses were
                        then imitated and reproduced by her followers. From the imitative flowery
                        pomp we got from the previous century, we now get a form of puritanism from
                        this erudite translator. </p>
                    <p>Figures 11 and 12 show an alignment around Dacier’s text and a small part of
                        the same text tokenized in blocks in the interface. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Paul Jérémie Bitaubé, 1785</head>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure10.png]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Multiple alignments around Paul Jérémie Bitaubé</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure11.png]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Paul Jérémie Bitaubé's aligned text</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure11.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Bitaubé’s works show similar tendencies as Dacier’s. Bitaubé’s native
                        language was German. When he decided to learn French, he saw it as a
                        scholarly language, a language that tends towards excellence. Thanks to his
                        first publication of the <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title>
                        <ptr target="#bitaube1764"/>, he became an academic in Berlin. He decided
                        for a scholarly style that he calls <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#bitaube1764"><foreign xml:lang="fr">prose
                            cadencée</foreign></quote> (<quote rend="inline"
                            source="#bitaube1764">prose in rythm</quote>): <quote rend="block"
                            source="#bitaube1764"><foreign xml:lang="fr">Il n’est pas aisé
                                d’écrire dans une prose cadencée, harmonieuse, qui s’élève (elle
                                le peut), au ton de la poésie ; et je soutiens que la gêne d’une
                                grande fidélité, lorsqu’on s’y assujettit scrupuleusement, n’est
                                pas si éloignée qu’on le pense de celle de traduire en
                                vers.</foreign><note><cit>
                                    <quote rend="inline" source="#bitaube1764">It is not easy to
                                        write in prose with rhythm, harmony and worthy (it can be)
                                        of poetry ; and I am sure that the uneasiness due to
                                        scrupulous accuracy is not as far as we might think from the
                                        difficulty of writing poetry</quote>
                                    <ptr target="#bitaube1764"/>
                                </cit></note></quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>To assert this scientific ambition, Bitaubé is one of the first to
                        explicitly mention any translator before him. What is more, not only does
                        Bitaubé want to be exact in the meaning, he also aims at accuracy
                        concerning style, imitating, as much as possible, Homer’s <foreign
                            xml:lang="la">brevitas</foreign>. As a result, in only one century, the
                        reader goes from imitative flowery pomp to scholarly puritanism. In our
                        text, Bitaubé tries to maintain both the Greek syntax (just as Dacier did),
                        but also its polysemous terms. For example, where Dacier used two
                        coordinates, for <q><foreign xml:lang="grc">λαβὼν</foreign></q> and
                                <q><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐλλισάμην</foreign></q>, Bitaubé
                        chooses juxtaposition, maintaining the Greek hypotyposis. The blackness and
                        the liquid aspect of the <q><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >κελαινεφές</foreign></q> is now explicit (<q><foreign xml:lang="fr"
                                >les noirs torrents</foreign></q>). Bitaubé also attempts, as much
                        as possible, to reproduce the Greek redundancy <q><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >νεκύων κατατεθνηώτων</foreign></q>. Finally, he strictly imitates
                        the Greek syntax, maintaining the paratactic syntax and the adjectives
                        describing the dead. </p>
                    <p>After Bitaubé, the 19th century flourishes with many translations of Homer’s
                        epics. The French Revolution, and especially the Terror has given a new
                        gleam to the ancient poets, supposed to be the witnesses of a higher moral
                        value, lost in modern times, both aesthetically and politically. Bitaubé is
                        in an in-between conception of the Greek literature as the <title
                            rend="quotes">Dictionnaire bibliographique à l’usage des
                            collèges</title> will say about him, <quote rend="block"
                            source="#michaud1843"><foreign xml:lang="fr">Il s’applique à conserver
                                la marche et les formes de la phrase grecque, il imite assez bien
                                l’abondance et la rondeur de l’original, et sa traduction a un air
                                antique, et ne manque pas d’un certain charme ; mais l’audace, la
                                majesté, l’éloquence variée d’Homère, la richesse de ses couleurs,
                                le mouvement rapide de son style, la hardiesse et l’impétuosité du
                                langage, on les cherche en vain ; on lui demanderait plus vainement
                                encore la mollesse et la grâce, l’harmonie générale du style
                                homérique, les expressions touchantes, cette mélodie suave</foreign><note><cit>
                                    <quote rend="inline" source="#michaud1843">He is intent on
                                        keeping the Greek movement and syntax, he fairly well
                                        imitates the abundance and roundness of the original text,
                                        and his translation seems antique, somehow charming; but for
                                        Homer’s boldness, majesty and various eloquence, for his
                                        rich colours, his audacious and daring language, you may
                                        look in vain. One might even less ask him for gentleness and
                                        gracefulness, the general harmony of Homer’s style, his
                                        touching expressions, his smooth melody.</quote>
                                    <ptr target="#michaud1843"/>
                                </cit></note></quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>A major evolution can be noticed here; a greater attention is given to
                        Homer’s style rather than moral teachings, and Bitaubé, although frequently
                        reprinted at the time, especially in school books, is not criticized for the
                        possible rashness of his translation, but on the contrary for his lack of
                        Homeric style. </p>
                    <p>Figures 13 and 14 show an alignment around Bitaubé’s text and a small part of
                        the same text tokenized in blocks in the interface. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Charles François Lebrun, 1819</head>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure12.png]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Multiple alignments around Charles François Lebrun</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure12.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure13.png]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Charles François Lebrun's aligned text</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure13.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The thermidorian reaction to this way of perceiving the Classics puts to an
                        end the cult of a lost Antique virtue. Volney, for example, will say: <quote
                            rend="block" source="#volney1799"><foreign xml:lang="fr">Ce sont ces
                                livres classiques si vantés, ces poètes, ces orateurs, ces
                                historiens, qui, mis sans discernement aux mains de la jeunesse,
                                l’ont imbue de leurs principes ou de leurs sentiments. Ils ont
                                oublié que cette prétendue république, diverse selon les époques,
                                fut toujours une oligarchie composée d’un ordre de noblesse et de
                                sacerdoce, maître presque exclusif des terres et des emplois, et
                                d’une masse plébéinne grevée d’usures, n’ayant pas quatre arpents
                                par tête, et ne différant de ses propres esclaves que par le droit
                                de les fustiger, de vendre son suffrage, et d’aller vieillir ou
                                périr sous le sarment des centurions, dans l’esclavage des camps et
                                les rapines militaires.</foreign><note><cit>
                                    <quote rend="inline" source="#volney1799">Those classics, that
                                        we praised so much, those poets, those orators, those
                                        historians, all of those, indiscriminately given to the
                                        youth, nourrished her of their principles and feelings. We
                                        all forgot that this so-called republic, variable during
                                        different eras, was always an oligarchy, made of the
                                        noblemen and the church, exclusive masters of lands and
                                        works, and of a crowd of common people weighed down by
                                        debts, not even posessing four acres each, only differing
                                        from their own slaves by the right to punish them, sell
                                        them, sell their vote, and grow old and die under the
                                        Centurions’ flags, as camp slaves used to pillaging
                                        soldiers.</quote>
                                    <ptr target="#volney1799"/>
                                </cit></note></quote></p>
                    <p>As a result of this violent reaction, the Greek will again be given to the
                        youth of the time, but not as a moral model, but much more as a potential
                        source of erudition and scientific knowledge. Le Prince Lebrun is one of the
                        heirs of such teachings. </p>
                    <p>Le Prince Lebrun is, above all, a <foreign xml:lang="la">homo
                            publicus</foreign>. He escapes many of the massacres from the French
                        Revolution, avoids death during the final period of Napoleon’s reign, and
                        holds many public offices. His <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>,
                        translated when he was young, was an exercise to make himself famous among
                        the erudite society. His <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title>
                        <ptr target="#lebrun1819"/>, however, is the work of a man that has already
                        achieved social fame. He is one of the many men of power to demonstrate, by
                        publishing poorly translated works, his ability to be both an important man
                        and a scholar. His works, as a result, though very well known at the time
                        and republished many times, were completely forgotten thirty years after his
                        death. </p>
                    <p>In our text, we can see that he tends to strictly imitate the Greek, often in
                        a clumsy way, and sometimes with great inaccuracy. This entire translation
                        has no footnotes, no preface, no post-face. He has none of Dacier’s or
                        Bitaubé’s ethnographic care, although it is clear that he has read Bitaubé,
                        as we can see from our program, as he reuses many words that had previously
                        only be used by Bitaubé. This translation is the direct result of the
                        educative principles initiated by Dacier and Bitaubé. </p>
                    <p>Lebrun’s translation is an echo of the way Greek was taught at the time.
                        Indeed, an enormous amount of partial scholarly translations appear during
                        the second half of the 19th century that clearly tend to privilege the
                        strict accuracy to the Greek text, without the help of Latin. The Greek
                        Classics have become a source of linguistic benefits (the necessity to learn
                        Greek at the time is often justified by the ability it should give to
                        students to enhance their intellectual capabilities as well as their
                        analytic skills, reasoning, and logic) and ethnological information (the
                        Greek text should be perceived as a literary testimony). </p>
                    <p>Figures 15 and 16 show an alignment around Lebrun’s text and a small part of
                        the same text tokenized in blocks in the interface. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Edouard Sommer, 1854</head>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure14.png]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Multiple alignments around Edouard Sommer</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure14.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure15.png]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Edouard Sommer's aligned text</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure15.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>From the second half of the 19th century, many juxtalinear translations are
                        published. For the first time, the aim is to publish a large amount of
                        abridged translations, and if a certain abstract has more success than
                        others, publish the entire translation. These translations are
                        typographically recognizable; the first page is a word-to-word translation,
                        unreadable and not supposed to be fluent, and the second page is a
                        linguistically acceptable translation. This practical use of translation
                        reveals two essential points in the evolution of translation practices.
                        Firstly, in order for a translation to be judged adequate, it must show that
                        the translator perfectly understood the syntactic problems of the Greek text
                        and secondly, that Greek and Latin studies have never been more important in
                        general education. </p>
                    <p>However, Sommer’s many translations <ptr target="#sommer1854"/> do not aim at
                        being original or stylistically distinguishable, but mainly tend to explain
                        Greek syntactic problems. In our text, Sommer never omits a single word,
                        keeping each redundancy, without seeking poetic effects (e.g.: the <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#sommer1854"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ψυχαὶ
                                νεκύων κατατεθνηώτων</foreign></quote> is simply translated by
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#sommer1854"><foreign xml:lang="fr">les
                                âmes des morts</foreign></quote>). What is more, Sommer tends to
                        maintain Greek temporality: he keeps aorists and imperfects, not considering
                        French habits (<quote rend="inline" source="#sommer1854"><foreign
                                xml:lang="fr">la pâle crainte s’emparait de moi</foreign></quote>,
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#sommer1854">the pale dread was getting
                            to me</quote>). Sommer’s translation is clearly and without any doubt
                        the nearest text to the Greek syntax. The syntactic similarities are at
                        their highest points throughout the text. What is more, the text displays an
                        enormous amount of green and blue words, that is to say extremely frequent
                        words. He does not aim at originality, but at reproducing the meaning word
                        by word. Finally he is one of the rare 19th century translators (along with
                        Leconte de Lisle) who share such a close proximity to the Greek at this
                        precise point. </p>
                    <p>Both Latin and Greek Classics seem at this time to have regained a certain
                        prestige. Many of the abridged translations are made for school use, and
                        their notes and parallel analysis show a new grammatical perception of both
                        languages. Almost paradoxically, the extreme accuracy asked for from the
                        students will sometimes generate much bolder translations such as Leconte de
                        Lisle’s. </p>
                    <p>Figures 17 and 18 show an alignment around Sommer’s text and a small part of
                        the same text tokenized in blocks in the interface. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Charles Marie René Leconte de Lisle, 1867</head>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure16.png]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Multiple alignments around Charles Marie René Leconte de Lisle</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure16.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure17.png]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Charles Marie René Leconte de Lisle's aligned text</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure17.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In this period translators stop adapting the text to their own language and
                        culture, but enrich their own style with the contact of strangeness. The
                        climax of this tendency seems to be reached with Leconte de Lisle <ptr
                            target="#leconte1867"/>. Not only does he use rare terms or even
                        hapaxes, but he also creates neologisms, and imitates the Greek itself as a
                        sound. Leconte de Lisle was one of the reasons we used the Greek text as
                        pivot as he is often quite literal in his phonetic imitations (he is without
                        doubt the author that has the more italics in his text); this means it tends
                        to be very different from traditional syntax. Indeed, the goal might have
                        been first to disassociate the reader from his own <foreign xml:lang="la"
                            >hic et nunc</foreign>, for lost and far away realities, but also to
                        create a form of poetic hermetism. As a result, the program points out that
                        in Leconte de Lisle’s translation there are many hapaxes and many word
                        similarities with the Greek, which is to say archaisms<note>As Henri
                            Meschonnic says for André Chouraqui, <quote rend="inline" source="#meschonnic1999"
                                    ><foreign xml:lang="fr">Chouraqui [...] ne fait rien de nouveau,
                                    sinon que, comme Leconte de Lisle avec les noms dans Homère, il
                                    les <emph>ensauvage</emph> en les
                                    <emph>originant</emph>.</foreign></quote>, <cit>
                                <quote rend="inline" source="#meschonnic1999">Chouraqui [...] does
                                    nothing new, but like Leconte de Lisle with names in Homer, he
                                        <emph>wilders</emph> the names by <emph>originating</emph>
                                    them.</quote>
                                <ptr target="#meschonnic1999"/>
                            </cit></note>. The goal is clearly to recreate a complete work of art,
                        poetic and independent from its source for a renewed modern language. In our
                        text, what is most noticeable is that Leconte de Lisle maintains most of the
                        Greek syntax and uses an enormous amount of hapaxes (the first in our whole
                        corpus to use so many hapaxes). In the first sentence, he strictly imitates
                        Greek temporality, and he is the first to explicitly keep the perfect
                        participle <foreign xml:lang="grc">κατατεθνηώτων</foreign> (accomplished
                        fact) with <quote rend="inline" source="#leconte1867"><foreign
                                xml:lang="fr">les morts qui ne sont plus</foreign></quote> (<quote
                            rend="inline" source="#leconte1867">the dead that are no
                        more</quote>). The <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ἐρέβευς</foreign> is also
                        phonetically imitated, as shown with the italics, translated as <q><foreign
                                xml:lang="fr">Erebos</foreign></q>. The following sentence exactly
                        maintains the Greek syntax (nominative juxtapositions, demonstrative pronoun
                                <q><foreign xml:lang="grc">οἳ</foreign></q>). But what is more,
                        Leconte de Lisle maintains, as much as possible, every assonance and
                        alliteration present in the Greek text (<quote rend="inline"
                            source="#leconte1867"><foreign xml:lang="grc">θεσπεσίῃ
                                ἰαχῇ</foreign></quote>, with three and two syllables: <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#leconte1867"><foreign xml:lang="fr"
                                >frémissement immense</foreign></quote>, with three and two
                        syllables). Even the books themselves are not books anymore but
                            <q>rhapsodies</q>. This tendency illustrated by Leconte de Lisle is
                        clearly seen at the time as an emancipation. Translating means working not
                        only on a source language, but on French itself. The fact that a new kind of
                        French is needed is visible in the way translators deliberately skew common
                        meanings and usage. Translation is not perceived only as a symbolic means of
                        understanding ideas and culture, but also as a new way to express impression
                        and sound. Translation itself is a new work of art. </p>
                    <p>However popular Greek studies might have been during the second half of the
                        19th century, their descent is quite tangible throughout the 20th, and so is
                        a drop in interest for literary Greek translation, especially in the first
                        twenty years of the century. This descent goes hand in hand with the
                        increasing specialization of scientific and documentary matter. Knowing
                        Greek means more and more that one should be familiar with a precise
                        contextualized Greek reality and history. The study of Greek becomes the
                        study of Greek history and archaeological value, not so much as purely
                        developing a stylistic and grammatical ability. </p>
                    <p>Figures 19 and 20 show an alignment around Leconte de Lisle’s text and a
                        small part of the same text tokenized in blocks in the interface. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Victor Bérard, 1924</head>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure18.png]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Multiple alignments around Victor Bérard</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure18.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure19.png]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Victor Bérard's aligned text</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure19.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Victor Bérard considered Homer’s <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> both
                        as a literary masterpiece and a considerable source of archaeological
                        information; he saw the epics as both a poem and a document. As a result,
                        Bérard’s translation <ptr target="#berard1924"/> was paradoxically easy and
                        challenging to align. It was easy because Bérard tends, writing in
                        hexameters, to reproduce the syntactic movement of the Greek verse. He also
                        tends to keep the polysemous aspects of each particular word as well as
                        keeping in mind the principle of <foreign xml:lang="la">brevitas</foreign>.
                        As a result, if we compare the syntax of each aligned chunk with its Greek
                        correspondent, we find an extraordinary proximity of length and syntax,
                        almost as high as Sommer’s. However, it was also, in some parts, difficult
                        to align. This is because because, being an archaeologist, Bérard tends to
                        force the original text into his own present reality. For example, he tends
                        to change toponyms so that they match real places in modern Greece. This
                        characteristic found in many of Bérard’s translations and works on Antiquity
                        has been qualified as the <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#montalbetti1997"><foreign xml:lang="fr"
                                    >complexe de Victor Bérard</foreign></quote>
                            <ptr target="#montalbetti1997"/>
                        </cit>. Bérard wanted to locate every single <foreign xml:lang="la"
                            >topos</foreign> described in the <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title>
                        in the modern world. To do so, from 1902 to 1912, he travelled throughout
                        the Mediterranean sea, and wrote four volumes of 400 pages each entitled
                            <title rend="italic">Les Navigations d’Ulysse</title>
                        <ptr target="#berard1927"/>. These <title rend="italic">Navigations</title>
                        follow Ulysses’ path throughout the <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title>.
                        Later in the <title rend="italic">Sillage d’Ulysse</title>
                        <ptr target="#berard1933"/>, Bérard collects all the photographs Fred
                        Boissonnas, who accompanied him on his trips, took in Greece and identified
                        each one as a specific Homeric <foreign xml:lang="la">topos</foreign>. This
                        is symbolic of what Bérard thinks about the art of translation, that it is
                        as much archaeological research as it is a poetic activity. He views it as a
                        way of combining past and present into a single universal reality. In our
                        text, Bérard mainly imitates the natural movement of the Greek line, using
                        the hexameter. For the first time, every Greek word is translated, this time
                        in the iconic <foreign xml:lang="la">brevitas</foreign> style, which makes
                        this translation a true masterpiece, being both poetic and precise. For
                        example, <quote rend="inline" source="#berard1933"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >κελαινεφές</foreign></quote> is translated by <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#berard1933"><foreign xml:lang="fr">les sombres
                                vapeurs</foreign></quote> which is the shortest and yet the most
                        literal translation we have. The same thing can be noticed about the word
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#berard1933"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >θύμος</foreign></quote>, erased from so many translations before,
                        literally maintained without awkwardness, by <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#berard1933"><foreign xml:lang="fr">portant au
                            coeur</foreign></quote> (<quote rend="inline" source="#berard1933"
                            >bearing in their heart</quote>). Let us also notice that the dread does
                        not have a clarity, but a color, a characteristic that he will be the first
                        one to use, and the nearest to the Greek so far. What is more, Bérard is
                        the first since Certon to fully express Odysseus’ fear with the hypotyposis
                        present throughout the description of the dead, and keeping the paratactic
                        asyndeton. We can notice a true evolution with Bérard’s translation,
                        initiated, we may suppose, by Leconte de Lisle. The strangeness of Greek
                        must be assumed both as a philologic information for the Hellenist and an
                        aesthetic novelty for the poet. We can therefore also see Bérard, apart from
                        Leconte de Lisle, as one of the first to assume fully Greek proper nouns,
                        many of which are in italics. We can also see that his translation, still
                        one of the most well known in France today, has been reused and changed (in
                        very different ways), both by Philippe Jaccottet and Frédéric Mugler.
                        Indeed, Frédéric Mugler is often seen to reuse Bérard’s translations without
                        citing him, which we can see in our program as he uses expressions that have
                        a very low frequency and that are only present in Bérard’s translation. For
                        example, just like in Bérard, the invocation is made to the <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">peuple des
                                défunts</foreign></q>, the animal’s throat is <q><foreign xml:lang="fr"
                                >tranchée</foreign></q> (just as in, and only in, Bérard and
                        Jaccottet), the old men are <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">chargés d’épreuves</foreign></q>, and
                        finally the dread is described with exactly the same words, <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">je
                                verdissais de crainte</foreign></q>. Concerning Jaccottet, it
                        seems to be a quite different matter, as he is the first, after Bérard, to
                        use French verses to translate the Greek epics. </p>
                    <p>Figures 21 and 22 show an alignment around Bérard’s text and a small part of
                        the same text tokenized in blocks in the interface. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Philippe Jaccottet, 1955</head>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure20.png]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Multiple alignments around Philippe Jaccottet</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure20.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <!--Here goes Figure [figure21.png]-->
                    <figure>
                        <head>Philippe Jaccottet's aligned text</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure21.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>We chose to analyze Jaccottet’s translation here <ptr target="#jaccottet1955"
                        />, as Jaccottet declares himself as an heir to Bérard (although not
                        entirely). We should just stress that with the program we could spot two
                        schemes: firstly Jaccottet’s lines, just like Bérard’s, tend to reproduce
                        Greek syntax, secondly, Jaccottet uses high frequency and everyday words,
                        which sets him apart from Bérard. This tends to illustrate what Jaccottet
                        may say himself about his own style: expression should be <q><foreign
                                xml:lang="fr">loyale</foreign></q> (both <q>accurate</q> and
                            <q>faithful</q>). From a translator’s point of view, this first means
                        that there is a promise of truth between the word and the object it
                        represents, but also between a foreign word and a familiar word. As
                        Jaccottet states himself: <quote rend="block" source="#jaccottet1955"
                                ><foreign xml:lang="fr">Y entendre ne fût-ce qu’un écho très
                                affaibli de l’admirable musique originale, il faut alors traduire,
                                dans la mesure du possible et sans tomber dans l’absurde, selon la
                                lettre même du texte. De même, il faut écouter plutôt que lire,
                                ainsi [...] le texte retrouve sa lenteur nécessaire, son mouvement,
                                quelque chose de sa résonance.</foreign><note><cit>
                                    <quote rend="inline" source="#jaccottet1955">One should be able
                                        to hear at least the feeble echo of the admirable original
                                        music, and we should translate, as far as it is possible,
                                        and without absurdity, according to the letter itself (...)
                                        the text should find its necessary slowness, something of a
                                        resonance</quote>
                                    <ptr target="#jaccottet1955"/>
                                </cit></note></quote></p>

                    <p>Both Bérard and Jaccottet, though to different extents, embody this
                        increasing attention to the poetics of their source material and the need to
                        reproduce an echo of what has been lost. In our text, we can first notice a
                        symmetric inversion of the syntactic order, emphasizing the liturgical
                        aspect of the scene and the Homeric tendency to maintain the hesitation
                        between the narrative and the incantation. The expression <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">les deux
                                bêtes</foreign></q> (<q>the two
                            beasts</q>), most unusual, may be due less to the context than to
                        the phonic imitation of <foreign xml:lang="grc">δὲ</foreign>. The word
                                <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">trou</foreign></q> is almost shocking, but
                        then again reflects the phonic imitation of <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >βόθρον</foreign>, and its extreme simplicity (an essential notion in
                        Jaccottet’s poetry). The problematic expression <q><foreign xml:lang="grc">ψυχαὶ νεκύων
                                κατατεθνηώτων</foreign></q> is translated with apparent ease,
                        both keeping the pleonasm and the naturalness of the language, with <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">les âmes des défunts
                                trépassés</foreign></q> (<q>the
                            souls of the departed dead</q>). The adjective <q><foreign
                                xml:lang="fr">étrange</foreign></q> (<q>strange</q>) maintains
                        Odysseus’ uneasy feeling (implied by <q><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >θεσπεσίῃ</foreign></q>), and while Jaccottet maintains the final
                        imperfect (also visible in the Greek text), he gives it an inchoative
                        connotation, which is most original. Finally, let us point out that there
                        are no capitals in Jaccottet’s poetry, corresponding both to his own
                        principle of <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">effacement</foreign></q>
                            (<q>disappearance</q>) and to a vision of poetic rhythm (conceived as a
                        blow, a wind, which should not be stopped). </p>
                    <p>Here we showed a larger sample of Jaccottet’s abstract, as a smaller sample,
                        similar to ones used for other translations, would not have highlighted
                        Jaccottet’s exceptional attention to accurately recreating the Greek. As we
                        saw, he tends to reproduce as many phonemes as he can, and many of his
                        proper nouns, but also many inner words, are in italics, and he has an
                        exceptional high similarity with the Greek syntax, comparable only to
                        Sommer’s. </p>
                    <p>Both Bérard and Jaccottet, following the path Leconte de Lisle had
                        initiated, have contributed to a new perception of translation, as a
                        masterpiece both in debt and independent from its source. We would like to
                        conclude this analysis of Jaccottet’s work with one of his own elegant
                        statements about translation in his preface: <quote rend="block"
                            source="#jaccottet1955"><foreign xml:lang="fr">Et tel aura été le
                                rêve, utopique, de cette traduction, défectueuse comme toute
                                traduction : que le texte vienne à son lecteur ou, mieux peutêtre,
                                à son auditeur un peu comme viennent à la rencontre du voyageur
                                ces statues ou ces colonnes lumineuses dans l’air cristallin de la
                                Grèce, surtout quand elles le surprennent sans qu’il y soit
                                préparé ; mais même quand il s’y attend, elles le surprennent,
                                tant elles viennent de loin, parlent de loin, encore qu’on les
                                touche du doigt. Elles demeurent distantes, mais la distance d’elles
                                à nous est aussi un lien radieux.</foreign><note><cit>
                                    <quote rend="inline" source="#jaccottet1955">And such has been
                                        the utopic dream of this translation, faulty like any
                                        translation: to make the text come to the reader, or better
                                        perhaps, to his listener just like come to the traveler
                                        these statues or these light columns in the crystalline air
                                        of Greece, especially when they surprise him completely
                                        unexpected; but even when expected, they surprise him, as
                                        they come from far away to speak although just perceived.
                                        They remain apart, but the distance from them to us is also
                                        a radiant link.</quote>
                                    <ptr target="#jaccottet1955"/>
                                </cit></note></quote></p>
                    <p>Figures 23 and 24 show an alignment around Jaccottet’s text and a small part
                        of the same text tokenized in blocks in the interface. </p>
                    <p>The program we made was extremely effective at analysing and identifying
                        different trends and patterns in a range of French translations from the
                        16th to the 20th century. Thanks to our efforts in alignment and improvement
                        of NLP tools within a single interface, we tried to give the common user
                        access to potentially enriched literary analysis. This has only been a
                        sample, but we hope to develop both our corpus (in different languages) and
                        our tools in future months. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion and future work</head>
                <p>Translation studies, but other fields as well, would benefit from such a
                    quantitative and qualitative approach, as many researchers would not have to
                    rely on intuition or personal estimation of manual comparisons, but could have
                    access to actual quantitative and qualitative results and facts, that could not
                    be obtained otherwise. Here we gave an example of a possible diachronic
                    interpretation done with the help of such a tool. Many works on the history of
                        translation<note>See for example, apart from Antoine Berman and Henri
                        Meschonnic, among others, the complete and thorough collection <title
                            rend="italic">Histoire des Traductions en Langue Française</title>, <ptr
                            target="#chevrel2012"/>, <ptr target="#chevrel2014"/></note> have been
                    printed where the researchers’ potential could not be given its full expression
                    due to the lack of data or the massive aspect of the analyzed corpus. Although
                    our work is still in progress, our goal is to fill that gap. </p>
                <p>In our analysis we tried to show that there is a tangible and possibly
                    explainable evolution in the way French translators saw and practised
                    translation from the 16th to the 20th century. At the beginning, when the
                    Homeric text was barely known and barely accessible in common language,
                    translation was more a matter of <foreign xml:lang="la">imitatio</foreign> than
                    proper <foreign xml:lang="la">translatio</foreign>. The source text would be
                    used as a moral pivot to enhance the inner stylistic value of the target
                    language. Translations were then quite far from the original, both because Greek
                    language was very poorly known, and because there was a need for a national
                    poetry that could not be satisfied by merely copying <foreign xml:lang="la">pro
                        verbo</foreign>. This perpetual adaptation and, some might say, mutilation
                    of the Greek text found its counterpart later on in a renewed interest in the
                    Greek text itself. This view led to the idea that the original text needed to be
                    re-evaluated and cleaned of all its modern modifications. Following this, there
                    was a movement to make the Greek language and Greek archaeological culture more
                    accessible to scholars and the wider public. Translations were then nearer to
                    their source and more respectful of its historical foundation. This new
                    scholarly interest in the Greek itself led to a wider grammatical and scientific
                    study of the language both in universities and schools. All translations of the
                    19th century are conditioned by this new linguistic approach, less and less
                    caring about its moral potential teachings. But the knowledge of the Greek,
                    precisely because of this grammatical and linguistic specialisation, was
                    progressively confined to a more restricted and scholarly area. The Homeric
                    epics became considered, especially after the First and Second World Wars of the
                    20th century, both as a poem and as a document. Therefore, up to Jaccottet’s and
                    Mugler’s translation, it did not lose its poetical value, but it was more
                    recently perceived as some forgotten sound, some echo of a culture that is
                    nowadays lost and that one cannot pretend to fully adapt to modern times. </p>
                <p>The program discussed in this paper has a variety of applications depending on
                    the interests of the researcher. These applications include analysing individual
                    authorial style or analysing the style of individual translations; they also
                    include comparing translations with the source text as well as comparing
                    different translations. The analysis presented in this paper is focused on a
                    short sample of the <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> and various
                    translations. A longer work would be able to address questions of whether these
                    translations are representative of contemporary literary fashions and styles, as
                    well as common cultural conceptions of the eras in which they were written. </p>
                <p>If these results are interesting in one language, it would be even better to
                    conduct research on diachronic translation corpora in different languages. Since
                    the alignment program works for many European idioms, similar research would be
                    possible using the same system. Aligning multilingual translations we could both
                    compare the features of contemporary translators in different languages aligned
                    to the original text and align different translators between themselves (for
                    example, we could align Madame Dacier’s <title rend="italic">Iliade</title> with
                    Casanova’s <title rend="italic">Iliade</title>), a direct way to compare styles
                    and approaches. We would like to compare, for example, the set of French
                    translations of the 11th book with a small group of Italian translations of the
                    same text, to identify unique and different trends in different languages. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <!-- Encode each bibliographic item as <bibl>, and delete dummy record below. @xml:id and @label are required. All values for @xml:id should be lower-case. -->
                <bibl xml:id="allauzen2009" label="Allauzen 2009">Allauzen, A., Wisniewski, G.
                    "Modèles discriminants pour l’alignement mot-à-mot", <title rend="italic"
                        >Traitement Automatique des Langues</title>, 50 (2009): 173–203.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berard1933" label="Bérard 1933">Bérard, V., Boissonnas, F. <title
                        rend="italic">Dans le sillage d’Ulysse (photographies de Fred.
                        Boissonnas)</title>. Librairie Armand Colin (1933).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berard1924" label="Bérard 1924">Bérard, V. <title rend="italic"
                        >L'Odyssée: Chants VIII - XV</title>. Les Belles Lettres (1924).</bibl>
                <!--NOT REFERENCED IN TEXT-->
                <bibl xml:id="berard1927" label="Bérard 1927">Bérard, V., Bérard, A. <title
                        rend="italic">Les Navigations d’Ulysse</title>. Armand Colin (1927).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bitaube1764" label="Bitaubé 1764">Bitaubé, PJ. <title rend="italic"
                        >L’Iliade: Traduction Nouvelle, Précedée De Réflexions Sur Homere</title>.
                    Prault (1764).</bibl>
                <!--NOT REFERENCED IN TEXT-->
                <bibl xml:id="boschetti2013" label="Boschetti 2013">Boschetti, F. "Acquisizione e
                    Creazione di Risorse Plurilingui per gli Studi di Filologia Classica in Ambienti
                    Collaborativi.” In M. Agosti and F. Tomasi (eds), <title rend="italic"
                        >Collaborative Research Practices and Shared Infrastructures for Humanities
                        Computing, Proceedings of Revised Papers AIUCD</title> (2013).</bibl>
                <!--NOT REFERENCED IN TEXT-->
                <bibl xml:id="boschetti2009" label="Boschetti 2009">Boschetti, F., Romanello, M.,
                    Babeu, A., Bamman, D. and Crane, G. "Improving OCR accuracy for classical
                    critical editions", In <title rend="italic">International Conference on Theory
                        and Practice of Digital Libraries</title>. Springer (2009), pp.
                    156–167.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boitel1638" label="Boitel 1638">Boitel, C. <title rend="italic">L’
                        Odissee D’Homere</title>. La Coste (1638).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brown2003" label="Brown 2003">Brown, P. F., Pietra S. A. D., Pietra V.
                    J. D., Mercer R. L. “The mathematics of statistical machine translation:
                    parameter estimation”, <title rend="italic">Computational linguistics</title>,
                    19 (1993): 263–311.</bibl>

                <bibl label="Certon 1604" xml:id="certon1604">Certon, S., <title rend="italic"
                        >L'Odyssée d'Homère au Roy, de la version de Salomon Certon</title>,
                    Langelier, (1604).</bibl>


                <bibl xml:id="chevrel2012" label="Chevrel 2012">Chevrel, Y., Hulst, L d’., Lombez,
                    C. (eds), <title rend="italic">Histoire des traductions en langue française, XVe
                        et XVIe siècles</title>. Verdier, Lagrasse (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chevrel2012a" label="Chevrel 2012a">Chevrel, Y., Hulst, L d’., Lombez,
                    C. (eds), <title rend="italic">Histoire des traductions en langue française,
                        XIXe siècle</title>. Verdier, Lagrasse (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chevrel2014" label="Chevrel 2014">Chevrel, Y., Cointre, A.,
                    Tran-Gervat, YM. (eds), <title rend="italic">Histoire des traductions en langue
                        française, XVIIe et XVIIIe siècles</title>. Verdier (2014).</bibl>
                <!--NOT REFERENCED IN TEXT-->
                <bibl xml:id="colonne1476" label="Colonne 1476">Colonne, G. <title rend="italic"
                        >Historia destructionis Troiae</title>. Van Westfalen, Johannes
                    (1476).</bibl>
                <!--NOT REFERENCED IN TEXT-->
                <bibl xml:id="dacier1692" label="Dacier 1692">Dacier, A. <title rend="italic"
                        >Comédies grecques [d’Aristophane]</title>. G. Gallet (1692).</bibl>
                <!--NOT REFERENCED IN TEXT-->
                <bibl xml:id="dacier1699" label="Dacier 1699">Dacier, A. <title rend="italic">Les
                        poesies d’Anacreon et de Sapho, traduites de grec an françois, avec des
                        remarques. Par Madame Dacier</title>. chez Paul Marret, marchand libraire
                    dans le Beurs-Straat, à la renommée (1699).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dacier1712" label="Dacier 1712">Dacier, A. <title rend="italic"
                        >Ilias</title>. Aux dépens de la Compagnie (1712).</bibl>
                <!--NOT REFERENCED IN TEXT-->
                <bibl xml:id="dacier1714" label="Dacier 1714">Dacier, A. <title rend="italic">Des
                        causes de la corruption du goust</title>. Rigaud (1714).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dacier1717" label="Dacier 1717">Dacier, A. <title rend="italic"
                        >L’Odyssée d’Homère</title>. aux dêpens de la Compagnie (1717).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dechelotte2007" label="Déchelotte 2007">Déchelotte, D., Schwenk, H.,
                    Bonneau-Maynard, H., et al. "A state-of-the-art statistical Machine Translation
                    System based on Moses", In <title rend="italic">MT Summit</title>. (2007), pp.
                    127–133.</bibl>
                <!--NOT REFERENCED IN TEXT-->
                <bibl xml:id="dekker2011" label="Dekker 2011">Dekker, RH., Middell, G.
                    "Computer-Supported Collation with CollateX: Managing Textual Variance in an
                    Environment with Varying Requirements", <title rend="italic">Supporting Digital
                        Humanities</title>, (2011): 17–18.</bibl>
                <!--NOT REFERENCED IN TEXT-->
                <bibl xml:id="dekker2015" label="Dekker 2015">Dekker, RH., Van Hulle, D., Middell,
                    G., et al. "Computer-supported collation of modern manuscripts: CollateX and the
                    Beckett Digital Manuscript Project", <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in
                        the Humanities</title>, 30 (2015): 452–470.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gabbrielli2010" label="Gabbrielli 2010">Gabbrielli, M., Martini, S.
                        <title rend="italic">Programming Languages: Principles and
                    Paradigms</title>. First. Springer London (2010).</bibl>

                <bibl label="Gale 1991" xml:id="gale1991">Gale, William A., and Kenneth Ward Church.
                        <title rend="quotes">Identifying Word Correspondences in Parallel
                        Texts</title>. <title rend="italic">HLT</title>. Vol. 91, (1991).</bibl>


                <bibl xml:id="gamma1995" label="Gamma 1995">Gamma, E., Helm, R., Johnson, R., et al.
                        <title rend="italic">Design Patterns: Elements of Reusable Object-oriented
                        Software</title>. Addison-Wesley Longman Publishing Co., Inc., Boston, MA,
                    USA (1995).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gao2011" label="Gao 2011">Gao, Q., Lewis, W., Quirk, C., et al.
                    "Incremental training and intentional over-fitting of word alignment", <title
                        rend="italic">Proceedings of the Thirteenth Machine Translation
                        Summit</title>, (2011): 106–113.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gao2008" label="Gao 2008">Gao, Q., Vogel, S. "Parallel implementations
                    of word alignment tool", In <title rend="italic">Software Engineering, Testing,
                        and Quality Assurance for Natural Language Processing</title>. Association
                    for Computational Linguistics (2008), pp. 49–57.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gao2008a" label="Gao 2008a">Gao, Q., Vogel, S. "Parallel
                    implementations of word alignment tool", In <title rend="italic">Software
                        Engineering, Testing, and Quality Assurance for Natural Language
                        Processing</title>. Association for Computational Linguistics (2008), pp.
                    49–57.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="garnier2002" label="Garnier 2002">Garnier, B. "Anne Dacier, un esprit
                    moderne au pays des Anciens", <title rend="italic">Portraits de
                        traductrices</title>, (2002): 13–54.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="germann2016" label="Germann 2016">Germann, U. "Bilingual document
                    alignment with latent semantic indexing", In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                        the First Conference on Machine Translation</title>. (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gomaa2013" label="Gomaa 2013">Gomaa, WH., Fahmy, AA. "A survey of text
                    similarity approaches", <title rend="italic">International Journal of Computer
                        Applications</title>, 68 (2013).</bibl>
                <!--NOT REFERENCED IN TEXT-->
                <bibl xml:id="hasan2007" label="Hasan 2007">Hasan, FM., Uzzaman, N., Khan, M.
                    "Comparison of different POS Tagging Techniques (N-Gram, HMM and Brill’s tagger)
                    for Bangla", In <title rend="italic">Advances and Innovations in Systems,
                        Computing Sciences and Software Engineering</title>. Springer (2007), pp.
                    121–126.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="henning2009" label="Henning 2009">Henning, M. "API Design Matters",
                        <title rend="italic">Communications of the ACM</title>, 52 (2009):
                    46–56.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hepp1968" label="Hepp 1968">Hepp, N. <title rend="italic">Homère en
                        France au XVIIe siècle</title>. (1968).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lamotte1714" label="Houdart de La Motte 1714"> Houdart de La Motte, A.
                        <title rend="italic">L’Iliade: poëme</title>. Gr. Dupuis (1714).</bibl>

                <bibl label="Leconte de Lisle 1867" xml:id="leconte1867">Leconte de Lisle, C. M. R.,
                        <title rend="italic">L’Odyssée, traduction nouvelle par Leconte de
                        Lisle</title>, Lemerre (1867).</bibl>


                <bibl xml:id="jaccottet1955" label="Jaccottet 1955">Jaccottet, P., Hartog, F. <title
                        rend="italic">"Homère:«L’Odyssée»", Paris, Club français du livre
                        (traduction qu’a reprise, en 1982, la Librairie François Maspéro, puis, en
                        1992, La Découverte)</title>, (1955).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lebrun1819" label="Lebrun 1819">Lebrun, C-F. <title rend="italic"
                        >Odyssée, traduite en français par le Prince Lebrun</title>. Ch. Gosselin
                    (1819).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="list2013" label="List 2013">List, J-M., Moran, S. "An Open Source
                    Toolkit for Quantitative Historical Linguistics.", In <title rend="italic">ACL
                        (Conference System Demonstrations)</title>. (2013), pp. 13–18.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ma2006" label="Ma 2006">Ma, X. "Champollion: A robust parallel text
                    sentence aligner", In <title rend="italic">LREC 2006: Fifth International
                        Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation</title>. (2006), pp.
                    489–492.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="maffei1523" label="Maffei 1523">Maffei, R. <title rend="italic">Homeri
                        Odyssea</title>. Hittorpius (1523).</bibl>
                <!--NOT REFERENCED IN TEXT-->
                <bibl xml:id="manmatha2006" label="Manmatha 2006">Manmatha, R., Feng, S. "A
                    hierarchical, HMM-based automatic evaluation of OCR accuracy for a digital
                    library of books", In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 6th ACM/IEEE-CS
                        Joint Conference on Digital Libraries (JCDL’06)</title>. IEEE (2006), pp.
                    109–118.</bibl>
                <!--NOT REFERENCED IN TEXT-->
                <bibl xml:id="manning2014" label="Manning 2014">Manning, CD., Surdeanu, M., Bauer,
                    J., et al. "The Stanford CoreNLP Natural Language Processing Toolkit.", In
                        <title rend="italic">ACL (System Demonstrations)</title>. (2014), pp.
                    55–60.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="meschonnic1999" label="Meschonnic 1999">Meschonnic, H. <title
                        rend="italic">Poétique du traduire</title>. Editions Verdier (1999).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="michaud1843" label="Michaud 1843">Michaud, LG., Desplaces, E.
                    "Bitaubé", In <title rend="italic">Biographie universelle, ancienne et moderne,
                        ouvrage rédigé par une société de gens de lettres</title>. (1843), pp.
                    376–378.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="monro1902" label="Monro 1902">Monro, DB., Allen, TW. <title
                        rend="italic">Homeri Opera, recognovit brevique adnotatione critica
                        instruxit</title>. Scriptorum Classicorum Bibliotheca Oxoniensis. E
                    typographeo Clarendoniano, Charles Baley (1902).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="montalbetti1997" label="Montalbetti 1997">Montalbetti, C. "La réalité
                    peut-elle être homérique ? Les filtres de la fiction", In <title rend="italic"
                        >Le voyage, le monde et la bibliothèque</title>. Presses universitaires de
                    France (1997).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="needleman1970" label="Needleman 1970">Needleman, SB., Wunsch, CD. "A
                    general method applicable to the search for similarities in the amino acid
                    sequence of two proteins", <title rend="italic">Journal of molecular
                        biology</title>, 48 (1970): 443–453.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nelken2006" label="Nelken 2006">Nelken, R., Shieber, SM. "Towards
                    Robust Context-Sensitive Sentence Alignment for Monolingual Corpora.", In <title
                        rend="italic">EACL</title>. (2006).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="och2003" label="Och 2003">Och, FJ., Ney, H. "A systematic comparison
                    of various statistical alignment models", <title rend="italic">Computational
                        linguistics</title>, 29 (2003): 19–51.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="och1999" label="Och 1999">Och, FJ., Tillmann, C., Ney, H. "Improved
                    alignment models for statistical machine translation", In <title rend="italic"
                        >Proceedings of the Joint SIGDAT Conf. on Empirical Methods in Natural
                        Language Processing and Very Large Corpora</title>. (1999), pp.
                    20–28.</bibl>
                <!--NOT REFERENCED IN TEXT-->
                <bibl xml:id="openNLP2011" label="OpenNLP, A. 2011">OpenNLP, A. "Apache software
                    foundation", URL http://opennlp.apache.org, (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="reiter2014" label="Reiter 2014">Reiter, N. "Discovering Structural
                    Similarities in Narrative Texts using Event Alignment Algorithms".
                    (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="robert2000" label="Robert 2000">Robert, MC. "Design principles and
                    design patterns". <title rend="italic">Object Mentor</title>, (2000):
                    1–34.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="salel1545" label="Salel 1545">Salel, H. <title rend="italic">Les Dix
                        premiers livres de l’Iliade d’Homere, prince des poetes : Traduictz en vers
                        Francois, par M. Hugues Salel...</title> Jean Loys pour Vincent Sertenas
                    (1545).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sommer1854" label="Sommer 1854">Sommer, E. <title rend="italic"
                        >L’Odyssée: chants</title>, 2, 6, 9 à 12. Hachette (1854).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tulach2008" label="Tulach 2008">Tulach, J. <title rend="italic"
                        >Practical API Design: Confessions of a Java Framework Architect</title>.
                    1st ed. Apress, Berkely, CA, USA (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lavalterie1708" label="de la Valterie 1708">de la Valterie, A.
                    "Préface", In <title rend="italic">L’Iliade</title>. (1708), pp. 1–16.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lavalterie1709" label="de la Valterie 1709">de la Valterie, A. <title
                        rend="italic">L’Odyssée D’Homere. Traduite En Francois. Par M. D*** Enrichie
                        de Figures en Taille Douce</title>. Chez Michel Brunet (1709).</bibl>
                <!--NOT REFERENCED IN TEXT-->
                <bibl xml:id="viterbi1967" label="Viterbi 1967">Viterbi, A. "Error bounds for
                    convolutional codes and an asymptotically optimum decoding algorithm". <title
                        rend="italic">IEEE transactions on Information Theory</title>, 13 (1967):
                    260–269.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="volney1799" label="Volney 1799">Volney, CF. "Leçons d’Histoire". In
                    Lecons d’histoire prononcees a l’ecole normale ... accompagnees de notes et de 3
                    plans (etc.). Brosson (1799), p. 230.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
