<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">German Narratives in International Television Format
               Adaptations: Comparing <title rend="italic">Du und Ich</title> (ZDF 2002) with <title
                  rend="italic">Un Gars</title>, <title rend="italic">Une Fille</title> (Quebec
               1997-2002)</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Edward <dhq:family>Larkey</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Maryland, Baltimore County</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>larkey@umbc.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Edward Larkey received his MA in Modern German Literature from the Universität
                     Marburg in 1978 and his Dr. Phil in Cultural Studies (Kulturwissenschaft) from
                     the Humboldt-Universität Berlin in 1986. He was Professor of German Studies and
                     Intercultural Communication at the University of Maryland, Baltimore County
                     (USA) until 2020 and is currently Professor Emeritus. He is the author of
                        <title rend="italic">Pungent Sounds: Constructing Identity with Popular
                        Music in Austria</title> (Peter Lang 1993) and <title rend="italic">Rotes
                        Rockradio: Populäre Musik und die Kommerzialisierung des
                        DDR-Rundfunks</title> (LIT-Verlag 2007) and many articles in English and
                     German on transnational issues in German language popular music. His more
                     recent work is devoted to comparing transnational television format adaptations
                     and developing culturally critical methodologies of cross-cultural comparison.
                     These incorporate computer annotation and visualization software toward
                     developing a multimodal methodology for cross-cultural comparisons of different
                     versions of television format adaptations.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000545</idno>
            <idno type="volume">015</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <date when="2021-05-21">21 May 2021</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
      	<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target=
      		"https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000545/000545.xml">GitHub
      	</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>This article cross-culturally compares the German remake of the Quebec sketch
               comedy/sitcom series <title rend="italic">Un Gars, Une Fille</title> ("A Guy and a
               Girl") the the original version by correlating quantitative data derived from the
               Adobe Premiere Pro annotation function on the duration of narrative segments and
               incorporating these data into a an interpretation of family conflict management
               strategies, gender roles and conflicts between the mother-in-law and the the young
               30-something couple as protagonists. The article examines a scene in which the
               daughter confronts her mother's trauma-inducing behavior on her as a young girl, and
               the boyfriend confronts the mother-in-law's animosity toward him. The article delves
               into the background for the transactional, belligerent, and obligational thinking
               behind the family relationship of the German couple compared to the more affectionate
               and conciliatory relationship in all other versions. The investigation postulates
               that the family relationships in the German context must be seen within the context
               of the <title rend="italic">Inability to Mourn</title>, a major psychological study
               by Margarete and Alexander Mitscherlich in the 1960s of politically salient post
               World War 2 trauma among a large variety of social groups in West (and East) Germany.
               The emotional repression as a result of various forms of guilt, which never
               explicitly surfaced in the confrontations, was passed down from generation to
               generation, while this same, or similar social psychological contexts was seemingly
               not a factor in other countries, many of which had also experienced repressive
               dictatorships during World War 2 and afterwards, in which adaptations of these series
               were produced. Further collaborative investigations would be required to uncover the
               reasons for this discrepancy.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>A comparison of the Quebec sitcom <title rend="italic">Un Gars, Une Fille</title> ("A
               Guy and a Girl") to its German remake using Adobe Premiere Pro annotation software
               and in the context of post-WWII emotional repression.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>The proliferation of global television formats since the 1950s, particularly those of
            scripted fictional narratives and their local adaptations, raise important questions
            about the nature and content of global culture and discourses, and the local
            contributions to those discourses. Each iteration is the result of cultural, historical,
            political, technical, and economic conditions specific to each country, and help
            determine how culturally, aesthetically, and discursively proxemic local narratives are
            created. German producers have long participated in the global format trade, both
            officially and <q>inofficially.</q> The German adaptation of the US crime series <title
               rend="italic">Dragnet</title> in the 1950s, known as <title rend="italic"
               >Stahlnetz</title>, became paradigmatic for a long tradition of German crime shows
            currently still popular, such as the West German <title rend="italic">Tatort</title>
            (ARD from 1971), and the East German <title rend="italic">Polizeiruf 110</title>, and
            the plethora of similar shows currently on both public service broadcasters ARD and ZDF,
            as well as their private broadcasting counterparts. Some of the more successful and
            popular ones, such as <title rend="italic">Ein Herz und eine Seele</title> (1973-1976),
            a loose adaptation of the British series <title rend="italic">Till Death Us Do
               Part</title> (BBC1 1965-1975), may not be immediately recognizable as an adaptation,
            and some of them, such as <title rend="italic">Lindenstrasse</title> (ARD 1985-2020) or
               <title rend="italic">Gute Zeiten Schlechte Zeiten</title> RTL 1992-) may have long
            surpassed the broadcast period of the original and therefore have become shows in their
            own right. </p>
         <figure>
            <head>List of different versions of <title rend="italic">Un Gars, Une Fille</title> and
               the dates of their first broadcast. Table courtesy of Avanti Cine Group.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/table01.jpg"/>
         </figure>
         <p>Some of the more recent prominent adaptations in German television like <title
               rend="italic">Verliebt in Berlin</title> (ZDF 2006-2008), adapted from the Colombian
            telenovela <title rend="italic">Yo soy Betty, la fea</title> (RCN 1999-2001), or <title
               rend="italic">Stromberg</title> (ProSieben 2004-2012), adapted from the Ricky
            Gervais/Steve Merchant UK mockumentary comedy <title rend="italic">The Office</title>
            (BBC2 2001-2003), are more or less recognizable adaptations of the originals. With the
            popularity and expansion of particular genres such as doctor and hospital dramas and
            comedies, it is sometimes difficult to determine if a series such as <title
               rend="italic">In aller Freundschaft-Die jungen Ärzte</title> (ARD 2015-) is an
            adaptation of the US <title rend="italic">Grey’s Anatomy</title> (ABC 2005) as is the
            clearly identifiable Turkish series <title rend="italic">Doktorlar</title> (Show TV
            2006-2011) of the Colombian <title rend="italic">El Corazon Abierto</title> (RCN
            2010-2011). </p>
         <p>Less successful adaptations have also been attempted on German television. The UK doctor
            series <title rend="italic">Doc Martin</title> (ITV 2004 -), adapted for German
            television as <title rend="italic">Doktor Martin</title> (ZDF 2006-2009) starring Axel
            Milberg, was cancelled after two seasons, while the US sitcom <title rend="italic"
               >Married with Children</title> (Fox 1987-1997), known in its German adaptation <title
               rend="italic">Hilfe, meine Familie spinnt</title> (1993), was less successful and
            unable to achieve the success of adaptations or the original in other markets such as
            the Russian, Argentinian, Chilean, or Colombian. Among the less successfully adapted
            series on German television was the adaptation of the Quebec series <title rend="italic"
               >Un Gars, Une Fille</title> (Radio Canada 1997-2002). Since the series went on to be
            successfully adapted in a wide variety of other markets up to the present, I believe it
            warrants a comparative investigation into factors which may or may not have contributed
            to its lack of success. The series started out in Quebec as a 6-10 minute stopgap sketch
            comedy show between primary half-hour or hour-long shows. Later, it was transformed into
            a half-hour sitcom-like comedy incorporating the separate sketch segments. While the
            French, Italian, and Spanish adaptations retain the same or similar sketch comedy
            length, most of the other adaptations, including the German, incorporate three such
            sketches to create a half-hour sitcom-like structure. In the twenty-year history of
            adapting the format (see Table 1 for the official versions), it has undergone some
            changes, but still retains its basic structure and sequencing.</p>
         <p>The current study will investigate adaptations from the standpoint of creating the
            content and structure of the adaptation as a hybrid narrative subject to analytical
            deconstruction and reconstruction by means of computer annotation software. For the
            purposes of the analysis in this study, Chalaby’s definition of a television format will
            be used, which, even though he applies it to reality and other non-scripted series, can
            also be applied to scripted dramas and comedies such as <title rend="italic">Un Gars,
               Une Fille</title>. Chalaby (2011) defines a format as <quote rend="inline">a show
               that can generate a distinctive narrative and is licensed outside its country of
               origin in order to be adapted to local audiences</quote>
            <ptr target="#chalaby2011" loc="296"/>. Chalaby’s definition includes also a narrative
            component and he refers to the concept used by the Format Recognition and Protection
            Association (FRAPA) that includes <quote rend="inline">a distinctive narrative
               progression</quote>
            <ptr target="#chalaby2011" loc="294"/>, <quote rend="inline">dramatic arcs,</quote>
            <quote rend="inline">storylines,</quote> and <quote rend="inline">trigger
               moments</quote>
            <ptr target="#chalaby2011" loc="295"/>. Chalaby cites Michel Rodrigue, one of the
            driving forces behind the international distribution of <title rend="italic">Un Gars,
               Une Fille</title>, who Chalaby also calls <quote rend="inline">one of the industry’s
               founding fathers</quote> to highlight the inherently transnational nature of formats.
            According to Rodrigue, a series becomes a format <quote rend="inline">only once it is
               adopted outside its country of origin</quote>
            <ptr target="#chalaby2011" loc="295"/>. A format entails <quote rend="inline">a transfer
               of expertise</quote> (Page 3 Top) contained in a set of rules of international and
            local knowledge passed down to the producers in a <q>bible.</q> Therefore, formats are
            hybrid and function as bridges to <quote rend="inline">take viewers through a succession
               of emotional states.</quote></p>
         <figure>
            <head>Bar graph of Part 1 of the Mother-in-Law scene illustrating shot length (in
               percentage) of the scene, with the smaller blue-colored fields indicating the
               transitions between the shots. The longest segments in most versions is the last
               light-brown colored segment which is the confrontation between the boyfriend and the
               mother-in-law. That has been excluded from the German version.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
         </figure>
         <figure>
            <head>Bar graph of Part 2 of the Mother-in-Law scene showing the longest shot to be the
               mother-daughter talk about trauma, a segment which has been excluded from the German
               version.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
         </figure>
         <p>There are digital instruments available for measuring shot length (<ref
               target="http://www.cinemetrics.lv">www.cinemetrics.lv</ref>) recognizing facial
            characteristics such that male and female characters may be distinguished and their
            screen times measured (<ref target="http://neurotechnology.com"
               >http://neurotechnology.com</ref>). There are also digital instruments, both
            commercial (Atlas.ti and MMA Video) and open source (ELAN, Anvil), which assist in the
            measurement of different kinds of segments to reveal specific localization strategies
            underlying success or lack thereof. The current project uses Adobe Premiere and Final
            Cut to multimodally compare the German <title rend="italic">Du und ich</title> with the
            Quebecois original and counterpart <title rend="italic">Un Gars, Une Fille</title>. The
            bar graph for Part 1 and Part 2 of the mother-in-law scene were developed using the
            annotation function of Adobe Premiere Pro, the results of which were tables of segment
            lengths after exporting to Microsoft Excel. In Excel, the tables were transformed into
            bar graphs that are displayed here.</p>
         <p>A multimodal investigation is appropriate since the entire range of modes of
            communication may be deployed in culturally salient ways in order to achieve what I am
            calling, with <ref target="#uribe-johngbloed2014">Uribe-Jungbloed and Medina
               (2014)</ref>, discursive proximity. Multimodal scholar Kay O’Halloran was a leading
            figure in the development of the video annotation software MMA-Image and MMA-Video. The
            software was developed at the Multimodal Analysis Lab in the Interactive and Digital
            Media Institute at the National University of Singapore and was designed to use a <quote
               rend="inline">multimodal digital semiotics approach involving the development of
               interactive software with functionalities for systematic multimodal analysis of text,
               images, and videos</quote>
            <ptr target="#ohalloran2016" loc="387"/>. In asserting that transcription is
            transduction, <ref target="#flewitt2013" loc="52">Flewitt et al (2013: 52)</ref>, point
            to the challenge of balancing <quote rend="inline">the accurate notation of
               events,</quote> the <quote rend="inline">clear description for the research
                  <q>reader,</q> and the transcription format adequate for the research purpose
               while doing justice to the type of data collected</quote>
            <ptr target="#flewitt2013" loc="50"/>. According to them, the use of annotation software
            results in <quote rend="inline">reduced versions of observed reality, where some details
               are prioritized and others are left out</quote>
            <ptr target="#flewitt2013" loc="50"/>. Television scholar Jeremy Butler, whose book
            employs a narratological approach to the study of televisual texts, investigated the use
            of digitally generated statistical data to study the editing style of the sitcom <title
               rend="italic">Happy Days</title> (1974-1984) with the online Shot Logger software
               <ref target="http://www.shotlogger.org">www.shotlogger.org</ref> to measure and
            compare cutting rates of season 1 and season 2 to determine a statistically significant
            difference between them due to the switch from a single to a multiple camera production
               <ptr target="#butler2014"/>.</p>
         <figure>
            <head>Illustration of the anomalous characteristics of the German version: Notice only
               one part of the Mother-in-Law visit scene instead of the two parts of the other
               versions. It is also little more than half the length of the longer pre-visit
               segments.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/table02.jpg"/>
         </figure>
         <p>Relevant approaches to cross-cultural and critical study of multimodality in my own work
            use concepts of <ref target="#jewitt2016">Jewitt (2016)</ref> for understanding general
            principles of multimodality in their interaction with each other in multimodal ensembles
            which are intentionally selected and configured for particular — and in our case
            cross-culturally salient — types of meaning making <ptr target="#jewitt2016" loc="15"/>,
            especially the interaction of image and writing <ptr target="#jewitt2016" loc="13"/>.
               <ref target="#bateman2011">Bateman and Schmidt (2011)</ref> are pertinent for cross-
            cultural film and television studies, since — derived from Metz, Bordwell, and others —
            they explicate the importance of and expound upon the notions of shots, scenes,
            spatiality, temporality and sequentiality underlying cross-cultural film and television
            analyses which include qualitative and quantitative data. Finally, <ref
               target="#machin2013">Machin (2013)</ref> assists in developing a methodology for
            cross-cultural multimodal critical discourse analysis. For him, critical discourse
            studies represent not only <quote rend="inline">a kind of knowledge about what goes on
               in a particular social practice, ideas about why it is the way it is and what is to
               be done,</quote> but also reveal <quote rend="inline">models of the world and why
               these are legitimate and reasonable ways of acting in the world</quote>
            <ptr target="#machin2013" loc="352"/>. I am therefore multimodally extending the notion
            of cultural proximity proposed by <ref target="#straubhaar2005">Straubhaar and La
               Pastina (2005)</ref> which is <quote rend="inline">at work at multiple levels due to
               peoples’ complex identities beyond linguistic, religious, geographic or other group
               cultures based on dress, ethnicity, gestures, humor etc.</quote>
            <ptr target="#machin2013" loc="274"/>, whereby audiences will prefer television programs
            that are <quote rend="inline">most proximate or most directly relevant to them in
               cultural and linguistic terms</quote>
            <ptr target="#machin2013" loc="273"/>. <ref target="#vankeulen2016">Van Keulen
               (2016)</ref> introduces the notion of aesthetic proximity to address the fact that
            certain technologically- based aesthetic components of audiovisual texts go beyond the
            linguistic and cultural systematic patterns to encompass the entire range of modes of
            communication in the adaptation process.</p>
         <figure>
            <head>Screen shot of video clips of nine different versions of <title rend="italic">Un
                  Gars Une Fille</title> (l to r, upper to lower: Quebec, Serb, Israeli, Polish,
               Ukrainian, Turkish, Latvian, Russian, Bulgarian) showing the use of the same music
               segment at different points in the narrative of the crucial confrontation scene
               between the boyfriend and the mother-in-law. The music indicates sympathy for the
               different characters in or outside the frame in the confrontation. The music cue
               therefore complete changes the focus of identification purely by its insertion at
               different times during the shot.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
         </figure>
         <figure>
            <head>Screen shot of Final Cut Pro timeline with the Mother-in-Law scene(s) of the
               one-part German series <title rend="italic">Du und ich</title> on top, and the
               two-part Quebec series scenes in <title rend="italic">Un Gars, Une Fille</title> on
               the bottom.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
         </figure>
         <figure>
            <head>Final Cut Pro timeline with Mother-in-Law scene(s) showing exploded view of the
               German series <title rend="italic">Du und ich</title> lined up with the corresponding
               segments in <title rend="italic">Un Gars, Une Fille</title>.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
         </figure>
         <p>The confluence of cross-culturality, multimodality and narratology is evident in Jeremy
            Butler’s characterization of the televisual text as polysemic, but he states the
            televisual text <quote rend="inline">does not present all meanings equally
               positively</quote> and explains that meanings are adjusted differently <quote
               rend="inline">through dialogue, acting styles, music, and other attributes of the
               text</quote>
            <ptr target="#butler2007" loc="10"/>. Butler also points out that the televisual text is
            implicitly structured in a pattern to be polysemic but reflects and supports those in a
            position of political power while allowing space for alternative or contested meanings
               <ptr target="#butler2007" loc="11"/>. Multimodal research aims for systematic
            interpretative analysis of televisual and filmic texts by <quote rend="inline">finding
               systems of contrasts that organize and pre-structure filmic devices</quote>
            <ptr target="#bateman2011"/>. The assumption underlying the research comparing the
            German <title rend="italic">Du und ich</title> with <title rend="italic">Un Gars, Une
               Fille</title> is that different modes and complexes of modes of communication are
            interculturally salient and are the component of a multimodal cross-cultural critical
            analysis.</p>
         <p>My own previous cross-cultural comparative research has identified different types of
            adaptation based on similarities and differences in narrative structure, content, and
            sequencing <ptr target="#larkey2016"/> of various adaptations, including <title
               rend="italic">Verliebt in Berlin</title> (2009a) and <title rend="italic"
               >Stromberg</title> (2009b), and other versions of <title rend="italic">Un Gars, Une
               Fille</title>. This research created a typology of adaptations which measured
            proximity to, or distancing from, the narrative structure, content, and sequencing of
            the original or many other adaptations.</p>
         <p>In a study entitled <title rend="quotes">Narrative as a Mode of Communication: Comparing
               TV Format Adaptations with Multimodal and Narratological Approaches,</title> (2019)
            in a volume edited by Wildfeuer, Pflaeging, Bateman, Tseng and Seizov (Eds.) entitled
               <title rend="italic">Multimodality. Towards a New Discipline</title>, I argue for
            incorporating quantitative and qualitative narratological data on the content, structure
            and sequencing into multimodal analyses of television format adaptations, using the
            example of the mother-in-law scenes in <title rend="italic">Un Gars, Une Fille</title>,
            in order to supplement multimodal hermeneutic interpretative analyses as an extra
            dimension. For this current study, I completed bar graphs (see Figures 2 and 3) of 10
            different versions which illustrated the relative lengths and durations of shots in
            percentages of total length of episodes to register culturally specific additions,
            deletions, and modifications made to the different versions to accommodate cultural
            proximity.</p>
         <figure>
            <head>Final Cut Pro timeline illustrating the gaps in the German series <title
                  rend="italic">Du und ich</title> indicating the exclusion of segments included in
               the Quebec original version, <title rend="italic">Un Gars, Une Fille</title>.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.jpg"/>
         </figure>
         <figure>
            <head>Final Cut Pro timeline showing how the additional segments thee German series
                  <title rend="italic">Du und ich</title> line up with the Quebec original version
               of that series <title rend="italic">Un Gars, Une Fille</title>.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.jpg"/>
         </figure>
         <figure>
            <head>Screen shot of the pre-visit decision in <title rend="italic">Une Gars, Une
                  Fille</title> to visit the Mother-in-Law just before the seduction of the
               boyfriend. The intimate and endearing seduction takes place in the couple’s
               bathroom.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.jpg"/>
         </figure>
         <figure>
            <head>Screen shot of the pre-visit decision to visit the mother-in-law (<title
                  rend="italic">Du und ich</title>) to get financial support for payment of a tax
               debt. The decision takes place in the kitchen and the couple displays less affection
               than the encounter in the Quebec version.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.jpg"/>
         </figure>
         <p>One of the unsolved challenges I encountered when presenting knowledge gained from this
            methodology was the inability of current computer visualizations based on graphics,
            tables, and charts derived from Microsoft Excel to adequately display the complex
            relationships of multimodal knowledge at the heart of audiovisual texts in general, and
            different television format adaptations in particular.</p>
         <p>In recent multimodal research on the same mother-in-law scenes <ptr
               target="#larkey2019a"/>, I compared different versions of <title rend="italic">Un
               Gars, Une Fille</title> and the role of music to guide the empathy of the viewer
            toward or away from different characters in culturally specific ways by slightly
            adjusting length and position of a particular segment of sad music in the audiovisual
            text to that particular character. These findings were placed within the context of
            gender role depictions and applied the dual-concern model of family conflict management
            strategies in the mother-in-law scenes of the different versions. It was thus possible
            to determine whether, in the different versions, different family members deployed
            yielding, problem-solving, contending, or inaction strategies toward the other members
            of the family in culturally specific ways, whether it be the mother-in-law, the
            daughter, or the male protagonist. This is illustrated in the video clip in which the
            same music segment is deployed in different positions of the shot to guide sympathy or
            empathy with a different character.</p>
         <p>The <q>story</q> of <title rend="italic">Un Gars, Une Fille</title> revolves around the
            relationship and domestic lives of a heterosexual, non-married and childless
            30-something couple, who has been together for at least 15 years. Because of its sketch
            comedy heritage, most adaptation contain three scenes of approximately 7-8 minutes
            during which the couple is engaged in activities and conversations about themselves,
            friends, and relatives in a variety of spaces, including domestic spaces at home
            (kitchen, bedroom, bathroom, living room) and public spaces (shopping centers,
            restaurants, bars, art exhibits, in a car, at a police station, etc.). The scene at the
            heart of the current investigation occurs at the apartment of the female’s mother, the
            mother-in-law of the male partner. The scene is divided into two parts in most of the
            versions except the German, and each shot or topic of conversation is divided by a
            distinctive transition which is comprised of music and graphics. The scene is usually
            monospatial, i.e., it takes place in the dining room of the mother-in-law only, with a
            stationary and largely point-of-view camera in which the mother is, to varying extents,
            outside of the frame. The visit to the mother-in-law is instigated by a sex scene during
            which the daughter has to convince the partner to go with her to her mother’s, and the
            scene ends when the couple leaves the apartment of the mother-in-law with leftovers.</p>
         <div>
            <head>The German Version’s Anomalous Narrative Structure and Content: Transactional
               Relationships </head>
            <p>All of my above-mentioned investigations excluded deeper comparisons with the German
               version, for the most part, due to the anomalous nature of the German version. The
               chart in Figure 4 illustrates that the German version of the pre-visit scene, in
               which the visit to the mother-in-law is anticipated, is more the twice as long as all
               other versions at 8:14, while the visit itself, divided into two separate episodes in
               most other versions, is put into one episode in the German version, and is thus half
               the length of the others. The anomalous character of the narrative sequencing and
               structure of the German version can be seen not only in the Figure, but also when the
               German version is lined up with the Quebec version on a Final Cut Pro timeline as in
               the four illustrations (Figures 5-8).</p>
            <p>This is one of several structural, content, and sequence modifications in the German
               adaptation which give an indication of the radically different historical and
               political context of family and gender discourses in that country compared to others.
               In most of the other versions, the motivation to visit the mother-in-law can be
               traced back to the daughter’s affection and emotional bond with her mother. In order
               to convince her boyfriend/husband to visit her mother, who hates him and likewise
               hates the mother-in-law, the female partner seduces him with oral sex, filmed
               tightly-framed in a bathroom while he is shaving, brushing his teeth, or cutting the
               hair in his nose. The shot takes approximately two minutes and is usually done in a
               comical, yet intimately positive manner highlighting the affection between them. This
               can be seen in the screen shot of the Quebec version in Figure 10.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Loyalty quality of German version with a primarily obligation-oriented
                  relationship motivation vs. other versions with a more affection- oriented
                  motivation to visit the mother of the daughter.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p>In the German version, on the other hand, the visit to the mother-in-law is motivated
               by an effort to get money from the mother to pay back a tax debt discovered after the
               female protagonist discarded her partner’s receipts needed to take deductions. She
               suggests a visit to her mother to see if the mother can <q>help them out.</q> This
               transactional instrumentalization of personal and family relationships stands in
               sharp contrast to the justification for visiting the mother-in-law in all other
               versions. This story line also forms the narrative arc for the visit in the German
               version since at the end of the visit the mother-in-law merely hands the couple an
               envelope upon which the address of her ex-husband’s tax attorney is attached so that
               they might consult with him later. Even though the transactional nature of the
               relationship seems to be discredited and reproached, the disappointed expectation of
               financial support casts the mother as calculatingly miserly and selfish, which
               resignifies both the mother-daughter relationship and the couple’s relationship to
               the mother as instrumentalized and transactional. This both legitimizes the
               skepticism of the male character while simultaneously revealing traces of affection
               between the mother and the daughter during the exchange. The screen shot of the
               German version (Figure 11) illustrates the difference in atmosphere by the change in
               location (the kitchen), the topic of conversation (tax debt vs mother), and the
               physical distance between the two during the conversation (close vs. distanced).</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Obligatory vs. Affectionate Loyalty</head>
            <p><title rend="italic">Family loyalty</title> is at the root of the visit in all
               versions, but the German version portrays this loyalty largely as an obligation,
               whereas the other versions foreground affection and the empathetic emotional bond
               between mother and daughter, even though the male character is sidelined in many of
               the shots. Psychologist Müller-Hohagen (1994) defines loyalty as a <quote
                  rend="inline">system of structured ethical demands and expectations</quote>
               internalized unconsciously as a family obligation by the child which guides it
               throughout its life <ptr target="#muller-hohagen1994" loc="48"/>. The chart (Figure
               12) illustrates the dual nature of loyalty - incorporating aspects of obligation as
               well as affection and emotion - as it is realized in the different versions of the
               series. In the face of the lighthearted and ironically comical, and, for the male
               partner, self-deprecating reason to visit the mother (he states that <quote
                  rend="inline">men have no principles</quote> when the opportunity for oral sex
               arises), the German version closes with a confrontation and argument between the
               couple about how the male partner refuses to take money from the mother. The sequence
               after that shows the couple in front of the mother’s apartment door, with the (out of
               frame) mother looking through the peep hole in a point-of-view shot, listening to the
               couple continue the argument about not taking money from the mother. There is a
               noticeable lack of warmth and intimacy between the couple in the German version
               compared to others, and this behavior is continued throughout the visit, during which
               irreconcilable differences between the male partner and the mother generate
               confrontation and derisive comments from both of them. It is interesting to note that
               important sequences in the other versions are excluded in the German version. In
               these sequences, the male partner exhibits compassion and understanding for the
               mother or the daughter in spite of their differences. </p>
            <figure>
               <head>The cover of the original US-version of the book by Nancy Friday, to which
                  different local versions of <title rend="italic">Un Gars, Une Fille</title> made
                  explicit reference in many local versions, excluding the German <title
                     rend="italic">Du und ich</title>.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure11.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>The German edition of the Nancy Friday book, references to which were excluded
                  in the German <title rend="italic">Du und ich</title>.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure12.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Finally, instances of physical contact between the male and female partners - all of
               which are included in the other versions - are likewise not as prevalent in the
               German version. One of the excluded segments in the German version is a discussion
               introduced by the daughter about the Nancy Friday book <title rend="italic">My
                  Mother, My Self</title>, also published in Germany as <title rend="italic">Wie
                  meine Mutter</title> (<title rend="italic">Like My Mother</title>) <title
                  rend="italic">My Mother My Self</title>. The daughter in the other versions uses
               this book to introduce the notion of trauma perpetrated upon the daughter by the
               mother, and engage the mother in a discussion about how the mother traumatized her in
               childhood. While there are variations on the activities created the trauma in the
               different versions - washing a beloved teddy bear in bleach by accident, refusing to
               let the daughter take a bath with the father, not giving porridge to the daughter
               before the father receives his own portion during a meal - it is significant that the
               notion of trauma in these versions is an individual psychological condition inflicted
               on the daughter by the mother with no further social consequences whatsoever and no
               trace of political or historical contextualization. In all other versions, the family
               relationship is depicted as a purely mother-daughter problem.</p>
            <p>This stands in sharp contrast to notions of trauma at the heart of psychoanalytical
               practice in Germany, as well as to notions of trauma at the heart of social and
               political discourse in Germany as a result of World War II and the Nazi period. The
               lack of mention of trauma in the German version is glaring due to its prominent role
               in German historical and psychoanalytic discourse. This was intitiated by Alexander
               and Margarete Mitscherlich with their 1967 book <title rend="italic">Die Unfähigkeit
                  zu trauern</title> (<title rend="italic">The Inability to Mourn</title>) and led
               to a broad array of subsequent investigations and publications of psychoanalytic
               practice into the role and effects of trauma in the transgenerational transmission of
               historical experiences in postwar German society since the 1940s. In comparing the
               German version of <title rend="italic">Un Gars, Une Fille</title> with any one of the
               other versions, particularly those from countries whose populations were drastically
               affected by World War 2 such as France, Poland, Russia, Ukraine, Greece, Israel, and
               Italy, the political consequences of the psychological issues should be incorporated
               into the analysis. This would necessitate a much longer analysis than can be
               accomplished here.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Political Roots of German Psychological Trauma</head>
            <p>Generic concepts of trauma and traumatization focus on individual experiences
               considered potentially life-threatening. These are combined with overwhelming
               feelings of fear and helplessness, and processing is hindered by a lack of physical
               and mental or emotional resources <ptr target="#hantke2012" loc="54"/>.
               Traumatization emerges after a particular event or series of events which are
               prevented from further processing and social or physical-psychological integration by
               the individual in its aftermath <ptr target="#hantke2012" loc="56"/>. In the German
               context, trauma discourse has been applied to the postwar experiences of both victims
               and perpetrators of the Nazi period and entails a social and historical,
               transgenerational component that is intertwined with the individual experiences of
               the traumatized and their second and third generation offspring. Psychoanalysts in
               Germany, Israel and other countries have grappled with trauma among the victims and
               perpetrators.</p>
            <p><ref target="#hondrich2011">Hondrich (2011)</ref> asserts that 55 to 60% of the
               German civilian population during the war had traumatic experiences, while
               approximately 30% were traumatized. In addition, Hondrich advocates including all
               European societies in the analysis of postwar trauma because according to him these
               societies also experienced trauma but there was no effort made to speak about the
               trauma nor engage in therapies to treat it, even though it deeply penetrated the
               personal biographies of many members of most of these other European societies. For
               this reason, the methodology employed in this comparative study, which investigates
               the intimate trauma-affected interconnection and layering of the personal and the
               political at the root of the encounter of the mother-in-law with the couple, could be
               paradigmatic for comparing other versions of this television format in other
               countries, particularly in light of the fact that other versions make explicit
               reference to trauma within the framework of Nancy Friday’s book <title rend="italic"
                  >My Mother, My Self</title>. The book, while it does not focus on trauma, still
               discusses the non-verbal transgenerational transmission of the contradictory sexual
               identities of being a sexual woman and partner to a male spouse on the one hand, and
               a non-sexual nurturer and provider of emotional security and love to all family
               members on the other. The nonverbal or paralinguistic transmission of these
               ambivalent identities participates in the same socialization and internalization
               processes as the traumatic experiences of the wartime and postwar generations.</p>
            <p>In spite of its lack of its explicit mention in the German version, there are several
               signals of transgenerational trauma transmission in the mother-in-law scene. The
               first evidence is the shock of the mother upon hearing that the daughter has visited
               a psychologist, an event that would explicitly and implicitly violate the efforts to
               keep silent about family trauma and its transmission to further generations observed
               in patients of German psychoanalytic practitioners (A and M Mitcherlich, Haarmann,
               Müller-Hohagen, Bode, and a plethora of others). In addition to showing and admitting
               fear, such visits would reveal the de-coupling of fright from the traumatic
               experiences among the mother’s post-war generation so repressed and denied by the
               subsequent generation <ptr target="#bohleber2011"/>.</p>
            <p>The second piece of evidence is the response of the daughter to her mother that the
               two of them <quote rend="inline">never spoke about anything</quote> in the family.
               This is a reference to what psychologists Frick-Baer and Baer (2015) and others point
               to as <quote rend="inline">keeping silent</quote> about crimes of the Nazis and other
               forms of war-induced trauma. They concluded that this <quote rend="inline"
                  >speechlessness</quote> facilitated the transmission of feelings of guilt to the
               second generation, who may not have directly experienced the cause of trauma, but
               were affected by its aftermath through the silence of the perpetrator generation <ptr
                  target="#baer2015"/>.</p>
            <p>The third indicator is the aforementioned transactional nature of the family
               relationship foregrounded for motivating the visit in which there is a noticeable
               deficit of affection between the couple. According to Gesine Schwan (72) and others,
                  <q>Beschweigen</q> or <q>keeping silent</q> about the extent of culpability in the
               participation of Nazi atrocities, as well as about the trauma as a result of the
               wartime experiences such as expulsion, bombings, hunger, fear, rape, death, and
               atrocities against others affects the ability to feel and express empathy in
               political and personal life, develop trust in oneself and strangers, and accept
               responsibility for one’s own life. Schwan speaks of <foreign xml:lang="de"
                  >Gefühlskälte</foreign> (coldness of feeling), i.e., a lack of emotional warmth
               and a sign of a damaged personality which seemed to prevail in many German families
               of the postwar period. Traditional pre-Nazi and Nazi varieties of masculine virtues
               as <q>hardness</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de">Härte</foreign>), fulfillment of duty,
               self- sacrifice, and refusal of empathy were passed on to the postwar generation,
               which learned to hide their pain, but perpetuated the emotional emptiness induced by
               that behavior in interpersonal and social relationships practiced by their parents,
               which in turn was compensated for by the following generation in obsessions about
               work and pursuing a consumer lifestyle as a <q>new utopia</q>
               <ptr target="#moser1993"/> inherent in the <q>Stunde Null</q> or <q>Zero Hour</q>
               myth of the beginning of the German economic <q>miracle.</q></p>
            <p>One shot in the German version is shared among all other versions in almost
               unmodified form, and epitomizes the transactional instrumentalization of
               relationships characterizing that version to a greater extent than all others. In all
               versions, the mother is playing the board game <title rend="italic">Monopoly</title>
               with the daughter and the daughter’s boyfriend, and the boyfriend is the first loser
               in the game and is thus the first to exit. This prompts the mother to mercilessly
               gloat about beating the male protagonist, while the daughter offers to bail out her
               partner, an impossibility since she has insufficient funds to do so. Still, the
               mother strenuously objects to the daughter’s bail-out attempt by claiming <quote
                  rend="inline">winner’s rights</quote> and displays a coarse ruthlessness towards
               the other two. The daughter vehemently protests to no avail, while her boyfriend is
               more than happy to put an end to his participation in the game. While the aggressive
               ruthlessness of the mother’s gaming strategy in the German version is framed as just
               one more aspect of the transactional and emotionally distanced relationship between
               the mother and the couple, in the other versions this kind of behavior is mitigated
               by other shots in which the mother and daughter are shown emotionally bonding over
               photographs, a shot that is missing in the German version. In addition, a further
               segment in the other versions features the boyfriend agreeing with the mother that
               she should rent out the daughter’s former room in the house/apartment, while the
               German version modifies the debate such that the mother appears to prefer the money
               to maintaining the daughter’s legacy in the house.</p>
            <p>All of the above-mentioned indicators point to the disturbed dialog between the
               generations, a dialog which <ref target="#schwan1997" loc="126">Schwan (1997:
                  126)</ref> considers crucial for the basic consensus of society about values and
               transgenerational relationships. <ref target="#muller-hohagen1994" loc="45"
                  >Müller-Hohagen (1994: 45)</ref> emphasizes that the dialog between the
               generations was impaired by the war experiences of the perpetrator generation, their
               denial, guilt and silence such that the trust and loyalty in families, which are
               otherwise imbued in the child before its conscious awareness, are undermined by the
               contradiction that the parents are both the child’s enablers and protectors, but were
               also culpable in the crimes of the Nazis. <ref target="#moser1993">Tilman Moser
                  (1993)</ref> underscores the collusionary culpability of second generation
               children in creating what he calls the <quote rend="inline">contract</quote> between
               the generations based on the de-realized ideal of child innocence at the core of
               parental silence. Through identification with the parental generation, the next
               generation learned to hide pain and fear. The children spared their parents from
               embarrassing and revelatory questions about their participation in the Nazi period in
               order to uphold the myth of the new beginning. Moser asserts that many of the
               repressed, denied, and manipulated experiences and values upheld by the Nazi regime
               were incorporated into the minds and behaviors of the war and postwar generations,
               but they were also transgenerationally transmitted to the third generations,
               something which he states is becoming harder and harder to recognize, especially
               since much of the transference of this influence is unconscious due to the fact that
               the children of the perpetrators, the passive supporters and victims kept silent and
               remained emotionally damaged instead of working through their trauma.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Mother-Boyfriend Relationship: Adversarial Animosity vs Begrudging
               Competition</head>
            <p> One of the most important segments in all other versions of <title rend="italic">Un
                  Gars, Une Fille</title> is the confrontation between the mother-in-law and the
               boyfriend. This segment is excluded from the German version with serious consequences
               for the narrative. In all other versions with the exception of the German, the
               adversarial relationship, mentioned in the pre-visit segment as the crucial reason
               the boyfriend needs extra persuasion to go along, is the topic of conversation
               between the mother-in-law and the boyfriend in the last shot before the end of the
               scene in the first part of the meeting, and helps reveal the reason for the animosity
               on the part of the mother. In this segment, the daughter, who is about to go to the
               toilet, admonishes both her mother and her boyfriend to behave themselves and not
               fight with each other during her absence. In most versions, the boyfriend then
               challenges the mother to state the reasons why she doesn’t like him. The mother
               replies that the boyfriend looks dishonest and untrustworthy, and looks <quote
                  rend="inline">like a polygamist.</quote> This statement undermines the credibility
               and justification for her animosity toward the boyfriend since she uses an obsolete
               term for her prejudice that the boyfriend is unfaithful to the daughter and has
               affairs on the side. In addition, the term polygamy is a legal term that is invoked
               when a couple is married, which is not the case with the relationship between the
               boyfriend and the daughter. Finally, the couple has been together for more than five,
               and in most cases for seven years in most of the versions, including the German, so
               the couple is clearly in a long-term, committed, and stable family-like relationship
               that the mother is obviously unable to accept because they are not officially
               married.</p>
            <p>In the German version of this series, the reason for the animosity between the mother
               and the boyfriend is never directly revealed nor resolved in an open conflict between
               the two. Compared to the other versions, in which there are several segments in which
               the two are able to treat each other with more magnanimity, the relationship between
               them in the German version is more adversarial and uncompromising, with merely a
               statement by the boyfriend stating to the daughter that her mother doesn’t like him
               because they are not married, but the mother herself never reveals the real reason
               for her hatred of the boyfriend and the needlessly destructive adversarial
               relationship between them is left unexplained. This could be interpreted as a further
               sign of <q>keeping silent</q> that characterizes the war-time and the postwar
               generation to which the mother belongs.</p>
            <p>If one were to classify the mother as a member of the postwar generation, i.e., the
               second generation of wartime parents, she displays a need for maintaining the value
               of a traditional, conventional marriage in which a child is produced and she becomes
               a grandmother. Even though she herself is a divorcee whose doctor husband has left
               her, she still has no tolerance for ambiguities in the relationship between her
               daughter and her boyfriend. The fact that she is divorced, a status unique to the
               German version since in all other versions the father has died, signals that she is
               at least somewhat culpable in her — seemingly — <q>defective</q> (in her eyes)
               status, while the death of the father/husband would absolve her of any culpability.
               Perhaps she is trying to overcompensate her guilt and culpability in the divorce from
               her husband by displaying her belligerence to the boyfriend, to whom she is
               projecting her distrust of men in general.</p>
            <p>This interpretation could be buttressed by the fact that another conversation in all
               other versions is omitted in the German, which is a discussion between the mother and
               her daughter about a former boyfriend. While the topic is unpleasant for the daughter
               since the relationship between her and the former boyfriend was years in the past,
               the mother still insists on pursuing it in the presence of her current partner, who
               has obviously been witness to this topic on previous occasions. He comments
               (ironically) to both that the old boyfriend must be gay because he maintains a
               Christmas-card correspondence with the mother throughout the years. Even though the
               mother’s remarks are directed against the current boyfriend, it provides a hint that
               perhaps not all men in general are questionable partners.</p>
            <p>It is unclear if the mother adheres to a relationship with her daughter that could be
               what <ref target="#bohleber2011">Bohleber (2011)</ref> considers to be <quote
                  rend="inline">narcissistic,</quote> one which egotistically instrumentalizes the
               children to satisfy the needs of the parent and not guide the children to be loving,
               self-sufficient, and independent personalities with their own identities.
               Psychologist Claudia Haarman, citing Diane Poole, explains several different types of
               narcissistic relationships between mothers and daughters, but it is ultimately
               unclear in the series if they have a <q>disorienting,</q> an <q>avoiding,</q> or an
                  <q>ambivalent</q> relationship based on the depictions in the various shots of the
               mother-in-law scene in the German version. On the other hand, the mother seems less
               emotionally available to the daughter than in other versions: The German version
               eliminates the segment in which both mother and daughter enjoy looking at old family
               photographs together, which marginalizes and ignores the boyfriend. It also excluded
               a segment in which the mother mentions that either an aunt or a family friend has
               been injured in a car accident, a segment that is in all other versions. In some
               situations, the mother seems to be emotionally “available” to the daughter and
               exhibits a semblance of the nurturing role that typifies the role of the mother
               throughout childhood, while in other situations such as the monopoly game, she
               appears distant.</p>
            <p>One particular instance in which the mother appears most distant is when the mother
               announces that she will be renting out the daughter’s former bedroom and requests
               that the daughter retrieve her belongings from the mother’s apartment. In all other
               versions of the series, the boyfriend agrees that the mother has the prerogative to
               undertake this step toward loosening relationship of both of them and letting go. In
               the German version of this series, however, the boyfriend supports his girlfriend’s
               protest against the mother’s efforts at removing the daughter’s cherished memorabilia
               from where she had grown up. The German version combines into one segment two
               different segments of the other versions with the result that the mother is depicted
               as emotionally unavailable to the daughter.</p>
            <p>The aforementioned segment in the German version is a combination of a discussion in
               all other versions about the mother-daughter relationship initiated with the mention
               of the Nancy Friday book, a discussion which results in the daughter in tears because
               of the mother’s insensitivity (and seeming emotional unavailability) to the
               mother-induced trauma. In several of the versions, the boyfriend consoles the
               daughter and is (falsely) accused by the mother of causing the daughter’s distress,
               something which is plainly not the case. Because of the elimination of the
               confrontation between the boyfriend and the mother in the German version, this is the
               only instance of him consoling the daughter.</p>
            <p>Still, if one were to take a comprehensive look at the relationships in the
               mother-in-law segment of the German version and compare these with other versions, it
               seems that in all versions the mother is irritated by the ambivalent nature of the
               relationship of her daughter with the boyfriend. If this were a traditional and
               conventional relationship of a married couple with a child, the mother would
               relinquish her role as nurturer to the boyfriend and evolve into a more equal partner
               with her daughter, in accordance with Nancy Friday’s characterization of these types
               of mother-daughter relationships. Because of the non-traditional nature of her
               daughter’s relationship with her boyfriend, however, the mother seems at times to be
               in competition with the boyfriend for the nurturing of the daughter. Friday asserts
               that the mother will lose this struggle due to the dual role of the daughter’s male
               partner as both a nurturer (in place of the mother) and as sexual partner (which the
               mother is unable to fulfill). Friday emphasizes that both partners see in each other
                  <quote rend="inline">an escape from the mother’s rules, dependence, and
                  control</quote>
               <ptr target="#friday1977" loc="252"/>. While this is more prominent in the other
               versions — the consolation segment with regard to the non-pregnancy in the conflict
               scene between the mother and the boyfriend prompts a snide remark by the mother that
               it is hard to watch them embrace and be intimate with each other. In these other
               versions, the daughter becomes most upset with the mother in the face of trying to
               determine whether the mother wants to be <q>a friend</q> or a — nurturing
                  <q>mother</q> to the daughter.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Contribution to Digital Humanities</head>
            <p>Measuring the length and duration of the narrative structure, content, and sequencing
               of all different adaptations enables a means of precisely determining the additions,
               modifications, and deletions when making cross- cultural comparisons of various
               versions of television formats. As shown above, it is possible to identify those
               segments and frame these within global socio-cultural and political discourses — in
               this case about gender roles and identities and family conflict management strategies
               — operating in each local society and cross-culturally compare these with each other.
               This kind of methodology represents a multimodal critical discourse analysis of
               different versions which may be applied to a cross-cultural analysis. This kind of
               quantitative data represents an additional dimension of analysis which may be used to
               identify complex multimodal relationships that may be culturally determined, and
               contributes to revealing culturally, aesthetically, or discursively proximate
               multimodal patterns and interrelationships that would otherwise not be visible.</p>
            <p>This study comprises a contribution to digital humanities that applies <quote
                  rend="inline">computation to the disciplines of the humanities</quote>
               <ptr target="#berry2017" loc="3"/>. It opens new questions and comparative forms of
               analysis of societies and cultures by using computation to gather and compare data
               otherwise unavailable to hermeneutic processing and interpretation. The
               computer-derived quantitative multimodal data on the conflict between the
               mother-in-law and the boyfriend allows us to register culturally significant, yet
               quantitatively slight shifts in the placement of musical cues in the shots of both
               characters, which otherwise would not be immediately revealed in a comparative
               analysis. </p>
            <p>From a narratological standpoint, drawing on computer-derived quantitative and
               qualitative data on the durations of multimodal narrative segments allows a more
               precise determination of narrative components explained by Jeremy Butler, such as the
               protagonist and antagonist and the amount of screen time devoted to them. For <ref
                  target="#butler2012" loc="25">Butler (2012: 25)</ref>, the protagonist of a film
               is a central character around which the story revolves and with whom an audience can
               identify. Especially in a case where the roles of protagonists may change and shift
               within a series or scene, placing a quantitative value on screen time may assist in
               defining the prominence of certain types of gender-specific roles, relationships, and
               power distribution between the characters. The narrative enigma or dilemma <ptr
                  target="#butler2012" loc="26"/>, which represents the explicit or implicit
               question in a drama in the series <title rend="italic">Un Gars, Une Fille</title>,
               revolves, in this scene, around the problematic mother-couple relationship. We used
               digital quantitative means for analyses to help decide if and how the conflictual
               relationship is resolved in the scene. Even though the German version varies
               substantially from the other versions in this respect, in none of the versions is the
               conflict definitively resolved. However, on the basis of different complexes of
               multimodal discursive components the empathy of the audience is directed to different
               characters on the basis of their identities and behaviors within the particular
               culturally specific narrative of the version.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baer2015" label="Baer and Frick-Baer 2015">Udo Baer, Gabriele Frick-Baer,
               2015. <title rend="italic">Kriegserbe in der Seele. Was Kindern und Enkeln der
                  Kriegsgeneration wirklich hilft</title>, Weinheim: Beltz.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bateman2011" label="Bateman and Schmidt 2011">John A. Bateman,
               Karl-Heinrich Schmidt, 2011. <title rend="italic">Multimodal Film Analysis. How Films
                  Mean,</title> New York: Routledge. Routledge Studies in Multimodality.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="berry2017" label="Berry and Fagerjord 2017">David M. Berry, Anders
               Fagerjord, 2017. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities. Knowledge and Critique in a
                  Digital Age</title>, Cambridge UK: Polity Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bode2005" label="Bode 2005">Sabine Bode, 2005. <title rend="italic">Die
                  vergessene Generation. Die Kriegskinder brechen ihr Schweigen</title>, München:
               Piper.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bohleber2011" label="Bohleber 2011">Werner Bohleber, 2011. <title
                  rend="quotes">Trauma — Transgenerationelle Weitergabe und
                  Geschichtsbewusstsein,</title> in <title rend="italic">Vererbte Wunden. Traumata
                  des Zweiten Weltkrieges, die Folge für Familie, Gesellschaft und Kultur</title>,
               Curt Hondrich (Hsg.), Lengerich: Pabst Science Publishers, pp. 9-24.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="butler2014" label="Butler 2014">Jeremy G. Butler, 2014. <title
                  rend="quotes">Statistical Analysis of Television Style: What Can Numbers Tell Us
                  about TV Editing,</title> in <title rend="italic">Cinema Journal</title> Vol. 54,
               No. 1, Fall, pp. 25-44.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="butler2012" label="Butler 2012">Jeremy G. Butler, 2012. <title
                  rend="italic">Television. Critical Methods and Applications</title>, 4th Edition.
               New York: Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="butler2007" label="Butler 2007">Jeremy G. Butler, 2007. <title
                  rend="italic">Television. Critical Methods and Applications</title>, 3rd Edition,
               New York: Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chalaby2011" label="Chalaby 2011">Jean K. Chalaby, 2011. <title
                  rend="quotes">The making of an entertainment revolution: How the TV format trade
                  became a global industry,</title> in <title rend="italic">European journal of
                  Communication</title>, 26:(4) 293-309. DOI: 10.1177/0267323111423414</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="flewitt2013" label="Flewitt et al. 2013">Rosie Flewitt, Regine Hampel,
               Mirjam Hauck, Lesley Lancaster, 2013. <title rend="quotes">What are multimodal data
                  and transcription?</title> in <title rend="italic">Routledge Handbook of
                  Multimodal Analysis</title>, 2nd Edition, New York: Routledge, pp. 44-59.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="friday1977" label="Friday 1977">Nancy Friday, 1977. <title rend="italic"
                  >My Mother, My Self. The Daughter’s Search for Identity</title>, New York:
               Delacorte Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="haarmann2008" label="Haarmann 2008">Claudia Haarmann, 2008. <title
                  rend="italic">Mütter sind auch Menschen: Mütter und Töchter begegnen sich
                  neu</title>, Berlin: Orlanda Verlag.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hantke2012" label="Hantke and Gorges 2012">Lydia Hantke, Hans-J. Gorges
               (Eds.) 2012. <title rend="italic">Handbuch Traumakompetenz. Basiswissen für Therapie,
                  Beratung und Pädagogik</title>, Paderborn: Junfermann Verlag.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hondrich2011" label="Hondrich 2011">Curt Hondrich (Ed.), 2011. <title
                  rend="italic">Vererbte Wunden. Traumata des Zweiten Weltkrieges, die Folge für
                  Familie, Gesellschaft und Kultur</title>, Lengerich: Pabst Science
               Publishers.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jewitt2016" label="Jewitt 2016">Carey Jewitt (Ed.), 2016. <title
                  rend="italic">Routledge Handbook of Multimodal Analysis</title>, New York:
               Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vankeulen2016" label="van Keulen 2016">Jolien van Keulen, 2016. <title
                  rend="quotes">Aesthetic proximity; The role of stylistic programme elements in
                  format localisation,</title> in <title rend="italic">VIEW. Journal of European
                  Television History and Culture</title>. Vol 5, Issue 9. DOI:
               10.18146/2213-0969.2016.jethc 105.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kress2012" label="Kress 2012">Gunther Kress, 2012. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Thinking about the notion of ‘cross-cultural’ from a social semiotic
                  perspective,</title> in <title rend="italic">Language and Intercultural
                  Communication,</title> 12:4, 369-385, DOI:10.1080/14708477.2012.722102.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="larkey2019a" label="Larkey 2019a">Edward Larkey, 2019a. <title
                  rend="quotes">Narratological Approaches to Multimodal Cross-Cultural Comparisons
                  of Global TV Formats,</title> in <hi rend="italic">VIEW, Journal of European
                  Television History and Culture,</hi> Vol 7, No. 14, pp. 38-58.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="larkey2019b" label="Larkey 2019b">Edward Larkey, 2019b. <title
                  rend="quotes">Narrative as a Mode of Communication: Comparing TV Format
                  Adaptations with Multimodal and Narratological Approaches,</title> in <title
                  rend="italic">Multimodality – Towards a New Discipline</title>, Janina Wildfeuer,
               Jana Pflaeging, Ognyan Seizov, Chiao-I Tseng, John A. Bateman (Eds.) Berlin:
               DeGruyter/Mouton, pp. 208-234.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="larkey2013" label="Larkey 2013">Edward Larkey 2013. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Ugly Betty and Verliebt in Berlin: Identitätskonstruktionen im transkulturellen
                  Vergleich,</title> in <title rend="italic">Transnationale Serienkultur, Theorie,
                  Ästhetik, Narration und Rezeption neuer Fernsehserien</title>, Susanne Eichner,
               Rainer Winter, Lothar Mikos (Eds.) Wiesbaden: Springer VS Verlag für
               Sozialwissenschaften, pp. 287-306.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="larkey2009" label="Larkey 2009">Edward Larkey 2009. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Transcultural Localization Strategies of Global TV Formats: The Office and
                  Stromberg,</title> in <title rend="italic">TV Formats Worldwide. Localizing Global
                  Programs</title>, Albert Moran (Ed.) Bristol UK: Intellect, pp. 188-201.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="larkey2016" label="Larkey et al. 2016">Edward Larkey, Landry Digeon,
               Ibrahim Er, 2016. <title rend="quotes">Measuring Transnationalism: Comparing TV
                  Formats Using Digital Tools,</title> in <title rend="italic">VIEW. Journal of
                  European Television History and Culture</title>, Vol. 5, No. 14, pp. 72-92.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="machin2013" label="Machin 2013">David Machin, 2013. <title rend="quotes"
                  >What is multimodal critical discourse studies?</title> in <title rend="italic"
                  >Critical Discourse Studies</title>, 10:4, 347-355, DOI:
               10.1080/17405904.2013.813770</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="misterlich1967" label="Misterlich 1967">Alexander und Margarete
               Mitscherlich, 1967. <title rend="italic">Die Unfähigkeit zu trauern. Grundlagen
                  kollektiven Verhaltens</title>, München: Piper.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="muller-hohagen1994" label="Müller-Hohagen 1994">Jürgen Müller-Hohagen,
               1994. <title rend="italic">Geschichte in uns. Psychogramme aus dem Alltag</title>,
               München: Knesebeck.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ohalloran2016" label="O'Halloran et al. 2016">Kay O’Halloran, Marissa
               K.L.E, Sabine Tan, 2016. <title rend="quotes">Multimodal Analytics. Software and
                  visualization techniques for analyzing and interpreting multimodal data,</title>
               in <title rend="italic">Routledge Handbook of Multimodal Analysis</title>, Jewitt
               (Ed.) 2nd Edition, New York: Routledge, pp. 386-395.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lapastina2005" label="La Pastina and Straubhaar 2005">Antonio C. La
               Pastina, Joseph D. Straubhaar, 2005. <title rend="quotes">Multiple Proximities
                  between Television Genres and Audiences. The Schism between Telenovelas’ Global
                  Distribution and Local Consumption,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Gazette, The International Journal for Communication
                  Studies</title>, Vol 67, No. 1, pp.271-288. DOI: 10.1177/0016549205052231.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="moser1993" label="Moser 1993">Tilmann Moser, 1993. <title rend="italic"
                  >Der Erlöser der Mutter auf dem Weg zu sich selbst: eine
                  Körperpsychotherapie</title>. Frankfurt/Main: Suhrkamp.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schwan1997" label="Schwan 1997">Gesine Schwan, 1997. <title rend="italic"
                  >Politik und Schuld. Die zerstörerische Macht des Schweigens</title>, Frankfurt/M:
               Fischer Taschenbuchverlag.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="uribe-jongbloed2014" label="Uribe-Jongbloed and Espinosa-Medina 2014"
               >Enrique Uribe-Jongbloed, Hernan David Espinosa-Medina, 2014. <title rend="quotes">A
                  clearer picture: Towards a new framework for the study of cultural transduction in
                  audiovisual market trades,</title>in <title rend="italic">Observatorio
                  Journal</title>, Vol. 8, No. 1, pp. 23-48.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
