<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Film and Video Analysis in the Digital Humanities –
               An Interdisciplinary Dialog</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Manuel <dhq:family>Burghardt</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Leipzig University, Germany</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>burghardt@informatik.uni-leipzig.de</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Manuel Burghardt is Professor for Computational Humanities at the Institute for Computer Science at Leipzig University. He received his PhD in Information Science in 2014, at the University of Regensburg. In his current research, Manuel ist interested in computational film studies and literary studies as well as in optical character recognition and layout detection.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Adelheid <dhq:family>Heftberger</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Bundesarchiv, Germany</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>adelheidh@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Dr. Adelheid Heftberger is Head of Film Access at the film department of the German Federal Archive (Berlin). She obtained her PhD in Russian studies and a Masters in Comparative Literature from the University of Innsbruck and Vienna. In 2016 she has also completed Library- and Information Sciences at the Humboldt-University in Berlin. She is also a full member of the Cataloging and Documentation Commission of FIAF and active in the Open Science movement.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Johannes <dhq:family>Pause</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Université du Luxembourg, Luxembourg</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>johannes.pause@uni.lu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Matthias Zeppelzauer is a senior researcher at the Institute of Creative\Media/Technologies at St. Pölten University of Applied Sciences, Austria. He received his PhD in Computer Science from Vienna University of Technology with highest distinction. His research focuses on multimedia retrieval, audio and video analysis and machine learning in interdisciplinary problem domains.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Niels-Oliver <dhq:family>Walkowski</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Université du Luxembourg, Luxembourg</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>niels-oliver.walkowski@uni.lu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Niels-Oliver Walkowski is a research scientist for digital literacy and research at the University of Luxembourg. He received his PhD in Literature from the Katholieke Universiteit Leuven, writing about the impact of digital technologies on scholarly publishing. He wrote several articles about colorimetric analysis of zombie movies and political thrillers and is the project coordinator of Melusina Press, a hybrid, multimodal press for research in Luxembourg.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Matthias <dhq:family>Zeppelzauer</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>St. Pölten University, Austria</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>matthias.zeppelzauer@fhstp.ac.at</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Matthias Zeppelzauer is a senior researcher at the Institute of Creative\Media/Technologies at St. Pölten University of Applied Sciences, Austria. He received his PhD in Computer Science from Vienna University of Technology with highest distinction. His research focuses on multimedia retrieval, audio and video analysis and machine learning in interdisciplinary problem domains.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000532</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               >014</idno>
            <idno type="issue">4</idno>
            <date when="2020-12-20">20 December 2020</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2020-12-04" who="jmurel">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>This editorial introduces the special issue on <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities &amp; Film Studies: Analyzing the Modalities of Moving Images,</title> which contains a total of eight exciting contributions. Moreover, this editorial aims to highlight the complementary disciplinary perspectives on the computer-aided analysis of moving images, which are important prerequisites to better understand and situate a common DH perspective</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>Introduction to Film Studies Special Issue</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>1. The Infrastructural Perspective: GLAM Institutions and Film Archives</head>
            <p>The computer-aided analysis of moving images is becoming an increasingly important
               topic within the digital humanities and it has been an interdisciplinary field since
               its beginnings: Computer science and media informatics, film and media studies as
               well as film archives and documentation centers have developed their own, independent
               approaches to the digital analysis of film. At the same time, however, several
               bridges have already been built between the individual disciplines: In computer
               science, for example, there has been research on automatic film and video analysis
               for more than 20 years, but it is still carried out without any visible connection to
               the field of film studies. Since the digital humanities have always been a place of
               interdisciplinary encounter and exchange, it is not surprising that the discovery of
               digital film studies (see <ref target="#grant2012">Grant [2012]</ref>) as a combination and continuation of the
               above-mentioned disciplinary traditions, has become a major topic in recent years.
               This special issue on <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities &amp; Film Studies:
                  Analyzing the Modalities of Moving Images</title> aims to promote an
               interdisciplinary dialog by presenting a variety of different articles from different
               fields. In order to get this dialog started, this introduction will try to work out
               the different disciplinary strands of computer-aided film and video analysis and to
               interconnect them in terms of a common digital humanities perspective.</p>
            <p>A first important strand can be found in the so-called GLAM (galleries, libraries,
               archives, museums) institutions, with their close connection to information science.
               Cultural heritage institutions traditionally consider it their mission to facilitate
               the creation and dissemination of knowledge and works of art by providing access to
               their collections. This not only means engaging with academics, but also connecting
               with a wider community and addressing their diverse needs. In libraries, archives and
               museums, systems had already been established over centuries to support information
               retrieval in their collections, for instance bibliographies, finding aids, citation
               systems and concordances. This information was also made available in publications,
               thus linking the publishers, librarians, archivists and curators to the researchers.
               Film archives lag considerably behind when it comes to actively facilitate sharing
               their collections, but recent developments within the international film archiving
               community show a growing interest in exploring alternative ways of providing access
               to filmographic metadata, inventory information and contextual information
               likewise.</p>
            <p>The beginnings of the fundamental restructuring of knowledge and the academic world
               can arguably be dated to 2003, when the National Science Foundation (NSF), the
               American government organization tasked with promoting basic research across
               disciplinary borders, commissioned a report, later colloquially named after then
               chairman <ref target="#atkins2003">Dan Atkins (2003)</ref>. In two subsequent reports from 2006 and 2007, published
               by the NSF and the American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS), the vision of a new
                  <quote rend="inline">cyberinfrastructure ... that supports peer-to-peer
                  collaboration and new modes of education based upon broad and open access to
                  leadership computing; data and information resources; online instruments and
                  observatories; and visualization and collaboration services</quote> was
               conclusively defined and disseminated <ptr target="#arden2007"/>. Already in 2009, in
               the pivotal <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities Manifesto 2.0</title>, Schnapp
               and Presner asked for a reevaluation of the relation between scholars and GLAM
               professionals and <quote rend="inline">affirm that modern universities still tend to
                  separate scholarship from curation, a fact that is hardly deniable. The latter is
                  normally reduced to a secondary and supportive role, thus sending curators within
                  the museums, archives and libraries into exile</quote>
               <ptr target="#heftberger2014" loc="142"/>. If we understand curation as the
               overarching process of taking care of the collection in various ways, it is probably
               closer to how the tasks in GLAM institutions have changed over the last ten
               years. </p>
            <p>GLAM institutions are typically interested in two types of digital humanities: On the
               one hand, they themselves have a need for new technologies in order to be able to
               analyze, enrich, index and make their holdings accessible. On the other hand, they
               often act as consulting institutions for connected researchers to support them with
               knowledge, infrastructure and technology (for a comprehensive discussion of this
               topic, see <ref target="#schaffner2014">Schaffner and Erway [2014]</ref>). It is,
               however, still not clear where the personnel for the mentioned tasks could come from.
               Are new digital humanities graduates a way to fill these positions? Is it better to
               form tandems of humanities scholars and computer scientists, or even change archival
               educational programs (see <ref target="#heftberger2018">Heftberger [2018]</ref>)?
               Questions like these were openly discussed at a recent workshop (February 2020), held
               at the German National Library in Frankfurt, which dealt with the broader question of
               how cultural heritage institutions position themselves when it comes to digital
               humanities.</p>
            <p>Nowadays, data management, data wrangling, data mapping and data sharing have become
               core elements of the daily work in archives, libraries or museums. As Julia Flanders
               describes, <quote rend="inline">most digital humanities work – as performed by
                  library staff, IT staff, and other para-academic staff who are not faculty – is
                  conceptualized according to one of the other models: hourly, by full-time
                  equivalent, or as an agenda of projects that granularizes and regulates the work
                  in quantifiable ways</quote>
               <ptr target="#flanders2012" loc="303"/>. According to Flanders, there is a tendency
               to define assignments in the framework of digital humanities (e.g. databases, online
               presentations, also perhaps long-term archiving) as projects and to outsource them to
               third parties. Although such a procedure is understandable, a chance is being missed:
               the opportunity to build in-house resources which would also enable engagement with
               collection content alongside the digital infrastructure and information management
               (see <ref target="#heftberger2018" loc="20">Heftberger [2018]: 20</ref>).</p>
            <p>One core task in the film archive is film identification and data enrichment via
               subject indexing, which is usually still done manually. In the meantime, it has
               become possible to annotate video files, to provide them with keywords to the
               precision of a frame, to annotate them with geographical data and to comment on them
               in free text. Potentially digital collections can be mined for patterns and objects,
               and research can take place at the level of content but also at the levels of
               metadata generation and meaningful web presentations. In recent years, in addition to
               an increasing tendency to aggregate metadata and inventory data (e.g. <ref
                  target="http://filmportal.de">filmportal.de</ref>), it can also be observed that
               the topic of Linked Open Data is becoming more important. In international working
               groups (e.g. in the Cataloguing Commission of the FIAF), ontologies for film as well
               as workflows for the use of identifiers from, for example, Wikidata are being
               collaboratively developed, and their usage will hopefully gain momentum (see <ref
                  target="#heftberger2020">Heftberger and Duchesne [2020]</ref>). If  we look at how
               processes of knowledge transformation in the twenty-first century can take place and
               how they can be understood by means of computer technology, interpretation must
               remain an important component of the discipline: <cit><quote rend="block">What the
                     community can do with the results of a digital humanities project is, like art,
                     often outside what a creator or project team might have envisioned for it — and
                     this is where the interpretation becomes important for multivalent digital
                     humanities projects. What does it mean that a database has been structured in a
                     certain way? What are the larger consequences for one design over another? How
                     does a certain project push the boundaries of what we consider acceptable
                     digital humanities work? How can new analytical processes or methodologies be
                     applied in different contexts? These are subjective and interpretative
                     questions that we must openly discuss.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#gibbs2011"/></cit></p>
            <p>Institutions can usually identify relatively clearly which tasks are suitable to be
               supported by software. Typically, subject indexing and visualizing collections online
               are named by professionals. In addition to these continuous duties, there are a large
               number of exciting sub-projects that could be worked on in collaboration with
               scholars and/or artists, and which would offer tremendous added value for both
               groups. Film collecting institutions bring their knowledge about analog material to
               the table as well as a comprehensive knowledge of film titles in their holdings,
               which are not digitally available yet. Their staff can assist with expertise in
               digitization as well as opening up film collections by viewing and cataloging titles
               which have not been widely disseminated yet. Thus, they can contribute to broaden a
               so far narrow view on film history which too many times only focuses on iconic titles
               and male directors. Even just looking into cast and credit roles and how they changed
               over the course of time in different languages may change our perspective, for
               example on the involvement of female editors (see Pearlman and Heftberger 2018).
               Making more film titles available and connecting resources digitally via sharing
               metadata and contextual information as well as visualizing their collections is a key
               task for film archives nowadays. One good example would be the BFI Filmography, which
               so far is a rare attempt to consider filmographic metadata research data for film
               historians and film scholars <ptr target="#pearlman2018"/>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>2.The Computational Perspective: Multimedia Information Retrieval</head>
            <p>Film scholars have a long tradition in the qualitative and quantitative analysis of
               film and more recently video. The automatic and automatically assisted analysis of
               filmic content has – compared to that – a rather short history. Due to the large
               amounts of data produced by digitized film and video and the associated high
               computing costs as well as the initially rare availability of digitized footage,
               research on automatic film analysis could only slowly establish when first digital
               media retrieval methods started to develop in the mid 1990s. Since then, we have
               observed a tremendous development of automatic film and video analysis which was
               fueled by breakthroughs in machine learning methodology (especially deep learning) as
               well as in the availability of annotated training data. Today, automatic film and
               video analysis has achieved a certain level of maturity and — as a result — is
               applied more and more in the digital humanities. We describe the origins of automatic
               film analysis in computer science and its rather young history in the following and
               identify important future challenges for automatic film analysis in the context of
               the digital humanities.</p>
            <p>The research field associated with automatic film analysis is called <title
                  rend="quotes">Multimedia Information Retrieval</title> (MMIR). MMIR has originally
               evolved as a branch of Information Retrieval (IR) (for some early examples see <ref
                  target="#mooers1950">Mooers [1950]</ref>, <ref target="#salton1983">Salton and
                  McGill [1983]</ref>, <ref target="#vanrijsbergen1997">van Rijsbergen [1997]</ref>)
               and has grown to a broad and independent field of research in recent years. In the
               last two decades, the amount of available digital media data has increased
               tremendously. In addition to textual information, image, audio and video data have
               become omnipresent due to the availability of cheap capturing hardware, the
               development of efficient compression and transmission techniques and the
               establishment of large, publicly accessible databases and media platforms on the
               Internet. Still, the access to these large amounts of multimedia data is rather
               restricted, as media data are often lacking textual descriptions. Also, it is
               difficult to derive semantically meaningful information from the content itself, for
               instance the individual pixels of an image or the samples of an audio signal. </p>
            <p>This is exactly where MMIR comes into play. MMIR aims at making sense of the raw
               media to make the media itself searchable by content <ptr target="#lew2006"/>.
               Thereby, MMIR makes large media databases instantly searchable. This enables a
               variety of useful applications, such as finding people and objects in images,
               retrieving videos that show and explain certain activities, finding unusual events in
               long-term video sequences, but also retrieving syntactic and semantic concepts from
               films <ptr target="#zaharieva2010"/> to support qualitative and quantitative studies
               by film scholars and to open up large-scale film and video corpora for systematic
               analyses. Research on MMIR goes back to the early 1990s <ptr target="#grosky1994"/>
               and has grown so broad today that it has become difficult to oversee the entire field
                  <ptr target="#pouyanfar2018"/>. The great diversity of media data has led to the
               development of several MMIR research branches, such as Content-Based Image Retrieval
               (CBIR), Content-Based Audio Retrieval (CBAR), and Content-Based Video Retrieval
               (CBVR), which over time have become research areas that can stand for themselves. </p>
            <p>Additionally, several cohesive modalities (e.g. video and its corresponding audio
               track) can be combined in multimodal retrieval approaches to leverage complementary
               information for more robust retrieval. Multimodal retrieval is often used synonymous
               with multimedia information retrieval and is also sometimes referred to as <title
                  rend="quotes">MMIR</title> in the literature. Multimodal retrieval can be defined
               as follows: <quote rend="inline">A multimedia information retrieval (MMIR) problem is
                  multimodal if it includes multiple input modalities, such as images, audio, 3D
                  data, textual and contextual information</quote>
               <ptr target="#baltrusaitis2018"/>. Multimodal retrieval can be considered an
               overarching branch of MMIR that combines and integrates methodology from different
               modality-specific branches. In multimodal retrieval, basically arbitrary data sources
               can be combined as long as they have a certain semantic relationship. Today's
               approaches toward automatic film and video analysis integrate methodology of all of
               the above-mentioned branches of MMIR. For this reason, they are briefly introduced in
               the following.</p>
            <div>
               <head>2.1 Content-based image retrieval (CBIR)</head>
               <p>CBIR focuses on the retrieval of images in an image archive or database from a
                  given query, which can be either textual or provided as an example image
                  (query-by-example). The first content-based retrieval systems came up in the 1990s
                  and included systems like QBIC <ptr target="#flickner1995"/> and VIRAGE <ptr
                     target="#gupta1997"/>, which were able to query a multimedia database by
                  example images. Aside from finding similar images to a query, typical CBIR
                  problems are the retrieval of objects, concepts and scene properties <ptr
                     target="#zhao2017"/> as well as image classification <ptr
                     target="#druzhkov2016"/>. CBIR is thus strongly interlinked with the fields of
                  computer vision and machine learning. Research in CBIR focuses on the retrieval of
                  patterns from various types of images, including medical images, remote sensing
                  imagery and user-generated content (e.g. in personal photo collections and in
                  social media). Broad surveys on the field of CBIR are provided by <ref
                     target="#datta2008">Datta et al. (2008)</ref> and more recently by <ref
                     target="#zhou2017">Zhou et al. (2017)</ref>. Automatic film analysis makes
                  intensive use of content-based image analysis. Even though the study object are
                  films and videos, many visual analysis problems in film analysis (e.g. object
                  detection in movies <ptr target="#fluckiger2019"/>, visual composition analysis
                     <ptr target="#mitrovic2001"/> and the recognition of shot size and shot type
                     <ptr target="#zaharieva2010"/>) can be performed on individual images without
                  taking the temporal dimension into account.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2.2 Content-based video retrieval (CBVR)</head>
               <p>Closely related to CBIR is Content-Based Video Retrieval (CBVR). Typical problems
                  in CBVR are the retrieval of similar videos to a query as well as temporal
                  segmentation of a video in shots and scenes <ptr target="#cotsaces2006"/>, action
                  and activity recognition <ptr target="#cheng2015"/> event recognition <ptr
                     target="#tzelepis2016"/>, motion retrieval <ptr target="#zeppelzauer2011a"/>,
                  video summarization <ptr target="#delmolino2016"/> and video browsing <ptr
                     target="#schoffman2010"/>. Content-based video retrieval integrates many
                  techniques from CBIR and extends them with temporal analysis (e.g. motion analysis
                  or object tracking). As a first step in CBVR, the video stream is usually
                  partitioned into smaller units, such as key frames, shots and scenes <ptr
                     target="#rui1998"/>. Next, information at the frame as well as the shot level
                  are extracted and aggregated for retrieval and classification. Typical types of
                  video data include sports videos, news videos and surveillance videos. Beyond
                  these types of motion images, there is a large corpus of literature on the
                  automatic analysis of movies, documentaries and archive film <ptr
                     target="#ewerth2009"/>
                  <ptr target="#zaharieva2010"/>, which has developed in parallel to visual research
                  in the digital humanities. A frequent pattern that can be observed from the
                  literature is that a broad range of filmic concepts has been investigated already
                  in the computer science, such as film rhythm, tempo, style and narrative
                  structures <ptr target="#adams2001"/>
                  <ptr target="#adams2002"/>
                  <ptr target="#choudhary2019"/> but with rather simplified definitions of these
                  concepts.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2.3 Content-based audio retrieval (CBAR)</head>
               <p>CBAR has developed similarly to CBIR in the early 1990s. Pioneering work is
                  presented by <ref target="#wold1996">Wold et al. (1996)</ref>, with their
                  development of an audio retrieval system called <title rend="quotes">Muscle
                     Fish</title> that was able to automatically distinguish between different types
                  of sounds (see <ref target="#pfeiffer1996">Pfeiffer et al. [1996]</ref>). Since
                  then, there has been rapid development in different directions, such as audio
                  segmentation, music information retrieval and environmental sound retrieval.
                  Furthermore, the analysis and recognition of speech, which has developed
                  separately, starting already in the 1950s, can be considered one sub-branch of
                  CBAR <ptr target="#juang2005"/>. Compared to the visual modality, the acoustic
                  modality is under-represented in automatic film analysis. One reason is that the
                  acoustic modality alone is often not sufficient for film analysis. Acoustic
                  information is, however, highly useful when combined with visual information in a
                  multimodal approach <ptr target="#snoek2005"/>. Information from soundtracks can
                  significantly help to classify film genre, scene types and film style <ptr
                     target="#choudhary2019"/>. Furthermore, the analysis of the affective dimension
                  of film requires acoustic and visual clues <ptr target="#soleymani2009"/>.
                  Finally, film montage may exhibit correlated patterns between the acoustic and
                  visual track <ptr target="#zeppelzauer2011b"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2.4 Concluding remarks on the field of multimedia information retrieval
                  (MMIR)</head>
               <p>From the brief review of the field of MMIR, we can observe that a large body of
                  automatic analysis approaches exists that would (at least in theory) be applicable
                  to filmic content investigated by film scholars. Especially in the early years of
                  MMIR, however, these methods were not powerful enough to model the complex
                  semantic concepts investigated by film scholars. Today, automatic visual (and
                  audio-visual) analysis is well advanced. Developments in machine learning and
                  especially in deep learning in the last decade have made significant progress in
                  the extraction of information from audio-visual media and in modeling semantic
                  relationships. Certain problems which appeared unsolvable 15 years ago can now be
                  solved automatically with almost human-level performance <ptr target="#he2015"/>.
                  This has therefore changed the situation for the digital humanities fundamentally.
                  MMIR has reached a level of maturity that can provide a real added value for film
                  scholars and the digital humanities in general. Many previously unanswered
                  research questions from film scholars are waiting to be (re)investigated by the
                  support of automatic film and video analysis methods.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>3. The Media Perspective: Digital Encounters in Film and Media Studies</head>
            <p>Recapitulating the history of digital tools, methods and practices within film and
               media studies is a particularly challenging task. Wherever the field has dealt with
               this topic, reflections on the status of digital tools and technologies have often
               superseded their use as a facilitator of research. The reason for this situation is
               as simple as it is convincing: it is the very insight that <quote rend="inline">the
                  medium is the message</quote>
               <ptr target="#mcluhan1964"/>. Hence, we should not just consider technology a tool, a
               means to an end that lies at the heart, at least of media studies.<note>Despite the
                  controversy about McLuhan’s concept of <q>media</q> and the bold claim he derives
                  from it no one, today, denies the idea that a medium significantly and often
                  unnoticed shapes what it mediates.</note> The decision, however, to make
               technology, and thus digital media, a research object of epistemological, cultural
               and sociological enquiry itself has also another consequence. It creates awareness
               about the fact that common narratives about the purpose of a certain piece of
               technology and actual usages of the same technology can be two very different things.
               It therefore sensitizes to alleged misusages of technologies. These misusages often
               exist in the margins of those approaches that are propagated by certain tool
               ideologies and instigate their own techno-social configurations. The histories of
               digital tool usage in film and media studies are thus entangled with different
               perspectives on the contingent nature of digital technologies and different
               understandings of scholarly engagement.</p>
            <div>
               <head>3.1 Notions of the digital and digital methodologies</head>
               <p>Using the plural form in histories is more than just acknowledging the democratic
                  attitude that writing history enforces. It is a reaction to the fact that it even
                  lacks an agreement about the same temporal dimension when researchers of the field
                  try to systematize the history of the use of digital technologies in film and
                  media studies. In Germany, for instance, <ref target="#sittel2017">Julian Sittel
                     (2017)</ref> states that film studies lags behind when it comes to the adoption
                  of digital humanities methods, while <ref target="#vonderau2017">Patrick Vonderau
                     (2017)</ref> suggests that digital humanities is the continuity of a certain
                  way to use digital technologies that has long been superseded by other usage
                  types. This claim is illustrated by an analysis of the use of digital technologies
                  in film and media studies that distinguishes three consecutive phases between 1985
                  and 2005: The first phase produced tools to manually annotate and segment movies.
                  The second phase introduced database-driven quantification of annotated and
                  classified units in moving images. The third phase gives testimony of a
                  repurposing of the goal of databases themselves. They now shift from facilitating
                  statistical analysis to becoming a metaphor and facilitator for the situational
                  and explorative organization of content of any kind in research in the logic of
                  the collage. Databases are more conceived of as an expression of an abstract
                  notion of media practice instead of just being a tool to query and count <ptr
                     target="#bohme2012"/>. </p>
               <p>In Vonderau's perspective, digital humanities is just an attempt to perfect narrow
                  use of digital technology that was predominant in the second phase. It lacks a
                  broad theoretical framing for digital transformation and technology as such and
                  thus misses new emerging paradigms of technology use. In Sittel's line of
                  argument, however, digital humanities are the clear sign of a more fundamental
                  shift; a shift that reconfigures the entanglement between theory, technology and
                  research – with respect to the first paragraph the media/message relationship –
                  itself and that, accordingly, cannot be integrated into film and media studies
                  appropriately. Claims such as those about <quote rend="inline">the end of
                     theory</quote>
                  <ptr target="#anderson2008"/> or the <quote rend="inline">fourth paradigm</quote>
                  <ptr target="#hey2009"/> come to mind here. In summary, different notions of
                  technology instigate different historical narratives as well as different
                  methodological portfolios and needs. Each of these configurations are,
                  furthermore, linked to struggles for disciplinary autonomy but also to debates
                  about the internal structure of the field itself. This is most obvious when
                  Vonderau declares that actually the main object of film studies – the analysis of
                  movies – mostly disappeared in film studies with the arrival of digital
                  technologies, while <ref target="#chavez-heras2012">Chavéz-Heras (2012)</ref>
                  announces that now, with digital tools, film analysis is reborn.</p>
               <p>Such media-reflexive preoccupations have caused a lot of alienation between film
                  and media studies on the one hand and digital humanities on the other.<note>It is
                     important to mention that in Europe this tension is stronger due to the fact
                     that in the US there has been branch of digital humanities that for long came
                     out of media studies and related fields <ptr target="#svensson2010"/>.</note>
                  It would, however, be misleading if digital humanities just considered it an
                  internal issue of film and media studies. In fact, the digital humanities have
                  cultivated their own version of the above-mentioned tension, a tension that
                  recently created a schism within in the field itself. Since 2014, concepts such as
                  the post-digital humanities <ptr target="#berry2014"/> or the critical digital
                  humanities <ptr target="#grimshaw2018"/>
                  <ptr target="#dobson2019"/> emerged within debates on digital humanities. The
                  former relates to the methodological inconsistencies behind the term digital
                  methods, while the latter stresses cultural conditions and impacts of algorithmic
                  meaning making processes. In opposition to these branches, in 2019, the
                  computational humanities research community spun off the field of digital
                  humanities, preceeded by debates that digital humanities had lost its core –
                  humanities computing – and that rather <q>techie</q> topics are not sufficiently
                  represented <ptr target="#elwert2019"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>3.2 Entanglements with the Digital and Post-Digital Humanities</head>
               <p>This example is just the entertaining expression of an open space of entanglements
                  between digital technologies and doing research. In film and media studies these
                  include approaches such as <term>artistic research</term>
                  <ptr target="#ruszev2018"/>, <term>speculative computing</term>
                  <ptr target="#drucker2009"/>, <term>statistics and stylometry</term>
                  <ptr target="#casey2014"/>
                  <ptr target="#baxter2017"/>, <term>digital surrealism</term>
                  <ptr target="#ferguson2015"/>
                  <ptr target="#ferguson2017"/>, or <term>multimodal storytelling</term> and
                     <term>videographic criticism</term>
                  <ptr target="#erlend2012"/>
                  <ptr target="#keathley2019"/>. The case of videographic criticism or the
                     <term>video-essay</term>, as it is sometimes called, is especially interesting
                  because it demonstrates how an object of research becomes the means of analysis
                  itself. It investigates movies by producing short movies and follows the media
                  reflexive idea that it might be best to represent facts of a certain modality
                  within that same modality. Although not computational in a strict digital
                  humanities sense, the video essay clearly is interpreted as a product of digital
                  technologies and an established method of film studies research <ptr target="#mcwhirter2015"/>.
                  Together with the above-mentioned dispute about the obsolescence or the revival of
                  the analysis of movies, the whole episode demonstrates very well that questions
                  raised by digital technologies are not just questions of new methods, and even
                  less questions of computational or statistical methods. They are, with similar
                  importance, questions about the changing status of research objects within a
                  changing, partially digital, environment. Accordingly, the challenge is not just
                  to define better or new methods, but also to develop a new sense of research
                  objects and research ecologies – all at the same time.</p>
               <p>With this in mind, it is necessary to critically re-approach the notion that film
                  and media studies lag behind. The holistic angle on digital research that not only
                  considers new methods for known objects but also new cultural embeddings for known
                  as well as unknown objects, suggests another kind of endeavor. In this respect it
                  is a meaningful observation that in the history of digital humanities, fields with
                  clearly definable and established research entities – the edition, the textual
                  source and the artifact among others – were the most influential. It goes without
                  saying that the analysis of our partially digital environment and its objects
                  enforces to also apply digital humanities methods in a stricter sense of the term
                  and cannot be carried out comprehensively without them. In consequence, film and
                  media studies researchers that might not have welcomed these methods, due to
                  methodological reasons, in the first place are, nevertheless, beginning to open up
                  as has been mentioned before. The challenge, both for the digital humanities and
                  for film and media studies, remains to integrate perspectives of method, object
                  and ecology without creating a hierarchy among them; be it methods for the digital
                  humanities or objects and ecology for film and media studies.</p>
               <p>It was a striking feature of Vonderau’s periodization that it ended around 2005,
                  which is more or less the same time in which the digital humanities began to
                  aspire. Both histories, the one that ended in the article's narrative and the one
                  that started with a companion, were motivated by the intent to separate one
                  research field from the other. The first history tried to show that the newly
                  emerging DH was in some sense always already part of the established field of film
                  and media studies. The second history presupposes that only by creating a new
                  field, the old will actually become the new. Comparing the history of digital
                  humanities methods in film and media studies with the history of film and media
                  studies topics in the digital humanities clearly shows that both lines of
                  arguments get it wrong, because in the growing number of encounters between film
                  and media studies and digital humanities, a new reality emerges that is both
                  post-humanistic and post-digital <ptr target="#cramer2014"/>.</p>
               <p>Certainly, film and media studies have to engage more profoundly with the
                  methodological part of statistical and algorithmic approaches. This has slowly
                  begun to happen throughout the last years, as projects such as the large-scale
                  video analytics project <ptr target="#kuhn2015"/>, activities of the scientific
                  networks Digital Cinema Studies<note><ref
                        target="https://www.digitalcinemastudies.com"
                        >https://www.digitalcinemastudies.com</ref></note> or New Directions in Film
                        Historiography<note><ref
                        target="https://www.uni-marburg.de/en/fb09/institutes/media-studies/research/research-projects/digitalfilmhistoriography"
                        >https://www.uni-marburg.de/en/fb09/institutes/media-studies/research/research-projects/digitalfilmhistoriography</ref></note>
                  or projects like FilmColors <ptr target="#fluckiger2017"/> and
                        Kinepoetics<note><ref
                        target="http://www.cinepoetics.fu-berlin.de/en/index.html"
                        >http://www.cinepoetics.fu-berlin.de/en/index.html</ref></note> suggest. At
                  the same time, it appears to be equally important for the digital humanities to
                  reflect on their rather broad conception of technology, in order to continue to
                  make substantial contributions to the reconfiguration of research by digital
                  technologies. A fuzzy reference to the <quote rend="inline">big tent</quote>
                  <ptr target="#terras2013"/> or the <quote rend="inline">big humanities</quote>
                  <ptr target="#svensson2016"/> will not suffice in this respect.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>4. Toward an Integrated Perspective: Digital Film Studies and Digital
               Humanities</head>
            <p>In this section we bring together the individual disciplinary perspectives on digital
               film studies in an integrated perspective within the digital humanities. The three
               disciplinary perspectives of (1) GLAMs and archives, (2) computer science, and (3)
               film and media studies align very well with the three sub-areas of Digital Humanities
               as identified by <ref target="#roth2019">Roth (2019)</ref>: the digitized humanities,
               the numerical humanities and humanities of the digital. In the following, we
               illustrate the different variants of digital film studies with respect to the three
               sub-areas of digital humanities by means of concrete examples. We also use this basic
               classification to introduce the eight research projects and studies that are part of
               this special issue.</p>
            <div>
               <head>4.1 Digitized humanities</head>
               <p>This branch of DH is mostly concerned with the digitization of cultural artifacts.
                  This also includes the modeling of analog artifacts, i.e. the formal
                  representation of a cultural object. This formalization is an important
                  prerequisite for digital preservation and dissemination strategies, but also for
                  computational analyses of the material. For the formal representation of film, the
                  fundamental question is: how can we model a time-based and multimodal medium such
                  as film to be represented in discrete categories? As this is obviously a demanding
                  and complex task, it is important for scholars to be clear in advance – i.e.
                  before the actual modeling – about what they want to investigate: Are setting and
                  scene boundaries relevant for later analyses? Are they interested in
                  constellations of characters or the use of leitmotifs? Or do they want to take a
                  closer look at the dialog level? Due to the modeling effort involved, it is hardly
                  possible in practice to model everything pro forma, so a prior research question
                  is indispensable for the digitization and modeling of film and video. </p>
               <p>As a consequence, it is rather challenging to create film and video resources that
                  can be reused by a variety of scholars, as the research questions (and modeling
                  implications, cf. <ref target="#unsworth2002">Unsworth [2002]</ref>) vary widely
                  and as there are hardly any established annotation standards as known for other
                  types of media, for instance the <title rend="italic">Text Encoding
                     Initiative</title> (TEI) or the <title rend="italic">Music Encoding
                     Initiative</title> (MEI).<note>Note that there have been first steps toward
                     establishing a <title rend="italic">Film Encoding Initiative</title> (FEI) that
                     is based on the MEI: <ref target="https://github.com/cemfi/FEI"
                        >https://github.com/cemfi/FEI</ref>. However, this format does not seem to
                     be as established as TEI and MEI.</note> Further challenges are raised by born
                  digital videos, for example YouTube videos or Twitch.tv streams, as specific
                  concepts for offline storage and potential long-term preservation are needed that
                  lead to open copyright issues and new requirements for digital infrastructure. In
                  this special issue, Eva Hielscher contributes to the topic of modeling and
                  representing films by presenting an extensive case study on video annotation for a
                  corpus of <q>City Symphonies</q> in her article titled <title rend="quotes">The
                     Phenomenon of Interwar City Symphonies: A Combined Methodology of Digital Tools
                     and Traditional Film Analysis Methods to Study Visual Motifs and Structural
                     Patterns of Experimental-Documentary City Films</title>.<note><ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/4/000495/000495.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/editorial/000495/000495.html</ref></note> Another article in this special issue is on <title rend="quotes"
                     >Matching Computational Analysis and Human Experience. Performative Arts and
                        the Digital Humanities</title>.<note><ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/4/000496/000496.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/editorial/000496/000496.html</ref></note> Here, Jan-Hendrik
                  Bakels et al. investigate the combination and mediation of experience-based and
                  data-driven analytical procedures in film studies. They transfer common film
                  analytical vocabulary into a machine-readable ontology to set up a systematic
                  annotation routine for films that can be visualized and queried.</p>
               <p>Digitization of films and videos is also important for film heritage institutions,
                  as it helps to collect filmographic information from diverse sources by means of
                  specialized search functions, OCR or image recognition among others. This can also
                  support digital archives with <q>mining</q> their objects, for example finding
                  certain subjects/topics/people etc. Therefore, archives are excellent agents for
                  advancing the standardization of filmographic metadata, for instance by
                  benefitting from experiences with metadata standards such as EN 15907 (see <ref
                     target="#heftberger2014" loc="143">Heftberger [2014]: 143</ref>). Another key
                  task here is the presentation of collections (or parts thereof) online in an
                  appealing, sensible and effective way. Institutions are fully aware that building
                  good interfaces is critical, but there seem to be many obstacles still in their
                  way. Insufficient financial resources might be one of those obstacles, being stuck
                  in building traditional entry points to collections may be another one. Masson et
                  al. provide a deep and comprehensive discussion of traditional and new paradigms
                  in this area in their article titled <title rend="quotes">Exploring Digitised
                     Moving Image Collections: The SEMIA Project, Visual Analysis and the Turn to
                     Abstraction</title>.<note><ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/4/000497/000497.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/editorial/000497/000497.html</ref></note> Additionally, they are able to
                  substantiate this discussion by introducing the SEMIA platform, a convincing
                  example for how adequate interfaces might be designed.</p>
               <p>In the past film archives, for the most part, differentiated between technical
                  expertise and work with content. However, a greater permeability between the areas
                  of responsibility is required in the future in order to comply with the
                  abovementioned challenges. It is already the case that many tasks are no longer
                  addressable by traditional roles. Digital data management, for instance, cannot be
                  restricted to just one area of material (e.g. films, photos or documents) and
                  metadata must be managed across the boundaries of collections in order to use
                  technical infrastructures and personnel resources in the best possible way among
                  other reasons. The strategy must therefore be twofold in the future: Teaming up
                  with researchers and artists as well as staffing their places with technically
                  savvy people who at the same time understand archival objects and are interested
                  in exhibition. Digital humanities as digitized humanities have organized around
                  such entanglements for years and may, therefor, provide valuable points of
                  reference for the field of digital film studies.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>4.2 Numerical humanities</head>
               <p>This second category is oftentimes also referred to as <term>computational
                     humanities</term>, highlighting the aspect of empirical analyses by means of
                  statistical procedures and machine learning techniques. In recent years, we have
                  seen a gradual extension of the established formal-stylistic analyses <ptr
                     target="#salt1974"/>
                  <ptr target="#tsivian2009"/>, which mostly relied on the lengths and frequencies
                  of shots within a movie. Going well <quote rend="inline">beyond shot
                     lengths</quote>
                  <ptr target="#burghardt2016"/>, a whole series of studies have been carried out
                  recently, for example to examine the color dimension <ptr target="#burghardt2017"/>
                  <ptr target="#fluckiger2017"/>
                  <ptr target="#pause2018"/>
                  <ptr target="#pause"/> or the dialogs of films <ptr target="#bednarek2018"/>
                  <ptr target="#holobut2016"/>. Another branch of work in this category can be found
                  in the area of visual analytics <ptr target="#burghardt2018"/>
                  <ptr target="#hoyt2014"/>
                  <ptr target="#kurzhals2016"/>, as visualizations can greatly facilitate the
                  analysis of visual time-based media such as film and video <ptr
                     target="#manovich2013"/>.</p>
               <p>This special issue features two numerical humanities studies that investigate the
                  textual dimension of series and movies. In their article on <title rend="quotes"
                     >The Stylometry of Film Dialogue: Pros and Pitfalls</title>,<note><ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/4/000498/000498.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/editorial/000498/000498.html</ref></note> Agata Hołobut and Jan Rybicki analyze 300 film dialogs by means of
                  stylometry and sentiment analysis to detect patterns of similarity and difference
                  between screenwriters and/or a priori IMDB-defined genres. Joanna Byszuk goes in a
                  similar direction with her article called <title rend="quotes">The Voices of
                     Doctor Who – How Stylometry Can be Useful in Revealing New Information About TV
                     Series</title>.<note><ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/4/000499/000499.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/editorial/000499/000499.html</ref></note> More concretely, she uses stylometry
                  to examine the changes driving the development of the "Doctor Who" series from a
                  character-oriented to a showrunner-oriented series. </p>
               <p>As part of the numerical humanities, deep learning approaches are also
                  increasingly being used in the sense of <quote rend="inline">deep watching</quote>
                  <ptr target="#howanitz2019"/> or <quote rend="inline">distant viewing</quote>
                  <ptr target="#arnold2019"/>, in order to automatically segment films and identify
                  objects or people. In this special issue, Barbara Flückiger and Gaudenz Halter
                  contribute an article on <title rend="quotes">Methods and Advanced Tools for the
                     Analysis of Film Colors in Digital Humanities</title>,<note><ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/4/000500/000500.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/editorial/000500/000500.html</ref></note> which provides an excellent example for numerical humanities, showcasing
                  a sophisticated deep learning approach to investigate color usage in film. Another
                  deep learning example is provided in the article <title rend="quotes">Automated
                     Visual Content Analysis for Film Studies: Current Status and Challenges</title>,<note><ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/4/000518/000518.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/editorial/000518/000518.html</ref></note> by Ralph Ewerth et al. The authors provide a thorough
                  survey of approaches and tools for automated video analysis to support
                  quantitative and qualitative analysis in film studies. </p>
               <p>For digital film studies, the digital humanities as numerical humanities mostly
                  represent methods that try to automate the identification of established entities
                  and units within film studies research. By doing so, they mimic analytical methods
                  of the field, but on a much larger scale than would be possible by means of
                  qualitative analyses of – typically – just a few films. In recent time, however,
                  there are also new approaches that aim at a semi-automatic and, thus, more
                  interactive analysis which seem to prioritize exploration instead of extraction.
                  This re-evaluation of priorities may well open-up the perspective for
                  contributions to a more diverse understanding of numerical and computational
                  approaches to the study of films.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>4.3 Humanities of the digital</head>
               <p>This category describes humanities scholars’ broader interest for the inclusion of
                  phenomena that emerge from the <q>digital culture.</q> In the field of film
                  studies, this might, for instance, entail the abovementioned investigation of born
                  digital videos, which very often also brings with it a dimension of mass
                  communication and thus big data: either, because a multitude of videos are
                  available, or because there is additional mass communication channel available,
                  e.g. in the form of comments about a video (reception aesthetics). It also
                  includes an examination of digital aesthetics as well as of new forms of
                  production and reception in an increasingly digitized, post-cinema film culture.
                  Such changes inevitably raise theoretical questions that, at the same time, are
                  necessarily linked to new research practices. Due to the sheer volume of digitally
                  available material, a serious opening of the humanities towards digital culture
                  obviously requires an increased integration of digital methods into scholarly
                  practices as well.</p>
               <p>From the perspective of film studies, the central challenge humanities of the
                  digital imposes, is the need for a holistic instead of a pragmatic integration of
                  digital methods, not the least because these methods have become methods of
                  production and analysis (film essay) at the same time. A central task in this
                  context is to reflect on the changing relationship between research instrument and
                  research subject, to bring together quantitative and qualitative methods, to find
                  ways to mediate between metrization and interpretation. It is important to
                  demonstrate that approaches of data-driven research can be particularly productive
                  in the field of film and media studies when they are conceived of as tools within
                  the framework of a diverse practice (cf. <ref target="#antonijevic2015"
                     >Antonijevic [2015]</ref>) or mixed methods <ptr target="#pereira2019"/>. In
                  this setup, digital methods are part of a practice, but not its overarching theme.
                  One example for such a more praxeologically oriented approach to the integration
                  of digital methods in film studies has been recently systematized under the term
                     <term>scalable viewing</term>
                  <ptr target="#burghardt2018"/>
                  <ptr target="#pause2020"/>.</p>
               <p>In this context, the <q>Humanities of the Digital</q> provide theoretical
                  foundations for new notions of the digital that have the potential to make digital
                  methods more accessible for film studies research. Such notions root deeper in the
                  tradition of the humanities, while at the same time highlighting the necessity and
                  added value of algorithmic strategies. In this special issue, Sarah-Mai Dang
                  contributes to this third sub-field of digital humanities by presenting an article
                  on <title rend="quotes">Unknowable Facts and Digital Databases: Reflections on the
                     Women Film Pioneers Project and Women in Film History</title>.<note><ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/4/000528/000528.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/editorial/000528/000528.html</ref></note> More concretely, she discusses the epistemological function and the
                  scholarly implications of databases in film and media studies.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>5. Conclusions</head>
            <p>The challenges that have been outlined throughout the entire editorial call for a
               joint interdisciplinary effort of computer scientists, film studies scholars and
               archivists and represent an exciting research agenda for the coming years. While it
               seems to be the case that each of the digital humanities sub-areas gravitates around
               one particular discipline – namely <term>digitization</term> with GLAM,
                  <term>numerical</term> with computer science and <term>digital</term> with film
               and media studies – it would be dangerous to just equate them with each other. Tools
               that are used for video criticism often build upon the same statistical and machine
               learning methods that are used in the numerical humanities, and without doubt, both
               GLAM and computer science are evaluating the broad field of new research objects in
               digital media. The horizon, however, that is particularly addressed by the digital
               humanities, is one in which one discipline is not just informed by the others but in
               which each discipline contributes on all levels to a shared space of insights,
               developments and practices.</p>
            <p>The FilmColors <ptr target="#fluckiger2017"/> project, for example, started from the
               insight, that approaches for the extraction of dominant colors, common in computer
               science have significant drawbacks. Based on this insight, the project defined a new
               approach that makes use of cultural concepts about how spectators process the
               kinematic image. It, however, did not just provide these insights to computer
               scientists, it also implemented a new machine learning pipeline for colorimetric
               analysis that is immediately available to the field of computer science for further
               optimization. The project, moreover, introduced innovations to the presentation of
               colorimetric information on the user interface level that are certainly inspiring for
               the aforementioned issues in the GLAM sector. It is precisely these overlaps out of
               which film and moving image analysis inside the umbrella of digital humanities might
               emerge as a field of its own. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="adams2001" label="Adams et al. 2001">Adams, B., Dorai, C., and Venkatesh,
               S. <title rend="quotes">Automated film rhythm extraction for scene analysis.</title>
               <title rend="italic">ICME 2001: Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on
                  Multimedia and Expo</title> (2001): 1056-1059.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="adams2002" label="Adams et al. 2002">Adams, B., Dorai, C., and Venkatesh,
               S. <title rend="quotes">Formulating Film Tempo. The Computational Media Aesthetics
                  Methodology in Practice.</title> In C Dorai and S Venkatesh (eds.), <title
                  rend="italic">Media Computing: Computational Media Aesthetics</title>. Kluwer
               Academic Publishers, Norwell, MA (2002): 57-84.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="atkins2003" label="Atkins 2003">Atkins, D. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Revolutionizing Science and Engineering through Cyberinfrastructure. Report of
                  the National Science Foundation Blue-Ribbon Advisory Panel on
                  Cyberinfrastructure,</title> US National Science Foundation (2003). [ <ref
                  target="http://www.nsf.gov/cise/sci/reports/atkins.pdf"
                  >http://www.nsf.gov/cise/sci/reports/atkins.pdf</ref>] </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="anderson2008" label="Anderson 2008">Anderson, C. <title rend="quotes">The
                  End of Theory: The Data Deluge Makes the Scientific Method Obsolete.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Wired</title> 16.7 (2008).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="antonijevic2015" label="Antonijevic 2015">Antonijevic, S. <title
                  rend="italic">Amongst Digital Humanists. An ethnographic study of digital
                  knowledge production</title>. Palgrave Macmillan, London (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="arden2007" label="Arden 2007">Arden, L. <title rend="quotes">Cyberinfrastructure Vision for 21st Century Discovery.</title> National Science Foundation. US National Science Foundation (2007). [<ref target="https://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2007/nsf0728/nsf0728.pdf">https://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2007/nsf0728/nsf0728.pdf</ref>]
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="arnold2019" label="Arnold and Tilton 2019">Arnold, T. and Tilton, L.
                  <title rend="quotes">Distant Viewing: Analyzing Large Visual Corpora.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> (2019).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baltrusaitis2018" label="Baltrusaitis et al. 2018">Baltrusaitis, T.,
               Ahuja, C., and Morency, L.-P. <title rend="quotes">Multimodal machine learning: A
                  survey and taxonomy.</title>
               <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis &amp; Machine
                  Intelligence</title> 41.2 (2018): 423-443.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baxter2017" label="Baxter et al. 2017">Baxter, M., Khitrova, D., and
               Tsivian, Y. <title rend="quotes">Exploring Cutting Structure in Film, with
                  Applications to the Films of D. W. Griffith, Mack Sennett, and Charlie
                  Chaplin.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> 32.1
               (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bednarek2018" label="Bednarek 2018">Bednarek, M. <title rend="italic"
                  >Language and Television Series: A Linguistic Approach to TV Dialogue</title>.
               Cambridge University Press, Cambridge (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="berry2014" label="Berry 2014">Berry, D. M. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Post-Digital Humanities: Computation and Cultural Critique in the Arts and
                  Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Educause</title> 49.3 (2014): 22-26. [ <ref
                  target="http://www.educause.edu/">http://www.educause.edu</ref>].</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bohme2012" label="Böhme et al. 2012">Böhme, S., Nohr, R. F., and Wiemer,
               S. <title rend="italic">Sortieren, Sammeln, Suchen, Spielen. Die Datenbank als
                  mediale Praxis</title>. LIT Verlag, Münster (2012).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="burghardt2016" label="Burghardt et al. 2016">Burghardt, M., Kao, M., and
               Wolff, C. <title rend="quotes">Beyond Shot Lengths. Using Language Data and Color
                  Information as Additional Parameters for Quantitative Movie Analysis.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Book of Abstracts of the International Digital Humanities
                  Conference (DH)</title> (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="burghardt2017" label="Burghardt et al. 2017">Burghardt, M., Hafner, K.,
               Edel, L., Kenaan, S., and Wolff, C. <title rend="quotes">An Information System for
                  the Analysis of Color Distributions in MovieBarcodes.</title> Proceedings of the
               15th International Symposium of Information Science (ISI) (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="burghardt2018" label="Burghardt et al. 2018">Burghardt, M., Kao, M., and
               Walkowski, N.-O. <title rend="quotes">Scalable MovieBarcodes. An Exploratory
                  Interface for the Analysis of Movies.</title>
               <title rend="italic">IEEE Vis4DH Workshop</title> (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="casey2014" label="Casey and Williams 2014">Casey, M., and Williams, M.
                  <title rend="quotes">ACTION (Audio-Visual Cinematic Toolbox for Interaction,
                  Organization, and Navigation): An Open-Source Python Platform.</title> White Paper
               HD-51394-11 (2014). [<ref
                  target="https://securegrants.neh.gov/publicquery/main.aspx?f=1&amp;gn=HD-51394-11"
                  >https://securegrants.neh.gov/publicquery/main.aspx?f=1&amp;gn=HD-51394-11</ref>].</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chavez-heras2012" label="Chavéz-Heras 2012">Chávez-Heras, D. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Malleable Computer: Software and the Study of the Moving
                  Image.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Frames Cinema Journal</title> 1.1 (2012). [<ref
                  target="https://framescinemajournal.com/article/the-malleable-computer/"
                  >https://framescinemajournal.com/article/the-malleable-computer/</ref>].</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cheng2015" label="Cheng et al. 2015">Cheng, G., Wan, Y., Saudagar, A. N.,
               Namuduri, K., and Buckles, B. P. <title rend="quotes">Advances in human action
                  recognition: A survey.</title> arXiv preprint, arXiv:1501.05964 (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="choudhary2019" label="Choudhary et al. 2019">Choudhary, P., Goel, N., and
               Saini, M. <title rend="quotes">A Multimedia Based Movie Style Model.</title>
               <title rend="italic">IEEE International Conference on Multimedia &amp; Expo Workshops
                  (ICMEW)</title> (2019): 72-77. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cotsaces2006" label="Cotsaces et al. 2006">Cotsaces, C., Nikolaidis, N.,
               and Pitas, I. <title rend="quotes">Video shot detection and condensed representation.
                  A review.</title>
               <title rend="italic">IEEE Signal Processing Magazine</title> 23.2 (2006):
               28-37.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cramer2014" label="Cramer 2014">Cramer, F. <title rend="quotes">What Is
                     <q>Post-Digital</q>?.</title>
               <title rend="italic">A Peer-Reviewed Journal About Post Digital Research</title>
               (2014). [<ref target="https://aprja.net/article/view/116068"
                  >https://aprja.net/article/view/116068</ref>]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="datta2008" label="Datta et al. 2008">Datta, R., Joshi, D., Li, J., and
               Wang, J. Z. <title rend="quotes">Image retrieval: Ideas, influences, and trends of
                  the new age.</title>
               <title rend="italic">ACM Computing Surveys (CSUR)</title> 40.2 (2008): 5.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="delmolino2016" label="Del Molino et al. 2016">Del Molino, A. G., Tan, C.,
               Lim, J.-H., and Tan, A.-H. <title rend="quotes">Summarization of egocentric videos: A
                  comprehensive survey.</title>
               <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Human-Machine Systems</title> 47.1 (2016):
               65-76.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dobson2019" label="Dobson 2019">Dobson, J. <title rend="italic">Critical
                  Digital Humanities: The Search for a Methodology</title>. University of Illinois
               Press, Urbana (2019). [<ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5406/j.ctvfjd0mf"
                  >https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5406/j.ctvfjd0mf</ref>].</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2009" label="Drucker 2009">Drucker, J. <title rend="italic"
                  >SpecLab: Digital Aesthetics and Projects in Speculative Computing</title>.
               University of Chicago Press, Chicago (2009).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="druzhkov2016" label="Druzhkov and Kustikova 2016">Druzhkov, P. and
               Kustikova, V. <title rend="quotes">A survey of deep learning methods and software
                  tools for image classification and object detection.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Pattern Recognition and Image Analysis</title> 26.1 (2016):
               9-15.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="elwert2019" label="Elwert 2019">Elwert, F. <title rend="quotes">The Sudden
                  but Consequential Rise of the Computational Humanities. Billet.</title>
               <title rend="italic">A Belter's Life</title> (Blog) (2019). [<ref
                  target="https://belter.hypotheses.org/64"
               >https://belter.hypotheses.org/64</ref>].</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="erlend2012" label="Erlend 2012">Erlend, L. <title rend="quotes">The Video
                  Essay: The Future of Academic Film and Television Criticism?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Frames Cinema Journal</title> 1 (2012). [<ref
                  target="https://framescinemajournal.com/article/the-video-essay-the-future/"
                  >https://framescinemajournal.com/article/the-video-essay-the-future/</ref>]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ewerth2009" label="Ewerth et al. 2009">Ewerth, R., Mühling, M.,
               Stadelmann, T., Gllavata, J., Grauer, M., and Freisleben, B. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Videana: a software toolkit for scientific film studies.</title> In M. Ross, M.
               Grauer, B. Freisleben (eds.), <title rend="italic">Digital Tools in Media Studies.
                  Analysis and Research. An Overview</title>. Transcript, Bielefeld (2009): 101–116. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ferguson2015" label="Ferguson 2015">Ferguson, K. L. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Volumetric Cinema.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Transition: Journal of Videographic Film and Moving Image
                  Studies</title> 2 (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ferguson2017" label="Ferguson 2017">Ferguson, K. L. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Digital Surrealism: Visualizing Walt Disney Animation Studios.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 11.1 (2017). [<ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/1/000276/000276.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/1/000276/000276.html</ref>].</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="flanders2012" label="Flanders 2012">Flanders, J. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Time, Labor, and <q>Alternate Careers.</q></title> In M. K. Gold (ed.), <title
                  rend="italic">Digital Humanities Knowledge Work. Debates in the Digital
                  Humanities</title>. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2012):
               292-308.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="flickner1995" label="Flickner et al. 1995">Flickner, M., Sawhney, H.,
               Niblack, W., Ashley, J., Qian Huang, Dom, B., Gorkani, M., Hafner, J., Lee, D.,
               Petkovic, D., Steele, D., and Yanker, P. <title rend="quotes">Query by image and
                  video content: The QBIC system.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Computer</title> 28.9 (1995): 23-32.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fluckiger2017" label="Flückiger 2017">Flückiger, B. <title rend="quotes">A
                  Digital Humanities Approach to Film Colors.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Moving Image: The Journal of the Association of Moving Image
                  Archivists</title> 17.2 (2017): 71-94.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fluckiger2019" label="Flückiger 2019">Flückiger, B. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Cinematic worlds in color. Technology, aesthetics, analysis.</title> In <title
                  rend="italic">BITForum. Film techniques and technology: illusion, reality,
                  virtuality, innovation</title>. Busan, South Korea (2019): 11-39.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gibbs2011" label="Gibbs 2011">Gibbs, F. <title rend="quotes">Critical Discourse in the Digital Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 1.1 (2011)</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="grant2012" label="Grant 2012">Grant, C. <title rend="quotes">Film and
                  moving image studies: Re-born digital? Some participant
                  observations.</title> <title rend="italic">Frames Cinema Journal</title> 1.1
               (2012).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="grimshaw2018" label="Grimshaw 2018">Grimshaw, M. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Towards a Manifesto for a Critical Digital Humanities: Critiquing the Extractive
                  Capitalism of Digital Society.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Palgrave Communications</title> 4.1 (2018): 1-8. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="grosky1994" label="Grosky 1994">Grosky, W. I. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Multimedia information systems.</title>
               <title rend="italic">IEEE Multimedia</title> 1.1 (1994): 12-24.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gupta1997" label="Gupta and Jain 1997">Gupta, A. and Jain, R. <title
                  rend="quotes">Visual information retrieval.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Communications of the ACM</title> 40.5 (1997): 70-79.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="he2015" label="He et al. 2015">He, K., Zhang, X., Ren, S., and Sun, J.
                  <title rend="quotes">Delving deep into rectifiers: Surpassing human-level
                  performance on imagenet classification.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Computer
                  Vision</title> (2015): 1026-1034.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="heftberger2014" label="Heftberger 2014">Heftberger, A. <title
                  rend="quotes">Film archives and digital humanities - an impossible match? New job
                  descriptions and the challenges of the digital era.</title>
               <title rend="italic">MedieKultur: Journal of media and communication research</title>
               30.57 (2014): 135-153 [<ref
                  target="http://ojs.statsbiblioteket.dk/index.php/mediekultur/issue/view/2200"
                  >http://ojs.statsbiblioteket.dk/index.php/mediekultur/issue/view/2200</ref>
               <ref target="https://tidsskrift.dk/mediekultur/article/view/16487/17534"
                  >https://tidsskrift.dk/mediekultur/article/view/16487/17534</ref>].</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="heftberger2018a" label="Heftberger 2018a">Heftberger, A. <title
                  rend="italic">Digital Humanities and Film Studies: Visualising Dziga Vertov's
                  Work</title>. Springer International Publishing, Cham (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="heftberger2018b" label="Heftberger 2018b">Heftberger, A. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Current Landscape of Film Archiving and How Study Programs can
                  Contribute.</title>
               <title rend="italic">SYNOPTIQUE - An Online Journal of Film and Moving Image
                  Studies</title>, Special Issue. <title rend="italic">The Current Landscape of Film
                  Archiving and How Study Programs can Contribute</title> 6.1 (2018): 58-69. [<ref
                  target="http://synoptique.ca/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/9-adelheid-heftberger-the-current-landscape-of-film-archiving-and-how-study-programs-can-contribute.pdf"
                  >http://synoptique.ca/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/9-adelheid-heftberger-the-current-landscape-of-film-archiving-and-how-study-programs-can-contribute.pdf</ref>] </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="heftberger2020" label="Heftberger and Duchesne 2020">Heftberger, A. and
               Duchesne, P. <title rend="quotes">Cataloguing Practices in the Age of Linked Open
                  Data: Wikidata and Wikibase for Film Archives.</title> International Federation of
               Film Archives, Brussels, Belgium (2020). [<ref
                  target="https://www.fiafnet.org/pages/E-Resources/Cataloguing-Practices-Linked-Open-Data.html"
                  >https://www.fiafnet.org/pages/E-Resources/Cataloguing-Practices-Linked-Open-Data.html</ref>]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hey2009" label="Hey et al. 2009">Hey, T., Tansley, S., and Tolle, K.
                  <title rend="italic">The Fourth Paradigm: Data-Intensive Scientific
                  Discovery</title>. Microsoft Research, Redmond (2009).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="holobut2016" label="Hołobut et al. 2016">Hołobut, A., Rybicki, J., and
               Woźniak, M. <title rend="quotes">Stylometry on the Silver Screen: Authorial and
                  Translatorial Signals in Film Dialogue.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Book of Abstracts of the International Digital Humanities
                  Conference (DH)</title> (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="howanitz2019" label="Howanitz et al. 2019">Howanitz, G., Bermeitinger, B.,
               Radisch, E., Sebastian G., Rehbein, M., and Handschuh, S. <title rend="quotes">Deep
                  Watching - Towards New Methods of Analyzing Visual Media in Cultural
                  Studies.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Book of Abstracts of the International Digital Humanities
                  Conference (DH)</title> (2019).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hoyt2014" label="Hoyt et al. 2014">Hoyt, E., Ponot, K., and Roy, C. <title
                  rend="quotes">Visualizing and Analyzing the Hollywood Screenplay with
                  ScripThreads.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 8.4 (2014). [<ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/4/000190/000190.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/4/000190/000190.html</ref>] </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="juang2005" label="Juang and Rabiner 2005">Juang, B.-H. and Rabiner, L. R.
                  <title rend="quotes">Automatic speech recognition - a brief history of the
                  technology development.</title> Technical report. Georgia Institute of Technology,
               Atlanta Rutgers University and the University of California, Santa Barbara
               (2005).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="keathley2019" label="Keathley et al. 2019">Keathley, C., Mittell, J.,
               Grant, C., Faden, E. and Lee, K.B. <title rend="italic">The Videographic Essay:
                  Criticism in Sound &amp; Image</title>. Caboose Books, Montréal (2019).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kuhn2015" label="Kuhn et al. 2015">Kuhn, V., Craig, A., Simeone, M.,
               Satheesan, S. P., and Marini, L. <title rend="quotes">The VAT: Enhanced Video
                  Analysis.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2015 XSEDE Conference on Scientific
                  Advancements Enabled by Enhanced Cyberinfrastructure - XSEDE '15</title>. Louis,
               Missouri (2015): 1-4. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kurzhals2016" label="Kurzhals et al. 2016">Kurzhals, K., John, M.,
               Heimerl, F., Kuznecov, P., and Weiskopf, D. <title rend="quotes">Visual Movie
                  Analytics.</title>
               <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Multimedia</title> 18.11 (2016). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lew2006" label="Lew et al. 2006">Lew, M. S., Sebe, N., Djeraba, C., and
               Jain, R. <title rend="quotes">Content-based multimedia information retrieval: State
                  of the art and challenges.</title>
               <title rend="italic">ACM Transactions on Multimedia Computing, Communications, and
                  Applications (TOMM)</title> 2.1 (2006): 1-19.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="manovich2013" label="Manovich 2013">Manovich, L. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Visualizing Vertov.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Russian Journal of Communication</title> 5.1 (2013): 44-55.
                </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcluhan1964" label="McLuhan 1964">McLuhan, M. <title rend="italic"
                  >Understanding Media. The Extensions of Man</title>. 1st ed. McGraw-Hill, New York
               (1964).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcwhirter2015" label="McWhirter 2015">McWhirter, A. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Film Criticism, Film Scholarship and the Video Essay.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Screen</title> 56.3 (2015): 369-377. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mitrovic2001" label="Mitrovic et al. 2001">Mitrovic, D., Zeppelzauer, M.,
               Zaharieva, M., and Breiteneder, C. <title rend="quotes">Retrieval of Visual
                  Composition in Film.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 12th International Workshop on Image Analysis
                  for Multimedia Interactive Services</title>. Delft (2001).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mooers2007" label="Mooers 2007">Mooers, C. N. <title rend="quotes">The
                  theory of digital handling of non-numerical information and its implications to
                  machine economics.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Association for Computing Machinery
                  Conference</title>. National Science Foundation (2007).  <ref
                  target="http://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2007/nsf0728/index.jsp?org=EEC"
               >[</ref>http://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2007/nsf0728/index.jsp?org=EEC]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pause2018" label="Pause and Walkowski 2018">Pause, J. and Walkowski, N.O.
                  <title rend="quotes">Everything is Illuminated. Zur Numerischen Analyse von
                  Farbigkeit in Filmen.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Zeitschrift für digitale Geisteswissenschaften</title> (2018). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pause2020" label="Pause and Walkowski 2020">Pause, J. and Walkowski, N.O.
                  <title rend="quotes">Welten abnehmenden Lichts. Ein Multi-Scale Viewing des
                  Politthrillers im 21. Jahrhundert.</title>
               <title rend="italic">montage AV. Zeitschrift für Theorie und Geschichte
                  audiovisueller Kommunikation</title> 29 (2020): 59.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pause" label="Pause and Walkowski (forthcoming)">Pause, J. and Walkowski,
               N.O. <title rend="quotes">Zombies, Conspiracies, and Esthetics in Crisis. A
                  computational engagement with film genre.</title> In I. Ritzer (eds.), <title
                  rend="italic">Media and Genre. Dialogues in Aesthetics and Cultural
                  Analysis</title>. Cham (forthcoming)</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pearlman2018" label="Pearlman and Heftberger 2018">Pearlman, K. and
               Heftberger, A. <title rend="quotes">Editorial: Recognising Women’s Work as Creative
                  Work.</title> In A. Heftberger and K. Pearlman (eds.), <title rend="italic">Women
                  at the Editing Table: Revising Soviet Film History of the 1920s and 1930s</title>.
               Special Issue of <title rend="italic">Apparatus. Film, Media and Digital Cultures in
                  Central and Eastern Europe</title> 6 (2018)<title rend="italic">.</title>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pereira2019" label="Pereira 2019">de sá Pereira, M. <title rend="quotes">Mixed Methodological Digital
               Humanities.</title> In M. K. Gold and L. F. Klein (eds.), <title rend="italic">Debates in the
               Digital Humanities 2019</title>. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis
               (2019): 405-412.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pfeiffer1996" label="Pfeiffer et al. 1996">Pfeiffer, S., Fischer, S., and
               Effelsberg, W. <title rend="quotes">Automatic audio content analysis.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Forth ACM International Conference on
                  Multimedia '96</title>. Boston, MA (1996).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pouyanfar2018" label="Pouyanfar et al. 2018">Pouyanfar, S., Yang, Y.,
               Chen, S.-C., Shyu, M.-L., and Iyengar, S. <title rend="quotes">Multimedia big data
                  analytics: A survey.</title>
               <title rend="italic">ACM Computing Surveys (CSUR)</title> 51.1 (2018): 10.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vanrijsbergen1979" label="van Rijsbergen 1979">van Rijsbergen, C. <title
                  rend="italic">Information Retrieval</title>. Butterworth-Heinemann, London
               (1979).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="roth2019" label="Roth 2019">Roth, C. <title rend="quotes">Digital,
                  digitized, and numerical humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> 34.3 (2019):
               616-632.  </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rui1998" label="Rui et al. 1998">Rui, Y., Huang, T. S., and Mehrotra, S.
                  <title rend="quotes">Exploring video structure beyond the shots.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Multimedia
                  Computing and Systems</title> (1998): 237-240.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ruszev2018" label="Ruszev 2018">Ruszev, S. <title rend="quotes">Rhythmic
                  Trajectories. Visualizing Cinematic Rhythm in Film Sequences.</title> In
               Heftberger, A. and Grgic, A. (eds.), <title rend="italic">Women Cutting Movies:
                  Editors from East and Central Europe. </title>Special Issue of <title
                  rend="italic">Apparatus. Film Media and Digital Cultures of Central and Eastern
                  Europe</title> 7 (2018). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="salt1974" label="Salt 1974">Salt, B. <title rend="quotes">Statistical
                  Style Analysis of Motion Pictures.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Film Quarterly</title> 28.1 (1974): 13-22.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="salt2006" label="Salt 2006">Salt, B. <title rend="italic">Moving into
                  Pictures. More on Film History, Style, and Analysis</title>. Starword Publishing,
               London (2006).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="salton1983" label="Salton and McGill 1983">Salton, G. and McGill, M.
                  <title rend="italic">Introduction to modern information retrieval</title>.
               McGraw-Hill, New York (1983).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schaffner2014" label="Schaffner and Erway 2014">Schaffner, J. and Erway,
               R. <title rend="quotes">Does Every Research Library Need a Digital Humanities
                  Center?</title> OCLC Research, Dublin, Ohio (2014). [<ref
                  target="http://www.oclc.org/content/dam/research/publications/library/2014/oclcresearch-digital-humanities-center-2014.pdf"
                  >http://www.oclc.org/content/dam/research/publications/library/2014/oclcresearch-digital-humanities-center-2014.pdf</ref>]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schoffman2010" label="Schöffmann et al. 2010">Schöffmann, K., Hopfgartner,
               F., Marques, O., Boeszoermenyi, L., and Jose, J. M. <title rend="quotes">Video
                  browsing interfaces and applications: a review.</title>
               <title rend="italic">SPIE Reviews</title> 1.1 (2010). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sittel2017" label="Sittel 2017">Sittel, J. <title rend="quotes">Digital
                  Humanities in der Filmwissenschaft.</title>
               <title rend="italic">MEDIENwissenschaft: Rezensionen | Reviews</title> 4 (2017): 472. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="snoek2005" label="Snoek and Worring 2005">Snoek, C. G. and Worring, M.
                  <title rend="quotes">Multimodal video indexing: A review of the
                  state-of-the-art.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Multimedia Tools and Applications</title> 25.1 (2005):
               5-35.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="soleymani2009" label="Soleymani et al. 2009">Soleymani, M., Chanel, G.,
               Kierkels, J. J., and Pun, T. <title rend="quotes">Affective characterization of movie
                  scenes based on content analysis and physiological changes.</title>
               <title rend="italic">International Journal of Semantic Computing</title> 3<title
                  rend="italic">.</title>2 (2009): 235-254.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="svensson2010" label="Svensson 2010">Svensson, P. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Landscape of Digital Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 4.1 (2010). [<ref
                  target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/1/000080/000080.html"
                  >http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/1/000080/000080.html</ref>]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="svensson2016" label="Svensson 2016">Svensson, P. <title rend="italic">Big
                  Digital Humanities: Imagining a Meeting Place for the Humanities and the
                  Digital</title>. University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor (2016). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="terras2013" label="Terras 2013">Terras, M. <title rend="quotes">Peering
                  Inside the Big Tent.</title> In M. Terras, J. Nyhan and E. Vanhoutte (eds.),
                  <title rend="italic">Defining Digital Humanities</title>, London (2013):
               263-270. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tsivian2009" label="Tsivian 2009">Tsivian, Y. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Cinemetrics, Part of the Humanities' Cyberinfrastructure.</title> In M. Ross, M.
               Grauer and B. Freisleben (eds.), <title rend="italic">Digital Tools in Media
                  Studies</title>. Bielefeld (2009): 93-100. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tzelepis2016" label="Tzelepis et al. 2016">Tzelepis, C., Ma, Z., Mezaris,
               V., Ionescu, B., Kompatsiaris, I., Boato, G., Sebe, N., and Yan, S. <title
                  rend="quotes">Event-based media processing and analysis: A survey of the
                  literature.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Image and Vision Computing</title> 53 (2016): 3-19.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vonderaus2017" label="Vonderau 2017">Vonderau, P. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Quantitative Werkzeuge.</title> In M. Hagener and V. Pantenburg (eds.), <title
                  rend="italic">Handbuch Filmanalyse</title>. Wiesbaden (2017): 1-15. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wold1996" label="Wold et al. 1996">Wold, T., Blum, D., and Wheaton, J.
                  <title rend="quotes">Content-based classification, search, and retrieval of
                  audio.</title>
               <title rend="italic">IEEE Multimedia</title> 3 (1996): 27-36.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zaharieva2010" label="Zaharieva et al. 2010">Zaharieva, M., Zeppelzauer,
               M., Mitrovic, D., and Breiteneder, C. <title rend="quotes">Archive film
                  comparison.</title>
               <title rend="italic">International Journal of Multimedia Data Engineering and
                  Management</title> 1.3 (2010): 41-56.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zeppelzauer2011a" label="Zeppelzauer et al. 2011a">Zeppelzauer, M.,
               Zaharieva, M., Mitrovi¢, D., and Breiteneder, C. <title rend="quotes">Retrieval of
                  motion composition in Film.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Creativity</title> 22.4 (2011): 219-234.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zeppelzauer2011b" label="Zeppelzauer et al. 2011b">Zeppelzauer, M.,
               Mitrovic, D., and Breiteneder, C. <title rend="quotes">Cross-modal analysis of
                  audio-visual film montage.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of 20th International Conference on Computer
                  Communications and Networks (ICCCN) </title>(2011): 1-6. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zhao2017" label="Zhao et al. 2017">Zhao, B., Feng, J., Wu, X., and Yan, S.
                  <title rend="quotes">A survey on deep learning-based fine-grained object
                  classification and semantic segmentation.</title>
               <title rend="italic">International Journal of Automation and Computing</title> 14.2
               (2017): 119-135.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zhou2017" label="Zhou et al. 2017">Zhou, W., Li, H., and Tian, Q. <title
                  rend="quotes">Recent advance in content-based image retrieval: A literature
                  survey.</title> arXiv preprint, arXiv:1706.06064 (2017).</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
