<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Tremendous Mechanical Labor: Father Busa’s
                    Algorithm</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Geoffrey <dhq:family>Rockwell</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Alberta</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>grockwel@ualberta.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Geoffrey Rockwell is a Professor of Philosophy and Digital Humanities at
                            the University of Alberta where he is also the Director of the Kule
                            Institute for Advanced Study and Associate Director of AI for Society
                            signature area. He publishes on textual visualization, text analysis,
                            pachinko, ethics and technology and on digital humanities including a
                            co-authored book with Stéfan Sinclair titled <title rend="italic"
                                >Hermeneutica</title> from MIT Press (2016). He is co-developer with
                            Sinclair of Voyant Tools (<ref target="voyant-tools.org/"
                                >voyant-tools.org</ref>), an award winning suite of text analysis
                            tools. He is currently the President of the Canadian Society for Digital
                            Humanities (CSDH-SCHN).</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Stéfan <dhq:family>Sinclair </dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>McGill University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Stéfan Sinclair was an Associate Professor of Digital Humanities at
                            McGill University. His primary area of research was in the design,
                            development, usage and theorization of tools for the digital humanities,
                            especially for text analysis and visualization. He led or contributed
                            significantly to projects such as Voyant Tools, the Text Analysis Portal
                            for Research (TAPoR), the MONK Project, the Simulated Environment for
                            Theatre, the Mandala Browser, and BonPatron. In additional to his work
                            developing sophisticated scholarly tools, he had numerous publications
                            related to research and teaching in the Digital Humanities, including
                            Visual Interface Design for Digital Cultural Heritage, co-authored with
                            Stan Ruecker and Milena Radzikowska (Ashgate 2011) and Hermeneutica with
                            Geoffrey Rockwell (MIT Press 2016). He was active in the digital
                            humanities community serving as President of both the Association for
                            Computers and the Humanities (ACH), VP of the Canadian Society for
                            Digital Humanities / Société pour l'étude de médias interactifs
                            (SDH/SEMI) and an editor of Digital Humanities Quarterly (Digital
                            Humanities Quarterly). We grieve his untimely passing on August 6th,
                            2020. An obituary is available at <ref
                                target="https://csdh-schn.org/stefan-sinclair-in-memoriam-2/"
                                >https://csdh-schn.org/stefan-sinclair-in-memoriam-2/</ref>.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000456</idno>
                <idno type="volume">014</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2020-09-25">25 September 2020</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2022-08-10" who="BRG">fixed encoding errors</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>This paper looks at innovations in Busa’s <title rend="italic">Index
                        Thomisticus</title> project through the tension between mechanical and human
                    labour. We propose that Busa and the IBM engineer Paul Tasman introduced two
                    major innovations that allowed computers to process unstructured text. The first
                    innovation was figuring out how represent unstructured text on punched cards,
                    the way data was encoded and handled at that time. The second innovation was
                    figuring out how to tokenize unstructured phrases on cards into words for
                    further counting, sorting and concording. We think-through these innovations
                    using replication as a form of media archaeology practice that can help us
                    understand the innovations as they were thought through at the time. All this is
                    framed by a letter found in the Busa archives criticizing the project as a
                        <quote rend="inline">tremendous mechanical labour ... of no great
                        utility.</quote> We use this criticism to draw attention to the very
                    different meshing of human and mechanical labour developed at Busa’s concording
                    factory. </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Examines innovations in <title rend="italic">Index Thomisticus</title> and their
                    implications for mechanical and human labour</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <epigraph>
                <quote rend="block">From the standpoint of philosophy and theology, it is my opinion
                    that the proposed work would have no utility commensurate with the tremendous
                    mechanical labor it would involve. While an Index of technically philosophical
                    and theological terms occurring in the <title rend="italic">Opera Omnia</title>
                    of St. Thomas would be very useful, the extension of the work to include
                        <emph>all</emph> words in St. Thomas’ works (including, I presume,
                    conjunctions, prepositions, etc.) seems to me : — 1) of no great utility; 2) a
                    sort of fetish of scholarship gone wild, and 3) a drift in the direction of pure
                    mechanical verbalism which would tend to deaden rather than revivify the thought
                    of St. Thomas. (I think he himself would have been horrified at the
                    thought!)</quote>
                <note> Letter from Daniel L. McGloin S.J., Chairman of the Philosophy department to
                    the President/Rector at Loyola University of Los Angeles. The date would have
                    been before February 14th, 1950 when the President/Rector, Charles S. Casassa
                    S.J., enclosed this letter with one he wrote back to Busa on that date. These
                    letters are held in the Busa Archive.</note>
            </epigraph>
            <div>
            	<head/>
                <p>Early in 1950, Daniel L. McGloin, the Chair of Philosophy at Loyola University of
                    Los Angeles (now Loyola Marymount) wrote a letter critical of the idea of the
                        <title rend="italic">Index Thomisticus</title> project that Father Busa had
                    been promoting in order to get support. We know from the correspondence
                    preserved in the Busa Archive that Busa had sent out letters describing the
                    project and soliciting letters of support. While most correspondents did write
                    supportive letters, at least one did not. McGloin’s review of the project was
                    for his Rector who enclosed it in his note back to Busa. The project was,
                    according to McGloin, <quote rend="inline">a sort of fetish of scholarship gone
                        wild</quote>. It was the one negative response we have on record and it is
                    clear that McGloin was appalled.</p>
                <p>What exactly bothered McGloin so much? What can we learn from the criticism of
                    what is arguably the first digital humanities project? In what could be the
                    first instance of a long tradition of pointing out the dark side of automation
                    in the humanities, McGloin the philosopher was horrified by what he perceived to
                    be the <quote rend="inline">mechanical verbalism which would tend to deaden
                        rather than revivify the thought of St. Thomas.</quote> He could see the
                    value of a concordance of philosophical and theological terms, but not of
                        <emph>all</emph> words. He thought this was <quote rend="inline">of no great
                        utility</quote>, especially considering the <quote rend="inline">tremendous
                        mechanical labor it would involve.</quote><note>Jones (2016) discusses this
                        letter in Chapter 3 of his book. He points out that McGloin believed the
                        project was <quote rend="inline">insufficiently interpretative — a complaint
                            that would continue to be brought against computing in the humanities
                            for decades and, indeed, continues today to figure in critiques of the
                            digital humanities.</quote> (Location 2336)</note> In criticizing Busa’s
                    project he played with a contrast between the living (and the labor that
                    revivifies thought) against the mechanical (and the mindless work that
                        deadens).<note>McGloin’s judgement of Busa’s project can be understood as an
                        extension of an essay he published while in graduate school in 1945 about
                            <title rend="quotes">Revitalizing Liberal Education.</title> (Note the
                            <soCalled>vital</soCalled> language in the title.) In this he complained
                        about the technological materialism guiding life at the end of the war.
                            <quote rend="inline">Unconsciously, we have come to view life after the
                            analogy of an assembly-line. We construct an educational system as we
                            blueprint an efficient factory, which is an aggregation of machines and
                            operators. Bring your material in, run it through the machines, and out
                            comes a tank.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mcgloin1945" loc="135"/></note> In doing so he alerts us to a
                    tension in how digital methods change the actual work of the humanist: who does
                    the work and how technologies are woven into our practices.</p>
                <p>This paper sets out to understand that tension by revisiting the mechanical labor
                    of Busa’s project, or more precisely, by trying to replicate exactly how
                    automation was developed for concording Aquinas. Replication here is a praxis of
                    media archaeology that can help us understand the context of a technology as
                    understood in its time <ptr target="#zielinski2008"/>
                    <ptr target="#parikka2012"/> by trying to imitate what was done. Needless to
                    say, to understand the mechanical labor we also have to touch on the human labor
                    and how humans were integrated, though the human labor is not our primary focus
                    here.</p>
                <p>From the comfortable distance of more than half a century later, living as we do
                    in an epoch defined by language engineering companies like Alphabet (Google), we
                    can say that Busa and his IBM-based collaborator Tasman proved to be prescient,
                    despite McGloin’s complaints. No one today would question the usefulness of the
                    tremendous language processing techniques that are currently used, and that is
                    part of what makes it harder to understand the work that went into actually
                    developing ways for processing textual data back then. What were the mechanical
                    processes? What was the data processed and what processing techniques allowed
                    Busa and Tasman to generate a <quote rend="inline">First example of word indexes
                        automatically compiled and printed by IBM punched card machines</quote> (the
                    subtitle of Busa’s <title rend="italic">Varia Specima</title>)? Further, how was
                    what we today would call an algorithm for language processing conceived? For
                    better or worse, these techniques initiated a new era of mechanical and
                    eventually computer-assisted language engineering. It is therefore worth
                    recovering an understanding of what was achieved, and we will do that in four
                    moves.</p>

                <list>
                    <item>First, we will briefly discuss the historiography around Busa’s project.
                        What resources do we have access to if we want to understand the techniques
                        developed then? Where and how did he discuss this project?</item>
                    <item>Second, we will focus on the punched card data format that they developed.
                        How was text chosen and encoded for this project?</item>
                    <item>Third, we will look at the key tokenizing process that produced word cards
                        from phrases. We hope to convince readers that this was a significant
                        innovation for its time.</item>
                    <item>Fourth and finally, we will return to McGloin’s concerns around deadening
                        labor.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Historiography of a Project</head>
                <p>If projects are central to digital humanities practice <ptr target="#burdick2012"
                        loc="124"/>, then we must recognize that we have largely neglected that
                    aspect in the considerable literature on digital humanities as a discipline, and
                    it is time to ask how we can study projects. Concretely, for Busa’s project, a
                    first step would be to do a historiography of the <title rend="italic">Index
                        Thomisticus</title> project and the host of the project, the
                        GIRCSE<note>GIRCSE or the Gruppo Interdisciplinare di Ricerche per la
                        Computerizzazione dei Segni dell'Espressione (Interdiscplinary Group for
                        Research into the Computerization of Expressive Signs) was set up by Busa in
                        the 1970s. GIRCSE evolved into CIRCSE (Centro Interdisciplinare di Ricerche
                        per la Computerizzazione dei Segni dell’Espressione — Interdisciplinary
                        Centre for Research into the Computerization of Expressive Signs). See <ref
                            target="http://centridiricerca.unicatt.it/circse-centro-interdisciplinare-di-ricerche-per-la-computerizzazione-dei-segni-dell-il-centro-di-ricerca"
                            >http://centridiricerca.unicatt.it/circse-centro-interdisciplinare-di-ricerche-per-la-computerizzazione-dei-segni-dell-il-centro-di-ricerca.</ref></note>
                    centre. To understand ourselves in our paradigmatic project practices we need to
                    ask how one studies projects and labs when their scholarly outputs tend to hide
                    (deliberately or otherwise) their labor and infrastructure.</p>
                <p>In the case of GIRCSE and the <title rend="italic">Index Thomisticus</title> we
                    are unusually fortunate to have four types of resources in addition to the set
                    of publications where Busa and Tasman explicitly discuss their methods. First,
                    we have the extensive Busa Archive at the Library of the Catholic University of
                    the Sacred Heart in Milan (Biblioteca dell'Università Cattolica). Busa’s team
                    organized and kept an extraordinary record of unpublished documents related to
                    the project, from sales correspondence to every one of Busa’s
                        publications.<note> In addition, Busa’s family friend, student, and
                        colleague, Dr. Marco Passarotti is at the Catholic University and he has
                        been of great help promoting the value of the Archive and interpreting the
                        gems found. One of the authors (Rockwell) heard Passarotti talk at a
                        conference in Darmstat and as a result went to visit. Once at the archive
                        Rockwell met the archivist Paolo Senna, who is working hard to preserve and
                        digitize the extraordinary collection. He kindly scanned and allowed us to
                        show the <soCalled>Flow Chart</soCalled>.</note> These are now being
                    catalogued by the Library of the Catholic University. Some of the key documents
                    from the Archive include letters like the one from McGloin and others where Busa
                    described his method in different contexts. There are also sample punched cards;
                    a <soCalled>Flow Chart</soCalled>; photographs, including some of the people at
                    work on the project on the ex-factory floor; and a project
                        proposal.<note>Rockwell posted a long blog essay on <title rend="quotes">The
                            Index Thomisticus as Project</title> that describes many of the
                        documents we found useful in the Busa Archive. See <ref
                            target="http://theoreti.ca/?p=6096">http://theoreti.ca/?p=6096.</ref>
                        This also discusses the need for a historiography. The project proposal
                        dates from 1962.</note></p>
                <p>A second type of important resource is secondary sources like Steven Jones’ book
                        <title rend="italic">Roberto Busa, S. J., And the Emergence of Humanities
                        Computing: The Priest and the Punched Cards</title> (2016). Books like this
                    provide background context including many of the resources, key events, and
                    cultural contexts.<note> Steven Jones is now developing a web project <title
                            rend="quotes">Reconstructing the First Humanities Computing
                            Center</title>, with a contribution from us, that documents the Busa
                        project site in Gallarate. The site includes a 3D reconstruction of the
                        factory and a selection of images from the Busa Archive. See <ref
                            target="https://avc.web.usf.edu/images/RECAAL/"
                            >https://avc.web.usf.edu/images/RECAAL/.</ref></note> It is also the
                    best guide into understanding the origins of the project. Another valuable work
                    is Winter’s article <title rend="quotes">Roberto Busa, S.J., and the Invention
                        of the Machine-Generated Concordance</title> (1999) which defends the claim
                    that Busa was the first to automate concording.</p>
                <p>Thirdly, there are oral testimonies by those who worked on the project or knew of
                    it and related materials. Julianne Nyhan and Melissa Terras have been gathering
                    information about the women who worked on the <title rend="italic">Index
                        Thomisticus</title> project.<note> See Nyhan &amp; Terras 2017. See also
                        Melissa Terras’ blog essay at <ref
                            target="http://melissaterras.blogspot.co.uk/2013/10/for-ada-lovelace-day-father-busas.html"
                            >http://melissaterras.blogspot.co.uk/2013/10/for-ada-lovelace-day-father-busas.html.</ref>.</note>
                    Nyhan traveled to Italy and interviewed many of the women operators; she has a
                    book forthcoming on <title rend="italic">Uncovering <q>hidden</q> contributions
                        to the history of Digital Humanities: the Index Thomisticus’ female keypunch
                        operators.</title></p>
                <p>Finally, there are the publications by the project leaders like Busa and Tasman
                    describing the methods they were developing. Julianne Nyhan and Marco Passarotti
                    are putting together an edited and translated collection of some of Busa’s key
                    papers which will make it much easier to study Busa’s published thought. The key
                    publications used in this paper are, in chronological order:</p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>The <title rend="italic">Varia Specima Concordantium</title> from 1951
                        which is a concordance of the poetry of St. Thomas Aquinas that was the
                            <quote rend="inline">First example of word indexes automatically
                            compiled and printed by IBM punched card machines,</quote> as the
                        subtitle put it. This publication was the proof-of-concept project for the
                        much larger <title rend="italic">Index</title> and it was the first fruit of
                        the support from IBM for the <title rend="italic">Index.</title> It has a
                        bilingual Introduction (English and Italian) that describes their innovating
                        process.</item>
                    <item>Tasman’s 1957 article in an IBM trade journal on <title rend="quotes"
                            >Literary Data Processing.</title></item>
                    <item>Busa’s chapter from 1958 on <title rend="quotes">The Use of Punched Cards
                            in Linguistic Analysis</title> in a larger collection on <title
                            rend="italic">Punched Cards.</title></item>
                    <item>Busa’s project proposal from 1962 to IBM for completing the <title
                            rend="italic">Index</title> in time to show it at the New York World’s
                        Fair in 1964, <title rend="quotes">Per Completare Lo Index Thomisticus Per
                            L’Esposizione Mondiale Di New York 1964 – 1965</title> (For Completing
                        the Index Thomisticus For the New York World’s Fair 1964-1965).<note> See
                            the blog entry by Rockwell mentioned above at <title rend="quotes">The
                                Index Thomisticus as Project,</title>
                            <ref target="http://theoreti.ca/?p=6096"
                                >http://theoreti.ca/?p=6096.</ref></note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>In all of these there is a summary of the technical process they developed, a
                    clear indication of their awareness of the importance of the developing process
                    at the time. In the introduction of <title rend="italic">Varia Specima</title>
                    Busa summarizes this process as five stages and this summary is worth quoting as
                    a description of a workflow of the labor involved.<quote rend="block">I bring
                        down to five stages the most material part of compiling a concordance: <list
                            type="ordered">
                            <item>transcription of the text, broken down into phrases<note>The word
                                    for <soCalled>phrase</soCalled> used in the parallel Italian,
                                    which Busa probably wrote first, is the more technical word
                                        <soCalled>pericope</soCalled> which means a <quote
                                        rend="inline">coherent unit of thought</quote> and
                                    etymologically comes from <quote rend="inline">a
                                        cutting-out</quote>. (See the Wikipedia entry on Pericope,
                                        <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pericope"
                                        >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pericope</ref>.) In Tasman
                                    (1957) the word used is <quote rend="inline"
                                            ><emph>phrases</emph> (meaningful sub-grouping of words…
                                        .</quote> (p. 253)</note>, on to separate cards;</item>
                            <item>multiplication of the cards (as many as there are words on
                                each);</item>
                            <item>indicating on each card the respective entry (lemma);</item>
                            <item>the selection and placing in alphabetical order of all the cards
                                according to the lemma and its purely material quality;</item>
                            <item>finally, once that formal elaboration of the alphabetical order of
                                the words which only an expert's intelligence can perform, has been
                                done, the typographical composition of the pages to be published.
                                (p. 20)</item>
                        </list></quote></p>
                <p>He goes on to say that the IBM system could “carry out all the material part of
                    the work” of steps 2, 3, 4, and 5, though he also talks (p. 26) about the need
                    to have a philologist intervene at stage 3 to disambiguate and lemmatize words.
                    In Paul Tasman’s <title rend="quotes">Literary Data Processing</title> (1957)
                    the stages outlined are different. Instead of one step for <quote rend="inline"
                        >transcription of text</quote> he has two steps, that of the scholar who
                    marks up the text and that of the keypunch operator who copies it onto cards.
                    This more clearly separates the scholarly from the data entry work. <list
                        type="ordered">
                        <item>The scholar analyzes the text, marking it with precise instructions
                            for card punching.</item>
                        <item>A clerk copies the text using a special typewriter which operates a
                            card punch. This typewriter has a keyboard similar to that of a
                            conventional typewriter and produces the phrase cards. (p. 254)</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>In “The Use of Punched Cards” Busa describes yet another process. Here is the
                    flow chart that Busa provides in <title rend="quotes">The Use of Punched
                        Cards</title> (1958, 359). It focuses on who is doing the work: <figure>
                        <head>Flow chart from <quote rend="inline">The Use of Punched
                            Cards</quote></head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                    </figure>In this flow chart from 1958 we again have two operations at the start
                    – that of the scholar marking the original text and that of the entry of the
                    phrases by a key-punch operator. What is new is that the last two stages of 1951
                    are represented by one operation in 1958, but it is clear that the one box
                    covers many processes for different types of indexes.</p>
                <p>One thing that stands out in this process, especially when one looks at other
                    materials like the photographs of the space where the work was done, is how many
                    people were needed for what we today think of as an automated process. The
                    machines may have done some of the tedious work, but it took human labor to
                    prepare texts for data entry, then there was the data entry itself, there was
                    programming, there was the moving of stacks of cards from machine to machine,
                    and then were all the management tasks. The 1962 project proposal gives a break
                    down of the staff needed, admittedly for an accelerated completion. The number
                    of staff proposed, divided by department is listed as: <list>
                        <item>Machine Department: 33 staff (likely to be mostly women
                            operators)</item>
                        <item>Research Department: 21 staff</item>
                        <item>Programming Department: 7 staff</item>
                        <item>Management and Services: 9 staff</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>This is a total of 70 staff for a project that was supposed to be showing the
                    advantages of automation! What also stands out is the gendering of the
                    departments. The operators of the Machine Department, which was the largest
                    proposed unit, were mostly women. As Terras points out in her Ada Lovelace day
                    blog post (2013), it was women who actually ran the machines and they are often
                    shown in the photographs demonstrating the computing to men.</p>
                <p>Returning to the processes that were automated — and looking at the details of
                    the descriptions Busa and Tasman give us — two key innovations stand out that
                    made linguistic data processing possible. <list type="ordered">
                        <item>First, they developed a way of representing a text fully so that it
                            could be processed by machines, and</item>
                        <item>Second, they developed a process for tokenizing the text — generating
                            words cards with the electro-mechanical machines of the day.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>These innovations changed the integration of people and technologies that went
                    into concording, and for that matter, changed how data was processed (previously
                    cards had been used for structured data such as census information, but not for
                    unstructured linguistic data). It seems obvious now, but these innovative uses
                    of machines made possible a different organization of people and technology
                    where data entry was separated from programming which was separated from the
                    scholarly work. Technologies, as philosophers Ihde (1998) and Winner (1980)
                    remind us, are not neutral tools. McGloin may have intuited how Busa’s project
                    would still call for tremendous human labor despite the machines and that much
                    of that labor would be mechanical for the women involved.<note>It should be
                        noted that there was also repetitive labor, often gendered, in traditional
                        hand techniques of concording. What the technology changed was the division
                        of labor or the arrangement of humans and technologies.</note></p>
                <p>In sum, Busa’s team conceived a new way to break down the work of concording by
                    first figuring out how to represent text as data that could be processed by
                    machine and then figuring out how to process that data into tokens (words) that
                    could then be manipulated to generate various types of indexes. In these two
                    connected innovations they essentially developed literary data processing, no
                    small feat at the time.</p>
                <p>The next two parts of this paper will look at these two stages and discuss the
                    replication of what they might have actually done as a way of probing our
                    understanding. <quote rend="block">This is a story from early in the
                        technological revolution, when the application was out searching for the
                        hardware, from a time before the Internet, a time before the PC, before the
                        chip, before the mainframe. From a time even before programming itself. <ptr
                            target="#winter1999" loc="3"/></quote></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Punched Cards</head>
                <p>From today’s perspective it is hard to appreciate how different the
                        <emph>data</emph> of <soCalled>data processing</soCalled> was in those early
                    years. Busa could not go onto the internet or scan the texts he needed. All
                    input had to be punched by hand — there was no <soCalled>data</soCalled>,
                    nothing given. There weren’t any standard ways of representing texts for data
                    processing and punched cards were limiting. He wasn’t even using what would
                    today be considered a digital computer. The <title rend="italic">Varia
                        Specima</title> project (1951) which demonstrated the concept used
                    electro-mechanical machines to sort, replicate, and print on cards. This was a
                    liminal moment between mechanical data processing instruments with pre-defined
                    functions and digital, programmable computers with punched cards in common as a
                    way to enter, store, and record data and results.</p>
                <p>The one technology that had been at least partially standardized was the punched
                    card as a way of entering and storing data. The punched card, despite later
                    discussion about folding, spindling, or mutilating, was a robust way of entering
                    information so that it could be processed manually <emph>and</emph> by
                        computers.<note>The one technology that had been at least partially been
                        standardized was the punched card as a way of entering and storing data. The
                        punched card, despite later discussion about folding, spindling, or
                        mutilating, was a robust way of entering information so that it could be
                        processed manually and by computers. As a data technology it goes back to
                        the Jacquard loom and is still used today, such as in some voting machines
                        like those used in Florida in the 2000 presidential election between Bush
                        and Gore.</note> As a data technology it goes back to the Jacquard loom and
                    is still used today, such as in some voting machines like those used in Florida
                    in the 2000 presidential election between Bush and Gore.</p>
                <p>The Busa project used the IBM card format. This had been developed in 1928 and
                    had become a de facto standard. Each card was 7⅜ inches wide by 3¼ inches tall.
                    They were made of stiff paper with a notch in the upper left for orientation.
                    The arrangement of holes was standardized so that all relevant machines could
                    process them. Given the size, the IBM card could fit 80 columns and 12 rows of
                    punch locations. While the dimensions and punch zones were standardized,
                    projects could overprint with ink whatever they wanted on the cards as what was
                    printed wouldn’t affect the data processing; printing was intended for human
                    processing, not machine processing. <figure>
                        <head>Detail of <title rend="italic">Index Thomisticus</title> card from the
                            Busa Archive</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>It is also worth noting that Busa’s project was large and different enough that
                    they had their own non-standard cards, including some with bubbles for manual
                    pencil marks. Figure 2 shows an example card from the Busa Archive with the
                    areas and labels related to <title rend="quotes">Philological Analysis.</title>
                    These printed zones could have been used by scholars to manually add annotations
                    as needed for human sorting as part of hybrid machine/human processing. Or they
                    could have been used for easily reading the punched data. Either way, it was
                    common for punched cards in those days to have to be handled by both humans and
                    by machines <ptr target="#casey1951"/>. The <title rend="italic">Index
                        Thomisticus</title> project was no different; there would have been a
                    tremendous amount of human labor associated with handling the stacks of cards.
                    The human labor would have gone into preparing cards, moving them, checking
                    them, annotating them and even hand sorting them. It would be interesting to try
                    to recreate the flow of Busa’s hybrid processes, but that is for another
                        project.<note>One can get some sense of the flow from the images and
                        recreation of the project space in the Steve Jones’ <title rend="quotes"
                            >Reconstructing the First Humanities Computing Center</title> project.
                        See <ref target="http://www.recaal.org/"
                        >http://www.recaal.org/</ref>.</note></p>
                <dhq:passThroughCode lang="xhtml" rend="block">
                    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                        <iframe class="iframe-class" style="width: 100%; height: 600px;"
                            width="100%" height="480"
                            src="https://rawgit.com/sgsinclair/epistemologica/master/punchcard.html"
                            frameborder="0" scrolling="no" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0"
                            allowtransparency="true"><p>Your browser does not support iframes. Embedded document may be found at <a href="https://rawgit.com/sgsinclair/epistemologica/master/punchcard.html">https://rawgit.com/sgsinclair/epistemologica/master/punchcard.html</a>
        </p></iframe>
                    </div>
                </dhq:passThroughCode>
                <p>To return to understanding what Busa may have done in the way of digitally
                    representing textual data we have tried to virtually replicate the data
                    dimension of his punch cards with a simple interactive punch card that shows you
                    what holes would be punched in order to represent the data you want the card to
                    bear (see below). This is set up with our best guess of the card data format
                    they used — feel free to enter examples and see if you get what you expected. We
                    have here used replication as a way of thinking through the history of
                    computing. In the replication of a technology we can discover aspects of the
                    technology that wouldn’t occur when just documenting it and others can test our
                    hypothesis as to how data was encoded. Among other things the punched card
                    interactive helped us better understand how this encoding system was actually a
                    curious blend of a decimal-based system (0 to 9 with a couple of extra control
                    rows) and the more binary-based digital processing (0 or 1). A typical punched
                    card had 12 rows to represent any one character, which in fact is potentially
                    very high resolution (12-bit = 4096 possibilities), whereas the first character
                    sets for computers were at most 4, 5 or 6-bit (64 possibilities).</p>
                <p>In this case we were forced to figure out exactly which IBM format was used.
                    Emulating the cards raises the issue of <emph>what</emph> data Busa could encode
                    and <emph>how</emph> it was encoded on cards. Our best guess, looking at example
                    cards in the Archive, and reading descriptions, is that they used something like
                    the 48-character BCDIC (Binary-Coded Decimal Interchange Code). We know that by
                    the early 1930s there was a 40-character BCDIC format that combined more than
                    one hole per column to provide 40 characters (Space, 0-9, A-Z and a couple of
                    special characters.) By the late 1950s BCDIC had been extended and the IBM chain
                    printers were capable of printing 47 graphics (characters) along with a space to
                    make the 48-character BCDIC with 11 special characters, namely: .'$,#%-&amp;*/ ¤
                    . Keypunch equipment was also becoming available so users that could input any
                    of these characters with one key stroke, as opposed to having the operator
                    select the punch hole combinations for each character <ptr
                        target="#mackenzie1980" loc="88"/>. From the Tasman article we know that the
                    project used at least /, #, ‘, and ¤. <ptr target="#tasman1957" loc="254"/>
                    which is why our guess is that the project was using something close to
                    48-character BCDIC.<figure>
                        <head>Punching Positions for 48-character BCDIC<note>This comes from a web
                                page on the IBM 026 Key punch which we think Busa used as he listed
                                it in the 1962 project proposal <title rend="quotes">Per Completare
                                    Lo Index Thomisticus…</title>. See <ref
                                    target="http://www.columbia.edu/cu/computinghistory/026.html"
                                    >http://www.columbia.edu/cu/computinghistory/026.html.</ref></note></head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>It is worth noting however, that they did not need to adhere to any particular
                    standard the way we need to today. There was no operating system or
                    off-the-shelf software enforcing standards. There were no other projects that
                    might use their data. The only issue was what the keypunch could enter, what
                    could be read, and what the printers could print, if printing was needed. At
                    that time you could extend things and program the machines to operate on your
                    own hole combinations. It could very well be that the <title rend="italic">Index
                        Thomisticus</title> project provided some of the impetus behind the
                    extension to 48 character BCDIC as it would have been a major project defining
                    IBM’s move into linguistic engineering.</p>
                <p>Having explored some of the <emph>how</emph> of Busa’s work with punched cards,
                    we will now turn to the <emph>what</emph> or purpose of the work, because that
                    is where Tasman and Busa figured out a practical way to adapt the technology at
                    hand to text processing. The key was realizing that they only needed two sets of
                    cards for most literary/linguistic operations: a set of Sentence (or Phrase)
                    Cards making up the whole text, with associated information, and a set of Each
                    Word Cards (EWC) with all the words (tokens) and associated information. In
                    today’s terms they needed only two database tables to generate the various forms
                    of indexes they wanted; one was the full text, the second was a word index. In
                    the processing they showed that you can go from one to the other using the one
                    best suited for the analytic process. This is the precursor of analytical tools
                    that cache a word index in addition to the text for efficiency purposes.<quote
                        rend="block">Each phrase is preceded by the reference to the place where
                        this line is found and provided with a serial number and a special reference
                        sign. <ptr target="#tasman1957" loc="254"/></quote></p>
                <p>What was actually held on the two types of cards? The sentence or phrase cards
                    held the location/reference in the original text, the text of the phrase, a
                    number for the phrase (serial number) and a special reference mark to indicate
                    if the phrase was thought to be by St. Aquinas himself or a reference to words
                    by another. The amount of text for each card, given the limitations of 80
                    columns (not counting the columns reserved for reference data), would be decided
                    by the scholar who divided the text up into logical thoughts and then into
                    meaningful phrases that would fit on a card. It is important to note that human
                    intervention was needed to fit the ongoing unstructured text onto 80-column
                    cards.</p>
                <p>The EWCs had less text and more associated information. By the time of Tasman’s
                    article, each word card would have encoded in the punched holes the following
                    (some fields are further explained below): <list>
                        <item>A reference to the phrase card (and hence phrase location),</item>
                        <item>A special reference mark,</item>
                        <item>The word itself as it appears in the text,</item>
                        <item>A number (order) of the word in the text,</item>
                        <item>The first letter of the preceding word,</item>
                        <item>The first letter of the following word,</item>
                        <item>A Form Card number (alphabetical sequence), and</item>
                        <item>An Entry Card number.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>The Form Cards were the headings for each different word. The Entry cards were
                    the entry headings that presumably would appear in the final printed concordance
                    for the different word types after lemmatization and disambiguation
                        (<emph>dance</emph> as a verb or as a noun would have different entries, for
                    instance). These were created by a second intervention by scholars and would be
                    the entries in any published concordance. In Figure 4 you can see where in the
                    flow chart the Different Word Cards (or Form Cards) are generated along with the
                    summaries and lists that allow the Scholar to write a list of Entry Words.<figure>
                        <head>Detail from the 1953 <title rend="quotes">Flow Chart</title> from the
                            Busa Archive</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>There are a few noteworthy aspects about the project’s use of punched cards.
                    First, data on cards was material in the sense that users could physically touch
                    the carrier of the data — the punched card. Many of the processes from
                    keypunching to sorting involved physically manipulating the cards themselves,
                    not data in memory. The human was also part of the sequence of operations as
                    someone would have to load cards, move stacks from machine to machine, and cards
                    would actually be consulted by humans at certain points. Busa would have been
                    aware that he was setting up a system that integrated people and machines in new
                    configurations, at least for the humanities.<figure>
                        <head>Image of EWC in Tasman 1957 with a <quote rend="inline">Mark sensing
                                area for use of scholar in selecting, collating, printing, or
                                revising information</quote> (p. 250-1)</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>Busa and Tasman made full use of the materiality of the punched card. They
                    actually had at least three orders of information on the cards. There was what
                    we are going to call the data proper that was punched on the card and could be
                    operated on mechanically. Then they would print (not punch) extra information on
                    the front or back of the cards for human consultation. For example, they would
                    print the data punched on the top of the fronts of the cards so that they could
                    be checked by eye, or they could print up to 9 lines (phrases) of context on the
                    backs of EWCs so a scholar could easily check the context when lemmatizing
                    without having to call up the phrase card. Finally, they had an area on the left
                    of cards that would take lead pencil marks so scholars could mark cards for
                    additional processing.<note>It isn’t clear if Busa used optical mark readers on
                        the cards or if cards thus marked would be manually processed.</note> In
                    Tasman’s (1957) article we see that both the Sentence Cards and EWCs had such
                    areas.</p>
                <p>One way to appreciate the difference between data then and now is to reflect on
                    how the project was not about using computers or software as we understand them
                    now. The actual work involved punching information onto cards, proofing of
                    cards, using electromechanical machines to process the cards, creating new
                    cards, printing things on cards, moving cards from machine to machine,
                    duplicating them, and marking them for further processing. The
                        <soCalled>programming</soCalled> in this context was the design of the cards
                    so that various sorting, replicating and counting processes produce what was
                    needed. (It was also the wiring/configuring of the machines.) The cards enabled
                    and constrained what could be done. The work of the project as described by
                    Tasman was really the work of managing punched cards as tokens to be
                    interpreted. The cards were a surrogate for the text that could be processed to
                    produce a new concorded text.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Processing</head>
                <p>Now to the second innovation of Busa and Tasman and that is the algorithmic one.
                    It is fascinating to reconstruct the mechanical processes with which all this
                    information could be generated and added to the cards in successive passes with
                    a limited number of standard machines. For example, to add the first letter of
                    each following card the stack of EWCs would be sorted in reverse order of
                    appearance and then run through starting with the last word. The first character
                    of each word would then be carried forward (or backward in this case) and
                    written out on the next card, which illustrates another property of the material
                    cards, the fact that data can be incrementally added to the blank areas with
                    proper planning. We do not have space here to go through all the succession of
                    processes. Instead, we will focus on the one process that made literary data
                    processing possible, and that is the tokenizing of the Sentence Cards to
                    generate Each Word Cards (EWCs). This is the crucial innovation that showed how
                    systems designed for accounting could be used for unstructured text.<quote
                        rend="block">This is equivalent to state that each line was multiplied as
                        many times as words it contained. I must confess that in actual practice
                        this was not so simple as I endeavoured to make it in the description; the
                        second and the successive words did not actually commence in the same column
                        on all cards. In fact, it was this lack of determined fields which
                        constituted the greatest hindrance in transposing the system from the
                        commercial and statistical uses to the sorting of words from a literary
                        text. The result was attained by exploring the cards, column by column, in
                        order to identify by the non-punched columns the end of the previous word
                        and the commencement of the following one; thus, operating with the sorter
                        and reproducer together, were produced only those words commencing and
                        finishing in the same columns. <ptr target="#busa1951" loc="24/26"/></quote>
                    This would have been considered difficult at the time. As Busa writes in 1951,
                    the existing commercial accounting and statistical uses of punched cards assumed
                    that there would be zones on the card that constituted predictable fields. These
                    fields could hold alphabetic information like names in a personnel dataset, but
                    the start of each name – the zone of the card where it appeared - would be known
                    in advance, allowing processing operations to be easily set up.</p>
                <p>By contrast, with a phrase of unstructured text only the first word on each card
                    is in a predictable place and even then there is no information about where the
                    field ends. Thus the problem they had to solve was how to explore the Sentence
                    Cards over and over, identifying each successive word … and in 1951 they had to
                    do this using only sorting machines with replicators to create the new EWCs.
                    This was the key mechanical process that allowed one type of data — phrase cards
                    – to be processed to generate another — word cards. Everything else could in
                    theory then be generated using these two sets of cards (along with a bit of
                    human work lemmatizing/disambiguating.)</p>
                <p>To figure out how this could be done we have again replicated the process, though
                    in code rather than with an emulated machine.<note>See <ref
                            target="http://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/sgsinclair/epistemologica/blob/master/PunchcardOperations.ipynb"
                            >http://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/sgsinclair/epistemologica/blob/master/PunchcardOperations.ipynb.</ref></note>
                    We imagined that one would start by exploring all the cards, sorting out those
                    with a space in the second column. Those would be the cards with a one letter
                    word at the start. These would be run through the replicator which would now
                    know what zone the word to find was in and thus could create an EWC for the one
                    letter word. Then one would sort the remaining cards to find those with a space
                    in the third position and so on until one had explored every possible location
                    of a word between two spaces. We suspect that this actually would have involved
                    a lot of physical moving of stacks and also keeping track of the subsets of
                    cards – not an entirely mechanical process, but one less prone to error and much
                    faster than writing things out by hand. Tremendous semi-mechanical labor
                    indeed.</p>
                <p>Later they found other ways to do this. By 1958 Busa had actually developed three
                    ways to do this crucial process. In <title rend="quotes">The Use of Punch
                        Cards</title> (1958) Busa describes the 3 options (on page 361) as: <list
                        type="ordered">
                        <item>The keypunch operator could just punch individual word cards (whether
                            in addition or instead of phrase cards.) Punching just the EWCs was the
                            most efficient way if all you need was a word index.<note>In a letter
                                dated March 16, 1957 Busa tells a Rev. William Le Saint S.J. who had
                                enquired about creating an index of Tertullian that <quote
                                    rend="inline">If you intend only an index verborum, then work
                                    will be extremely easy and economical for then you could start
                                    by punching the word cards directly.</quote> (p. 1 of
                            2)</note></item>
                        <item>The keypunch operator could punch the Sentence Cards and then, using
                            sorting and replicating machines, the EWCs could be machine generated.
                            This is the approach described in the <title rend="italic">Varia
                                Specima</title> quoted above.</item>
                        <item>Or a last process <quote rend="inline">using the Cardatype, recently
                                developed by IBM</quote>
                            <ptr target="#busa1958" loc="361"/>. This is the process that is
                            diagramed in the 1952 <soCalled>Flow Chart</soCalled> prepared by PT and
                            JEG, probably Paul Tasman and an unidentified draftsman. Figure 5 shows
                            the relevant detail of the flow chart where Sentence Cards are handled
                            by the Cardatype:</item>
                    </list>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Detail from 1952 <soCalled>Flow Chart</soCalled> from the Busa
                            Archive</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>The Cardatype was a modular and multi-function machine which makes it hard to
                    figure out exactly what they did with it. It had one or more IBM electric
                    typewriters, a verifier, and could have a tape-punching unit attached that would
                    output a paper tape which could then control a card punch that would punch the
                    EWCs <ptr target="#stanford1951" loc="403"/> There seems to have been enough
                    intelligence in the Cardatype to output to paper tape the data needed to punch
                    the EWCs.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusions</head>
                <p>To conclude we begin by noting that Busa provided answers, of sorts, to McGloin’s
                    criticism. Father Busa in his 1980 reflection on the <title rend="italic">Index
                        Thomisticus</title> defended the concording of function words by arguing
                    that <quote rend="inline">all functional or grammatical worlds … manifest the
                        deepest logic of being which generates the basic structures of human
                        discourse. It is this basic logic that allows the transfer from what the
                        words mean today to what they meant to the writer</quote>
                    <ptr target="#busa1980" loc="83"/>. The paradigmatic example for Busa was the
                    one he used to open his 1980 article: understanding <emph>presence</emph>
                    through prepositions like <emph>in</emph> as he tried to do in his doctoral
                    thesis. Busa the philologist valued all the language of Aquinas as a way of
                    understanding the historical context. McGloin wanted to focus on the philosophy
                    and theology which he felt needed to be brought to life and made relevant to the
                    modern world. This is an old tension in the humanities <ptr target="#turner2014"
                    />. McGloin may not have objected to the concording of function words <emph>per
                        se</emph>; rather it was amount of work that he expected to be tremendous
                    and useless. One wonders if Busa could have convinced him of the philosophical
                    value of concording prepositions like <emph>in</emph>? That would not, however
                    answer McGloin’s concern about the amount work required. As mentioned, McGloin
                    probably (and rightly) inferred that the tremendous mechanical work would also
                    mean tremendous human labor to set it all up and then deal with the results. And
                    it should be noted that the <title rend="italic">Index Thomisticus</title>
                    project did involve an extensive human crew working in a converted factory space
                    for decades <ptr target="#jones2016"/>. McGloin probably suspected that Busa was
                    proposing a concording assembly line that would not be philosophically rewarding
                    work but mechanical work that could have been better dedicated to something
                    else.</p>
                <p>A different sort of answer can be found in an article by Paul Tasman, Busa’s IBM
                    engineering collaborator. He believed that innovations like the
                    machine-searching application developed by the project <quote rend="inline">may
                        initiate a new era of language engineering.</quote>
                    <cit>
                        <quote rend="block">The indexing and coding techniques developed by this
                            method offer a comparatively fast method of literature searching, and it
                            appears that the machine-searching application may initiate a new era of
                            language engineering. It should certainly lead to improved and more
                            sophisticated techniques for use in libraries, chemical documentation,
                            and abstract preparation, as well as in literary analysis. <ptr
                                target="#tasman1957" loc="256"/></quote></cit></p>
                <p>Tasman saw the business potential for IBM in the innovations of the <title
                        rend="italic">Index Thomisticus</title>. While Thomas J. Watson Sr. (the CEO
                    of IBM) may have been skeptical of the project when he first met Father Busa
                        <ptr target="#busa1980"/>, he ended up supporting it and it paid off in
                    terms of innovation. In this Tasman was right. The language engineering
                    innovations of the project underlie the digital turn of our age where not just
                    language, but multiple media are either born digital or digitized for
                    engineering on the computer. The computer has become the universal machine for
                    processing information in any form. The project was the first step away from
                    using the computer solely for numbers and towards using it for other forms of
                    information. It should also be noted that IBM took advantage of the publicity
                    that the Busa project offered, including it as part of their display at the 1964
                    New York World’s Fair (see <ptr target="#jones2016"/>).</p>
                <p>Having a sense of some of the tremendous mechanical labor involved in Busa’s
                    project, something McGloin didn’t really have when commenting, we can conclude
                    by asking again if such labor was worth it. Obviously, from an efficiency point
                    of view, it was worth it if you grant that Busa was right about the value of a
                    full concordance. Tasman <ptr target="#tasman1957" loc="255"/> estimated that
                    mechanizing concordancing would reduce the time needed for the <title
                        rend="italic">Index Thomisticus</title> to a tenth of what a manual process
                    would take, with a fifth of the people. One could also argue, as Tasman does,
                    that Busa’s project not only produced a concordance but also developed
                    innovative ways of ways of using the technologies at hand for <soCalled>language
                        engineering.</soCalled> These developments we now know led to much more than
                    concordances. They led to a whole alphabet of services. But, to be fair to
                    McGloin, he was only reviewing the usefulness of the <title rend="italic">Index
                        Thomisticus</title> for studying Aquinas, not reviewing the potential of the
                    technology. McGloin argued that focusing on the technology would become a fetish
                    of its own, distracting us from the interpretation of Aquinas, and he was right.
                    But, would such tremendous labor not make it easier for others to interpret
                    Aquinas? To claim that some words are more important and therefore more worthy
                    of indexing for research seems to betray a limited imagination of what research
                    could be. McGloin’s view, in retrospect, is conservative when it comes to
                    imagining research usefulness but prescient if he meant to also alert us to
                    reconfigurations of labor and machines.<cit>
                        <quote rend="block">Big Data has emerged a system of knowledge that is
                            already changing the objects of knowledge, while also having the power
                            to inform how we understand human networks and community<ptr
                                target="#boyd2012" loc="665"/>.</quote>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>McGloin was right to focus on labor and the changes in attention, what he calls
                    fetish, though we disagree with his unquestioned association of mechanism with a
                    loss of life. Changes in the labor of research change the object of research and
                    the methods with which we think-through (and vice versa). Busa and Tasman were
                    aware of this in that they discussed some of the implications of the new methods
                    they were developing and could see some of the possibilities for different types
                    of research and answers. McGloin is right to ask about these changes, but wrong
                    to assume there is something necessarily dead about mechanised methods while the
                    existing objects and methods are sacred. McGloin poses the critical question
                    about what and how we are interpreting, but he is a romantic who does not
                    question his own practices. As boyd and Crawford argue for big data (2012)
                        <quote rend="inline">it is time to start critically interrogating this
                        phenomenon, its assumptions, and its biases</quote> (665). We would add that
                    to critically interrogate a new phenomenon one needs to also ask about that with
                    which it was contrasted in its time and also ask about the metaphors of
                    contrast. One of the best ways to interrogate such a phenomenon of literary and
                    linguistic computing is to do the archaeology of the technologies that actually
                    changed the labor, objectives and methods, and that is what we have tried to do
                    here. Much can be brought to life in the replication of liminal moments like
                    Busa’s <title rend="italic">Index Thomisticus</title> project.</p>
                <p>Following boyd and Crawford, an aspect of the labor that McGloin might have
                    objected to if he had had more time would have been the factory-like management
                    systems developed for this big data project and the ways they might change what
                    is considered knowledge in the humanities. Busa and Tasman didn’t just develop
                    new technologies, they had to develop a physical center where the work could
                    take place and an organization capable of carrying out so much human and
                    mechanical labor. This wasn’t the first large scale humanities project, there
                    had been large projects for some time, including concording projects, dictionary
                    projects, archaeological projects, and editorial projects. It was, however, one
                    of the first projects to integrate information technology and human labor so
                    closely. The project needed deliberate planning, fund raising, management,
                    public relations, and training in the use of computers. Jones (2016) has gone a
                    long way towards documenting how this was the first humanities computing
                    project. Nyhan and Terras have documented the gendered division of labor between
                    male scholars and female punch card operators.<note>They have a forthcoming book
                        with translated interviews and research on exactly what the processes
                        were.</note> Jones leads a web project <title rend="quotes">Reconstructing
                        the First Humanities Computing Center</title> to which many have contributed
                    that is reconstructing the physical space in Gallarate of the Centro per
                    L’Automazione dell’Analisi Letteraria (Center for the Automation of Literary
                    Analysis) or CAAL.<note>See <ref target="https://avc.web.usf.edu/images/RECAAL/"
                            >https://avc.web.usf.edu/images/RECAAL/.</ref> Accessed June 11,
                        2019.</note> Rockwell and Passarotti (2019) have looked at the project as a
                    project.</p>
                <p>From today’s perspective McGloin might have commented on how the challenge of
                    dealing with so much text led to the development of a new organizational model
                    for humanities projects where the integration of technology forced a new
                    division of labor on the humans. It forced humanists to develop practices which
                    integrated scholars with punch card operators, technical staff and engineers. We
                    are still struggling with issues of credit and project management around these
                    new configurations. These new configurations change the communities of knowledge
                    and may have also changed the way knowledge is conceived. Information, often in
                    the form of large amounts of data, has become synonymous with knowledge. The
                    datafication of the cultural record has changed our thinking about knowledge.
                    Scholarship has given way to information management.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Replications</head>
                <list>
                    <item>Punched Card Emulator Blog: <ref
                            target="http://stefansinclair.name/punchcard/"
                            >http://stefansinclair.name/punchcard/</ref></item>
                    <item>Simple Punched Card Emulator: <ref
                            target="https://cdn.rawgit.com/sgsinclair/epistemologica/master/punchcard.html"
                            >https://cdn.rawgit.com/sgsinclair/epistemologica/master/punchcard.html</ref></item>
                    <item>Busa Operations: <ref
                            target="http://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/sgsinclair/epistemologica/blob/master/PunchcardOperations.ipynb"
                            >http://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/sgsinclair/epistemologica/blob/master/PunchcardOperations.ipynb</ref></item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Image Credits</head>
                <p>All images from the Busa Archive are property of the Biblioteca dell'Università
                    Cattolica. They are shared in this presentation with permission. For further
                    information, or to request permission for reuse, please contact Paolo Senna at 
                    paolo_dot_senna_at_unicatt_dot_it.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>This paper was originally presented at Loyola, Chicago in 2016. Rockwell and
                    Passarotti also presented some of these ideas as part of a different paper in
                    Rome, Italy in 2017 at the 6th AIUCD Conference. That paper was published in
                    2019 under the title <title rend="quotes">The Index Thomisticus as a Big Data
                        Project.</title></p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>

                <bibl xml:id="boyd2012" label="Boyd and Crawford 2012">Boyd, D. and K. Crawford
                    (2012). <title rend="quotes">Critical Questions for Big Data.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Information, Communication &amp; Society.</title> 15:5.
                    662-679.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burdick2012" label="Burdick et al 2012">Burdick, A., et al. (2012).
                        <title rend="italic">Digital_Humanities.</title> Cambridge, MA, MIT
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="busa1951" label="Busa 1951">Busa, R., S. J. (1951). <title
                        rend="italic">S. Thomae Aquinatis Hymnorum Ritualium Varia Specima
                        Concordantiarum.</title> Primo saggio di indici di parole automaticamente
                    composti e stampati da macchine IBM a schede perforate. Milano, Fratelli
                    Bocca.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="busa1958" label="Busa 1958">Busa, R. (1958). <title rend="quotes">The
                        Use of Punched Cards in Linguistic Analysis.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Punched Cards: Their Applications to Science and
                        Industry.</title> Eds. R. S. Casey, J. W. Perry, M. M. Berry and A. Kent.
                    New York, Reinhold Publishing: 357 - 373.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="busa1980" label="Busa 1980">Busa, R. (1980). <title rend="quotes">The
                        Annals of Humanities Computing: The Index Thomisticus.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Computers and the Humanities.</title> 14:2: 83-90.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="casey1951" label="Casey and Perry 1951">Casey, R. S. and J. W. Perry
                    (1951). <title rend="italic">Punched Cards: Their Application to Science and
                        Industry.</title> New York, Rheinhold Publishing.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ihde1998" label="Ihde 1998">Ihde, D. (1998). <title rend="italic"
                        >Expanding Hermeneutics: Visualism in Science.</title> Evanston, Illinois,
                    Northwestern University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jones2016" label="Jones 2016">Jones, S. E. (2016). <title
                        rend="italic">Roberto Busa, S. J., And the Emergence of Humanities
                        Computing: The Priest and the Punched Cards.</title> New York,
                    Routledge.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lubar1992" label="Lubar 1992">Lubar, S. (1992). <title rend="quotes"
                            ><q>Do Not Fold, Spindle or Mutilate</q>: A Cultural History of the
                        Punch Card.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of American Culture.</title> 15:4. 43-55.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mackenzie1980" label="Mackenzie 1980">Mackenzie, C. E. (1980). <title
                        rend="italic">Coded Character Sets, History and Development.</title>
                    Reading, Massachusetts, Addison-Wesley.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcgloin1945" label="McGloin 1945">McGloin, D. (1945). <title
                        rend="quotes">Revitalizing Liberal Education.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Jesuit Educational Quarterly.</title> VII:3. 133 -
                    138.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nyhan2017" label="Nyhan and Terras 2017">Nyhan, J. and Terras, M.
                    (2017). <title rend="quotes">Uncovering <q>hidden</q> contributions to the
                        history of Digital Humanities: the Index Thomisticus’ female keypunch
                        operators.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Conference Proceedings of Digital Humanities 2017.</title>
                    Montréal, Canada: 313-4.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="parikka2012" label="Parikka 2012">Parikka, J. (2012). <title
                        rend="italic">What is Media Archaeology?</title> Cambridge, UK,
                    Polity.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rockwell2019" label="Rockwell and Passarotti 2019">Rockwell, G. and
                    Passarotti, M. (2019) <title rend="quotes">The Index Thomisticus as a Big Data
                        Project.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Umanistica Digitale.</title> Vol. 5. DOI: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2532-8816/8575"
                        >10.6092/issn.2532-8816/8575.</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stanford1951" label="Stanford 1951">Stanford, S. C. and C. D. Gull
                    (1951). <title rend="quotes">Transcription Problems in Preparing and Using
                        Punched-Card Files</title>. <title rend="italic">Punched Cards: Their
                        Application to Science and Industry.</title> Eds. R. S. Casey and J. W.
                    Perry. New York, Rheinhold Publishing: 395-404.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tasman1957" label="Tasman 1957">Tasman, P. (1957). <title
                        rend="quotes">Literary Data Processing.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">IBM Journal of Research and Development.</title> 1:3.
                    249-256.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="terras2013" label="Terras 2013">Terras, M. (2013). <title
                        rend="quotes">For Ada Lovelace Day — Father Busa’s Female Punch Card
                        Operatives</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Melissa Terras' Blog.</title>
                    <ref
                        target="http://melissaterras.blogspot.com/2013/10/for-ada-lovelace-day-father-busas.html"
                        >http://melissaterras.blogspot.com/2013/10/for-ada-lovelace-day-father-busas.html.</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="turner2014" label="Turner 2014">Turner, J. (2014). <title
                        rend="italic">Philology: The Forgotten Origins of the Modern
                        Humanities.</title> Princeton, New Jersey, Princeton University
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="winner1980" label="Winer 1980">Winner, L. (1980). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Do Artifacts Have Politics?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Daedalus.</title> 109:1. 121-136.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="winter1999" label="Winter 1999">Winter, T. N. (1999). <title
                        rend="quotes">Roberto Busa, S.J., and the Invention of the Machine-Generated
                        Concordance.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Classical Bulletin.</title> 75:1. 3-20.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zielinski2008" label="Zielinski 2008">Zielinski, S. (2008). <title
                        rend="italic">Deep Time of the Media: Toward an Archaeology of Hearing and
                        Seeing by Technical Means.</title> Cambridge, Massachusetts, MIT
                    Press.</bibl>

            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
