<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">BigDIVA and Networked Browsing: A Case for Generous
               Interfacing and Joyous Searching</title>
            <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
               <dhq:author_name>Joel <dhq:family>Schneier</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>North Carolina State University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>jischnei@ncsu.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Joel Schneier is a doctoral candidate in the Communication Rhetoric &amp;
                     Digital Media program at NC State University.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
               <dhq:author_name>Timothy <dhq:family>Stinson</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>North Carolina State University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>tlstinso@ncsu.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Timothy Stinson is Associate Professor of English and a University Faculty
                     Scholar at North Carolina State University.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
               <dhq:author_name>Matthew <dhq:family>Davis</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>McMaster University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>matthew@matthewedavis.net</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Matthew Davis is a Postdoctoral Fellow in the Sherman Centre for Digital
                     Scholarship at McMaster University.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000376</idno>
            <idno type="volume">012</idno>
            <idno type="issue">2</idno>
            <date when="2018-07-03">03 July 2018</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>networked browsing</item>
                  <item>digital archives</item>
                  <item>usability</item>
                  <item>interface studies</item>
                  <item>cybernetics</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
         <change/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
            <p>This paper examines the potentialities of <term>networked browsing</term>, a form of
               faceted searching that visualizes digital archives in the form of a force-directed
               network graph. Using BigDIVA.org as an example of networked browsing, this paper
               presents the results of a small usability study that compared how participants (<hi rend="italic">N</hi> = 8) engaged with BigDIVA’s networked browsing in comparison
               to use of a search engine such as Google. In doing so, we situate our study within
               performative conceptualizations of human-computer interfaces <ptr target="#drucker2013"/> in order to explore the potential becomings when human and
               nonhuman machinic component are entangled together. Based on the observations from
               our usability study, we argue that networked browsing is suggestive of Whitelaw’s
               (2015) <quote rend="inline" source="#x_drucker2013">generous interfacing</quote> that emphasizes browsing as
               a tool for exploring relationships between nodes in archives, as well as
               Shneiderman’s (1996) <quote rend="inline" source="#x_drucker2013">joyous experience</quote> for interfacing
               with the web.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
            <p>Examines the potentialities of <term>networked browsing</term>, using BigDIVA.org as
               an example.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head/>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Conducting a search query through Google or scholarly archives is a performance. It
               requires curation of key terms or phrases from memory, fingered articulation upon a
               keyboard, recall from the database, selection and then uptake from a list of results.
               This ubiquitous everyday performance, while providing information access and
               retrieval across the world, is nonetheless a narrowly defined operation in which a
               given search query is matched to a given resource. As Mitchell Whitelaw (2015)
               argues, the process of browsing limits a user to understanding and exploring the
               scores of information available online. If an online archive is analogous to a
               museum, then Whitelaw argues that starting with a search query is the equivalent to
               being told to wait at the entrance to the Louvre until you explicitly request to see
               the Mona Lisa. Citing Ben Shneiderman’s two-decade-old appeal to make information
               exploration a <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#shneiderman1996">joyous experience</quote>
                  <ptr target="#shneiderman1996"/>
               </cit> as well as Johanna Drucker’s (2013) call for the humanities to take a central
               role in such endeavors, <ptr target="#whitelaw2015"/> outlines the numerous
               possibilities for online archives and databases to design <quote rend="inline" source="#x_whitelaw2015">generous interfaces</quote> in order to allow users to explore relationships
               between nodes of information across the web. This paper examines BigDIVA (short for
               Big Data Infrastructure Visualization Application) as one such instantiation of a
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#x_whitelaw2015">generous interface</quote> that invokes performative
               materiality for an online database cataloguing archives in the Advanced Research
               Consortium (ARC). </p>
            <p>BigDIVA<note>
                  <ref target="http://www.bigdiva.org">www.bigdiva.org </ref>
               </note> is a database that visualizes the ARC catalog<note> The ARC catalog is an
                  index of information collected from a number of federated websites and placed into
                  a Solr index</note> through an interactive force-directed graph in which network
               nodes represent specific catalogued archives, collections, or resources (see <ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>). Its name invokes the concept of Big Data, and
               as such provides users with visualization of the <emph>entire</emph> ARC catalog,
               while search queries either narrow or shrink the webbed catalog. This paper argues
               that searching and browsing online archives through a networked visualization
               interface (henceforth <term>networked browsing</term>) allows users to explore and
               interpret relations between archived sources (nodes) and to perform contingent
               in-the-moment search queries outside of the search box. In this sense, networked
               browsing prioritizes play and meaning-making that is co-constituted with the
               distributed materiality of the database itself. This turns traditional browsing
               performances on their heads and downplays the human-centered process that directs a
               subject from search query to resource, and instead directs the subject(s) to explore
               and infer relationships between the human user, the machinic components of the
               interface, and the networked points that make up the archived subjects. </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure01">
               <head>BigDIVA’s home screen representing the force-directed graph of the ARC
                  catalog</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
               <figDesc>Screenshot of BigDIVA home screen.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>This paper will explore two questions that situate BigDIVA within ongoing discussions
               of interfaces (see <ptr target="#drucker2013"/>; <ptr target="#whitelaw2015"/>; and
                  <ptr target="#schofield2015"/> from this journal), performative materialism, and
               digital archives: First, <hi rend="italic">how do human participants use BigDIVA in
                  comparison to a more traditional browser interface such as Google</hi>? In the
               simplest terms, networked browsing disrupts the expectations of traditional web
               browsing. As such, these disruptions will necessarily manifest behaviorally (i.e.,
               facial gestures, mouse clicks, vocalizations) and temporally (i.e., time spent on
               each search task). Such distinctions in usage may suggest how new users might
               interact with BigDIVA’s interface as well as networked browsing. Second, <hi rend="italic">how does usage of BigDIVA’s interface (as well as self-reports of
                  usage) afford and evidence generous interfacing or archival liveness</hi>? While
               design choices may be theoretically grounded, those choices may not always be
               transparent to the intended users and thus the interface still risks becoming
               functionally fixed. Thus, we intend to explore how users' experiences — as well as
               perceptions of their experiences — of BigDIVA may explicitly reflect interfacing that
               is theoretically grounded in the notion of performative materiality, wherein various
               bodies and distributed components meet at the point of the interface to perform a
               search. </p>
            <p>This paper will proceed with a background discussion concerning performative
               materiality and interfaces, the technical background concerning networked browsing
               and BigDIVA, results from the usability study, and lastly a discussion and conclusion
               section. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Performative Materiality and Joyous Interfacing</head>
            <p>A performative conception of human and machine interfacing places the utmost
               importance on what subjects are doing in a given assemblage, and how their actions
               co-constitute one another. Questions are more concerned with what a subject does,
               rather than what it is <ptr target="#drucker2013"/>. Karen Barad argues that <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#barad2003">The move toward performative alternatives to
                     representationalism shifts the focus from questions of correspondence between
                     descriptions and reality (e.g., do they mirror nature or culture?) to matters
                     of practices/doings/actions.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#barad2003" loc="802"/>
               </cit> This move away from representationalism (i.e., concern with what subjects are)
               is an effort to grant and explore the agency of subjects that are otherwise agentless
               through practices that seek understandings of definitions and boundaries. For
               example, a representationalist understanding would render a BigDIVA user’s keyboard
               as an input apparatus that is acted upon by human agents. While not necessarily
               inaccurate, this definition is necessarily based upon a priori knowledge of the
               keyboard (i.e., how it <emph>has been used</emph>), and subsequently obscures its
               infinite range of potentialities (i.e., how it <emph>could be used</emph>). However,
               as argued by <ptr target="#kittler1999"/>, keyboards, which were originally designed
               as writing devices for the blind, were not necessarily intended as primary input
               devices for computers. The agentive trajectory of components in a cybernetic
               assemblage are thus not pre-determined. Interfaces are therefore an exemplary site to
               explore such cybernetic performances since multiple bodies constituting multiple
               agencies and materialities meet at the point of interface. </p>
            <p>Barad argues that in casting aside representational concerns about <quote rend="inline" source="#x_barad2003">inherent boundaries and properties,</quote> bodies are instead
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#x_barad2003">material-discursive phenomena</quote> that engage in unique
               performances that create meaning through their performances <ptr target="#barad2003" loc="823"/>. She elaborates that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#barad2003"><q>Human</q> bodies are not inherently different from
                        <q>nonhuman</q> ones. What constitutes the <q>human</q> (and the
                        <q>nonhuman</q>) is not a fixed or pregiven notion, but nor is it a
                     free-floating ideality</quote>
                  <ptr target="#barad2003" loc="823"/>
               </cit>. In this way, what a subject does in constellation with other subjects is what
               continually configures and reconfigures the notion of that subject. In Barad’s
               framework, which she terms <term>agential realism</term>, meaning is made in the
               spaces in which these bodies come to meet together, which she calls
                  <term>intra-activity</term>. </p>
            <p>Barad’s framework, which draws attention to how meaning is made through bodies
               performing together, is crucial for digital media scholars in order to understand
               that when humans and technology intra-act that the range of potential meanings,
               realities, and uses are not predetermined. Drawing on groundbreaking principles of
               quantum physics, particularly the philosophy-physics of Niels Bohr, Barad uses the
               term <term>apparatus</term> to describe the site of human and nonhuman bodies coming
               together: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#barad2003">apparatuses are not mere static arrangements in the world, but
                     rather apparatuses are dynamic (re)configurings of the world, specific agential
                     practices/intra-actions/performances through which specific exclusionary
                     boundaries are enacted.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#barad2003" loc="816"/>
               </cit> Whether a factory floor, scientific instrument, or a typewriter keyboard, when
               humans act with any apparatus they — together — create new potential meanings.
               Barad’s framework therefore reminds us that understanding and studying digital media
               apparatuses requires attention to how they are made meaningful <emph>through
                  use</emph>. </p>
            <p>To return to our previous question: how does a performative materiality reveal the
               material-discursive phenomena at play within the interface? First, it is worth noting
               that Johanna Drucker (2013) argues that the interface should be conceptualized as a
                  <emph>space</emph> rather than a <emph>thing</emph>, specifically, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#drucker2013">a space of affordances and possibilities structured into
                     organization for use</quote>
                  <ptr target="#drucker2013" loc="para. 31"/>
               </cit>. Thinking of an interface in terms of a space therefore entangles more than
               just the machinic components, but enfolds the multiple bodies and agencies that
               organize around possibilities of use. Alexander Galloway (2012) has similarly argued
               that an interface, like that of a computer, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#galloway2012">is a process or active threshold mediating between two
                     states</quote>
                  <ptr target="#galloway2012" loc="23"/>
               </cit>, and thus an <emph>effect</emph> of the meeting of bodies. Understanding an
               interface as a <emph>space</emph> and an <emph>effect</emph> of the meeting between
               bodies therefore requires attention to the numerous distributed components — on both
               sides of the threshold — that meet at the point of interface, from the human user to
               the device to the networked archive. </p>
            <p> Drucker (2013), drawing upon Jean­François Blanchette, argues that all of these
               components that meet in digital media interfaces are complex cybernetic assemblages
               that constitutes a <term>distributed materiality</term> in which multiple components
               are <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#drucker2013">locked into relations with each other that are governed by
                     their material design and constraints in ways that have an effect on the costs
                     and efficient operation of the system</quote>
                  <ptr target="#drucker2013" loc="para. 6"/>
               </cit>. Such an assemblage’s operation (i.e., <hi rend="italic">performance</hi>)
               might be most evident at the point of interface, but Drucker argues that the various
               components that are <quote rend="inline" source="#x_harwood2011">locked into</quote> that performance may be
               distributed at points quite distant from the point of interface. This is not so
               surprising considering that ergonomic design traditions for complex computer
               interfaces frequently encourage concealment of the elaborate distributed components
               that make up the machine <ptr target="#harwood2011"/>, as well as how they often draw
               upon adjacent cultural metaphors (e.g., the computer <q>desktop</q>).</p>
            <p>In the case of a website, then, the distributed components include the computer
               screen, the mouse, the site interface, the network that connects the computer to the
               site, the server that hosts the site, the cooling system that prevents the servers
               from overheating, etc. With so many components locked together in play, Drucker
               argues that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#drucker2013">[e]very person produces a work as an individual experience,
                     according to their disposition and capacity</quote>
                  <ptr target="#drucker2013" loc="para. 22"/>
               </cit>. This performance may thus occur at various points of distribution in
               contributing to what <ptr target="#schofield2015"/> termed <term>archival
                  liveness</term>. In this way, an empirical investigation of the unique
               reconfigurations at play when a human accesses a website requires attention to
               multiple agentive components. </p>
            <p> Between Barad’s conceptualization of the apparatus, which emphasizes meaning-making
               through intra-activity, and Drucker’s conceptualization of the interface, which
               emphasizes cybernetic assemblages as a space that enfolds a distributed materiality,
               it is possible to understand the potentialities of human interaction with digital
               media through attention to <emph>use</emph>. As we hope to demonstrate in this paper,
               observing these interactions by concentrating on use may allow for observation of how
               the bodies (human and distributed nonhuman components) performatively materialize one
               another, specifically by concentrating observation on the point of contact — the
               interface. In the case of BigDIVA, we specifically wish to understand how a shift in
               the design of an online browsing interface engenders new performances and
               understandings of the components on either side of the interface. In the following
               section, we detail how the design of online browsing interfaces, as well as attempts
               to understand the <emph>usability</emph> of these interfaces, have thus far
               contributed to understanding these relationships in terms of performative
               materialities. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Web Browsing, Interfaces, and Usability</head>
            <p> In this section we provide background into discussions about the application of
               design principles to web browsing and online interfaces — much of which comes from
               fields such as design, human-computer interaction (HCI), and user experience (UX). We
               additionally make an attempt to couch this material within the contexts of ongoing
               discussions in the digital humanities about how to understand how individuals
               experience and <emph>use</emph> digital media within DH contexts, as well as the
               application of theory in these contexts. While these discussions certainly draw upon
               the aforementioned disciplines, similarly as we do, our primary intention in
               discussing them in the first place is to bring to the fore the tension between
               understandings of <emph>use</emph> and <emph>usability</emph> across various
               disciplines. </p>
            <div>
               <head>Designing Data Types</head>
               <p>In 1996, Brian Shneiderman made a plea to designers that <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#shneiderman1996">information exploration should be a joyous
                        experience</quote>
                     <ptr target="#shneiderman1996" loc="336"/>
                  </cit>. Noting the rising demand for information-seeking online services in the
                  days before Google’s ubiquity, Shneiderman argued that as online archives expanded
                  that the <quote rend="inline" source="#x_shneiderman1996">visual presentation</quote> as well as <quote rend="inline" source="#x_shneiderman1996">direct-manipulation</quote> of information would be critical for
                  users to be able to deliberately sort through the slew of search results without
                  experiencing cognitive overload. The <quote rend="inline" source="#x_shneiderman1996">visual
                     presentation</quote> of different types of data would therefore be critical to
                  managing user experience, and Shneiderman outlined several data types in order to
                  aide how designers conceptualized the user’s relationship between data and
                  directly manipulating this data. His taxonomy included data that he considered
                  1-dimensional (e.g., textual data), 2-dimensional (e.g. maps), 3-dimensional
                  (e.g., <soCalled>real-world</soCalled> objects like the human body), temporal
                  (e.g., timelines), multi-dimensional (e.g., combination of multiple data types),
                  treed (e.g., hierarchical tree-structured data), and networked (e.g., network
                  visualizations that show relationships between data)<note> We cite Shneiderman’s
                     (1996) description of data types in order to provide context to his argument
                     about information exploration, and would like to acknowledge that this taxonomy
                     is not without its criticisms. In particular, we caution against an
                     unquestioned reading of Shneiderman’s suggestion that texts are 1-dimensional
                     (see discussions about texts as social bodies from Bruno Latour, Yrjo
                     Engestrom, and Jerome McGann). </note>
                  <ptr target="#shneiderman1996" loc="337"/>. Shneiderman (1996) insisted that
                  accommodating several data types simultaneously would be necessary to design
                  information search interfaces, and further suggested that the goals and interests
                  of users conducting searches would likely affect the use of
                  visualization/manipulation tools such as filtering <ptr target="#shneiderman1996" loc="339"/>. </p>
               <p>In the last two decades, much of Shneiderman’s taxonomy is highly visible in
                  various iterations of web-based browsing applications and design literature,
                  particularly dynamic queries which are frequently represented as faceted
                  searching. Fagan (2010) noted that contemporary instantiations of faceted search
                  tools aimed to represent data types and provide tools for users to narrow
                  information search results. A typical example might start with a single search
                  term, and then facet by the type or resource, the date range, or even availability
                  of digitized copies (see <ref target="resources/images/figure02.png">Figure
                     2</ref> for an example of faceted search). After examining numerous studies
                  that empirically investigated faceted searching, Fagan (2010) reported on a bevy
                  of benefits to faceted search, perhaps most notably that faceted search may
                  contribute to users finding a greater amount of relevant results as well as
                  creating mental navigation structures and specifically benefits user’s ability to
                  search within specific time-frames or by specific authors <ptr target="#fagan2010" loc="62–63"/>.</p>
               <p>Xiao et al. (2009) demonstrated that successfully navigating and interacting with
                  an online search tool, such as Yahoo.com, on a mobile device stresses the
                  importance of <emph>limiting</emph> the available visual real estate by stacking
                  blocks of space horizontally, and limiting the amount of text simultaneously
                  visible on-screen. Faceted search interfaces, as shown in <ref target="resources/images/figure02.png">Figure 2</ref>, represent significant
                  obstacles to such challenges from a visual perspective. While designers and
                  scholars have explored mobile-specific interfaces for faceted search, the
                  challenges outlined by <ptr target="#xiao2009"/> are pervasive. For example, <ptr target="#schneider2013"/> finds that certain modifications, such as presenting
                  facets in a list or a grid, might significantly improve usability but not
                  necessarily user enjoyability of the search experience. Incorporating lessons from
                     <ptr target="#shneiderman1996"/> and <ptr target="#xiao2009"/>, <ptr target="#kleinen2014"/> designed a custom mobile application that combined text
                  and visuals to conduct faceted search tasks, so that a user might begin by
                  entering or selecting text based on prior knowledge, and then selecting the next
                  facet through a map with geographically specific <q>points of interest.</q> In
                  this way, at each point of faceting the user is presented with a different
                  dimensionality of the interface so that they may go from map, to list, to detailed
                  visual, to detailed text. Such an example of faceted searching that incorporates
                  multidimensional data, Kleinen et al. argue, may yield more enjoyable search
                  experiences. </p>
               <p>Regardless of the device, it is apparent that online activities like web-browsing
                  and searching are unique performances that are configured with the apparatus that
                  user and site interface through (as well as how that interface is reconfigured
                  with the apparatus). These usability studies further reveal representations and
                  visualizations of dimensions of faceted searching may inhibit or encourage
                  alternate forms of exploration. In particular, an undercurrent of the studies
                  reported in <ptr target="#fagan2010"/> as well as <ptr target="#schneider2013"/>
                  is that faceted search interfaces are intended to guide users to specific
                  information based on <foreign xml:lang="la">a priori</foreign> knowledge or data
                  type dimensions. Kleinen et al. (2014) caution that as online data types, sources,
                  devices, and interfaces increase in size and complexity faceted search interfaces
                  will need to accommodate an <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#kleinen2014">a-priori <emph>unknown</emph> number of data categories
                        and data instances</quote>
                     <ptr target="#kleinen2014" loc="57, emphasis ours"/>
                  </cit>. Therefore, the concern is not simply a matter of device- and screen-size,
                  but rather, a concern of the relationship between what the user wants — in terms
                  of inquiry and affect — and what the archive wants — in terms of liveness and data
                  dimensionality. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Use and Usability in DH</head>
               <p> Our study is not the first within the digital humanities to draw upon the idea of
                  usability and to consider user experience in ways similar to the studies described
                  in the previous section. For example, <ptr target="#gibbs2012"/> incorporated a
                  series of virtual panels, much like a focus group, to discuss online tools with
                  historians, and <ptr target="#warwick2012"/> incorporated a usability study to
                  observe novice and expert users of an online archeological database. While both of
                  these studies used methods familiar to UX studies, an emphasis on users with
                  specific background knowledge, expertise, and scholarly practices (i.e.,
                  historians or archeologists) suggests greater consideration for <emph>use</emph>
                  and <emph>users</emph> in addition to <emph>usability</emph>. </p>
               <p> Since the DH ethos values both the evolution of traditional research practices
                  from humanities scholars as well as knowledge production in humanities classrooms,
                  it is reasonable that DH scholars seeking better understanding and improved
                  designs of digital media are concerned with a wider context than that of the
                  interface. Burkick &amp; Willis (2011) have argued that 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>-century literacy practices are <emph>design</emph> practices, which
                  transforms digital scholarship and knowledge production into a process of thinking
                  through designing. This <emph>user-oriented</emph> approach <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#burdick2011">takes into account not only how an application is used but
                        also the kinds of subject positions, world-views, and models it
                        affords</quote>
                     <ptr target="#burdick2011" loc="550"/>
                  </cit>. User-oriented designs would account for Gibbs &amp; Owens’s (2012)
                  recommendation that DH tools be designed more holistically for the needs of
                  humanities scholars and students, specifically tools that are <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#gibbs2012">more transitory than revolutionary</quote>
                     <ptr target="#gibbs2012" loc="para. 35"/>
                  </cit>. </p>
               <p> Warrick (2012) has additionally argued that studying users in context is key to
                  understanding how scholars and students of varying expertise use digital tools and
                  media as part of their broader scholarly practices. This encourages
                     <emph>use</emph> in addition to <emph>usability</emph>, and attention to what
                  users (i.e., scholars) <emph>want</emph> and how they might engage in practice
                  with digital tools — regardless of usability <ptr target="#kemman2014"/>. By
                  focusing on the user in context, Kemman &amp; Kleppe (2014) argue that
                  observations will inform design, which may then result in a feedback loop between
                  design and use. This user-centered design process requires iterative attention to
                  use in context, such as through extended and longitudinal usability studies <ptr target="#warwick2012"/>. </p>
               <p> While this surely requires an extended discussion on its own, it is worth noting
                  that the tension between a <emph>user</emph> and <emph>use</emph> for DH scholars
                  and <emph>usability</emph> from UX approaches are not mutually exclusive, and, as
                  suggested by <ptr target="#warwick2012"/>, the two can inform one another.
                  Software and methods intended for usability studies, which may include screen
                  capture, log-file data, and even front-facing cameras to capture facial
                  expressions, may well yield rich and well-rounded understandings of
                     <emph>use</emph> as well as <emph>usability</emph>. In our study of BigDIVA, we
                  therefore sought to further understand how new ways of visualizing and
                  encountering data types may serve as a <soCalled>transitory</soCalled> practice
                  for humanities scholars, and our use of a usability study may be seen as an
                  intervention to elicit not only potential understandings of how users initially
                  use BigDIVA, but also how they may perceive its potential use in their own
                  practices. In the following section we provide details of BigDIVA’s configuration.
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Networked Browsing and BigDIVA</head>
            <p>In Shneiderman’s (1996) taxonomy of data types, network data accounts for
               relationships between and among items in an online archive. The configuration of
               these relationships, or <term>network topologies</term>, are commonly visualized
               through force-directed graphs in which items are nodes and lines connect related
               nodes <ptr target="#galloway2007"/>. Shneiderman cautions that network
               representations risk overwhelming complexity (particularly as archives access large
               amounts of items), as can be seen in attempts to document the topology of the
               internet. However, he does suggest that network representation may allow users the
               opportunity to find the shortest routes between nodes in order to establish mental
               representations of relationships between items and clusters of items. </p>
            <p>BigDIVA operationalizes faceted searching through presenting a model of the network
               through one of four user-defined facets: <hi rend="italic">resource</hi>, <hi rend="italic">genre</hi>, <hi rend="italic">discipline</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">format</hi>. While <hi rend="italic">resource</hi> is the primary representation
               by default, users can choose to begin with one of the other three. This is
               accomplished without extensive revision to the existing schema because the ARC
               catalog is a fairly shallow example of faceted search, with its categories largely
               existing as sister nodes under a central tree. The tool takes advantage of this
               functionality to create ad-hoc trees based on the user’s defined needs and ARC
               catalog schema. </p>
            <p>Once a user has selected their initial facet, they are then presented with a group of
               sub-nodes that consist of the various recognized categories in the schema. For
               example, a user that selects <hi rend="italic">Genre</hi> as their initial limitation
               will be presented with sub-nodes with categories such as Law, Scripture, and Drama.
               From there, they can select the desired category, whereupon they are presented with
               the total number of items under that category in a sidebar and the ability to refine
               further based on either the remaining categories or the individual records. This
               refinement can be narrowed further by repeating the process with the newly-refined
               category until all four aspects of the site have been selected upon.</p>
            <p>Regardless of the level at which they are selected, the individual resources provide
               a truncated version of the catalog information and, most importantly, a link for the
               user to go to that resource, which will then appear in a new window. At the same
               time, the user can see the entire path between their initial category and the
               individual item, maintaining a visual representation of the mental model they were
               operating under while making that selection. Furthermore, they can select different
               nodes and combinations of categories to visualize multiple mental pathways at the
               same time, a functionality that is not possible in most faceted search systems. In
               all instances, the nodes are color-coded to help the user to understand at a glance
               what selections have been made, while unavailable choices are greyed out. This
               maintains both the full picture of the ARC catalog while simultaneously foregrounding
               those items that are of most import to the researcher. Finally, because the ARC
               catalog deals with historical objects, a timeline is provided at the bottom of the
               workspace, which allows a user who works in a particular period to view only those
               items of interest within that period.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure02">
               <head>Faceting by Genre, to Resource, to Discipline, to Format, to individual
                  result</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p> Since BigDIVA therefore allows users to manipulate the data visualizations through
               multiple means simultaneously, i.e., the user-defined facets, a timeline, as well as
               more direct manipulation of the network nodes, it may afford a unique browsing
               experience. While simply overlaying multiple types of interactive data is not alone a
               cure-all, the combination of a networked graph of the entire catalogue, combined with
               the ability to expand the network graph through faceting based on category as well as
               time-line may serve as complementary tasks. However, the inclusion of a standard
               search bar as a way to filter out archival items from the network visual may serve as
               a source of confusion since one is a standard search feature while the other is not.
               In other words, a key aspect of understanding BigDIVA’s usability as well as the
               experiences of users will be the perceived relationship between these starkly
               different data types, in Shneiderman’s terms. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>BigDIVA Usability Study</head>
            <p>In order to take first steps to understand the potential uses and experiences that
               BigDIVA’s networked browsing has to offer, we designed a usability study intended to
               compare networked browsing with more traditional web browsing. In doing so, we hoped
               to observe not only whether individuals could successfully use BigDIVA as a search
               tool without any training, but also how BigDIVA’s networked browsing engaged
               individuals in unique acts of online information searching. In short, we sought to
               understand BigDIVA’s operational <emph>usability</emph>, but also the potential user
               experience it may engender. Our resulting study design therefore compared search
               tasks using Google and BigDIVA, tracked the timing patterns for each task as well as
               input-related actions, and elicited self-reported perceptions by first-time users.
               The study design will be briefly discussed below, followed by discussion of our
               results. </p>
            <div>
               <head>Study Design</head>
               <p>This study was conducted entirely within a labspace designed specifically for
                  usability studies in the library of a Mid-Atlantic U.S.-based university. This lab
                  was outfitted with a desktop computer running Morae software<note>
                     <ref target="https://www.techsmith.com/morae.html">
                        https://www.techsmith.com/morae.html </ref>
                  </note>, designed for computer-based usability testing, and a Logitech C920 webcam
                  with stereo microphones. Morae was able to simultaneously record on-screen video
                  (including highlighting of cursor actions), audio-video footage from the webcam,
                  and log-file data from the keyboard, mouse, and onscreen applications. The
                  resulting recording (see <ref target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref> below) could then
                  be viewed and analyzed with Morae software. </p>
               <p>Participants were guided through the study tasks through a Google Forms file that
                  provided instructions for, as well as logged performance of, each task. First,
                  participants were asked to complete a brief pre-study questionnaire to self-report
                  expertise with generic information search, as well as fields of expertise. Next,
                  participants were guided through three search tasks that required using Google to
                  find a famous work by William Blake, a relief etching by William Blake, and an
                  etching of Blake’s <title rend="quotes">Milton: a Poem.</title> These three tasks
                  in particular were intended for participants to find increasingly specialized
                  information and to use Google’s faceting feature for searching via dimensions such
                  as Image, Web, or Video. Following these three tasks, participants were then
                  required to use BigDIVA to identify collections with large results for <q>William
                     Blake,</q> an individual result from this search, meta-data from a specific
                  result for Blake’s <title rend="quotes">Night Thoughts,</title> and an example
                  search result that contains the text string <q>chastity.</q> It should be noted
                  that all of the search tasks are listed in the Appendix, and that the BigDIVA
                  search tasks were intentionally longer simply to observe users interacting with
                  BigDIVA for longer. Following the search tasks, the first author engaged the
                  participants in a brief follow-up interview to solicit self-reported experiences
                  with BigDIVA. </p>
               <figure xml:id="figure03">
                  <head>Still frame from the Morae recording overlaying webcam and screen-capture
                     video footage</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Results</head>
               <p>Participants (<hi rend="italic">N</hi> = 13) were recruited from networks
                  connected to a Mid-Atlantic university in order to engage participants that were
                  likely familiar with web-based archival search tools beyond Google. All
                  participants were currently enrolled in graduate coursework or had completed
                  graduate coursework, and were from a variety of fields and academic positions
                  including tenured professors, graduate teaching/research assistants, library &amp;
                  information scientists, industry workers, and one individual currently between
                  jobs. A small group of participants (<hi rend="italic">N</hi> = 5) piloted the
                  study design during the spring of 2015, which led to subsequent adjustments to the
                  study’s task design (i.e., particular phrasing of task instructions, and
                  streamlining of the Google Forms interface). The remaining participants (<hi rend="italic">N</hi> = 8) engaged in the study between late 2015 and early
                  2016, and will make up the primary participant pool to be discussed throughout the
                  remainder of this paper. </p>
               <p>Analysis was conducted using Morae Manager to code and extract data, and
                  visualizations were produced in R Studio <ptr target="#rstudio2015"/>. Participant
                  usability sessions were analyzed according to three dimensions: Time On Tasks
                  (TOT), Actions Within Tasks (AWT), and Log-File data (primarily Mouse and cursor
                  actions). TOT data was primarily continuous, i.e., based upon duration of time a
                  participant spent on each individual task, whereas AWT and Log File data were
                  discrete, i.e., a specific type of action that occurred at a specific moment of
                  time. <ref target="#table01">Table 1</ref> below outlines each specific dimension
                  along with its corresponding codes.</p>
               <table xml:id="table01">
                  <head>Dimensions of Analysis</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">Time on Tasks</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">Actions Within Tasks</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">Log File</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <list type="unordered">
                           <head>Google Tasks:</head>
                           <item>Task 1_1</item>
                           <item>Task 1_2</item>
                           <item>Task 1_3</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="unordered">
                           <head>BigDIVA Tasks:</head>
                           <item>Task 2_1a</item>
                           <item>Task 2_1b</item>
                           <item>Task 2_2a</item>
                           <item>Task 2_2b</item>
                           <item>Task 2_3a</item>
                           <item>Task 2_3b</item>
                           <item>Task 2_4</item>
                        </list>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> SEARCH: enters or modifies a<lb/> search query in the search bar<lb/>
                        OPENSRESULT: clicks on an<lb/> individual result <lb/> NODEPLAY: Highlights,
                        pins,<lb/> or moves around a node<lb/> FACETS: uses faceting after a<lb/>
                        search query has been entered<lb/> DIMENSIONSWITCH: facets<lb/> prior to a
                        search query has<lb/> been entered<lb/> ENTERSTASK: enters or<lb/> modifies
                        an answer for a search<lb/> task<lb/> QUITS: abandons the search<lb/> task,
                        typically marked by<lb/> entering <q>Not found</q> or such<lb/> into the
                        answer for a search task<lb/> CHEATS: uses an alternative<lb/> method to
                        complete a search task<lb/> (e.g., prior knowledge, another<lb/> search
                        engine)<lb/> CTRLF: uses the Control+F<lb/> search function within a
                        page<lb/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <list type="unordered">
                           <head>Mouse Actions:</head>
                           <item>Movement</item>
                           <item>Scrolling</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="unordered">
                           <head>Cursor Actions:</head>
                           <item>Right click</item>
                           <item>Left click</item>
                           <item>Double left click</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="unordered">
                           <head>Keystroke Actions:</head>
                           <item>Alphanumeric keys</item>
                           <item>Functions keys</item>
                        </list>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p> Participants spent a total of 30.51 minutes on the three Google tasks, and 144.78
                  minutes on the seven BigDIVA tasks (see <ref target="#table02">Table 2</ref> for
                  breakdown of TOT). When looking at TOT for each individual task, as shown in <ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref> below, we can see that, while in many cases
                  the TOT for BigDIVA tasks varied within the same range as the Google tasks, the
                  BigDIVA tasks witnessed greater variability in terms of TOT. In particular, the
                  two BigDIVA tasks that required the most specific information (Task 2_3a and
                  Task2_4) generally took the longest. A paired samples <hi rend="italic">t</hi>-test comparing participants’ mean TOT for Google and BigDIVA tasks
                  demonstrated that mean TOT for BigDIVA was significantly longer ( <hi rend="italic">t</hi> (6) = -2.85, <hi rend="italic">p</hi> = .029). </p>
               <table xml:id="table02">
                  <head>TOT for all tasks</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Task</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Total TOT (min)</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Mean TOT (min)</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Median TOT (min)</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">1_1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> 7.59 </cell>
                     <cell> 0.95 </cell>
                     <cell> 0.95 </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">1_2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> 10.64 </cell>
                     <cell> 1.33 </cell>
                     <cell> 1.12 </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">1_3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> 12.28 </cell>
                     <cell> 1.54 </cell>
                     <cell> 1.53 </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic ">All Google Tasks</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">30.51</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">1.27</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">1.11</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">2_1a</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> 18.18 </cell>
                     <cell> 2.27 </cell>
                     <cell> 1.73 </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">2_1b</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> 22.68 </cell>
                     <cell> 2.84 </cell>
                     <cell> 1.39 </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">2_2a</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> 26.08 </cell>
                     <cell> 3.26 </cell>
                     <cell> 1.89 </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">2_2b</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> 7.60 </cell>
                     <cell> 0.95 </cell>
                     <cell> 0.78 </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">2_3a</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> 29.69 </cell>
                     <cell> 3.71 </cell>
                     <cell> 3.57 </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">2_3b</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> 7.60 </cell>
                     <cell> 0.95 </cell>
                     <cell> 0.48 </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">2_4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> 32.95 </cell>
                     <cell> 4.12 </cell>
                     <cell> 3.53 </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">All BigDIVA Tasks</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">144.78</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">2.59</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">1.80</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>Since all participants self-assessed themselves as <q>Very Good</q> or
                     <q>Excellent</q> Google-users, it is certainly reasonable that they would need
                  to spend less time on the Google search tasks. Directly comparing aggregate TOT
                  for Google and BigDIVA tasks does not account for time necessary to adapt to an
                  unfamiliar search tool; therefore, understanding the value of aggregating TOT
                  across tasks and search platforms requires more nuance. For example, based on
                  comparison of TOT for BigDIVA tasks only, it becomes apparent that following the
                  first BigDIVA task (Task 2_1a), some participants appeared to become more
                  time-efficient (particularly for Task 2_2b and 2_3b), which suggests that they
                  overcame a learning curve and adjusted to aspects of networked browsing. Further,
                  some participants that exhibited similar difficulties with search tasks
                  (particularly Task 2_3a-b and 2_4) spent more time on each task. For example,
                  participant B06 and B08 were both unable to complete these three tasks for similar
                  reasons (as will be discussed below), but B06 spent much longer (5.66 minutes on
                  all three tasks) than B08 (3.74 minutes on all three tasks). This suggests that
                  successful or unsuccessful adaptation to BigDIVA is not necessarily dependent on
                  how much time a user spends on task. </p>
               <figure xml:id="figre04">
                  <head>A boxplot for Time on Task for each task</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
               </figure>
               <p>In order to look deeper than TOT data, the AWT data is able to provide more
                  fine-grained comparisons of what participants did for each task with the time
                  allotted. <ref target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref> provides a timeline for each
                  participant colored for any occurrence of an AWT action type. This provides a
                  window into the interplay and sequencing between multiple action types over the
                  course of the entire study, and shows that a typical action sequence for Google
                  tasks involved entering a search query, adjusting for search dimension (i.e.,
                  Image, News, Scholarly), opening a result (maybe two), and then eventually
                  entering an answer for the task. For BigDIVA, these sequences were more complex as
                  participants were required to explore and manipulate interface elements they were
                  previously unfamiliar with. Interestingly, at first glance of BigDIVA’s
                  force-directed network, all participants found the search bar and entered a query
                  in a matter of seconds. However, once a search query was entered, participants
                  variably played with the network nodes, switched dimensions (e.g., <hi rend="italic">Genre</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Format</hi>), enlarged the
                  screens, faceted, etc. In other words, the sequence from search query to facet to
                  search result was broken. Entering or modifying the search query makes up a much
                  smaller portion of AWT actions for BigDIVA tasks (with the exception of Tasks 2_3a
                  and 2_4), while experimenting and playing with the faceting features and the nodes
                  were much more frequent. The greater frequency of these action types suggests that
                  participants’ unfamiliarity with BigDIVA — specifically the aspects of networked
                  browsing — are likely indicative of a sense of fascination and playfulness, or
                  even confusion and frustration, with these features in order to understand their
                  function. The novelty of these features may have encouraged participants to spend
                  time playing with these features in order to better understand them, which may
                  explain how some participants spent less time for later tasks.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure05">
                  <head>A timeline for each participant based upon AWT action types. (Note that
                     sessions for participants B02 and B03 included server interruptions which
                     explain the large gaps in action) </head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="figure06">
                  <head>Distribution of AWT action types for each task </head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Log-File actions additionally present a complex picture. While Mouse and cursor
                  actions dominate input actions during the Google tasks, the first four BigDIVA
                  tasks witnessed a steady decrease in mouse action as participants engaged with the
                  keyboard and various other AWT action types more frequently. While Tasks 2_3a-b
                  appear to revert to Google-like behavior, the frequency of mouse and cursor
                  actions glaringly decreases for the BigDIVA tasks, despite the fact that BigDIVA’s
                  functionality is primarily dependent on the cursor (with the exception of the
                  search bar). </p>
               <figure xml:id="figure07">
                  <head>Distribution of Log-File actions plus all AWT actions for each task</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Lastly, since not all participants were able to complete every search task, it is
                  worth looking more closely at those participants and what their actions were.
                  Furthermore, in order to have a comparison of these Non-Finisher participants to
                  those that did, we made a subgroup of the two Non-Finishers (B06 and B08) and two
                  Finishers (B01 and B04). This sub-group was determined by developing a rudimentary
                  scoring system for each task in which participants received 1 point for completing
                  the task as designed, 0.5 points for completing the task not as designed, and 0
                  points for not completing the task at all. After rating all participants, B06 and
                  B08 scored the lowest, while B01 and B04 scored the highest. </p>
               <p>In terms of AWT action types, <ref target="#figure08">Figure 8</ref> demonstrates
                  both groups overall were not strikingly different. Besides the action type QUIT,
                  both the Finishers and Non-Finishers engaged in similar distribution of AWTs as
                  the Finishers. The primary distinction is for the action type DIMENSIONSWITCH, as
                  the Finishers switched dimensions in BigDIVA more than half as much as the
                  Non-Finishers. After looking more closely at when and how these participants
                  switched dimensions, it was observed that both groups had developed distinct
                  understandings of this feature’s function: the Finishers would switch dimensions
                  and then enter a search query, whereas the Non-Finishers would enter a search
                  query and then switch dimensions. While a seemingly inconsequential distinction in
                  Google, this sequence of action in BigDIVA is the difference between filtering
                  results based on a search query and resetting the force-directed network
                  visualization of the archive to another dimension. Thus, when the Non-Finishers
                  entered a search query, and then switched dimensions, they effectively negated
                  their query and reset the visualization to view all archive content — albeit in a
                  different dimension. In other words, the Non-Finishers were very likely unable to
                  finish all of the BigDIVA tasks because they had failed to adjust to this specific
                  feature of BigDIVA’s functionality, and instead appeared to transfer their
                  understanding of this functionality directly from Google. </p>
               <figure xml:id="figure08">
                  <head>Distribution of AWT action types for Finisher and Non-Finisher
                     sub-groups</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Furthermore, when comparing TOT data for the Finishers and Non-Finishers, the
                  Non-Finishers appear to take more time in general to adjust to BigDIVA search
                  tasks. Indeed, by Task 2_3a, the Non-Finishers demonstrated so much difficulty in
                  using BigDIVA in order to complete each search task that they appeared more
                  inclined to abandon the tasks rather than adjust their understanding of the
                  functionality; whereas the Finishers — who had done a better job of understanding
                  the functionality — were willing to spend more time in order to complete the
                  tasks. </p>
               <figure xml:id="figure09">
                  <head>TOT comparison for Finisher and Non-Finisher sub-groups</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Self-Reports</head>
               <p>While audio-video data captured from the webcam does coordinate on-screen actions
                  with affective reaction as gauged by facial expression, it is beyond the scope of
                  this current study to adequately or appropriately surmise how using BigDIVA
                  resulted in participants’ affective reactions. After all, since BigDIVA was new to
                  the participants while Google was used daily, some manner of novelty effect would
                  be expected. Further, since BigDIVA did require some manner of learning curve (and
                  at least two participants experienced delays due to server interruptions), such
                  analysis would likely have been biased towards affects such as frustration or
                  confusion <ptr target="#dmello2012"/>. Nevertheless, at first glance of BigDIVA’s
                  network visualization all users did display unique momentary reactions. For
                  example, B04 noticeably smiled, B01 appeared surprised, B02 exclaimed quietly to
                  himself <quote rend="inline" source="#x_dmello2012">What,</quote> and B08’s brow furrowed. In other
                  words, the novelty of networked browsing appeared to induce affectations — perhaps
                  even <quote rend="inline" source="#x_dmello2012">joyous</quote> in some cases — that in and of itself may
                  offer participants hope of a new manner of searching.</p>
               <p>Indeed, based on the self-report questionnaire following the search tasks,
                  participants were largely in agreement about the potentialities of networked
                  browsing. While many elaborated on early frustrations with the new functionalities
                  of the search tools, or the initial learning curve, all participants remarked
                  about BigDIVA’s ability to establish an understanding of the relationship between
                  the collections and their individual archive sources. In particular, three common
                  themes were apparent from the participants’ self-reports: that the novelty of
                  BigDIVA’s networked browsing was either <quote rend="inline" source="#x_table03">fun</quote> or <quote rend="inline" source="#x_table03">interesting,</quote> that BigDIVA could be most useful for
                  specialized archives or use in scholarly settings, and that the networked
                  visualizations may be pedagogically valuable for demonstrating relationships
                  between scholarly sources (see <ref target="#table03">Table 3</ref> below). </p>
               <p>Another unique theme expressed by participants related to the nature of web-based
                  search queries altogether. In particular, while participants noted that after a
                  brief adjustment period they were able to successfully search and find specific
                  information using BigDIVA, that they would still use a more typical visualization
                  such as Google — even if networked browsing were an option with Google.
                  Participants justified this preference with the fact that a text-based list of
                  results still might be simpler and quicker if the user already knows what they are
                  looking for; whereas networked browsing would be preferable if the user was not
                  certain what they were looking for. In other words, networked browsing would be
                  more suitable for exploring the contents of an archive without a predisposition
                  for specific results. </p>
               <table xml:id="table03">
                  <head>Transcriptions of participant self-reports</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Networked Visualization Features</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <list type="unordered">
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">Different colors for visualizing resource,
                                 genre, and so on is neat — this would be helpful if someone is
                                 looking for a specific source</quote></item>
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">Fun to play with!</quote></item>
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">Very interesting to get to see the number of
                                 results as well as the networks and communities</quote></item>
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">Good for kids who are used to visual
                                 interfaces</quote></item>
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">The instant landscaping of sources that could
                                 be explored was unique</quote></item>
                        </list>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Scholarly Usage</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <list type="unordered">
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">Provides a quicker way to filter scholarly
                                 data like in a library database. It really helps to see the source
                                 of information</quote></item>
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">Help for interdisciplinary searches if you're
                                 not entirely certain of what you’re looking for, and if you're
                                 interested in intersections in disciplines</quote></item>
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">It helps you realize the results might pertain
                                 to the critic or scholar, not the author</quote></item>
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">Great tool to explore topics I'm already
                                 familiar with</quote></item>
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">Very good for research in the humanities that
                                 involves multimedia formats</quote></item>
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">Could be good for academic searches but also
                                 government records and medical research in order to organize
                                 specific types of data</quote></item>
                        </list>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Pedagogical Usage</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <list type="unordered">
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">Interesting as a pedagogical tool for getting
                                 students to see connections between sources</quote></item>
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">Good for younger kids who are used to visual
                                 interfaces — it would be great at capturing the attention of those
                                 audiences</quote></item>
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">it would be good to show to students who
                                 really don’t understand too much about searching</quote></item>
                        </list>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Everyday Use</hi></hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <list type="unordered">
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">If I was trying to get a better conceptual
                                 understanding of relationships between sources</quote></item>
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">Probably to explore topics I’m already
                                 familiar with</quote></item>
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">mainly to see connections with locations of
                                 sources, as well as prioritization. It would be great for really
                                 digging</quote></item>
                           <item><quote rend="inline" source="#x">I wish that Google’s Image Search would have
                                 this sort of node quality</quote></item>
                        </list>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Discussion</head>
            <p>This study set out to explore how networked browsing allows subjects to explore and
               interpret relations between archived resources. Our guiding research questions were:
                  <hi rend="italic">how do participants use BigDIVA in comparison to a more
                  traditional browser interface such as Google</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">how does
                  BigDIVA’s interface afford and evidence generous interfacing or archival
                  liveness</hi>? While our small and preliminary usability study certainly does not
               exhaustively answer either of these questions, we are left with valuable evidence
               that point towards the potential range of experiences and materialities that
               networked browsing has to offer. </p>
            <p>In response to our first research question, the BigDIVA usability study provided
               evidence of how the process of searching with BigDIVA compares to a more traditional
               search tool like Google. According to our analysis of users’ input-related actions,
               we observed that despite the fact that BigDIVA employs traditional faceted search
               functionality (albeit with networked visualization) participants experienced browsing
               differently for Google and BigDIVA. Participants took significantly longer to
               complete BigDIVA tasks, in some cases were unable to complete certain tasks, and in
               some cases attempted to transfer functionalities from Google. Additionally,
               participants generally used the search bar less, the mouse and cursor less, and the
               faceting features more when completing BigDIVA tasks compared to Google tasks. It was
               therefore apparent that, perhaps because of the comparative study design, when
               participants shifted from using Google to BigDIVA that they experienced a
               performative disruption. The spike in mouse clicks for the first BigDIVA task, which
               subsequently leveled out for participants, exemplified the learning curve or
               adaptation to the distinctive performances engendered by networked browsing. </p>
            <p> Analysis of input actions or completion of search tasks on their own, while key
               components in understanding the cybernetic assemblage, do not tell the whole story of
               how — in Barad’s and Drucker’s terms — a human intra-acting with the distributed
               machinic components is made discursively meaningful. Self-reports of users’
               experiences and perceptions regarding BigDIVA therefore revealed the most surprising
               observations and indications of what it is like to perform networked browsing.
               Participants described their initial impressions of networked browsing as <quote rend="inline" source="#x">fun,</quote>
               <quote rend="inline" source="#x">interesting,</quote> or <quote rend="inline" source="#x">different</quote> —
               regardless of their success or failure in the search tasks. They additionally
               reflected on the potential scholarly and pedagogical applications, and yet, most
               surprising, participants remained skeptical of networked browsing’s usefulness for
               everyday web browsing (i.e., in place of typical search interfaces like Google);
               however, numerous participants suggested it would be more fitting functionality for
               finite archives (i.e., such as the ARC catalog). </p>
            <p> That participants generally reported such positive experiences and perceptions of
               BigDIVA, in spite of its more specialized use, is a promising indication that
               networked browsing may indeed engender Shneiderman’s (1996) <quote rend="inline" source="#x">joyous experience</quote> for interfacing with the web. Indeed, such experiences
               are difficult to observe by examining input-related actions alone and without facial
               recognition software to analyze affect. In future study, we therefore intend to place
               greater emphasis on <emph>how</emph> users experience networked browsing with an eye
               toward longitudinal designs and repeated self-report measures in addition to analyses
               more common in usability research. These observations follow Warrick’s (2012)
               suggestions for the combined use of log-file data to track input and output actions
               in addition to more traditional ethnographic methods, such as interviews and
               longitudinal participant observation, in order to examine usability and use of new
               tools in the digital humanities. If our study observed even an inkling of how new
               users performatively intra-acted and engaged in meaning-making with BigDIVA, then
               more prolonged and iterative observations would be able to richly observe use in
               context. </p>
            <div>
               <head>Limitations and Future Research</head>
               <p>Of course, as implied already, our study was not without its limitations. In
                  addition to a small sample size, we wish to emphasize that the comparative design
                  of our study is one such limitation, because, as participants self-reported,
                  BigDIVA prioritized a different kind of browsing than Google. Finding information
                  in BigDIVA did not require a scavenger hunt amongst a hierarchical text-based list
                  that required prior knowledge encoded in the form of a query. Instead, BigDIVA
                  made information available without a search query, thus begging participants to
                  visually untangle and play with the networked catalog. Our study design admittedly
                  prioritized specific search tasks in order to target use of specific features as
                  well as to allow easy comparison to search tasks in Google. Open-ended tasks or
                  longitudinal observation, per <ptr target="#warwick2012"/>, would therefore be
                  well-suited alternatives. </p>
               <p>At the same time, comparative methods are still valuable for design and
                  experiential considerations of these interfaces. After all, if networked browsing
                  indeed affords unique performative understandings and meaning-making experiences
                  compared to other operationalizations of faceted search functions, then more
                  detailed comparative studies could reveal the distinctions in those processes,
                  particularly comparing similar scholarly faceted search tools such as a university
                  library database. As suggested above, such a comparative study would do well to
                  not solely rely on input-based behavioral measures that privilege the machine
                  components of the interface, and instead privilege the human components in the
                  interface by observing affect, metacognitive processes, as well as self-report
                  measures to emphasize users’ perceptions of their experiences. In particular, such
                  methods could potentially parse out the distinction between users’ understanding
                  of search functionality from archive architecture, as well as how, in their own
                  terms, they may find joy in their browsing experiences. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p> Based on the observations from our study, networked browsing may indeed be
               suggestive of Whitelaw’s (2015) <quote rend="inline" source="#x">generous interfacing</quote>
               that emphasizes browsing as a tool for exploring relationships between nodes in
               archives. The possibilities for exploration and play are evidenced not only in how
               archives may be accessed and searched for specific scholarly aims, but also for
               configuring new relational understandings of the distributed materiality of an
               archive itself. In other words, networked browsing may help users conceptualize
               archives as agential or living material bodies. In doing so, searching through an
               archive is no longer a linear act of retrieval, but perhaps an exploratory and
               contingent act of meaning-making. </p>
            <p> Of course, our study’s observations and what they suggest only yield more questions
               about networked browsing, faceted search functions, and generous interfacing. As
               mentioned above, further research design would do well to observe how individuals
               might use BigDIVA over a longer span of time, involve more open-ended tasks, and
               involve multidimensional analysis. In particular, future research should question
               what could users learn or discover with BigDIVA when simply given time and freedom to
               experiment with networked browsing and explore the archive? Would they come to a more
               detailed understanding of its components (i.e., collections, individual resources,
               faceting structures)? Would they become more fluent with the interface’s
               functionality? Such questions, which we see as central to the study of
               knowledge-production in the digital humanities, would require attention to
                  <emph>usability</emph> of digital tools as well as a well-rounded and holistic
               model of who a digital <emph>user</emph> is and how they engage in <emph>use</emph>.
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Appendix</head>
            <table>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="bold">BigDIVA Usability Study Procedures</hi><lb/>
                     <list type="ordered">
                        <head>I: Preliminary Questionnaire:</head>
                        <item>What is your current degree level?</item>
                        <item>What is your current academic or professional position?</item>
                        <item>What would you consider your <soCalled>field</soCalled>?</item>
                        <item>How frequently do you use Google or another search engine to look up
                           casual information?</item>
                        <item>How would you rate your skill level at using search engines?</item>
                        <item>Can you explain the difference between these search queries: macaroni
                           and cheese, macaroni AND cheese?</item>
                        <item>For academic or scholarly research, how do you begin to search for
                           resources and materials? </item>
                     </list><lb/>
                     <list type="ordered">
                        <head>II: Google Search Tasks: </head>
                        <item>What is one of William Blake's famous works? [GENERAL QUERY]</item>
                        <item>Find an example of a relief etching by William Blake. Provide the URL
                           of the image [FACETING, RESOURCE META-INFORMATION]</item>
                        <item>Search for an etching from William Blake's <title rend="quotes">Milton
                              a Poem</title>. [FACETING, QUERY MODIFICATION, SORTING RESULTS]</item>
                     </list><lb/>
                     <list type="ordered">
                        <head>III: BigDIVA Search Tasks: </head>
                        <item>A) Using BigDIVA, search for WILLIAM BLAKE. What are the names of a
                           collection that appear to have the most results? B) What about when you
                           visualize by Genre instead of Resource? [GENERAL QUERY, FACETING]</item>
                        <item>A) What is an individual result from one of these collections? B) What
                           about a still image or a manuscript? [FACETING, SORTING RESULTS]</item>
                        <item>A) Search for WILLIAM BLAKE again visualizing for Resource, and find
                           the Blake Archive node. What is the publication year of Night Thoughts,
                           copy 1 (object 28)? B) What is the first line from object 28? [FACETING,
                           RESOURCE META-INFORMATION]</item>
                        <item>Search for <q>chastity</q> and find one individual result that
                           contains that search term in the primary source text [QUERY MODIFICATION,
                           RESOURCE ASSESSMENT, SORTING RESULTS]</item>
                     </list><lb/>
                     <list type="ordered">
                        <head>IV: Follow-Up Interview:</head>
                        <item>What were your general impressions of BigDIVA?</item>
                        <item>What were your experiences finding an individual result in BigDIVA
                           compared to Google?</item>
                        <item>What was new or unique about BigDIVA?</item>
                        <item>What was easy to adjust to?</item>
                        <item>What was difficult to adjust to?</item>
                        <item>What do you think the BigDIVA search visualization is particularly
                           good for? What is it bad for?</item>
                        <item>If Google or another popular search engine offered the option to do
                           search visualization like BigDIVA, would you use it? Why or why
                           not?</item>
                     </list>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="barad2003" label="Barad 2003">Barad, K. 2003. <title rend="quotes">Posthumanist Performativity: Toward an Understanding of How Matter Comes to
                  Matter</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Women in Culture and
                  Society,</title> 28, 801-831.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="burdick2011" label="Burdick and Willis 2011">Burdick, A., &amp; Willis, H.
               2011. <title rend="quotes">Digital Learning, Digital Scholarship and Design
                  Thinking.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Design Studies</title>, 32, 546-56.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dmello2012" label="D’Mello and Graesser 2012">D’Mello, S. K., &amp;
               Graesser, A. C. 2012. <title rend="quotes">Dynamics of affective states during
                  complex learning</title>. <title rend="italic">Learning and Instruction,
                  22,</title> 145-157.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2013" label="Drucker 2013">Drucker, J. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Performative Materiality and Theoretical Approaches to Interface</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 7(1).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dunne2015" label="Dunne et al. 2015">Dunne, C., Ross, S.I., Shneiderman,
               B., &amp; Martino, M. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Readability metric feedback for
                  aiding node-link visualization designers</title>. <title rend="italic">IBM Journal
                  of Research &amp; Development</title>, 59, 1-16.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fagan2010" label="Fagan 2010">Fagan, J.C. 2010. <title rend="quotes">Usability Studies of Faceted Browsing: A Literature Review</title>. <title rend="italic">Information Technology and Libraries</title>, 29, 58-66.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="galloway2007" label="Galloway and Thacker 2007">Galloway, A.R., &amp;
               Thacker, E. (2007). <title rend="italic">The Exploit: A Theory of Networks</title>.
               Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="galloway2012" label="Galloway 2012">Galloway, A.R. 2012. <title rend="italic">The Interface Effect</title>. Malden, MA: Polity. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gibbs2012" label="Gibbs and Owens 2012">Gibbs, F., &amp; Owens, T. 2012.
                  <title rend="quotes">Building Better Digital Humanities Tools: Toward Broader
                  Audiences and User-Centered Designs.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 6. <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8080/dhq/vol/6/2/000136/000136.html">http://digitalhumanities.org:8080/dhq/vol/6/2/000136/000136.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="harwood2011" label="Harwood 2011">Harwood, John. 2011. <title rend="italic">The interface: IBM and the transformation of corporate design,
                  1945-1976</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="henry2008" label="Henry, Bezerianos, and Fekete 2008">Henry, N.,
               Bezerianos, A., &amp; Fekete, J.D. 2008. <title rend="quotes">Improving the
                  Readability of Clustered Social Networks using Node Duplication</title>. <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>,
               14, 1317-1324. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kemman2014" label="Kemman and Kleppe 2014">Kemman, M., &amp; Kleppe, M.
               2015. <title rend="quotes">User Required? On the Value of User Research in the
                  Digital Humanities.</title> Selected Papers from the CLARIN 2014 Conference,
               October 24-25, 2014, Soesterberg, The Netherlands, 63–74. <ref target="http://www.ep.liu.se/ecp_article/in">http://www.ep.liu.se/ecp_article/in</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kittler1999" label="Kittler 1999">Kittler, F. 1999. <title rend="quotes">Typewriter</title>. In <title rend="italic">Gramophone, film, typewriter</title>.
               (G. Winthrop-Young and M. Wutz, Trans.). Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press.
               (Original work published in 1986). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kleinen2014" label="Kleinen, Scherp, and Staab 2014">Kleinen, A., Scherp,
               A., &amp; Staab, S. 2014. <title rend="quotes">Interactive facete</title>d search and
               exploration of open social media data on a touchscreen mobile phone. <title rend="italic">Multimedia Tools Applied</title>, 71, 39–60.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rstudio2015" label="RStudio Team 2015">RStudio Team (2015). RStudio:
               Integrated Development for R. RStudio, Inc., Boston, MA. URL <ref target="http://www.rstudio.com">http://www.rstudio.com</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ren2010" label="Ren, Sarvas, and Cali 2010">Ren, K., Sarvas, R., &amp;
               Cali, J. 2010. <title rend="quotes">Interactive search and browsing interface for
                  large-scale visual repositories</title>. <title rend="italic">Multimedia Tools
                  Applied</title>, 49, 513–528.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schneider2013" label="Schneider, Scherp, and Hunz 2013">Schneider, M.,
               Scherp, A., &amp; Hunz, J. 2013. <title rend="quotes">A comparative user study of
                  faceted search in large data hierarchies on mobile devices</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 12th International Conference on Mobile and
                  Ubiquitous Multimedia</title>, 1-10.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shneiderman1996" label="Shneiderman 1996">Shneiderman, B. 1996. <title rend="quotes">The Eyes Have It: A Task by Data Type Taxonomy for Information
                  Visualizations</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings 1996 IEEE Symposium on
                  Visual Languages</title>, 336-343.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schofield2015" label="Schofield et al. 2015">Schofield, T., Kirk, D.,
               Amaral, T., Dörk, M., Whitelaw, M., Schofield, G., &amp; Ploetz, T. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Archival Liveness: Designing with Collections Before and During
                  Cataloguing and Digitization</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                  Quarterly</title>, 9(3).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="warwick2012" label="Warwick 2012">Warwick, C. 2012. <title rend="quotes">Studying users in digital humanities.</title> In Warwick, C., Terras, M. and
               Nyhan, J. (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities in Practice</title>. Facet
               Publishing, London, pp. 1–21.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whitelaw2015" label="Whitelaw 2015">Whitelaw, M. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Generous Interfaces for Digital Cultural Collections</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 9(1).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="xiao2009" label="Xiao et al. 2009">Xiao, X., Luo, Q., Hong, D., Fu, H.,
               Xie, X., &amp; Ma, W.Y. 2009. <title rend="quotes">Browsing on Small Displays by
                  Transforming Web Pages into Hierarchically Structured Subpages</title>. <title rend="italic">ACM Transactions on the Web</title>, 3, 1-36.</bibl>
         </listBibl>

      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>