<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Automatic Identification of Rhetorical Elements
                    in Classical Arabic Poetry</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Heyam <dhq:family>Abd Alhadi</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID"
                        ><!-- if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000 --></idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Haifa</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>heyam.abdalhade@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Ali Ahmad <dhq:family>Hussein</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID"
                        ><!-- if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000 --></idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Haifa</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>ahussein@univ.haifa.ac.il</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Tsvi <dhq:family>Kuflik</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID"
                        ><!-- if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000 --></idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Haifa</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>tsvikak@is.haifa.ac.il</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id"
                    ><!-- including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110 -->000673</idno>
                <idno type="volume"
                    ><!-- volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date/>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>Text mining</item>
                        <item>Arabic natural language processing</item>
                        <item>rule-based</item>
                        <item>classical Arabic poetry</item>
                        <item>rhetorical elements</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Replace "XXXXXX" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
            <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
                    target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000673/000673.xml"
                    >GitHub </ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>A novel, rule-based, automatic framework for identifying rhetorical elements in
                    Classical Arabic poetry is described. Since rule-based approaches have
                    well-known limitations, it is proposed as an interim solution until a sufficient
                    quantity of annotated text has been amassed with which to train a
                    machine-learning algorithm. The manual process of identifying rhetorical
                    features in Classical Arabic poetry is both time-consuming and requires
                    high-level expertise in Arabic literature. Hence, an automatic recognition
                    system will solve this challenge. Automatic identification is, however,
                    challenging, mainly because there is no existing annotated corpus with which to
                    train a machine-learning-based classifier. The framework proposed here combines
                    natural language-processing techniques with a rule-based reasoning approach, and
                    will continually improve as more examples become available. It is intended as an
                    initial step toward building the essential annotated corpus. Its focus is 20
                    rhetorical elements, all of importance according to Classical Arabic
                    rhetoricians, and it achieves the extremely encouraging result of an overall
                    F-measure of 0.902.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>A novel, rule-based, automatic framework for identifying rhetorical elements in
                    Classical Arabic poetry is described.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head/>
            <div>
                <head>1. Introduction</head>
                <p>Rhetoric, <foreign xml:lang="ar">balāgha</foreign> in Arabic, is the art of
                    persuasion as well as affectation through language. It is the means of conveying
                    an idea in the most effective and convincing way, and with the most emotional
                    impact [28]. In Arabic criticism, the term <foreign xml:lang="ar"
                        >balāgha</foreign> refers both to figures of speech (such as <q>simile</q>)
                    and stylistic — including embellishing — elements (such as <q>paronomasia</q>)
                    that are used by critics to analyse the aesthetic value of an artistic
                    expression, mainly in classical Arabic poetry and the Qurʾān [32].</p>
                <p>Since the ninth century CE, study of rhetoric has been stimulated by an increased
                    interest in understanding the structure and development of poetry as well as by
                    the need to rationalise the aesthetic implications of the theological postulate
                    of the uniqueness (<foreign xml:lang="ar">iʿjāz</foreign>) of the Qurʾān
                    [32].</p>
                <p>Despite the great potential for study of rhetoric for so wide a range of research
                    priorities both in and beyond itself, it remains lamentably neglected in modern
                    research. Whereas there has been extensive research into Greek and mediaeval
                    European rhetoric, there is nothing comparable for that of Arabic-Islamic texts,
                    despite their high level of sophistication and their derivation from a major
                    world civilisation. Among many factors which may explain this is the very large
                    number of the rhetorical elements. In late rhetorical anthologies from the
                    eighteenth century CE, their number is about one hundred and eighty. Identifying
                    these elements in the thousand Classical Arabic poems that have been preserved
                    from the pre-Islamic to the later Islamic periods, is a hard, if not impossible,
                    mission. Tracing the development of rhetoric in this poetry is one way of
                    understanding its development through ages. This is done by analysing their use
                    in different poems during different periods, which is a lengthy and demanding
                    undertaking far beyond a scope of a single study or researcher.</p>
                <p>In order to make this feasible, our Arabic Rhetoric Identifier (known as the REI)
                    had to be developed.<note><ref
                            target="https://arabic-rhetoric.haifa.ac.il/#/aboutApp.html"
                            >https://arabic-rhetoric.haifa.ac.il/#/aboutApp.html</ref></note> The
                    REI was created by a team led by A. Hussein and T. Kuflik. Its purpose is to
                    enable researchers to annotate manually the rhetorical elements in Arabic
                    poetry, and compile them into a database of rhetorical elements in Classical
                    Arabic poetry between the 5th and 16th centuries CE. The canon comprises 26,925
                    Classical Arabic poems, only 75 of which have, to date, been manually analysed.
                    The main challenges to researchers are the time-consuming nature of manual
                    annotation and the high level of expertise required to identify and comprehend
                    the properties of each element [see, for example, the elements in 12, 22, 23].
                    While automating this process is thus very necessary, it is also extremely
                    challenging.</p>
                <p>While there are many modern studies of rhetorical usage in non-Arabic
                    literatures, there is a lacuna in the modern era in Arabic literature (see, for
                    example, Western literature’s rich bibliography in comparison with its scarce
                    listing for metaphor and metonymy in the Bibliography of <title rend="italic"
                        >Metaphor and Metonymy</title><note><ref
                            target="https://benjamins.com/online/met/"
                            >https://benjamins.com/online/met/</ref></note>). Scholars of classical
                    Arabic poetry agree that the differing use of rhetoric is the main difference in
                    Classical Arabic poetry in its different periods [16; cf. chapters 1, 2].
                        <foreign xml:lang="ar">Badīʿ</foreign> — literally <term>the new
                        style</term> (or the novel, original, extraordinary style) — was the term
                    used by Classical Arabic rhetoricians to describe the sophisticated use of some
                    rhetorical elements in this poetry, a use which renders the literary text more
                    sophisticated and more aesthetic. In short, scholars agree that rhetoric was
                    used in pre- and early Islamic poetry (5th-8th centuries CE), although it was
                    considered more important in the ʿAbbāsid era (from the 8th century CE; their
                    poetry was defined as <foreign xml:lang="ar">muḥdath</foreign> or
                        <term>new</term> poetry). The <foreign xml:lang="ar">badīʿ</foreign> is the
                    major element which distinguishes ʿAbbāsid from pre-ʿAbbāsid poetry (or <foreign
                        xml:lang="ar">muḥdath</foreign> from pre-<foreign xml:lang="ar"
                        >muḥdath</foreign> poetry) — although which figurative speeches in <foreign
                        xml:lang="ar">badīʿ</foreign> style and how they were used to make this
                    difference remains unresolved.</p>
                <p>Despite the importance of <foreign xml:lang="ar">badīʿ</foreign>, studies which
                    discuss it are few and incomplete [17; cf. pp. 28-41]: <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Most discuss <foreign xml:lang="ar">badīʿ</foreign> in separate and
                            randomly chosen verses rather than in complete poems. Considering this
                            style in complete poems gives a far more accurate picture of the nature
                            of <foreign xml:lang="ar">badīʿ</foreign> in classical Arabic
                            poetry.</item>
                        <item>Since the main hypothesis of modern research (and of classical
                            scholars) is that <foreign xml:lang="ar">badīʿ</foreign> is more
                            important in ʿAbbāsid than in the pre-Islamic era, modern studies focus
                            on the <foreign xml:lang="ar">badīʿ</foreign> of this poetry in the
                            later period.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>As far as we know, there are no comparative studies that analyze the development
                    of <foreign xml:lang="ar">badīʿ</foreign> from one period to another, other than
                    those recently conducted by one author of this article [17], and by Wolfhart
                    Heinrichs in 1994 [14]. Our approach is that the essence of <foreign
                        xml:lang="ar">badīʿ</foreign> in Classical Arabic periods, especially in
                    ʿAbbāsid and pre-ʿAbbāsid times, cannot be described without identifying and
                    analysing the rhetorical elements in complete poems. There are some 180
                    rhetorical elements described in classical books on rhetoric [10]. The number of
                    Classical Arabic poems, from the pre-Islamic era until the most recent
                    pre-modern period, is enormous, making manual rhetorical analysis for the entire
                    corpus a mission impossible. For this reason, Hussein and Kuflik began
                    developing a system that will automatically analyse several rhetorical elements
                    in an existing corpus of some 26,000 poems<note><ref
                            target="https://arabic-rhetoric.haifa.ac.il/"
                            >https://arabic-rhetoric.haifa.ac.il/</ref></note> (in development so
                    access is currently restricted). This corpus includes poetry from pre-Islamic
                    times to the Mamluk era, which ended early 16th century. All the poems were
                    entered manually into the system by students of Arabic language and literature,
                    according to printed versions of the poems. This article reports on the
                    automatic analysis of 20 rhetorical elements. A manual analysis by A. Hussein of
                    several poems in the present corpus showed these to be the main, recurrent
                    rhetorical elements in the pre- and early Islamic period, including the ʿAbbāsid
                    poetry in its first four centuries (that is, until the tenth century CE). In
                    addition, most of these elements (nos. 1, 2.3, 3.3, 10, 12, 14, 16, 17, 18,
                    19-20) are discussed in the first and oldest books on Arabic rhetoric, while the
                    others appear only as later developments and feature in later rhetoric books.
                    These were the two reasons for focusing on these elements in the present study. </p>
                <p>The classical automation approach uses text-mining and machine-learning
                    techniques to identify rhetorical elements in the text. This approach requires
                    collecting a large set of examples for each rhetorical element, and training a
                    machine-learning-based classifier to recognize them. As we did not have an
                    annotated set of examples, our first task was finding a way for assembling a
                    sufficient number of analyzed poems to train a classifier. Our proposal aims at
                    automating this step by proposing a framework to identify individual rhetorical
                    elements in Classical Arabic poetry by combining natural language processing
                    (NLP) techniques with a rule-based approach. This framework has been evaluated
                    on a small set of Arabic poems, and results have been extremely encouraging.</p>
                <p>The development of this automatic framework will make a vital contribution to the
                    study of rhetoric in Classical Arabic poetry. It will enable automatic
                    recognition of the 20 selected rhetorical elements in a vastly larger corpus
                    (26,925 poems) than cannot be handled manually. Analyzing the rhetoric in a
                    corpus of this size will yield better understanding of the development of
                    rhetoric in Classical Arabic poetry from the pre-Islamic period to the 16th
                    century CE.</p>
                <p>It is nonetheless important to note that rule-based systems have their own
                    limitations [13], including the need for continuous maintenance and updating by
                    experts – as demonstrated by this research. This is why we see it as an interim
                    approach until sufficient sets of examples are available for training
                    state-of-the-art machine learning algorithms for the task.</p>
                <p>Another challenge is the imprecise nature of such systems. Not only do they tend
                    to misclassify examples, they also miss relevant elements (false negatives) and
                    suggest wrong elements (false positives). Even the current framework, which
                    achieved, overall, extremely encouraging results, had widely differing success
                    rates for different elements. There is more work to do to ensure a success rate
                    closer to 100%.</p>
                <p>This paper is structured as follows. Section 2, which follows this introductory
                    section, gives background and reviews related work. Section 3 describes the
                    features of Classical Arabic poems. Our framework is delineated in Section 4,
                    together with the NLP tools and resources used in its implementation. The
                    dataset, experiments and results are described in Section 5, and Section 6
                    discusses the study’s implications and limitations. Conclusions and future work
                    are considered in Section 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. Background and Related Work</head>
                <p>Over the years, considerable research efforts have been invested in developing
                    methods and tools for NLP of Arabic. NLP of Arabic poetry, and, especially,
                    identifying characteristics in this poetry, remain challenging.</p>
                <p>Previous studies have focused on a range of aspects — morphology, morphological
                    decomposition, morpho-syntactic analysis, sentiment analysis, semantic analysis
                    and many others. One main research avenue is morphological analysis of Arabic
                    texts, for which several tools exist. Among them are AlKhalil Morpho Sys 2 [5],
                    MADA [11], MADA+TOKAN [18], MADAMIRA [29], ASMA [30], MAGEAD [19], BAMA [6, 9],
                    SAMA [26], SALMA [30], Arabic Sentence-level [33] and ArSenL [8].</p>
                <p>Of these, AlKhalil2 [5] is the most recent and seems to be the best. It is an
                    Arabic morpho-syntactic analyzer with a large database, which it uses to segment
                    and then analyze partially or totally vocalized Arabic words. For each, the
                    resulting analysis is derived as a set of features — prefix, stem, type, pattern
                    of word, root, part of speech (POS), lemma, pattern of lemma and suffix. It
                    outperforms BAMA and SAMA, achieving coverage of over 99%, as well as performing
                    better in identifying various features, including those determined in the word
                    context: the lemma, the stem and the diacritized form. This, therefore, was the
                    tool used in our study.</p>
                <p></p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl/>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
