<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article">Twisty Little Passages Almost All Alike: Applying the FRBR
                    Model to a Classic Computer Game</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Jerome <dhq:family>McDonough</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Graduate School of Library and Information Science, University
                        of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign </dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>jmcdonou@illinois.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Jerome McDonough is an Assistant Professor in the Graduate School of
                            Library and Information Science at the University of Illinois at
                            Urbana-Champaign. He holds a Ph.D. in Library and Information Studies
                            from the University of California at Berkeley, and has been actively
                            involved in the use of markup languages for library applications for the
                            past decade. His current research focuses on metadata and digital
                            preservation.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Matthew <dhq:family>Kirschenbaum</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities, University
                        of Maryland</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>mgk@umd.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Matthew G. Kirschenbaum is Associate Professor in the Department of
                            English at the University of Maryland, Associate Director of the
                            Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH, an applied
                            thinktank for the digital humanities), and Director of Digital Cultures
                            and Creativity, a new <q>living/learning</q> program in the Honors
                            College. He is also an affiliated faculty member with the Human-Computer
                            Interaction Lab at Maryland, a Vice President of the Electronic
                            Literature Organization. His first book, <title rend="italic">Mechanisms: New Media and the Forensic Imagination</title>, was
                            published by the MIT Press in 2008 and won the 2009 Richard J. Finneran
                            Award from the Society for Textual Scholarship (STS), the 2009 George A.
                            and Jean S. DeLong Prize from the Society for the History of Authorship,
                            Reading, and Publishing (SHARP), and the 16th annual Prize for a First
                            Book from the Modern Language Association (MLA). Kirschenbaum speaks and
                            writes often on topics in the digital humanities and new media; his work
                            has received coverage in the <title rend="italic">Atlantic</title>,
                                <title rend="italic">New York Times</title>, National Public Radio,
                                <title rend="italic">Wired</title>, Boing Boing, Slashdot, and the
                                <title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher Education</title>. See <ref target="http://www.mkirschenbaum.net">http://www.mkirschenbaum.net</ref> for more.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Doug <dhq:family>Reside</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities, University
                        of Maryland</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>dreside@umd.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Doug Reside is associate director of the Maryland Institute for
                            Technology in the Humanities (MITH) at the University of Maryland in
                            College Park. He holds a Ph.D. in English from the University of
                            Kentucky and undergraduate degrees in English and Computer Science from
                            Truman State University. In addition to Preserving Virtual Worlds, his
                            current projects include Music Theatre Online, the Open Annotation
                            Collaboration, and the Text Image Linking Environment.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Neil <dhq:family>Fraistat</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities, University
                        of Maryland</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>fraistat@umd.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Neil Fraistat is Professor of English and Director of the Maryland
                            Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH) at the University of
                            Maryland. He is a founder and general editor of the Romantic Circles
                            Website, the Co-Chair of centerNet, and he has published widely on the
                            subjects of Romanticism, Textual Studies, and Digital Humanities in
                            various articles and in the eight books he has authored or edited. He is
                            currently preparing for the press The Cambridge Companion to Textual
                            Scholarship and Volume III of The Complete Poetry of Percy Bysshe
                            Shelley. Fraistat has been awarded the Society for Textual Scholarship's
                            biennial Fredson Bowers Memorial Prize, the Keats-Shelley Association
                            Prize, honorable mention for the Modern Language Association's biennial
                            Distinguished Scholarly Edition Prize, and the Keats-Shelly
                            Association's Distinguished Scholar Award.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Dennis <dhq:family>Jerz</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>English — New Media Journalism, Seton Hill
                        University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>jerz@setonhill.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Dennis G. Jerz is Associate Professor of English — New Media Journalism
                            at Seton Hill University in southwestern Pennsylvania. His publications
                            include <title rend="quotes">Somewhere Nearby is Colossal Cave:
                                Examining Will Crowther's Original <q>Adventure</q> in Code and in
                                Kentucky</title> (<title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                                Quarterly</title>, 2007), <title rend="quotes">An Annotated
                                Bibliography of Interactive Fiction Scholarship</title> (<title rend="italic">Text/Technology</title>, 2002), <title rend="italic">Technology in American Drama, 1920-1950: Soul and Society in the
                                Age of the Machine</title> (Greenwood Press, 2003), a simulation of
                            the motion of wagons in a medieval pageant in York, England
                            (ReSoundings, 1997), and articles about blogging, memes, and education.
                            Since 1999, he has maintained Jerz's Literacy Weblog (<ref target="http://jerz.setonhill.edu/weblog">http://jerz.setonhill.edu/weblog</ref>), where he explores his
                            interests in new media, literature, journalism, and writing. He holds a
                            Ph.D. in English from the University of Toronto, and an M.A. and B.A. in
                            English from the University of Virginia.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000089</idno>
                <idno type="volume">004</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2010-09-01">1 September 2010</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2010-07-08" who="Alyssa">conformed to DHQ</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>Humanities scholars and librarians both confront questions regarding the
                    boundaries of texts and the relationships between various editions, translations
                    and adaptations. The Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records (FRBR)
                    Final Report from the International Federation of Library Associations has
                    provided the library community with a model for addressing these questions in
                    the bibliographic systems they create. The Preserving Virtual Worlds project has
                    been investigating FRBR's potential as a model for the description of computer
                    games and interactive fiction. While FRBR provides an attractive theoretical
                    model, the complexity of computer games as works makes its application to such
                    software creations problematic in practice.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>Computer games do not possess the clear boundaries of a physical artifact such as
                    a book.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head>Twisty Little Passages Almost All Alike: Applying the FRBR Model to a Classic
                Computer Game</head>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Humanities scholars have continually confronted questions regarding the
                    boundaries of the texts that they study and the complex inter-relationships that
                    can exist among various editions, printings, translations, and adaptations — in
                    short, the versions — of a work. While librarians have long recognized the
                    distinction between a work as an intellectual creation and its embodiment within
                    a particular physical form (and the need to adequately describe both), the
                    publication of the Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records Final
                    Report by the IFLA Study Group on the Functional Requirements for Bibliographic
                    Records (FRBR) marked a pronounced increase in the level of attention that the
                    library community has devoted to these issues. FRBR proposed a formal model for
                    bibliographic description that recognizes four classes of entities as implicated
                    in descriptive practice: Works (unique intellectual or artistic creations),
                    Expressions (the realization of Works), Manifestations (the physical embodiment
                    of particular Expressions), and Items (single exemplars of a Manifestation).
                    Attributes commonly found in bibliographic description, such as publisher or
                    title, are bound in the FRBR model to one of these four entities.</p>
                <p>In the decade since the Final Report was issued, a tremendous amount of
                    discussion has occurred regarding the interpretation of FRBR and its appropriate
                    application within bibliographic systems. At the same time, there has been
                    almost no cross-communication between humanities scholars engaged in the kind of
                    work described above (<q>textual studies,</q> as it is called) and library
                    specialists. In fact, discussions of distinctions between various ontological
                    states occupied by a textual object well predate the genteel deliberations of
                    textual scholars and IFLA study groups alike. <quote rend="inline" source="#shelley1903">[W]hen
                        composition begins,</quote> wrote <ptr target="#shelley1903" loc="39"/>,
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#shelley1903">inspiration is already on the decline, and the most
                        glorious poetry that has ever been communicated to the world is probably a
                        feeble shadow of the original conceptions of the poet.</quote> These
                    conceptions have typically been recast as the author’s <q>intentions</q> by
                    20th-century editors seeking to adjudicate between different versions of a poem
                    or novel by appealing to their ability to intuit what the author would have
                    wished, could he or she only be given the opportunity to declare it once and for
                    all. The so-called eclectic editions that resulted — standardized texts that
                    were in fact composites of any number of multiple, surviving documentary
                    instances of the work — also gave rise to an elaborate philosophical framework
                    which is perhaps most clearly articulated by <ptr target="#tanselle1989"/> in
                    his tripartite distinction among works, texts, and documents. The vocabulary
                    here is striking: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#tanselle1989">Photocopying a manuscript book or a printed book
                            creates a new document, the latest in the series of attempted
                            reproductions of the work its text represents...</quote>
                        <ptr target="#tanselle1989" loc="54"/>
                    </cit> Tanselle’s discourse on works, texts, and the documents in which they are
                    manifest clearly would not seem out of place in the FRBR report; his view of
                    textuality, which reinforced and extended the writings of key Anglo-American
                    bibliographers such as W. W. Greg and Fredson Bowers, was only seriously
                    challenged in the closing decades of the 20th century, when editors such as D.
                    F. McKenzie and Jerome McGann advanced theories that laid stress on the
                    interaction between individual textual artifacts and the larger social and
                    material fields in which they are embedded. One is finally interested not in a
                    definitive text but in the documentary text.</p>
                <p>Within the world of traditional manuscripts and print publications, the
                    relationships between the various versions of a particular text are already
                    extraordinarily complicated; applying these existing categories to new forms of
                    creative electronic texts (including interactive fiction and computer games)
                    makes these relationships become even more vexing and difficult to describe than
                    we had anticipated. Because each individual or subsequent encounter with the
                    same interactive work can generate different outputs, the adequacy of
                    traditional descriptive models applied by librarians to enable scholars' access
                    to textual materials needs to be carefully examined. From the scholar's (or
                    teacher's) perspective, even mundane activities such as a textual citation or
                    assigning students a particular passage to read become problematic. Moreover,
                    even the simplest electronic <q>text</q> is in fact a composite of many
                    different symbolic layers, from microscopic traces on physical storage media up
                    through machine code, higher-level languages, and finally the visible characters
                    one actually reads on a screen. Of course without the kind of preservation that
                    comes from recognition of such creations as part of our late 20th-century
                    cultural heritage, any such issues will be rendered moot for future generations
                    since the work will not survive in any accessible or recoverable form.</p>
                <p>The Rochester Institute of Technology, Stanford University, the University of
                    Illinois at Urbana-Champaign and the University of Maryland are currently
                    investigating the preservation of computers games and interactive fiction.
                    Sponsored under the Library of Congress’ National Digital Information
                    Infrastructure for Preservation Program (NDIIPP), this project seeks to identify
                    the specific difficulties in the preservation of computer games and interactive
                    fiction that distinguish them from other forms of digital information we wish to
                    preserve, to develop metadata and packaging practices to allow us to manage the
                    long-term preservation of these digital materials in a manner consistent with
                    the Open Archival Information System Reference Model, and to test those
                    practices via ingest of computer games and interactive fiction into a set of
                    functioning digital repositories.</p>
                <p>The project employs a case set methodology, focusing on a limited number of
                    computer games and works of interactive fiction chosen to highlight a variety of
                    potentially problematic issues. The works were intentionally chosen to represent
                    a variety of different periods in computer history, different computing
                    platforms, different styles of artistic work, and different intellectual
                    property issues. Works within our case set include <list type="unordered">
                        <item>
                     <hi rend="italic">Spacewar!</hi> — The first graphical computer game,
                                <hi rend="italic">Spacewar!</hi> is a space combat simulation based
                            on E. E. <q>Doc</q> Smith's <title rend="italic">Lensman</title> series
                            of books, created in 1962 at MIT for the PDP-1 computer. It was later
                            used as the basis for two different commercial arcade video games and
                            has been ported to a number of different platforms, including the Atari
                            2600 and more recently the iPhone.</item>
                        <item>
                     <hi rend="italic">ADVENTURE</hi> — One of the most influential
                            interactive fiction works, ADVENTURE was created by Will Crowther at BBN
                            Planet in 1976 and expanded upon by Don Woods at Stanford. The
                            availability of the game's source code on the early Arpanet has led to
                            its being modified by a number of individuals to add new puzzles, traps
                            and monsters, and to it being ported to innumberable different
                            programming languages and operating systems.<note>Versions of ADVENTURE
                                have already been released for both the Android operating system
                                (see <ref target="http://www.ecsoftwareconsulting.com/node/11">http://www.ecsoftwareconsulting.com/node/11</ref>) and the
                                iPhone/iPad (<ref target="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/advent/id284446752?mt=8">http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/advent/id284446752?mt=8</ref>).</note>
                  </item>
                        <item>
                     <hi rend="italic">Star Raiders</hi> — Originally published by Atari
                            for the Atari 400 and 800 computers, a modified version of <hi rend="italic">Star Raiders</hi> would become one of the most popular
                            games for the Atari 2600 game console and be ported to the Atari 5200
                            and Atari ST machines, with a relatively unsuccessful sequel, <hi rend="italic">Star Raiders II</hi>, released in 1986.</item>
                        <item>
                     <hi rend="italic">Mystery House</hi> — Created by Roberta and Ken
                            Williams in 1980 for the company which would later be named Sierra
                            Online, this is the first interactive fiction work to employ computer
                            graphics. A binary executable version of the original game for the Apple
                            II system was put into the public domain in the late 1980s, but the
                            apparent loss of any source code for the game limited development of
                            derivative versions, until the <hi rend="italic">Mystery House Taken
                                Over</hi> project produced and released a reverse engineered version
                            of the game in 2005.</item>
                        <item>
                     <hi rend="italic">Mindwheel</hi> — Published by Brøderbund Software in
                            1984, this work by Poet Laureate Robert Pinsky is also notable for being
                            a compound analog/digital work, containing both a print novella and the
                            game software.</item>
                        <item>
                     <hi rend="italic">Doom</hi> — Published by iD Software in 1993, this
                            game came to define the first-person shooter style of game,
                            revolutionized 3D graphic display technology for games, and as a result
                            of both the game's design and iD Software's decision to open source the
                            original game engine led to a whole new Internet culture of game
                            customization and modification. Like ADVENTURE, Doom has been ported to
                            a large number of different operating systems, including OS X, all
                            versions of Windows, Linux and Android, as well as various console
                            platforms including the Atari Jaguar, Game Boy Advance, Nintendo 64,
                            Sega Saturn, Sony Playstation and Nintendo SNES systems.</item>
                        <item>
                     <hi rend="italic">Second Life</hi> — Launched in 2003 by Linden Lab,
                            this has become one of the most popular of the non-role playing game
                            multiuser virtual worlds. Our project is focusing on the preservation of
                            several islands contained within <hi rend="italic">Second Life</hi>,
                            including the International Spaceflight Museum and Stanford Humanities
                            Lab's Hotgates Island. Given that islands in Second Life exhibit
                            on-going development and change and can be the work of a number of
                            different individuals, preserving any island in Second Life is more akin
                            to trying to preserve a collaborative performance art piece while it is
                            being produced than trying to preserve a data file.</item>
                    </list>
            </p>

                <p>The first phase of our project, which we have recently completed, has examined
                    the games in this case set to try to identify representative issues they present
                    for the long-term preservation of computer games and interactive fiction. As a
                    particular test of existing library practices we have been examining the
                    application of the FRBR entity-relationship model to computer games and
                    interactive fiction, including the seminal work ADVENTURE. FRBR, a model
                    developed primarily to assist in end-user access to library materials may seem
                    an unusual choice for a project concerned with digital preservation, but as <ptr target="#thibodeau2002"/> has trenchantly stated, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#thibodeau2002">In order to preserve a digital object we must be able
                            to identify and retrieve all of its digital components</quote>
                        <ptr target="#thibodeau2002" loc="12"/>
                    </cit>. A fundamental aspect of any effort to preserve digital resources is thus
                    the development of systems to describe and track the components of a digital
                    work and to relate works (and their physical embodiments) to each other,
                    including describing the provenance of manifestations as a work evolves over
                    time. Such activity is important not only for librarians and archival
                    caretakers, but also (as we have seen) for scholars, including those who may in
                    the future wish to produce the equivalent of a critical edition for a computer
                    game, as well as a wide variety of more casual users, including hobbyists, fans,
                    and enthusiasts. This paper will examine the difficulties encountered by the
                    project in seeking to apply the FRBR entity relationship model within the realm
                    of computer games, and our project’s suggestions for <q>pretty good</q>
                    practices for the application of FRBR and traditional bibliographic descriptive
                    practices to this ever-evolving electronic genre.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records &amp; Their
                    Discontents</head>
                <p>FRBR is, at first glance, a promising mechanism for representing this twisty
                    little maze of cultural heritage. It is an entity-relationship model capable of
                    discriminating among changes to the substance or <q>content</q> of the work, as
                    well as its physical embodiment in particular carrier media. In a traditional
                    FRBR representation, one might start with the work that is <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title>. The different versions of the play that are extant are the
                    work's expressions. These expressions are realized in manifestations, i.e. the
                    folios and quartos that have survived, as well as the more modern editions based
                    upon those sources. A discrete artifact that one holds in hand, for example the
                    copy of the Arden Shakespeare sitting nearby on my bookshelf, is an item. FRBR
                    also recognizes the possibility of more complex relationships between the
                    various types of entities it enumerates. A copy of Plays and Poems of
                    Shakespeare <ptr target="#shakespeare1878"/> may constitute a single item
                    exemplifying a single manifestation, but that manifestation embodies multiple
                    expressions and works. The various FRBR entities may also recursively contain
                    one another; the rock musical version of Hamlet by Czech musician Janek Ledecký
                        <ptr target="#ledecky2000"/> contains a number of individual songs, each of
                    which can be considered as works in their own right.</p>
                <p>The quartet of Work, Expression, Manifestation and Item form what the FRBR report
                    calls the Group 1 entities. Group 2 entities are <q>Person</q> and <q>Corporate
                        Body,</q> the entities which create Works, realize Expressions, produce
                    Manifestations, and own Items. Group 3 entities define different types of
                    subject matter with which a Work may be concerned, and include <q>Concept,</q>
                    <q>Object,</q>
                    <q>Event</q> and <q>Place.</q> The FRBR report also notes that Group 1 and Group
                    2 entities may serve as the subject matter of Works as well.</p>
                <p>In addition to defining the basic relationships between Group 1 entities
                    discussed above, the FRBR report also describes a number of other possible
                    relationships that may exist between Group 1 entities. <ref target="#table01">Table 1</ref> shows the various possible relationships between the Group 1
                    entities enumerated in the FRBR report. A number of these relationships can be
                    of use when describing video games and interactive fiction. If we consider a
                    game franchise such as the Doom series from iD software, for example, we can
                    easily find examples of successor relationships between Works (the original Doom
                    is succeded by Doom II), supplemental relationships (the original Doom is
                    supplemented by the Doom Wiki (<ref target="http://doom.wikia.com">http://doom.wikia.com</ref>), and even transformation relationships (the
                    original game Doom was transformed into the movie version starring Dwayne <q>The
                        Rock</q> Johnson). Other Group 1 relationships are also easy to identify in
                    the case of Doom. The original shareware expression of Doom has a revision
                    relationship to the full, registered commercial expression (with the full
                    registered version containing two weapons, the plasma gun and the BFG9000, not
                    available in the shareware version). An expression-to-expression translation
                    relationship also exists between the source code implementation of the original
                    Doom game engine and a binary executable version of the game engine compiled
                    from that source code for a Windows '95 machine. The DVD manifestation of the
                    movie Doom has an alternate manifestation, the Blu-ray manifestation. The item
                    consisting of our library's copy of Doom 3 for the PC platform has two other
                    items as parts: a CD-ROM containing the software, and a print manual.</p>
               <table xml:id="table01">
                  <head>Table 1 - Relationships between FRBR Group 1 Entities</head>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Work to Work</cell>
                        <cell>Expression to Expression</cell>
                        <cell>Expression to Work</cell>
                        <cell>Manifestation to Manifestation</cell>
                        <cell>Manifestation to Item</cell>
                        <cell>Item to Item</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">has a successor</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">has a supplement</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">has a complement</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">has a summary</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">has adaptation</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">has a transformation</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">has an imitation</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">has part</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">has an abridgement</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">has a revision</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">has a translation</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">has an arrangement (music)</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">has a reproduction</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">has an alternate</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">has a reconfiguration</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>At the same time that FRBR seems to promise a useful and detailed modeled for
                    description of library materials, including games, certain long-standing
                    challenges still exist even with more traditional applications of the FRBR
                    model. For example, there is no formal consensus on how much of the work has to
                    change before a new expression is declared. Catalogers (for FRBR is primarily a
                    cataloger's tool) are asked to rely upon common sense, community practice, and
                    other heuristics. Catalogers are all too aware, however, that even textual
                    materials within libraries can raise complex issues with respect to the question
                    of <q>how different</q> a particular text must be to qualify as a new
                    edition.</p>
                <p>In the case of an electronic object, the complications proliferate almost
                    exponentially <ptr target="#renear2006"/>. At first it might seem that all
                    versions of ADVENTURE should be grouped under a single <q>Work,</q> a particular
                    instance of the game (the last version modified by Don Woods, for instance)
                    should be the <q>Expression,</q> a particular file with a unique MD5 hash should
                    be the <q>Manifestation,</q> and an individual copy of that file (perhaps on a
                    Commodore 64 664 Block disk) would be the <q>Item.</q> But what if the text read
                    by the reader is exactly the same, but the underlying code is different? These
                    variants might be simple (a comment added to the FORTRAN source code),
                    peripheral (such as the ability to recognize <q>x</q> as a synonym for the
                    command <q>examine</q>), or very large (a port of the code from FORTRAN to
                    BASIC). Should these code level variants be considered different expressions? To
                    further complicate matters, what if the FORTRAN code were exactly the same but
                    compiled to two different chips? For example, an IBM mainframe and a Commodore
                    64 might both have a FORTRAN compiler, but the two compilers will interpret the
                    FORTRAN to a different set of machine instructions. It might also be the case
                    that two FORTRAN compilers designed by different programmers will generate
                    slightly different machine language. Even the same compiler might generate
                    slightly different machine code from a single source code file depending on the
                    options with which it is invoked. Should these compiled executables, different
                    in their binary structure but based on the same FORTRAN code, represent
                    different <q>Manifestations</q> or different <q>Expressions</q>?</p>
                <p>Finally, even two files with exactly the same MD5 signature participate in a
                    larger software environment at runtime. The drivers that run the display
                    interface, the keyboard, the memory, and the disk drives arguably become part of
                    ADVENTURE when the user is playing the game. For instance, the experience of
                    playing the game using the 6507 chip in a Commodore 64 hooked up to a black and
                    white television may be different than the experience of playing the game on the
                    same chip in a Commodore SX64 (the all-in-one machine some felt fit to call
                        <q>portable</q>). Should the software environment on which the binary is
                    executed be a part of the classification scheme at all? Would playing the game
                    on a video monitor (which displays only a fixed number of lines at a time)
                    provide a substantially different experience from a session with the same game
                    played on a Teletype (which saves the output indefinitely on paper)?</p>
                <p>We have applied the FRBR model to several different and specific instances of
                    ADVENTURE: the source and data files for the original Don Woods version, as well
                    as two early variants produced by Will Crowther, retrieved on April 27, 2008 at
                    6:01 pm from Dennis Jerz’s server (<ref target="http://jerz.setonhill.edu/if/crowther/">http://jerz.setonhill.edu/if/crowther/</ref>), as well as the DOS Windows
                    executable of these files edited to compile under GNU g77, a free FORTRAN
                    compiler (<ref target="http://www.russotto.net/%7Erussotto/ADVENT/">http://www.russotto.net/%7Erussotto/ADVENT/</ref>). This work will be
                    presented in the course of the paper, together with rationale and discussion in
                    the context of the kind of issues enumerated above. We will also discuss the
                    significance of this work for the broader digital humanities community, insofar
                    as it represents the intersection of library and information science, textual
                    studies, and software forensics.</p>
                <p>As more and more libraries and repositories begin the process of collecting
                    born-digital objects, they will invariably encounter material that transcends
                    the boundaries of documents, email, and other more or less conventional forms of
                    electronic records. ADVENTURE, as both a working computer program and as a
                    virtual world, as well as an artifact with widespread popular interest, is a
                    harbinger of the kind of content which increasingly needs to be accessioned,
                    cataloged, and described. FRBR represents the library community’s best effort to
                    date to distinguish between different versions and editions of a work. We
                    believe the work discussed represents an important test case for FRBR's
                    applicability to complex born-digital objects.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>ADVENTURE's Passages</head>
                <p>Will Crowther originally developed the game ADVENTURE in the mid-1970s while he
                    was working at BBN, the company responsible for launching the ARPANET. The game
                    focuses on the exploration of a cave complex in which a variety of puzzles and
                    hostile antagonists (including an axe-throwing dwarf) must be defeated. Crowther
                    made a compiled version of the game available through his BBN account, and a
                    copy ended up in the hands of Don Woods, a graduate student at Stanford
                    University. Woods contacted Crowther and obtained from him a copy of the game's
                    FORTRAN source code, which he modified to change the game play, adding several
                    additional fantasy elements. The game, as modified by Woods, was widely
                    distributed on the ARPANET and was a significant influence on early hacker
                    culture, with phrases from the game such as <soCalled>a maze of
                        twisty little passages, all alike</soCalled> and the magic word <soCalled>xyzzy</soCalled> having been appropriated and re-used in a
                    variety of contexts. The game provided the first instance of a new genre of
                    work, interactive fiction. It also sparked the creation of a slew of successors
                    as other programmers picked up the source code distributed by Woods and modified
                    it to suit their taste (whether in terms of game play or programming language of
                        choice).<note>See <ptr target="#jerz2007"/> and <ptr target="#montfort2003"/> for detailed discussions of ADVENTURE's origins and
                    significance.</note>
            </p>
                <p>The game's wide distribution and immense popularity in the early days of
                    networked computing, along with the ready availability of the FORTRAN source
                    code modified by Woods, led to a proliferation of new versions of the game as
                    programmers ported it to new languages, new operating platforms, and modified
                    its structure to add new puzzles, monsters and territory. <ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref> shows a very partial family tree for
                        ADVENTURE<note>The information in this figure is based on a listing of
                        ADVENTURE variants compiled by <ptr target="#dalenberg2006"/>. Note that
                        some of the instances of ports shown here may involve migration between
                        different versions of a programming language. So, the transition from
                        Blackett's version of ADVENTURE to Supnik's involves migrating from two
                        variant implementations of the FORTRAN IV programming language.</note>,
                    starting with the original Crowther and Woods versions and showing the path of
                    succession as particular versions of the software are picked up by other
                    programmers and modified. Of particular importance in this tree is the variation
                    in types of descent. We can identify three major types of change that can occur
                    when a programmer takes a pre-existing version of ADVENTURE and modifies it. One
                    of the more common forms of variation occurs when the programmer ports the
                    source code from one programming language into another (or into a significant
                    variant of the original language), while making no changes (or as few and as
                    minor as possible within the scope of changing the programming language) to the
                    game play itself. You can see many instances of this in <ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>, such as the transition from the original Don Woods FORTRAN
                    IV version from 1977 to the Jim Gillogly port to the C language in 1993. Another
                    type of change is one in which the programming language is maintained from one
                    version to the next, but the source code is modified to change the game play.
                    The transition from the original Will Crowther version of ADVENTURE to Don
                    Wood's version would qualify as such a modification. While the programming
                    language was still FORTRAN, Woods modified the game to add new antagonists and
                    puzzles. The final type of change is the most extreme, a reimplementation in
                    which both the source code language and the game play are modified. An example
                    of this would be the reimplementation of ADVENTURE that Don Woods undertook
                    using the C programming language in 1995.<note>It should be noted that the
                        difference between what is considered a port, a modification or a
                        reimplementation is a matter of both degree and interpretation. The
                        transition from Wellsch's C language interpretation to Strobl's was a matter
                        of moving from an implementation intended to work on Unix-style operating
                        systems to one intended to work on Microsoft Windows machines. While Strobl
                        did not intend to alter the game play, he did put a Windows graphical user
                        interface on top of the game that allowed the user to respond to various
                        requests for game input via buttons. Whether this constitutes a major change
                        in game play depends on which aspects of the original you consider
                        significant and which you do not.</note>
            </p>
               <figure xml:id="figure01">
                  <head>A partial family tree of ADVENTURE, showing ports,
                     modifications and reimplementations.</head>
                    <figDesc/>
                    <graphic url="...000089/resources/figure01.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>This typology of changes highlights one of the unique features about interactive
                    fiction works such as ADVENTURE as textual artifacts, and one of the
                    difficulties they present for those trying to describe them within the bounds of
                    the FRBR model. A port of a game from one language to another involves a
                    significant amount of creative, intellectual effort and results in the creation
                    of a source code <q>text</q> which, while implementing similar algorithms, may
                    otherwise bear very little resemblance to the original source code on which it
                    is based. Significant variations in the source code, however, may result in no
                    visible changes in the game play presented by a compiled executable of the new
                    code. If we consider the transition from the original Don Woods FORTRAN version
                    to the Gillogly C language version as programmers looking at the source code, we
                    see enough changes to qualify the Gillogly version as not merely a new
                    expression in the FRBR sense, but in all probability an entirely new work. The
                    Gillogly version certainly seems to answer to the FRBR criteria that when <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ifla1997">the modification of a work involves a significant
                            degree of independent intellectual or artistic effort, the result is
                            viewed, for the purposes of this study, as a new work</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ifla1997" loc="18"/>
                    </cit>. From the point of view of a player interacting with the game, however,
                    the two different versions are practically identical. So, in determining whether
                    something constitutes a new work or expression in the world of interactive
                    fiction, should we assume the point of view of the programmer, or the point of
                    view of the game player?</p>
                <p>While it is tempting to try to resolve this question through reference to user
                    needs, different users will have very different needs when approaching gaming
                    materials, and those differing needs will have a profound impact on the users'
                    preferred intellectual organization for games. From the point of view of someone
                    interested in playing the game, an executable prepared from the Gillogly source
                    code and one prepared from the Woods code are essentially equivalent and of
                    equal interest. From the point of view of a programmer interested in game
                    programming techniques in the C language, the two could not be more different.
                    From the point of view of a scholar of game history, the two are different, but
                    highly inter-related. Establishing the dividing lines between Group 1 entities
                    in FRBR has always been a somewhat subjective matter, but interactive fiction
                    (and perhaps software generally) highlight the way in which differing and
                    incompatible subjectivities may reside in a library's or archive's patrons.</p>
                <p>A closer examination of some of the specific instances of the game ADVENTURE
                    reveals further complexities for those seeking to apply the FRBR
                    entity-relationship model to the description of computer games. In our research,
                    the earliest version of ADVENTURE that we have been able to examine is the
                    original FORTRAN version created by Will Crowther, consisting of a FORTRAN
                    source code file which is 727 lines in length, and a separate 733 line data file
                    containing a dictionary of terms that the game employs to interpret user
                    commands, a set of textual responses provided by the game in response to user
                    commands, and the geometry of the virtual world which the player explores. While
                    the FORTRAN source code file does contain a few comments, these serve only to
                    describe the operation of the code; there is nothing resembling bibliographic
                    metadata in either file, with no authorship or date of creation provided. The
                    files in question were retrieved by Dennis Jerz with Don Woods' cooperation from
                    a backup tape of Don Woods' student account at Stanford University, and are
                    named advf4.77-03-11 and advdat.77-03-11. Research by <ptr target="#jerz2007"/>
                    indicates that the date contained within the filenames is probably an indication
                    of when Don Woods obtained the source code from Will Crowther. The backup tape
                    also contained two new versions of the FORTRAN source code created by Don Woods,
                    modifications of the code provided by Will Crowther. These two new source code
                    files were named advf4.77-03-23 and advf4.77-03-31. There was also a new version
                    of the game data file that was created by Woods, named advdat.77-03-31. The
                    changes made to the source code by Woods in the two later files were relatively
                    minor and do not reflect the more significant changes that he made in the
                    version he eventually distributed. The changes between the advf4.77-03-11
                    version and the advf4.77-03-23 version consisted of changing one line of
                    existing code and adding another 16 lines of new code. The new lines of code
                    appear to implement an external FORTRAN function that Will Crowther's code had
                    invoked, but which was not available on the PDP-10 system that Woods was using.
                        <ref target="#table02">Table 2</ref> shows the differences between the two
                    versions, with modified code in the March 23rd version italicized, and new code
                    in bold face.</p>
                <table xml:id="table02">
                   <head>Table 2 - Differences between W. Crowther's and D. Wood's FORTRAN
                      IV source code</head>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell>
                     <emph>advf4.77-03-11</emph>
                  </cell>
                        <cell>
                     <emph>advf4.77-03-23</emph>
                  </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                     <eg>CALL SHIFT(A(J+1),7*(I-6),YY) </eg>
                  </cell>
                        <cell>
                     <eg>
                        <hi rend="italic">CALL SHIFT(A(J+1),7*(K-6),YY)</hi>
                                <hi rend="bold">SUBROUTINE SHIFT (VAL,DIST,RES) IMPLICIT INTEGER
                                    (A-Z) RES=VAL IF(DIST)10,20,30 10 IDIST=-DIST DO 11 I=1,IDIST J
                                    = 0 IF (RES.LT.0) J="200000000000 11 RES =
                                    ((RES.AND."377777777777)/2) + J 20 RETURN 30 DO 31 I=1,DIST j =
                                    0 IF ((RES.AND."200000000000).NE.0) J="400000000000 31 RES =
                                    (RES.AND."177777777777)*2 + J RETURN END</hi>
                     </eg>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The differences between Don Wood's version, dated March 23, 1977, and the one
                    dated March 31, 1977, were of about the same magnitude, with 14 lines of code in
                    the March 23rd version modified in the March 31st version, and one line in the
                    March 23rd version deleted. The differences between the original game data file,
                    advdat.77-03-11, and the modified version by Woods, advdat.77-03-31, have no
                    impact on game play whatsoever and consist solely of changes in numeric
                    identifiers assigned to twelve terms contained in the game's dictionary.</p>
                <p>The files retrieved from Don Wood's old student account can be viewed as
                    comprising three different versions of the game ADVENTURE. The first is the
                    original Will Crowther version consisting of the two files advf4.77-03-11 and
                    advdat.77-03-11. The second is a version with the FORTRAN source code file
                    advf4.77-03-23 modified by Don Woods but with the original Will Crowther data
                    file of advdat.77-03-11. The third is a further modification by Woods consisting
                    of his FORTRAN source code file named advf4.77-03-31 and his modified data file
                    advdat.77-03-31. However, while there are modifications to source code or data
                    file (or both) for all three of these versions, they are all essentially
                    identical in terms of game play. While Don Woods would later further modify
                    ADVENTURE to add new monsters and puzzles, these early changes do not include
                    those later changes to the game. A player engaged with executable programs
                    prepared from these three source code versions would insist that they are, in
                    fact, all the same.</p>
                <p>Given that all three versions present an identical <q>text</q> to the game
                    player, and substantially similar text to an individual reading the source code,
                    an analysis of these three instances might conclude that all represent the same
                    FRBR work. However, the issue of FRBR expression is somewhat more complicated.
                    Certainly there are changes in the source code and data files between the three
                    versions, and given their relative historic importance within game studies,
                    recognizing them as distinct expressions seems reasonable. However, each of the
                    versions, if compiled and played, would be indistinguishable from an end user
                    perspective. Or at the very least, the game play would be indistinguishable.
                    From the perspective of a user interested in experiencing the actual original
                    game, these many instances are effectively a single expression.</p>
                <p>Our discussion so far has somewhat glossed over the fact that our hypothetical
                    game-playing end user would not be interacting with a source code file, but an
                    executable file created from a FORTRAN source code file using a compiler. FRBR
                    states that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ifla1997">Inasmuch as the form of expression is an inherent
                            characteristic of the expression, any change in form (e.g., from
                            alpha-numeric notation to spoken word) results in a new expression.
                            Similarly, changes in the intellectual conventions or instruments that
                            are employed to express a work (e.g., translation from one language to
                            another) result in the production of a new expression</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ifla1997" loc="20"/>
                    </cit>. A compiler translates human readable text into machine code; it
                    therefore alters both the language of the work and the notation employed. Any
                    executable expression a user can actually interact with is clearly a distinct
                    expression from the source code used to create it, albeit one that can be
                    produced algorithmically from the source code expression.</p>
                <p>This gives us at least some basis for considering the three versions of the game
                    as unique and separate expressions, even when viewed from the game player's
                    perspective. The executables compiled from the three different versions of
                    source code will not be identical. They will contain minor variations in their
                    structure and file size that will be visible to an end user should they choose
                    to investigate it. On that basis, an argument could be made that each version of
                    the game constitutes a unique expression, even from the point of view of the
                    game player, and that if we combine the five original files in our possession
                    with compiled executables of the source code files, we have six expressions of a
                    single work, as seen in <ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref>. But at some
                    level, this does not seem a very satisfactory result. Users interested in game
                    play will be more likely to consider the actual interactive experience provided
                    by the software to constitute the basis for determining whether something is a
                    unique expression, not its size in bytes or the internal structure of the op
                    codes contained within an executable file.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure02">
                  <head>FRBR Expressions of ADVENTURE</head>
                    <figDesc/>
                    <graphic url="...000089/resources/figure02.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Unfortunately, an alternative in which we claim that all three source code
                    expressions produce a single executable expression with three different
                    manifestations is difficult to model accurately in existing bibliographic
                    systems. It also runs afoul of the relationships established between Group 1
                    entities in the FRBR model. <ref target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref> demonstrates
                    the problem. It is possible to establish a set of Group 1 entities for the
                    versions of ADVENTURE in our possession that includes a single FRBR Expression
                    for the executable versions of the program, but in order to express the
                    relationship between the source code versions and their executable derivatives
                    we need to state that a particular source code manifestation has a translated
                    form in a particular executable manifestation (as noted by the dashed arrows).
                    While this may be a relatively accurate assertion, the FRBR model as expressed
                    in <ptr target="#ifla1997"/> only provides for asserting a translation
                    relationship at the level of FRBR Expressions, not at the Manifestation level.
                    Thus, the only model for the different versions of ADVENTURE we have in hand
                    appears to be one in which we have six Expression-level entities for ADVENTURE
                    (3 source code Expressions, and 3 corresponding executable Expressions), a model
                    that may impede the search efforts of end users interested in playing the
                    game.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure03">
                  <head>ADVENTURE with a Single Executable
                     Expression</head>
                    <figDesc/>
                    <graphic url="...000089/resources/figure03.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The compilation of the three different source files here raises other questions
                    with respect to the nature of games and their description within a FRBR
                    framework. Crowther wrote the original ADVENTURE FORTRAN source code file to
                    compile on a DEC PDP-10 running the TOPS operating system. It includes a call to
                    an external function, IFILE, used to read in the data file (which was to be
                    named <q>TEXT</q>). The IFILE function was not part of the FORTRAN language used
                    on the TOPS-10 and TOPS-20 operating systems <ptr target="#dec1987"/>, and can
                    be found at statement 1001 in the source code:</p>
                
 <eg>1001 LTEXT(I)=0 I=1 CALL IFILE(1,'TEXT')</eg>
                
                <p>As the source code defines a variety of other subroutines within itself, we can
                    assume that IFILE was probably part of an external library of FORTRAN functions
                    in use on the PDP-10 at the time the game was written.<note>We have not been
                        able to identify a FORTRAN library for the TENEX and TOPS-20 operating
                        systems in use at BBN at the time Will Crowther authored ADVENTURE that
                        contained an IFILE function. However, there was an IOFIL FORTRAN library
                        created for the DECSystem-20 that contained an IFILE function to support
                        software written for the DEC F40 FORTRAN IV compiler for the PDP-10. A
                        report listing software converted from DECSystem-10 to DECSystem-20
                        mentioning the library can be found at <ref target="http://pdp-10.trailing-edge.com/decuslib20-01/01/decus/20-0000/conversion-status.mem">http://pdp-10.trailing-edge.com/decuslib20-01/01/decus/20-0000/conversion-status.mem</ref>.</note>
                    This example is similar to the case mentioned previously, where Don Woods
                    reimplemented a function named SHIFT that apparently was an extrinsic function
                    called by Will Crowther's code. These cases demonstrate that the boundaries of
                    what constitutes the software are not equivalent to the boundaries of the files
                    that a programmer might identify as constituting the source code for the game.
                    Even in this relatively early game, we see programmers beginning to rely on
                    libraries of functions distributed with compilers and operating systems to
                    simplify the job of authoring code. In modern computer games, programmers are
                    even more reliant on libraries provided by third parties to simplify the
                    development of game software. Compiling code into an operational copy of the
                    game requires not just the code developed by the game author, but also all of
                    the code present in any third party library functions that might be invoked by
                    the game. Warcraft III, for example, relies on DirectX libraries distributed by
                    Microsoft for various multimedia functions.</p>
                <p>Computer games do not possess the clear boundaries of a physical artifact such as
                    a book. Games (and all software) are embedded in and intertwined with a
                    technological environment that includes compilers, linkers, code libraries,
                    operating system facilities, and various kinds of hardware. A functioning copy
                    of a computer game requires not only the game software but also a complete
                    computer system. When we set out to describe a game within the FRBR framework,
                    we immediately confront the question of <q>what constitutes the game,</q> and
                    that question can be difficult to answer. The case of ADVENTURE reveals that
                    some of the complexity involved in answering that question is due to the fact
                    that the game is a compound work containing a variety of subsidiary FRBR works,
                    authored by different people at different times for different purposes. The
                    IFILE library function presumably was not written to be part of ADVENTURE; it
                    was written to provide file I/O services for any program. But it formed an
                    essential component of the game, which could not be compiled (or played) without
                    it.</p>
                <p>The FRBR framework allows for these types of whole/part relationships at both the
                    Work and Expression levels, and modeling computer games using these types of
                    FRBR relationships actually allows us to assert a variety of relationships
                    between different entities that might be of interest to end users (see the
                    transformation and translation relationships in <ref target="#figure04">Figure
                        4</ref>). However, practical application of FRBR in the world of computer
                    games could easily prove to be a tremendous burden on those describing games. A
                    complete description of a computer game within the FRBR framework would need to
                    identify all of the various subsidiary Works constituting the games'
                    technological components, whether created by the game author or not, delineate
                    the relationships between all of the different components, and provide some
                    level of intellectual description for each. For a game like ADVENTURE, defined
                    by one source code file and one data file (at least if we limit ourselves to a
                    single instance), identifying implicated components such as compile-time
                    libraries might be slightly onerous but on its face does not appear an
                    impossible task. But in more modern games, containing thousands of files created
                    by dozens or hundreds of individuals working at a variety of different companies
                    and distributed as parts of different products, complete description within a
                    FRBR framework would be an insurmountable burden on current cataloging
                    resources.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately, there are several credible use scenarios for description that
                    require this fine level of detail. For those concerned with preservation of
                    computer games, the need for some level of description down to the individual
                    computer file level is a real concern. Librarians and archivists concerned with
                    copyright issues may need to be aware that the putative creator of a game may
                    not be the only creative agent involved in production of game software and that
                    subcomponents of a game may have differing intellectual property status.
                    Scholars studying games may be quite interested in patterns of use and reuse of
                    game components among both game companies and game players, and without
                    fine-grained description, investigating these issues will become much more
                    difficult.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure04">
                  <head>FRBR Group 1 Entity Relationships for two ADVENTURE
                     Works</head>
                    <figDesc/>
                    <graphic url="...000089/resources/figure04.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The description of computer games within the FRBR model provides a reasonably
                    compelling justification for the notion of a Superwork, a potential addition to
                    the set of FRBR entities that would collocate multiple Works under a single
                    descriptive banner for the purposes of retrieval. As <ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref> makes clear, for a game like ADVENTURE, the number of
                    instances of a game which can be said to be, in Svenonius's terms, "similar by
                    virtue of emanating from the ur-work" <ptr target="#svenonius2000" loc="38"/>
                    can be very large and continue to grow over a period of decades after a game's
                    initial release. While a legitimate case can be made that many of the versions
                    of ADVENTURE could be placed under the banner of a single Work, our research on
                    game preservation has also led us to examine games such as Doom from id Software
                    where a culture of <q>modding</q>
               <note>
                  <q>Modding</q> refers to taking an
                        existing game and making modifications to it to alter game play in some
                        fashion. The game Doom, like ADVENTURE, kept the data which was displayed to
                        the user in a separate file. In the case of DOOM, this data file (known as a
                        WAD file) was reverse engineered by the gamer community, which then started
                        modifying it to add new monsters, game levels, weapons and other
                        changes.</note> has arisen among the user community, and in such cases the
                    number of separate works, all emanating from the original Doom ur-Work (and in
                    many cases employing the original game engine), can easily number in the
                    hundreds. The ability to collocate these resources is important for users: they
                    care quite a bit about which version of Doom was used in generating a particular
                    mod, and they also wish to be able to distinguish Doom mods from mods of other
                    games such as Quake. An examination of gaming web sites such as FilePlanet (see
                        <ref target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref>
               <note>Image taken from <ref target="http://www.fileplanet.com/31773/90004/section/DOOM-Series">http://www.fileplanet.com/31773/90004/section/DOOM-Series</ref> on Oct.
                        7, 2009.</note>) show that the user community for games already engages in
                    collocation activities for themselves that group games not only by a game series
                    but within a series by a particular edition. A variety of Doom mods have been
                    written to work with specific source ports of the original Doom engine, so the
                    ability to collocate mods that work with a specific implementation of Doom is
                    important to game players. Given the users' obvious desire to collocate works
                    associated with a particular engine, with a particular version of Doom, and
                    across the entire Doom series, application of a Superwork entity may be the
                    simplest means of enabling users' preferred mode of searching.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure05">
                  <head>Doom Series Game Mods Page from
                     fileplanet.com.</head>
                    <figDesc/>
                    <graphic url="...000089/resources/figure05.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>One final comment should be made about the FRBR model and its application to
                    computer games and interactive fiction. While the focus of our analysis has
                    concentrated on description of games within the framework of the FRBR Group 1
                    entities, the fact that we are working on a project involving software
                    preservation has meant that we have had to devote a certain amount of attention
                    to intellectual property issues. It is unfortunate, in our view, that the FRBR
                    model does not mention intellectual property rights in discussing the
                    relationships that exist between Group 1 and Group 2 entities (person, corporate
                    body). Given the examples set forth in the IFLA Study Group's report, e.g.,
                        <quote rend="block" source="#ifla1997">
                        <l>
                     <hi rend="bold">W1</hi> Franz Schubert's Trout quintet</l>
                        <l>     <hi rend="italic">e1</hi> the composer's
                            notated music</l>
                        <l>     <hi rend="italic">e2</hi> the musical work
                            as performed by Rosina Lhevinne, piano, Stuart Sankey, double bass, and
                            members of the Juilliard String Quartet</l>
                        <l>
                     <ptr target="#ifla1997" loc="20"/>
                  </l>
                    </quote> it would appear that copyright can adhere at the level of both the Work
                    and the Expression. If not, it would be difficult to account for cases such as a
                    recorded song that possesses both a recording performance production copyright
                    and a creator copyright within the FRBR framework. Greater clarity on how the
                    IFLA Study Group conceived of intellectual property rights fitting into their
                    model would be of great benefit to those trying to work on games. While
                    ADVENTURE is not a particularly problematic game with respect to this issue,
                    having passed into the public domain, modern games can have extremely
                    complicated rights situations, in which music with separate performance and
                    creator copyrights are included in a game copyrighted by yet another
                        entity.<note>The language of FRBR with regards to Item/Group 2 entity
                        relationships is also somewhat problematic for those dealing with game
                        collections. While <q>owned by</q> is described within the IFLA Study Group
                        report as including either ownership or custody of an item, it is highly
                        unusual to find a computer game (or other software) which a purchaser will
                        actually own. They instead obtain a license to possess and use the software.
                        The use of <q>owned by</q> as a relationship term could be seen as
                        misleading to users if presented in the context of software
                        collections.</note>
            </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Our research has found that the FRBR model provides a mechanism capable of
                    describing some of the web of relationships that exist between games and between
                    the component parts that make up a game. This is impressive given the sheer
                    extent of the component parts and the intricacy of their relationships in any
                    modern computer game or interactive fiction work. However, there are a variety
                    of both practical and theoretical problems that must be addressed when seeking
                    to apply FRBR in the world of computer games and interactive fiction. While the
                    practical issues may be susceptible to technological solutions, the theoretical
                    ones will require further development of the FRBR standard if it is to realize
                    its promise as a descriptive mechanism for these types of interactive art.</p>
                <p>The relationships between Group 1 entities in the FRBR model, when applied to
                    computer games such as DOOM, tend to favor descriptions composed of a number of
                    different Works, rather than a number of different Expressions under the banner
                    of a single Work. This may make it more difficult for searchers to collocate
                    variants of a game under a single banner. While asserting relationships between
                    Works (particularly successor relationships) may alleviate this problem
                    somewhat, identifying all of the relationships to record may be difficult and
                    time-consuming. Game aficionados may be willing to invest the time and energy in
                    deciphering relationships between instances of a game such as those shown in
                        <ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>, but asking catalogers to engage in
                    this level of detail may be unrealistic.</p>
                <p>The multiplication of Work-level entities in the description of games and
                    interactive fiction is further promoted by the need to describe the various
                    component pieces of games individually. This in turn leads to a need to assert
                    even more whole/part relationships between Expression-level entities. Each of
                    these constituent parts can obviously come with their own set of additional
                    Work-to-Work relationship issues, primarily to indicate succession
                    relationships.</p>
                <p>All of the preceding makes practical application of the FRBR model to computer
                    games a time-consuming and expensive enterprise. This is not necessarily a fault
                    of FRBR; the reality is that detailed description of games, particularly within
                    a preservation environment, is time-consuming and expensive. Our work has been
                    carried out within a context of ensuring the preservation of games in the
                    long-term, and that requires fairly detailed description of the software,
                    including identification of its component parts and dependencies on other
                    software and hardware. FRBR provides a theoretical framework that can be applied
                    to this task, but it cannot in itself lessen the costs associated with such
                    detailed description.</p>
                <p>Our work with ADVENTURE and other computer games, however, does highlight two
                    deficiencies in the FRBR entity-relationship model. The first problem arises
                    from the complex tangle of derivative works associated with any particular game.
                    As <ptr target="#smiraglia1992"/> noted, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#smiraglia1992">Bibliographic families can be as complex as human,
                            genealogical families. Many generations can exist on the same plane at
                            the same time</quote>
                        <ptr target="#smiraglia1992" loc="72"/>
                    </cit>. Computer games and interactive fiction provide ample evidence of this,
                    with the number of derivative works created for some games easily numbering in
                    the hundreds. Neither catalogs as they exist today nor FRBR provides sufficient
                    facilities to ease collocation of these works for users. Computer games provide
                    one of the stronger arguments for the concept of a Superwork and adding support
                    for Superworks to our bibliographic systems, and to the FRBR model. The second
                    problem is the omission of any mention of intellectual property rights within
                    the FRBR model. While <ptr target="#ifla1997"/> made it clear that they were not
                    enumerating every attribute of or relationship existing between bibliographic
                    entities, the failure to account for intellectual property relationships between
                    Group 1 and Group 2 entities is extremely problematic for those attempting to
                    describe computer games, and we suspect much other digital material. While on
                    its face, copyright might be seen to constitute a relationship between a FRBR
                    Expression entity and a Group 2 entity, case law on copyright has wavered over
                    the years with respect to how it handles the distinction between uncopyrightable
                    ideas and copyrightable expressions <ptr target="#samuels1989"/>, particularly
                    with respect to software. Alignment of legal theory and cataloging theory
                    regarding the separation between artistic/intellectual creations and their
                    expression in particular forms is, we suspect, a difficult task that will
                    require the input of the both communities.</p>
                <p>ADVENTURE and its passages also offer a compelling demonstration of the extent to
                    which complex born-digital objects, especially those that are popular,
                    historically significant, or cherished by communities of enthusiasts, will
                    demand other kinds of expertise not likely to reside within a typical cataloging
                    department. Our work applying FRBR to ADVENTURE required an advanced knowledge
                    of antiquarian computers, systems, and programming languages, as well as an
                    appreciation for how the game has been ported and reworked by diverse
                    constituencies over the course of several decades. Digital humanities is well
                    suited to serve as a disciplinary rubric for uniting these disparate kinds of
                    interests and expertise, and we believe that the bibliography of complex
                    electronic objects must become an increasingly significant aspect of activity
                    for those who consider themselves its practitioners.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dalenberg2006" label="Dalenberg 2006" key="dalenberg2006">
                    <author>Dalenberg, Russel</author>. <title rend="italic">Versions and Ports of
                        ADVENTURE, Version 2.6.7.</title>
                    <date>2006</date>. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.io.com/~ged/www/advelist.html">http://www.io.com/~ged/www/advelist.html</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dec1987" label="Digital Equipment Corp. 1987" key="dec1987">
                    <author>Digital Equipment Corp.</author>
                    <title rend="italic">TOPS--10/TOPS--20 FORTRAN Language Manual. AA-N3838-TK,
                        AD-N3838-T1.</title>
                    <pubPlace>Maynard, MA</pubPlace>. <date>February 1987</date>. Retrieved from
                        <ref target="http://bitsavers.org/pdf/dec/pdp10/TOPS10_softwareNotebooks/vol11/AA-N383B-TK_fortLangMan.pdf">http://bitsavers.org/pdf/dec/pdp10/TOPS10_softwareNotebooks/vol11/AA-N383B-TK_fortLangMan.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ifla1997" label="IFLA 1997" key="ifla1997">
                    <author>IFLA Study Group on the Functional Requirements for Bibliographic
                        Records</author>
                    <title rend="italic">Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records Final
                        Report.</title>
                    <pubPlace>The Hague, Netherlands</pubPlace>: <publisher>International Federation
                        of Library Associations and Institutions.</publisher>. <date>Sept. 1997, as
                        amended through Feb. 2009</date>. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.ifla.org/files/cataloguing/frbr/frbr_2008.pdf">http://www.ifla.org/files/cataloguing/frbr/frbr_2008.pdf</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jerz2007" label="Jerz 2007" key="jerz2007">
                    <author>Jerz, Dennis</author>
                    <title rend="quotes">Somewhere Nearby is Colossal Cave: Examining Will
                        Crowther's Original <title rend="quotes">ADVENTURE</title> in Code and in
                        Kentucky.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 1.2 <date>2007</date>.
                    Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/001/2/000009.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/001/2/000009.html</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ledecky2000" label="Ledecký 2000" key="ledecky2000">
                    <author>Ledecký, Janek</author>
                    <title rend="italic">Hamlet.</title>
                    <pubPlace>Prague</pubPlace>: <publisher>BMG Ariola ČR</publisher>.
                        <date>2000</date>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="montfort2003" label="Montfort 2003" key="montfort2003">
                    <author>Montfort, Nick</author>
                    <title rend="italic">Twisty Little Passages: An Approach to Interactive
                        Fiction.</title>
                    <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>.
                        <date>2003</date>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="powers2000" label="Powers 2000" key="powers2000">
                    <author>Powers, Richard</author>
                    <title rend="italic">Plowing the Dark.</title>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Farrar, Strauss, and
                        Giroux</publisher>. <date>2000</date>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="renear2006" label="Renear 2006" key="renear2006">
                    <author>Renear, Allen</author>
                    <title rend="quotes">Is An XML Document a FRBR Manifestation or a FRBR
                        Expression? - Both, Because FRBR Entities are note Types, But Roles.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages 2006, Montreal,
                        Quebec, August 7-11, 2006.</title>
                    <date>2006</date>. Retrieved from <ref target="http://conferences.idealliance.org/extreme/html/2006/Renear01/EML2006Renear01.html">http://idealliance.org/papers/extreme/Proceedings/html/2006/Renear01/EML2006Renear01.html#tod0e5</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="samuels1989" label="Samuels 1989" key="samuels1989">
                    <author>Samuels, Edward</author>
                    <title rend="quotes">The Idea-Expression Dichotomy in Copyright Law.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Tennessee Law Review</title> 56(321). <pubPlace>Knoxville,
                        TN</pubPlace>: <publisher>The University of Tennessee College of
                        Law</publisher>. <date>1989</date>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shakespeare1878" label="Shakespeare 1878" key="shakespeare1878">
                    <author>Shakespeare, William</author>
                    <title rend="italic">The Plays and Poems of Shakespeare; with One Hundred and
                        Seventy Illustrations; from Designs by Eminent Artists.</title>
                    <editor>A. J. Valpy, A.M.</editor>
                    <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Bell &amp; Daldy</publisher>.
                        <date>1878</date>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shelley1903" label="Shelley 1903" key="shelley1903">
                    <author>Shelley, Percy Bysshe</author>
                    <title rend="italic">A Defense of Poetry.</title>
                    <editor>Albert S. Cook</editor>. <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>: <publisher>Ginn
                        &amp; Company.</publisher>
                    <date>1903</date>. Retrieved from <ref target="http://books.google.com/books?id=u2s3qZXXsIAC&amp;dq=inauthor%3A%22Percy%20Bysshe%20Shelley%22%20%22when%20composition%20begins%22&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;pg=PR1#v=onepage&amp;q=inauthor:%22Percy%20Bysshe%20Shelley%22%20%22when%20composition%20begins%22&amp;f=false">http://books.google.com/books?id=u2s3qZXXsIAC&amp;dq=inauthor%3A%22Percy%20Bysshe%20Shelley%22%20%22when%20composition%20begins%22&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;pg=PR1#v=onepage&amp;q=inauthor:%22Percy%20Bysshe%20Shelley%22%20%22when%20composition%20begins%22&amp;f=false</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="smiraglia1992" label="Smiraglia 1992" key="smiraglia1992">
                    <author>Smiraglia, Richard Paul</author>
                    <title rend="italic">Authority Control and the Extent of Derivative
                        Bibliographic Relationships.</title> Ph.D. Dissertation, <publisher>Graduate
                        Library School, University of Chicago</publisher>. <date>1992</date>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="svenonius2000" label="Svenonius 2000" key="svenonius2000">
                    <author>Svenonius, Elaine</author>
                    <title rend="italic">The Intellectual Foundation of Information
                        Organization.</title>
                    <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>: <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>.
                        <date>2000</date>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tanselle1989" label="Tanselle 1989" key="tanselle1989">
                    <author>Tanselle, G. Thomas</author>
                    <title rend="italic">A Rationale of Textual Criticism.</title>
                    <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Pennsylvania
                        Press</publisher>. <date>1989</date>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thibodeau2002" label="Thibodeau 2002" key="thibodeau2002">
                    <author>Thibodeau, Kenneth</author>
                    <title rend="quotes">Overview of Technological Approaches to Digital
                        Preservation and Challenges in Coming Years.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The State of Digital Preservation: An International
                        Perspective, Conference Proceedings, Documentation Abstracts, Inc.
                        Institutes for Information Science, Washington, DC, April 24-25,
                        2002.</title>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Council on Library &amp;
                        Information Resources.</publisher>
                    <date>July 2002</date>. Retrieved from <ref target="http://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub107/thibodeau.html">http://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub107/thibodeau.html</ref>. </bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>