<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Changes in Lyrical and Hit Diversity of Popular
                    U.S. Songs 1956-2016</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Peter <dhq:family>Meindertsma</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Department of Language Technology - Computational Linguistics,
                        University of Groningen, Netherlands</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>research@petermeindertsma.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Peter Meindertsma currently teaches courses on web design and usability
                            at the departments of Communication and Information Studies, and
                            Journalism and Media Studies at the University of Groningen in the
                            Netherlands. His research focuses on the macro analysis of popular
                            music: <ref target="http://www.petermeindertsma.com/lyrics/">http://www.petermeindertsma.com/lyrics/</ref></p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000440</idno>
                <idno type="volume">013</idno>
                <idno type="issue">4</idno>
                <date when="2019-12-14">14 December 2019</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>Billboard</item>
                        <item>charts</item>
                        <item>lyrics</item>
                        <item>popular music</item>
                        <item>cultural diversity</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2019-11-04" who="murelj">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>To examine changes in the diversity of popular songs over time, I have analyzed
                    the lyrics of 99% of all songs sung in English that have appeared on the U.S.
                    Billboard Hot 100 chart from 1956 up to and including 2016 (n=27.108). I have
                    found the number of songs that reached the Hot 100 per year more than halved
                    between 1966 and 2002, which indicates a loss in diversity. I have also found
                    that the variation of valence (or level of <term>pleasantness</term>) in the
                    songs’ lyrics and the variation of a sampled Type Token ratio (an indicator for
                    lexical complexity) decreases over time. This indicates that lyrics of popular
                    songs become more similar and again signify a loss of diversity.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p/>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>In September 2012 the Universal Music Group completed the acquisition of EMI
                    Music, reducing the number of worldwide music label conglomerates from four to
                    three: Universal, Sony Music and Warner Music Group. This was another step in
                    the concentration of media corporations that accelerated in the 1980s and 1990s
                        <ptr target="#bagdikian2004"/> and gradually became a global media
                    oligopoly, a form in which a market or industry is dominated by a small number
                    of sellers. This oligopoly now not only controls music (e.g. 85% of the U.S.
                    recording music industry <ptr target="#lule2012"/>) but also broadcasting,
                    movies, publishing and advertising markets. This concentration of media
                    ownership frequently raises concerns about the reduction of cultural diversity
                    communicated through major media channels. Some argue that this concentration
                    results in a shift away from serious news to infotainment <ptr
                        target="#owen2012"/> and that it becomes harder for independent record
                    companies to get airplay while large companies become more selective in the
                    artists offered to radio stations <ptr target="#lee2004"/>. Even decades ago,
                    Theodor Adorno warned about the eroding effects of the transition from
                    autonomous works of art to profitable cultural products and the resulting
                    impediment of the development of individual consciousness due to a strong
                    cultural industry <ptr target="#adorno1975"/>. Yet, despite all these concerns,
                    the aforementioned acquisition of EMI clearly indicates that the process of
                    media convergence has not been halted.</p>
                <p>This creates an opportunity to investigate the diversity of cultural output over
                    time to see if there is a homogenization of cultural meanings, values and
                    tastes. To do so, I have chosen to examine the diversity of an important and
                    omnipresent cultural product: popular music, by looking at changes in the number
                    of hit songs (songs that appeared on a chart, ranked by sales or popularity) and
                    lyrical variation over time.</p>
                <p>Instead of stitching together lyrics of a few selected songs to represent popular
                    music, which has been, until recently, the default method for lyric related
                    studies, I will apply a macro analytic approach to grasp popular music as a
                    whole. With the ever increasing capacity and speed of computers it becomes
                    easier to create and quantitatively analyze large corpora of digitized texts and
                    other media to study underlying phenomena. It has been applied successfully in
                    many studies (e.g. <ref target="#moretti2005">Moretti, 2005</ref>; <ref
                        target="#jockers2011">Jockers, 2011</ref>; <ref target="#michel2011">Michel,
                        2011</ref>; <ref target="#mauch2015">Mauch, 2015</ref>). Note that
                    challenges remain, such as adequately representing popular culture. Merely
                    creating a large collection of song lyrics is not sufficient, for one can wonder
                    if every included song qualifies to represent popular culture. And perhaps even
                    more important: does the absence of all other similarly qualifying songs result
                    in bias? Many studies of lyrics of popular songs tackle this issue by using
                    charts, usually the U.S. Billboard Hot 100, to select songs that have earned a
                    certain level of popularity. These charts remain a <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#stewart2012">crude but effective</quote> means to measure the
                    cultural impact of a song among the record buying public <ptr
                        target="#stewart2012"/>.</p>
                <p>However studies that rely on hit song charts predominantly use subsets, e.g. top
                    10 songs for every tenth year, and are therefore limited in scope and detail. To
                    contribute to the extensiveness of this study, I tried to collect lyrics of all
                    songs that appeared on the Billboard Hot 100.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Dataset and Methodology</head>
                <p>The focus of this study is on lyrics from popular songs that charted in the USA,
                    arguably the most important market in popular culture. To overcome limitations
                    by scale, where only a few songs represent a much larger group, a major goal is
                    to collect and analyze as much lyrics as possible of songs that have appeared on
                    the Billboard Hot 100. Just by reaching a position on this chart, these songs
                    have proven their popular cultural mass appeal.</p>
                <p>Despite its shortcomings, e.g. payola scandals and frequent changes in the
                    balancing of digital and physical sales and airplay influence, the Billboard Hot
                    100 is still by far the leading song chart of the USA and for several decades it
                    has been used for scientific research. By many it is regarded as the most
                    appropriate source for songs that were most representative of general cultural
                    preferences across time in the USA <ptr target="#pettijohn2009"/>.</p>
                <p>In order to have ample charting songs per year to be collected and analysed, the
                    scope is restricted to the years from 1956 up to and including 2016. Billboard
                    changed its weekly Top 40 chart of popular singles into a Top 100 in November
                    1955 and was renamed the Hot 100 in 1958. The year 1955 also roughly coincides
                    with the dawn of the <term>rock age</term> when Rock ‘n’ Roll got a grip on the
                    Billboard charts and quickly turned the focus of popular music primarily towards
                    the youth and shaped popular music for at least the next forty years <ptr
                        target="#garofalo2008" loc="2"/>.</p>
                <p>The main source for the chart listings of songs, artists and years is Bullfrogs
                    Pond’s Billboard database, an extensive collection of Billboard related chart
                    data (1890-2017) maintained by an anonymous ‘avid music lover’ since 1999
                    (Bullfrog, 2016). Many randomly selected songs’ peak positions and years were
                    double checked with official Billboard Chart data (at Billboard.com and Joel
                    Whitburn’s <title rend="quotes">Top Pop Singles 1955-2012</title> (2013)) and
                    chart data at Top40db.net to verify the reliability of this source. Based upon
                    these sources I found that of all top 100 hits from 1956 up to and including
                    2016 (n=28.477), about 96% (n=27.387) of these songs have (predominantly) lyrics
                    in English, when instrumental (3.5%, n=986) and non-English lyric songs (0.4%,
                    n=104) are excluded.</p>
                <p>The texts of these songs with lyrics in English were extracted automatically
                        <note>To obtain lyrics from online archives, a parser was written in Perl.
                        It included instructions to retrieve the lyrics at random delay times to
                        avoid bot detection (i.e. non-human behaviour) and potential
                        blacklisting.</note> from several online archives<note>The lyrics were
                        predominantly retrieved from Lyrics.com. Additional lyrics were acquired
                        from Top40db.net, metrolyrics.com, lyricsfreak.com and, to a lesser extent
                        from lyrics.wikia.com, releaselyrics.com, lyricsmode.com, azlyrics.com,
                        lyricsdomain.com, lyricstime.com, lyricsmania.com, and
                        musicsonglyrics.com.</note>. Simultaneously, automatic and manual
                    corrections were applied to restore song structures (e.g. replacing lines like
                        <q>repeat chorus</q> with the fully transcribed chorus) and to remove
                    mark-up, punctuation and metadata about performers or musical segments (e.g.
                    phrases like <q>written by</q>, <q>intro</q> or <q>guitar solo</q>). Eventually
                    I managed to obtain the lyrics of all but 1% (n=279) of all songs sung in
                    English that charted on the Billboard top 100 charts from 1956 up to and
                    including 2016. This resulted in a corpus of 7.727.622 words in 27.108 song
                    files with an average of 444 examined songs per year, <ref target="#figure01"
                        >see Figure 1</ref>.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure01">
                    <head>Total and collected number of Billboard Hot 100 hit song lyrics per year
                        1956-2016. Lyrics of instrumental (3.5%), non-English (0.4%), and
                        unobtainable (1,0%) songs were not collected.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Results</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">1. Changes in hit diversity</hi></p>
                <p>Inspired by Lee’s research on the radio industry <ptr target="#lee2004"/>, I
                    first examined the frequency of charting songs per year and found a sharp
                    decrease in the annual number of songs that obtained top 100, top 40, top 10 or
                    number 1 positions (see Figure 2a, and 2b, a detailed version of 2a).</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure02">
                    <head>Total top 100, 40, 10 and number 1 hits in the Billboard Hot 100 per year
                        (1956-2016).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02a.png"/>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02b.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The number of annual Hot 100 hits reached its low point in 2002 when 294 songs
                    charted, which is less than 40% of its peak in 1966 when 743 songs appeared on
                    the chart. Note that Figure 2b clearly shows a sharp decline in the total number
                    of yearly top 10 and number 1 hits after 1991.</p>
                <p>It is very likely that these changes around the year 1991 were caused by an
                    alteration in the way Billboard tracks sales. In that year the Billboard Hot 100
                    switched to Nielsen SoundScan, a digital and improved system for tracking sales,
                    based upon data that represents over 90% of the U.S. music retail market <ptr
                        target="#billboard2013"/>. It replaced a manual, error-prone and easy to
                    manipulate system of calling selected stores about sales figures. Additionally,
                    Billboard then also started to remove descending songs after twenty weeks that
                    fell below position number 50, in order to make the charts more <q>current</q>
                    <ptr target="#billboard2013"/>. In theory this could make more chart positions
                    available for new and yet uncharted songs, but it apparently did not prevent the
                    previously observed sharp decrease of annual charting songs, and led to an
                    increase in the average time songs spent on the charts. Perhaps the previously
                    used manual system caused an even greater removal of descending songs from the
                    chart.</p>
                <p><ref target="#figure02">Figure 2a and 2b</ref> also show that for the period
                    prior to the introduction of SoundScan in 1991, the number of Top 100, 40 and 10
                    hits per year was, except for a peak in the number of Top 10 songs during the
                    1980s, steadily decreasing since 1966. In the latter year 743 songs charted on
                    the Hot 100 and by 1990 this number was nearly halved to 376. Since several
                    studies have shown a positive relation between the number of different
                    recordings that reached the hit song charts and intensity of market competition
                        <ptr target="#peterson1975"/>
                    <ptr target="#rothenbuhler1982"/>
                    <ptr target="#burnett1989"/>, Figure 2a and 2b therefore indicate a loss of
                    market competition and diversity.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">2. Changes in word usage</hi></p>
                <p>Inspired by Google’s Ngram Viewer <ptr target="#michel2011"/>, I arranged the
                    lyric files by year and constructed a bigram viewer (see <ref
                        target="http://www.petermeindertsma.com/lyrics/">http://www.petermeindertsma.com/lyrics/</ref>) to examine changes in the
                    popularity of word and term usage. In order to limit the influence of duplicate
                    terms in transcribed parts of the lyrics, e.g. in repeated choruses etc., I
                    calculated the percentage of annual songs in which these words occur, so each
                    song can only make one contribution to the popularity of a given word or term
                    per year. This method enabled me to visualize the popularity of these words over
                    time in order to signal trends, <ref target="#figure03">see Figure 3</ref>.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure03">
                    <head>Relative frequencies of song lyrics that contain selected (case
                        insensitive) terms on the Billboard Hot 100 (1956-2016). An * indicates that
                        all suffixes are included, e.g. <q>darlin*</q> includes <q>darling</q> and
                            <q>darlin’</q>.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>For example, a word like <q>darling</q> (or <q>darlin’</q>) clearly lost its
                    popularity (<ref target="#figure03">Figure 3A</ref>). In a similar way this tool
                    can visualize the impact and duration of hypes in their times, e.g. dance crazes
                        (<term>disco, twist</term>) (<ref target="#figure03">Figure 3B</ref>), and
                    what was on our collective minds (e.g. <term>war</term> and <term>money</term>)
                        (<ref target="#figure03">Figure 3C</ref>). This macro analytic approach
                    demonstrates a major benefit: results become quantifiable: For example, the term
                        <term>twist</term> is used in nearly twice as many songs in its peak year
                    compared to the term <term>disco</term> (<ref target="#figure03">Figure
                    3B</ref>). It can also visualize trends like the rapid increase of profanity in
                    lyrics since 1991 (<ref target="#figure03">Figure 3D</ref>), especially when
                    compared to its gradual growth rate in books<note>See Google Books Ngram Viewer:
                            <ref
                            target="https://books.google.com/ngrams/graph?content=fuck,shit&amp;year_start=1956&amp;year_end=2014&amp;corpus=15&amp;smoothing=0&amp;share=&amp;direct_url=t1;,fuck;,c0;.t1;,shit;,c0"
                            >
                            https://books.google.com/ngrams/graph?content=fuck,shit&amp;year_start=1956&amp;year_end=2014&amp;corpus=15&amp;smoothing=0&amp;share=&amp;direct_url=t1;,fuck;,c0;.t1;,shit;,c0</ref></note>.
                    This seems to signify an important change in American popular (music) culture
                    and deserves more research.</p>
                <p>Although this visualization method can signal changes in the popularity of word
                    usage, it is too limited to examine changes in the homogeneity of popular
                    lyrics. Therefore other methods are needed, like the analysis of sentiment and
                    lexical complexity.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Changes in sentiment</hi></p>
                <p>To examine an aspect of changes in sentiment over time, I applied the Affective
                    Norms for English Words (ANEW) list. This is a word list developed by Bradley
                    and Lang to classify texts by valence (or <quote rend="inline">level of
                        pleasantness</quote>) <ptr target="#bradley1999"/>
                    <ptr target="#osgood1957"/>. This list contains 1034 words in English that have
                    a score for emotional weight on a scale from 1 to 9. For example, <q>love</q>
                    has a score of 8.72, <q>suicide</q> has 1.25. By adding these scores together
                    for each of these ANEW words’ occurrences, the average emotional weight for each
                    song is calculated. The resulting analysis is consistent with Danforth and
                    Dodds’ findings <ptr target="#danforth2010"/> that the average valence of lyrics
                    from popular songs is decreasing over time and songs on average are less
                        <q>happy</q> than ever before, <ref target="#figure04">see Figure
                    4</ref>.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure04">
                    <head>Average valence scores of songs on the Billboard Hot 100 per year
                        (1956-2016).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Finally, I examined the variance (standard deviation) of the average valence of
                    all songs per year, <ref target="#figure05">see Figure 5</ref>.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure05">
                    <head>Standard deviation of average valence of Billboard Hot 100 songs per year
                        (1956-2016).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Beside short-term fluctuations, the overall trend is a slow decrease in variance
                    over time, which indicates a trend towards homogeneity in lyrics of popular
                    songs.</p>
                <p>4. Changes in lexical complexity</p>
                <p>To examine changes in lexical complexity, I computed the average number of words
                    per song per year (<ref target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref>) and used Bullfrogs
                    Pond’s data to find the average duration (length in seconds) per song over time
                        (<ref target="#figure07">Figure 7</ref>).</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure06">
                    <head>Average number of words per song on the Billboard Hot 100 per year
                        (1956-2016).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure07">
                    <head>Average length in seconds of songs on the Billboard Hot 100 per year
                        (1956-2016).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Both graphs show a gradual increase over time. By 1994 the average number of
                    words per song has nearly doubled since 1960, while the average duration of
                    songs has increased by about 60% between 1960 and 1991.</p>
                <p>With this data, I also calculated the average number of words per second, which
                    remained fairly stable at about 1.2 words per second until around 1991 when it
                    started to increase rapidly and reached its (preliminary) peak in 2004 with 1.87
                    words per second, <ref target="#figure08">see Figure 8</ref>.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure08">
                    <head>Average words per second of songs on the Billboard Hot 100 per year
                        (1956-2016).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>This increase of the average of number of words per second in songs hints at an
                    increase in lyrical complexity. It also suggests, like my previous findings,
                    that a big change has occurred in popular music around 1991.</p>
                <p>To further examine this likely increase in lexical complexity, I computed the
                    percentage of unique words per text or Type Token ratio. This is a frequently
                    used method to provide an estimate of lexical complexity where a higher
                    percentage indicates a higher level of complexity. However, this ratio is
                    affected by varying lengths of texts. Since I have previously demonstrated that
                    the average number of words per song has roughly doubled between 1960 and 1994
                        (<ref target="#figure06">see Figure 6</ref>), I have used a sampling method
                    to compensate for the changes in average length of lyrics over time. From each
                    song’s lyrics, 75 words (sample size) were selected randomly to calculate the
                    song’s Type Token ratio. To reduce the influence of potential unintended effects
                    of this random selection, I repeated this process fifty times (!) per song in
                    order to achieve an average sampled Type Token Ratio. For different sample sizes
                    (50, 75 and 100 words), I found an increase in this sampled Type Token ratio
                    which indicates an increase in lyrical complexity, see Figure 9.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure09">
                    <head>Average Type Token ratio of songs on the Billboard Hot 100 per year
                        (1956-2016), based upon a sample size of 75 words per song.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Note that the average Type Token ratio starts to increase considerably around
                    1990. This coincides with the rapidly increasing popularity of hip hop on the
                    Billboard Hot 100 around that time. For example, Katznelson et al. have found a
                    higher type token ratio for hip hop songs compared to rock and pop songs between
                    1989 and 2009 <ptr target="#katznelson2011"/>.</p>
                <p>As for changes in lexical diversity, I have also examined the variance (standard
                    deviation) of this sampled Type Token ratio and it clearly fluctuates over time,
                        <ref target="#figure10">see Figure 10</ref>.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure10">
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
                    <figDesc>Standard deviation of sampled Type Token Ratio of songs on the
                        Billboard Hot 100 per year (1956-2016).</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p>This variance roughly seems to behave like a sine wave cycle, repeating nearly
                    every twenty years. The global trend, however, is a slowly decreasing variance,
                    which means that lyrics become more similar and again indicates a loss of
                    diversity.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Limitations</head>
                <p>The results of this study support the argument that the lyrics of popular songs
                    reveal a trend toward homogeneity over time. However, this work has several
                    limitations and acknowledging these can provide a better understanding of the
                    scope of these results and might improve further related research.</p>
                <p>A first limitation is the restriction of using only lyrics of songs that charted
                    in the USA. Since this country currently accounts for about 4.5% of the world’s
                    population, these results cannot be applied internationally <ptr
                        target="#arnett2008"/>
                    <ptr target="#dewall2011"/> and require further research into other cultures.
                    Also note that this study focuses solely on the pop singles charts, which relate
                    strongly to youth culture. Other aspects of popular culture, e.g. more adult
                    oriented pop albums, radio station playlists, music venue owners, movie scripts,
                    popular fiction novels or special interest magazine articles, may yield
                    different results.</p>
                <p>A second restriction is the potential imperfection of the examined lyrics. Due to
                    the lack of access to or absence of official sources, the lyrics were collected
                    from several Internet websites, and were, unfortunately, subject to errors.
                    These lyrics were most likely transcribed by individuals and could potentially
                    not always accurately reflect the official spelling of the words used. For
                    example, lyrics by British musicians could have been transcribed by American
                    individuals choosing the word <q>color</q> over <q>colour</q> and vice versa.
                    Additionally, since there were basically no online lyric archives before the
                    1990s, it is safe to assume that most of the transcriptions of songs from
                    previous decades were made long afterwards. Since language and peoples’
                    preferences gradually change over time, it seems likely that these lyrics do not
                    necessarily reflect the preferred spelling (fashions) of its original times,
                    e.g. words like <q>kissing</q> and <q>love</q> could have been replaced by
                        <q>kissin’</q> and <q>luv</q> respectively. For further analysis, stemming
                    and lemmatization techniques are recommended to improve some of these
                    issues.</p>
                <p>A further challenge is related to the increasing average number of words used per
                    song over time. As I have shown previously <ref target="#figure06">in Figure
                        6</ref>, the average number of words per song has doubled between 1960 and
                    1994. This means that, regarding my method of visualizing term usage over time
                        (<ref target="#figure03">see Figure 3</ref>), songs from 1994 can, in
                    theory, contribute to the popularity of twice as many different terms compared
                    to that of songs from 1960. A word-weighing formula might be considered to
                    compensate for this.</p>
                <p> Finally, the used method of measuring <term>valence</term> has its limitations.
                    It is based upon only 1034 words that constitute the ANEW list and this in
                    general works better for longer texts. Also, the method of counting specific
                    words or phrases does not necessarily overlap with intended meaning, e.g.
                    sarcasm, hidden messages or context, like changes in time and space <ptr
                        target="#danforth2010"/>. For example, some words with a low
                        <term>valence</term> value are from time to time used as words of approval
                    like <q>wicked</q> and <q>sick</q> and should therefore deserve a distinct and
                    higher value.</p>
                <p> Unfortunately, this study’s focus on extensiveness comes with a price, as most
                    of the limitations mentioned above illustrate less paid attention to detail.
                    Ideally, for an all encompassing and thorough study, this macro analytic
                    approach can therefore not replace the traditional method of close reading, but
                    rather supplement it. For similar or larger sized corpora, this combination can
                    become very labor intensive. Nevertheless, for examining underlying phenomena
                    less focus on detail is required, as Bernoulli’s law of large numbers should
                    prove. The methods and results of this study therefore should only be applied to
                    improve our understanding of the big picture.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion and Discussion</head>
                <p>In this study I have devised and applied a macro analytic approach for
                    re-evaluating our understanding of popular music’s last sixty years, especially
                    to examine if changes occurred in its homogeneity over time. Using this method,
                    I have analyzed the diversity of hit songs and their lyrics over time and found
                    that the number of annual charting songs on the Billboard Hot 100 has gradually,
                    but steadily been decreasing since the 1960s until 2005<note>The number of
                        annual charting songs began to increase again in 2005, especially in the
                        lower chart regions.</note>. I have also demonstrated that the variances of
                    valence (a level of pleasantness) and the variances of sampled Type Token ratio
                    (an indicator for lexical complexity) have decreased over time.</p>
                <p>These findings all indicate a loss of diversity of popular songs and will
                    hopefully inspire further research to take the next step: examine if this
                    observed trend toward homogenization is a symptom of the aforementioned media
                    convergence, e.g. by analyzing differences in output diversity of large vs.
                    independent record labels over time.</p>
                <p>Additionally, this study’s findings also demonstrate remarkable changes around
                    the year 1991. It is very likely that Billboard’s switch to SoundScan in 1991
                    influenced these changes, but the findings suggest other causes as well. The
                    rapid increase in the average number of words per song (<ref target="#figure06"
                        >see Figure 6</ref>), words per second (<ref target="#figure08">see Figure
                        8</ref>) and sampled Type Token Ratio (<ref target="#figure09">see Figure
                        9</ref>), the further decrease in valence (<ref target="#figure05">see
                        Figure 5</ref>) and the remarkable increase of profanity in song’s lyrics
                        (<ref target="#figure03">see Figure 3D</ref>) indicate that popular music in
                    the USA has changed considerably at that time. This coincides with the time when
                    hip hop became a dominant music genre on the charts, at the expense of others,
                    e.g. music by British musicians and especially (classic, alternative and hard-)
                    rock music. This shift is arguably the most important event that shaped the
                    Billboard charts in the last sixty years <ptr target="#mauch2015"/>.</p>
                <p> As Figure 10 points out, I have also found that the variance of the sampled Type
                    Token Ratio roughly behaves like a sine wave cycle over time. Further research
                    can hopefully specify if periods of rapid increases (e.g. 1989-1994) correspond
                    with transitional periods in popular music (e.g. increased market competition
                    and changes of dominating genres), while the rapid decreases (e.g. 1977-1981)
                    are years of stabilization. This method can then facilitate predictions of
                    coming changes in the development in popular music and add to the debate whether
                    cultural products go through cycles <ptr target="#peterson1975"/>.</p>
                <p>Finally, the remarkable increase in the number of annual charting songs that peak
                    between position 40 and 100 since 2005 (<ref target="#figure02">see Figure
                        2a</ref>), indicates new changes in chart diversity, especially in the lower
                    chart regions, for the number of yearly Top 40, Top 10 and Number 1 songs has
                    not changed that much since 2005. This increase of annual charting songs is
                    likely due to Billboard’s inclusion of digital sales from online retail stores
                    such as iTunes for compiling the weekly Hot 100 charts since 2005 <ptr
                        target="#billboard2013"/>. These stores are in general not depending on the
                    physical availability and storage of singles and can offer a much larger and
                    more diverse and quickly accessible stock compared to offline retailers. Songs
                    are also no longer required to have a physical single release in order to chart,
                    which is exemplified by the simultaneous charting of many album tracks when
                    current popular artists like Taylor Swift and Eminem release much anticipated
                    new albums. It also enables short chart runs for (in general) short-lived
                    televised song performances, e.g. by American Idol artists (since 2002) and the
                    cast of the TV series Glee (since 2009). This increase in annually charting
                    songs could in theory indicate a new period of increased song diversity on the
                    charts, although the variances of valence (<ref target="#figure05">see Figure
                        5</ref>) and Type Token ratio (<ref target="#figure10">see Figure 10</ref>)
                    are still (slightly) below average.</p>
                <p>It is nevertheless very likely that the composition of the Billboard Hot 100
                    chart will continue to change. For example, in February 2013 it started to
                    include YouTube (Vivo) streams, making it more susceptible for songs that
                    suddenly become a hit on the Internet (e.g. <title rend="italic">Harlem
                        Shake</title> by Baauer). This change could lead to a further increase in
                    the number of annual charting songs and future research should reveal how this
                    affects the diversity of popular songs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgements">
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>I want to thank Valerio Basile, Johan Bos, Leonie Bosveld-de Smet, Gosse Bouma,
                    Douwe Draaisma, Dicky Gilbers, Dore van Hoorn, Carel Jansen, Matthew Jockers,
                    Henny Klein, Daniël de Kok, Laura MacDonald, Kim Middel, Gertjan van Noord, Erik
                    Tjong Kim Sang, Nynke van der Vliet, Tity de Vries, George Welling, Dirk Jan
                    Wolffram and especially John Nerbonne and Kristin McGee for their time and
                    insightful comments.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="adorno1975" label="Adorno and Rabinbach 1975">Adorno, T. W. and
                    Rabinbach, A. G. <title rend="quotes">Culture Industry Reconsidered</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">New German Critique</title>, 6 (1975): 12-19.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="arnett2008" label="Arnett 2008">Arnett, J. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Neglected 95%: Why American Psychology Needs to Become Less
                    American</title>, <title rend="italic">American Psychologist</title>, 63 (2008):
                    602-614.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bagdikian2004" label="Bagdikian 2004">Bagdikian, B. <title
                        rend="italic">The New Media Majority</title>, Beacon Press, Boston
                    (2004).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="billboard2013" label="Billboard 2013">Billboard.com. <title
                        rend="italic">Billboard Charts Legend</title>. <ref
                        target="http://www.billboard.com/biz/billboard-charts-legend">
                        http://www.billboard.com/biz/billboard-charts-legend</ref> (accessed 10
                    September 2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bradley1999" label="Bradley and Lang 1999">Bradley, M. M. and Lang, P.
                    J. <title rend="quotes">Affective norms for English words (ANEW): Instruction
                        manual and affective ratings</title>, <title rend="italic">Technical Report
                        C-1</title>, The Center for Research in Psychophysiology, University of
                    Florida (1999).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bullfrog2013" label="Bullfrog 2013">Bullfrogspond.com. <title
                        rend="quotes">Billboard Pop ME (1890-2014)</title>.
                    http://bullfrogspond.com/ (accessed 15 May 2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burnett1989" label="Burnett and Weber 1989">Burnett, R. and Weber, R.
                    P. <title rend="quotes">Concentration and Diversity in the Popular Music
                        Industry 1948-1986</title>, Paper presented at the 84th Annual Meeting of
                    the American Sociological Association (1989).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="danforth2010" label="Danforth and Dodds 2010">Danforth, C. M. and
                    Dodds, P. S. <title rend="quotes">Measuring the Happiness of Large-Scale Written
                        Expression: Songs, Blogs, and Presidents</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >Journal of Happiness Studies</title>, 11 (2010): 441-456.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dewall2011" label="DeWall et al. 2011">DeWall, C.N., Pond Jr., R.S.,
                    Campbell, W.K., and Twenge, J.M. <title rend="quotes">Tuning in to psychological
                        change: Linguistic markers of psychological traits and emotions over time in
                        popular U.S. song lyrics</title>, <title rend="italic">Psychology of
                        Aesthetics, Creativity, and the Arts</title>, 5(3) (2011): 200-207.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="garofalo2008" label="Garofalo 2008">Garofalo, R. <title rend="italic"
                        >Rockin’ Out: Popular Music in the U.S.A.</title>, Pearson, Boston
                    (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jockers2011" label="Jockers 2011">Jockers, M. L. <title rend="quotes"
                        >On Distant Reading and Macroanalysis</title>. <ref
                        target="http://www.matthewjockers.net/2011/07/01/on-distant-reading-and-macroanalysis/"
                        >
                        http://www.matthewjockers.net/2011/07/01/on-distant-reading-and-macroanalysis/</ref>
                    (accessed 1 April 2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="katznelson2011" label="Katznelson et al. 2011">Katznelson, N., Gelman,
                    J., Lindblom, K., and Caput, M. <title rend="italic">American Song Lyrics. A
                        Corpus-Based Research Project</title>, <ref
                        target="http://mariecaput.myefolio.com/Uploads/737final.doc">
                        http://mariecaput.myefolio.com/Uploads/737final.doc</ref>. (accessed 12 May
                    2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lee2004" label="Lee 2004"> Lee, S.S. <title rend="quotes">Radio
                        Industry Structure and Music diversity: 1989-2002</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Poetics</title>, 32 (2004): 325-342.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lule2012" label="Lule 2012">Lule, J. <title rend="italic"
                        >Understanding Media and Culture: An Introduction to Mass
                        Communication</title> (online book), <ref
                        target="http://catalog.flatworldknowledge.com/bookhub/reader/3833?e=lulemedia_1.0-ch06_s03"
                        >
                        http://catalog.flatworldknowledge.com/bookhub/reader/3833?e=lulemedia_1.0-ch06_s03</ref>
                    (accessed 1 September 2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mauch2015" label="Mauch et al. 2015">Mauch, M., MacCallum, R.M., Levy,
                    M., and Armand, L.M.\ <title rend="quotes">The Evolution of popular music: USA
                        1960-2010</title>, <title rend="italic">Royal Society Open Science</title>,
                    2 (2015): <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rsos.150081"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rsos.150081</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="michel2011" label="Michel et al. 2011">Michel, J.B. et al. <title
                        rend="quotes">Quantitative Analysis of Culture Using Millions of
                        Books</title>, <title rend="italic">Science</title>, 331 (2011):
                    176-182.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moretti2005" label="Moretti 2005">Moretti, F. <title rend="italic"
                        >Graphs, Maps, Trees: Abstract Models for a Literary History</title>. Verso,
                    London (2005).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="osgood1957" label="Osgood et al. 1957">Osgood, C., Suci, G. and
                    Tannenbaum, P. <title rend="italic">The Measurement of Meaning</title>.
                    University of Illinois, Urbana (1957).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="owen2012" label="Owen 2012">Owen, D. <title rend="quotes">Media
                        Consolidation, Fragmentation and Selective Exposure in the USA</title>. In
                        <title rend="italic">SAGE Handbook of Political Communication</title>, SAGE
                    Publications Ltd, London (2012): pp. 402.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="peterson1975" label="Peterson and Berger 1975">Peterson, R. and
                    Berger, D. <title rend="quotes">Cycles in Symbol Production: The Case of Popular
                        Music</title>, <title rend="italic">American Sociological Review</title>,
                    40(2) (1975): 158-173.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pettijohn2009" label="Pettijohn and Sacco 2009">Pettijohn, T. and
                    Sacco, D. <title rend="quotes">The Language of Lyrics. An Analysis of Popular
                        Billboard Songs Across Conditions of Social and Economic Threat</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">Journal of Language and Social Psychology</title> 28(3)
                    (2009): 297-311.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rothenbuhler1982" label="Rothenbuhler and Dimmick 1982">Rothenbuhler,
                    E. and Dimmick, J. <title rend="quotes">Popular music: concentration and
                        diversity in the industry</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of
                        Communication</title> 32(1) (1982): 143-149.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stewart2012" label="Stewart 2012">Stewart, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >What's Going On: Anti-War and Pro-War Hits on the Billboard Singles Charts
                        during the Vietnam War Era (1965–1975) and the 'War on
                        Terror'(2001–2010)</title>. In S. Gibson and S. Mollan. (eds), <title
                        rend="italic">Representations of Peace and Conflict</title>. Palgrave
                    Macmillan, Basingstoke (2012): pp. 67-85. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="whitburn2013" label="Whitburn 2013">Whitburn, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Top Pop Singles 1955-2012 (14th edition)</title>. Record Research,
                    Menomonee Falls, WI (2013).</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
