<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article">Because It's Not There: Ekphrasis and the Threat of Graphics in
          Interactive Fiction</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Aaron <dhq:family>Kashtan</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Department of English, University of Florida</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>akashtan@ufl.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Aaron Kashtan is an ABD Ph.D. candidate in the Department of English at the
              University of Florida, specializing in digital humanities and comics studies. His
              dissertation is on the interaction between computer graphics and fantasies of
              handwriting. He is the moderator of the comixscholars-l listserv and a member of the
              editorial collective of <title rend="italic">ImageTexT: Interdisciplinary Comics
                Studies.</title>
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000101</idno>
            <idno type="volume">005</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <date when="2011-05-02">2 May 2011</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
          <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
          <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Alyssa" when="2011-03-02">encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>Existing scholarship on interactive fiction (IF, also known as the text adventure) tends
          to treat it as a video game genre and/or as a category of electronic literature. In this
          essay I argue that IF can be understood as participating in traditions of visual prose and
          ekphrastic textuality, insofar as IF consists of room and object descriptions which direct
          the player to visualize the things they describe. Unlike traditional ekphrastic
          literature, however, IF also asks the player to take practical actions in response to the
          images he or she visualizes. During the commercial era of IF, ekphrasis was the most
          effective means available of providing players with immersive visual experiences. However,
          graphical video games have now surpassed IF in this area. Therefore, in order to justify
          the continued existence of IF, contemporary IF authors have been forced to conceive of the
          visuality of IF otherwise than in terms of the logic of transparency. One strategy for
          doing this, exemplified by Nick Montfort's game, <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title>,
          is to abandon visuality almost entirely and emphasize IF's linguistic and textual
          qualities. An alternative strategy, exemplified by Emily Short's game <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title>, is to assert that IF is visual in a non-transparent way,
          because IF offers visual experiences which are user-generated rather than pre-rendered.
        </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Can text-based video games be visual experiences?</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Because It's Not There: Ekphrasis and the Threat of Graphics in Interactive
          Fiction</head>
            <p>The genre of interactive fiction has enjoyed increasing critical attention over the past
          few years, particularly since the publication of Nick Montfort's <title rend="italic">Twisty Little Passages: An Approach to Interactive Fiction</title>. <note>Hereafter
            abbreviated IF. The genre of IF is also known as the text adventure, although these
            terms are not precisely synonymous. The term <term>interactive fiction</term> includes
            all or nearly all works that use a text-based parser, while the term <term>text
              adventure</term> privileges gamelike works that feature <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#montfort2005">out-of-the-ordinary undertakings involving risk and danger</quote>
                     <ptr target="#montfort2005" loc="6"/>
                  </cit>. (For further discussion of the difference
            between these terms, see <ptr loc="6–8" target="#montfort2005"/>.) <term>Interactive
              fiction</term> implies a view of IF as an aesthetic object, while <term>text
              adventure</term> implies a view of IF as a gaming genre. As Jeremy Douglass argues,
            however, these perspectives are not mutually exclusive: <quote rend="inline" source="#douglass2007">IF objects
              are sometimes games that are played, and sometimes stories that are read, and often
              both or neither. Further, their narrative and rule aspects interact continuously at a
              deep level</quote>
                  <ptr target="#douglass2007" loc="15"/>. In this paper I'm going to focus on what
            Douglass broadly defines as the <quote rend="inline" source="#douglass2007">narrative</quote> aspects of IF,
            specifically including its manipulation of signifiers and its creation of imagined
            worlds, and I will give less attention to the ludic or gamelike aspects of IF. This
            makes it easier to compare IF to non-digital forms of visual textuality which are only
            minimally gamelike if at all. However, it must be understood that the aesthetic and
            gamelike qualities of IF are inseparable.</note> According to Eric Eve's definition, an
          interactive fiction is <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#eve2007">a turn-based program driven by textual
              input from the player, responding with output that is principally or wholly textual,
              and involving a parser and a world model</quote>
                  <ptr target="#eve2007" loc="para. 1"/>
               </cit>. In other words, IF is a program that (1) simulates a diegetic world containing
          various spaces and objects (the world model), (2) presents that world to the user/player
          through the medium of unillustrated or sparsely illustrated text, and (3) permits the user
          to interact with its simulated world by inputting textual commands. IF, then, is
          distinguished from other genres of video games by its lack of images, and from other forms
          of recombinatory or procedural textuality by its inclusion of a world model.</p>
            <p>Up to this point, IF has typically been examined from the viewpoint of its textual and
          programmatic aspects. For Montfort and others, IF descends from the canonical traditions
          of riddle-making and ergodic textuality and participates in the contemporary movement of
          electronic literature. According to these claims, the value of IF for scholarly study lies
          in what it tells us about textuality, literariness, and the transformations of both in the
          digital era. The existing critical discourse presents IF as a primarily
            <emph>textual</emph>, <emph>procedural</emph> and <emph>ludic</emph> phenomenon — as an
          art form or communicative medium which is composed of verbal signifiers that are subject
          to rule-based manipulations, and which has historically been used to produce
            games.<note>See, for example, <ptr loc="2" target="#montfort2005"/> (claiming that IF
              <quote rend="inline" source="#montfort2005">has been a major current in electronic literature</quote>) and
              <ptr loc="37–63" target="#montfort2005"/> (explaining how IF descends from and is
            comparable to the textual riddle). Similarly, Jeremy Douglass's dissertation on IF
            begins, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#douglass2007">Re-examining historical and contemporary IF
                illuminates the larger fields of electronic literature and game studies</quote>
                     <ptr target="#douglass2007" loc="ix"/>
                  </cit>. Douglass further suggests that the two
            primary critical perspectives on IF are electronic literature and games studies <ptr target="#douglass2007" loc="14"/>. </note> With rare exceptions, critics have
          neglected the visuality of IF. In this paper I will explain the necessity of rectifying
          this neglect, and take tentative steps toward doing so.</p>
            <p>The distinction between the textual and the visual, or between the verbal and the visual
          signifier, is impossible to define precisely, because, as W.J.T. Mitchell argues, such
          distinctions are always already political: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#mitchell1990">Every theoretical
              answer to the questions, What is an image? How are images different from words? seemed
              inevitably to fall back into prior questions of value and interest that could only be
              answered in historical terms</quote>
                  <ptr loc="3" target="#mitchell1990"/>
               </cit>. For the narrow purposes of the present
          analysis, we might define a textual signifier as a sign whose visual appearance is not
          directly linked to its signifying value. For example, the visual appearance of the letter
          P can vary, to a certain predetermined extent, without altering its semantic value.
          Similarly, a novel can be set in a variety of typefaces while still being understood as
          the <soCalled>same</soCalled> text, and a computer program will carry out the same
          processes regardless of the font in which it is written. A visual signifier or image, by
          contrast, is one whose semantic or affective value is linked directly to its specific
          visual appearance, including its material embodiment and/or its phenomenological effect on
          the viewer. I will use the term <term>image</term> to refer interchangeably to
            <soCalled>real</soCalled> images and mental visualizations. While <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#mitchell1990">pictorial images are inevitably conventional and contaminated by
              language</quote>
                  <ptr target="#mitchell1990" loc="42"/>
               </cit>, the image at least tries to claim that its
            <term>meaning</term> is contingent on its physical appearance. <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#mitchell1990">The
            image is the sign that pretends not to be a sign, masquerading as (or for the believer,
            actually achieving) natural immediacy and presence</quote>
               <ptr loc="43" target="#mitchell1990"/></cit>. Obviously, this word-image distinction is as
          problematic and open to critique as any such distinction; see, for example, <ptr target="#drucker2002" loc="154–160"/> for an argument that something <emph>is</emph>
          indeed lost when the materiality of a letter is altered. I claim merely that this
          distinction represents a commonsensical understanding of what distinguishes words from
          images. It reflects the way in which IF critics typically understand these terms when they
          don't interrogate them further.</p>
            <p>Critics have typically paid little attention to the visuality of IF — which includes both
          its use of actual visible signs, and the visual images it may evoke in the player's mind.
          This may seem hardly surprising since, by the second element of the above definition, IF
          consists mostly or entirely of textual signifiers and makes limited use of images. In the
          present paper, however, I will suggest that interacting with IF is in fact a visual
          experience in crucially important ways, and that IF therefore has important things to
          teach us about the fate of the visual aspects of verbal signifiers in the digital era.</p>
            <p>Without denying that IF participates in various traditions of potential literature and
          ludic textuality, as Montfort and others suggest, I here want to suggest that IF is also
          an heir to equally longstanding traditions of ekphrasis and of visual prose. As such, IF
          poses questions of the relation between descriptive text and readerly visualization that
          go back as far as Homer's description of the shield of Achilles — though by virtue of its
          ergodic nature, IF also significantly transforms those questions. By viewing IF as a
          visual-textual phenomenon, we can improve our understanding of the transformation of
          visual prose and readerly visuality in the digital era.</p>
            <p>Moreover, a focus on the visuality of IF can improve our understanding of how the genre
          defines itself. A recurring concern of ekphrastic poetry is the definition of the relation
          of poetry to painting and, more recently, to still photography and film. As Mitchell
          argues, ekphrasis is the genre in which text (in the narrow sense given above) confronts
          its other: <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#mitchell1994">Ekphrastic poetry is the genre in which texts encounter
            their own semiotic <soCalled>others,</soCalled> those rival, alien modes of
            representation called the visual, graphic, plastic, or <soCalled>spatial</soCalled>
            arts</quote>
               <ptr target="#mitchell1994" loc="para. 9"/></cit> This argument expands on James Heffernan's
          reading of ekphrasis as paragonal — that is, as enacting a competitive struggle between
          word and image. Elizabeth Bergmann Loizeaux suggests, by contrast, that ekphrasis may also
          be motivated by <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#loizeaux2008">such modest, and profound, feelings as
              companionship or friendship, the terms in which poets often describe their ekphrastic
              motives</quote>
                  <ptr target="#loizeaux2008" loc="15"/>
               </cit>. Under either model, however, a central
          drive behind ekphrasis is the desire to define poetry or <soCalled>textual</soCalled> art
          itself by contrast to its other. By directly addressing the image, poetry makes claims for
          what it can do that the image can't, and/or asks how it can do what images seem capable of
          doing more effectively.</p>
            <p>This task becomes especially pressing in the present cultural moment. Ekphrastic
          literature has perhaps always been both fascinated and repelled by the apparently superior
          mimetic power of images to text. As Murray Krieger argues, ekphrasis entails <quote rend="inline" source="#krieger1992">the defensive concession that language, as arbitrary and with a sensuous
            lack, is a disadvantaged medium in need of emulating the natural and sensible medium of
            the plastic arts,</quote> which exists in an ambivalent relation to <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#krieger1992">the prideful confidence in language as a medium privileged by its very
              intelligibility</quote>
                  <ptr loc="12" target="#krieger1992"/>
               </cit>. However, the more images advance in both
          ubiquity and mimetic power, the more unequal the terms of this relation become. Loizeaux
          observes that twentieth-century poets' interest in ekphrasis arises from ambivalent
          reactions to the growing cultural importance of the image: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#loizeaux2008">The
              widespread presence of ekphrasis in twentieth-century poetry can be understood as both
              a response to and a participant in what W.J.T. Mitchell has called “the pictorial
              turn” from a culture of words into a culture of images that began in the late
              nineteenth century with the advent of photography and then film, and has accelerated
              since the mid twentieth century with the invention of television and, now, digital
              media. Excited — and haunted — by a sense of images' increasing power in western
              culture, poets have taken up ekphrasis as a way of engaging and understanding their
              allure and force.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#loizeaux2008" loc="3–4"/>
               </cit> At the same time that images have attained
          unprecedented cultural power, poetry has now <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#loizeaux2008">further lost
              popular readership and its significant social role</quote>
                  <ptr target="#loizeaux2008" loc="6"/>
               </cit>. Explicit confrontation with the image now
          becomes a way of justifying he continued appeal, if not the very existence, of poetry
          itself.</p>
            <p>Similarly, IF authors and critics feel a need to distinguish IF from graphical video
          games in order to explain why IF should continue to exist today, despite its apparent
          commercial and technological inferiority to graphical video games. Graphics both threaten
          and fascinate IF authors in much the same way that paintings both threaten and fascinate
          poets. IF authors and critics feel a need to distinguish IF from graphical video games in
          order to explain why IF should continue to exist today, despite its apparent commercial
          and technological inferiority to graphical video games.</p>
            <p>As an example of the study of IF from a visual perspective, in this essay I offer
          readings of two recent works of IF that represent opposing conceptions of the genre's
          visual aspects. My first text, Nick Montfort's <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title>
          (2000), goes further than perhaps any other work of IF in stressing the genre's textual
          properties at the expense of its visual properties. In calling attention to the textual
          nature of the IF interface and of the player's input, <title rend="italic">Ad
            Verbum</title> defines itself as a purely verbal artifact. My second text, Emily Short's
            <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title> (2003), seeks instead to accentuate its own
          visuality by providing evocative descriptions accompanied by abstract imagery. Yet the
          mode of visuality that this game proposes is affective, evocative and phantasmal, rather
          than vivid and immediately present. This game proposes that IF can be a visual experience,
          but that its visuality differs in significant ways from that of the graphical video game.
          Though these games approach visuality in very different ways, a central question for both
          games is whether and how the visual properties of text can compete with those of more
          mimetic forms of imagery. This, I would argue, is as crucial a question for interactive
          fiction as it is for ekphrastic poetry, because it touches upon the larger question of
          what happens to less explicitly transparent forms of visuality and textuality at a time
          when transparent forms of visuality seem to have attained a position of cultural
          dominance. As I will argue, IF, like ekphrastic poetry, offers visual experiences which
          are indirect, phantasmal, and dependent on the player's imagination. How can such visual
          experiences compete with the transparent visual experiences offered by media like computer
          games and CG film? Do we still want or need such visual experiences, and if so,
            why?<note>The unstated assumption behind these questions is that computer graphical
            media, like video games and CG animated films, <emph>do</emph> in fact offer visual
            experiences which are transparent rather than phantasmal or indirect. Although this
            assumption is commonly made by authors like Dibbell, it is in fact just as questionable
            as the assumption that IF doesn't offer any visual experiences. I even believe that
            phantasmal and indirect visuality is commonly found in CG films and video games,
            although this claim is beyond the scope of this essay. I would suggest, however, that
            for IF authors and critics, it's strategically useful to mischaracterize computer
            graphics as primarily focused on transparent visuality. Such a mischaracterization leads
            to a stark divide between the visuality (or lack thereof) of IF and that of video games,
            which makes it possible to carve out an exclusive niche for IF.</note> The two games
          I'll be discussing represent two possible answers to these pressing questions.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Toward a Theory of IF Visuality</head>
            <p>For most IF critics, IF is a verbal, textual and literary medium whose closest affinities
          are with the tradition of ergodic textuality that extends from the <title rend="italic">I
            Ching</title> and the Exeter Book, through the Oulipo and Cortázar, to hypertext
          fiction. On this assumption, the visual aspects of IF, if any, are usually ignored. Espen
          Aarseth, for example, treats IF as <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth1997">a new type of literary
              artifact</quote>
                  <ptr loc="107" target="#aarseth1997"/>
               </cit>. His reading of the Infocom game <title rend="italic">Deadline</title> considers only its literary and ludological aspects.
          Montfort, the leading authority on the genre, has equally little to say about its visual
          qualities. According to the historical narrative he provides, the antecedents of IF are
          textual genres, including riddles and Oulipian potential literature <ptr target="#montfort2005" loc="37, 65"/>. The major exception to this neglect of IF’s
          visuality is Dennis Jerz’s article <title rend="quotes">Somewhere Nearby is Colossal
            Cave,</title> which compares the geography of Will Crowther and Don Woods’s <title rend="italic">Colossal Cave</title> (or <title rend="italic">Adventure</title>), usually
          considered the first work of interactive fiction, to the geography of the real cave on
          which the game was based. In a photo-essay, Jerz juxtaposes Crowther's room descriptions
          with photographs of the real-world locations on which those descriptions are based.
          However, Jerz's stated goal here is to <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#jerz2007">establish that Crowther's
              original was not only faithful to the geography of the real Colossal Cave, but was
              also a fantasy remediation of that site</quote>
                  <ptr target="#jerz2007" loc="para. 2"/>
               </cit>. The question that interests Jerz is the
          extent to which the simulated cave faithfully reflects the real one. What he leaves
          unexamined is the general question of whether the exploration of such simulated spaces can
          be a spatial and visual experience.</p>
            <p>This critical neglect of the visuality of IF seems unsurprising, given that one might
          have difficulty identifying any visual aspects of the genre. What could be the importance
          of visuality in a medium which, by definition, includes few or no visual images and relies
          primarily on text? If we distinguish visual and textual signifiers according to the
          definitions given above, the signifiers that make up a work of IF seem to fall into the
          latter category, as their semantic value doesn't depend on their precise visible
          instantiation. Contemporary IF interpreters give the player the option of altering details
          such as the font, text color and background color, without altering either the precise
          text that the program generates, or the code that generates it.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure01">
               <head>A scene from <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title>. Reproduced by
                  permission.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="figure02">
               <head>The <q>same</q> scene from <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title>
                  with a different font, font color and background color. Reproduced by
                  permission.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>According to a common-sense understanding, the IF work <emph>is</emph> the source code,
          or perhaps the string of signifiers produced in the execution of that code, but not the
          material instantiation of that code. Two players who play the same version of <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title> using the two sets of interface options shown in figures
          1 and 2 are playing the <soCalled>same</soCalled> game; the differences in font and color
          are purely cosmetic. This is analogous to the commonsensical assumption that the identity
          of a literary text resides in the text — the ordered array of signifiers — and that the
          material instantiation of those signifiers is merely a cosmetic feature.<note>Obviously
            this is a naïve assumption which has long since been called into question by textual
            critics. See, for example, McGann's demonstration of the importance of <quote rend="inline" source="#mcgann1991">bibliographic codes</quote> to the interpretation of texts <ptr target="#mcgann1991"/>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Yet I argue, counterintuitively, that IF may be viewed as a visual and visual-verbal
          genre. In the first place, and even before we consider the visual aspects of the IF
          interface itself, a central element of nearly all works of IF is the ancient rhetorical
          trope of ekphrasis. In ekphrasis, an absent object is described in terms which permit the
          reader or listener to visualize that object, to “see” it in the mind's eye as if it were
          physically present.</p>
            <p>From the reader's perspective, the principal textual components of IF are room
          descriptions and object descriptions. The basic purpose of both these types of texts is
          designed to enable the player to visualize the phenomena described by the text. As Eric
          Eve explains, in IF, <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#eve2007">the physical world is generally modelled as
              a series of discrete locations known as <term>rooms</term>. The totality of rooms in a
              given work of IF is often referred to as the <term>map</term>. Such rooms could
              correspond to rooms in a building, but they need not and frequently do not[...].
              Conceptually, a room is that segment of physical space that is immediately accessible
              to the player character.</quote>
                  <dhq:citRef>
                     <ptr target="#eve2007" loc="para. 7"/>
              (emphasis in original)</dhq:citRef>
               </cit> In other words, the typical arrangement of
          space in IF is that the gameworld is divided or segmented into several discrete, mutually
          exclusive chunks. Such a spatial arrangement is not unique to IF. The fifth item of Mark
          J.P. Wolf's taxonomy of video game spatial structures is <quote rend="inline" source="#wolf2002">adjacent
            spaces displayed one at a time</quote>
               <ptr loc="59" target="#wolf2002"/>.<note>This spatial arrangement is the sixth item in
            Wolf's taxonomy of spatial structures in video games. It is essentially the same spatial
            arrangement we find in graphical adventure games like <title rend="italic">Myst</title>
            or in the LucasArts games developed using the SCUMM engine, except that in such games
            the individual chunks of space are represented in three dimensions, not two. As Wolf
            observes, this spatial structure is similar to the continuity editing style in film.
              <quote rend="inline" source="#wolf2002">Adjacent spaces displayed one at a time</quote> is also the
            characteristic spatial arrangement of comics and graphic novels.</note> In graphical
          video games dating back to the late 1970s, such as <title rend="italic">Superman</title>
          and <title rend="italic">Berserk</title>, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#wolf2002">adjacent spaces or
              rooms are displayed as a series of nonoverlapping static screens which cut directly
              one to the next without scrolling</quote>
                  <ptr loc="59" target="#wolf2002"/>
               </cit>. However, in a text adventure game, by
          definition, these chunks of space cannot be represented by onscreen images.<note>Some IF
            games, such as the late Infocom game <title rend="italic">Arthur: The Quest for
              Excalibur</title> (1989), do employ graphical depictions of rooms and objects.
            Usually, however, these depictions serve merely to illustrate the text, and the player
            needn't refer to them in order to complete the game. For example, <title rend="italic">Arthur</title> gives the player the option of turning off the graphics. Roberta and
            Ken Williams's <title rend="italic">Mystery House</title> (1983) was revolutionary
            because it included vector graphics alongside its textual room descriptions, and these
            graphics included essential information not given in the text. </note> Instead, a block
          of onscreen text — the <soCalled>room description</soCalled> — is used to make the player
          aware of the relevant properties of the present room, including the exits from that room
          and the objects it contains. The room description might be said to take the place of the
          absent graphical image of the room, although this formulation is anachronistic insofar as
          IF predates graphical adventure games. Furthermore, the image of the room is not
            <soCalled>absent</soCalled> in the sense of having been removed or abstracted, inasmuch
          as it never existed to begin with.</p>
            <p>Consider, for example, the following room description from <title rend="italic">Zork I:
            The Great Underground Empire</title>: <cit><quote rend="block" source="#blank1980">
                  <p>You are in the living room. There is a
              doorway to the east, a wooden door with strange gothic lettering to the west, which
              appears to be nailed shut, a trophy case, and a large oriental rug in the center of
              the room.</p>
                  <p>Above the trophy case hangs an elvish sword of great antiquity.</p>
                  <p>A battery-powered brass lantern is on the trophy case.</p>
               </quote><ptr target="#blank1980"/></cit> This text names
          the room and enumerates all the visible exits from the room (the doorway and the wooden
          door) and the visible objects in it (the door again, the trophy case, the rug, the sword
          and the lantern). These objects are all <soCalled>implemented.</soCalled> That is, they
          are defined in the game’s source code as objects that have certain properties, one of
          which is that the avatar may be able to interact with them. The description mentions no
          objects that aren’t implemented (although room descriptions often do mention such
          objects), and it does not fail to mention any visible objects that are implemented.</p>
            <p>The qualifier <q>visible</q> is necessary because there's a trap
          door under the rug. This object is left unmentioned because on first entering the room,
          the avatar can't see it. Finding the trap door (by moving the rug) is a puzzle. The player
          may well know about the trap door before moving the rug, perhaps from having played the
          game before, but such knowledge does not extend to the avatar. If the player inputs a
          command referring to the trap door before moving the rug, the game responds, <q>You can’t see any trap door here!</q> In this case the player may be
          able to visualize the trap door under the rug, and perhaps the avatar can even imagine
          that there's a trap door there, if we imagine the avatar as being capable of having
          cognitive operations that the player doesn't share. However, the avatar still can't
            <emph>see</emph> the trap door in the sense that it is not physically within his or her
          visual field.<note> Similarly, many games feature hidden exits or switches that aren't
            mentioned in room descriptions, and can't be used, until the avatar learns about them.
            For example, in Jon Ingold's <title rend="italic">The Mulldoon Legacy</title>, the
            avatar can open a secret passage by feeling a certain wall. However, this action only
            works if the avatar has already learned, from information given elsewhere in the game,
            that there is a secret passage behind the wall. If the player tries to feel the wall
            before the avatar has received this information, then the parser replies <quote rend="inline" source="#ingold2000">Playing a restored game, are we?</quote> thereby criticizing the player
            for breaking the fourth wall. See <ptr target="#ingold2000"/>.</note> Thus the room
          description represents what the avatar, not the player, sees when he or she looks around
          the room. It is a translation of the avatar's direct visual experience into words. The
          player then has the opportunity to back-translate those words by activating the faculty of
          readerly visuality — by forming an imaginary visualization of the things the avatar
            <emph>sees</emph>.</p>
            <p>The primacy of <emph>seeing</emph> in IF is indicated by the ubiquitous presence of light
          sources in <title rend="italic">Adventure</title> and games descended from it. Exploration
          can't take place in the absence of light, and light source conservation and transport are
          common puzzle themes. As Jeremy Douglass observes, this made sense in <title rend="italic">Adventure</title>
               <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#douglass2007">as it is highly dangerous to wander around cave systems in the
              dark</quote>
                  <ptr target="#douglass2007" loc="132"/>
               </cit>, but the need for light sources
          subsequently became divorced from its original context and evolved into a generic
          convention. Games like Taro Ogawa's <title rend="italic">Enlightenment</title> (1998),
          where the player's goal is to extinguish all the light sources in a room, or Andrew
          Plotkin's <title rend="italic">Hunter, in Darkness</title> (1999), where exploration takes
          place via senses other than sight, are deliberate reactions against this primacy of sight
            <ptr target="#douglass2007" loc="134"/>. The default assumption in IF is that the avatar
          experiences the gameworld through the visual faculty, and that the text presents the
          avatar's visual experience to the player.</p>
            <p>As translations of visual objects in the medium of language, IF room descriptions (and
          object descriptions, of which room descriptions are special cases) are examples of
          ekphrasis. In current critical discourse ekphrasis is most often defined as the verbal
          description of a visual work of art, but Janice Hewlett Koelb argues that this meaning of
          the term is a twentieth-century invention, dating back no earlier than Leo Spitzer’s 1955
          essay on Keats's <title rend="quotes">Ode on a Grecian Urn</title>
               <ptr loc="2" target="#koelb2006"/>. Ancient rhetoricians defined ekphrasis as <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#koelb2006">[a] speech which leads one around (<term>
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">periegematikos</foreign>
                     </term>) bringing the subject matter vividly
                  (<term>
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">enargos</foreign>
                     </term>) before the
              eyes</quote>
                  <ptr target="#koelb2006" loc="23"/>
               </cit>, whatever that subject
          matter might be. IF games like <title rend="italic">Zork</title> certainly meet this
          definition. The degree of vividness (or <term>
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">enargeia</foreign>
               </term>) with which the subject matter is <quote rend="inline" source="#koelb2006">brought before the eyes</quote> is a factor that varies between different games, and
          also between different players, since players might mentally visualize the gameworld more
          or less visually depending on how visually inclined they happen to be. On an anecdotal
          level, I tend to visualize extensively when I play IF games, but I know other IF players
          who claim that they don't do so, and that they understand room descriptions in a
          conceptual or propositional way. However, I suggest that IF games must supply the
            <emph>potential</emph> for visualization in order to provide a meaningful play
            experience.<note>According to game designers Katie Salen and Eric Zimmerman,
              <term>meaningful play</term> is the criterion by which the success of game design is
            measured. They define it as <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#salen2003">the process by which a player
                takes action within the designed system of a game and the system responds to the
                action. The meaning of an action in a game resides in the relationship between
                action and outcome</quote>
                     <ptr target="#salen2003"/>
                  </cit>.</note> What we might call
            <term>visualizability</term> is a basic requirement for traversing most if not all
          interactive fictions, especially those that include multiple rooms or rooms with multiple
          objects in physical contact with each other. In order to productively interact with the
          gameworld, the player must possess at least a minimal understanding of the spatial
          relationships between the objects in each room and between the rooms themselves. This
          requires constructing a mental (or actual) map, which is, to a substantial degree, a
          visual operation. As Eve observes, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#eve2007">[t]he totality of rooms in a
              given work of IF is often referred to as the <emph>map</emph> 
                  </quote> 
                  <dhq:citRef>emphasis in original <ptr loc="para. 7" target="#eve2007"/>
                  </dhq:citRef>
               </cit> and this is <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#eve2007">probably because someone
              designing a work of IF containing more than a handful of rooms almost certainly needs
              to draw a map indicating their spatial relations before attempting to write the game,
              and players often find it useful to draw schematic maps as they play</quote>
                  <ptr target="#eve2007" loc="fn5"/>
               </cit>.</p>
            <p>When visualizability breaks down — that is, when room and object descriptions fail to
          accurately represent what the avatar can see — meaningful play and the ability to traverse
          the game successfully may be impeded.<note>I want to carefully distinguish here between
              <term>visualizability</term> and <term>visualization</term>. Visualizability is a
            property of the IF text. Visualization is a faculty of the player, which represents one
            of several possible modes of realizing visualizable information. It's possible that
            players might understand a visualizable text in a nonvisual way. For example, IF is
            popular among blind computer users, who are obviously unable to visualize the things the
            text mentions. I conjecture that such players might process the visual information in
            the text in a haptic or tactile way.</note> This may happen, for example, when an object
          mentioned in a room description is not implemented. By convention, if the player tries to
          interact with such an object, the game responds that the object is not important.
          Sometimes, however, the game fails to acknowledge the object’s existence and instead
          outputs a standard response to commands that reference nonexistent objects, such as <q>You can’t see any such thing</q> or <q>I don’t see
            that here.</q> This behavior is generally considered a design flaw or even a bug, as
          Eve explains: <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#eve2007">It looks very clumsy if, having told the player that
            the room is decorated with striped wallpaper, the game responds with <q>You see no such
              thing</q> when the player tries to examine it</quote>
               <ptr target="#eve2007" loc="para. 15"/></cit>.<note>Eve probably chose to use wallpaper as an
            example because of Andrew Plotkin’s game <title rend="italic">Delightful
              Wallpaper</title>, in which the avatar is an incorporeal ghost, and is thus unable to
            interact with the titular wallpaper or with any other object. Nonetheless, Plotkin
            includes many implemented objects in the game and goes to the trouble of including
            descriptions for all these objects. According to one reviewer, it was precisely these
            descriptions that made Plotkin's game more than a mere puzzlefest <ptr target="#bond2006"/>.</note> Such behavior creates a gap between the visual experience
          of the avatar and the verbal experience of the player. Somehow, the player can read about
          things the avatar can’t see, and this destroys the illusion that the room description
          represents the avatar’s visual experience.</p>
            <p>An opposite but perhaps more egregious breach of visualizability occurs when the text
          fails to mention objects that are implemented and that the avatar should be able to see.
          For example, in Dave Baggett and Carl de Marcken's 1994 game <title rend="italic">+=3</title>, the avatar must give three objects to a troll as a toll to cross a bridge.
          The INVENTORY command reveals that the avatar is holding just one object, and the game's
          single room contains no other objects that can be acquired. The solution is to take off
          the avatar’s shirt, shoes, pants, socks, glasses and/or underwear, thereby supplying the
          missing two items. This solution, though perfectly logical, is cruelly unfair because none
          of these articles of clothing are referred to anywhere in the game.<note>In fact, this
            game was created specifically to prove that a puzzle could be simple and logical without
            being fair. During a debate on the rec.arts.int-fiction newsgroup, Baggett asserted that
            such a puzzle was possible, and created <title rend="italic">+=3</title> to demonstrate
            this point.</note> In particular, they aren't mentioned in the responses to the commands
          INVENTORY and EXAMINE ME. According to conventions which were well established by 1994,
          experienced players would thus conclude that the avatar was wearing nothing important,
          because on looking at himself or herself, the avatar sees nothing worth mentioning. The
          player would assume that the avatar is wearing clothes (otherwise the avatar's nudity
          would be mentioned), but that the clothes have no relevance to gameplay. Objects left
          unmentioned are assumed to be below the avatar’s perceptual threshold, and thus either
          nonexistent, or irrelevant to the task of traversing the game. The underlying assumption
          here is that everything the avatar sees will be translated into descriptive text. In
          violating this assumption, <title rend="italic">+=3</title> precludes meaningful play.</p>
            <p>Thus, IF is an ekphrastic medium because it consists of texts which describe visual
          phenomena and which prompt the reader to create imaginary visualizations of those
          phemonena. However, IF difers from other ergodic media by virtue of being
            <term>prescriptive</term> rather than <term>autotelic</term>. The reading of a static
          ekphrastic text, like Diderot's <title rend="italic">Salons</title> or Ruskin's
          word-paintings, is a self-contained experience.<note>These are two of the texts Alexandra
            Wettlaufer discusses in <title rend="italic">In the Mind's Eye: The Visual Impulse in
              Diderot, Baudelaire and Ruskin</title>. She cites them as examples of the <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#wettlaufer2003">
                        <soCalled>visual impulse</soCalled>, that is, the desire to render the
                act of reading a visual experience</quote>
                     <ptr target="#wettlaufer2003" loc="21"/>
                  </cit>.</note> These texts describe absent
          visual phenomena in such a way as to permit the viewer to visualize them, but they do not
          prompt the reader to take any action in response to these visualizations. The experience
          of imagining what the text describes is its own reward. By contrast, when an IF player
          reads a room or object description, he or she is expected to take an action in response
          (i.e. to do work, hence the term <term>ergodic</term>). The player is prompted to give
          commands to the avatar based on the visual and other information in the description.</p>
            <p>My argument, thus, is that ekphrasis is the characteristic mode of visual representation
          in IF. During the commercial era of IF (approximately coinciding with the lifespan of
          Infocom, from 1979 to 1989), ekphrasis, as a means of visual rendering, had certain
          comparative advantages over graphics. Graphical video games predate <title rend="italic">Colossal Cave</title> by at least 15 years, but these games ran on mainframes or
          dedicated arcade machines. The creation of sophisticated graphics was beyond the
          technological capabilities of contemporary home computers. Displaying text was much less
          labor-intensive. For example, the first commercially successful personal computer was the
          Osborne 1, released in 1981. This computer had a monochrome screen which was incapable of
          displaying bitmap graphics <ptr target="#wikipedia2009"/>. On such a platform, a visual
          depiction of a building with keys, a brass lamp, food and water on the ground would have
          been out of the question. Text made it possible to <soCalled>show</soCalled> visual
          phenomena that could not have been depicted with the graphic resources available.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure03">
               <head>
                  <title rend="italic">Adventure</title> running on an Osborne 1.
                  Originally uploaded by Cetcom. Licensed under the GNU Free Documentation
                  License.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>Furthermore, text was far more cross-platform than graphics. Infocom games were designed
          for the Z-Machine, a <quote rend="inline" source="#montfort2005">software computer [which] could be implemented
            on many different platforms, including almost all of the popular microcomputers in the
            United States during the 1980s</quote> including business machines as well as dedicated
          gaming machines <ptr target="#montfort2005" loc="126"/>. Since all of these computers were
          capable of displaying text, all the Infocom games could be ported to any platform at once
          simply by writing a new implementor for that platform. The use of graphics, by contrast,
          would have made such cross-platform availability an insurmountable obstacle.<note>The most
            sophisticated treatment of the text-rendering capabilities of early video game platforms
            is <ptr target="#whalen2008"/>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For these and other reasons, the use of ekphrasis rather than graphics made the
          commercial success of IF possible. According to the standard view of the genre’s history,
          however, IF's reliance on text was also the cause of its commercial decline.<note>IF still
            remains significantly more cross-platform than most graphical video games, however, and
            this factor makes IF one of the easiest video game genres to teach.</note> Over the
          course of the 1980s, as the graphical capabilities of home computers advanced, the new
          genre of the graphical adventure gradually rendered IF obsolete.<note>See <ptr target="#montfort2005"/> for a detailed account of the history of IF. Douglass
            critiques Montfort's historical account by arguing that the commercial era was in fact
            an anomalous exception to the norm of independent development of IF.</note> According
          to Espen Aarseth, this was a natural succession because graphics, compared to ekphrasis,
          are a naturally superior mode of visuality: <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth1997">Images, especially moving
            images, are more powerful representations of spatial relations than texts, and therefore
            this migration from text to graphics is natural and inevitable</quote>
               <ptr loc="102" target="#aarseth1997"/></cit>.<note>See also Mark J.P. Wolf's observation, that
                <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#wolf1997">[p]art of the reason for the use of all text, at least
                initially, was the difficulty of doing graphics</quote>
                     <ptr target="#wolf1997" loc="13"/>
                  </cit>.</note> By Aarseth's logic, the purpose of a
          game is to serve as a transparent window into an imagined space. According to what Bolter
          and Grusin call the logic of transparency <ptr target="#bolter2003"/>, the game seeks to
          erase its own materiality and present the player with a vivid, sensuously present
          experience of existence in another world. For this purpose to be fulfilled, the gameworld
          must be presented with maximum visual richness. Clearly games that translate the avatar's
          visual experience into text do all these things less effectively than games that display
          the avatar's visual experience onscreen.</p>
            <p>The assumption here is that video game history follows a teleological progression from
          lesser to greater transparency. IF becomes commercially unviable because it represents an
          earlier stage in this progression. For some authors, this is only natural: the fact that
          computer graphics have outstripped the capacities of IF is cause for celebration. An
          example of such a view is Julian Dibbell's dismissive description of <title rend="italic">Adventure</title> as an inferior precursor to <title rend="italic">Myst</title>:
              <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#dibbell2001">It's hard to believe that that world once represented the
              high frontier of computer gaming. Where players of latter-day quests like <title rend="italic">Myst</title> point-and-click their way through complex graphical
              environments of an almost liquid radiance […] <title rend="italic">Adventure</title>
              was strictly hunt and peck</quote>
                  <ptr target="#dibbell2001"/>
               </cit>. Other authors characterize the gaming industry's
          ideology of transparency as unfortunate, and describe IF nostalgically as having been
          sacrificed on the altar of progress. Aarseth regrets that the text adventure game, a
              <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth1997">young, vigorous, if somewhat bland tradition of textual
              entertainment [...] was quickly overrun by the entertainment market</quote>
                  <ptr target="#aarseth1997" loc="128"/>
               </cit>. More recently, Andy Klien began a 2005
          article on IF by writing, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#douglass2007">Only once in my life have I seen a
              wonderful medium effectively wiped out by new technology</quote>
                  <dhq:citRef>qtd. in
                <ptr target="#douglass2007" loc="21–22"/>
                  </dhq:citRef>
               </cit>.</p>
            <p>Yet interactive fiction still exists today, when the graphical capabilities of personal
          computers are far more sophisticated than at the time of IF's commercial collapse. New IF
          games are now produced by independent hobbyists and artists rather than by commercial
          firms. However, for contemporary IF authors graphics represent an elephant in the room, a
          topic that may not be directly discussed but that can't be ignored. Authors of IF in the
          post-graphical era cannot avoid the question of why they should bother, since graphics are
          now better than IF text at doing what IF text does, for which reason IF will probably
          never again be a commercially viable medium. By way of answering this question, IF authors
          and critics have sought to claim for IF another type of legitimacy, emphasizing its
          aesthetic and scholarly appeal rather than its commercial appeal. If IF can't be a popular
          and commercial medium, it can be an auterist and artistic medium. But in order to prove
          the aesthetic legitimacy of IF, it becomes necessary to show that IF is an independent
          medium from the graphical video game because IF text has properties that graphics
          lack.</p>
            <p>Where contemporary IF authors and critics differ is in their conception of the precise
          nature of these distinctive properties of IF. Within contemporary IF work we can
          distinguish two very different approaches to defining the specificity of the genre. The
          first approach is to argue that IF is a linguistic and anti-visual medium.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>
               <emph>Ad Verbum</emph>: Interactive Fiction and Representational Friction</head>
            <p>One way in which IF responds to the seemingly superior representational capabilities of
          text is by ignoring ekphrasis almost entirely and foregrounding the textual and verbal
          qualities of the IF interface. The paradigmatic example of this approach is Nick
          Montfort's 2000 game <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title>.</p>
            <p>The player's goal in this game is to remove all the objects from a house belonging to the
          Wizard of Wordplay. Nearly all of the game’s puzzles must be solved by entering commands
          according to various linguistic constraints. Exploiting Bolter and Grusin's logic of
          hypermediacy, this game forcibly reminds the player of its nature as a text-based computer
          program, rather than a window into a simulated world. This is evident immediately in the
          introductory text of the game: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#montfort2000">
                     <p>With the cantankerous Wizard of
                Wordplay evicted from his mansion, the worthless plot can now be redeveloped. The
                city regulations declare, however, that the rip-down job can't proceed until all the
                items within have been removed.</p>
                     <p>That's what the demolition contractor explains to you, anyway, as you stand eagerly
                on the adventurer's day labor corner. Once he learns of your penchant for
                puzzle-solving and your kleptomaniacal tendencies, he hires you for the job. You hop
                into the bed of his truck, type a few Zs, and arrive at the site, eager
              …</p>
                  </quote>
                  <ptr target="#montfort2000"/>
               </cit>
               <title rend="quotes">Z</title> is the standard abbreviation for the
            <soCalled>wait</soCalled> command, so the last sentence erases the boundaries between
          player and avatar, between typing commands and performing actions. Throughout the game the
          player is consistently reminded that he or she is not exploring a diegetic world, but
          typing commands in response to verbal descriptions. Some of <title rend="italic">Ad
            Verbum</title>'s puzzles in fact involve no interaction with objects or spaces, only
          manipulation of language. For example, on the first floor of the mansion, the player
          encounters a little boy, Georgie, who refuses to give up his toy dinosaur unless the
          player can name more dinosaurs than Georgie can. Georgie knows an arbitrarily large number
          of real dinosaur names, so the solution is to input fake dinosaur names — i.e. nonsense
          words ending in <soCalled>saur</soCalled> or <soCalled>saurus</soCalled> — until Georgie
          gets frustrated and gives up. Since all the player has to do to solve this puzzle is think
          of nonsense words, it doesn't matter whether or how the player visualizes the space where
          Georgie is located.</p>
            <p>Other puzzles in the game do force the avatar to interact with rooms and objects, but in
          order to make the avatar do so, the player has to satisfy certain linguistic constraints.
          Most notably, the game contains several <soCalled>constrained rooms</soCalled> where the
          output text consists entirely of words starting with a specific letter. For example, at
          the bottom of <ref target="#figure04">figure 4</ref> we see the initial room description
          of the <title rend="quotes">Wee Wardrobe.</title>
               <figure xml:id="figure04">
                  <head>Screenshot from <title rend="italic">Ad
                     Verbum</title>. Reproduced by permission.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc/>
               </figure> This same
          constraint applies to the player's input. Obvious solutions like TAKE WEAPON don't work;
          if the player enters a command containing a word that doesn't start with W, the parser
          replies, <q>Wha? Wha? Withhold wrong words. Write wholesomely.</q>
          The puzzle, therefore, is to command the avatar to take the two objects in the room and
          then leave, using only words beginning with W.<note>One solution is WIELD WEAPON, then
            WHACK WAINSCOTING WITH WEAPON (revealing a <soCalled>weird widget</soCalled>)
            then WIN WIDGET, then WITHDRAW.</note> This constraint applies even to nondiegetic
          commands like HINT, SAVE, RESTART, RESTORE and QUIT, and on first entering a constrained
          room, the player must read a warning alerting him or her to this fact.</p>
            <p>The constrained rooms call attention to the fact that the world of this game is a
          linguistic construct, a tissue of words and letters. Of course, this is true in a sense of
          the diegetic world of any IF game: the white house in <title rend="italic">Zork</title>
          doesn't exist independently of the language that describes it.<note>To this extent, room
            descriptions in IF games are what John Hollander calls <term>notional ekphrases</term>,
            i.e. ekphrastic texts describing visual phenomena that don't actually exist and can't
              <emph>be</emph> seen <ptr loc="4" target="#hollander1995"/>.</note> 
               <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title>’s innovation is to make explicit the linguistic
          nature of the IF gameworld. Since the spaces of <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title> are
          called into being by language, it's logical that these spaces can have linguistic
          properties, like the property of only containing objects that start with W. However, by
          virtue of being defined in purely verbal terms, these spaces resist translation into
          images. What would a room would look like if it contained only things beginning with S?
          The first letter of an object’s name is not a property which can be perceived by looking
          at it, especially if the object has various possible names. One can imagine a space based
          on the physical form of a letter — for example, an S room where the walls, ceiling and
          furniture have sinuous, snaky curves, or a V room full of sharp, severe triangles. But
          there is no suggestion that the constrained rooms in <title rend="italic">Ad
            Verbum</title> are organized according to the visual properties of their corresponding
          letters. These are entirely linguistic spaces, and the language of which they are composed
          is in a sense stripped of visuality. In <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title>, a letter
          is defined purely in relational terms, as a member of a set with 26 members. The question
          of the physical instantiation of letters is ignored.<note>In an unpublished essay, Edmond
            Chang asserts that <emph>Ad Verbum</emph> emphasizes the materiality of letters,
            including their physical presence. He suggests that when, for example, the player is
            prevented from using the constrained passage while carrying items, there is a sense that
            the words themselves are obstructing the player – whereas in any other IF game, the
            player would imagine that the <emph>objects</emph> the words represent were causing the
            obstruction <ptr target="#chang2004" loc="paragraph 10"/>. I would suggest, though, that
            if the words in Ad Verbum are material, they are material in a strange way. No attention
            is paid to their typographic properties or type design; we don't know, for example, what
            font is used to write the words in the game. Nor does <emph>Ad Verbum</emph> engage in
            the sort of typographic play that we find in a text like Otto Messmer's <title>Felix the
              Cat</title> cartoons, where characters can physically interact with punctuation
            marks.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If descriptions in IF are translations of what the avatar sees into words, the <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title> avatar sees things that can't <emph>be</emph> seen — for example,
          what letter an object starts with, or whether it contains the letter E. This avatar’s
          visual experience is fundamentally anti-visual. So the game frustrates the player’s
          ability to imaginatively reproduce the avatar’s visual experience. If the things the
          avatar <soCalled>sees</soCalled> are unseeable, the player can't imagine what it's like to
          see those things. This forcibly reminds the player that IF is at bottom a linguistic and
          programmatic rather than a spatial experience.</p>
            <p>Montfort thereby demonstrates that the world represented in an IF game is dissimilar to
          the material, namely language, that represents that world. This is what James Heffernan, a
          scholar of ekphrastic poetry, describes as the trope of representational friction, in
          which the ekphrastic poem calls attention to the artificiality of the artwork it describes
            <ptr target="#heffernan2004" loc="4, 18–19, 37"/>. For example, Homer's description of
          the shield of Achilles includes the statement that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#heffernan2004">the earth
              darkened behind [the ploughmen] and looked like earth that has been ploughed / though
              it was gold </quote>
                  <ptr target="#heffernan2004" loc="19"/>
               </cit>. At the same time that Homer celebrates
          the amazing power of art to reproduce reality, he reminds the reader that the work of art
          is ontologically dissimilar to the reality it reproduces. Homer celebrates <quote rend="inline" source="#heffernan2004">the wonder [...] of graphic verisimilitude</quote> specifically by telling
          the reader <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#heffernan2004">that what appears on the shield is not the ploughed
              earth itself, but gold that has been somehow made dark enough to resemble it</quote>
                  <ptr target="#heffernan2004" loc="19"/>
               </cit>. Because the shield is made of gold, not
          dirt, it can represent dirt only via artifice and convention. By analogy, because poetry
          is made of language and not images, it can represent images only through a similar
          artifice. Representational friction, thus, is a trope that foregrounds the dissimilarity
          between the descriptive poem and what it describes. It reminds the reader that the poem is
          a poem, not a painting or sculpture: that the reader is not beholding a physically present
          picture, but imagining a picture based on his or her interpretation of graphic signifers.
          Representational friction reminds the reader of the nature of the activity he or she
          performs in reading a poem. It defines the specificity of poetry as distinct from painting
          and sculpture.</p>
            <p>But of course IF players perform an activity that readers of poetry typically don't. In
          IF, the player does more than interpret signifiers; he or she also enters commands in
          response to those signifiers. These commands produce changes, often of a permanent nature,
          in the diegetic gameworld, and thereby determine what signifiers will be given for
          interpretation next. Montfort also reveals the verbal nature of the process of entering
          commands. The standard conceit is that when the player types a command, this is equivalent
          to, and can be visualized as, the avatar performing that action. When I type <q>take lantern</q> and press the enter key, I may imagine that my avatar
          reaches out his or her hand and takes the lantern. Of course, what actually happens is
          that the game program interprets the words <q>take lantern</q> as an
          action, then checks for whether the action can succeed or not in the present condition of
          gameplay. If it can succeed, the lantern is moved from its current position and added to
          the player's inventory <ptr loc="87" target="#nelson2001"/>. But when Montfort places
          constraints on the player's ability to enter commands, he reminds the player that commands
          don't actually involve interaction with objects in or attributes of a diegetic world; all
          they involve is the generation of signifiers. One puzzle requires the avatar to acquire
          four books using commands that follow the linguistic constraints used in the text of the
          books. For example, the <soCalled>dust casing</soCalled> does not accept commands that
          include the letter E, and the <soCalled>abecedarian book</soCalled> only accepts commands
          in which the first word starts with A and the second word starts with B. If the player
          tries to take these books using inappropriate commands, <q>a mysterious
            force holds the book to the … shelves.</q> Possible solutions include ACQUIRE BOOK
          and LIFT CASING.<note>These two books allude to Georges Perec's novel <title rend="italic">La Disparition</title> and Robert Pinsky's poem <title rend="italic">ABC</title>.
            Perec's book is written without the letter E. Pinsky's poem consists of 26 words, the
            first beginning with A, the second with B, and so on. Montfort's abecedarian book
            follows a similar constraint but is limited to two words, which is the most common
            length of an IF command.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the context of obtaining a book, the words TAKE, GET, ACQUIRE, and LIFT all describe
          the same action. When I pick up a book, I can use any of these verbs interchangeably to
          describe what I'm doing. But in <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title>, the <q>mysterious force</q> that governs the books will accept only some of
          these actions and not others. The force allows the avatar to rip the casing or uproot the
          copybook but not take or get them, merely because the former two actions satisfy the
          constraint and the latter two don't, even though the four actions are not semantically
          distinguishable and can all be visualized in the same way. Here Montfort is deliberately
          subjecting the player to the notorious <soCalled>guess the verb</soCalled> situation,
          where the player knows what he or she wants the avatar to do, but has difficulty finding
          the specific verb that tells the avatar to do it. When this phenomenon occurs in games,
          players typically see it a design flaw, because it violates the logic of transparency. In
          real life, if one knows what one wants to do and if one is physically capable of doing it,
          one can simply do it. In a graphical video game, the player can just press the button that
          makes the avatar take the desired action. So why should it be any different in an IF game?
          Though this is a rhetorical question, Montfort answers it by arguing that an IF game does
          not follow the procedures of real life, nor those of a graphical video game. An IF game is
          neither the real world nor a transparent representation thereof, but rather a computer
          program in which both the input and the output consist entirely of text.</p>
            <p>In <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title>, representational friction and guess-the-verb
          puzzles ultimately serve to define the specificity of IF as opposed to graphical video
          games. Since IF is clearly incapable of competing with graphical video games in terms of
          commercial appeal, Montfort seeks to claim for IF another type of legitimacy in terms of
          aesthetic or academic appeal. Montfort does this by stressing that the visual and spatial
          aspects of IF are metaphorical, not literal, because IF is a fundamentally linguistic
          medium. IF is an independent and aesthetically legitimate medium because of, not despite,
          its lack of graphics. Contemporary IF is not an atavistic throwback to the era before the
          graphical video game, but an artistic medium in its own right. By situating IF as a
          textual medium, Montfort is also able to connect it to earlier, more canonical forms of
          ludic textuality. Thus, <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title> contains explicit
          references to famous constrained texts like Walter Abish's <title rend="italic">Alphabetical Africa</title> and Georges Perec's <title rend="italic">La
            Disparition</title>. In <title rend="italic">Twisty Little Passages</title>, Montfort
          continues this project by arguing that IF has important similarities to the literary genre
          of the riddle. </p>
            <p>Montfort doesn't refute the allegation that computer graphics are more effective in some
          ways than words at representing the contents of fictional spaces. He tacitly accepts this
          critique and suggests that the true strength of IF lies elsewhere, in its ability to
          manipulate the material of language, an ability that graphical video games lack. If the
          graphical video game is a visual medium, then IF is a textual medium. Visual effects are
          the proper province of graphical games, while textual effects are specific to IF.</p>
            <p>A similar strategy is at work in many other more recent games that exploit the textual
          properties of the IF browser, although I don't know of any other game that does this to
          the same extent as <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title>. For example, Jeremy Freese's
            <title rend="italic">Violet</title>, the winner of the 2008 Interactive Fiction
          Competition, features a parser which is personified as the avatar's eponymous girlfriend.
          This effect is possible in IF because the parser is simultaneously the voice of a narrator
          and the means by which the diegetic world is presented to the player. The parser not only
          narrates the events of the gameworld, but actually produces that world for the player. In
          graphical video games, these two functions are separated. If <title rend="italic">Violet</title> were a graphical game, Violet would be no more than what André
          Gaudreault calls a delegated narrator (see <ptr target="#gaudreault2009" loc="135–146"/>).
          It would be difficult to create the illusion that Violet was actually creating the
          gameworld by speaking about it.</p>
            <p>Moreover, if IF is an independent artistic medium in its own right, rather than an
          atavistic precursor of graphical video games, then it becomes reasonable to use IF for
          purposes other than gaming. This is the idea behind the genre of puzzleless IF, which uses
          IF scripting languages but often abandons the elements of spatial exploration and
          puzzle-solving. The classic example of puzzleless IF is Adam Cadre's <title rend="italic">Photopia</title> (1998) and the genre also includes sophisticated chatbots like Emily
          Short's <title rend="italic">Galatea</title> (2000).</p>
            <p>But Montfort's strategy of stressing the linguistic and anti-visual properties of IF is
          only one way of arguing for the aesthetic legitimacy of the genre. Another approach is to
          argue that IF is in fact a visual genre, but that it possesses a type of visuality which
          is in some degree unavailable to graphical games. By coincidence, one of the key advocates
          of this approach to IF is the aforementioned Emily Short.<note>The fact that Emily Short
            can be identified with both the <q>anti-visual</q> and the <q>differently visual</q> approaches to IF is evidence that these two
            approaches are not mutually exclusive, although they may coexist somewhat
            uneasily.</note> Eve probably chose to use wallpaper as an example because of Andrew
          Plotkin’s game <title rend="italic">Delightful Wallpaper</title>, in which the avatar is
          an incorporeal ghost, and is thus unable to interact with the titular wallpaper or with
          any other object. Nonetheless, Plotkin includes many implemented objects in the game and
          goes to the trouble of including descriptions for all these objects. According to one
          reviewer, it was precisely these descriptions that made Plotkin's game more than a mere
          puzzlefest <ptr target="#bond2006"/>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Affective Ekphrasis in <emph>City of Secrets</emph>
            </head>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title> (2003) is a game about spaces. For most of
          this game the avatar's goal is simply to explore the setting of the game, known simply as
          the City, in order to find a mysterious woman named Evaine. The game's puzzles are mostly
          about overcoming barriers to further exploration, and the primary reward the player gets
          for solving these puzzles is the ability to explore previously unseen spaces. The City
          itself is inherently worth exploring because it's a tourist destination, a place of great
          historical and cultural importance. Short's innovation in <title rend="italic">City of
            Secrets</title> is to encourage the player to see this space rather than simply read
          about it. Short's descriptive language is precise and detailed, but also deliberately
          limited in terms of what it reveals. However, by deliberately limiting the visual
          information she provides, Short encourages the player to supply this information by
          exercising the faculty of readerly visuality.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure05">
               <head>Screenshot from <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title>.
                  Reproduced by permission.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>The descriptions reproduced in <ref target="#figure05">figure 5</ref> accomplish the
          primary practical tasks of an IF room description: they enumerate the exits from each room
          and the implemented objects in them, thereby making this part of the game's geography
          visualizable. However, the descriptions are in no way ultraprecise; they provide
          insufficient information to permit the player to visualize exactly what these spaces look
          like. Short neglects to describe the architectural style of the buildings or to specify
          the number of buildings or the things depicted in the statues. This omission of detail is
          a deliberate choice on Short's part, since she has also written descriptions which are
          obsessively detailed. Her 2000 game <title rend="italic">Metamorphoses</title> contains a
          number of murals which can be both examined and looked at through a magnifying glass,
          revealing additional details which can themselves be examined. Short comments, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#short2009">In writing <title rend="italic">Metamorphoses</title> I did think of
              what I was doing as specifically ekphrasis, and that’s one reason there are so many
              layers of detail within the scenery, especially the murals: I was trying to capture a
              little of the sense, found in Ovid and Catullus, that worked pictorial objects have
              astounding levels of detail</quote>
                  <ptr target="#short2009"/>
               </cit>.</p>
            <p>What happens instead in <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title> is that the omission
          of details from the text creates gaps in the player's visualization of the scene, gaps
          which the player then has the opportunity to fill. As Wolfgang Iser has argued, filling in
          gaps in a text is one of the major cognitive operations performed by readers. Iser
          characterizes this process as a propositional or linguistic one, but Peter Schwenger, a
          theorist of readerly visuality, suggests that readers perform this process with images as
          well as words. Schwenger notes that Iser <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#schwenger1999">speaks of syntheses
              below the level of consciousness, which he calls <q>passive syntheses</q>. Of such
              syntheses the basic element is the image</quote>
                  <ptr target="#schwenger1999" loc="57"/>
               </cit>. Another way to theorize this process is
          through Scott McCloud's concept of closure, the process whereby the reader of a comic
          creates mental images that fill the gaps (or gutters) between the comic's panels <ptr target="#mccloud1993" loc="66–68"/>. If the concept of closure was designed to account
          for texts that consist of sequences of images, then it applies to the IF text insofar as
          IF, as encountered by the player, involves precisely such a sequence.<note>Douglass claims
            that closure operates in IF at the level of the command line, where the player makes
                <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#douglass2007">an attempt (which may be frustrated) to discover or solve
                the gap between the current state of the simulation and its next state</quote>
                     <ptr target="#douglass2007" loc="244"/>
                  </cit>. He argues, however, that closure in
            comics is purely <term>retrospective</term> (it operates only after the second panel is
            read) whereas closure in IF is <term>prospective</term>, acting to fill a gap before the
            player knows what's on the other side of the gap. I'd suggest that retrospective closure
            is also involved in IF; it operates to connect adjacent room or object descriptions, or
            even adjacent pieces of visual information in a single room or object description.
          </note> As explained above, in playing IF the player is presented with a series of visual
          experiences translated into verbal terms. Closure is what sutures the gaps in this
          sequence of disparate images.</p>
            <p>Schwenger and Iser's visual <q>filling in,</q> which operates when
          we read a verbal narrative, is closely analogous to McCloud's <q>closure,</q> which operates when we read a narrative composed of images. Both these
          modes of reading involve a synesthetic interplay between the viewer's imagination and the
          signifiers of the text, whether these signifiers are defined as visual or verbal in
          nature. Indeed, the similarity of <q>closure</q> to <q>filling in</q> suggests that these two modes of reading are less
          distinct than they may appear — that the decision of whether to define a narrative as
          visual or verbal is to some extent an arbitrary decision, one which is influenced by
          cultural politics as well as by the phenomenology of the reading experience. Even if we
          choose to define IF as a genre that employs purely verbal means, the experience of playing
          IF may not be all that different from the experience of playing a game that employs
          (ostensibly) visual means.</p>
            <p>Playing IF, then, could be as much a visual experience as playing a graphical video game.
          However, that doesn't rule out the possibility that these two experiences could be visual
          in different ways: the visuality of IF might differ from the model of visuality associated
          with graphical video games. As early as 1983, Infocom took precisely this position,
          arguing in an advertisement that their games <q>unleash[ed] the world's
            most powerful graphics technology,</q> i.e. the human brain: <q>We
            draw our graphics from the limitless imagery of your imagination — a technology so
            powerful, it makes any picture that's ever come out of a screen look like graffiti by
            comparison.</q>This argument, however, still adheres to the logic of transparency:
          it holds that imagined visuality is more transparent than graphical visuality and
          therefore better.</p>
            <p>A more nuanced way to distinguish between readerly and graphical visuality might be to
          emphasize the personal, subjective or affective aspects of the former. For Schwenger,
          reading is necessarily accompanied by a continuous passive process of image generation,
          but the reader's preexisting visual inclinations and his or her mental repertory of visual
          images affect the way in which he or she concretizes the text's descriptions: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#schwenger1999">[L]iterature consists of a steady stream of erased
                imperatives, according to Elaine Scarry, imperatives that are often
              instructions to produce mental pictures. Yet no matter how detailed or precise those
              instructions may be, they are never comprehensive enough to override the individual’s
              memory bank of images and associations. These play upon the author’s dictated
              pictures, an obbligato of the unconscious, of memory and desire.</quote><ptr target="#schwenger1999" loc="4"/></cit> Even if Short's room descriptions were more
          detailed than they are, they would be unable to supersede the reader's preexisting mental
          pictures of analogous rooms; for example, however Short described the Sun Court temple, I
          would inevitably imagine it as looking like the U.S. Capitol. (By contrast, when I visit a
          similar location in a graphical video game — say, the Bevelle Temple in <title rend="italic">Final Fantasy X</title> — I see <emph>only</emph> what the game designers
          want me to see, and I see the same temple as every other player. The way I understand this
          visual image is specific to me, but the way I visualize it is not.) What Short does do,
          however, is to condition how the player sees whatever it is that he or she sees, to
          suggest the affective resonances of the mental pictures that the player may form. The
          effect of Short's descriptions say less about what precisely the avatar sees than about
          how the avatar is affected by what is seen, as Short notes: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#short2009">With
                <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title>, though, it’s true that I was trying to
              do something a little bit different [as compared to <emph>Metamorphoses</emph>]: to
              hint at the protagonist’s perceptual filters by describing styles and trends rather
              than straightforward physical detail</quote>
                  <ptr target="#short2009"/>
               </cit>.</p>
            <p>For example, the description of the mosaic in the Sun Court reads, <quote rend="inline" source="#short2009">The mosaic is an elegant job and executed in rich materials, but the design has a
            facile modern quality that does not entirely appeal to you.</quote> The temple is
          described as <quote rend="inline" source="#short2009">[b]uilt in an old style, but unworn, unchipped,
            unpolluted.</quote> Combined with the profusion of illusionistic artwork in this area of
          the City, especially the façade-painting, these descriptions suggest that the Sun Court is
          an insincere place. It is recognizably less ancient than it appears to be. This suggests
          that the City's government, of which this space is the public architectural symbol, is
          trying to pass itself off as something it's not. Inasmuch as it is conditioned by such
          hints as these, the player's visualization of this space becomes affectively charged. As a
          counterpoint to this, here is Short's description of a nightclub called Scheherazade:
            <quote rend="block" source="#short2009">Despite the light that leaks in through the windows, the place seems
            to be trying for a dark and anonymous ambiance, with high-backed booths and wood
            paneling, a ceiling painted black, and hanging swatches of brocaded purple velvet. The
            decorations are mostly allusions to the City's distant shady past as an outpost of
            thieves and smugglers on the Vuine.</quote> Most of these details, again, are not
          relevant to completing the game, but they assist the player in creatively visualizing the
          place. The few details that Short does provide — the black ceiling, high-backed booths,
          and purple velvet — hint at what gives this place a <quote rend="inline" source="#short2009">dark and
            anonymous ambiance,</quote> but the player is invited to fill in the remaining details
          in his or her own way. The decorations, involving thieves and smugglers, suggest why the
          place is <q>trying for</q> such an ambiance: it is a place of
          darkness, of secrecy and anonymity, a hideout for outlaws or at least for people who have
          something to conceal. But at least this is a place that doesn't seek to present itself as
          something it's not.</p>
            <p>What all these descriptions do is to condition how the player visualizes the room. They
          add an affective dimension to the mental picture of the room that the player involuntarily
          creates for himself or herself in response to the textual representation of the room.</p>
            <p>This effect is further complicated by Short's limited use of graphics. <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title> includes a frame containing images, located to the
          left of the main gameplay window. However, these images are more suggestive or symbolic
          than mimetic. They suggest the dominant mood or tonality of the scene the player is
          witnessing, rather than showing anything in that scene. Accordingly, Jeremy Douglass calls
          the images in this game <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#douglass2007">ambient illustrations</quote>
                  <ptr target="#douglass2007" loc="45"/>
               </cit>. In <ref target="#figure05">figure 5</ref>,
          for example, we see a stylized representation of the sun against a field of orange fading
          into white. This image doesn't depict anything in the Sun Court, except perhaps the sun
          symbol on the pavement, but it suggests the offputting, blinding sunniness of the
            scene.<note>Note also that these images aren't mapped to specific rooms; they change
            when the player triggers important events in the game's narrative.</note> What we see
          here is a complex, synaesthetic interplay between the images described <emph>in</emph> the
          text and the images that the text <emph>is</emph>. The actual images help to shape the
          player's mental images, at the same time that the latter inflect the player's
          interpretation of the former.</p>
            <p>This is a text that attends to the way in which text is inescapably a visual phenomenon.
          In this context it's worth noting that although <title rend="italic">City of
            Secrets</title> allows the player to change the font, text color and other such options,
          the title screen and the left-hand window include text which is not affected by such
          changes.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure06">
               <head>Screenshot from <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title>.
                  Reproduced by permission.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>Without speculating on the metaphorical associations of this font, I merely note that it
          was chosen deliberately. The player enters this game through the threshold of an image
          which is primarily composed of textual signifiers, yet contrary to my commonsensical
          definition of <term>text</term>, the precise visual instantiation of these signifiers is
          clearly important.</p>
            <p>For a certain subset of the game's audience, <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title>
          was an even more material and visual experience than it is today. On releasing the game,
          Short offered players the opportunity to purchase a special edition of the game that came
          with a boxed set of <soCalled>feelies.</soCalled> The term <term>feelies</term> refers to
              <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#douglass2007">[m]ultimedia epitexts such as journals, maps, and artifacts,
              bundled to illustrate the IF work. Popularized by Infocom</quote>
                  <ptr target="#douglass2007" loc="392"/>
               </cit>. Commercial IF games were physical
          artifacts — floppy discs packaged in boxes and sold in brick-and-mortar stores — and the
          inclusion of feelies further intensified the physicality of those objects. (Feelies served
          the additional practical function of copy protection; games like <title rend="italic">Sorcerer</title> and <title rend="italic">Leather Goddesses of Phobos</title> were
          unsolvable without information which was printed on the feelies, and which, in a pre-World
          Wide Web era, would have been otherwise unavailable.) This physical side of the IF
          experience was lost when IF moved to a digital model of distribution. Seeing this as an
          unfortunate development, Short helped to create a website, <ref target="http://feelies.org">feelies.org</ref>, that produced and distributed feelies for
          contemporary works of IF: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#loguidice2004">
                     <ref target="http://feelies.org">feelies.org</ref> started with a conversation that I had with some of my friends in
              the IF community, about how the one aspect of commercial IF we really missed (as
              players) was the feelies. Some modern IF comes with <soCalled>virtual
                feelies</soCalled> — PDF files or fake Websites or whatever that are distributed in
              a Zip file with the game — and I like those, but we were also missing the tangible
              physical objects.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#loguidice2004" loc="n.p."/>
               </cit> The <title rend="italic">City of
            Secrets</title> feelies included such items as a <quote rend="inline" source="http://feelies.org">[t]ourist guide to
            the City, including map, digitally-offset printed by Imagers.com in full color on glossy
            paper</quote> and a <quote rend="inline" source="#http://feelies.org">[q]uantity of dried liontail in a labeled
            plastic bag, contained in velvet and/or satin gift bag from boutique magic shop.</quote>
          For players who did not purchase the paper feelies, Short also created an online website
          for the Southern Light Rail company (this website is now defunct, but has been cached by
          the Internet Wayback Machine). This website prominently features the same font used in the
          game's title screen.</p>
            <p>The fact that Short paid so much attention to the physical and material aspects of <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title> indicates that for her, the visual instantiation
          of an IF game is not an irrelevant cosmetic detail. It directly influences the player's
          experience of the game, an experience which is visual in multiple senses. The visuality of
            <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title> results from a collaboration between the
          preexisting visual memory of the player and the visual details, verbal and graphical,
          supplied by the author, as focalized through the <soCalled>perceptual filters</soCalled>
          of the avatar — who, unlike the avatars in <title rend="italic">Zork</title> and <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title>, is a well-defined character with a particular
          personality and history. The visual experience of this game depends on a complex and
          shifting interplay between the player's visual memory, the details the author provides via
          the protagonist-avatar, and the imagetextual aspects of the gaming itself.</p>
            <p>Now I suggest that such a visual experience has little to do with transparent immediacy.
          A transparent visual representation, by definition, is minimally mediated; it presents the
          visualized scene without distorting filters, so that it looks the way it would if it were
          present before the viewer. The goal of Short's language in this game is not to create such
          visual representations. In a text-based game, the only way to create such visual
          transparency would be to provide a large amount of precise descriptive detail, so as to
          permit the reader to imagine exactly what every aspect of the scene looks like. However,
          Short argues in her blog post “The Prose Medium and IF” that such “detail for detail's
          sake” is unnecessary and potentially harmful in IF, where ekphrasis is
            <emph>prescriptive</emph>, not autotelic.<note>Excessive use of detail also tends to be
            considered harmful when it occurs in prose fiction; overly vivid descriptions are often
            criticized as <term>purple prose</term>. As Seymour Chatman notes, the amount and
            granularity of detail are among the major factors in which film differs from narrative
            fiction <ptr loc="48" target="#chatman2004"/>, and this certainly also applies to IF and
            graphical video games.</note> The purpose of details in IF prose is to give the player
          the information he or she needs to complete the game. Players are expected not just to
          process the details but to use them as a guide for how to interact affectively with the
          game's operations and its diegetic world. Providing excessive detail would be distracting
          and tiresome. Short explains, however, that detail can do something else: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#short2008">Some of the most effective writers of mood create their effect not with a
              large number of common details (the flowers are red, the door is yellow, etc) but with
              a small number of very particular ones; and I think that that is especially true in
              IF. Words in interactive fiction individually carry more weight than they carry in
              static prose, if only because of the amount of attention we demand the player give to
              each one. […] I think I would find [P.D. James's descriptions] to be overkill in an IF
              game. They’d need to be shortened and focused, because each sentence would do the work
              of three or four sentences in the static prose version. In this respect IF is closer
              to poetry than to conventional prose: it is worth taking more time to select fewer
              words, because each one will be inspected through a jeweler’s loupe.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#short2008" loc="para. 19, 20"/>
               </cit> Short suggests here that the purpose
          of details in IF is not to create a vivid, immediate and sensuously present mental picture
          of a scene, but to suggest the mood associated with that scene. It does this by providing
          sparse but carefully selected details, which serve the player as building blocks around
          which a more complex and personal vision of the scene can be created.<note>A literal
            version of this process occurs in the science fiction film <title rend="italic">Inception</title> (2010), where <q>dream architects</q> create
            blueprints for dream spaces, and the individual dreamer then fleshes out these
            blueprints by adding <q>projections</q> of objects drawn from his
            or her memory.</note> When Short mentions that Scheherazade has high-backed booths, a
          dark ceiling, and decorations that show thieves and smugglers, she does more than simply
          inform us that these things are present; she also hints at the affective resonance of this
          place. She doesn't tell us what precisely this place looks like, but she provides us with
          affective lenses that we can apply to our own visualization of the place. Short's goal in
          this game is not to match the transparency of graphical video games, but to activate a
          mode of visuality which is affectively rather than sensuously vivid. Ekphrasis has been
          used for this purpose since ancient times: Quintillian wrote, for example, that lawyers
          should use ekphrasis only where <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#koelb2006">motivated […] by the speaker’s
              emotional engagement with and amplification of his client’s plight</quote>
                  <dhq:citRef>qtd. in <ptr target="#koelb2006" loc="29"/>
                  </dhq:citRef>
               </cit>. For ancient
          rhetoricians, ekphrasis was not a transparent means of visual representation but a tool
          for augmenting the emotional resonance of the described scene. <title rend="italic">City
            of Secrets</title> suggests that this effect becomes, if anything, more potent when the
          described scene is an interactive one.</p>
            <p>In <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title>, the player needs to directly engage with the
          verbal properties of IF in order to finish the game. <title rend="italic">City of
            Secrets</title> doesn't similarly require the player to visualize in order to complete
          the game (except at the minimal level described above with reference to <title rend="italic">Zork</title>), but this is because <title rend="italic">City of
            Secrets</title> is a deliberately simple game. As Short writes in the game's ABOUT text,
            <q>This game is meant to be playable even by someone who has never
            encountered interactive fiction before, and be a gentle introduction to the genre. It is
            not terribly difficult, nor is it possible to die until the very end.</q> However,
          her other works do often require the player to visualize and to do so in an affective and
          critical way. In <title rend="italic">Savoir Faire</title> (2002), a deliberately
          challenging adventure game, the player has the magical power to create
            <soCalled>links</soCalled> between two similar objects, whereby one object takes on the
          properties of the other or is affected by events that occur to the other. In order to use
          this power effectively, the player has to observe visual (and other) similarities between
          the two objects, and this may require a minute inspection of the two objects involved. For
          example, the first puzzle in the game is to open a locked pair of doors.<note>The same
            example is used in a different context in <ptr target="#mitchell2009"/>.</note> The
          description of the doors reads, <q>A pair of white-painted doors that
            lead into the upstairs corridor of the house. Each door panel is decorated with the
            family crest, picked out in ostentatious gold, as though to warn servants not to wander
            that direction uninvited.</q> In a nearby room the player finds a teapot, whose
          object description reads, <q>In order to make the linkages possible,
            however, it has been painted a glossy white, and the crest of the family executed on one
            side in intricate detail.</q> The solution to the puzzle is to link the doors to the
          teapot, then open the lid of the teapot, causing the doors to open. This works because the
          teapot and the doors are both white, openable, and decorated with the same crest. To
          notice these similarities, the player has to read the descriptions of both objects <q>through a jeweler's loupe.</q> In doing so, the player may visualize
          the two objects, but even if the player doesn't do this, the player's activity of closely
          reading the descriptions is equivalent to the avatar's activity of closely examining the
          objects. Solving this puzzle requires engaging in a mental operation in which
            <term>reading</term> and <term>looking</term> are inextricably linked. Yet this
          reading/looking process is not exclusively goal-directed. At the same time that the object
          descriptions provide the player with the information necessary to solve the puzzle, they
          also help the player to imagine both the visual appearance and the affective resonances of
          the objects referenced. As this example suggests, affective ekphrasis can be a technique
          of both puzzle-solving and worldbuilding; using Douglass's distinction, it contributes to
          both the <q>gamelike</q> and the <q>narrative</q> qualities of IF.</p>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title> combines the emotional vividness of visual
          prose with the ability to interact with the visualized world through an avatar, a
          combination which is perhaps unique to IF. Instead of trying to match the transparent
          visuality of the graphical video game, it provides an IF-specific experience of affective
          textual visuality. This is a second possible way in which IF can define itself as an
          artistically viable medium and not an inferior precursor to the graphical video game.</p>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title> and <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title>
          adopt two opposing strategies for demonstrating the continuing value of IF in a
          post-graphical age. <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title> suggests that IF needn't try to
          compete with the visuality of graphical games because IF's strengths lie in its nonvisual
          aspects. <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title>, by contrast, demonstrates that IF
          can be visual in a way which may be inaccessible to graphical games. What both games
          implicitly argue is that even if IF games can't (or shouldn't) compete with the visual
          transparency of graphical video games, the creation of IF games can still be a viable
          artistic pursuit. The coming of graphics doesn't kill IF, but it does force IF to
          adapt.</p>
            <p>To summarize, I have argued that IF is an ekphrastic medium insofar as it provides the
          player with a textual translation of the avatar's direct visual experience. Unlike
          traditional ekphrastic poetry and prose, however, IF is prescriptively ekphrastic in that
          it asks the player to perform concrete actions in response to its textual pictures. In the
          post-graphical age, prescriptive ekphrasis becomes a threatened mode of visual
          representation because computer graphics seem to have a superior ability to model the
          diegetic world of the game. In order to justify the continued production of IF,
          contemporary IF authors have adopted at least two strategies for responding to this
          threat. The point of both approaches is to argue that IF offers players experiences that
          graphical video games cannot match — an argument which ekphrastic poetry often implicitly
          makes with respect to painting. Where the two approaches differ is in how they
          characterize these experiences which are unique to IF. One strategy, as demonstrated in
            <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title>, is to abandon prescriptive ekphrasis and
          concentrate on the purely textual experiences that IF can offer. The other strategy, which
          we find in <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title>, is to employ an affective rather
          than a mimetic mode of ekphrasis, thereby creating emotional effects that would be
          difficult to replicate with graphics.</p>
            <p>Even the first strategy, however, is still predicated on the visual properties of the IF
          genre. Despite claiming to present a world composed purely of linguistic signifiers,
            <title rend="italic">Ad Verbum</title> still structures those signifiers according to a
          world model composed of rooms and objects, and such a world model, as I've argued, must be
          visualizable in order to be navigable. In <title rend="italic">City of Secrets</title>,
          visualization of the world model becomes the primary appeal of the game. To differing
          extents, both texts ultimately offer the player the opportunity to collaborate with the
          author in imagining a world. As the product of the player's affective visualization, this
          world is, at least ostensibly, more intimate and personal than the vivid, transparent
          worlds of commercial video games can possibly be. If authors like Montfort and Short still
          write IF, and if players like me still play it, then this testifies to the existence of a
          desire for spatial and visual experiences which are more imaginary or affective than
          transparent. Regardless of the vivid immediacy of the spaces that graphical video games
          allow us to inhabit, we still want to inhabit spaces which, to quote the inscription on
          the living room door in <title rend="italic">Zork</title>, are intentionally left
          blank.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>This paper couldn't have been written without the inspiring teaching and dedicated
          assistance of Terry Harpold. I thank Nick Montfort and Emily Short for their encouraging
          comments and for permission to reproduce images.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label="Aarseth 1997" xml:id="aarseth1997" key="aarseth1997">Aarseth, Espen J. <title rend="italic">Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic Literature</title>. The Johns Hopkins University
          Press, 1997.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baggett1994" label="Baggett &amp; de Marcken 1994" key="baggett1994">Baggett, Dave, and Carl
          de Marcken. <title rend="italic">+=3</title> (game). <ref target="http://www.wurb.com/if/game/6">http://www.wurb.com/if/game/6</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Blank et al. 1980" xml:id="blank1980" key="blank1980">Blank, Marc, Dave Lebling, Bruce Daniels
          and Tim Anderson. <title rend="italic">Zork I: The Great Underground Empire</title>
          (game). <ref target="http://www.batmantis.com/Zorks/">http://www.batmantis.com/Zorks/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Bolter &amp; Grusin 2003" xml:id="bolter2003" key="bolter2003b">Bolter, Jay David, and
          Richard Grusin. <title rend="italic">Remediation</title>. MIT Press, 2003.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bond2006" label="Bond 2006" key="bond2006a">Bond, Stephen. <title rend="quotes">Reviewing the
            mazes.</title> Online posting. 17 Nov 2006. 27 Dec 2009 <ref target="http://groups.google.com/group/rec.games.int-fiction/                             msg/92fb6839263f1f04">http://groups.google.com/group/rec.games.int-fiction/
          msg/92fb6839263f1f04</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Chang 2004" xml:id="chang2004" key="chang2004">Chang, Edmond. <title rend="quotes">Words
            Matter: Nick Montfort's Ad Verbum - A Very Close Reading.</title>
               <ref target="http://web.archive.org/web/20040925022928/http://www.edmondchang.com/668k/wordsmatter.html">http://web.archive.org/web/20040925022928/http://www.edmondchang.com/668k/wordsmatter.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chatman2004" label="Chatman 2004" key="chatman2004">Chatman, Seymour. <title rend="quotes">What
            Novels Can Do That Films Can't (And Vice Versa).</title>
               <title rend="italic">Film Theory and Criticism: Introductory Readings</title>. 6th ed. Ed.
          Leo Braudy and Marshall Cohen. Oxford University Press, 2004.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dibbell2001" label="Dibbell 2001" key="dibbell2001">Dibbell, Julian. <title rend="quotes">Adventure.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Supercade!: A Visual History of the Videogame Age 1971- 1984</title>.
          Ed. Van Burnham. The MIT Press, 2001. 135.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Douglass 2007" xml:id="douglass2007" key="douglass2007a">Douglass, Jeremy. <title rend="quotes">Command Lines: Aesthetics and Technique in Interactive Fiction and New Media.</title>
          Diss. UC Santa Barbara, 2007. <ref target="http://jeremydouglass.com/dissertation.html">http://jeremydouglass.com/dissertation.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2002" label="Drucker 2002" key="drucker2002a">Drucker, J. <title rend="quotes">Intimations
            of Immateriality: Graphical Form, Textual Sense, and the Electronic Environment.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Reimagining Textuality: Textual Studies in the Late Age of
            Print</title>. Ed. Loizeaux, E. B, and N. Fraistat. Univ of Wisconsin Pr, 2002:
          152–177.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Eve 2007" xml:id="eve2007" key="eve2007">Eve, Eric. <title rend="quotes">All Hope Abandon:
            Biblical Text and Interactive Fiction.</title> 1.2 (2007): n. pag. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>. 27 Dec 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gaudreault2009" label="Gaudreault &amp; Barnard                                     2009" key="gaudreault2009">Gaudreault,
          André, and Timothy Barnard. <title rend="italic">From Plato to Lumière: Narration and
            Monstration in Literature and Cinema</title>. University of Toronto Press, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="heffernan2004" label="Heffernan 2004" key="heffernan2004">Heffernan, James A. W. <title rend="italic">Museum of Words: The Poetics of Ekphrasis from Homer to Ashbery</title>.
          University of Chicago Press, 2004.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Hollander 1995" xml:id="hollander1995" key="hollander1995">Hollander, John. <title rend="italic">The Gazer's Spirit: Poems Speaking to Silent Works of Art</title>. 1st ed. University
          of Chicago Press, 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ingold2000" label="Ingold 2000" key="ingold2000">Ingold, Jon. <title rend="italic">The Mulldoon
            Legacy</title> (game). <ref target="http://www.wurb.com/if/game/451">http://www.wurb.com/if/game/451</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Jerz 2007" xml:id="jerz2007" key="jerz2007">Jerz, Dennis G. <title rend="quotes">Somewhere
            Nearby is Colossal Cave: Examining Will Crowther's Original "Adventure" in Code and in
            Kentucky.</title> 1.2 (2007): n. pag. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
            Quarterly</title>. 26 Oct 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="koelb2006" label="Koelb 2006" key="koelb2006">Koelb, Janice Hewlett. <title rend="italic">The
            Poetics of Description: Imagined Places in European Literature</title>. Palgrave
          Macmillan, 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Krieger 1992" xml:id="krieger1992" key="krieger1992">Krieger, Murray, and Joan Krieger. <title rend="italic">Ekphrasis: The Illusion of the Natural Sign</title>. Johns Hopkins
          University Press, 1992.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="loguidice2004" label="Loguidice 2004" key="loguidice2004">Loguidice, Bill. <title rend="quotes">Interactive Fiction and Feelies: An Interview with Emily Short.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Armchair Arcade</title>. 31 August 2010.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Loizeaux 2008" xml:id="loizeaux2008" key="loizeaux2008">Loizeaux, Elizabeth Bergmann. <title rend="italic">Twentieth-Century Poetry and the Visual Arts</title>. Cambridge University
          Press, 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mccloud1993" label="McCloud1993" key="mccloud1993">McCloud, Scott. <title rend="italic">Understanding Comics</title>. Tundra Pub., 1993. </bibl>
            <bibl label="McGann 1991" xml:id="mcgann1991" key="mcgann1991">McGann, Jerome J. <title rend="italic">The
            Textual Condition</title>. Princeton University Press, 1991.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mitchell1990" label="Mitchell 1990" key="mitchell1990">Mitchell, W. J. <title rend="italic">Iconology: Image, Text, Ideology</title>. Univ. of Chicago Presss, 1990. </bibl>
            <bibl label="Mitchell 1994" xml:id="mitchell1994" key="mitchell1994a">Mitchell, W.J.T.<title rend="italic">Picture Theory: Essays on Verbal and Visual Representation.</title> Univ. of Chicago
          Press, 1994.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Mitchell &amp; Montfort 2009" xml:id="mitchell2009" key="mitchell2009a">Mitchell, Alex P., and
          Nick Montfort. <title rend="quotes">Shaping Stories and Building Worlds on Interactive
            Fiction Platforms.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Digital Arts and Culture Conference 2009: After
            Media: Embodiment and Context</title>. 12 Dec. 2009. 31 August 2010.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="montfort2000" label="Montfort 2000" key="montfort2000">Montfort, Nick. <title rend="italic">Ad
            Verbum</title> (game). <ref target="http://www.wurb.com/if/game/912">http://www.wurb.com/if/game/912</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Montfort 2005" xml:id="montfort2005" key="montfort2005">Montfort, Nick. <title rend="italic">Twisty Little Passages: An Approach to Interactive Fiction</title>. The MIT Press,
          2005.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nelson2001" label="Nelson 2001" key="nelson2001">Nelson, Graham. <title rend="italic">The
            Inform Designer's Manual</title>. Dan Sanderson, 2001.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Salen &amp; Zimmerman 2003" xml:id="salen2003" key="salen2003">Salen, Katie, and Eric
          Zimmerman. <title rend="italic">Rules of Play: Game Design Fundamentals</title>.
          Illustrated edition. The MIT Press, 2003.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schwenger1999" label="Schwenger                                             1999" key="schwenger1999">Schwenger, Peter.
            <title rend="italic">Fantasm and Fiction: On Textual Envisioning</title>. 1st ed.
          Stanford University Press, 1999.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Short 2000" xml:id="short2000" key="short2000">Short, Emily. <title rend="italic">Metamorphoses</title> (game). <ref target="http://www.wurb.com/if/game/910">http://www.wurb.com/if/game/910</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="short2002" label="Short 2002" key="short2002">Short, Emily. <title rend="italic">Savoir
            Faire</title> (game). <ref target="http://www.wurb.com/if/game/1821">http://www.wurb.com/if/game/1821</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Short 2003" xml:id="short2003" key="short2003">Short, Emily. <title rend="italic">City of
            Secrets</title> (game). <ref target="http://www.wurb.com/if/game/2106">http://www.wurb.com/if/game/2106</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="short2008" label="Short                                                         2008" key="short2008">Short, Emily.
            <title rend="quotes">The Prose Medium and IF.</title> Blog posting. <ref target="http://emshort.wordpress.com/how-to-play/writing-if/my-articles/the-prose-medium-and-if/">http://emshort.wordpress.com/how-to-play/writing-if/my-articles/the-prose-medium-and-if/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Short 2009" xml:id="short2009" key="short2009">Short, Emily. Comment in response to Nick
          Montfort's blog posting, <title rend="quotes">IF, Visuality, and Other Bits of
            DAC.</title>
               <ref target="http://nickm.com/post/2009/12/if-visuality-and-other-bits-of-dac/#comments">http://nickm.com/post/2009/12/if-visuality-and-other-bits-of-dac/#comments</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wettlaufer2003" label="Wettlaufer 2003" key="wettlaufer2003">Wettlaufer, Alexandra K. <title rend="italic">In the Mind's Eye: The Visual Impulse in Diderot, Baudelaire and
            Ruskin</title>. Editions Rodopi B.V., 2003.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Whalen 2008" xml:id="whalen2008" key="whalen2008b">Whalen, Zach. <title rend="quotes">The
            Videogame Text: Typography and Textuality.</title> Diss. University of Florida,
          2008.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wikipedia2009" label="Wikipedia 2009" key="wikipedia2009">
               <title rend="quotes">Osborne 1.</title>
          Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia. 26 Dec 2009, 18:05 UTC. 28 Dec 2009 <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.phptitle=Osborne_1&amp;oldid=334122161">http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.phptitle=Osborne_1&amp;oldid=334122161</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Wolf 1997" xml:id="wolf1997" key="wolf1997">Wolf, Mark J.P. <title rend="quotes">Inventing
            Space: Toward a Taxonomy of On- and Off-Screen Space in Video Games.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Film Quarterly</title> 51:1 (Autumn 1997): 11-23.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wolf2002" label="Wolf 2002" key="wolf2002">Wolf, Mark J. P. <title rend="italic">The Medium of the Video Game</title>. 1st ed.
          University of Texas Press, 2002.</bibl>
         </listBibl>

      </back>
  </text>
</TEI>