<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <author>Amy Earhart</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Amy <dhq:family>Earhart</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Texas A&amp;M University</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Amy Earhart is an Assistant Professor of English at Texas A&amp;M University.
                     Her work has appeared in <title rend="italic">Reinventing the Peabody
                        Sisters</title> (Iowa UP), <title rend="italic">ATQ: American Transcendental
                        Quarterly</title>, and <title rend="italic">Resources in American Literary
                        Study</title>. Forthcoming work will appear in <title rend="italic">Digital
                        Humanities Quarterly</title>, <title rend="italic">Documentary
                        Editing</title>, <title rend="italic">The Thoreau Society Bulletin</title>,
                     and the <title rend="italic">Oxford Handbook to Transcendentalism</title>. She
                     has co-edited the forthcoming University of Michigan Press collection of essays
                     titled <title rend="italic">The American Literature Scholar in the Digital
                        Age</title> with Andrew Jewell. Earhart is at work on a monograph titled
                        <title rend="quotes">Traces of the Old, Uses of the New: The Emergence of
                        the Digital Humanities.</title> In addition, she is developing the NEH
                     funded 19th-Century Concord Digital Archive in partnership with the Concord
                     Free Public Library.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <author>Maura Ives</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Maura <dhq:family>Ives</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Texas A&amp;M University</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Maura Ives is Associate Professor of English and Director of the Digital
                     Humanities Program at Texas A&amp;M University. She works in 19th century print
                     and digital textual studies, focusing on Victorian women writers (especially
                     Christina Rossetti and Jean Ingelow) and on bibliographical and literary
                     subgenres of Victorian women's religious writing (hymns, devotional calendars,
                     illuminated texts, periodicals). </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000050</idno>
            <idno type="volume">003</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2009-09-29">29 September 2009</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace"
                  rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword
                     taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2009-06-15" who="mpw">Initial encoding</change>
         <change when="2009-08-12" who="Alyssa">encoded revised version</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>This is the introduction to the issue of <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> that grew
               out of the October 2006 Digital Textual Studies: Past, Present and Future Symposium
               held at Texas A&amp;M University.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Introduction to DHQ issue based on the Oct. 2006 Digital Textual Studies: Past,
               Present, and Future Symposium, Texas A&amp;M University.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>Digital Textual Studies: Past, Present and Future</head>
         <p>This issue of <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> grew out of the October 2006 Digital
            Textual Studies: Past, Present and Future Symposium held at Texas A&amp;M University.
            The symposium brought together pioneers in the field and emergent scholars, who, through
            a series of talks and an evening poster session, responded to our charge to address the
            current state of the field and to muse on important issues that continue to challenge
            digital textual scholarly work. As Peter Robinson recalls, <q>This was an opportunity to
               refresh the community, and to consider, collectively, where we are and where we are
               going.</q> The symposium was invigorating and exciting, the more so because of ample
            opportunities for broad and wide-ranging discussions among participants and attendees.
            At the close of the symposium our focus on the future of digital textual scholarship
            took a more immediate and practical turn as we considered how best to bring our
            discussions to the broader digital humanities community. The then-new journal <title
               rend="italic">DHQ</title> presented an ideal venue through which we could provide a
            more dynamic view of the energy and ideas generated at the symposium by inclusion of the
            full range of presented materials: both the invited speakers’ formal essays and the more
            informal posters. </p>
         <p>A keynote talk by Jerome McGann, though not reprinted here, helped to frame the
            symposium’s central concerns, situating our particular moment within the rich, if still
            surprisingly recent, history of digital innovation in the world of textual and
            hypertextual studies. Much of what has happened in the field of digital textual studies
            has happened in localized environments, supported by innovators like McGann who took
            advantage of reputations developed in print work to advocate for digital work,
            convincing recalcitrant disciplines and colleagues to support and accept experimentation
            in the digital, and urging us to see the necessity of continued engagement on the part
            of humanities scholars in the remediation of our cultural heritage. The development of
            digital humanities centers and working groups has helped to provide infrastructure to
            nurture work that often resists standard modes of humanities scholarship. In retrospect,
            even the largest of scholarly digital projects, produced independent of publishers and
            in collaboration across multiple disciplines, still seem to represent a space that is
            not only quantitatively but qualitatively distinct from the projects such as Carnegie
            Mellon’s Universal Digital Library, which aims <cit>
               <quote rend="inline" source="http://www.ulib.org/ulibaboutus.htm#visionbkmark">to
                  capture all books in digital format</quote>
               <ref target="http://www.ulib.org/ulibaboutus.htm#visionbkmark"
                  >http://www.ulib.org/​ULIBAboutUs.htm#visionBkMark</ref>
            </cit>. Our attention is increasingly drawn to questions of scale, of what humanities
            scholars might do, or do differently, with a million (or a few million) books, rather
            than to questions about how to define, implement, support, and engage with more focused
            collections whose value lies in careful management of the details of remediation. These
            questions, expressed both in practical and theoretical terms, remain central to the work
            of digital textual scholars, but it would be a mistake to assume that they are not
            equally relevant to mass digitization or to the myriad commercial full text databases
            that try to offer the best of both worlds through some measure of focused selection,
            technological transparency, and scholarly oversight.</p>
         <p>In considering the various <q>ends</q> – understood not only as aims or goals, but also
            in terms of shifts in editorial methods, concepts, and media – that have reshaped the
            field, Peter Robinson traces the emergence of digital editing from the larger field of
            textual studies, establishing a history of the conflicts of theory and practice within
            the digital environment and pointing to the continuing challenges that digital work
            presents for humanists who embark on a digital scholarly edition. Editorial work,
            especially digital editorial work, is both labor intensive and dependent upon access to
            expertise and resources that are often scarce or unsuited to the needs of humanities
            scholars. Specifically, in the absence of easily mastered digital tools, humanists have
            depended upon access to <q>technical experts</q> in order to carry out their work – a
               <q>broken model</q> that has restricted the development of digital editing to a few
            scholars at a few institutions that can provide the level and continuity of technical
            expertise that this work requires. Robinson calls for freely available texts and robust
            digital tools that empower humanities scholars to engage in digital work, and allow for
            collaborative textual scholarship. </p>
         <p>Focusing on the specific technological and institutional concerns presented by digital
            imaging, Morris Eaves traces the history of the incorporation of images into digital
            materials through his work with the <title rend="italic">Blake Archive</title>. As Eaves
            observes, our everyday and scholarly lives increasingly unfold within a <q>sea of
               images, most of them digitized</q>; it is now impossible to imagine textual
            scholarship without high-quality images, yet digital images present a variety of
            challenges for digital projects. Intellectual property restrictions complicate the
            acquisition of images for open access electronic projects, while technological concerns
            include the particularly knotty question of the outdated jpeg format, as well as the
            problems of appropriately attaching metadata and search terms to images, and maintaining
            image quality in the face of another sea of <q>image robbers: service providers,
               operating systems, browsers, video cards, display settings, displays, and the user’s
               own highly variable eyes and brain.</q> Eaves, like Robinson, recognizes the need for
            further development of technologies that support digital textual scholarship, a problem
            made more complicated by the degree to which <q>[i]n technical areas we are, much of the
               time, pathetically dependent on the expertise of others whose investments are
               elsewhere.</q> Compromise remains a practical editorial necessity.</p>
         <p>In Kenneth Price’s discussion of naming, the shifting technical boundaries of digital
            work are mirrored by the shifting vocabularies with which we attempt to define and
            explain that work. As Price argues, terminology matters: <q>The shorthand we invoke when
               explaining our work to others shapes how we conceive of and also how we position
               digital scholarship.</q> Interestingly, Price discovers that the technological limits
            that emerge in this context have to do not so much with digital tools but with framing
            mechanisms that derive from the technologies of print. Drawing examples from the <title
               rend="italic">Whitman Archive</title> and other digital projects, Price considers
            whether our reliance on terms from print might curtail the possibilities of the digital,
            weighing the implications of using terms such as <term>edition</term>,
               <term>project</term>, <term>database</term>, <term>archive</term> and <term>thematic
               research collection</term> to describe text-based electronic scholarship. He suggests
            that we should adopt a new term to represent the possibilities for exploration within
            the new environment and proposes <term>arsenal</term> as a term that conceptualizes our
            common and collaborative endeavors and reflects the ways in which humanities scholars
            are repurposing commercial and (in the case of the Internet) military technological
            tools to serve our own needs and purposes.</p>
         <p>Like Peter Robinson, Peter Shillingsburg acknowledges the need for better digital tools
            and a collaborative editorial environment, and advocates making digital editions and
            archives more accessible and <q>convenient</q> for readers and editors. But
            Shillingsburg offers a cautionary approach to digital editing, arguing that to date, the
            model for most digital humanities projects has been to solve problems in ways that are
               <q>local, limited, proprietary, and/or inapplicable to the problems of others.</q>
            Shillingsburg imagines a future in which <q>instead of having electronic editions
               conceived, constructed, and completed by an editor and published like books to sit
               neglected on the shelf, electronic textual scholarship will occupy a communal space
               where the intellectual work of the future will be built on the textual foundations
               laid down electronically by the present generation,</q> and proposes the creation of
            a centralized editing space for communal work to create holistic projects.</p>
         <p>Julia Flanders’s essay reminds us that the lack of appropriate tools for digital
            humanities research exists alongside an unprecedented technological abundance that has
            shaped the way we think about digital scholarship. Noting the ubiquity and unprecedented
            capacity of computers --quickly becoming <q>not a specialized tool but part of the
               tissue of the world,</q> -- as well as the successful development of specialized
            tools such as XML text encoding, Flanders recognizes that while the digital humanities
            often participate a generalized narrative of technological progressivism, resistance to
            that narrative produces an <q>unease</q> that constitutes a productive force for
            critical inquiry. These disruptions in our understanding of the significance of medium,
            of the institutional structures and scholarly protocols that shape our work, of
            representation and scale, promise to give us new ways to think about our world.</p>
         <p>The posters included in this issue shift our attention away from the history, theory,
            and intellectual positioning of digital textual studies to speak instead to the
            engagement of textual studies with emergent trends in digital humanities, including
            mapping, visualization, recovery and more. For example, a number of posters suggest how
            digital <q>add-ons</q> might benefit the more static representations of manuscripts,
            such as Olin Bjork’s audio and annotation program attached to <title rend="italic"
               >Paradise Lost</title>, Eugene Lyman’s Elwood viewer, or the representation of
            Quixote Iconography under development by Eduardo Urbina, Richard Furuta, and Steven E.
            Smith. Mapping is used for innovative purposes in Amy Roundtree’s rhetorical and ethical
            analysis of Hurricane Katrina, while Amy Earhart experiments with Google map hacks to
            develop an interface for literary materials. Wesley Raabe and Laura Mandell’s poster
            suggests that the digital is a way to correct and recover literary texts. Raabe’s work
            with <title rend="italic">Uncle Tom’s Cabin</title> deconstructs the myth of the flawed
            digital text, demonstrating that the electronic version of the text is the most accurate
            available for scholarly use, while Mandell’s poster demonstrates the creation of the
            Poetess archive, a digital project that recovers the crossnational history of women’s
            popular poetry.</p>
         <p>While some of the poster participants are attached to major digital humanities centers,
            such as IATH, a surprising number of poster participants are working on small scale
            projects at institutions that have little institutional structures to support digital
            humanities work. While we praise the work occurring in the multiple areas, it does serve
            as a note of caution that the institutional frameworks to fully support this work have
            not kept pace with the rapid emergence of this developing field. Still, much has changed
            since 2006: the National Endowment for the Humanities now sponsors an Office of Digital
            Humanities, and a growing number of foundational documents, such as the final report of
            the ACLS Commission on Cyberinfrastructure in the Humanities and Social Sciences
            released in Fall 2006, and the Council on Library and Information Resources’ <title
               rend="italic">A Survey of Digital Humanities Centers in the United States</title>
            (November 2008), point to an encouraging level of attention, and of focused discussion,
            of support needs within, across, and beyond institutional boundaries. We present these
            essays and posters in recognition that the past is indeed prologue to a bright, yet
            unpredictable, digital future. And we call for continued exploration into this future,
            asking as does Peter Robinson, <q>We are moving, certainly: but where are we moving? Do
               we know where we want to go, and how we are going to get there? And where, exactly,
               are we heading?</q>
         </p>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="unsworth2006" label="Unsworth, et al.  2006" key="unsworth2006">Our
               Cultural Commonwealth: The report of the American Council of Learned Societies
               Commission on Cyberinfrastructure for the Humanities and Social Sciences. John
               Unsworth, et al. 2006. <ptr
                  target="http://www.acls.org/uploadedfiles/publications/programs/our_cultural_commonwealth.pdf"
               />
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zorich2008" label="Zorich 2008" key="zorich2008">A Survey of Digital
               Humanities Centers in the United States. Diane M. Zorich. CLIR pub 143: November,
               2008. <ptr target="http://www.clir.org/pubs/abstract/pub143abst.html"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="udl" label="The Universal Digital Library" key="udl">The Universal Digital
               Library. Carnegie Mellon University. <ptr target="http://www.ulib.org/"/>
            </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
