<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Scholarly Primitives of Scholarly Meetings: A
                    DH-Inspired Exploration of the Virtual Incunabular in the Time of COVID
                    19</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Jennifer <dhq:family>Edmond</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9991-1637</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Trinity College Dublin, Ireland</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>jennifer.edmond@tcd.ie</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Jennifer Edmond is Associate Professor of Digital Humanities at Trinity
                            College Dublin, Co-director of the Trinity Center for Digital
                            Humanities, Director of the MPhil in Digital Humanities and Culture and
                            a funded Investigator of the SFI ADAPT Centre. Jennifer also serves as
                            President of the Board of Directors of the pan-European research
                            infrastructure for the arts and humanities, DARIAH-EU. Her research
                            explores interdisciplinarity, humanistic and hybrid research processes,
                            and the emergence of critical digital humanities as a contributor to
                            both research and technology development.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Nicole <dhq:family>Basaraba</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1753-9160</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Maastricht University, the Netherlands</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>nicole.basaraba@coventry.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Nicole Basaraba is a Lecturer in Media and Communications at Coventry
                            University, UK. Her research focuses on developing and evaluating
                            interactive digital narratives for cultural heritage, tourism, public
                            history, and digital humanities projects. Recently she has been
                            investigating how the concept of digital place-making and different
                            creative techniques can be used to contribute to storytelling about
                            heritage and identity. She holds a PhD in Digital Humanities from
                            Trinity College Dublin (Ireland) and a Master of Arts in Communications
                            and Technology from the University of Alberta (Canada).</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Michelle <dhq:family>Doran</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7850-6886</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Centre for Digital Humanities, Trinity College Dublin,
                        Ireland</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>doranm1@tcd.ie</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Michelle Doran is a Research Fellow and Research Projects and
                            Communications Officer at the Trinity College Dublin Centre for Digital
                            Humanities. She holds a PhD in Medieval Irish Studies, and her principal
                            research interests lie in the field of humanities research and the
                            underlying epistemological and ideological premises.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Vicky <dhq:family>Garnett</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1349-7031</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>DARIAH-EU</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>vicky.garnett@dariah.eu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Vicky Garnett is the Training and Education Officer for DARIAH-EU, the
                            pan-European research infrastructure for the arts and humanities, based
                            at the Trinity College Dublin, Ireland. Her role includes managing and
                            curating training resources on the DARIAH-Campus training discovery
                            platform, and advocating for the training needs of the DARIAH Community.
                            Her background is in (socio)linguistics, specifically language variation
                            and change. She has previously worked in EU projects, including
                            PARTHENOS, Europeana Cloud, and DigCurV.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Courtney Helen <dhq:family>Grile</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0442-097X</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>School of Creative Arts, Trinity College Dublin,
                        Ireland</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>grilec@tcd.ie</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Courtney Helen Grile is a theatre artist and PhD candidate in the
                            department of Drama at Trinity College Dublin and an early career
                            researcher in the Trinity Long Room Hub. Her current research looks at
                            the intersection of applied drama and democracy, with a focus on
                            deliberative democratic practices. She has worked in the United States
                            and Ireland as an administrator, adjunct instructor, teaching artist,
                            performer, facilitator, and director. Her passion is for using applied
                            drama and theatre techniques to work in community settings.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Eliza <dhq:family>Papaki</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3943-5012</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>DARIAH-EU</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>eliza.papaki@dariah.eu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Eliza Papaki works as the Outreach and Communications Officer of
                            DARIAH-EU, the pan-European research infrastructure for the arts and
                            humanities, based at the Trinity College Dublin, Ireland. She completed
                            studies in History and Archaeology and holds an MPhil in Public History
                            and Cultural Heritage from Trinity College Dublin. Before joining
                            DARIAH-EU, Eliza worked in various EU-funded Digital Humanities projects
                            at the Centre for Digital Humanities, Maynooth University and the
                            Digital Curation Unit, Research Centre ATHENA in Greece.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Erszébet <dhq:family>Toth-Czifra</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5350-067X</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>DARIAH-EU</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>erzsebet.toth-czifra@dariah.eu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Erzsébet Tóth-Czifra works as the Open Science Officer of DARIAH-EU where
                            she is responsible for fostering and implementing policies and practices
                            related to the open dissemination of research results in the humanities.
                            She received her PhD in Cultural Linguistics and also has a background
                            in scholarly communication.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000607</idno>
                <idno type="volume"
                    ><!-- volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006 -->016</idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 -->2</idno>
            	<date when="2022-04-01">01 April 2022</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2022-08-03" who="BRG">fixed ORCID typo</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>This article documents the theoretical and practical considerations underpinning
                    the COVID-19-inspired digital humanities event: <title rend="quotes">The
                        Scholarly Primitives of Scholarly Meetings.</title>  Drawing from both the
                    long tradition of work on scholarly primitives as well as the rush of new work
                    that appeared in the early months of 2020, the event described here was designed
                    as both an exercise in critical making and a response to the constraints of the
                    virtual incunabular state so many organisations found themselves in, attempting
                    to recreate their planned face-to-face meetings in virtual formats without due
                    consideration of the affordances and constraints of each context. As a
                    structurally distributed organisation, the DARIAH European Research
                    Infrastructure as event host was able to bring its experience of virtual
                    interaction to the recosideration of these challenges, but also the sensitivity
                    to research processes and practices that is central to our positioning in the
                    digital humanities. As such, the resulting model for a virtual event, realised
                    in May 2020 and described in this paper, was built upon a very self-conscious
                    set of considerations, meta-reflection, and goals regarding what we might
                    tacitly and could expect from a virtual event. The instruments designed to
                    deliver this, as well as their performance in practice, is documented alongside
                    consideration of what lessons the experience delivers about both virtual
                    meetings and more generally about the interactions of scholarly communities.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head/>
            <div>
                <head/>
                <p>In March 2020, the DARIAH ERIC, a pan-European research infrastructure for the
                    arts and humanities, was deeply engaged in the planning for their May annual
                    event, but this annual event had to be postponed and ultimately moved online due
                    to the outbreak of the global COVID-19 pandemic. For DARIAH, however, we did not
                    want to lose the opportunity to share knowledge and exchange ideas in our usual
                    vibrant format. Our position within digital humanities and the meta-relation to
                    our chosen event theme of <title rend="quotes">Scholarly Primitives</title> made
                    us hyperaware that virtual interactions were impoverished and lacking. However,
                    there was little investigation of exactly what functions could be easily
                    transposed into the virtual format and which ones could not. This event, which
                    we referred to not as a conference but as a Virtual Exchange (VX) event, would
                    seek to maximise audience engagement and interaction, minimise participant
                    cognitive load, foster serendipity and discovery, and specifically explore the
                    human side of what happens at in-person versus online scholarly meetings. This
                    field report details how the DARIAH VX team theorised, built, lived and
                    evaluated the strengths of the virtual scholarly meeting through the contextual
                    lens of <title rend="quotes">Scholarly Primitives</title> and how future online
                    events could learn from and apply these strategies and specific practices.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>In March 2020, the DARIAH ERIC, a pan-European research infrastructure for the
                    arts and humanities, was deeply engaged in the planning for their May annual
                    event, putting final touches on its three-day schedule of papers, panels,
                    posters and meetings featuring reflections on the twentieth anniversary of the
                    publication of John Unsworth’s seminal paper on the <title rend="quotes"
                        >Scholarly Primitives</title> of humanities research. And then, suddenly, we
                    weren’t.</p>
                <p>Like so many other events in 2020, the DARIAH Annual Event had to be postponed
                    and ultimately moved online due to the global COVID-19 pandemic. For DARIAH,
                    however, the difficult process of coming to terms with losing our opportunity to
                    share knowledge and exchange ideas in our usual vibrant format was accompanied
                    by two strong resonances. First of all, as a distributed organisation, the
                    DARIAH community was somewhat ahead of the curve in terms of moving to online
                    meetings. While the rest of the world seemed to be just discovering the joys of
                        <q>Zoom fatigue</q> and that seminal <foreign xml:lang="fr">cri de
                        coeur</foreign> of the virtual meeting <q>please mute your mic,</q> DARIAH
                    was already a heavy user of this platform since 2016, and had developed a robust
                    calendar balancing virtual and face-to-face interactions for its core and
                    peripheral team members so as to maximise the utility of each mode of
                    interaction. Watching the transformation of professional interaction from our
                    position of relative experience with virtual work made us uniquely sensitive to
                    the manner in which the blunt instrument of videoconferencing was suddenly
                    needing to be applied to nearly every human interaction, many of which had not
                    been imagined as use cases when the tools were designed. We were finding
                    ourselves in a period of the <quote rend="inline">virtual incunabular</quote>
                    (drawing on the idea developed in <ptr target="#crane2006"/> of the <q>digital
                        incunabula</q>) where the usage of a new knowledge technology was being
                    applied according to the norms and affordances of an older one, and not always
                    with fully satisfactory results, a model alternatively referred to by <ptr
                        target="#weinberg2020"/> as the <q>online insert</q> model.</p>

                <p>We were inspired not only by our observations of the incunabular, however, but
                    also by our sensitivity, honed by our engagement with the digital humanities, to
                    the research and exchange processes that our chosen event theme of <title
                        rend="quotes">Scholarly Primitives</title> had made us so aware of. It was
                    an accepted truism that virtual interactions were impoverished and lacking, but
                    there was very little investigation of exactly what was missing and, as a
                    corollary, what functions could be easily transposed to the virtual format, and
                    what ones could not. Rather than merely accept or ignore these simplistic
                    insights, we decided instead to approach this question of efficient scholarly
                    communications as a research challenge, to be framed by the research question
                    how one might apply the concept of scholarly primitives to our communal, social
                    knowledge-creating and -sharing processes, breaking down the functions of the
                    scholarly meeting in the same way that Unsworth had with research processes. Our
                    central argument was that through such an application of canonical DH theory we
                    could better understand a different, but not unrelated, subset of our research
                    practices within the digital humanities, as well as develop widely transferable
                    insight regarding the tactical use of virtual interactions that might transcend
                    the virtual incunabular. Had we not been long aware already of the fact that we
                    should be reconsidering our modes of interaction within the research ecosystem
                    in the light of climate change anyway, the late 2019/early 2020 rush of opinion
                    pieces questioning academic conferences would have certainly brought this to our
                    minds (see for example <ptr target="#wolff2019"/> and <ptr
                        target="#macdonald2020"/>), and, as these commentators also emphasised,
                    COVID-19 was our sudden and unwelcome, yet undeniably still fertile, opportunity
                    to participate in a grand experiment.</p>

                <p>The experiment this positionality inspired us to undertake was centred on the
                    need to pivot our development of the physical event planned for May to a virtual
                    one, but this virtual event would seek to harness different interaction
                    paradigms from those we had thus far been considering. To do this we would draw
                    from scholarship on scholarly interaction and knowledge exchange, on carbon
                    neutral conferencing, but also pedagogical paradigms and the methodologies of
                        <quote rend="inline">critical making</quote>
                    <ptr target="#ratto2011"/>. With this event, which we eventually came to refer
                    to not as a conference but as a Virtual Exchange (VX) event, we would seek to
                    maximise audience engagement and interaction, minimise participant cognitive
                    load, foster serendipity and discovery, and deeply explore the human side of
                    what happens at scholarly meetings. What follows is an account of how the DARIAH
                    VX team theorised, built, lived and evaluated this attempt to play to the
                    strengths of the virtual scholarly meeting, and the lessons we learned in the
                    process.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Informing a novel approach to scholarly meetings: Primitives, NCN Events and
                    beyond.</head>
                <p>In 2000, John Unsworth presented a tentative list of <term>scholarly
                        primitives</term>, described as <quote rend="inline">basic functions common
                        to scholarly activity across disciplines, over time, and independent of
                        theoretical orientation</quote>
                    <ptr target="#unsworth2000"/>. The immediate intention underlying Unsworth’s
                    explication of scholarly primitives was to suggest some (recursive) functions of
                    humanities scholarship that might be usefully embodied in tool-building in
                    humanities computing. Unsworth’s list comprised seven discrete functions —
                    discovering, annotating, comparing, referring, sampling, illustrating and
                    representing — with Unsworth further noting that <quote rend="inline"
                        >referring</quote> and <quote rend="inline">referencing</quote> are the two
                    true primitives, as they are in some way related to all of the others.</p>
                <p>In an interview conducted in 2011, Unsworth reiterated the point that his list of
                    scholarly primitives was not intended to be exhaustive. Rather, in his initial
                    contribution he welcomed and encouraged debate on the subject. Indeed,
                    Unsworth’s approach of using scholarly primitives as a means of understanding
                    humanities’ research processes and building digital tools for scholarship in the
                    humanities has been, and continues to be, the subject of much discussion within
                    the fields of Digital Humanities and Information Sciences. The following sample
                    of that body of literature gives an overview of these trends. </p>
                <p>In a 2009 report on the state of knowledge of scholarly information behaviour
                    compiled for the Online Computer Library Center (OCLC), Carole Palmer and her
                    co-authors presented an adapted definition of Unsworth's concept of a primitive
                        <quote rend="inline">by emphasizing a sense of the primitive as something at
                        the base or beginning of a larger process</quote>. This amended definition
                    was closely related to the authors’ concept of scholarly information activities
                    which emphasised <quote rend="inline">the explicit role of information in the
                        conduct of research and production of scholarship</quote>
                    <ptr target="#palmer2009" loc="7"/>. Palmer et al. derived a framework of five
                    core scholarly activities — searching, collecting, reading, writing and
                    collaborating — with two or more primitives identified within these broader
                    categories. Similar to the <quote rend="inline">true primitives</quote> of
                    Unsworth’s model, the authors also distinguish four cross-cutting primitives
                    that are related to at least two individual scholarly activities. <ptr
                        target="#palmer2009"/>
                </p>
                <p>The following year, the US-based Project Bamboo (2008-2012), a
                    cyberinfrastructure initiative for the arts and humanities, published the
                    findings of a series of workshops held in 2008 with an international cohort of
                    digital humanities practitioners with the aim of charting <quote rend="inline">a
                        direction for cyberinfrastructure development in the humanities</quote>
                    <ptr target="#projectbamboo2010"/>. This report identifies thirteen themes of
                    scholarly practice and the authors of the report map the Bamboo themes to
                    Unsworth’s scholarly primitives and Palmer et al.’s scholarly information
                    activities <ptr target="#palmer2009"/>. In 2014, Annie Murray and Jared
                    Wiercinski further developed this body of research by supplementing it to better
                    reflect the specific activities of humanities scholars who work with audio
                    formats <ptr target="#murray_wiercinski2014"/>. Moreover, Murray and Wiercinski
                    recommend familiarity with the work of Unsworth, Palmer and Project Bamboo as
                    the foundation for an evidence-based design methodology for building digital
                    tools for humanities scholars.</p>
                <p>Unsworth’s Scholarly Primitives had been highly influential in the context of
                    DARIAH. During DARIAH’s preparatory phase, Sheila Anderson et al. combined the
                    related concepts of methodological commons and primitives <quote rend="inline"
                        >to map research work in arts and humanities e-Science, and to assist in
                        scoping the research infrastructure for the European project DARIAH</quote>
                    <ptr target="#anderson2010"/>. Lastly, in the context of this brief review of
                    the literature on scholarly primitives that informed and inspired the DARIAH VX,
                    the Scholarly Domain Model (SDM) proposed by the Digitised Manuscript to
                    Europeana (DM2E) project proposed to bridge the <quote rend="inline">practices
                        of humanist research approaches in both the analogue and digital
                        world</quote>
                    <ptr target="#DM2E2015" loc="8–9"/>. The SDM, which consists of four <quote
                        rend="inline">different layers of abstraction</quote> — Areas, Scholarly
                    Primitives, Scholarly Activities and Scholarly Operations — was based on the
                    assumption that an understanding of Unsworth’s Scholarly Primitives is
                    fundamental to any model of the scholarly domain <ptr target="#DM2E2015" loc="9"
                    />. </p>
                <p>This long tradition of discourse and practice in the theory and application of
                    scholarly primitives did not necessarily prepare the DARIAH group (later to
                    become the VX Event Programme Committee, the authors of this paper) to
                    intentionally apply these frameworks in the specific context of scholarly
                    meetings, however. Our first exercise as a group, therefore, was to try to
                    translate the various components of a typical scholarly meeting into their
                    functions (the results of which are summarised in Table 1).</p>
                <table>
                    <head> DARIAH VX Preliminary List of Scholarly Activities and Primitives in
                        Meetings</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Component</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Presumed or possible function(s)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Papers, roundtables, keynotes</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Knowledge sharing, verification and certification</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Poster sessions, networking events, hallway chats, coffee
                            breaks</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Semi-structured and serendipitous individual or small
                            group interactions</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">
                            <q>Social listening,</q> common experiences, registration, name badges,
                            buffet dinners, <q>letting hair down</q> with professional peers</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Shared Experiences for community identity building</cell>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Workshops, sidebar meetings</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Collaborative work and learning</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>These results were in some ways not surprising: for example, some elements of a
                    scholarly meeting would inevitably map on to the traditional mechanisms for
                    formal scholarly communications (i.e. the registration, dissemination,
                    certification and archiving functions of scholarly publishing) (c.f. <ptr
                        target="#roosendaal1997"/> and <ptr target="#prosser2013"/>, as cited in
                        <ptr target="#vandeweel_praal2020" loc="26"/>). Other aspects seemed to
                    recognise that for the digital humanities at least, the shifting of traditional
                    practices of sole authorship and single scholarship to more collaborative modes
                    of knowledge co-creation <ptr target="#edmond2016"/>, were driving the scholarly
                    exchange space to be ever more an opportunity to also meet specific milestones
                    for the work of subgroups attending. Perhaps most interesting in the light of
                    later findings, however, was the large amount of space and time we could
                    identify at events that was dedicated to the development of informal networks
                    and social capital. This of course represents trends in the wider scholarly
                    communications ecosystem, but also a certain irony, given that the rise of
                    printed periodicals in the late 17th century was driven in large part as
                    mechanism by which to preserve ephemeral fragments of knowledge that tended to
                    disappear after the informal exchanges from which they originated <ptr
                        target="#fyfe2019" loc="9"/>.</p>
                <p>We were able to apply two further measures to attempt to check any unconscious
                    biases we might be inadvertently allowing overt influence over the event we
                    would design, namely a wider literature review and an effort to crowdsource
                    further input for our model from our event itself. To deliver on the first of
                    these, we sought out existing adjacent research literature to inform our
                    activities, in particular work on <q>Nearly Carbon Neutral</q> (NCN)
                    professional meetings was of great relevance for the questions it had been
                    asking about how and why we might meet in the future, albeit from a perspective
                    driven by environmental sustainability, rather than a global pandemic. Given its
                    connections to the DH community, of special interest were the set of
                    pre-publication blog posts and releases for the collection <title rend="italic"
                        >Right Research: Modelling Sustainable Research Practices in the
                        Anthropocene</title>
                    <ptr target="#rockwellforthcoming"/>. In particular the taxonomy of
                        <q>presences</q> developed there, highlighting social, cognitive and
                    leadership presences, as well as the space where research agendae can be
                    negotiated <ptr target="#rockwell2020a"/> provided the DARIAH VX team with a
                    perspective on the values of the scholarly meeting that organised similar
                    observations to our own according to a different organising principle. </p>
                <p>Clancy <ptr target="#clancy2020"/> provides an excellent review of research
                    across a number of fields into the question of whether conferences facilitate
                    collaboration. In spite what one might see as a relatively narrow, STEM specific
                    conceit underlying the studies he cites (the measure of collaboration being a
                    shared publication or funding application within a relatively limited period of
                    time) the results did still provide a resounding confirmation of the vibrancy of
                    interactions as a facilitator for knowledge consolidation, with one study <ptr
                        target="#boudreau2017"/> demonstrating that being in a randomly assigned
                    discussion room increased the probability of submitting a joint grant proposal
                    by 75%. On the other hand, as the author concluded, these studies all focussed
                    on face-to-face interaction itself, not in comparison with virtual alternatives. </p>
                <p>Interestingly, we found that our conceptualisation of the virtual scholarly
                    meeting from the ground up led us to very different conclusions from some of the
                    existing literature. Two particular points of departure were the benefits of
                    asynchronicity as proposed by <ptr target="#rockwell2020b"/> and the capacity
                    for virtual meetings to be more inclusive (a benefit cited by <ptr
                        target="#byrdforthcoming"/>). On the former issue, while of course making
                    materials available in multiple formats provides some benefits, our analysis of
                    the social and intellectual processes involved in a scholarly meeting led us to
                    believe that it was precisely the informality and ephemerality of many of these
                    engagements that delivered the most value, and that enhancing their formal
                    aspects might achieve a different aim, but not perhaps the most crucial ones of
                    supporting openness and disruptive thinking and interaction. On the second
                    issue, while we would agree that anything that increases access to knowledge for
                    marginalised groups is a benefit, we saw strong threats possible that the
                    virtual could lower barriers in some ways only to raise them in others. This
                    could bring not only the impact of technical digital divides and time zones more
                    to the fore, but of course also make it more difficult to hear voices, such as
                    those of early career researchers, that might not come in to such a meeting
                    already confident or empowered. It could perhaps also perpetuate assumptions
                    that just because someone <emph>can</emph> log in to a meeting from their home
                    means that they <emph>will</emph> be afforded the time and space they need to
                    truly participate.</p>
                <p>The unprecedented times made us aware of a need to gather perspectives specific
                    to the current moment as well, however. We therefore decided that, in the spirit
                    of inclusivity and engagement we wanted to place at the heart of the DARIAH VX
                    event, we would also solicit input from participants at the point of
                    registration as to what they felt the latent and manifest purposes of scholarly
                    meetings were, and what place these events held for them in the landscape of
                    inputs and opportunities they might have for personal and professional
                    development. In the registration form, we included two sets of questions. The
                    first question asked: <quote rend="inline">Please give us up to three of your
                        most important reasons for attending meetings with other
                        researchers.</quote> We also asked, for each example, whether the person
                    felt that a given <q>primitive</q> was better served by the analogue context,
                    the virtual context, or both. The second information request was more open, and
                    designed to explore the anecdotal and emotional weight of scholarly meetings:
                        <quote rend="inline">Please share with us your strongest memory of a
                        scholarly meeting (positive or negative)</quote>.</p>
                <p>Ultimately, 85 people registered for the event and filled in this information,
                    from which we then extracted and aligned key terms with each other (as we had
                    not controlled the participant’s vocabulary) and with our enriched internally
                    defined set of functions. While the crowdsourced responses to the first question
                    did not contradict the initial framework, they did enrich it greatly, and
                    brought out a couple of key nuances, in particular the very strong weight given
                    to the informal, open-ended aspects of the interaction meetings enabled and fact
                    that these <q>people processes</q> were perceived to be far less well-served in
                    the virtual environment than those that supported the circulation of ideas.
                    These responses were distilled into the following visualisation in Figure 1.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Visualisation of the Emerging Primitives as Processes</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                    <figDesc>flowchart of crowdsourced responses to what purposes serve, arranged
                        from left to right in order of which purposes are well-served by virtual
                        platforms to which are poorly served. From best-served to worst-served, the
                        groups of purposes are: Formal publication; Present, get feedback,
                        listen/learn; Discuss, exchange informally, experience; and Build networks,
                        build projects, build/maintain communities, something more...</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p>What perhaps is more interesting and surprising for its intensity, if not its
                    content per se, was the overwhelming preponderance of strongly positive accounts
                    given in the personal anecdotes. With one exception, all of the responses to
                    this question related not just positive experiences, but very strongly positive
                    ones, deeply personal and often life-changing. An extract of some of the common
                    terms appearing in this corpus is as follows in Table 2.</p>
                <table>
                    <head>Emotional Vocabulary of Scholarly Meetings, Extracted from Participant
                        Anecdotes</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Inspiration, Productive, Passion, Creativity, Liberating
                            departure from the norm, Different contexts coming together, Taking
                            risks, Discovery, Unique ideas, Contacts made, Connections solidified,
                            Still vivid, Conversations through the night, Lasting impact, Curiosity
                            and motivation, Feel part of a community, Share, Delighted, Supportive,
                            Friends smiling, Warmth, Glad to be valued, Recognised, Positive
                            experience</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">Changed my attitude, Changed my life</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>This led us to conclude that while the manifest purpose of scholarly meetings
                    might well be achieved in a number of ways, the latent purpose of building
                    careers, friendships and professional identities was not only present, but
                    exceptionally strong.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Creating the Virtual Exchange Event</head>
                <p>We decided upon a suite of seven tactics that we felt would have the most impact
                    on making the event both informative but also different, in the sense of the
                    idea of paradigmatic regression developed by Joris van Zundert <ptr
                        target="#vanzundert2016"/>, questioning preconceived notions in the attempt
                    to achieve something different. These tactics were as follows:</p>
                <p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>A pre-workshop virtual exhibition to allow participants to <q>settle
                                in</q> to the cognitive space</item>
                        <item>Use of plenaries to establish a common set of themes, informal tone,
                            build community and instill certain social norms</item>
                        <item>Incorporation of crowdsourced insight from registration into the
                            event, including professional assessments and personal anecdotes</item>
                        <item>Emphasis on breakout session discussions</item>
                        <item>Embed a contrasting, but complementary, arts research
                            perspective</item>
                        <item>Keeping technologies deployed few and simple</item>
                        <item>Rich and open communication before the event and documentation
                            afterward</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>This set of guiding principles and the instruments that delivered them mapped
                    onto our refined set of primitives we wanted to address as per Table 3, which
                    are discussed in more detail below.</p>
                <table>
                    <head>Mapping Primitives to Event Activities</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label"><q>Primitive</q> or transversal</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Our Response</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">A. Management of the constraints: transparent technology,
                            ‘channelled’ distraction</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Small number of commonly used, well-tested tools, well
                            prepared and socially supported implementation, strong
                            ‘narrative’</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">B. Community identity building and sharing of experiences,
                            embodied and situated learning</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Sharing of stories, ‘crowdsourced’ plenary, unique format
                            and informal tone, artistic reflection, opening breathing exercise,
                            Embedded ‘Liveness’ project</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">C. Serendipitous discovery, making (new, contextualised)
                            connections between ideas and people</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Break out session format and interactions, exhibition,
                            encouragement to network</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="data">D. Semi-formal knowledge sharing: presenting, learning,
                            feedback</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Plenary, approach to documentation (recordings, notes,
                            capture, reports), pre-event questionnaire, post-event survey</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <div>
                    <head> A. Managing the technologies and data: before, during and after the event </head>
                    <p>Mapping the above considerations about the scholarly primitives of online
                        events into the practicalities of setting the virtual stage for the
                        synchronous event also entailed making informed choices about the technology
                        we relied on. The enormous impact the COVID-19 pandemic had on IT
                        infrastructures and especially on online meeting services (see e.g. <ptr
                            target="#abusaada_elshater2020"/>, <ptr target="#zaveri2020"/>) made the
                        ethical complexities inherent in their use, acquisition and development,
                        together with how exposed we were to them (see e.g. discussed in <ptr
                            target="#stoviac2020"/>, <ptr target="#lau2020"/>) even more malleable.
                        Although many of us would have preferred an open source alternative
                        (particularly given some of Zoom’s privacy issues, see <ptr
                            target="#doyle2020"/>), we had to prioritise three core criteria at
                        short notice: reliable performance, rich functionality, and the degree of
                        familiarity of DARIAH communities with the tools in question. We also wanted
                        to ensure we followed best practices shared in our broader communities, such
                        as the experiences of the COPIM team with moving events online and setting
                        up breakout rooms the smoothest possible way <ptr target="#barnes2020"/>. </p>
                    <p>To keep a delicate balance between giving to our audience the richest
                        possible experience vs. avoiding cognitive overload in online meetings and
                        learning environments (see e.g. <ptr target="#costley2020"/>), we decided
                        not to involve external tools (e.g. Mentimeter, Miro, Mural etc.) but put
                        the emphasis on maximizing the potentials of Zoom (e.g. via using break out
                        rooms, facilitating exchange in different chat rooms, enabling the audience
                        to share content etc.) instead to facilitate serendipitous discussions of
                        different sorts between and across speakers, breakout chairs and the members
                        of the audience. In doing so, the help of technical facilitators was
                        required. These support roles, forming human bridges between the technical
                        and people, included a technical coordinator who was responsible for the
                        overall smooth running of the online event (setting up and tailoring the
                        virtual environment to our needs, testing, managing different contributor
                        roles and enabling content sharing, setting up the break out rooms and
                        assigning people to them, supporting members of the audience with connection
                        problems or getting lost in the virtual spaces) and technical facilitators
                        (members of the DARIAH Central Office) in each breakout room. They made sure
                        that everyone arrived and felt comfortable in their breakout rooms and also
                        provided help with note taking (using the one additional tool we did allow
                        ourselves, Google documents). </p>
                    <p>DARIAH’s well-established routine of conducting virtual scholarly meetings as
                        well as the best practices we incorporated in our technical set-up enabled
                        the smooth running of the synchronous event. However, the following three
                        specificities of online events are noteworthy for organizers of future
                        events. Firstly, we saw a significant difference between the number of
                        registrations to the event (with breakout room pre-assignments) versus the
                        actual participants. Although, a discrepancy in registrations and actual
                        online participation is common, it was a challenge to assign the sufficient
                        number of participants to all the seven breakout rooms. Secondly, enabling
                        small-group interactions in itself does not break down academic hierarchy.
                        We observed that not all the attendees felt comfortable joining the
                        discussions in smaller breakout room settings, even with the encouraging and
                        sensible contributions of the breakout chairs. Thirdly, for these sessions
                        to work well, they need to be well staffed, and those contributors need to
                        be well briefed on their specific roles. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head> B. Structuring the synchronous event for community building </head>
                    <p>Although the preparation phase for this event was given particular attention,
                        we did not feel that any more than a two-hour event would be productive: one
                        of the greatest misunderstandings of the early days of day-long face-to-face
                        meetings being taken virtual was the assumption that an eight hour session
                        in a room could simply be replaced by a similar day of work online. Even
                        within this limited window, we felt that a variety of interaction types
                        would be needed, each no longer than 30 minutes. We therefore ultimately
                        decided on a structure composed of 1) an opening plenary; 2) breakout
                        sessions; 3) a short break followed by a presentation on presence and
                        connection informed by a piece of performing arts research we would
                        commission; and 4) a closing plenary to share the results of the breakout
                        groups and wrap up the event. In each of these sessions, we were mindful of
                        what we wanted both the meeting and and the virtual medium to achieve, with
                        the results as follows.</p>
                    <div>
                        <head> Opening and closing plenaries </head>
                        <p>Given the goal of the meeting to draw people together into a sense of
                            having experienced something communal, we felt that we would not be able
                            to avoid an opening plenary. The risk of this strategy, however, was
                            that people would fall too easily into the habits of large virtual
                            meetings, (over)stretching their cognitive capacities in a state that
                            technology consultant, Linda Stone, has named <quote rend="inline"
                                >Continuous Partial Attention</quote>
                            <ptr target="#stone2009"/>. We therefore deployed a number of specific
                            measures within this block in order to maintain not just shreds of
                            attention, but engagement with the ideas and topics we were hoping to
                            focus on. </p>
                        <p>Firstly, we considered the impact that recording the event may have on
                            the comfort level of participants to exchange semi-formally. The
                            plenaries were the only sessions we recorded, in spite of our desire to
                            have as full a record as possible of the event. Ultimately, we decided
                            that having the comprehensive record that technology <emph>could</emph>
                            give us should not be allowed to exercise a potential chilling effect or
                            over-formality on what the participants <emph>would</emph> give us,
                            particularly in the breakout sessions. In-person conference exchanges
                            are not traced and documented, and the DARIAH VX Event aimed to promote
                            the freedom of the ephemeral.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, the plenary moderator (DARIAH Director, Jennifer Edmond) asked
                            all of the participants to pause before the start of the session to take
                            three breaths with her. The idea of using this technique to open the
                            programme was suggested by the arts researcher on the programme
                            committee, Courtney Grile, as a way to bring an element of the shared
                            physical grounding of the face-to-face meeting — the tang of a
                            particular floor cleaner, the waft of an urn of coffee outside the door,
                            the humidity on a rainy day, the shadows through the windows on a sunny
                            day — that we lose in virtual spaces. Breath is a powerful centre point
                            for creating a communal experience, but also had a signalling function
                            for us, indicating that it was our intention to deliver an event that
                            did not abide by the established heuristics by which scholars generally
                            navigate their meetings. </p>
                        <p>Thirdly, we laid the desired foundation for how we wanted people to
                            participate. Some of these were simple and general aspects of good
                            virtual behaviour: mute your microphone, turn off notifications to the
                            extent you can, try to keep your attention on the topic, if not on the
                            presentation, be kind, be generous, be empathetic. But we also used this
                            phase to encourage what could have been seen as a new social norm with a
                                <q>rule-breaking</q> role, namely that we encouraged the virtual
                            version of chatting in the back of the plenary room. We drew attention
                            to the participants list and the chat window, and explicitly encouraged
                            people to take advantage of whatever back channels they were comfortable
                            with to reach out to fellow participants they knew. For people who might
                            be new to the community, we explicitly invited them to make contact with
                            one of three programme committee members (the authors of this paper)
                            whose role in that session was specifically to be available for
                            questions and informal conversation. The rationale for this
                            encouragement to not to pay attention to the plenary was twofold: first,
                            full attention was unlikely anyway but second, we wanted to try to
                            emulate the experience of what we referred to as <q>shared social
                                listening,</q> that communal experience of not just hearing the same
                            words and processing the same ideas at the same time, but of also
                            weaving those words and ideas into our own neural and social networks,
                            the intellectual and relational components of our professional
                            identities.</p>
                        <p>After these preliminaries, we moved to the opening plenary presentation
                            of what we wanted the event to achieve and what inspirations underpinned
                            it. In this session as well, however, the emphasis was on the communal
                            experience of knowledge creation, balancing aspects of our formal
                            secondary literature review with the insights from the registration
                            process, described above. This attempt to keep the focus on the
                            knowledge of the group assembled, rather than of the programme committee
                            or of a small group of individuals was continued in the closing plenary
                            as well, which moved through four stepping stones chosen to bring a
                            sense of closure to the group and the experience. </p>
                        <p>The closing included an efficient, open and thought-provoking reporting
                            format from the breakout discussions (see a description of this below);
                            a <q>reveal</q> of how our event had been conceptualised to meet the
                            needs the collected input led us to focus on; a brief report drawn from
                            expert input on the question of what the future technologies for virtual
                            interaction might hold (as provided in advance of the event by Professor
                            Sarah Kenderdine, a member of the DARIAH Scientific Advisory Board), and
                            a brief reflection on some of the lessons the DARIAH VX programme
                            committee felt they had learned in the course of developing the VX
                            content and structure. Recordings of these plenaries were added to the
                            virtual exhibition after the event so participants could re-visit them
                            and reflect upon any key moments or inspired thoughts they had. The
                            advantage of digital media is that participants could use the recordings
                            as memory triggers for any desired follow-up actions, which can be
                            common outcomes after non-virtual conferences. These recordings are
                            available at: <ref target="https://www.virtualexchange.dariah.eu/"
                                >https://www.virtualexchange.dariah.eu/</ref>.<note>For
                                sustainability reasons, the VX team decided to guarantee the
                                availability of this website for 2 years after the event.
                                Furthermore, an archived version of it is available at the Internet
                                Archive: <ref
                                    target="https://web.archive.org/web/20210228115702/https://www.virtualexchange.dariah.eu/"
                                    >https://web.archive.org/web/20210228115702/https://www.virtualexchange.dariah.eu/</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head> C. Serendipity and the prepared mind: The Virtual Exhibition &amp;
                            Liveness Investigation </head>
                        <p>If engagement, serendipity, discovery and connection all seemed to be
                            impoverished in virtual meetings, The DARIAH VX would need to find some
                            way to encourage its participants to give themselves the time and space
                            to prepare their minds if the event was to be a success. In addition, we
                            realised in our preparations that what we could never recreate in a
                            virtual space was the situated, physical, embodied experiences and
                            learning of the face-to-face meeting, and thus we had to think from an
                            early moment of how we might bring in an explicit conceptual element to
                            our event to explore these aspects. DARIAH’s position as an
                            infrastructure for the arts as well as the humanities gives us a broad
                            community of practitioners, and no one knows better than theatre
                            practitioners the difference between live engagement and interactions
                            mediated by space, cameras and microphones. Thus, we engaged in a meta
                            reflection of this through the Liveness Investigation. </p>
                        <div>
                            <head>The Virtual Exhibition</head>
                            <p>The intention behind the exhibition was to recreate the sense of
                                anticipation and serendipity in knowledge acquisition that one
                                achieves through conference attendance by creating a <foreign
                                    xml:lang="de">Wunderkammer</foreign> of resources: offering
                                multiple routes to different items, with no expectation that all
                                participants might engage with every single item on display. To
                                achieve this, a few different platforms were investigated, however,
                                in order to complete this in the limited time available and to keep
                                it simple, it was decided that a Wordpress.org based site was the
                                most feasible and the layout allowed for the serendipitous
                                discovery. </p>
                            <p>The structure of the virtual exhibition was informed by the most
                                common spaces found at face-to-face meetings, and the information
                                one may find in them (see Figures 2-4). For example, the
                                Registration Desk offered lists of fellow participants, practical
                                information such as how to sign up to the main Virtual Exchange
                                event, and a programme of events. It also introduced the
                                organisation (DARIAH) and the team behind the event, and provided
                                some links relevant to the topic of Scholarly Primitives. The main
                                auditorium, renamed here as the Knowledge Exchange Space, had the
                                items related to the themes of the live event grouped thematically,
                                sometimes overlapping, or offering different perspectives on similar
                                topics. Finally came the Coffee Break Space that encouraged
                                interaction and allowed for less formal discussions around the
                                themes of the event (including the participant anecdotes and
                                COVID-19). The Coffee Break section of the virtual exhibition also
                                included resources intended to invoke, if not truly serve, some of
                                the most prominent latent purposes of scholarly meetings,
                                referencing interpersonal connections and a sense of space and place
                                with links to various audio-visual experiences elsewhere on the
                                internet. This included a Spotify playlist<note>Available at: <ref
                                        target="https://open.spotify.com/playlist/2NY1Niw6CNmcBWYCMGkBGP?si=ba00cf7dbaff48ce"
                                        >https://open.spotify.com/playlist/2NY1Niw6CNmcBWYCMGkBGP?si=ba00cf7dbaff48ce</ref></note>
                                compiled by members of the DARIAH Coordination Office, who are
                                themselves dispersed across Europe and offer a wide selection of
                                idiosyncratic musical tastes, and a place to upload a <q>deskie</q>
                                photo that would allow participants to share images of their
                                participation spaces with the wider group. </p>
                            <figure>
                                <head>Virtual Exhibition <q>Registration Desk</q> Page</head>
                                <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                                <figDesc>Screencapture of the Registration Desk page of the DARIAH
                                    website. It features a banner image at the top showing a stock
                                    image of a lobby, with a receptionist at a desk in the
                                    foreground and groups of people walking through the lobby. Below
                                    the banner image are navigation icons which read <title
                                        rend="quotes">About this event,</title>
                                    <title rend="quotes">About DARIAH,</title>
                                    <title rend="quotes">On Scholarly Primitives,</title> and <title
                                        rend="quotes">Programme Committee.</title></figDesc>
                            </figure>
                            <figure>
                                <head>Entry page for the <q>Knowledge Exchange</q> Space</head>
                                <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                                <figDesc>Screencapture of the Knowledge Exchange entry page. At the
                                    top of the page is a brief description of the knowledge exchange
                                    space. The description reads, <quote rend="inline">Here you can
                                        explore a selection of resources and ideas exploring the
                                        many primitives of and issues surrounding scholarly
                                        meetings, together with a broader range of source relating
                                        to the current COVID-19 crisis.This living online
                                        exhibition, organised by DARIAH-EU, will be updated from 21
                                        until 28 May 2020. This exhibition acts as a pool of prompts
                                        and provocations for thought and conversation, a dialogue
                                        that will culminate in a 2-hour synchronous virtual exchange
                                        session on the 28th (from 14:00-16:00 UTC+1). Further
                                        information about the event, the team behind it, the topic
                                        and other COVID-related initiatives that inspired this
                                        structure are available here.(ed note — the word here is a
                                        hyperlink.) To facilitate and encourage serendipitous
                                        discovery, we have arranged the resources in the following
                                        formats: 1. as a set of Thematic Research Collection; 2. As
                                        a provisional list of scholarly primitives of scholarly
                                        meetings; 3. As an exhibition "floor plan;" 4. As a dynamic,
                                        multi-dimensional presentation.</quote> Below it are
                                    navigation icons which read <title rend="quotes">Thematic
                                        Research Collection,</title>
                                    <title rend="quotes">Scholarly Primitives,</title>
                                    <title rend="quotes">Exhibition Floor Plan,</title> and <title
                                        rend="quotes">VX Presentation.</title></figDesc>
                            </figure>
                            <figure>
                                <head>Navigation in the <q>Coffee Break</q> Space</head>
                                <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                                <figDesc>Screencapture of the Coffe Break navigation icons, which
                                    read <title rend="quotes">Social Dinner,</title>
                                    <title rend="quotes">My Corona 2020 Playlist,</title>
                                    <title rend="quotes">Send a#DHDeskie,</title>
                                    <title rend="quotes">Networking,</title>
                                    <title rend="quotes">A sense of place,</title> and <title
                                        rend="quotes">Talking Covid.</title></figDesc>
                            </figure>
                            <p>These three elements within the Virtual Exhibition allowed
                                participants to spend as much or as little time as they wanted
                                (without making them feel it was something they needed to
                                    <q>complete</q>) finding new perspectives on the theme of the
                                Virtual Exchange. There was discussion among the programme committee
                                as to whether we should include a <q>floor plan</q> that listed all
                                the items on offer, or whether it would be best to allow
                                participants to discover things for themselves, in an <q>easter
                                    egg</q> style. Ultimately we decided to keep the sense of
                                serendipitous discovery by not providing this floor plan. Additional
                                challenges in creating this space lay in the decisions around which
                                items best fit into which spaces, and identifying at what point we
                                might start imposing our own biases on the pathways people could
                                take through the exhibition and risk removing the sense of
                                accidental discovery that we wanted to achieve. As ever, knowledge
                                organisation and asset curation is a challenge, so we made sure to
                                flag very clearly to participants the status of these resources as
                                    <q>prompts and provocations</q> rather than a complete, fully
                                theorised, scholarly collection. A full list of the assets in the
                                Virtual Exhibition appears in Appendix 1 of this paper.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head> The Liveness Investigation: An arts-based response </head>
                            <p>The ideas of liveness and co-presence are inextricably linked with
                                drama practice. While many theatre arts practitioners have begun to
                                play with new technologies in order to adapt and bring them into
                                arts practice, the COVID-19 pandemic has accelerated innovation and
                                rethinking of how it might be possible to practice the craft in an
                                online setting. Within applied drama praxis, with its focus on
                                embodiment and collaboration, the tools of drama/theatre were
                                specifically utilised in the DARIAH VX event in order to explore
                                ideas and create dialogue amongst participants. The collective
                                knowledge that is generated through this process relies on
                                participants’ absorption and interpretation of information through
                                their entire being: all of their senses, body, mind, and
                                feelings/emotions. How is this altered when it is moved into a
                                completely online space? What might be gained? What might be
                                lost?</p>
                            <p>In the spirit of <q>show me, don’t tell me</q> (a mantra of theatre
                                educators around the globe), the <title rend="quotes">Liveness
                                    Investigation</title> created specifically for this DARIAH VX
                                event sought to explore this topic as a meta-reflection through a
                                presentation and discussion of a piece of research that compared two
                                instances of theatrical collaboration with the same format and
                                participants, but delivered ten years apart. The first collaboration
                                was conducted in a physical space that was captured during the
                                development of a 2011 project entitled <title rend="quotes">The
                                    Other F Word</title>, and then again with the same participants
                                in a virtual space. The presentation to the DARIAH VX participants
                                also included the reflections from the <title rend="quotes">The
                                    Other F Word</title> workshop participants on the adaptation
                                from an in-person setting to an online one, and of the project
                                leaders.</p>
                            <p>The biggest takeaway from this exploration for the participants and
                                the Artist-Researcher who facilitated it was the understanding that
                                moving the practice online created something new, with new
                                possibilities. Many elements of connection that manifest when
                                sharing physical space, such as nuanced nonverbal communication
                                (especially eye contact) and kinetic information relayed through
                                placement, proxemics, and direction were largely lost in the online
                                space. The in-person <q>machines</q>, which were made up of small
                                groups of live performing artists, allowed for each contributor to
                                build upon what the previous person had offered. The creative
                                process for working in shared physical space allowed for deeper
                                co-creation and collaboration intrinsically during the act of
                                creation. This is in contrast with the <q>machines</q> that were
                                created online being much more of a collage of individual
                                contributions to the ideas offered (such as the <q>love machine</q>
                                or <q>hate machine</q>). The online creative process was marked by
                                most individuals responding<note>There is one exception where a
                                    participant expressed afterward that their contribution was in
                                    response to an earlier contributor, but this was not readily
                                    apparent to any other participant during the reflection.</note>
                                on their own to create within a kind of vacuum — with the
                                collaboration and meaning-making actually coming afterward in the
                                workshop reflection in which there was an attempt to create
                                understanding about the machine as a whole. The online practice
                                showed signs of potentially further empowering participants to
                                contribute more personal, individualised responses, however.</p>
                            <p>In light of these discoveries, what becomes clear is that the format
                                (in-person or online) which will be most conducive for a meeting,
                                workshop, or gathering depends on the purpose and goals of the
                                gathering. If it is crucial to build a sense of community and
                                co-create contemporaneously, then an in-person setting would be
                                ideal. However, if it is crucial to allow space for each participant
                                to act individually, then an online platform may well be optimal for
                                highlighting that endeavour. The nature of these differences, and
                                the manner in which technological affordances might be modified in
                                order to be more focussed on certain kinds of interaction defined in
                                these terms, is still largely unexplored. While a great deal more
                                remains to be explored in this area, it feels necessary to encourage
                                a <q>both/and</q> way of moving forward with in-person and online
                                gatherings rather than an <q>either/or</q> model when it becomes
                                available post-COVID. Insights from this exploration were further
                                integrated into the DARIAH VX event through the inclusion of a small
                                breathing exercise informed by applied drama praxis. The Prezi and
                                videos of the Liveness Investigation can be found here: <ref
                                    target="https://prezi.com/view/sBDCS3iZisELjh76VCq1/"
                                    >https://prezi.com/view/sBDCS3iZisELjh76VCq1/</ref></p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head> D. Breakout sessions and semi-formal knowledge sharing </head>
                        <p>The breakout sessions in the DARIAH VX event were included as a way to
                            encourage engagement and connection among participants on topics that
                            are not commonly appearing in the research-output focused programmes of
                            in-person conference. The same registration form that solicited their
                            input about events and primitives was also used to recruit presentations
                            and to identify and cluster their interests resulting in seven breakout
                            session themes, titled as follows:</p>
                        <p>
                            <list type="ordered">
                                <item><title rend="quotes">Making (virtual) interactions work
                                        better</title>
                                    <lb/> Presenters: Rimi Nandy (Adamas University) and Sarah
                                    Middle (Open University)</item>
                                <item><title rend="quotes">Breaking down barriers — of career stage,
                                        language, discipline or other — between researchers</title>
                                    <lb/> Presenters: Paul Spence (King's College London) and Nicole
                                    Basaraba (Trinity College Dublin)</item>
                                <item>
                                    <title rend="quotes">Academics in the Ether: Tackling the
                                        challenges of working away from the office</title>
                                    <lb/>Presenters: Claire Warwick (Durham University) and Mariann
                                    Hardey (Durham University) </item>
                                <item><title rend="quotes">DH Methods and Tools Gone Wrong:
                                        Discoveries, Failures &amp; Advice for the Future</title>
                                    <lb/>Presenters: Quinn Dombrowski (Stanford University) and
                                    Amelia del Rosario Sanz (Universidad Complutense)</item>
                                <item><title rend="quotes">Working together to move forward:
                                        Fostering collaboration for projects, grant proposals, or
                                        publications</title>
                                    <lb/>Presenters: Michelle Doran (Trinity College Dublin) and
                                    Francesca Morselli (DARIAH-EU)</item>
                                <item><title rend="quotes">The Academic Footprint: Sustainable
                                        methods for knowledge exchange</title>
                                    <lb/>Presenter: Geoffrey Rockwell (University of Alberta)</item>
                                <item><title rend="quotes">In Praise of Presence: Why do we travel
                                        to meet?</title>
                                    <lb/>Presenters: Vicky Garnett (Trinity College Dublin) and
                                    Courtney Grile (Trinity College Dublin)</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Participants were informed before the sessions that discussion would take
                            place in small groups, last 30 minutes, and were designed as
                            opportunities to make connections based on common interests and share
                            ideas. Each session was supported by a DARIAH VX organising team member,
                            a chair, a support person who served as rapporteur of the discussions
                            and one or two presenters who opened the discussion with some
                            thought-provoking ideas in a five-minute presentation. The Zoom platform
                            breakout groups function was used to move participants to/from the small
                            group which was pre-selected based on shared interests stated in the
                            pre-attendance questionnaire. Participants were also informed that the
                            sessions would not be recorded and that we had set up shared documents
                            for each group in which they could keep a record of their discussion. </p>
                        <p>Each of the seven breakout sessions focussed on some facet of academic
                            conferences, in-person versus virtual, and the impacts these formats
                            have in terms of travel, sustainability, and ability and methods for
                            researcher collaborations, and were designed to provide participants
                            with a chance to emulate the informal discussions that happen in the
                            hallways after conference presentations or at the coffee station, rather
                            than more formal question and answer discussions after a 15-20 minute
                            presentation from each speaker. The breakout sessions were 30 minutes
                            long and participants were pre-divided into groups of less than 10
                            people each, to ensure the potential for real discussion. The breakout
                            sessions were not recorded but the rapporteur took notes in a shared
                            Google document that all session participants could view and contribute
                            to. Across the seven sessions, four main themes of conversation emerged
                            which were: (1) navigating personal and professional spaces, (2)
                            technical and financial practicalities, (3) methods of communication,
                            and (4) academic status.</p>
                        <p>In terms of navigating personal and professional spaces, breakout session
                            participants discussed how working from home during COVID-19 has created
                            greater challenges in separating the formal workspace and time from
                            leisure and family time in the home. Academics may try to multitask
                            during online conferences, but they need to explicitly block out time
                            for virtual conferences as they would when travelling for an in-person
                            conference. The physical separation of colleagues during COVID-19 had
                            made people more conscious about connecting with those whom they would
                            normally meet informally without making specific plans. This extended to
                            the casual relationship-building that happens at in-person conferences
                            when new people meet professionally, but serendipitously form
                            friendships through the collective experience of listening to
                            presentations and participating in the social and cultural activities.
                            The consensus was that virtual conferences and meetings could be most
                            useful for people who have already met and established a working
                            relationship, but that establishing this rapport was more difficult to
                            build online when meeting someone for the first time.</p>
                        <p>The second theme that arose in discussions surrounded the technical and
                            financial considerations for virtual conferences and meetings. Zoom had
                            emerged as the most popular platform among academics, and video calls
                            often lasted between one to two hours. However, Zoom calls can be
                            exhausting because they take more mental effort to carefully consider
                            what you say since you are in a <q>performance-like</q> situation. There
                            can also be a multitude of possible environmental distractions,
                            including the background views of individuals’ personal spaces, and if
                            two people are meeting for the first time on Zoom, these distractions
                            could be considered unprofessional by the other person due to the lack
                            of a pre-existing relationship. If Zoom calls are recorded, it often
                            results in modified behaviours of participants. There have also been
                            technical and security issues with some virtual calls as well as data
                            protection issues, which in some cases resulted in weakened trust. It
                            was noted that funding would be needed to have technical support for
                            large virtual conference calls, which may also have smaller breakout
                            sessions, in order to permit conversations and presentations to flow
                            without interruption.</p>
                        <p>In regards to methods of communication, some key differences were
                            highlighted between in-person and virtual conferences. DARIAH VX
                            participants noted that sometimes it can be difficult to read people’s
                            body language when online. Tone of voice alone is not always the best
                            way to understand colleagues or conference participants. Another person
                            said that they can become distracted by seeing their own face and
                            background during a video call. Each academic community, whether it be
                            at an annual conference or the specific disciplinary conventions, has
                            different styles and expectations for presentations and interactions,
                            but across the board, it was noted that ability to digitally access and
                            share content is very important to virtual academic exchanges. Issues of
                            inclusion were very much on the minds of the DARIAH participants as
                            well: the presence of a moderator or chair is often needed for larger
                            groups to ensure each voice is heard and that those with questions or
                            comments from the <q>audience</q> get the chance to speak up. In
                            addition, as when many in-person academic conferences are in English,
                            linguistic marginalisation can flatten diversity in the discussions and
                            the academic discipline more generally, a situation only intensified by
                            the impoverishment of online communications. One possible solution
                            offered was to include slides in another language to allow for better
                            communication to those who may not speak or understand English as their
                            primary language. This would allow them to get more out of the
                            presentation/content if they can follow along in their first language.
                            Finally, it can be difficult to connect with another scholar/participant
                            until they give their presentation, as the ability to discuss ideas
                            flows easier after one hears about the other’s interests in more detail.
                            Collaboration often relies on serendipity, but social distancing has
                            drained much of the serendipity out of our professional lives, with
                            everything needing to be scheduled and social media offering an active
                            space for connection, but one in which diversity, complexity and context
                            might be diminished. </p>
                        <p>The final theme that emerged in the discussions was the role of
                            hierarchies and status in academia in relation to attending and playing
                            specific roles in conferences. For example, flying to conferences
                            confers status, yet this culture needs to change for academia to be more
                            inclusive of those who cannot get university funding to travel to
                            exchange knowledge. Another consideration is the limited discussions on
                            academic methods and practice. Early-career researchers may fear that
                            publishing or speaking about their <q>failures</q> or methods that did
                            not produce fruitful research results could have negative consequences
                            for their academic career. On the contrary, in a situation where status
                            or reputation is already assured, it is easier to talk about research
                            shortcomings one has experienced. Without discussing or sharing
                                <q>failures</q> scholarship can fail to move forward, with other
                            scholars making the same mistakes because nobody has documented a
                            similar attempt that did not work. A solution that was offered was that
                            if one scholar does not want to bear the weight of <q>failure</q> alone,
                            they could discuss or publish it as a collective group or write in other
                            venues like on social media.</p>
                        <p>The difference in terms of the keynote speakers versus PhD candidates and
                            the lack of informal conversations between senior and early career
                            scholars is a gap at virtual conferences that some felt in-person
                            conferences were perhaps far better able to facilitate, though not
                            without the investment needed to break down barriers. Thoughts on
                            whether a better model could be developed in the virtual context was an
                            exciting opportunity to explore. People, after all, are the focus of
                            collaboration: we do not work with institutions, we work with each
                            other. Even while there may be an enduring valorisation of the solitary
                            scholar, there is also a generation of scholars who recognise that we
                            often work better together.</p>
                        <p>These breakout sessions offered the participants opportunities not only
                            to explore the themes of the workshop, and put them into the context of
                            their own words and experiences, but also to connect their current
                            experiences to their wider personal and professional lives. In
                            particular topics like hierarchies, dealing with failures, isolation and
                            mental health, and inclusiveness cut to the heart of not just how we
                            might as a community of scholars navigate the <q>new normal,</q> but
                            also how we might use this moment to improve conditions of the
                            preexisting state of scholarly communities. Many of these topics were
                            not specific to digital humanities, and yet the context and many of the
                            connections made, such as the role of collaboration and the tensions
                            between cultural and communicative signals and the technology that
                            mediated them, most certainly were.</p>
                        <p>The DARIAH VX approach to reporting back from the plenaries also
                            reflected our intention to use the opportunity of the COVID-19 forced
                            change in format as an opportunity to rethink the format of the
                            scholarly meeting at a higher level. The group shared a certain
                            frustration with the level of engagement that tended to be accorded to
                            the mechanisms of sharing breakout discussions with a plenary, while
                            also recognising their important role as a social buffer between larger
                            and smaller groups. We therefore asked each group to provide back to the
                            plenary five keywords that reflected central points of their discussion,
                            one challenge statement and one opportunity statement. These inputs were
                            included in the slides for the final plenary, where they were presented
                            and connections between them drawn out, without the opportunity for a
                            longer discussion. The results of this exercise appear in Appendix
                            2.</p>
                        <p>This method had the benefit of allowing the discussions to be seen from
                            an almost <q>distant reading</q> point of view, while also not
                            increasing potential cognitive load on participants with a session of
                            reports that could easily have run long or lacked structure. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Evaluating the DARIAH VX Experience</head>
                    <p>As the DARIAH VX came to an end, the programme committee gathered again to
                        discuss and evaluate the event as an experience both for us as organisers,
                        but also for the audience participating and following the event through
                        social media. What was their experience and how did this compare to ours?
                        Was the event considered meaningful and useful? Had we succeeded in creating
                        an engaging virtual experience? Soon after the event, we launched a
                        post-event survey to capture these reactions and opinions. This survey
                        consisted of eleven multiple choice and three open questions and was left
                        open for two weeks. It welcomed answers from participants but also
                        presenters in the various sessions and organisers. In the end, thirteen
                        people completed the survey and overall they valued positively the event and
                        their participation. Although there was a low response rate, as is also
                        common in optional post-event surveys and not a statistically authoritative
                        sample, it was indicative of another observed phenomenon of the pandemic
                        period, namely a certain virtual activity fatigue, and there were enough
                        strong trends in the responses to merit some concluding reflections
                        here.</p>
                    <p>One of the aims of the event was to encourage informal conversations
                        happening in the background, in parallel to the event, either in social
                        media or in the chat. This was also stressed in the opening keynote, as
                        discussed above. Conferences are great networking opportunities, places to
                        meet colleagues and friends but also make new acquaintances and start new
                        collaborations. Encouraging people to replicate this in the virtual event
                        was again an aspect we hoped to experiment with, to see if we could improve
                        upon the current average standard for this online. In the respective
                        question in the follow up survey (a true/false response to the statement
                            <quote rend="inline">the event helped me to broaden my scholarly
                            networks and make new contacts</quote>) the answers were very diverse.
                        Despite the fact that people did feel part of a community during the event
                        (nine positive responses), most of them were not able to network and start
                        new discussions/collaborations in the background. </p>
                    <p>The whole event, its innovative approach and the rich collection of sources
                        hosted in the virtual exhibition made a very positive buzz on social media
                        and in particular Twitter (the Twitter moment for the event can be found
                        here: <ref
                            target="https://twitter.com/i/moment_maker/preview/1265955693984731136"
                            >https://twitter.com/i/moment_maker/preview/1265955693984731136</ref>).
                        Researchers and projects following the event through Twitter or indeed
                        participating in the DARIAH VX had very positive remarks to share about the
                        experimental approach, take away messages and new terminology emerging with
                        this new virtual space for interaction, the need for conferences and why
                        they are vital to a researcher’s work. These responses also included more
                        informal and personal information, such as images of their home offices and
                        reflections on how they adapted to the new situation. With a feeling of
                            <q>we are in this together</q>, the DARIAH VX created a virtual space
                        for sharing scholarly notions, expressing personal remarks and concerns on
                        the future of conferences, traveling, research and the scholarly profession
                        that was greatly appreciated and was in some way comforting at a time when
                        no physical contact was possible. Providing such an opportunity for personal
                        connection, transcending our disciplines and institutions, may have been in
                        fact one of the most important and telling contributions of the DARIAH
                        VX.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusions</head>
                    <p>The DARIAH VX was an exercise in both theorising a new kind of virtual
                        scholarly meeting based upon a scholarly primitives approach, and,
                        simultaneously, building an exemplary event to demonstrate how such a new
                        paradigm might be enacted. While it may therefore have only cast some
                        tentative first seeds on this broad field for experimentation and
                        consideration, we can certainly propose some of the following as key
                        learnings and points for future work to begin from in the consideration of
                        the future of scholarly meetings:</p>
                    <p>First, we need to better harness the explosion of accepted paradigms for
                        informal scholarly interaction online as resources to hone our virtual and
                        face-to-face meetings. In the realm of written scholarly communications, we
                        are observing a sea change in the rise of informal outlets for sharing
                        scholarly knowledge. While we still may have a long way to go toward
                        protecting this knowledge (in every sense), a better understanding of the
                        interplay between formal and informal layers of scholarship can also improve
                        our practices of meeting.</p>
                    <p>Second, we need to still gather people, e.g. in small, virtually connected
                        groups, so as to <q>seed</q> rich experiences and empathetic responses while
                        still respecting the nomadic nature of knowledge (as already proposed by
                            <ptr target="#fraser2017" loc="540–546"/>) The DARIAH VX <q>Liveness
                            Investigation</q> made clear the essential role of presence in
                        supporting empathy, attention and engagement, but it also asked the question
                        of how much presence we need: is it enough to have a small group around you,
                        to model the kind of trustful, attentive and mindful attitude we should
                        generally approach our scholarly meetings with? Could technology that
                        enabled certain things currently lost, such as <q>real</q> eye contact, make
                        a difference?</p>
                    <p>Third, we need to use mobility more deftly, holistically, mindfully and
                        evenly, making it accessible in ways that don’t simply introduce new and
                        different barriers. Better thinking is needed on how to improve access to
                        knowledge exchange opportunities across the board for non-native English
                        listeners, caregivers, participants in non- or less privileged power
                        hierarchy positions such as Early Career Researchers, not to mention people
                        with disabilities, slow or unreliable broadband, or any number of other
                        challenges to participation.</p>
                    <p>Fourth, we need interaction technologies to get us beyond the skeuomorphic
                        facsimiles of meetings that we have to become spaces of productive
                        interaction. There is incredible tech out there, but for every collaborator
                        you may have who is dedicated to one platform or another, there is another
                        for whom that new tool may present an annoyance, at least, or barrier at
                        worst, in terms of learning curve, bandwidth or screen management.</p>
                    <p>The DARIAH experiment in applying the very central digital humanities
                        paradigm of the scholarly primitive to our interactions rather than our
                        research processes also yielded fruitful and interesting results, bearing
                        out our hypothesis that digital humanities could learn and contribute
                        greater precision to the contemporary debates about how we might optimally
                        adjust to post-incunabular virtual meeting practices. This builds from the
                        foundation where the arts and cultural heritage took an early leadership
                        position in driving social innovations to soften the force of fear and
                        isolation. Cultural heritage institutions from across the world transcended
                        their usual user engagement strategies to innovate and plan virtual paths
                        that would, in the first instance, showcase their content and artifacts and,
                        in the second, make culture a comforting place for people to retreat to and
                        learn from. The challenge of maintaining human contact within and across
                        virtual spaces presented an opportunity and an imperative to understand the
                        art in our science. A recent consideration of art and AI comes to the
                        conclusion that:</p>
                    <cit><quote rend="block">… art emerged as a way for our Pleistocene ancestors to
                            strengthen their social ties and social status. For example, art can
                            serve as gifts, as fitness signals for mating, and as displays of status
                            and tribal affiliation. In each role, the fundamental purpose of art is
                            to affect peoples' relationships with each other, where the
                            relationships are themselves important.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hertzman2020"/></cit>
                    <p>Hertzmann’s ultimate conclusion is that computers can create art, but they
                        don’t need to: people, however, do. While people do also need to create
                        scientific knowledge, they can’t do this without the communities, contexts
                        and interactions that nurture their minds, bodies and souls. Let us hope
                        that we can find creative ways to usher in new forms of scholarly meetings
                        that combine the incentives of both science and art.</p>

                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Appendix 1: DARIAH VX Virtual Exhibition Site Map</head>
                    <p>Parent/child relationships between pages are indicated as follows</p>
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>HOME PAGE</item>
                        <item><list type="simple">
                                <item>Registration Desk</item>
                                <item><list type="simple">
                                        <item>About This Event</item>
                                        <item>About DARIAH</item>
                                        <item>Our Scholarly Primitives**</item>
                                        <item><list>
                                                <item>John Unsworth's Scholarly Primitives</item>
                                                <item>Scholarly Information Practices</item>
                                                <item>Scholarly Primitives of the Scholarly
                                                  Meeting**</item>
                                            </list></item>
                                        <item>Programme Committee</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>Knowledge Exchange</item>
                                <item><list type="simple">
                                        <item>Thematic Research Collection</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <list type="simple">
                                                <item>Art In A Crisis</item>
                                                <item>
                                                  <list type="simple">
                                                  <item>Jogging in Lipstick</item>
                                                  <item>How art can help in an emergency</item>
                                                  <item>Dear Ireland</item>
                                                  <item>Investigating Liveness**</item>
                                                  </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>Exploring and Recording the Cultural Heritage
                                                  Record</item>
                                                <item>
                                                  <list type="simple">
                                                  <item>The Coronavirus Corpus Living in
                                                  Lockdown</item>
                                                  <item>Journal of a Plague Year**</item>
                                                  <item>The Future of Museums</item>
                                                  <item>New Tech and the Preservation of Cultural
                                                  Heritage</item>
                                                  <item>An Intimacy with the Physical World</item>
                                                  <item>Beyond COVID-19</item>
                                                  </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>Eco Conferencing</item>
                                                <item>
                                                  <list type="simple">
                                                  <item>Successful e-conferences</item>
                                                  <item>What Hypocrisy</item>
                                                  <item>A Nearly Carbon-Neutral Model</item>
                                                  <item>The Shift Project</item>
                                                  </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>Virtual Tools &amp; Technology Choices</item>
                                                <item>
                                                  <list type="simple">
                                                  <item>The Sudden Urgency of Online Academic
                                                  Conferences</item>
                                                  <item>A Nearly Carbon-Neutral Model</item>
                                                  <item>A Conference Call in Real Life</item>
                                                  <item>Covid study: Remote working collaboration
                                                  using digital tech</item>
                                                  <item>The reason zoom calls drain your
                                                  energy</item>
                                                  <item>The Brief — Zoom diplomacy</item>
                                                  <item>Move Fast and Roll Your Own Crypto</item>
                                                  <item>Suggestions for protecting <ref
                                                  target="https://zoom.us">zoom.us</ref>
                                                  meetings</item>
                                                  <item>How to keep uninvited guests out of your
                                                  Zoom Event</item>
                                                  <item>Tech against coronavirus</item>
                                                  <item>The Online First model**</item>
                                                  <item>Definitive Guide to Facilitating Remote
                                                  Workshops</item>
                                                  <item>Experimental Models of Knowledge
                                                  Exchange**</item>
                                                  <item>Virtual Conferences: A Guide to Best
                                                  Practices</item>
                                                  </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>Semi Formal Knowledge Exchange</item>
                                                <item>
                                                  <list type="simple">
                                                  <item>Collaboration and Cancelled
                                                  Conferences</item>
                                                  <item>The Learning Conference</item>
                                                  <item>Investigating Liveness**</item>
                                                  <item>The Online First model**</item>
                                                  <item>A Trip Around the World**</item>
                                                  <item>First Aid for Listeners</item>
                                                  <item>Re-examining the role of conference
                                                  paper</item>
                                                  </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>The Role of Space &amp; Place</item>
                                                <item>
                                                  <list type="simple">
                                                  <item>Investigating Liveness**</item>
                                                  <item>Why I Travel (for work)</item>
                                                  <item>Experimental Models of Knowledge
                                                  Exchange**</item>
                                                  </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>Inclusivity &amp; Accessibility</item>
                                                <item>
                                                  <list type="simple">
                                                  <item>Representation at DH Conferences
                                                  (2000-2015)</item>
                                                  <item>A Family-Friendly Policy?</item>
                                                  <item>Publication Submission During
                                                  Coronavirus</item>
                                                  <item>Be More Than Binary</item>
                                                  <item>Liberating Structures</item>
                                                  <item>A Trip Around the World**</item>
                                                  </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>The Value of the AHSS</item>
                                                <item>
                                                  <list type="simple">
                                                  <item>World Pandemic Research Network</item>
                                                  <item>Why We Need More Than Just Scientists</item>
                                                  <item>Covid-19 Crisis Blog</item>
                                                  <item>Mapping the Public Value of the
                                                  Humanities</item>
                                                  <item>Interdisciplinarity in the Times of
                                                  Crisis</item>
                                                  <item>Shaping Interdisciplinary Practices in
                                                  Europe</item>
                                                  <item>Irish Humanities Alliance</item>
                                                  <item>Integrating Social Sciences and Humanities
                                                  in Interdisciplinary Research</item>
                                                  <item>Using Social and Behavioural Science to
                                                  Support COVID-19 Pandemic Response</item>
                                                  <item>Sociology and the Social Sciences in the
                                                  COVID-19 crisis</item>
                                                  </list>
                                                </item>
                                            </list>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>Scholarly Primitives**</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <list type="simple">
                                                <item>John Unsworth's Scholarly Primitives</item>
                                                <item>Scholarly Information Practices</item>
                                                <item>Scholarly Primitives of the Scholarly
                                                  Meeting**</item>
                                            </list>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>Exhibition Floor Plan</item>
                                        <item>VX Presentation</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>Coffee Break</item>
                                <item>
                                    <list type="simple">
                                        <item>Social Dinner</item>
                                        <item>MY Corona Spotify Playlist</item>
                                        <item>Send A #Deskie</item>
                                        <item>Networking</item>
                                        <item>Talking Covid</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <list type="simple">
                                                <item>Times Higher Ed COVID</item>
                                                <item>Hungary AVOBMAT</item>
                                                <item>Journal of a Plague Year**</item>
                                                <item>Erzsébet's Open Science Blog Post</item>
                                                <item>FT COVID Stats</item>
                                                <item>Irish Humanities Response</item>
                                            </list>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>Sense of Place</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <list type="simple">
                                                <item>Noises Of Paris</item>
                                                <item>Musee D\'Orsay</item>
                                                <item>Sounds Of Home</item>
                                                <item>Zagreb Arts And Crafts</item>
                                                <item>BL Wildlife Sounds</item>
                                                <item>Claire Warwick Slides</item>
                                            </list>
                                        </item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Appendix 2:Reporting from the DARIAH VX Breakout Sessions</head>

                    <p>The list of keywords was as follows: uneasy, domestic, accessibility, aura,
                        interactivity, participation, trust, intentionality, diversity, failing
                        gloriously, distance, mentorship, connecting individuals, eternal
                        prototypes, respect, networking, place, noise, stigma, facilitating (role of
                        institution) cultural experience, social bonds. </p>
                    <p>The list of challenges was: <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Where it is hard to concentrate, compose oneself or know when to
                                be heard;</item>
                            <item>Attention of participants/ Control of Students / Multiple channels
                                / Risk Situation / Surveillance;</item>
                            <item>What's stopping you from talking about failure? It could be
                                (mostly) unfounded to think too much about what funders/colleagues
                                may think;</item>
                            <item>Small conferences are/might be better in handling this — digital
                                conferences which by aspiration/default are large are less suitable
                                for that;</item>
                            <item>We do not want to lose the connection and the rich
                                experience;</item>
                            <item>Personal VS professional life, how much do we share; and</item>
                            <item>The environmental impact of travel, the monetary expense and if we
                                can travel in after times</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The list of opportunities was: <list type="unordered">
                            <item>To experience new ways to simply 'be' in digital space.</item>
                            <item>maybe we can make interactions more accessible across barriers
                                (economic, career stage, regional)</item>
                            <item>Flexibility and inclusiveness</item>
                            <item>Towards a taxonomy of failure</item>
                            <item>We need a look-up, inspirational corner about conference formats,
                                flavours — a kind of chocolate box you can choose from; elements
                                other disciplines are good at, and one might try out;</item>
                            <item>personal VS professional life, how much do we share; and</item>
                            <item>Zoom offers moments of insight — get to see where someone
                                lives!</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                    <p>The authors of this paper would like to thank all of their colleagues within
                        DARIAH EU and beyond for their contributions, in particular the break out
                        session speakers, the staff and volunteers from who assisted in delivering
                        the event, and the artists and director of <title rend="quotes">The Other F
                            Word. </title>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="abusaada_elshater2020" label="Abusaada and Elshater 2020">Abusaada,
                    H., and Elshater, A. <title rend="quotes">COVID-19 Challenge, Information
                        Technologies, and Smart Cities: Considerations for Well-Being.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">International Journal of Community Well-Being</title> 3:3
                    (2020), 417-24 <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s42413-020-00068-5"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1007/s42413-020-00068-5</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="anderson2010" label="Anderson et al. 2010"> Anderson, S., Blanke, T.,
                    and Dunn S. <title rend="quotes">Methodological commons: arts and humanities
                        eScience fundamentals.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society A:
                        Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences</title>, 368:1925 (2010),
                    3779–3796. <ref
                        target="http://rsta.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/368/1925/3779.short"
                        >http://rsta.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/368/1925/3779.short</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barnes2020" label="Barnes 2020"><title rend="quotes">Moving a Workshop
                        Online: What Works and What Doesn’t?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">COPIM</title>, March 26, 2020. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.21428/785a6451.370f67b5"
                        >https://doi.org/10.21428/785a6451.370f67b5</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boudreau2017" label="Boudreau et al. 2017"> Boudreau, Kevin J., Tom
                    Brady, Ina Ganguli, Patrick Gaule, Eva Guinan, Anthony Hollenberg, and Karim R.
                    Lakhani. <title rend="quotes">A Field Experiment on Search Costs and the
                        Formation of Scientific Collaborations.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Review of Economics and Statistics</title> 99:4
                    (October 2017): 565–76. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1162/REST_a_00676"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1162/REST_a_00676</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="byrdforthcoming" label="Byrd forthcoming"> Byrd, N. <title
                        rend="quotes">Online Conferences: Some History, Methods, and
                        Benefits.</title> In Rockwell, G., Miya, C., and Rossier, O. (eds.) <title
                        rend="italic">Right Research: Modelling Sustainable Research Practices in
                        the Anthropocene.</title> United Kingdom: Open Book Publishers. Preprint
                    version also available at: <ref target="https://philpapers.org/rec/BYROCS"
                        >https://philpapers.org/rec/BYROCS</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="costley2020" label="Costley et al. 2020"> Costley, J., Fanguy, M.,
                    Lange, C., and Baldwin, M. <title rend="quotes">The Effects of Video Lecture
                        Viewing Strategies on Cognitive Load.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Computing in Higher Education</title>, April 6,
                    2020. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12528-020-09254-y"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1007/s12528-020-09254-y</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="crane2006" label="Crane et al. 2006">Crane G., Bamman, D., Cerrato,
                    L., Jones, A., Mimno, D., Packel, A., Sculley, D., Weaver, G., <title
                        rend="quotes">Beyond Digital Incunabula: Modeling the Next Generation of
                        Digital Libraries.</title> In: Gonzalo J., Thanos C., Verdejo M.F., Carrasco
                    R.C. (eds) <title rend="italic">Research and Advanced Technology for Digital
                        Libraries.</title> ECDL 2006. <title rend="italic">Lecture Notes in Computer
                        Science</title>, vol 4172. Springer, Berlin, Heidelberg. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1007/11863878_30"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1007/11863878_30</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="DM2E2015" label="DM2E 2015"> Hennicke, S., Gradmann S., Dill, K.,
                    Tschumpel, G., Thoden, K., Morbindoni C. and Pichler, A. <title rend="italic"
                        >D3.4 — Research Report on DH Scholarly Primitives.</title> 2015. <ref
                        target="https://dm2e.eu/files/D3.4_2.0_Research_Report_on_DH_Scholarly_Primitives_150402.pdf"
                        >https://dm2e.eu/files/D3.4_2.0_Research_Report_on_DH_Scholarly_Primitives_150402.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="doyle2020" label="Doyle et al. 2020">Doyle, P. Mortensen, J. and
                    Clifford, D. <title rend="quotes">The Trouble with Zoom,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Australian Financial Review.</title> March 24, 2020. <ref
                        target="https://www.afr.com/technology/zoom-is-the-next-privacy-challenge-20200324-p54dff"
                        >https://www.afr.com/technology/zoom-is-the-next-privacy-challenge-20200324-p54dff</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="edmond2016" label="Edmond 2016"> Edmond, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Collaboration and Infrastructure,</title> In: Schreibman, S., Siemens, R.,
                    and Unsworth, J. (eds.) <title rend="italic">A New Companion to Digital
                        Humanities.</title> Malden, MA: John Wiley and Sons, 2016, pp. 54-65. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hertzman2020" label="Hertzman 2020"> Hertzmann, A. <title
                        rend="quotes">Computers Do Not Make Art, People Do.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Communications of the ACM</title> 63:5 (May 2020), 45–48.
                        <ref
                        target="https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/articles/244330-computers-do-not-make-art-people-do/fulltext"
                        >https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/articles/244330-computers-do-not-make-art-people-do/fulltext</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lau2020" label="Lau 2020"> Lau, J. <title rend="quotes">To Zoom or Not
                        to Zoom? That Is the Question,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Times Higher Education (THE)</title>. April 17, 2020. <ref
                        target="https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/zoom-or-not-zoom-question"
                        >https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/zoom-or-not-zoom-question</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="macdonald2020" label="Macdonald 2020"> Macdonald M. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Sudden Urgency of Online Academic Conferences.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">University Affairs.</title> April 8, 2020. <ref
                        target="https://www.universityaffairs.ca/features/feature-article/the-sudden-urgency-of-online-academic-conferences/"
                        >https://www.universityaffairs.ca/features/feature-article/the-sudden-urgency-of-online-academic-conferences/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="murray_wiercinski2014" label="Murray and Wiercinski 2014"> Murray, A.,
                    and Wiercinski, J. <title rend="quotes">A Design Methodology for Web-based Sound
                        Archives.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 8: 2 (2014). <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/2/000173/000173.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities. org/dhq/vol/8/2/000173/000173.html</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="palmer2009" label="Palmer et al. 2009"> Palmer, C.L., L.C. Teffeau and
                    C.M. Pirmann. <title rend="italic">Scholarly Information Practices in the Online
                        Environment: Themes from the Literature and Implications for Library Service
                        Development.</title> 2009. <ref
                        target="www.oclc.org/programs/publications/reports/2009-02.pdf"
                        >www.oclc.org/programs/publications/reports/2009-02.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="projectbamboo2010" label="Project Bamboo 2010"> Project Bamboo. <title
                        rend="italic">Scholarly Practices Report.</title> 2010. <ref
                        target="http://www.projectbamboo.org/wp-content/uploads/Project-Bamboo-Scholarly-Practices-Report.pdf"
                        >http://www.projectbamboo.org/wp-content/uploads/Project-Bamboo-Scholarly-Practices-Report.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ratto2011" label="Ratto 2011"> Ratto M. <title rend="quotes">Critical
                        Making: Conceptual and Material Studies in Technology and Social
                        Life,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Information Society,</title> 27:4, 252-260, DOI:
                    10.1080/01972243.2011.583819 </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rockwellforthcoming" label="Rockwell et al. forthcoming">
                    <title rend="italic">Right Research: Modelling Sustainable Research Practices in
                        the Anthropocene.</title> Cambridge, OpenBook. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0213"
                        >https://doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0213</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rockwell2020a" label="Rockwell et al. 2020a"> Rockwell, G., Miya, C.
                    and Rossier, O. <title rend="quotes">What Do Conferences Do — and Can
                        Econferences Replace Them?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Open Book Publishers Blog</title>. March 24, 2020. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0173.0117"
                        >https://doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0173.0117</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rockwell2020b" label="Rockwell et al. 2020b"> Rockwell, G., Miya, C.
                    and Rossier, O. <title rend="quotes">Successful Econferences: Examples and Case
                        Studies,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Open Book Publishers Blog,</title> March 24, 2020. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0173.0120"
                        >https://doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0173.0120</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fyfe2019" label="Fyfe 2019"> Fyfe, A. <title rend="quotes">Digital
                        Transformation in Scholarly Communication.</title> Event Report, Brussels,
                    20 and 21 November 2019. <ref
                        target="https://www.scienceeurope.org/media/yyjngo3x/se-workshop-report-digital-transformation.pdf"
                        >https://www.scienceeurope.org/media/yyjngo3x/se-workshop-report-digital-transformation.pdf</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stone2009" label="Stone 2009"> Stone, L. <title rend="quotes">Beyond
                        Simple Multi-Tasking: Continuous Partial Attention.</title>
                    <ref
                        target="https://lindastone.net/2009/11/30/beyond-simple-multi-tasking-continuous-partial-attention/"
                        >https://lindastone.net/2009/11/30/beyond-simple-multi-tasking-continuous-partial-attention/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stoviac2020" label="Stoviac 2020"> Stoviac, B. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Broader Impact of Zoom Going down on the First Day of Classes for Many
                        Students (Opinion)</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Inside Higher Ed,</title> August 25, 2020. <ref
                        target="https://www.insidehighered.com/views/2020/08/25/broader-impact-zoom-going-down-first-day-classes-many-students-opinion"
                        >https://www.insidehighered.com/views/2020/08/25/broader-impact-zoom-going-down-first-day-classes-many-students-opinion</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="unsworth2000" label="Unsworth 2000"> Unsworth, J. <title rend="italic"
                        >Scholarly Primitives: what methods do humanities researchers have in
                        common, and how might our tools reflect this?</title> Symposium on
                    Humanities Computing: formal methods, experimental practice sponsored by King's
                    College, London, 13 May 2000. <ref
                        target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/~jmu2m/Kings.5-00/primitives.html"
                        >http://www.iath.virginia.edu/~jmu2m/Kings.5-00/primitives.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vandeweel_praal2020" label="Van de Weel and Praal 2020">Van de Weel,
                    A. and Praal, F. 2020 <title rend="quotes">Publishing in the Digital Humanities:
                        The Treacle of Academic Tradition</title> in Edmond, J. (ed.) <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Practices and the Practices of Humanities
                        Research.</title> Cambridge: Open Book, pp. 21-48. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vanzundert2016" label="Van Zundert 2016"> Van Zundert, J.<title
                        rend="quotes">The Case of the Bold Button: Social Shaping of Technology and
                        the Digital Scholarly Edition.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> 31, no. 4
                    (December 1, 2016): 898–910. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqw012"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqw012</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weinberg2020" label="Weinberg 2020"> Weinberg, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Online-First Model: On Hosting an Awesome Online Academic Conference
                        (Guest Post by Catharine St. Croix).</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Daily Nous,</title> March 16, 2020. <ref
                        target="https://dailynous.com/2020/03/16/online-first-model-hosting-awesome-online-academic-conference-guest-post-catharine-st-croix/"
                        >https://dailynous.com/2020/03/16/online-first-model-hosting-awesome-online-academic-conference-guest-post-catharine-st-croix/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wolff2019" label="Wolff 2019"> Wolff, J. <title rend="quotes">What
                        Hypocrisy, I Think Guiltily, as I Jet off to Academic Conferences Far and
                        Wide,</title> The Guardian. October 29, 2019. <ref
                        target="http://www.theguardian.com/education/2019/oct/29/hypocrisy--guilt-jet-off-to-academic-conferences-plane-travel"
                        >http://www.theguardian.com/education/2019/oct/29/hypocrisy--guilt-jet-off-to-academic-conferences-plane-travel</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zaveri2020" label="Zaveri 2020"> Zaveri, P. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Microsoft Teams Added 12 Million Daily Active Users in a Single Week amid
                        the Coronavirus Crisis, Bringing It up to 44 Million Total.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Business Insider.</title> March 19, 2020 <ref
                        target="https://www.businessinsider.com/microsoft-teams-coronavirus-daily-active-users-2020-3"
                        >https://www.businessinsider.com/microsoft-teams-coronavirus-daily-active-users-2020-3</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="clancy2020" label="Clancy 2020"> Clancy, M. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Collaboration and Canceled Conferences: Do conferences really help you
                        network?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">New Things Under the Sun</title>, March 26, 2020. <ref
                        target="https://mattsclancy.substack.com/p/collaboration-and-canceled-conferences"
                        >https://mattsclancy.substack.com/p/collaboration-and-canceled-conferences</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fraser2017" label="Fraser et al. 2017">Fraser, Hannah, Kylie Soanes,
                    Stuart A. Jones,Chris S. Jones, and Matthew Malishev. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Value of Virtual Conferencing for Ecology and Conservation.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Conservation Biology</title>, 31:3 (2017), 540–546.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="roosendaal1997" label="Roosendaal and Geerts et al. 1997">Roosendaal,
                    H. E., and P. A. Th. M. Geurts. <title rend="quotes">Forces and Functions in
                        Scientific Communication: An analysis of their interplay,</title>
                    unpublished conference paper at Cooperative Research Information Systems in
                    Physics, Oldenburg, Germany, 31 August–4 September 1997, <ref
                        target="http://www.physik.uni-oldenburg.
                        de/conferences/crisp97/roosendaal.html"
                        >http://www.physik.uni-oldenburg.
                        de/conferences/crisp97/roosendaal.html</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="prosser2013" label="Prosser 2013">Prosser, David C. <title
                        rend="quotes">Researchers and Scholarly Communications: An Evolving
                        Interdependency.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Future of Scholarly Communication.</title> Shorley,
                    Deborah, and Michael Jubb, eds. London: Facet, 2013, pp. 39–49. <ref
                        target="https://doi.
                        org/10.29085/9781856049610.005">https://doi.
                        org/10.29085/9781856049610.005</ref></bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
