<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
	xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
	xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
	xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				
				<title type="article" xml:lang="en"><title
						rend="quotes">Follow the Money?</title>: Funding and Digital
					Sustainability</title>
				
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					
					<dhq:author_name>Jessica <dhq:family>Otis</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID"
						>https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5519-8331</idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>Roy Rosenzweig Center for History and New Media, George Mason University</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>jotis2@gmu.edu</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Jessica Otis is an Assistant Professor of History and Director of Public Projects at the Roy Rosenzweig Center for History and New Media, where she is in charge of the center's sustainability and archiving efforts. Her research focuses on the cultural history of mathematics, plague, and cryptography in early modern England, and her first book, <title rend="italic">By the Numbers: Understanding the World in Early Modern England</title> is forthcoming from Oxford University Press.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
				<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
				<!--This information will be completed at publication-->
				<idno type="DHQarticle-id"
					><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000666</idno>
				<idno type="volume"
					>017<!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
				<idno type="issue">1<!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
				<date when="2023-05-26">26 May 2023</date>
				<dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
				<availability status="CC-BY-ND">
					
					<cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Article written by Jessica Otis for the special issue on Project Resiliency. The papers in this special issue were first presented at a symposium organized by the Endings Project team at the University of Victoria.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
					<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en" extent="original"/>
				
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
					
					<list type="simple">
						<item>digital humanities</item>
						<item>ethics</item>
						<item>infrastructure</item>
						<item>project management</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
					
					<list type="simple">
						<item>project resiliency</item>
						<item>funding</item>
						<item>granting agencies</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
					<list type="simple"/>
						</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
					target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000666/000666.xml"
					>GitHub </ref>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en" type="original">
		<front>
			<dhq:abstract>
				
				<p>This essay will explore the role of soft and hard funding in the digital
					humanities, with particular attention paid to the ways funding intersects
					with sustainability. It will discuss a variety of types of soft funding
					available from public, private, and institutional sources, and the ways the
					needs of funders can align with or compete with the desires of scholars.
					The availability and sustainability of funding as project needs change over
					time, along with funders' agendas, can influence project teams' decisions
					about the direction a project will take, who leads it, who can contribute
					to it, what technology supports it, on what servers it is hosted, if and
					when it can be updated, as well as if and where it will be preserved. Not
					considering the implications of financial support received can be
					detrimental to both the project and the researchers involved. Seeking
					funding should become part of wider strategies that enable the formation of
					mutually beneficial relationships, promising avenues of research, and
					sustainable revenue streams, rather than a time sink that explodes a
					project's scope in ways that undermine the project.</p>
			</dhq:abstract>
			<dhq:teaser>
				
				<p>Follow the Money? Funding and Digital
					Sustainability</p>
			</dhq:teaser>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div>

				<head/>
				<p> Humanities scholarship requires funding, whether for books or journals,
					database access or server space, research assistants or a trip to the
					archives, or simply a scholar's time to think and create. In the
					traditional book- and article-based humanistic workflows, colleges,
					universities, archives, special collections, publishers, and libraries have
					established labor and funding models that aim to support text-based
					research, writing, publishing, distribution, and preservation pipelines.
					But digital humanities (DH) projects don't fit neatly into these pipelines
					and digital humanists often struggle to work within these preexisting labor
					and funding models. While the differences between traditional and digital
					forms of humanities scholarship can cause funding difficulties at any stage
					of a DH project's lifecycle, these differences are particularly
					problematic when it comes to sustainability.</p>
				<p> There are two common funding narratives often associated with DH projects in
					the United States. First, that DH projects are always grant-funded and that
					digital humanists are thus <q>cash cows</q> who bring in large amounts of
					external funding into an institution with projects that could be
					accomplished only due to those infusions of outside cash. And second, that the
					open-source, open-access, and collaborative ethos of DH makes it possible
					for scholars to do DH for <q>free,</q> without any institutional
					investments. Neither narrative is entirely false — and, indeed, the
						<q>free</q> project model is crucial for many contingent and
					independent scholars who lack institutional support — but not only do most
					DH projects exist somewhere on the spectrum between <q>free</q> and
						<q>fully funded,</q> but also each narrative obscures the financial
					realities that exist at those poles.</p>
				<p> No DH project is ever free; even if no money changes hands, there are always
					real costs associated with the work.<note> I would like to thank the folks
						at the Nonprofit Finance Foundation, especially Robert Kagan and Cecil
						Daniels, for introducing me to the concept of real costs.</note> At
					minimum, a <q>free</q> DH project created by a single independent scholar
					with open-source software on their personal computer relies on the donated
					labor and resources of both that scholar and the community that created and
					shared the software. Larger DH projects with multiple collaborators rely on
					the donated labor and resources of all the project team members. If the
					project is web-facing, these donated resources may include real money for
					costs such as domain name registration or server space rental.
					Collaborators with access to institutional resources also effectively
					donate those resources to the project team on behalf of their institutions
					— from the costs of their salary and benefits, to hardware and software
					costs, to office space and utilities, to interlibrary loans and database
					access, and more. Some collaborators further involve their students as a
					source of <q>free</q> project labor — exchanging student labor for course
					credit in a model that should involve significant additional labor from the
						instructor.<note> I believe it <emph>is</emph> possible to incorporate
						work on active DH projects into for-credit courses, but only if the
						instructor is explicit about the conflicts of interest and prioritizes
						student learning outcomes over progress on the project. For a longer
						take on the ethical issues of using unpaid student labor on DH
						projects, see <ptr target="#keralis2018"/>. </note> As a funding
					model, then, the <q>free</q> project model is actually a self-funded or
					collaborator-funded project model. </p>
				<p> When projects reach the limits of what can be accomplished for <q>free,</q>
					or are conceived of in such a way that they can't even be attempted in such
					a model, one of the common next steps is for the project leaders to shift
					towards the other pole and seek grant funding — something that usually,
					though not always, requires institutional backing.<note> It is common for
						grants to be awarded to institutions rather than individuals, making
						it impossible for independent scholars to even apply for those grants
						in the first place unless they find a collaborator at an institution
						to serve as their project's figurehead.</note> US university and
					college administrators are particularly pleased when humanists join
					scientists and social scientists in bringing in outside funds to support
					both scholarly research and the overall operating costs of the institution.
					However, the grant application process itself has real costs, primarily in
					the form of the labor to write and submit the applications, which can take
					from days to weeks depending on how involved the application process is.
					Furthermore, most humanities grants are capped at a low dollar amount
					compared to other disciplines and funding ratios for both major
						<emph>and</emph> minor grants are also comparatively low. As of 2021,
					two of the major US grant opportunities that support digital project
					creation — the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) Digital
					Humanities Advancement Grants and Digital Projects for the Public —
					together fund a mere 30 projects a year, with a 14-15% funding ratio and
					maximum awards of $400,000.<note> Most of the grants awarded under these
						programs are for less than the maximum, especially as the advancement
						grants require matching funds to go above $350,000. <ptr
							target="#neha"/>; <ptr target="#nehb"/>. Overall, the NEH funds
						approximately 900 projects a year, across all subject domains, whereas
						the National Science Foundation funds a whopping 12,000 projects a
						year, with an average award of over $400,000 and a funding ratio of
						28% <ptr target="#nehc"/>; <ptr target="#nsf"/>.</note> On average,
					then, an institution should expect to submit 6-7 DH grants to the NEH to
					get one success, translating to tens of thousands of dollars of investment
					with no guarantee of a return. Grant writing is thus a resource-intensive
					gamble that doesn't always pay off, especially for scholars playing outside
					a research-intensive institution who lack access to infrastructures
					designed to support grant writing and administration.<note> Even within a
						research-intensive institution, access to grant writing and grant
						administrating infrastructure can vary dramatically, especially for
						scholars working in units without a history of receiving
						grants.</note>
				</p>
				<p> Each of these models has implications for project sustainability, here
					defined as keeping the project live on a server and accessible to members
					of the public through typing a URL into a browser. This is different from
					preserving a digital project or keeping the <q>bits</q> of the project safe
					somewhere — such as zipping up files and placing them into an institutional
					repository — even if they are not easily accessible.<note> For a
						book-based analogy: a sustained project is like a book on the open
						shelves of a library, whereas a preserved project is like one held in
						a special collections vault. See <ptr target="#otis2023"/>.</note> The sustainability of self-funded
					projects is reliant on team members continuing to invest their personal
					resources into — and generate internal team enthusiasm for — the project.
					If leadership and enthusiasm can be maintained, these projects have the
					potential to live on indefinitely. But this stream of donations can dry up
					at any time, at which point the project will begin to fall apart.
					Web-facing projects will even abruptly disappear at the first failure to
					renew server space rental or domain name registration.<note> This is not a
						problem unique to DH projects. For more on the problem of link rot and
						disappearing websites see <ptr target="#zittrain2021"/> and Coble &amp; Karlin in this issue.</note> By
					contrast, grant-funded projects have pre-determined end dates; they can
					generally be relied upon to survive to that point, but afterwards no more
					funds will be forthcoming from the granting body. Unless the project team
					successfully finds a different source of funding to sustain the project —
					often in the form of new grant applications — it will begin to die slowly
					the day its grant funds run out.</p>
				<p> While both funding models can work reasonably well for the traditional
					humanities research output of printed books, neither model is ideal to meet
					the sustainability requirements of digital projects. Both printed books and
					digital projects require a major initial investment, in time and research
					materials, to produce. But after the book is printed, it is no longer the
					creator's responsibility. Instead, hundreds, thousands, or tens of
					thousands of effectively identical copies are scattered across the globe.
					And the upkeep costs are low for each individual copy placed on a scholar's
					or a library's bookshelves: once an appropriate space is set up to hold
					bookshelves, the marginal cost of each additional book added to those
					shelves is negligible until there is no more room and either collection
					items must be deaccessioned or the space must be expanded again.<note> In
						addition to the sunk costs of creating such a space, there
							<emph>are</emph> costs to maintaining the space. However, these
						costs are effectively independent of the space's contents; adding a
						book or even 100 books to a bookshelf will have no measurable impact
						on the space's heating bill or property taxes.</note> Barring a roof
					leak, mouse infestation, or careless coffee spills, the book may remain in
					good shape for decades without much if any active curation; indeed, most
					books survive best by being left alone.<note> Note, however, that not all
						books share the same physical properties — a book printed on acidic
						paper will have a far shorter lifespan and need greater curation than
						one printed to modern archival standards <ptr target="#goddard2020"
							loc="38"/>.</note> In the carefully controlled environments of a
					special collections vault, books can last centuries. And as long as at
					least one physical copy of a book survives, its scholarly contents survive
					as well. Books thus require an upfront, time-limited financial investment
					for production, after which point their survival is turned over to a
					distributed series of owners who pay a set infrastructural cost to sustain
					hundreds, thousands, or millions of these physical objects.</p>
				<p> While digital technologies are all too new to know if any DH projects will
					last for centuries, right now most are struggling to even last years, much
					less decades <ptr target="#davis2019"/>. In stark contrast to books,
					digital projects are generally centralized to one copy, and they decay if
					they are not actively maintained.<note> While diligent scholars may create
						numerous copies of their digital projects, and archive them in various
						places across the internet, these still pale in comparison to the
						number of physical objects printed in a single print run of a book.
						Furthermore, if these copies are not independently maintained, they
						are likely to face the same sustainability problems at the same time
						as links break (see Coble and Karlin in this issue), embedded content
						stops resolving, and outdated code leaves databases and servers open
						to hacking by malicious outside parties.</note> From a financial
					perspective, sustaining a digital project is more akin to sustaining a car
					than a book.<note> No metaphor is perfect, including this one. There are
						absolutely times when a book-based metaphor makes more sense, such as
						when a junior scholar is trying to explain their digital project to a
						hiring or tenure committee. The car metaphor is specifically intended
						for discussions of the resources necessary to ensure digital projects'
						sustainability. See <ptr target="#otis2023"/> for my first use of the car metaphor.</note> Like a newly-purchased car, DH projects tend to
					run well for five to seven years with minimal recurring costs for server
					space or domain name renewal, only to begin to suffer increasingly dramatic
					breakdowns that require equivalently hefty <q>mechanic's bills</q> to
						fix.<note> The average lifespan of a DH project is 5 years, which is
						about the same length as the extended warranty on a new car purchase
							<ptr target="#meneses2019"/>.</note> And after a decade or maybe
					two, both cars and DH projects reach a point where they either become too
					much trouble to be worth fixing or they reach <q>classic car</q> status and
					are deemed worth saving regardless of the costs.<note> The question of what
						projects to sustain and what projects to let decay or delete is a
						vexed one. While the intellectual merits of any particular project can
						be debated, there are some objective measures that can be used to
						assess them. These include the size of their userbase, whether they
						host unique or rare (born digital or digitized) cultural content, and
						whether they have been deemed prestigious by a scholarly community
						through, for example, citation as canonical works in a body of literature.
						These intellectual merits can then be placed in conversation with an
						analysis of the difficulty of remediation, current security risks, and
						projected long-term sustainability costs. For an example of this
						triage process, see <ptr target="#smithies2019"/>.</note>
					Unfortunately for digital humanists, book-based financial models falter and
					fail when faced with a <q>fleet</q> of digital objects whose costs are
					ongoing, increasing, and directly related to the number of objects that
					need to be sustained.</p>
				<p> The first step for ensuring the financial sustainability of a digital
					project is thus to understand the technical construction — and associated
					maintenance costs — of complex digital objects and plan accordingly. Simply
					being able to accurately predict the ongoing costs of sustaining a website
					will help ensure that any funding plan is adequate to meet the project's
					technical needs for its expected lifespan. A custom-coded phone <q>app</q>
					will be more difficult and expensive to sustain than a website based on an
					open-source content management system (CMS) such as WordPress, which in
					turn is more difficult and expensive than a website without an underlying
					database, such as a <q>flat</q> website built only with HTML, CSS, and
					JavaScript. If the predicted funding requirements of sustaining the project
					end up too high, then building — or planning to reduce a project upon its
					completion — to the minimum viable complexity will reduce the
					sustainability costs of the project to a more achievable level. Once a
					project's needs have been identified, scholars can seek funding from a
					variety of diverse sources, prioritizing those that best fit the project. </p>
				<p> Scholars associated with institutions can start by taking advantage of
					hard-funded institutional resources, such as specialized email addresses,
					listservs, or subdomains of their institutional domain, which have low
					marginal costs to the institution and are likely to be made available to
					employees who have a need for them. In institutions with more resources, IT
					services or the library might even supply shared server space for projects
					running a specific CMS, along with basic systems administration services
					such as keeping a WordPress installation and its plug-ins up to date. Hard
					funding and institutional inertia will help sustain projects built with
					such resources, so long as their creators remain associated with the
					institution, the projects continue to see active use, and nothing opens up
					the institution to legal or security threats — e.g. violating GDPR through
					listserv mis-management or using obsolete and vulnerable CMS plug-ins that
					open shared server spaces to hackers.<note> For more on the problem of
							<q>orphaned</q> projects that rely on institutional resources but
						no longer have an employee champion, see Cummings in this
						issue.</note> And in the most well-resourced institutions, scholars
					may have access to student research assistants, course releases, or other
					research funds that can be deployed in support of digital project
					costs.</p>
				<p> In addition to hard-funded resources, institutions can give scholars access
					to a variety of irregular — but still internal — funding sources.
					Research-intensive institutions often provide access to start-up funds and
					internal funding competitions for prototyping, with the implicit or
					explicit goal of leveraging those prototypes into external funding to
					further implement those projects. Some may even have internal, endowed
					prizes that could be sources of unrestricted funds; while they are rarely
					huge amounts of money, they may still be a significant source of project
					funds for humanities scholars who regularly apply for external grants as
					small as $500 or $1000 USD. But the biggest source of irregular
					institutional income by far is appropriations — money set aside for
					specific centers, departments, or projects — from friendly administrators
					who see the value in promoting DH on their campuses. While these funds
					sometimes <q>roll over</q> from year to year, the funds are more likely to
					be allocated on an annual basis, vanishing at the end of the budget year if
					not spent. These "use or lose" funds are good targets — especially for
					scholars with existing high-profile projects that need a brief bump in
					sustainability support, such as to pay for a CMS upgrade — because they
					must be spent down every year for the administrative unit in question to
					receive the same amount, or more, in their budget for the following
						years.<note> Whenever possible, scholars should compile metrics on
						their projects that can be used to make a case for support to
						administrators. A project that is regularly featured in news outlets,
						has won awards, or receives hundreds of thousands of site visits a
						year will be more attractive to administrators than a project without
						a tangible track record.</note> The funds themselves come from a wide
					variety of sources, including tuition dollars, government appropriations
					for public institutions, endowment income for wealthier institutions, and
					grant overheads for research-intensive institutions.</p>
				<p> Beyond institutional support there are, of course, external sources of
					financial resources. Digital humanists regularly participate in the grant
					economy, seeking funds from government agencies, foundations,
					not-for-profits, and corporations.<note> Corporations can also be a source
						of in-kind donations, especially data. Organizations with academic or
						teaching-centered business models — such as JSTOR, Gale, ProQuest,
						university presses, etc. — are often able and willing to provide data
						to scholars to help them achieve research goals. However, a more
						in-depth or long-term industry partnership is only likely if it
						eventually results in a monetizable product such as a
						subscription-only database or an educational resource that can be sold
						to teachers and students. While monetization can be good for
						sustainability — generating revenue that can be used to sustain the
						project itself — it may conflict with data-sharing agreements or
						field-wide expectations surrounding open access, and such arrangements
						should be approached carefully.</note> Grants might seem like the
					optimal solution to digital humanists' funding problems, as they entail
					receiving funding for a specific length of time to generate a specific
					project, much as other humanists are funded to visit a specific archive or
					come under contract to write a specific book. A variety of funders offer
					grants of varying sizes for the creation of digital projects, which makes
					it possible to align a scholarly agenda with the agenda of those funders in
					order to create something mutually beneficial. Furthermore, grants come
					with numerous additional benefits, including a peer review process that
					helps to establish the digital project's scholarly value prior to the
					investment of significant time and money; built-in project publicity from
					the grant funding announcement; and institutional and external prestige for
					having won a grant. </p>
				<p> However, the grant-funding ecology favors the sciences and is not always
					friendly to humanists. Anyone applying for grant funding in the humanities
					will quickly recognize there are a limited number of major funders — the US
					has the NEH and ACLS, and other nations have their own analogous funders —
					and most of them have limited funding available for specific projects.
					These grants are not always sufficient to complete, much less sustain, a
					project, which means scholars must create projects in stages and
					occasionally creatively re-envision the project. Scope creep — adding
					unnecessary features to make a project appealing to a new funder — is an
					ever-present danger that must be guarded against. Opportunities may also be
					limited by funder agendas. If a project could go two directions and only
					one is fundable, choosing that direction is not scope creep, but it is a
					lost opportunity. Similarly, institutional and funder requirements may
					limit team members' participation — insisting, for example, that team
					leaders have PhDs or be citizens of specific countries — and prohibit
					specific project activities, such as event catering. Funders also, quite
					reasonably, expect grantees to spend funds on the activities they agreed to
					fund; pivoting the project to new, unanticipated directions thus requires
					obtaining funder permission.</p>
				<p> But the biggest funding issue, from a sustainability perspective, is the
					fact that grant-funding is term limited. No matter if a grant is for one,
					three, five, or more years, there is always a planned end to the financial
					support. There are ways to avoid a hard cut-off of funds, for example by
					writing a pre-payment for hosting or other sustainability costs into the
					budget. Scholars should also become familiar with their institution's
					policies on grant overhead, a surcharge added to all direct grant expenses
					intended to support the general operating of the institution.<note> While
						overhead is often a source of contention — especially when a third or
						half of a grant's already limited funds are taken up by such charges —
						it is important to recognize that the work of digital scholars is
						still embodied. Outside of an institutional setting, they might have
						had to pay rent, utilities, and a myriad of other expenses that are
						not directly charged to them within a university setting. Overhead
						payments help cover these real costs. This is not to defend, for
						example, Harvard University's current 69% overhead rate but rather to
						explain the general purpose of such funds <ptr target="#harvard"
						/>.</note> A percentage of these funds often "trickles down" from the
					institution writ large through the scholar's various administrative units —
					e.g. some goes to the university for general operating expenses, some to
					the scholar's college, some to the scholar's department, and some to the
					scholar themselves. For scientists, these overhead funds often help support
					their lab infrastructure. For digital humanists, these overhead funds can
					be funneled back into a project to support its long-term sustainability.
					However, these funds can only extend grant support so far past the grant's end
					date.</p>
				<p> While there are no easy solutions to sustainability funding, the last decade
					has seen a growing sentiment that not everything needs to be free on the
					internet and that independent artists, writers, and other digital content
					creators should be paid for their work.<note> This can be best summarized
						by a common creators' retort to offers of being <q>paid</q> in
						exposure: <quote rend="inline">people die of exposure.</quote> See, for
						example, <ptr target="#leckie2013"/>,
						<ptr target="#fcphillipa2015"/>, and
						<ptr target="#lucas2020"/>.</note> Digital humanists can and should
					view themselves as digital content creators and pay attention to the
					business models “indies” use to support themselves. Not all these models
					will be appropriate to adopt — e.g. for scholars associated with an
					institution, a grant will bring more prestige and fit better into
					institutional workflows than a Kickstarter campaign — but an awareness of
					these models will help scholars creatively seek and acquire funding to
					create and sustain their projects.</p>
				<p> Any list of current indie business models is likely to age poorly, and it's
					less important to debate the benefits of Patreon vs. Kofi vs. BuyMeACoffee
					here than to note the existence of business models based on community
					support. Universities and other large institutions are accustomed to
					fundraising for large amounts of money, because it costs money to process
					donations and a $1 USD donation might actually cost more to process than
					the donation itself. However, there are now and will likely continue to be
					a variety of platforms that support tip-jar-style microdonations of $1, $5,
					or even 10¢. There are also platforms that allow audience members to
					sponsor — or provide recurring donations to — creators, often in exchange
					for exclusive or early access to content. Freemium models — with a large
					amount of content available for free and additional content or services
					available for money — are also popular, and WordPress.com runs on this
					model; one can create a basic WordPress site on a WordPress.com subdomain
					for free, but it costs money to remove the advertisements and have a custom
					URL <ptr target="#wordpress"/>. The Mozilla Foundation — creators of
					Firefox — have similarly been exploring freemium models to reduce digital
					advertising and support user privacy.<note> See for example <ptr
							target="#mozilla"/>, <ptr target="#grant"/>, and <ptr
							target="#scire2020"/>.</note> And while advertisements can annoy
					users and raise ethical considerations about advertised content, they are
					an established model for earning revenue on free content. Podcast
					advertising, in particular, is a growing market segment that podcasting
					scholars should be aware of <ptr target="#interactive2021"/>. Crucially,
					these are all models that often are effective for people or projects with
					robust pre-existing audiences, which is often a key factor in determining
					which digital projects in a person or institution's portfolio should be
					prioritized for sustainability funds.<note> At the Roy Rosenzweig Center
						for History and New Media, we assign the highest priority to
						sustaining sites that receive over 100,000 unique visitors a year,
						whereas sites that receive less than 1,000 unique visitors a year are
						likely to be archived rather than sustained once their functionality
						begins to deteriorate. For sites in between, we look at the difficulty
						of remediation, security risks, intellectual merits, and project
						prestige to help assess whether sites that have begun to break should
						be remediated in their original format or flattened to static
						HTML/CSS/JS to ensure their sustainability with minimal additional
						investment of time or money.</note>
				</p>
				<p> With no one set path for financing their work, digital humanists need to use
					a variety of funding strategies across their digital projects' lifespans,
					optimizing strategies to fit a project’s evolving needs. Strategies that
					work well during the creation phase of a project are often insufficient to
					sustain the project after its completion, when it needs to be actively
					maintained for continued public access. Digital humanists need to be
					flexible about seeking money for their work — both from within their
					institutions and outside of it — and pay attention to larger funding trends
					among independent digital content creators. But most importantly, digital
					humanists need to be clear-sighted about the real costs of their project,
					aware of their prospective future revenue streams, and proactive in
					minimizing the technical complexity of projects so that their future
					revenues are able to cover future costs. Digital humanists need to follow
					the money — not in the sense of continuously reimagining their scholarly
					agendas to fit those of funders, but rather in the sense of understanding
					their project's technical needs, the real costs of that work, and the
					various avenues available for funding their project at every life stage.
					Only then can they choose paths that accomplish their intellectual
					objectives in a fiscally sustainable manner.</p>

			</div>


		</body>
		<back>
			<listBibl>
				<bibl xml:id="davis2019" label="Davis 2019"> Davis, R. C. (2019) <title
						rend="quotes">The Final Death(s) of Digital Scholarship — An Ongoing
						Case Study of DH2005 Projects</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.robincamille.com/presentations/death_of_digital_scholarship/"
						>https://www.robincamille.com/presentations/death_of_digital_scholarship/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="estill2020" label="Estill 2020"> Estill, L. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Legacy
						technologies and digital futures</title> in Crompton, C., Lane, R, and
					Siemens, R. (eds.),<title rend="italic"> Doing More Digital Humanities</title>.
					New York: Routledge, pp. 7–24.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="fcphillipa2015" label="FC_Phillipa 2015"> FC_Phillipa. (2015)
						<title rend="quotes">Don't work for free – people die of
						exposure!</title>
					<title rend="italic">Freelance Confidence</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="http://freelanceconfidence.com/dont-work-free-people-die-exposure/"
						>http://freelanceconfidence.com/dont-work-free-people-die-exposure/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="goddard2020" label="Goddard &amp; Seeman 2020"> Goddard, L. and Seeman, D.
					(2020) <title rend="quotes">Negotiating Sustainability: Building digital
						humanities projects that last</title> in Crompton, C., Lane, R, and
					Siemens, R. (eds.) <title rend="italic"> Doing More Digital
						Humanities</title>. New York: Routledge, pp. 38–57.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="grant" label="Grant for the Web n.d.">
					<title rend="quotes">Grant for the Web</title>. (n.d.) Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.grantfortheweb.org"
						>https://www.grantfortheweb.org</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="harvard" label="Harvard University n.d."> Harvard University,
					(n.d.) <title rend="quotes">Indirect Costs</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://research.fas.harvard.edu/indirect-costs-0"
						>https://research.fas.harvard.edu/indirect-costs-0</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="interactive2021" label="Interactive Advertising Bureau 2021">
					Interactive Advertising Bureau. (2021) <title rend="quotes">U.S. Podcast Ad
						Revenues Grew 19% YoY in 2020; set to exceed $1B this year and $2B by
						2023</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.iab.com/news/us-podcast-ad-revenues-grew-19-yoy-in-2020-set-to-exceed-1b-this-year-and-2b-by-2023/"
						>https://www.iab.com/news/us-podcast-ad-revenues-grew-19-yoy-in-2020-set-to-exceed-1b-this-year-and-2b-by-2023/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="keralis2018" label="Keralis 2018"> Keralis, S. D. C. (2018) <title rend="quotes"
						>Disrupting Labor in Digital Humanities; or, The Classroom is Not Your
						Crowd</title> in Kim, D. and Strommel, S. (eds.), <title rend="italic"
							>Disrupting the Digital Humanities</title>. New York: Punctum Books. pp. 273–294.
					Available at: <ref target="https://library.oapen.org/handle/20.500.12657/25400"
						>https://library.oapen.org/handle/20.500.12657/25400</ref>. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="leckie2013" label="Leckie 2013"> Leckie, A. (2013) <title
						rend="quotes">People Die of Exposure</title>.
					<title rend="italic">Ann Leckie Blog</title>, Available at: <ref
						target="https://annleckie.com/2013/06/10/people-die-of-exposure/"
						>https://annleckie.com/2013/06/10/people-die-of-exposure/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="lucas2020" label="Lucas 2020"> Lucas, M. W. (2020) <title
						rend="italic">Cash Flow for Creators: How to Transform Your Art Into a
						Career</title>. n.p.: Tilted Windmill Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="meneses2019" label="Meneses &amp; Furuta 2019"> Meneses, L. and Furuta, R. (2019)
						<title rend="quotes">Shelf life: Identifying the abandonment of online
						digital humanities projects</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital
						Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 34, pp. 129–134, Available at: <ref
						target="https://academic.oup.com/dsh/article/34/Supplement_1/i129/5270841"
						>https://academic.oup.com/dsh/article/34/Supplement_1/i129/5270841</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="mozilla" label="Mozilla Foundation n.d."> Mozilla Foundation.
					(n.d.) <title rend="quotes">Unfck the Internet</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://web.archive.org/web/20220608064838/https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/unfck/"
						>https://web.archive.org/web/20220608064838/https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/unfck/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="neha" label="National Endowment for the Humanities n.d.a">
					National Endowment for the Humanities. (n.d.a.) <title rend="quotes"
						>Digital Projects for the Public</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.neh.gov/grants/public/digital-projects-the-public"
						>https://www.neh.gov/grants/public/digital-projects-the-public</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="nehb" label="National Endowment for the Humanities n.d.b"> National Endowment for
					the Humanities. (n.d.b.) <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities Advancement
						Grants</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.neh.gov/grants/odh/digital-humanities-advancement-grants"
						>https://www.neh.gov/grants/odh/digital-humanities-advancement-grants</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="nehc" label="National Endowment for the Humanities n.d.c"> National Endowment for
					the Humanities. (n.d.c.) <title rend="quotes">NEH's Application Review
						Process</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.neh.gov/grants/application-process"
						>https://www.neh.gov/grants/application-process</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="nsf" label="National Science Foundation n.d."> National Science
					Foundation. (n.d.) <title rend="quotes">Funding Rate by State and
						Organization from FY 2019 to 2020 for NSF</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://dellweb.bfa.nsf.gov/awdfr3/default.asp"
						>https://dellweb.bfa.nsf.gov/awdfr3/default.asp</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="otis2023" label="Otis 2023">Otis, J. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Managing the Digital Backlist: Sustaining, Preserving, and Deleting Old Projects</title>. <title rend="ital">The Dev Log</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://jessicaotis.com/digital-humanities/managing-the-digital-backlist/">https://jessicaotis.com/digital-humanities/managing-the-digital-backlist</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="scire2020" label="Scire 2020"> Scire, S. (2020) <title
						rend="quotes">Scroll and Mozilla's Firefox team up to bring ad-free
						news to a wider audience</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.niemanlab.org/2020/03/scroll-and-mozillas-firefox-team-up-to-bring-ad-free-news-to-a-wider-audience/"
						>https://www.niemanlab.org/2020/03/scroll-and-mozillas-firefox-team-up-to-bring-ad-free-news-to-a-wider-audience/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="smithies2019" label="Smithies et al. 2019"> Smithies, J.,
					Westling, C., Sichani, A., Mellen, P., and Ciula, A. (2019) <title
						rend="quotes">Managing 100 Digital Humanities Projects: Digital
						Scholarship &amp; Archiving in King's Digital Lab</title>.
					<title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 13(1). Available at: <ref
						target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/13/1/000411/000411.html"
						>http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/13/1/000411/000411.html</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="wordpress" label="Wordpress.com n.d."> Wordpress.com (n.d.) <title
						rend="quotes">There's a plan for you</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://wordpress.com/pricing/"
						>https://wordpress.com/pricing/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="zittrain2021" label="Zittrain 2021"> Zittrain, Jonathan. (2021) <title
						rend="quotes">The Internet is Rotting</title> (originally published as
						<title rend="quotes">The Internet is A Collective Hallucination</title>).
						<title rend="italic">The Atlantic</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2021/06/the-internet-is-a-collective-hallucination/619320/"
						>https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2021/06/the-internet-is-a-collective-hallucination/619320/</ref>.</bibl>
			</listBibl>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
