<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Making of <q>Our Cultural Commonwealth</q>
            </title>
            <author>John Unsworth</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>John <dhq:family>Unsworth</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Graduate School of Library and Information Science, University of
                  Illinois, Urbana-Champaign</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>unsworth@uiuc.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>In 2008, John Unsworth was named Director of the Illinois Informatics
                     Institute, a campus-wide organization that serves to coordinate and encourage
                     informatics-related education and research. He also continues to serve as Dean
                     of the Graduate School of Library and Information Science (GSLIS) at the
                     University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, a post to which he was appointed in
                     2003. In addition to being a Professor in GSLIS, he also holds appointments in
                     the department of English, and on the Library faculty. During the previous ten
                     years, from 1993-2003, he served as the first Director of the <ref target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/">Institute for Advanced Technology in
                        the Humanities</ref>, and a faculty member in the English Department, at the
                     University of Virginia. For his work at IATH, he received the <ref target="http://nationalhumanitiescenter.org/lymanaward/index.htm">2005
                        Richard W. Lyman Award</ref> from the National Humanities Center. He chaired
                     the national commission that produced <ref target="http://www.acls.org/uploadedFiles/Publications/Programs/Our_Cultural_Commonwealth.pdf">Our Cultural Commonwealth</ref>, the 2006 report on Cyberinfrastructure for
                     Humanities and Social Science, on behalf of the American Council of Learned
                     Societies, and he has supervised research projects across the disciplines in
                     the humanities. He has also published widely on the topic of electronic
                     scholarship, as well as co-directing one of nine national partnerships in the
                     Library of Congress's National Digital Information Infrastructure Preservation
                     Program, and securing grants from the National Endowment for the Humanities,
                     the National Science Foundation, the Getty Grant Program, IBM, Sun, the Andrew
                     W. Mellon Foundation, and others. His first faculty appointment was in English,
                     at North Carolina State University, from 1989 to 1993. He attended Princeton
                     University and Amherst College as an undergraduate, graduating from Amherst in
                     1981. He received a Master's degree in English from Boston University in 1982
                     and a Ph.D. in English from the University of Virginia in 1988. In 1990, at
                     NCSU, he co-founded the first peer-reviewed electronic journal in the
                     humanities, <ref target="http://pmc.iath.virginia.edu/"><title rend="italic">Postmodern Culture</title></ref> (now published by Johns Hopkins
                     University Press, as part of Project Muse). He also organized, incorporated,
                     and chaired the <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml">Text Encoding
                        Initiative Consortium</ref>, co-chaired the <ref target="http://www.mla.org/resources/committees/comm_publications/comm_scholarly">Modern Language Association's Committee on Scholarly Editions</ref>, and
                     served as President of the <ref target="http://www.ach.org/">Association for
                        Computers and the Humanities</ref> and later as chair of the steering
                     committee for the <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/">Alliance of
                        Digital Humanities Organizations</ref>, as well as serving on many other
                     editorial and advisory boards. He was born in 1958, in Northampton,
                     Massachusetts; in 1978, he married Margaret English, with whom he has three
                     children: Bill, Thomas, and Eleanor. Further information is at <ref target="http://www3.isrl.uiuc.edu/~unsworth/">http://www3.isrl.uiuc.edu/~unsworth/</ref>.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000073</idno>
            <idno type="volume">003</idno>
            <idno type="issue">4</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2010-03-20">20 March 2010</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace" rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword
                     taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2010-04-05" who="jhf">Final link correx</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>Reflections on the ACLS Commission on Cyberinfrastructure</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>What does it take to deliver a national report on cyberinfrastructure for humanities
               and social sciences?</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head/>
            <p>In Memory of Roy Rosenzweig</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head/>
            <epigraph>
               <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#undocumented">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Farewell to an idea . . . The cancellings,</l>
                        <l>The negations are never final.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
                  <ref type="offline">Wallace Stevens, <title rend="quotes">Auroras of
                        Autumn</title>
                  </ref>
               </cit>
            </epigraph>
            <div>
               <head>Background</head>
               <p>In January of 2003, the USA's National Science Foundation published a report from
                  a <title rend="quotes">Blue-Ribbon Advisory Panel on Cyberinfrastructure,</title>
                  a panel chaired by Dan Atkins, then Dean of the School of Information at the
                  University of Michigan. The Atkins report was perceived by many as presaging some
                  major changes in the discussion (and funding) of computational infrastructure for
                  the sciences, and it prompted a number of follow-up reports and responses from
                  other quarters. One of these responses was commissioned by the American Council of
                  Learned Societies, and it focused on cyberinfrastructure for humanities and social
                  sciences.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Process</head>
               <p>This essay reflects on what goes into producing such a report. In practical and
                  procedural terms, it takes: <list type="unordered">
                     <item>A preliminary meeting (September 17, 2003) for about twenty-five people
                        to discuss the idea of doing a report, after which a chair was
                        appointed.</item>
                     <item>A planning grant proposal from the ACLS to the Andrew W. Mellon
                        Foundation (November 2003) to support the process of setting up the
                        Commission.</item>
                     <item>Conversations about Commission membership (December/January 2003/2004)
                        with the chair, ACLS, and Mellon.</item>
                     <item>An invitational workshop (February 2004) to provide feedback on the draft
                        charge to the commission, suggestions of venues for information-gathering,
                        and nomination of commission members.</item>
                     <item>Ten Commission members, scholars and innovators with backgrounds in
                        economics, art history, georaphy, archives, libraries, documentary film and
                        television, literature, history, archaeology, and scholarly communication,
                        appointed in March 2004.</item>
                     <item>Nine domestic advisors, from the National Science Foundation, the
                        Berkeley Data Center, the National Endowment for the Humanities, the
                        Coalition for Networked Information, the Library of Congress, UCLA's
                        Department of Information Studies, the Council on Library and Information
                        Resources, and the American Council of Learned Societies.</item>
                     <item>Ten international advisors, from England, France, Germany, Norway,
                        Amsterdam, Canada, and Australia. A full proposal for funding submitted
                        (March, 2004).</item>
                     <item>Thirteen committee meetings (2004-2006) including six public
                        information-gathering sessions in different cities around the United States
                        (April 27, 2004, Washington, DC; May 22, 2004, Chicago, IL; June 19, 2004,
                        New York, NY; August 21, 2004, Berkeley, CA; September 18, 2004, Los
                        Angeles, CA; October 26, 2004, Baltimore, MD).</item>
                     <item>A mailman discussion list for the committee, and another for public
                        comments on drafts.</item>
                     <item>Three private drafts (March 2005, August 2005, October 2005), two public
                        drafts (November 2005, March 2006), and a final version (November 29,
                        2006).</item>
                     <item>Two editors (Abby Smith from April 2004-May 2005; Marlo Welshons from
                        June 2005-November 2006) and an editorial subcommittee of four members of
                        the Commission (Chuck Henry, Roy Rosenzweig, Steve Wheatley, John
                        Unsworth).</item>
                     <item>Meetings to review drafts with community stakeholders (February 2006) and
                        representatives of funding agencies (June 2006).</item>
                     <item>And for the chair, about 400 electronic documents, 1600 email messages,
                        and 100,000 frequent flyer miles (for travel to sixteen presentations
                        concerning the report at university colloquia, scholarly societies, summits,
                        and other meetings in the United States, China, Australia, the United
                        Kingdom, and Germany).</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Results and Reactions</head>
               <p>What actually happens as a result of such a report? In this case, as with the NSF
                  Cyberinfrastructure report, the object was to change the funding landscape, but in
                  our case there is no one funder who dominates that landscape as the NSF does in
                  computational science. Therefore, in some real sense, it was an important outcome
                  just to get representatives of the private foundations and the public funding
                  agencies to talk with one another about a shared agenda, and it was an equally
                  important outcome for the Commission to be able to represent the scholarly
                  community in setting that agenda.</p>
               <p>The meeting with funders in June of 2006 to discuss the draft report was
                  particularly interesting. The meeting was co-hosted by the Andrew W. Mellon
                  Foundation and the Institute of Museum and Library Services, and held at IMLS.
                  Present, in addition to Mellon and IMLS representatives, were representatives of
                  the National Historical Publications and Records Commission, the Library of
                  Congress, the National Science Foundation, the J. Paul Getty Trust, the Teagle
                  Foundation, the National Endowment for the Humanities, and the National Archives
                  and Records Administration. There were a number of useful and substantive
                  suggestions made at that meeting, especially about the recommendations of the
                  report and how to focus them more effectively on particular audiences and
                  respondents. But for me, at least, the most striking thing about that meeting was
                  the realization that it was extremely useful and important for the funding
                  agencies to have a group and a process that could credibly claim to represent the
                  aspirations of the community which those agencies served, because it would allow
                  them to base their recommendations for programmatic goals on something other than
                  their own perceptions of what was needed. In short, it would help them to make the
                  case to their own boards, or (in the case of federal funders) to the legislature,
                  that certain goals and activities were important to support. I have been working
                  with both federal and private funders for fifteen years now, and in retrospect it
                  should have been perfectly obvious to me that this was an important reason for
                  doing the report, but it was not. Why? I think the reason is that when faculty
                  think about research funding, we find it difficult to step outside of our
                  immediate role as petitioners and think about the funding landscape from another
                  perspective--that of the funder. It is a commonly understood dynamic, in science
                  and engineering, that the community needs to come together and agree on research
                  priorities for a particular field, in order for funding agencies to prioritize the
                  programs they will offer and the goals they will pursue. Obviously, there are also
                  other forces at work in setting funding priorities, and the process of <q>agreeing
                     on research priorities</q> in a discipline is not necessarily a process that
                  ends in consensus, or in a framework into which everyone fits. But in the
                  humanities, the very notion of asking <q>What are the top research priorities?</q>
                  in history or in English seems absurd, since the value of a research project in
                  humanities disciplines is defined, to a large extent, by the originality with
                  which it defines the question it aims to address. Nonetheless, one clearly useful
                  outcome of the ACLS Commission's report was that it gave voice to some priorities
                  of a research community--even if those priorities did not take the form of
                  research problems to be solved, but of resources needed in digital form, or
                  training and support, or policy changes.</p>
               <p>Some of the direct effects of the ACLS Commission's report on funding agencies can
                  be seen in their own framing of new programs. For example, in presenting its
                  JISC/NEH Transatlantic Digitization Collaboration Grants program, the NEH notes
                  that <quote rend="block" source="#http://www.neh.gov/whoweare/cio/centers/">Collaboration between U.S. and English institutions is a
                     key requirement for this grant category, based in part on the recommendations
                     for international collaboration in Professor Sir Gareth Roberts's <title rend="quotes">International Partnerships of Research Excellence U.K.-U.S.A
                        Academic Collaboration</title> (25-page PDF) and the report (51-page PDF) of
                     the American Council for [sic] Learned Societies' Commission on
                     Cyberinfrastructure for the Humanities and Social Sciences.</quote> Other
                  indications are in the meetings sponsored, for example the NEH Summit Meeting of
                  Digital Humanities Centers (April 12-13, 2007), organized with the Maryland
                  Institute for Technology in the Humanities and hosted at the NEH itself. The NEH's
                  description says that <quote rend="inline" source="#x_http://www.neh.gov/whoweare/cio/centers/">The meeting is part of NEH's Digital
                     Humanities Initiative and was inspired by a recent report by the American
                     Council of Learned Societies’ Commission on Cyberinfrastructure</quote>
                  <ref target="http://www.neh.gov/whoweare/cio/centers/">http://​www.neh.gov/​whoweare/​cio/centers/</ref>.
                  The Digital Humanities Initiative as a whole can be seen as a programmatic
                  response to the ACLS report, and it was initiated about the same time that the
                  draft report appeared for public comment. Other indicators of impact in funding
                  agencies may be seen in the particular projects funded; for example, in the IMLS
                  National Leadership Grants for 2007, the Council on Library and Information
                  Resources was funded for <title rend="quotes">A National Program for Scholars'
                     Analysis and Development of Cyberinfrastructure,</title> which aims to
                  coordinate <quote rend="inline" source="#x_http://www.imls.gov/news/2007/092507_list.shtm">the new large-scale digital initiatives that are
                     being developed across the country in line with the recommendations of the
                     American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS) Commission on Cyberinfrastructure
                     for the Humanities and Social Sciences</quote>
                  <ref target="http://www.imls.gov/news/2007/092507_list.shtm">http://​www.imls.gov/​news/​2007/​092507_list.shtm</ref>.
                  Further signs might be seen in what program officers are writing and speaking
                  about, for example Joyce Ray (IMLS) speaking on <title rend="quotes">Building the
                     Cyberinfrastructure in the U.S.</title> at the JISC Digitisation Conference in
                  Cardiff, Wales, July 19-20, 2007, or Chris Mackie (Mellon Foundation) writing on
                     <title rend="quotes">Cyberinfrastructure, Institutions, and
                     Sustainability</title> in <title>First Monday</title> in June 2007 <ref target="http://firstmonday.org/issues/issue12_6/mackie/index.html">http://​firstmonday.org/​issues/​issue12_6/​mackie/​index.html</ref>,
                  and what community thought-leaders are speaking about, for example Greg Crane's
                  talk on <title rend="quotes">Repositories, Cyberinfrastructure And The
                     Humanities</title> at the NSF/JISC Repositories Workshop in April, 2007, in
                  Arizona <ref target="http://www.sis.pitt.edu/~repwkshop/papers/crane.html">http://​www.sis.pitt.edu/​~repwkshop/​papers/​crane.html</ref>.
                  There's also been some international impact, as evidenced in <title rend="quotes">Our Cultural Commonwealth - notes de lectures,</title> a largely favorable
                  French commentary on the report dated January 5, 2007 <ref target="http://artist.inist.fr/article.php3?id_article=376">http://​artist.inist.fr/​article.php3?id_article=376</ref>,
                  and in Australia, where 2007's annual forum on Scholarly Communication, sponsored
                  by the Australian Academy of the Humanities, featured discussion of the ACLS
                  Commission's report <ref target="http://www.humanities.org.au/events/nscf/nscf2007/nscf2007.htm">http://​www.humanities.org.au/​Events/​NSCF/​NSCF2007/​NSCF2007.htm</ref>. </p>
               <p>Not everyone was happy with the Commission's report, of course. And while there
                  were some <hi rend="italic">amicus curiae</hi> briefs filed by scholars and
                  academic libraries, the stakeholders who felt most alienated by the report were
                  university presses and scholarly societies. This was in part because the draft of
                  the report submitted for public comment was directly critical of presses and
                  societies for failing to take risks, for taking a narrow view of their mission,
                  and for lacking imagination. After some sharp feedback on the draft, the
                  Commission did take a different tack in the final report, emphasizing positive
                  examples rather than negative ones, and credit rather than blame, but publishers
                  were not much mollified. A more or less typical response is this one, from Robert
                  Townsend of the American Historical Association: <quote rend="block" source="#x">[T]he report
                     offers a rather fanciful lesson in the economics of scholarly publishing that
                     makes first-copy costs and sustainability disappear into a fog of <q>public
                        goods</q> and <q>collective action.</q> The resulting picture should really
                     trouble non-profit publishers, as the commission rather blithely erases our
                     role in the system of scholarly communication along with the costs we have to
                     recover. As a result, we seem to be re-cast as an unnecessary impediment to the
                     development of a cyberinfrastructure. When the commission then calls on us to
                     engage with other parties (librarians and university administrators) about
                     these issues, it just seem to be inviting us into a dialogue about the
                     arrangements for our own funerals.</quote> A more recent response, by Sandy
                  Thatcher, director of Penn State's Press, repeats the complaint that the ACLS
                  Commission's report is uninformed and unrealistic with respect to the harsh
                  economic realities of university press and scholarly society publishing: <quote rend="block" source="#x">[U]niversity presses would welcome the freedom to engage in the
                     supply of a <q>pure public good</q> like knowledge free of severe economic
                     constraints. Only the Commission doesn't tell us how to get to this promised
                     land. It doesn't even include in the final report the acknowledgment of the
                     draft report that...a variety of activities that presses could pursue...<quote rend="inline" source="#x">could well produce sufficient value for libraries to be paid
                        for in the cash economy in which publishers now largely operate, if
                        publishers were properly capitalized to retool so they could provide such
                        services.</quote> But that is just the point. Where does such capital come
                     from?</quote> And later in the same piece: <quote rend="block" source="#x">University
                     presses have been chronically underfunded, and even today few universities seem
                     to have much inclination to invest in their presses so that they could
                        <q>retool</q> themselves. On the contrary, to provide just one recent
                     example, the announcement of the position of director of the SUNY Press
                     includes this among its expectations: <quote rend="inline" source="#x">increase financial
                        assets of the Press with the goal of achieving financial sustainability
                        within five years.</quote> In other words, the SUNY administration expects
                     the press soon to operate with no subsidy from the university at all. There is
                     no better way to hamstring a press from engaging in the kind of retooling and
                     experimentation that the Commission calls for in this report. So long as such
                     attitudes prevail among university administrators, the road to <q>open
                        access</q> will remain closed as far as university presses are
                     concerned.</quote> What continues to puzzle me, as chair of the ACLS
                  Commission, is that Presses don't see the report as anything that could be useful
                  to them in their conversations with university administrators about just these
                  issues, and also that these publishers--both university presses and scholarly
                  societies--seem always to start from the premise that the status quo is
                  non-negotiable, and then proceed to explain why they have no choice but to act as
                  they have been acting, since the economic conditions under which they operate are
                  non-negotiable. Certainly libraries and funding agencies did not respond to the
                  report in that way, nor have libraries often missed the opportunity to turn
                  criticisms to advantage, in their negotiation with university administrators.
                  Still, it is true that there are some exceptional presses who are doing
                  exceptional work that needs to be recognized--especially in those places where the
                  press has worked out a productive partnership with the library (and, sometimes,
                  the campus computing organization): Columbia's EPIC, The University of California
                  Press's Mark Twain project (and CDL collaborations), and the University of
                  Virginia Press's Rotunda imprint, which publishes a number of digital scholarly
                  projects that began as library projects, or the University of Illinois' History
                  Cooperative, which allows individual journals to experiment with pricing policies
                  in a shared infrastructure for e-journal publishing. But these are remarkable
                  precisely because they are exceptions, and the recent report from Ithaka (<title rend="quotes">University Publishing in a Digital Age</title>) makes it clear
                  that university presses are losing mind-share with their campus-level
                  administrators, and losing the initiative to university libraries: <quote rend="block" source="#x">In our interviews we detected significant detachment from
                     administrators about publishing's connection to their core mission; a high
                     level of energy and excitement from librarians about reinventing their roles on
                     campus to meet the evolving needs of their constituents; and a wide range of
                     responses from press directors, from those who are continuing to do what they
                     have always done, to those who are actively reconnecting with their host
                     institutions’ academic programs and engaging in collaborative efforts to
                     develop new electronic products.</quote> According to this report, press
                  directors <quote rend="block" source="#x">acknowledge that they have not participated actively
                     enough in the academic life of their campus, nor have they effectively
                     demonstrated their worth to faculty and administrators. As a director said,
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#x">We don’t do a good job of telling our universities why
                        we are important to them.</quote> One director spoke of a <q>feeling of
                        divorce</q> from the university leadership, expressing what seems to be a
                     common feeling among press leaders.</quote> That divorce is not going to come
                  with alimony, though, and if university presses don't figure out how to recast
                  their role as more central to the campus each lives on, they will not be
                  continuing their work somewhere else--they will be dismantled, possibly to be
                  replaced by scholarly publishing offices in libraries, or by commercial
                  publishers. Karla Hahn, who oversees the Association of Research Libraries' office
                  of scholarly communication, estimated in a recent public presentation at the
                  University of Illinois that over half of ARL libraries are now engaged in some
                  kind of publishing activity.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Conclusion</head>
               <p>These are internecine disputes, though. The most important audience for the
                  humanities, and the audience least likely to be reached by a report from the
                  American Council of Learned Societies--or by university presses, or by university
                  libraries, for that matter--is the general public. And this was also the most
                  difficult audience for the humanities scholars who addressed the Commission, and
                  for the Commission itself. This is a point worth examining. The problem seemed to
                  be that humanities scholars found it very difficult to say exactly why the work
                  they do should matter to the general public; in fact, they often did not believe
                  that it would. I believe that this is directly related to the aforementioned
                  rhetoric of problem-solving: the sciences have a glorious and durable narrative of
                  progress toward the greater good through medical advances, technological
                  development, and scientific discoveries. Science, technology, and medicine are,
                  arguably, insufficiently self-conscious about whether or not their research
                  produces an unalloyed public good: in the history of the 20th century, for
                  example, they seem remarkably untroubled by Hiroshima, at least in their public
                  rhetoric; by contrast, the humanities seem to be keenly self-aware that expertise
                  in the practice and appreciation of literature, music, philosophy didn't save
                  Germany from Naziism, so they are reluctant to make simple-minded arguments about
                  intrinsic social good arising from the appreciation of high culture. And the more
                  complicated arguments that scholars might make for the value of their research or
                  the importance of their disciplines seem to them to be arguments that will matter
                  most to those who have already accepted the grounding assumption that the activity
                  itself is worthy, rather than being arguments that would persuade someone to share
                  that assumption. Interestingly, I think this self-abnegation is shared and even
                  reinforced by university presses, who seem, on the whole, unable to believe in the
                  Long Tail--unable, in other words, to believe that there are relatively large but
                  widely dispersed and non-professional audiences for almost any humanities topic.
                  In fact, I would argue that in this regard the humanities are much better off than
                  the sciences: the public might want the results of scientific research, but they
                  are not all that interested in the actual content and conduct of that research; in
                  the humanities, research does have a general audience, but publishers aren't
                  accustomed to looking for it. We need to look for it, though, and we need to
                  connect with the public, in the cyberinfrastructure they increasingly inhabit in
                  their daily lives. As I said in a 2006 presentation to the Association of American
                  University Presses on <title rend="quotes">Vernacular Computing,</title> the
                  urgency to do this isn't just the presses'; it is also the universities': <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="http://www3.isrl.uiuc.edu/~unsworth/AAUP.2006.html">Fifteen years ago, the challenge before us was to imagine
                        how new technology might provide a new platform for the practice of
                        scholarship in the humanities, but today our challenge is the reverse. It is
                        no longer about opening the university and inviting the public in: it's
                        about getting out where they already live, and meeting the public in the
                        information commons, on the same terms that everyone else does. In fact,
                        it's almost too late for us. We will find that hard to believe, ensconced
                        (as we all are) in solid-seeming residential universities, with long
                        histories and the expectation of a long future — but older institutions on
                        more solid foundations have been swept away or radically transformed in
                        cultural upheavals of the past. In spite of the inertia of these
                        institutions, which we all know so well, the forces of change outside the
                        institution have much greater inertia, and all of the practical furniture of
                        our daily academic lives could easily be gone, or changed beyond
                        recognition, in a generation.</quote>
                     <ref target="http://www3.isrl.uiuc.edu/~unsworth/AAUP.2006.html">http://​www3.isrl.uiuc.edu/​~unsworth/​AAUP.2006.html</ref>
                  </cit>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Recent Reports Relevant to Cyberinfrastructure in Humanities and Social
               Sciences</head>
            <p>
               <list type="unordered">
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">Making the Humanities Count: The Importance of
                        Data,</title> American Academy of Arts &amp; Sciences. Robert M. Solow,
                     Phyllis Franklin, Calvin C. Jones, John D’Arms, Francis Oakley. 2002. <ref target="http://www.amacad.org/publications/monographs/making_the_humanities_count.pdf">http://​www.amacad.org/​​publications/​​monographs/​​Making_the_Humanities_Count.pdf</ref>.</item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">Revolutionizing Science and Engineering Through
                        Cyberinfrastructure: Report of the National Science Foundation Blue-Ribbon
                        Advisory Panel on Cyberinfrastructure.</title> Dan Atkins et al. 2003. <ref target="http://www.nsf.gov/od/oci/reports/toc.jsp">http://​www.nsf.gov/​​od/​​oci/​​reports/​​toc.jsp</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">Knowledge Lost in Information. Report of the NSF Workshop
                        on Research Directions for Digital Libraries.</title> Ronald Larsen, Howard
                     Wactlar. 2003. <ref target="http://www.sis.pitt.edu/~dlwkshop/report.pdf">http://​www.sis.pitt.edu/​​~dlwkshop/​​report.pdf</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">The United Nations World Summit on the Information
                        Society.</title> 2003, 2005. <ref target="http://www.itu.int/wsis/">http://​www.itu.int/​​wsis/</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">Cyberscience: Research in the Age of the Internet.</title>
                     Michael Nentwich. Austrian Academy of Sciences Press. 2003. <ref target="http://hw.oeaw.ac.at/cyberscience">http://​hw.oeaw.ac.at/​​cyberscience</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">Report on the Delos/NSF working group on Emerging Language
                        Technologies and the Rediscovery of the Past: A Research Agenda.</title>
                     Gregory Crane, Kalina Bontcheva. 2003. <ref target="http://www.ercim.org/publication/ws-proceedings/Delos-NSF/Ephilology.pdf">http://​www.ercim.org/​​publication/​​ws-proceedings/​​Delos-NSF/​​Ephilology.pdf</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">The Book as the <q>Gold Standard</q> for Promotion and
                        Tenure in the Humanistic Disciplines: A Report to Provosts and Arts and
                        Sciences Deans in CIC Universities.</title> Leigh Estabrook, Library
                     Research Center, Graduate School of Library and Information Science, University
                     of Illinois Urbana-Champaign. 2003. <ref target="http://lrc.lis.uiuc.edu/reports/cicbook.html">http://​lrc.lis.uiuc.edu/​​reports/​​CICBook.html</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">Beyond Productivity Committee on Information Technology
                        and Creativity.</title> William J. Mitchell, Alan S. Inouye, and Marjory S.
                     Blumenthal, Editors. Computer Science and Telecommunications Board Division on
                     Engineering and Physical Sciences. The National Academies Press. Washington,
                     D.C. 2003. <ref target="http://books.nap.edu/catalog.php?record_id=10671">http://​books.nap.edu/​​catalog.php?record_id=10671</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">A Survey of Digital Cultural Heritage Initiatives and
                        Their Sustainability Concerns.</title> Diane M. Zorich, Council on Library
                     and Information Resources. Washington, D.C. 2003. <ref target="http://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub118/contents.html">http://​www.clir.org/​​pubs/​​reports/​​pub118/​​contents.html</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">Business Planning for Cultural Heritage
                        Institutions.</title> Liz Bishoff and Nancy Allen, Council on Library and
                     Information Resources. 2004. <ref target="http://www.clir.org/pubs/abstract/pub124abst.html">http://​www.clir.org/​​pubs/​​abstract/​​pub124abst.html</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">That full complement of riches: the contributions of the
                        arts, humanities and social sciences to the nation’s wealth.</title> The
                     British Academy. 2004. <ref target="http://www.britac.ac.uk/policy/contribution/index.cfm">http://​www.britac.ac.uk/​policy/​contribution/​index.cfm</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">DigiCULT Resource Discovery Technologies for the Heritage
                        Sector Thematic, Issue 6.</title> 2004. <ref target="http://www.digicult.info/pages/themiss.php">http://​www.digicult.info/​​pages/​​themiss.php</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">Foundation Funding for the Humanities: An Overview of
                        Current and Historical Trends.</title> Loren Renz, Steven Lawrence. The
                     Foundation Center, in cooperation with The American Academy of Arts &amp;
                     Sciences. 2004. <ref target="http://foundationcenter.org/gainknowledge/research/pdf/human.pdf">http://​foundationcenter.org/​​gainknowledge/​​research/​​pdf/​​human.pdf</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">E-based Humanities and E-humanities on a SURF platform: A
                        report commissioned by SURF-DARE.</title> Dr. Joost Kircz, Kircz Research
                     Amsterdam. 2004. <ref target="http://dare.uva.nl/record/119979">http://​dare.uva.nl/​​record/​​119979</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">Final Report: NSF SBE-CISE Workshop on Cyberinfrastructure
                        and the Social Sciences.</title> F. Berman and H. Brady. 2005. <ref target="http://vis.sdsc.edu/sbe/reports/sbe-cise-final.pdf">http://​vis.sdsc.edu/​​sbe/​​reports/​​SBE-CISE-FINAL.pdf</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">Marketing Culture in the Digital Age.</title> Peter
                     Kaufman. Ithaka. 2005. <ref target="http://www.intelligenttelevision.com/marketingcultureindigitalage.pdf">http://​www.intelligenttelevision.com/​​MarketingCultureinDigitalAge.pdf</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">ICT Strategy Reports.</title> David Bates, Mark
                     Greengrass, Lesly Huxley, Claire Warwick, Sheila Anderson, Alan Marsden, Mike
                     Pringle. 2006. <ref target="http://www.ahrcict.rdg.ac.uk/activities/strategy_projects/reports/index.htm">http://​www.ahrcict.rdg.ac.uk/​​activities/​​strategy_projects/​​reports/​​index.htm</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">Use and Users of Digital Resources: A Focus on
                        Undergraduate Education in the Humanities and Social Sciences.</title> Diane
                     Harley, Jonathan Henke, Shannon Lawrence, Ian Miller, Irene Perciali, and David
                     Nasatir. 2006. <ref target="http://cshe.berkeley.edu/research/digitalresourcestudy/report/">http://​cshe.berkeley.edu/​​research/​​digitalresourcestudy/​​report/</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">University Publishing In A Digital Age.</title> Laura
                     Brown, Rebecca Griffiths, Matthew Rascoff. Ithaka. 2007. <ref target="http://www.ithaka.org/strategic-services/Ithaka%20University%20Publishing%20Report.pdf">http://​www.ithaka.org/​​strategic-services/​​Ithaka%20University%20Publishing%20Report.pdf</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <title rend="quotes">Faculty Attitudes and Behaviors Regarding Scholarly
                        Communication: Survey Findings from the University Of California.</title>
                     University of California Office of Scholarly Communications. 2007. <ref target="http://osc.universityofcalifornia.edu/responses/materials/OSC-survey-full-20070828.pdf">http://​osc.universityofcalifornia.edu/​​responses/​​materials/​​OSC-survey-full-20070828.pdf</ref>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Responses to the report of the ACLS Commission on Cyberinfrastructure in
               Humanities and Social Sciences</head>
            <p>
               <list type="unordered">
                  <item>Jean-Michel Salaün et al. <title rend="quotes">Our Cultural
                        Commonwealth--Notes de lectures.</title> January, 2007. <ref target="http://artist.inist.fr/article.php3?id_article=376">http://​artist.inist.fr/​​article.php3?id_article=376</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sanford Thatcher. <title rend="quotes">From the University
                        Presses--Collaborating to Create Cyberinfrastructure: A Critique of the ACLS
                        Report on <q>Our Cultural Commonwealth</q>
                     </title>, in <title rend="italic">Against the Grain</title>. September 2007.
                     54-55.</item>
                  <item>Robert Townsend. <title rend="quotes">Review of the ACLS Cyberinfrastructure
                        Report</title> in <title rend="italic">The Exchange Online</title>,
                     Association of American University Presses. February 9, 2002<ref target="http://aaupblog.aaupnet.org/?p=11">http://​aaupblog.aaupnet.org/​​?p=11</ref>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label=""> </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>