<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Rewiring Digital Humanities through an Ethics of
                    Ecological Care</title>
                <!-- Add a <title rend="italic">
 with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Photini<dhq:family>Vrikki</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1007-3292</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>PLACEHOLDER</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>gunes.tavmen@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>PLACEHOLDER</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Gunes<dhq:family>Tavmen</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6532-5285</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University College London</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>p.vrikki@ucl.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>PLACEHOLDER</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <!-- This information should be added when the file is created -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000802</idno>


                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="volume">019</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date><!--PLACEHOLDER-->August 29, 2025</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/wiki/DHQ-Topic-Keywords; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->

                    <!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new <term> element for each -->
                    <term corresp="#pedagogy"/>
                    <term corresp="#ecocriticism"/>
                    <term corresp="#ethics"/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>ethics of ecological care</item>
                        <item>praxis</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Replace "XXXXXX" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
            <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
                    target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000802/000802.xml"
                    >GitHub </ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>This paper advocates for a fundamental transformation of the Digital Humanities
                    (DH) field through the adoption of an <hi rend="italic">ethics of ecological
                        care</hi>, challenging the discipline’s current entanglement with
                    environmentally damaging digital infrastructures. Drawing on feminist care
                    ethics, postcolonial ecocriticism, and environmental humanities, we argue that
                    DH must move beyond surface-level sustainability and engage in a deep, critical
                    reassessment of its pedagogies, methodologies, and institutional affiliations.
                    The paper critiques DH’s complicity in extractive practices and digital
                    techno-solutionism, calling for a shift from neutrality to active environmental
                    accountability by introducing a two-pronged strategy: rewiring DH methodologies
                    to reflect ecological awareness and embedding ecological care into DH education.
                    By examining existing projects within Digital Environmental Humanities (DEH) and
                    eco-critical DH, we highlight pathways for building more inclusive, decolonial,
                    and care-centred practices. We imagine a rewired DH that is not a neutral
                    academic space but a dynamic, ethical actor capable of contributing to planetary
                    health and environmental justice. Positioning DH as a critical site for
                    cultivating collective responsibility in the face of ecological precarity, the
                    paper envisions a <q>care-full</q> DH committed to resisting exploitative
                    systems and fostering sustained, interdisciplinary engagement with the climate
                    crisis.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>PLACEHOLDER</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>More than a decade has passed since Bethany Nowviskie’s (2015) ground-breaking
                    keynote address at the 2014 Digital Humanities conference in Lausanne <ptr
                        target="#nowviskie_2015"/>. Nowviskie’s talk, delivered amidst the
                    burgeoning recognition of the Anthropocene as a new geological epoch marked by
                    profound human impact on Earth, posed a poignant challenge to the field of
                    Digital Humanities (DH). She interrogated the capacity of DH to grapple with the
                    complexities of the climate emergency, specifically questioning the discipline’s
                    ability to maintain its humanistic core while operating at the vast scales
                    arising from the potential of digital tools to both empower and alienate human
                    agency. Indeed, while navigating this paradox of progress, DH sits at the crux
                    of promoting technological advancement and societal development while also
                    recognising the ways in which these changes are intricately linked to
                    environmental degradation. Ten years on, with scientists setting off warning
                    bells on our planet’s future <ptr target="#fletcher_2024"/>, Nowviskie’s inquiry
                    rings more urgent, probing us into the possibility of fostering progress within
                    DH while simultaneously critiquing and resisting the dominant narratives that
                    have contributed to the global ecological crisis. </p>
                <p>In this paper, we build on this type of inquiry by carrying out a reflective
                    discussion on the ways in which DH may be complicit in the impending climate
                    crisis by relying on the infrastructures and extractive practices that
                    contribute to depletion of resources. With this, we hope to provide a conceptual
                    framework through which the field’s methodologies and pedagogies could play a
                    key role in contributing to thriving ecosystems. Our proposal for the discipline
                    is to adopt an Ethics of Ecological Care that requires a commitment to
                    environmentally conscious practices that could subsequently contribute to
                    achieving environmental justice. By this, we envision going beyond the Western
                    conceptualisation of environmentalist practices, such as the promotion of ‘green
                    growth’ or ‘green consumption’, that are often considered as main pillars of
                    sustainability <ptr target="#bell_2020"/> and engage with the care-related
                    aspects of the ecological crisis we are heading towards. Such a strategy demands
                    a critical move from silence and a superficial focus on partiality or
                    sustainable development goals <ptr target="#drucker_2021"/>, towards a more
                    profound vision of ecological care inclusive of an ecologically aware critical
                    pedagogy <ptr target="#freire_1979"/>. </p>
                <p>Neutrality, accompanied by a conspicuous silence regarding the environmental
                    repercussions of digital technologies, has become increasingly indefensible. At
                    this critical juncture, DH alongside other institutional actors, bears a
                    responsibility to critically examine its role in the climate crisis and to
                    actively pursue strategies for its mitigation. DH, as a discipline deeply
                    enmeshed with digital infrastructures and computational methodologies, is
                    uniquely positioned at the intersection of technology and society. The field’s
                    extensive reliance on data collection, data management, data storage,
                    high-performance computing, and large-scale digital archives undoubtedly
                    contributes to energy and resource depletion as well as producing a significant
                    carbon footprint. This should compel DH scholars to critically assess the
                    environmental dimensions of their work. By interrogating the lifecycle impacts
                    of digital tools and practices, from data creation and curation to storage and
                    dissemination, DH scholars can evaluate the ecological costs of digital
                    preservation, the energy demands of algorithmic processing, the sustainability
                    of current technological infrastructures, and the waste created as a result. DH
                    requires a rewiring beyond the role of a neutral ally, to employ a paradigmatic
                    and engaged position that may urge everyone and their work to become part and
                    parcel of the pursuit of an equitable, just, and care-full ecology. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>From an Interdisciplinary Present to Environmentally Care-full Futures</head>
                <p>Transformative and meaningful change within this framework of care postulates
                    traversing a complex interplay of forces. Any attempt to radically alter a
                    discipline, particularly one as intricately interwoven as Digital Humanities
                    (DH), will undoubtedly encounter friction between established institutional
                    interests and the pursuit of novel agendas. Under these circumstances, we
                    suggest a need to explore an alternative course of action, moving away from the
                    inertia within academia which can act as an impediment to transformative change.
                    The interdisciplinary core of Digital Humanities itself <ptr
                        target="#smithies_2017"/>
                    <ptr target="#odonnell_2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#thaller_2012"/> encompasses the critical application and
                    interrogation of computational and digital methodologies across various domains
                    such as digital heritage, libraries, culture, and society <ptr
                        target="#edmond_2021"/>
                    <ptr target="#deegan_2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#wolfe_2007"/>. The precise interdisciplinarity and inclusiveness
                    of the field is already a niche school of thought within DH with ongoing
                    scholarly debates stretching and narrowing the discipline's definition
                    constantly <ptr target="#klein_2015"/>. Yet many refer to the field as
                    expansive, an umbrella term, a tactical label, a generic framework, or simply a
                    conducive environment for fostering connections and building bridges between
                    diverse spheres of study <ptr target="#liu_2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#berry_2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#borgman_2010"/>. Indeed, the concept of the <q>big tent</q> as
                    described by <ptr target="#finneman_2014"/> diagnoses DH as an inclusive domain
                    that welcomes a broad range of participants, methodologies, and disciplines.
                    Challenged by <ptr target="#whitson_2017"/> and <ptr target="#svensson_2016"/>,
                    this <q>big tent</q> viewpoint stresses the local contexts and multiple
                    histories of DH and sees the field as a trading zone and meeting place. </p>
                <p>These contradictory — and often adversary perspectives — collectively suggest
                    that the field is diverse and dynamic, characterised by a range of disciplinary,
                    national, and outer-institutional contexts. In fact, the recent intersection of
                    postcolonial studies and digital humanities has exacerbated these connections
                    and disconnections and has seen scholars exploring the contradictions of this
                    second wave of DH through the lens of postcolonial information societies <ptr
                        target="#shah_2020"/>, exposing the role of colonial violence in digital
                        archives<ptr target="#gajjala_2019"/>, critiquing the technical and
                    commercial strategies of powerful entities in the sector<ptr target="#sanz_2013"
                    />, and promoting a decolonisation of digital humanities through intersectional
                    engagement <ptr target="#risam_2018"/>. This paper does not intend to contribute
                    to these extensive and fruitful discussions surrounding the definition of DH,
                    nor does it aim to establish a new moral foundation for the discipline. We
                    instead consider DH, in the broadest sense, as a discipline that includes both
                    cultural and humanities research done by digital and computational methods as
                    well as humanities informed research on the social, political, and cultural
                    implications of the digital and computation. Rather than viewing the ongoing
                    structural uncertainties as a hindrance or a constant, we propose that by
                    conceptualising DH as a dynamic process, one where its definition evolves rather
                    than remains rigidly fixed, we can unlock a fertile ground for exploring
                    synergies with other concepts, and more specifically through the concept of
                    ethics of ecological care. </p>
                <p>Over the past decade, two main strands have emerged to tackle the issue:
                    Eco-critical DH and Digital Environmental Humanities (DEH) which both advocate
                    for incorporating ecological awareness into DH pedagogy and research practices.
                    Eco-critical DH focuses on integrating environmental themes within DH
                    methodologies, while DEH emphasises the use of digital tools for environmental
                    humanities scholarship. <ptr target="#ryan_2023"/> exemplify DEH's potential to
                    cultivate environmental activism through practices like perennial
                    echo-archiving, digital storytelling of ecological loss, and citizen
                    eco-humanities projects. Similarly, <ptr target="#travis_2016"/> showcase the
                    application of digital tools and interdisciplinary strategies in environmental
                    damage mitigation by detailing a Norwegian project that uses data analysis to
                    monitor fishing practices and another that employs sensors, data analytics, and
                    virtual reality to study the environmental impact of human interaction in urban
                    settings. In the view of <ptr target="#posthumus_2014"/>, DEH can bridge the gap
                    between computational methods in DH and eco-criticism's focus on environmental
                    humanities. This, they argue, fosters a deeper understanding of nature's
                    representation in media and cultural narratives surrounding ecological issues.
                        <ptr target="#cohen_2016"/> built upon this foundation, advancing for
                        <q>ecological digital humanities</q> (EcoDH) within a special issue of PMLA.
                    EcoDH, they posit, necessitates a critical path that challenges the conventional
                    business-as-usual scholarship in the humanities. It encourages scholars to
                    harness digital media for the creation, composition, and restoration of
                    environmental narratives. Their approach proposes a disruption of unsustainable
                    innovation cycles and promotes environmentally responsible practices. While our
                    work aligns with these existing ideas, we propose a critical rewiring of DH’s
                    potential complicity in the environmental crisis while stressing the need for DH
                    to engage in self-reflection through a lens that fosters care-full ecological
                    consciousness. Our proposal is that we need to move beyond awareness to rewiring
                    the field through the lens of ecological care.</p>
                <p>In essence, we propose the transition of DH from a stance of presumed neutrality
                    to one of explicit accountability and a realm for purposeful and productive
                    action. We certainly do not suggest this rewirement as merely an academic
                    exercise; such a big shift clearly necessitates primarily an active engagement
                    with policy-making and institutional reforms that promote environmental justice.
                    To accomplish this, we introduce a two-pronged course to advance the integration
                    of DH into ecological care discourse. The first prong focuses on the
                    instrumentalisation of ecological care as a means to actively rewire DH
                    methodologies and tools. The recent shift toward decolonial and postcolonial
                    frameworks within DH provides a fertile ground for foregrounding reflective and
                    responsible ecological thinking in project design, enabling researchers to
                    redefine the field’s positionality in relation to environmental challenges. This
                    approach provides the foundations upon which we may cultivate research and
                    disciplinary practices that prioritise ongoing critical reflection, intentional
                    decision-making, and collaborative action in the pursuit of planetary wellbeing.
                    The second prong promotes a reconfiguration of DH pedagogic backbone by
                    incorporating ecological paradigms, prompting a critical reassessment of the
                    discipline’s pedagogical practices. This strategy not only integrates
                    environmental considerations into curricular design and digital/computational
                    tools and methodologies but also challenges established academic norms by
                    positioning sustainability as a central component of DH teaching. Focusing on
                    the methodologies and pedagogy of DH, currently intertwined with actors whose
                    influences neutralise the discipline’s capacity to address the climate crisis,
                    provides an imperative opportunity for critical self-examination through the
                    frame of ecological care we unpack in the next section. </p>
                <p>By acknowledging these entanglements, DH can begin to extricate itself from
                    inadvertently exacerbating environmental challenges and ecological destruction,
                    thereby realigning its practices. teaching, and tools with principles of
                    sustainability and accountability <ptr target="#fuller_2019"/>. As Gould argues,
                    the urgency and undeniable need for deliberate environmental intervention calls
                    for a shift within DH <quote rend="inline">to pursue an active [and activist]…
                        engaged praxis that connects technology, the environment and the ‘ethical
                        conditions of our vital here-and-now’</quote>
                    <ptr target="#gould_2021" loc="94"/> This shift opens new possibilities for the
                    field itself. By critically re-evaluating its methodologies and pedagogies as
                    environmental artifacts, DH can contribute to building a more eco-careful
                    future. Gould’s belief in the significance of <q>doing earth work,</q> directing
                    DH’s unique skill sets towards tackling environmental challenges, contributes to
                    our strategy in engaging with ethics of ecological care. Examining DH
                    reflectively adds a layer of complexity but at the same time highlights the need
                    for thoughtful and multifaceted approaches when integrating care into DH. To do
                    so we argue for ecological thinking in and through DH which resists the
                    environmentalist tactics that perpetuate colonialist, capitalist extraction
                    systems that perpetuate environmental destruction and injustices (see <ptr
                        target="#liboiron_2021"/>; <ptr target="#willoughby_2021"/>; <ptr
                        target="#bell_2014"/>. This also requires a process of unlearning to break
                    the cycle of disconnection, precarity, and destruction in which our society
                    seems to be stuck in <ptr target="#stephens_2024" loc="93"/>. The required shift
                    will not be achieved with incremental fixes; it requires a drastic, even
                    radical, challenge to <q>business as usual.</q> As Stephens puts it, <quote
                        rend="inline">Unlearning, the process of intentionally letting go of
                        previously acquired knowledge, beliefs, assumptions, and behaviours, is a
                        critical part of engaging with transformation and resisting hegemony</quote>
                    <ptr target="#stephens_2024" loc="50"/></p>
                <p>The following sections dissect the multifaceted discourse surrounding the future
                    of DH during the climate crisis. Our two-pronged strategy holds the potential to
                    guide the field’s trajectory through a range of active and vocal considerations,
                    including addressing ecological care within DH itself, fostering educational
                    initiatives, promoting fair innovation, and encouraging experimentation.
                    Different visions of the future hold varying degrees of emphasis on key areas,
                    and we need to ask: Which aspects of DH should be expanded or reduced,
                    developed, or resisted to achieve these ecologically care-full diverse future
                    configurations? This paper situates itself within these multifaceted debates,
                    fully acknowledging the absence of straightforward solutions. Rather than
                    offering a comprehensive blueprint for a future Digital Humanities predicated
                    solely on the ethics of ecological care, it engages with the inherent
                    complexities to envision a trajectory wherein ecological ethics are steadily
                    woven into the very identity of the field. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Ethics of Ecological Care</head>
                <p>Traditionally, environmental thinking, as developed in the Western societies, has
                    viewed nature as a backdrop to human activity; a collection of resources to be
                    managed or exploited. In other words, Western environmental thinking understood
                    society and environment as a binary, leading to the conceptualisation of
                    sustainability as a matter of ‘green growth’, an environmental agenda that has
                    been widely accepted and pursued by corporations and other international
                    policy-making organisations <ptr target="#throsby_2016"/>. By adopting
                    eco-critique, we bypass this Western framework and the Anthropocene Nowviskie
                    talked about in 2014, to follow Cubitt’s (2019) rejection of
                        <q>environmentalism</q> and argue for the need for a care that approaches
                    the current ecological crisis as a consequence of understanding the environment
                    as an externality <ptr target="#cubitt_2019"/>. As he states, <quote
                        rend="inline">This environmentalisation of the world, excluding it from
                        participation in human affairs, is the basis of rule […] What humans exclude
                        becomes externality, economists' term for resources that do not have to be
                        paid for</quote>
                    <ptr target="#cubitt_2019" loc="2"/>. Adapting Cubitt’s positionality, we
                    propose an ethics of ecological care for DH that conceives ecology as a network
                    of connections that generates things, instead of viewing things as separate
                    entities (including humans and their surroundings), which need to be connected
                    in the pursuit of environmentalism. This shift in perspective asks for a move
                    beyond simply managing resources and altering strategies, to understanding the
                    complex web of relationships that sustain ecological balance. By deploying
                    ecological care, we do not intend to create an addendum to the concept of DH; we
                    believe that it is a concept that is deeply intertwined in a world where our
                    work is interconnected along an axis of awareness and habits. In this section,
                    we suggest that a radical rewiring of DH can emerge from the adoption of ethics
                    of ecological care. Emerging nearly concurrently in the early 1980s within the
                    works of <ptr target="#gilligan_1982"/>, <ptr target="#noddings_1984"/>, <ptr
                        target="#ruddick_1980"/> and <ptr target="#ruddick_1989"/>, the concept of
                        <q>care ethics</q> challenged the prevailing justice-oriented moral theories
                    of utilitarianism, deontology, and rights theory to focus on traditionally
                        <q>feminine</q> domains like mothering and caregiving, addressing ethical
                    issues such as abortion decisions, care for the vulnerable, and the ethics of
                    intimate relationships. However, the concept has undergone a remarkable
                    transformation over the past few decades breaking new ground away from its
                    philosophical roots. Care ethics has now become a central concept across a wide
                    range of disciplines, such as political science, economics, sociology, history,
                    nursing, biomedical ethics, and theology. </p>
                <p>Here, we primarily focus on the practical underpinnings of care ethics, however,
                    we acknowledge the concept’s interdisciplinary trajectory as crucial, and more
                    significantly, we adopt its feminist articulation of <q>ecological care
                        feminism</q> (ECF). Feminist perspectives define care work as unrecognised
                    and undervalued labour, disproportionately shouldered by women, <quote
                        rend="inline">with no expectation of immediate pecuniary reward</quote>
                    <ptr target="#folbre_1995" loc="75"/> or as <quote rend="inline">a species of
                        activity that includes everything we do to maintain, contain, and repair our
                        ‘world’ so that we can live in it as well as possible</quote>
                    <ptr target="#tronto_1990" loc="40"/>. This framework highlights collective
                    action, fostering mutual support through <quote rend="inline">continual
                        affective and emotional adjustments</quote>
                    <ptr target="#bennett_2020"/>) and promoting well-being by minimising harm <ptr
                        target="#steiner_2017"/>. Extending this definition of care, ECF stresses
                    the historical association of women with nature and their commitment to
                    environmental conservation, further enriched by indigenous and feminist care
                    ethics, which highlight the interconnectedness of humans and nonhumans and the
                    importance of empowering communities to care for themselves and their
                    environments. </p>
                <p>ECF, as discussed by <ptr target="#warren_1991"/>, <ptr target="#merchant_1995"
                    />, <ptr target="#irwin_2013"/>, and <ptr target="#macgregor_2010"/>, challenges
                    the traditional association of women with nature and caregiving while advocating
                    for shared environmental responsibility. <ptr target="#warren_1991"/> reject
                    essentialist views, framing ecological care as a collective moral duty, while
                        <ptr target="#merchant_1995"/> critiques patriarchal exploitation of both
                    women and nature, calling for ethical ecological practices such as
                    interconnectedness and reciprocity, the rejection of exploitation, and holistic
                    and community-oriented paths. Irwin’s (2013) emphasis on structural and systemic
                    changes that integrate care ethics into decision-making <ptr
                        target="#irwin_2013"/>and MacGregor’s (2010) critique of romanticising
                    women’s caregiving roles <ptr target="#macgregor_2010"/>are both paramount here
                    as they justify a radical perspective that acknowledges care as both labour and
                    a moral responsibility, underscoring the need for its fair distribution across
                    society and policy. In our adaptation for DH, a radical rewire calls for
                    outgrowing individual acts of caring and translating them into field-wide
                    changes that may contribute to a comprehensive commitment to safeguarding people
                    while prioritising shared responsibility and mutual support. This critique is
                    particularly important when considering the application of care ethics to
                    environmental issues, where caring for the planet inquires for a collective
                    action and a redistribution of environmental labour.</p>
                <p>To expect or defer ecological care, labour, or responsibility to institutions,
                    universities, governments or funding bodies is to risk perpetual inaction.
                    Environmental accountability is not a duty to be outsourced — it is an ethical
                    imperative that must be embraced collectively and immediately by DH. By turning
                    to an ethics of ecological care, DH with its assemblage of tools and
                    methodologies, can reveal the intricate connections within ecosystems that
                    traditional approaches may miss. Below we attempt to centre on whether the
                    concept of <hi rend="italic">ethics of ecological care</hi> can truly provide a
                    DH ecological rewire and a defensible pedagogical purpose. Following from the
                    challenges faced in the discipline, we are called to dynamically uncover the
                    environmental links to the ever-changing nature of DH, where those changes are
                    visible, and the ways in which they influence its development. Through this we
                    attempt to connect the disconnections between the versions of DH as a means of
                    linking the scholarly community and exploring what lies ahead in a world that
                    urgently demands environmental action. DH moves fast and while the expansion of
                    the digital today has brought significant changes, including its focus on the
                    socio-political aspects of technologies and research on global digital cultures
                    and different digital mediums, we must ask: What is our positionality regarding
                    the role of DH during the environmental crisis?</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Rewiring Digital Humanities Methodologies through Ecological Care</head>
                <p>A recognition of the diverse links and environmental impacts of DH could be the
                    origin of generating an <hi rend="italic">ethics of ecological care</hi> for the
                    field, beyond awareness. To unpack those links and identify the responsibilities
                    we have as a discipline is a complex but manageable rewiring of our rhythms,
                    priorities, and practices. This unpacking asks for a fostering of inclusive
                    innovation in the development of DH, holding powerful entities and collaborators
                    accountable for their actions, and engaging in critical conversations that
                    acknowledge the diverse needs and experiences of individuals and communities. As
                        <ptr target="#stephens_2024" loc="3"/> puts it, most higher education
                    institutions prioritise and invest in technological innovation and technical
                    fixes instead of supporting and encouraging research and teaching on systemic
                    social change. In this techno-solutionist managerial institutional framework, DH
                    did not remain immune. For DH to reflect critically on how the field may be
                    complicit in perpetuating techno-optimism, one of the best places to start is to
                    resist the Silicon Valley type rhetoric of innovation and disruption we have
                    embraced in the last decade <ptr target="#hannah_2023"/>. In fact, the
                    fetishisation of the <q>free information-access</q> promise of the early
                    internet days seems to have canonised data exploitation by internet giants and
                    has diminished humanists’ expectations of bilateral benefits. Many features of
                    the modern Digital Humanities field have been consumed by this large-scale
                    digitalisation and almost global internet connection that have amplified our
                    access to content, data, and resources to conduct innovative research, which in
                    turn have broadened DH methods to study them <ptr target="#viola_2023"/>. </p>
                <p>The environmental impact of innovation on climate change is, however, not
                    distributed equally; to the contrary, those who least contribute to it, suffer
                    the most <ptr target="#baldwin_2020"/>, and adaptation strategies employed by
                    one group can inadvertently aggravate problems for another. This phenomenon,
                    known as maladaptation, highlights the unequal burden borne by developing
                    nations in the Global South, which face the brunt of climate change despite
                    contributing the least to historical greenhouse gas emissions <ptr
                        target="#young_2021"/>. This lack of parity extends to the realm of
                    technology. Information and Communication Technology (ICT), a fundamental pillar
                    of DH practices, has a significant ecological footprint, and a substantial
                    portion of the energy powering ICT infrastructure currently comes from fossil
                    fuels <ptr target="#freitag_2021"/>, contributing an estimated 2-2.5% of all
                    greenhouse gas emissions globally. When terms such as ‘innovation,’
                    ‘transformation,’ and ‘digitalisation’ dominate the talk of our evolving
                    discipline, the underlying political contexts, everyday realities, and material
                    cultures dissipate <ptr target="#wiens_2020"/>.</p>
                <p>The growing dependence on technology companies and social media platforms for
                    data collection, analysis, and the management of datasets or machine learning
                    applications in DH has raised concerns about a gradual erosion of responsibility
                    within the field. This trend is particularly disconcerting given that numerous
                    technology firms are known to financially support lobbyists and politicians who
                    challenge climate change initiatives, as evidenced by <ptr
                        target="#shefner_2024"/>. In parallel, social media outlets and current
                    advances in generative AI are frequently implicated in the spread of
                    climate-related misinformation <ptr target="#galaz_2023"/>. By increasingly
                    prioritising short-term benefits through alliances with these external actors,
                    DH risks deviating from its long-standing commitment to advancing human welfare,
                    preserving cultural heritage, and disseminating knowledge to diverse audiences.
                    Furthermore, the recent surge in public mistrust toward both technological
                    innovators and public institutions, exacerbated by the concentration of power
                    among a select few, could have a direct and adverse impact on fields such as DH
                        <ptr target="#boyd-davis_2021"/>. In effect, defining academic achievement
                    predominantly through economic partnerships with stakeholders whose ethical
                    standings are questionable may not only dilute the core mission of the
                    discipline but also contribute to its fragmentation and the erosion of trust
                    within the broader academic community.</p>
                <p>We propose that an ecocritical DH champions <quote rend="inline">slow
                        scholarship</quote>
                    <ptr target="#mason_2021"/>, entailing a more deliberate and care-full research,
                    careful planning, resource optimisation, and long-term impact. By slowing down
                    and prioritising long-term planetary health, DH can produce more durable and
                    impactful solutions to complex research problems and a more nuanced
                    understanding of the environmental implications of DH. This would also mean
                    resisting patriarchal and colonial structures of our institutions and actively
                    seeking to address systemic marginalisation <ptr target="#stephens_2024"/>.
                    Indeed, as mentioned earlier, when we look at the intersection of Environmental
                    Humanities and Digital Humanities (i.e. DEH), we find many guiding examples that
                    show how DH can be deployed to underpin environment related research that has
                    the capacity to advance the knowledge on environmental degradation. For example,
                        <ptr target="#ryan_2023"/> show that by embracing diverse theories and
                    practices, DEH can bring decolonial, arts-based, and practice-led models into
                    dialogue with qualitative and quantitative paths. Such practices align with the
                    ethics of care’s emphasis on building relationships, fostering empathy, and
                    ensuring the well-being of others. By prioritising an <hi rend="italic">ethics
                        of ecological care</hi>, we demonstrate respect for the lived experiences
                    and expertise of the communities we work for and with, forging partnerships with
                    environmental justice organisations, NGOs, and community groups.</p>
                <p>This strategy leverages existing knowledge and networks within these communities,
                    creating a more efficient and effective course of action for DH. However, the
                    benefits extend beyond efficiency, to foster a sense of shared responsibility
                    and empower communities to be active participants in finding solutions that
                    address their concerns as active research participants, from designing the
                    research, interfaces, and ensuring a fair distribution of research benefits. A
                    DH ethics of environmental care underscores responsiveness to the needs of
                    others, which in this context translates to ensuring research and data
                    collection prioritise the well-being of these communities. Ultimately, a
                    successful strategy to a rewired DH that cares about the environmental crisis
                    must ensure that the development process reflects the perspectives and needs of
                    marginalised communities. For instance, by prioritising data justice, we can
                    strive to ensure that data collection and analysis are conducted ethically and
                    with respect for community privacy and ownership <ptr target="#dencik_2019"/>.
                    Our growing data collection, analysis, and management methodologies and the turn
                    to building infrastructure for conducting research should hence incorporate the
                    analysis of structural inequalities, to reflect on how different groups and
                    communities experience technological processes such as datafication, unevenly.
                    An <hi rend="italic">ethics of ecological care</hi> encourages us to consider
                    diverse sources of knowledge beyond traditional academic research such as the
                    inclusion of Indigenous knowledge systems <ptr target="#whyte_2016"/> and other
                    ways of knowing that may be crucial in addressing environmental challenges.</p>
                <p>This infrastructural turn in DH has generated a substantial body of critical
                    scholarship addressing the environmental impact of digital technologies. In
                    particular, the emergent field of critical data centre studies <ptr
                        target="#edwards_2024"/> examines the continually expanding digital
                    infrastructure by analysing the contemporary social, cultural, political, and
                    environmental contexts of the data centre sector. As integral components of
                    multinational digital capitalism, data centres occupy a nexus at the
                    intersection of energy systems, local economies, and environmental politics <ptr
                        target="#brodie_2023"/>; their expansion relies on energy resources and
                    intersects with extractive industries, and carries profound planetary
                    implications, frequently undermining local livelihoods <ptr
                        target="#lehuede_2024"/>. In extension, the production of digital
                    technologies used, developed, and promoted for or within DH depends on the
                    extraction and processing of rare earth minerals that are crucial for many
                    hardware components <ptr target="#cubitt_2016"/>, a process that often imposes
                    considerable ecological costs. <ptr target="#parikka_2013"/> observes that
                    modern electronics operate as miniature mines for minerals and metals, while
                        <ptr target="#gabrys_2011"/> posits that these materials circulate within
                    complex economic, cultural, and political networks. The practices of mining and
                    earth extraction engender significant ecological harm through the generation of
                    hazardous waste, deforestation, and unsafe labour conditions (see, e.g., <ptr
                        target="#taffel_2015"/>). For <ptr target="#yusoff_2019"/>, such extraction
                    practices must be examined within the broader historical and ongoing contexts of
                    colonialism and violence against both people and the more-than-human world.
                    Consequently, an anti-colonial framework in this context demands not only the
                    integration of indigenous knowledge but also a critical awareness of the mineral
                    resources and mining practices that underpin technological production, the
                    labour involved in constructing these tools, and the energy resources that power
                    them. Through an <hi rend="italic">ethics of ecological care</hi> developed for
                    DH, researchers can acknowledge this uneven global distribution of environmental
                    burdens associated with technology.</p>
                <p>A comprehensive rewiring is feasible only if collaborations between academic and
                    non-academic partners are rigorously and ethically evaluated to preclude
                    extractivist practices and, where feasible, incorporate research partners and
                    participants in formulating research questions, refining methodologies, and
                    ensuring equitable benefits from the outcomes. Concurrently, a heightened
                    environmental consciousness necessitates a critical interrogation of local,
                    national, and global governance structures that have historically perpetuated
                    environmental injustices. Embedding an <hi rend="italic">ethics of ecological
                        care</hi> within the discipline entails acknowledging the uneven historical
                    trajectories that distinguish various digital humanities traditions and seeking
                    avenues for interdisciplinary integration that transcend existing divides. This
                    approach calls for reconfiguring collaborative practices and responses to the
                    ecological crisis in ways that are ethically sound and inclusive, thereby
                    fostering a research environment that aligns with both sustainable principles
                    and environmental justice imperatives.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Rewiring Digital Humanities Education</head>
                <p>It may be deemed both naïve and cynically unrealistic to push for an ethical
                    rewiring of Digital Humanities, a field that is already overextended,
                    structurally fragile, and deeply enmeshed in culturally specific contingencies.
                    Although the immediate benefits of such a reorientation remain ambiguous, this
                    shift holds the potential to enrich the fundamental objective of Digital
                    Humanities, namely, the synthesis of scientific methodologies with the
                    reflective traditions of the humanities education. We draw inspiration and frame
                    this final part of the discussion within Paulo Freire's work on ecological
                    awareness and critical pedagogy to champion an expansion of Digital Humanities
                    towards a system that integrates environmental care and ecocritical futures.
                    Freire’s work champions a form of education that transcends the purely
                    theoretical, aiming to construct frameworks that empower global communities,
                    foster mutual respect, cultivate social responsibility, and celebrate diversity
                        <ptr target="#freire_1979"/>. By mirroring this emphasis on justice within
                    its own principles, DH can evolve into a powerful entity for environmental
                    education and advocacy. In the same vein that Freire argues for the critical
                    inclusion of ecological concerns within any ‘radical, critical, and liberating’
                    educational practice <ptr target="#freire_1993"/>, DH may encourage researchers
                    to revisit foundational concerns of the humanities and engage with concerns
                    revolving around the constitution of the human as both a subject and object of
                    study, particularly in relation to non-human elements, such as generative AI.
                    Expanding on this encourages us to envision a future for DH that prioritises a
                    humane and eco-careful future that integrates environmental justice and
                    ecological concerns within the core educational mission of DH.</p>
                <p>Recent expansions in DH have signified a paradigmatic shift toward a more
                    globalised and critically engaged field. As discussed earlier, contemporary
                    developments are marked by an increased focus on global digital cultures, which
                    include robust discussions of decolonial and anti-colonial approaches, Black
                    digital archives and experiences, and analyses of the socio-political
                    implications of technology <ptr target="#banda_2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#gomez_2020"/>. This transformation reflects a fundamental
                    reconfiguration of the digital domain, from functioning merely as a publishing
                    platform to evolving into a dynamic arena for conversation, collaboration, and
                    multidimensional engagement. In doing so, DH has embraced a core humanities
                    tenet that regards texts as multifaceted entities incorporating diverse media
                    forms <ptr target="#lanham_2000"/>. This expanded scope stands to benefit
                    significantly from the integration of innovative educational frameworks,
                    including radical pedagogies, critical data studies, decolonial methodologies,
                    and ecocritical perspectives. Through such interdisciplinary and critically
                    engaged approaches, DH can contribute to the cultivation of educational futures
                    that are both socially equitable and environmentally sustainable.</p>
                <p>Some current examples, which demonstrate practical implementations and real-world
                    applications of principles such as sustainability, decolonialism, and
                    responsibility in addressing environmental and societal challenges, can serve as
                    valuable guides in shaping an <hi rend="italic">ethics of ecological care</hi>
                    that integrates diverse, contemporary experiences into an ethical framework.
                        <ptr target="#lyons_2022"/> offer an interesting case of a pedagogical
                    method used at the University of Pennsylvania where students were asked to use
                    digital storytelling to defend environmental justice. By connecting their
                    students with Colombian activists working against deforestation, air pollution,
                    and river pollution, and by using participatory action research methods, they
                    created a digital storytelling platform. This platform provided a visual
                    representation of the socio-environmental conflicts in Colombia, as well as
                    providing historical context and reporting on the organisations and their
                    activities in support of environmental justice. Throughout this project, Lyons
                    and Howarth also worked to de-centre English as the default language for both
                    digital humanities and environmental humanities in order to open up
                    opportunities for collaboration with diverse groups, such as Colombian
                    environmental activists in their case, and to open up new avenues for reaching a
                    wider audience. Another example comes from King's College London <ptr
                        target="#gray_2022"/>, where scholars Gray and Bounegru used their flipped
                    classroom technique to explore how hashtags and images were involved in the
                    contentious issue of Amazonian Forest fires. As a result, in collaboration with
                    the European Forest Institute, they created a 'cross-platform image dataset’
                    using qualitative analysis. </p>
                <p>Similarly, <ptr target="#ruiz_2017"/> offer a compelling example of how DH can be
                    used to decentre whiteness within dominant environmental narratives. Their
                    project, established at the California State University Digital Environmental
                    Humanities Lab, involved collaboration with Chicana/o first-generation
                    undergraduate students lacking prior formal research experience. Through
                    archival research using digital tools, these students critically examined the
                    centrality and dominance of whiteness in mainstream environmentalism discourses.
                    They identified and questioned the absence of records documenting the historical
                    contributions of Latinx, Indigenous American, and Black communities to
                    environmental movements <ptr target="#ruiz_2017"/>. In essence, the students
                    challenged the long-held narrative, perpetuated by predominantly white
                    middle-class male conservationists, that nature exists to be tamed and conquered
                    and instead, foregrounded alternative environmental histories and discourses.
                    These alternative narratives focused on working-class environmentalism <ptr
                        target="#bell_2020"/>, acknowledged the historical contributions of people
                    of colour to environmental movements in the United States, and addressed the
                    impact of slavery, colonialism, and imperialism on land dispossession and the
                    erasure of Indigenous knowledge concerning the environment. This project
                    exemplifies a productive and positive radicalisation of DH tool development and
                    use towards an ethics of environmental care that foregrounds the experiences of
                    marginalised communities and encourages a focus on the stories and perspectives
                    often neglected by dominant narratives. This collaborative course allowed
                    students to weigh in their own identities to inform the research process and
                    challenge dominant narratives within environmental discourse through the use of
                    DH tools.</p>
                <p>Evidently, the cornerstone of a successful education in the face of ecocriticism
                    lies in the creation of common, sustainable, intentional, and collective
                    pedagogical tools. These tools, as Crane argued in 1998, must be based on <quote
                        rend="inline">new experimentation as we explore and seek to understand a
                        radically new space</quote> for DH <ptr target="#crane_1998" loc="15"/>.
                    While Crane’s argument was made for digital libraries, the recent proliferation
                    of DH studies on fields such as digital infrastructures, platforms, and
                    cryptocurrencies reminds us of the same critical importance of these innovations
                    and the new connotations of the question related to the political dimensions of
                    these allegedly merely technical developments. Who owns, who controls, and who
                    benefits from these technologies? How sustainable are they? And do they
                    undermine current education structures? Often led by large conglomerates, these
                    innovations shape the performance of the economy, politics, regulations, and
                    society while they are also impacting our comprehension of key concepts such as
                    national borders, governments, and citizenship. </p>
                <p>An <hi rend="italic">ethics of ecological care</hi> can contribute to
                    environmental and planetary health in a meaningful way, instead of perpetuating
                    old environmental discourses that may propagate the same old power structures.
                    Embedding an ethics of environmental care in DH pedagogy can rewire an
                    environmentally conscious future that builds an open, trustworthy space through
                    which scholars and students are empowered. For this, we must support a care
                    strategy that enhances our values, our social benefit resonance, literacy, and
                    techno-cultural coherence. To do that we must champion a rewiring that can aid
                    us in creating an archetype that counters traditional and colonial hierarchical
                    notions of education and deploy ecocritical educational principles from the
                    outset, to guarantee that DH will be beneficial to all, encompassing planetary
                    health. This paper argues for a repositioning of the discipline towards a more
                    care-full DH, relying on shared understanding and development. Traditionally, DH
                    pedagogy has been conceptualised and developed in an isolated manner,
                    overlooking the interconnectedness of resources, networks, and infrastructure
                    that underpin our research and teaching. By viewing DH pedagogies and
                    methodologies as complex ecologies, we can cultivate a more environmentally
                    aware appeal to our professional endeavours. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>While the openness and flexibility of DH offer immense potential for tackling
                    contemporary challenges, the environmental impact of the field’s practices has
                    spurred a critical re-evaluation that has positioned it at a crossroads. This
                    paper argues that DH must embark on a transformative journey, embracing
                    environmental responsibility and actively contributing to the pursuit of an
                    ethics of environmental care. Neutrality and silence on the issue of climate
                    change is unacceptable at this stage; it is the responsibility of the field to
                    consider how they are contributing to the climate crisis and what they can do to
                    mitigate it. We depart from conventional approaches to Digital Humanities that
                    prioritise either top-down, institutionally driven solutions or bottom-up,
                    grassroots initiatives. We argue for a more nuanced exploration of the
                    interstitial space between these two extremes that fosters interconnected
                    opportunities that leverage the creative potential of both top-down and
                    bottom-up forces, thereby rewiring the possibilities of Digital Humanities. Our
                    primary focus is on the institutional transformation that arises from the
                    confluence of these two strategies since we believe it is within this nexus that
                    some of the most impactful ecological changes can and are unfolding. In this
                    context, we pose two critical questions: 1) What is the most effective
                    ecological strategy for a future Digital Humanities? 2) Should we endeavour to
                    reform existing institutional structures, establish idealised archetypes that
                    exist outside of these structures, or directly challenge these structures
                    altogether?</p>
                <p>In addition to the promises and problems associated with the growing Digital
                    Humanities, the focus on the debates around the definition of the discipline
                    draws attention away from pressing issues facing humanity and the planet. This
                    change necessarily implores transparency about the processes that constitute the
                    field. Our work should and often contains the dialogic history of its making,
                    and the experience of its research and teaching community to let it show how DH
                    professionals grow, change and stumble through their expertise and encounter
                    with other fields. We argue that the crucial caveat of what is being broadened
                    should also be predominantly grounded in the ethics of environmental care, which
                    has not been part of DH research as of yet. DH research should take seriously
                    the fact that inquiry not only happens inside universities but also outside it
                    and that we cannot remain neutral in the face of the climate crisis. We should
                    take seriously the ways in which our methodologies and pedagogies are shifting,
                    the materiality of the digital, the dynamics and politics of digital
                    technologies and finding ways to account for them, situated in the context in
                    which digital technologies are used and in which they matter
                    environmentally.</p>
                <p>This paper posits that an epistemic rewiring towards an environmentally conscious
                    Digital Humanities, characterised by critical self-reflection and theoretical
                    underpinnings, holds the potential not only to reconfigure the landscape of DH,
                    but also to catalyse ground-breaking and socially impactful methodologies and
                    pedagogy. By integrating <hi rend="italic">ethics of ecological care</hi> into
                    the fabric of DH’s core, scholars can embark on a transformative journey,
                    interrogating the anthropocentric tendencies inherent in existing practices and
                    fostering a more holistic understanding of human-environment interactions within
                    the digital realm. This paradigm shift necessitates a deliberate engagement with
                    theoretical frameworks from environmental humanities, ecocriticism, and
                    sustainability studies, enabling the development of innovative research agendas
                    that address pressing societal concerns amidst the backdrop of climate change.
                    An environmentally care-full Digital Humanities has the potential to transcend
                    disciplinary boundaries, fostering collaborative endeavours with diverse experts
                    and generating research outcomes that can contribute meaningfully to broader
                    conversations.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="baldwin_2020" label="Baldwin and Erickson 2020">Baldwin, A., and
                    Erickson, B. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Whiteness, coloniality,
                        and the Anthropocene</title>, <title rend="italic">Environment and Planning
                        D: Society and Space</title>, 38(1), pp. 3-11. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0263775820904485"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/0263775820904485</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="banda_2015" label="Banda 2015">Banda, F. (2015) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Decolonizing digital humanities</title>, in M. K. Gold and L. Schreibman
                    (Eds.), <title rend="italic">A companion to digital literary studies</title>.
                    Blackwell Publishing Ltd., pp 272-284</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bell_2014" label="Bell 2014" sortKey="Bella">Bell, K. (2014) <title
                        rend="quotes">The causes of environmental injustice,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Achieving environmental justice: A cross-national analysis
                        (Bristol, online edition)</title>. Policy Press Scholarship Online.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bell_2020" label="Bell 2020" sortKey="Bellb">Bell, K. (2020) <title
                        rend="italic">Working-class environmentalism: An agenda for a just and fair
                        transition to sustainability</title>. Springer International Publishing
                    AG.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bennett_2020" label="Bennett et al. 2020">Bennett, C. L. et al. (2020,
                    April) <title rend="quotes">The care work of access</title>, in <title
                        rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in
                        Computing Systems</title>, pp. 1-15.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berry_2012" label="Berry 2012">Berry, D. M. (2012) <title
                        rend="quotes">Introduction: Understanding the digital humanities</title>, in
                        <title rend="italic"> Understanding digital humanities</title>. London:
                    Palgrave Macmillan UK, (pp. 1-20).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="borgman_2010" label="Borgman 2010">Borgman, C. L. (2010) <title
                        rend="quotes">The digital future is now: A call to action for the
                        humanities</title>, <title rend="italic"> Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</title>, 3(4).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boyd-davis_2021" label="Boyd Davis et al. 2021">Boyd Davis, S. et al.
                    (2021) <title rend="quotes">Can I believe what I see? Data visualization and
                        trust in the humanities</title>,  <title rend="italic"> Interdisciplinary
                        Science Reviews</title>, 46(4), pp. 522-546.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brodie_2023" label="Brodie 2023">Brodie, P. (2023) <title
                        rend="quotes">Data infrastructure studies on an unequal
                        planet</title>, <title rend="italic"> Big Data and Society</title>, 10(1).
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/20539517231182402"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/20539517231182402</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cohen_2016" label="Cohen and LeMenager 2016">Cohen, J.J. and
                    LeMenager, S., (2016) <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Assembling the
                        ecological digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">
                    PMLA</title>, 131(2), pp. 340-346.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="crane_1998" label="Crane_1998">PLACEHOLDER</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cubitt_2016" label="Cubitt 2016" sortKey="Cubitta">Cubitt, S.
                        (2016) <title rend="italic"> Finite media: Environmental implications of
                        digital technologies</title>. Duke University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cubitt_2019" label="Cubitt 2019" sortKey="Cubittb">Cubitt, S. (2019)
                        <title rend="quotes">Ecocritique.</title> Media+Environment, 1(1). <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1525/001c.10784"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1525/001c.10784</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="deegan_2014" label="Deegan 2014">Deegan, M. (2014). <title
                        rend="quotes">‘This ever more amorphous thing called Digital Humanities’:
                        Whither the humanities project?</title>
                    <title rend="italic"> Arts and Humanities in Higher Education</title>, 13(1-2),
                    pp. 24-41. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1474022213513180"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/14740222135131</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dencik_2019" label="Dencik et al. 2019">Dencik, L. et al. (2019)
                        <title rend="quotes">Exploring data justice: Conceptions, applications and
                        directions</title>,  <title rend="italic"> Information, Communication and
                        Society</title>, 22(7), pp. 873-881. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1080/1369118X.2019.1606268"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1080/1369118X.2019.1606268</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker_2021" label="Drucker 2021">Drucker, J. (2021) <title
                        rend="quotes">Sustainability and complexity: Knowledge and authority in the
                        digital humanities</title>,  <title rend="italic"> Digital Scholarship in
                        the Humanities</title>, 36(Supplement_2), pp. ii86-ii94. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqab025"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqab025</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="edmond_2021" label="Edmond and Lehmann 2021">Edmond, J., and Lehmann,
                    J. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Digital humanities, knowledge complexity, and the
                        five ‘aporias’ of digital research.</title>  <title rend="italic"> Digital
                        Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 36(Supplement_2), pp. ii95-ii108.
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqab031"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqab031</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="edwards_2024" label="Edwards et al. 2024">Edwards, D. et al. (2024)
                        <title rend="quotes">The making of critical data center studies</title>,
                        <title rend="italic"> Convergence</title>, [Online first]. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1177/13548565231224157"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/13548565231224157</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="finneman_2014" label="Finnemann 2014">Finnemann, N. O. (2014) <title
                        rend="quotes">Digital humanities and networked digital media</title>, <title
                        rend="italic"> MedieKultur: Journal of media and communication
                        research</title>, 30(57), pp. 94-114. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.7146/mediekultur.v30i57.15592"
                        >https://doi.org/10.7146/mediekultur.v30i57.15592 </ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fletcher_2024" label="Fletcher et al. 2024">Fletcher, C. et al. (2024)
                        <title rend="quotes">Earth at risk: An urgent call to end the age of
                        destruction and forge a just and sustainable future</title>,  <title
                        rend="italic"> PNAS nexus</title>, 3(4), pp.106. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1093/pnasnexus/pgae106"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/pnasnexus/</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="folbre_1995" label="Folbre_1995">PLACEHOLDER</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="freire_1979" label="Freire 1970" sortKey="Freirea">Freire, P. (1970)
                        <title rend="italic"> Pedagogy of the Oppressed</title>. Seabury
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="freire_1993" label="Freire 1993" sortKey="Freireb">Freire, P. (1993)
                        <title rend="italic"> Pedagogy of Hope: Reliving Pedagogy of the
                        Oppressed</title>. Continuum.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="freitag_2021" label="Freitag 2021">Freitag, C. et al. (2021) <title
                        rend="quotes">The real climate and transformative impact of ICT: A critique
                        of estimates, trends, and regulations</title>,  <title rend="italic">
                        Patterns</title>, 2(9). <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.patter.2021.100340"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1016/j.patter.2021.100340</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fuller_2019" label="Fuller and Goriunova 2019">Fuller, M., and
                    Goriunova, O. (2019) <title rend="italic"> Bleak joys: Aesthetics of ecology and
                        impossibility</title>. Minnesota: University of Minnesota Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gabrys_2011" label="Gabrys 2011">Gabrys, J. (2011) Digital rubbish: A
                    natural history of electronics. University of Michigan Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galaz_2023" label="Galaz et al. 2023">Galaz, V. et al. (2023) <title
                        rend="quotes">AI could create a perfect storm of climate
                        misinformation</title>,  <title rend="italic"> arXiv</title> [preprint].
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2306.12807"
                        >https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2306.12807</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gajjala_2019" label="Gajjala 2019">Gajjala, R. (2019) <title
                        rend="quotes">Caring archives of subalternity</title>, in M. K. Gold and L.
                    F. Klein’s (Eds.), <title rend="italic"> Debates in the digital humanities
                        2019</title>. University of Minnesota Press, pp. 431-433.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gilligan_1982" label="Gilligan 1982">Gilligan, C. (1982) <title
                        rend="italic"> In a different voice</title>. Cambridge, MA: Harvard
                    University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gomez_2020" label="Gomez 2020">Gomez, C. (2020) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Toward a Black digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic"> Journal of
                        Librarianship and Scholarly Communication</title>, 8(2), eP2682. [DOI:
                    10.7710/jlsc.2682]</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gould_2021" label="Gould 2021">Gould, A. (2021) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Kitting the Digital Humanities for the Anthropocene: Digital metabolism and
                        Ecocritical DH</title>, in C. Miya, O. Rossier, O. and G. Rockwell’s (eds.),
                        <title rend="italic"> Right research: Modelling sustainable research
                        practices in the Anthropocene.</title> Cambridge, UK: Open Book
                    Publishers.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gray_2022" label="Gray et al. 2022">Gray, J. et al. (2022) <title
                        rend="quotes">Engaged research-led teaching: Composing collective inquiry
                        with digital methods and data</title>,  <title rend="italic"> Digital
                        Culture and Education</title>, 14(3), pp.55-86.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hannah_2023" label="Hannah 2023">Hannah, M. (2023) <title
                        rend="quotes">Toward a political economy of Digital Humanities</title>, in
                    M. K. Gold and L. F. Klein’s (Eds.) <title rend="italic"> Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities 2023</title>. University of Minnesota Press, p. 3-26.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="irwin_2013" label="Irwin 2013">Irwin, R. (2013). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Ecological ethics in the context of climate change: Feminist and indigenous
                        critique of modernity</title>,  <title rend="italic"> International Social
                        Science Journal</title>, 64(211-212), pp. 111-123. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1111/issj.12056"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1111/issj.12056</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="klein_2015" label="Klein et al. 2015">Klein, L. F. et al. (2015)
                        <title rend="quotes">Exploratory thematic analysis for digitized archival
                        collections</title>
                    <title rend="italic"> Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>,
                    30(suppl_1), pp. i130-i141. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqv052"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqv052</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lanham_2000" label="Lanham 2000">Lanham, R. A. (2000) <title
                        rend="italic"> The electronic word: Democracy, technology, and the future of
                        the book. University of Chicago Press</title>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lehuede_2024" label="Lehuedé 2024" sortKey="Lehuede">Lehuedé, S.
                    (2024) <title rend="quotes">An elemental ethics for artificial intelligence:
                        Water as Resistance within ai’s value chain</title>, <title rend="italic">
                        AI and Society: Journal of Knowledge, Culture and Communication</title>,
                        <ref target="https://ssrn.com/abstract=4756794"
                        >https://ssrn.com/abstract=4756794</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liboiron_2021" label="Liboiron_2021">Liboiron, M. (2021) <title
                        rend="italic"> Pollution is colonialism</title>. Duke University
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu_2013" label="Liu 2013">Liu, A. (2013) <title rend="quotes">The
                        meaning of the digital humanities</title>, PMLA, 128(2), pp.409-423.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lyons_2022" label="Lyons and Howarth 2022">Lyons, K. and Howarth, M.,
                    (2022) <title rend="quotes">The importance of hemispheric perspectives for the
                        environmental humanities: Reflections on bilingual digital environmental
                        justice storytelling</title>,  <title rend="italic"> Tapuya: Latin American
                        Science, Technology and Society</title>, 5(1), <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1080/25729861.2022.2098685"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1080/25729861.2022.2098685</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mason_2021" label="Mason 2021">Mason, W. (2021) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Radically slow? Reflections on time, temporality, and pace in engaged
                        scholarship</title>, in B. C. Clift, J. Gore, S. Gustafsson, S. Bekker, I.
                    C. Batlle, and J. Hatchard’s (Eds.) <title rend="italic"> Temporality in
                        qualitative inquiry</title>. Routledge, pp. 142-157.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="macgregor_2010" label="MacGregor_2010" sortKey="Macgregor">MacGregor,
                    S. (2010) <title rend="quotes">Earthcare or feminist ecological
                        citizenship?</title>  <title rend="italic"> FEMINA POLITICA–Zeitschrift Für
                        Feministische Politikwissenschaft</title>, 20(1), pp. 22-31.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="merchant_1981" label="Merchant 1981" sortKey="Merchanta">Merchant, C.
                    (1981) <title rend="quotes">Earthcare: Women and the environment</title>,
                         <title rend="italic"> Environment: Science and Policy for Sustainable
                        Development</title>, 23(5), pp. 6-40.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="merchant_1995" label="Merchant 1995" sortKey="Merchantb">Merchant, C.
                    (1995) PLACEHOLDER</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="noddings_1984" label="Noddings 1984">Noddings, N. (1984) <title
                        rend="italic"> Caring</title>, Berkeley, CA: University of
                    California.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nowviskie_2015" label="Nowviskie 2015">Nowviskie, B. (2015), <title
                        rend="quotes">Digital Humanities in the Anthropocene</title>
                    <title rend="italic"> Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>,
                    30(suppl_1), pp. i4–i15, <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqv015"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqv015</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="odonnell_2016" label="O'Donnell et al. 2016" sortKey="Odonnell"
                    >O'Donnell, D. P. et al. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Boundary land: Diversity as
                        a defining feature of the digital humanities</title>
                    <title rend="italic"> Digital Humanities 2016</title>: Conference at
                    Jagiellonian University and Pedagogical University, Kraków, pp. 76-82. <ref
                        target="https://n2t.net/ark:/13683/pdea/G5m"
                        >https://n2t.net/ark:/13683/pdea/G5m</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="parikka_2013" label="Parikka 2013">Parikka, J. (2013) <title
                        rend="quotes">The geology of media</title>, <title rend="italic"> The
                        Atlantic</title>. Available online: <ref
                        target="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2013/10/the-geology-of-media/280523/"
                        >https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2013/10/the-geology-of-media/280523/</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="posthumus_2014" label="Posthumus and Sinclair 2014">Posthumus, S., and
                    Sinclair, S. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Reading environment(s): Digital
                        humanities meets ecocriticism</title>, <title rend="italic"> Green
                        Letter</title>s, 18(3), pp. 254 - 273. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1080/14688417.2014.966737"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1080/14688417.2014.966737</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="risam_2018" label="Risam 2018" sortKey="Risama">Risam, R.
                        (2018) <title rend="italic"> New digital worlds: Postcolonial digital
                        humanities in theory, praxis, and pedagogy</title>. Northwestern University
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="risam_2019" label="Risam and Gairola 2019" sortKey="Risamb">Risam, R.,
                    and Gairola, R. K. (2019) <title rend="quotes">South Asian digital humanities
                        then and now</title>,  <title rend="italic"> South Asian
                    Review</title>, 40(3), pp. 141-154. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1080/02759527.2019.1599548"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1080/02759527.2019.1599548</ref>
                </bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="ruddick_1980" label="Ruddick 1980" sortKey="Ruddicka">Ruddick, S.
                    (1980) <title rend="quotes">Maternal thinking</title>, <title rend="italic">
                        Feminist Studies</title>, 6(2), pp. 342–367. <ref
                        target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/3177749"
                        >https://www.jstor.org/stable/3177749</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ruddick_1989" label="Ruddick 1989" sortKey="Ruddickb">Ruddick, S.
                    (1989) <title rend="italic"> Maternal thinking</title>, Boston, MA: Beacon
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ruiz_2017" label="Ruiz et al. 2017">Ruiz, J. M. et al. (2017) <title
                        rend="quotes">Radicalizing the digital humanities: Reimagining environmental
                        justice research and teaching</title>, <title rend="italic"> Journal for
                        Computing in the Humanities</title>, 53(2), pp. 227-248. <ref
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.5195/RT.2017.395"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5195/RT.2017.395</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ryan_2023" label="Ryan et al. 2023">Ryan, J. et al. (2023) <title
                        rend="quotes">The digital environmental humanities (DEH) in the
                        Anthropocene: Challenges and opportunities in an era of ecological
                        precarity</title>, <title rend="italic"> Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</title>, 17(3).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sanz_2013" label="Sanz 2013">Sanz, A. (2013) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Digital Humanities or hypercolonial studies?</title>, <title rend="italic">
                        Responsible Innovation</title>, 21. Available at <ref
                        target="https://docta.ucm.es/rest/api/core/bitstreams/028d8cf0-af59-434d-8e09-ed5a0a815804/content"
                        >https://docta.ucm.es/rest/api/core/bitstreams/028d8cf0-af59-434d-8e09-ed5a0a815804/content</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shah_2020" label="Shah 2020">Shah, N. (2020) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Digital humanities on the ground: Post-access politics and the second wave
                        of digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic"> South Asian Digital
                        Humanities</title>, 40(3), pp. 155-173. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1080/02759527.2019.1599551"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1080/02759527.2019.1599551</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shefner_2024" label="Shefner and Lamphere 2024">Shefner, J., and
                    Lamphere, J. A. (2024) <title rend="quotes">US climate politics: Strategic
                        Conditions and interactions among actors and structures</title>,  <title
                        rend="italic"> Humanity and Society</title>, 48(1), pp. 25-50. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1177/01605976231201645"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/0160597623120164</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="smithies_2017" label="Smithies 2017">Smithies, J. (2017) <title
                        rend="italic"> The digital humanities and the digital modern</title>.
                    Springer.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stephens_2024" label="Stephens 2024">Stephens, J.C. (2024) <title
                        rend="italic"> Climate justice and the university: Shaping a hopeful future
                        for al</title>l. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press.<ref
                        target="https://muse.jhu.edu/book/123270"
                        >https://muse.jhu.edu/book/123270</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="steiner_2017" label="Steiner 2017">Steiner, D. D. (2017) <title
                        rend="quotes">Organizational justice for understanding employee health and
                        well-being</title>, in C.Moliner, R. Cropanzano, and V. Martínez-Tur’s
                    (Eds.) <title rend="italic"> Organizational justice: International perspectives
                        and conceptual advances</title>. Routledge, pp. 160-180.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="svensson_2016" label="Svensson 2016">Svensson, P. (2016) <title
                        rend="italic"> Big digital humanities: imagining a meeting place for the
                        humanities and the digital</title>. University of Michigan Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taffel_2015" label="Taffel 2015">Taffel, S., (2015) <title
                        rend="quotes">Towards an ethical electronics? Ecologies of Congolese
                        conflict minerals</title>, <title rend="italic"> Westminster Papers in
                        Communication and Culture</title>, 10(1), pp.18-33. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.16997/wpcc.210"
                        >https://doi.org/10.16997/wpcc.210</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thaller_2012" label="Thaller 2012">Thaller, M. (2012) <title
                        rend="quotes">Controversies around the digital humanities: An
                    agenda</title>, <title rend="italic"> Historical Social Research/Historische
                        Sozialforschung</title>, 37(3), pp. 7-23. <ref
                        target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/41636594"
                        >https://www.jstor.org/stable/41636594</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="throsby_2016" label="Throsby and Petetskaya 2016">Throsby, D. and
                    Petetskaya, E. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Sustainability concepts in indigenous
                        and non-indigenous cultures</title>, <title rend="italic"> International
                        Journal of Cultural Property</title>, 23(2), pp.119-140.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="travis_2016" label="Travis and Holm 2016">Travis C. and Holm P. (2016)
                        <title rend="quotes">The digital environmental humanities — what is it and
                        why do we need it? The NorFish Project and SmartCity Lifeworlds</title>, in:
                    C. Travis and A. von Lünen’s (Eds.) <title rend="italic"> The digital arts and
                        humanities. Springer Geography</title>. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-40953-5_11"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-40953-5_11</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tronto_1990" label="Tronto and Fisher 1990">Tronto, J. C., and Fisher,
                    B. (1990) <title rend="quotes">Toward a Feminist Theory of Caring</title>, in E.
                    Abel, and M. Nelson’s (Eds.), Circles of Care. SUNY Press, pp. 36-54.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="viola_2023" label="Viola 2023">Viola, L. (2023). <title rend="italic"
                        >The Humanities in the digital: Beyond critical digital humanities</title>.
                    Springer Nature. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-16950-2"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-16950-2</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="warren_1991" label="Warren and Cheney 1991">Warren, K. J., and Cheney,
                    J. (1991) <title rend="quotes">Ecological feminism and ecosystem
                    ecology</title>,  <title rend="italic"> Hypatia</title>, 6(1), pp. 179-197. <ref
                        target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/3810040"
                        >https://www.jstor.org/stable/3810040</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="whitson_2017" label="Whitson et al. 2017">Whitson, R. et al. (2017)
                        <title rend="quotes">Alternate histories of the digital humanities: a short
                        paper panel proposal</title>, <title rend="italic"> DH2017, Alliance of
                        Digital Humanities Organizations</title>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="whyte_2016" label="Whyte and Cuomo 2016">Whyte, K. and Cuomo C. J.
                    (2016) <title rend="quotes">Ethics of caring in environmental ethics: Indigenous
                        and feminist philosophies</title> in S.M Gardiner and A. Thompson’s (Eds.)
                        <title rend="italic"> The Oxford Handbook of Environmental Ethics</title>.
                        <ref target="https://ssrn.com/abstract=2770065"
                        >https://ssrn.com/abstract=2770065</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wiens_2020" label="Wiens et al. 2020">Wiens, B. I. et al. (2020)
                        <title rend="quotes">Materializing data: New research methods for feminist
                        digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic"> Digital Studies/le Champ
                        Numérique</title>, 10(1). <ref target="https://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.373"
                        >https://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.373</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="willoughby_2021" label="Willoughby_2021">Willoughby, U. E. (2021)
                        <title rend="quotes">Race, health, and environment</title>, in J. Cohen and
                    S. Foote’s (Eds.) <title rend="italic"> The Cambridge companion to environmental
                        humanities</title>. Cambridge Companions to Literature. Cambridge University
                    Press, pp. 70-85. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wolfe_2007" label="Wolfe 2007">Wolfe, J. A. (2007) <title
                        rend="quotes">Digital libraries and the challenges of digital
                        humanities</title>, <title rend="italic"> Library Collections, Acquisitions,
                        and Technical Services</title>, 31(2), pp. 116-117. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1080/14649055.2007.10766158"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1080/14649055.2007.10766158</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="young_2021" label="Young 2021">Young, J. C. (2021) <title
                        rend="quotes">Environmental colonialism, digital indigeneity, and the
                        politicization of resilience</title>, <title rend="italic"> Environment and
                        Planning E: Nature and Space</title>, 4(2), pp. 230-251. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1177/2514848619898098"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/2514848619898098</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="yusoff_2019" label="Yusoff 2019">Yusoff, K. (2019) <title
                        rend="italic"> A Billion Black Anthropocenes or none</title>, University of
                    Minnesota Press.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
