<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:array="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/array"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:map="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/map"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">What Counts? Digital Humanities Pedagogy Seminars as Teaching</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Crystal <dhq:family>Hall</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1324-0364</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Bowdoin College</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>chall@bowdoin.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Crystal Hall is Associate Professor of Digital Humanities and affiliated faculty in Italian Studies at 
                     Bowdoin College in Brunswick, ME. Her research and teaching focus on the relationship between technology, 
                     textual expression, and the creation of knowledge with specializations in pre-modern Italy and the digital 
                     and computational artifacts of the 21st-century United States.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Lauren <dhq:family>Tilton</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4629-8888</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Richmond</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>ltilton@richmond.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Lauren Tilton is the E. Claiborne Robins Professor of Liberal Arts and Digital Humanities in the Department of 
                     Rhetoric and Communication Studies and Director of the Distant Viewing Lab (<ref target="https://www.distantviewing.org/">https://www.distantviewing.org/</ref>) 
                     at the University of Richmond. Her research focuses on analyzing, developing, and applying digital and computational 
                     methods to the study of 20th and 21st century documentary expression and visual culture. Her most recent book, 
                     <title rend="italic">Distant Viewing: Computational Exploration of Digital Images</title> 
                     (<ref target="https://www.distantviewing.org/book/">https://www.distantviewing.org/book/</ref>) with Taylor Arnold is 
                     open access with The MIT Press.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Griffin <dhq:family>Ng</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0009-0003-7210-9750</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Bowdoin College</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>griffin.z.ng@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Griffin Ng graduated with a B.A. in Mathematics and Digital and Computational Studies, magna cum laude, from Bowdoin 
                     College in Brunswick, ME. He recently taught English in Taiwan on a Fulbright fellowship.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date/>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <term corresp="#collaboration"/>
               <term corresp="#pedagogy"></term>
               <term corresp="#dh"></term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>labor</item>
                  <item>seminars</item>
                  <item>experimentation</item>
                  <item>intersectional feminism</item>
                  <item>values-based DH</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000721/000721.xml">GitHub
        	   </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>Digital Humanities pedagogy seminars (DHPSs) are a common occurrence on small liberal arts campuses that are seen as acts of 
               service within the logic of the Teaching-Research-Service model of tenure and promotion in the U.S. academy. Yet, the goal of 
               these events is to teach faculty colleagues DH methods, inflected by DH pedagogy values, which they can then use in their 
               undergraduate courses. As tenured and tenure-track DH specialists at small liberal arts colleges, we argue that a DHPS is 
               pedagogical labor and should be evaluated as teaching in order to enact values-based DH more broadly. The paper provides 
               qualitative data based on experiences at our institutions as well as quantitative data about 226 DHPSs offered in North 
               America from July 2015 to July 2019. We focus on the impact of DHPS duration and the home institutions and roles of instructors 
               on collaboration, experimentation, and intersectional feminism as practiced in the field.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>In the teaching-research-service triad of labor in higher education, reframing digital humanities pedagogy workshops as 
               teaching brings us closer to the goals of the field.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head/>
            <p>Digital Humanities pedagogy seminars (DHPSs) are a common occurrence on liberal arts
                campuses in the United States.<note>The authors wish to thank the anonymous reviewers
                who provided valuable feedback for strengthening this paper. We are deeply grateful for
                their time, particularly since this article was first reviewed during the 2020-2021
                academic year while we were all facing the challenges of COVID-19.</note> Their aim 
                is to introduce DH methods for integration into the curriculum. The seminar may be one day, 
                several days, or spread out over a semester or academic year. Yet, when it comes to 
                institutional assessment of faculty members, DHPSs are often overlooked as sites of 
                teaching, and seen instead as only acts of service within the logic of the 
                Teaching-Research-Service model of credit and promotion in the U.S. academy. In a field 
                already marked by precarity and temporariness, the DHPS aims for longevity of the field, 
                but is made vulnerable by evaluative practices such as these <ptr target="#boyles2018"/> 
                <ptr target="#bonds2017"/>. Moreover, the data that we report here provide a scale for 
                what many DH practitioners experience in isolation: the burden of growing and sustaining the
                field falls to colleagues who are not on the tenure track. Senior colleagues in the
                field, those with administrative roles, and DH scholars conducting evaluations for
                promotion have opportunities to shape staffing and the interpretation of this labor
                while DHPS instructors must be mindful about how they execute and communicate the
                work of the DHPS in this environment.
            </p>
            <p>We recognize our positionality at affluent, small liberal arts institutions may make
               our call seem like an issue unique to a privileged class of institutions. At the
               same time, the labor practices of elite institutions ripple through higher
               education. How well-resourced institutions hire, classify labor, and determine
               compensation often sets a standard, giving arguments for or against certain
               institutional behaviors. At a time when many arguments start with, <said>Well, [insert
               peer and aspirant institution] is doing [insert behavior], therefore we should</said>,
               institutions with power in higher education have even more of a responsibility to
               think carefully about the local as well as national effects of how they approach
               labor. Given that two co-authors on this paper are now-tenured faculty members, we
               will focus our analysis on ways in which re-alignments of the DHPS for faculty
               evaluation could be advantageous for the field at large, with the additional goal of
               using our privileged status to describe interventions that may also benefit
               colleagues in non-tenure line or precarious positions in DH. 
            </p>
            <p>To that end, we argue that DHPSs are pedagogical labor and should be evaluated as
               teaching for faculty who need it to count as such. This ideological reframing can
               have positive consequences for teachers of DHPSs. One outcome is that such a shift
               facilitates the practice of a values-based digital humanities <ptr target="#spiro2012"/> 
               <ptr target="#mccarthy2016"/>. Building from Lisa Spiro's argument to ground DH in values, this
               article identifies three DH values — collaboration, experimentation, and
               intersectional feminism — that are difficult to enact given the institutional labor
               categorization of the DHPS as service. We ground these arguments in qualitative data
               from our respective institutions and quantitative data gathered about DHPSs in the
               United States. A second outcome is the identification of actionable interventions in
               this system that will make visible, if not formal, the teaching of faculty and staff
               in ways that mitigate some of the challenges faced by the profession. 
            </p>
            <p>Although such arguments could engage with sociological theories of labor and
               institutional power, given our specializations as humanists we employ historical
               methods, including feminist data creation <ptr target="#klein2020"/>. Data creation
               around the instantiations of the DHPS brought to light the dimensions of the
               phenomenon and a broader view of the multiple threads in the field of DH that are
               currently at odds: how DHPSs are evaluated, where they are taught, and the values
               that we as a field promote for our pedagogy. The pedagogical theories of the field
               are difficult to enact under the institutional circumstances provided for those who
               do this important work for DH. In traditional humanistic fashion this article
               contextualizes the problem with the small liberal arts college (SLAC) environment, 
               uncovers inconsistencies in policies and priorities, and documents a portion of that labor. 
            </p>
            <p>The article has two sections that juxtapose the institutional logics of higher
               education in the United States and those of values-based DH. We begin the first
               section with an overview of the triad of Teaching-Research-Service that defines
               promotion and tenure guidelines followed by a definition of DHPS based on how it was
               enacted in the 5-year period represented by our data, 2015-2019. After addressing
               the institutional condition that all forms of labor that <q>count</q> must be assigned to
               a part of the triad, we argue for considering DHPSs as teaching. We then turn in
               the second section to how DHPSs struggle to enact DH values as long as they are
               limited to the categorization of Service. Along the way we identify and
               re-categorize DHPS labor with attention to the priorities of other labor in higher
               education. Importantly, the challenges we identify are at odds with other values of
               the field related to inclusion, credit, and the decentering of power structures.
               They also reinforce faculty-staff divides and contribute to the invisibility of the
               labor of care work and nurturing that often occurs outside the tenure stream. We
               will address this from the point of view of what counts as knowledge in these
               settings, but recognize that the conversation could and should expand to other
               theoretical perspectives.
            </p>
            <p>The DHPS is not a panacea to the myriad challenges facing higher education, but it
               can be a site of flexibility, creativity, and alterity. Even seemingly minor
               adjustments in how we organize, categorize, and credit labor have the potential to
               change affective and material conditions on the ground. This is particularly the
               case for those of us who labor in the hundreds of institutions of higher education
               where teaching is the most valued aspect of our work as faculty. While much has been
               written about what should count as research in DH, there is a noticeable gap in work
               about what counts as teaching. Attention to debates over how we define, credit, and
               acknowledge teaching is an important avenue for the field for making visible this
               care work that is so often left uncounted. As one peer reviewer added to our
               argument, doctoral institutions have the resources to compensate for the risks taken
               to model these best practices. 
            </p>
            <p>In particular, we focus on the implication of DHPSs as service in the context of the
               SLAC in the United States. There are two reasons for the focus. First, we are engaged in 
               DH at SLACs and therefore are best positioned to discuss DHPSs in this context. Second, the 
               primary focus of scholarship on DH pedagogy is situated in research-intensive universities. 
               Yet, tens of thousands of people labor in the academy at institutions where teaching is the 
               priority or on par with research <ptr target="#casselman2016"/>. Throughout the United 
               States, there are almost 250 institutions of higher education that are classified as 
               <quote rend="inline">Baccalaureate Colleges: Arts &amp; Sciences Focus</quote> by the 
               Carnegie Classification system. Our argument therefore is shaped by and aimed at scholars 
               laboring in this setting, which is often overlooked by the field. Given our roles as 
               tenure-stream faculty, we build our argument around those roles, and suggest implications for 
               colleagues in other kinds of positions and for the field at large. 
            </p>
            <p>While we hope this article will have broad appeal, a primary audience is
               tenure-stream and tenured faculty who have control over processes such as annual
               reviews, mid-course reviews, tenure and promotion, and who sit on school and
               university committees and may be rising in their administration. There is often a
               false-binary discussion about higher education between the faculty/staff and <q>the
               administration</q>. Yet, <q>the administration</q> is composed of colleagues who have risen
               through the ranks of the faculty and staff. At small liberal arts colleges and many
               institutions across the U.S., it is these very same faculty who become <q>the
               administration</q>. Therefore, we see shifting the discourse for how we frame our labor
               as a part of a longer shift in ideologies that we hope will lead to material
               changes, within departments, units, and hopefully at the very top, even if it takes
               time. We have more influence than is often a part of our national conversation.
               Let’s take part of the power back.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>I. Institutional Logic: Research-Teaching-Service</head>
            <p>The prevailing model for assessment of faculty is the tripartite of research,
               teaching, and service. To receive tenure and promotions, faculty must
               demonstrate their abilities in these three areas. The categories reflect the
               scope of work expected from each faculty member, which includes engaging in the
               creation of knowledge, enabling learning, and participating in supporting and
               building the institution. While they seem capacious, research and teaching are
               actually narrowly defined and beholden to priorities established during
               administrative shifts at land-grant institutions in the early-twentieth century
               and refined as the student population shifted after WWII <ptr target="#shuster2008"/>. 
               Research is meant to contribute knowledge to a particular scholarly community where 
               the work can be assessed for its <q>novelty</q> and <q>rigor</q> in the forms that 
               garner the most credit, i.e., <q>products</q> such as articles, books, and patents. 
               Teaching is aimed at students who are enrolled by the faculty member's employer and 
               includes course instruction alongside advising and mentorship. For example, Bowdoin 
               College's and the University of Richmond's guidelines for teaching define teaching as 
               student instruction in the classroom, consultation outside of the classroom (i.e., 
               office hours), and student advising. As a result, leading a DHPS at one's own or another 
               institution does not count as teaching. Rather, a DHPS is considered service, which has 
               become a catch all for labor that falls outside research and teaching. Even though service often
               includes intellectual labor that results in the transfer or creation of
               knowledge, it is frequently treated as lesser or second-tier work in
               institutional evaluation, compounding the vulnerability of DH practitioners not
               in permanent or tenure-track positions. 
            </p>
            <p>This is particularly fraught when the knowledge is centered on technology, often
               seen as a research tool rather than a research subject and a key way of knowing.
               A values-based DHPS is thus challenging to categorize, particularly when
               collaborative experimentation driven by intersectional-feminist priorities leads
               to new knowledge about an instructor's or participant's primary materials during
               a workshop. The instructor and participants with DH backgrounds could be
               learning more about the collaborative, experimental, and intersectional feminist
               affordances of the method and their related tools (per best practices in DH),
               while a non-DH participant will (hopefully) leave with at least a deeper
               understanding of the texts, images, or other data being used in the DHPS. The DH
               pedagogy components of the DHPS might remain invisible to these participants in
               spite of their necessary presence for achieving the outcomes related to those
               primary materials.
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore, the three categories of labor are not weighed equally across the
               higher education landscape in the United States. Different kinds of institutions
               emphasize particular parts, which (ideally) is explicitly addressed in tenure
               and promotion guidelines. Small liberal arts colleges like ours, for example,
               often discuss this triad as teaching, research, and service in order to
               communicate the order of importance. The University of Richmond explicitly
               states that <quote rend="inline">teaching is the most important area of faculty 
               performance</quote> <ptr target="#universityofrichmond2018"/>. Bowdoin College 
               declares that <quote rend="inline">a high standard of teaching... is essential</quote> 
               <ptr target="#bowdoincollege2019"/>. What one will almost never find is a guideline that 
               begins with service in university documents or in colloquial usage, placing the DHPS in 
               a vulnerable category of institutional labor. As scholarship in higher education has shown, 
               service is the least valued component of the triad and almost never a reason one is denied 
               tenure or promotion. In fact, departments actively try to shield early career faculty from
               service, emphasizing that attention should be focused on research and teaching.
               Given how little service <q>counts</q>, it is no wonder that faculty often focus
               their attention elsewhere.<note>We recognize that there are personal, political, and 
               institutional imperatives that mean that certain faculty can't choose to opt out. This is 
               particularly true for women and scholars of color who are asked to do a significant amount 
               of service on campus.</note> Reconfiguring how we count different parts of academic labor 
               becomes a necessity for recognizing the multiple sites in which DH pedagogy is practiced and 
               for enabling a values-based DH profession.
            </p>
            <p>Beyond this, the markers of formal instruction (i.e., a centralized curriculum,
               vetting and evaluation by a professional authority, and credentialing) include
               elements that are at odds with the collaborative, feminist, intersectional
               approach that many DH practitioners embody and share. The DHPS must almost
               always be customized at least to the institution, if not to the participants,
               and to the particular area(s) of DH in which the instructor has expertise,
               decentralizing the curriculum. Moreover, the ethos of collaborative resource
               sharing and the rate of change of technologies to support this work create a
               dynamic menu of activities, methods, and agendas for the locally instantiated
               DHPS. Suggesting that the DHPS could or should conform to one ideal that can be
               judged for common content or skill-based outcomes would curtail the agility of
               the field and its practitioners. This resistance to the markers of formal
               instruction risks relegating the DHPS to the status of informal learning (another
               devalued category in higher education), as though it were not led by a teacher,
               based on a shared set of values and practices, or reliant on lesson plans and
               pedagogical theory.<note>We focus here on digital humanities pedagogical theory, 
               while recognizing that instructional design theory would add other avenues of 
               exploration.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, DHPSs are often categorized as service because they are seen as professional
               development for attendees. The current institutional logic is as follows. While
               a researcher develops and shares scholarship, the person who leads a DHPS is
               leading professional development and therefore engaged in service. The person
               attending, on the other hand, can categorize the products of their time and
               labor as teaching. As a result, a DHPS is not a form of knowledge transfer that
               is recognized by institutional definitions as research, because it is not a
               finished product in the form of a publication or creative work, or teaching,
               because the attendees are not the institution's definition of a student. Yet,
               such logic is problematic.
            </p>
            <p>A comparison to other fields highlights the incongruities. When an aspiring
               Italian literary scholar wants to learn how to incorporate cinematic critique
               into their practice, they take a graduate course from a specialist. When an
               American studies scholar wants to include a contemporary ecological analysis of
               a site in a seminar, they invite a colleague to guest lecture and teach the
               class. That is, when we step outside our field or even subfield as pedagogues,
               there are formal and informal ways to include specialist methods and tools in
               our courses. These ways of expanding disciplinary coverage are recognized as
               pedagogical for the specialist who is bringing that information to the scholar's
               training or the colleague's class. If cinematic critique were treated as only
               showing a movie, or if environmental studies were introduced as only reporting
               test results, then the epistemologies, priorities, and ethics of those
               disciplines would be reduced to a tool or output. Since they are not, the
               specialists' roles as teachers are recognized. However, when it comes to
               computational and digital methods, the same process of sharing analytical
               methods through tools is often not seen as intellectual expertise that takes a
               knowledgeable pedagogue. 
            </p>
            <p>DHPSs and the roles of their instructors offer an additional challenge to this
               tripartite faculty evaluation. DH faculty regularly teach seminars across the
               curriculum from first year seminars to writing seminars to senior capstone
               seminars. Faculty introduce new concepts and experiment with new ideas. They may
               be centered on a particular topic and/or method. Tilton's <q>Introduction to
               Digital Humanities</q> course is a case in point. As a seminar, the class meets each
               week so that participants may develop their methodological toolkit. At Bowdoin,
               DH faculty frequently consult, via weekly meetings, with students conducting
               independent studies or Honors projects in another department. Those students
               become conduits for DH methods and mindsets into the practices of colleagues in
               those fields. How is this so different from a DHPS?
            </p>
            <p>We turn to another set of examples from the digital humanities community to
               further our argument that DHPSs should also be considered teaching. DH institutes
               are a popular form of knowledge creation and sharing, i.e., teaching, in the
               field. Examples include the Digital Humanities Summer Institute at the
               University of Victoria, Humanities Intensive Learning and Technology (HILT) in
               the United States, the European Summer Institute in Digital Humanities at the
               University of Leipzig, and the Winter Institute in Digital Humanities at New
               York University, Abu Dhabi. Along with learning new methodologies for research,
               courses also focus on DH pedagogy and praxis. DHSI courses at the University of
               Victoria have counted toward institutional credit, which indicates their value
               as teaching <ptr target="#proposal2014"/>. While most do not carry academic credit, 
               and we are not arguing that they necessarily should, the point is that the knowledge
               sharing that occurred was seen as commensurate with what is called teaching in
               the triad.
            </p>
            <p>The framing of DHPSs as service is also doubly confounding for small liberal arts
               colleges. If the emphasis is on teaching, then becoming an excellent teacher who
               is using appropriate and up-to-date scholarship and pedagogies, as is articulated in 
               many guidelines, requires learning.<note>For example, <quote rend="inline">appropriately 
               up-to-date materials and methodologies</quote> are expected at the University of Richmond, 
               according to their guidelines <ptr target="#universityofrichmond2018"/>.</note> Rather 
               than structurally disincentivizing a set of experts from teaching those would-be learners, 
               we argue that we need to rethink how we categorize the labor that makes DHPSs possible. 
               In other words, it is necessary to expand our definitions of who is teaching and learning and
               therefore how we define teaching in the promotion triad of the U.S. academy. This
               issue is more acute given that institutional assessment structures require that
               all labor be assigned to one part of the triad, otherwise that labor does not
               count. The aim is not only to make sure that this labor counts but also be
               recognized as important. While it may be tempting to dismiss this issue as an
               elite problem, there are also implications for the larger DH community to which
               we now turn. In the section that follows, we dive deeper into what we can learn
               from data about DHPSs.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Our Logic: Counting DHPSs as Institutional Accountability</head>
            <p>Rather than impose a definition of a DHPS based on our own experience of this
               work, we used the process of data creation as an epistemological method and
               created a data set in July 2019. As theorized by Klein and D'Ignazio, we
               approached data collection as a potential means of action against power
               imbalances, to better analyze the systems that maintain it, and to
               potentially shift our own framework of understanding <ptr target="#klein2020"/>. 
               This process drew our attention to the scope of the phenomenon of the DHPS, 
               the institutional categories that sustain it, the embedded hierarchies in its 
               presentation, and the range of definitions that can exist for this work. We thus 
               employ a broad definition for DHPS, understanding that the integration of pedagogical
               training alongside DH methods could occur with different proportions and
               intentions. This means that DHPS, as it is self-identified, encompasses
               presentations on teaching with DH, workshops on how to incorporate a DH
               method or tool into a course, and sessions dedicated specifically to DH
               pedagogy. We acknowledge that institutional capacities and interests impact
               the duration and frequency of DHPS offerings. In light of the labor concerns
               highlighted in this paper, opportunities for multiple-day, intensive
               workshops often require resources that are simply unavailable. Thus, a DHPS
               could be as short as a 20-minute presentation, a one-hour working lunch with
               collaborators, or several consecutive meetings of a cohort. Our definition
               embraces the largest tent for DH, relying on presenters and organizers to
               label their pedagogical interventions as part of the field.
            </p>
            <p>The data was found via <title rend="italic">Humanist</title> archives, Twitter, the 
               DH Slack channel, and specific college websites from January 2015 to July 2019. 
               Because we were using digital archives rather than a survey or interviews, DH 
               undergraduate researcher Griffin Ng aggregated from the online DH community information
               from announcements including the title, hosting institution, and description. Most were 
               one-paragraph workshop announcements or titles of presentations in a larger symposium. 
               For <title rend="italic">Humanist</title>, Ng searched every post in the archives from 
               2015 up to July 15, 2019 by using key terms such as <q>event</q>, <q>pedagogy</q>, and 
               <q>teach</q>. On Twitter, he searched by key hashtags: <q>#dhworkshop</q>, <q>#dhpedagogyworkshop</q>, 
               <q>#digitalpedagogy</q>, and <q>#dh</q>, documenting events that contained a variant 
               of <q>DH</q>, <q>pedagogy</q>, or <q>teaching</q> in the title or description. Hall and 
               Ng used a previously compiled list of colleges with digital humanities programs or centers 
               as the foundation for a keyword search similar to the one undertaken for 
               <title rend="italic">Humanist</title> archives, including <q>DH</q>, <q>digital humanities</q>, 
               <q>event</q>, <q>pedagogy</q> and <q>teach</q> to find events or news related to DHPSs on 
               campuses that might have received only local advertising <ptr target="#hall2016"/>. We 
               supplemented that list by also searching the sites of the home institutions for invited
               presenters and hosts of DHPSs that were advertised through other media.<note>We recognize that 
               this list is incomplete, and that it will always be out of date.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As a result, the data relies on organizers reporting the event through local, disciplinary, and 
               transnational digital communication channels, including internal university spaces such as 
               an online calendar, disciplinary communities such as the DH Slack, and public-facing social 
               media such as Twitter. The result was 226 events at 76 institutions. These do not include national 
               or regional conference presentations, nor do these events include instructional workshops for common 
               DH tools, unless they were advertised with a teaching or pedagogical component. We documented the 
               title of the event, a link to our source, information about instructor fields and titles, 
               institutional characteristics, and any moments in which we were estimating the length of the DHPS.
            </p>
            <p>Given the institutional priorities surrounding these events, the amount of funding for DH in general, 
               and our labor constraints, we anticipate that the 226 events in our final data set are a fraction 
               of the DHPS that have occurred since 2015 in North America. Aside from established summer
               institutes like DHSI, the DHPS is an intensely local event, meaning that documentation and visibility 
               of this labor exists at an institutional level, often unseen by the profession at large. The challenge 
               of identifying and aggregating data about DHPSs is itself an indicator of the limited outside
               visibility of what we do, which exacerbates the problematic understanding of how to categorize that 
               work according to the logic of institutions of higher education in the United States.
            </p>
            <p>Overall, the process of transforming DHPS announcements into quantifiable data drew our attention to 
               certain attributes of these events that inform the contextualization and recommendations that follow. 
               When we discuss the challenges that the structure of the DHPS creates for instilling a values-based DH more 
               broadly (in the second section of the article), we will discuss the relationship between the instructor and 
               the institution that hosts the DHPS, trends in duration of DHPSs, and the titles and status of DHPS instructors. 
               Here, for accountability purposes for institutional logic of evaluation, we focus on the types of institutions 
               hosting pedagogical workshops in DH.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>DHPSs and Institutional Types</head>
            <p>The data offers insights into scale and type of institutions engaged in DHPSs. What we find is the prevalence of 
               these events across institutional types, but with patterns that complicate the understanding of the DHPS in the
               Teaching-Research-Service structure of evaluation. While the events seem commonplace, they are more common at 
               certain types of institutions. Those institutions' structures directly impact the success of a values-based DH
               pedagogy. We note too, the continued scholarly attention in the field to large institutions that Wagner has 
               recently observed <ptr target="#wagner2019"/>. Our aim here is to bring to light the disproportional ways in which 
               the current DHPS framing impacts instructors at other schools.
            </p>
            <p>DHPSs are disproportionately hosted in research contexts when compared to available information about where 
               DH is taught in North America. We also contextualize our findings in Table 1 within the landscape of higher
               education as represented by the Carnegie Classification <ptr target="#indianauniversity2018"/>. The overwhelming 
               majority of workshop sites are doctoral institutions with very high research output (51%), and doctoral 
               institutions overall offered the most DHPSs. Baccalaureate colleges (11%) and Masters granting institutions (6%) 
               account for the remaining U.S. schools hosting workshops in our data set. The remainder were hosted at Canadian 
               (8%) and European (3%) institutions.
            </p>
            <p>
            <table>
              <head>Distribution of DHPSs and Institution Types</head>
                <row role="label">
                  <cell role="label">Level of Degree Granted</cell>
                   <cell role="label">Carnegie Data Set 2018 (2,069 schools)</cell>
                  <cell role="label">North American Institutions with DH (214 schools)</cell>
                  <cell role="label">DH Pedagogy Seminars at Institutions (222 workshops)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell role="label">Doctoral (codes 15, 16, 17)</cell>
                  <cell>20%</cell>
                  <cell>58%</cell>
                  <cell>72%</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell role="label">Masters (codes 18, 19, 20)</cell>
                  <cell>33%</cell>
                  <cell>14%</cell>
                  <cell>6%</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell role="label">Bachelors (codes 21, 22, 23)</cell>
                  <cell>35%</cell>
                  <cell>19%</cell>
                  <cell>11%</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell role="label">Associates (codes 1, 2)</cell>
                  <cell>12%</cell>
                  <cell>0.1%</cell>
                  <cell>0%</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell role="label">Canadian</cell>
                  <cell>N/A</cell>
                  <cell>7%</cell>
                  <cell>8%</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell role="label">European</cell>
                  <cell>N/A</cell>
                  <cell>N/A</cell>
                  <cell>3%</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            </p>  
            <p>At the international level, we observe sustained interest in presenting on pedagogy at conferences 
               (not documented in Table 1). 11 papers (presented by individuals, pairs, and teams, for a total of 
               20 scholars) at DH2016 in Poland include the tag <q>pedagogy</q> <ptr target="#eder2016"/>. 8 papers 
               at DH2017 had <q>pedagogy</q> in the title, and many of the presenters tackled the subject from
               an institutional perspective <ptr target="#lewis2017"/>. Similarly in Mexico, at DH2018, 11 papers had 
               <q>pedagogy</q> in the title, while a number approached the subject from a variety of practical, structural, 
               and theoretical viewpoints in the abstracts <ptr target="#gironpaulau2018"/>. At DH2019, 8 panels were 
               organized under the heading of <quote rend="inline">Scholarly Communities, Communication, Pedagogy</quote>, 
               along with two posters <ptr target="#dh2019"/>. Yet, pedagogy, and the work of pedagogical training is also not
               understood as research in the sense of the science of learning and teaching.
            </p>
            <p>The values of the field push practitioners into spaces of intellectual risk in the academy that exacerbate 
               professional risk. Experimentation can beget failure that is deemed unproductive in a publish-or-perish 
               research context; collaboration encounters the hurdle of devaluation in promotion and hiring; and intersectional, 
               feminist practices face institutionalized obstacles to adoption. In addition, because service is often the 
               least valued component of the model, DH pedagogy at the institutional level then becomes marginalized labor 
               even while it is essential to the program building that would offer less precarity for DH practitioners on 
               campus. There are then even greater stakes for DH specialists who are not on the tenure track. As
               long as the academy views this kind of labor as service, in spite of the pedagogical expertise it requires, 
               those instructors risk further marginalization. As a result, it is even more important to recognize DHPSs as
               teaching in the Teaching-Research-Service model of university labor.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>II. DH Values and the DHPS</head>
            <p>An ongoing debate in the digital humanities has been how to define the field. Definitions have been shaped 
               by disciplinary commitments, the hagiography of Roberta Busa, infusion of competitive funding, and 
               precarious labor practices <ptr target="#graban2019"/> <ptr target="#losh2018"/> <ptr target="#terras2016"/> 
               <ptr target="#tilton2018"/>. The implications are significant given efforts to institutionalize the field 
               through programs, departments, publishing, and academic associations. Rather than trying to define
               who is in and who is out, there has been work in DH to organize the field around values <ptr target="#ramsay2011"/>.
            </p>
            <p>As Lisa Spiro compellingly argues, organizing DH around values offers a way to define a community that 
               makes space for the various disciplinary, methodological, and labor configurations that animate the 
               field <ptr target="#spiro2012"/>. A value-centered approach also requires that practitioners come together to
               articulate not only shared intellectual commitments but how we want to engage with each other as a community. 
               Enacting her own focus on collaboration as a DH value, she noted that <quote rend="inline">a set of values 
               <emph>for</emph> a community should be done <emph>by</emph> the community</quote> <ptr target="#spiro2012"/>. 
               The community has responded.
            </p>
            <p>Along with Spiro's call for collaboration, openness, collegiality and connectedness, experimentation, and 
               diversity as a potential set of values for DH, Sean McCarthy and Michael Witmer have followed her lead focusing
               specifically on a set of values for DH pedagogy <ptr target="#mccarthy2016"/>. They adopt collaboration and 
               openness and add critical thinking and production, which they call the CCPO framework. Others include the 
               authors in Elizabeth Losh and Jacqueline Wernimont's edited volume in the <title rend="italic">Debates in the
               Digital Humanities</title> series, who collectively call for intersectional feminism as a value for the field 
               <ptr target="#losh2018"/>. In the sections that follow, we discuss how reconfiguring DHPSs as teaching 
               furthers three DH values: collaboration, experimentation, and intersectional feminism.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Collaboration</head>
            <p>The modeling and development of longer-term collaboration faces two challenges with the standard format 
               of DHPSs: the workshop structure and the institutional location of the instructors. Miriam Posner 
               is forthright about the challenges presented by these workshops: unscripted work is messy and
               hard, the timing of the workshop often doesn't align with the need for a new tool, and it is hard to feel 
               connected to a community of users in such a small window of time <ptr target="#posner2016"/>. Indeed, 
               for the workshops we studied at liberal arts colleges and Masters universities, 80% lasted 90 minutes or
               less. By comparison, 95% of DHPSs at doctoral institutions were 90 minutes or shorter. Often, panels are 
               broken into 15-20 minute segments for multiple presenters. Moreover, being given an opportunity to 
               report on pedagogical interventions is markedly different from teaching a class of adult learners
               how to blend the priorities and tools of DH with their current practice. We also acknowledge that 
               collaboration is often fraught with the labor tensions that cross the faculty-staff divide on many campuses 
               and that different collaborators may not share common goals <ptr target="#wagner2019"/> <ptr target="#graban2019"/>.
            </p>
            <p>We agree with Posner in her advocacy for bootcamps, longer training schedules, and immersive 
               experiences that enact as well as educate for collaboration <ptr target="#posner2016"/>. The implication 
               of this finding is that the DHPS instructor typically has the length of a single class period (or less)
               to report or instruct methodology as well as to model the ethos of digital humanities pedagogy, if not call 
               attention directly to the values embraced therein. While the space for explicit engagement with teaching is
               constrained, the environment of such DHPSs nonetheless requires the successful instructor to deploy 
               aspects of DH pedagogy to instruct colleagues. Collaboration is thus difficult to model, let alone teach, in
               the time allotted for DHPSs, when it is seen as service rather than teaching. Short periodization does not 
               allow for reflection or critique on the use of the tool, thus overemphasizing quick, transferable skill 
               building with the goal of a product, rather than engaging in a process of interrogation. Where collaboration 
               might be a stated value, institutional structures privilege an outcome that is antithetical to much of the 
               current conversation on DH values.
            </p>
            <p>The second challenge facing collaboration is the institutional location of the instructors and their 
               relationship to attendees. As a corollary to the challenges of timing identified above, one the basic 
               rules that Posner identifies is <quote rend="inline">nobody comes to workshops</quote> 
               <ptr target="#posner2016"/>. This is compounded by the number of invited instructors and the precarity 
               of instructors' roles at their home institution. For DHPSs hosted at liberal arts colleges in our
               data, we observed that 45% of instructors were invited to campus, meaning that their motivation to form 
               partnerships or ability to maintain collaborations were limited. (This is comparable to the 40% of invited 
               DHPS instructors at doctoral institutions.) For context, Wagner's 2019 study on DH research reported that 
               66% of partnerships involved collaborators at the same institution. At the University of Richmond, we 
               intentionally blended this in order to model cross-institutional collaboration as well as to build
               in sustainability. At Bowdoin, we have primarily focused on workshops with local instructors, allowing us 
               to offer several iterations over time and build a cohort of colleagues who are developing DH pedagogy 
               skills in text analysis specifically. Admittedly, we have benefitted from an institutional
               commitment to growing DH organically at the college.
            </p>
            <p>That commitment is important to note, because the greatest challenge to sustained collaboration 
               remains the precarity of many of the instructors and specialists in the field. As Christina Boyles, 
               Anne Cong-Huyen, Carrie Johnston, Jim McGrath, and Amanda Phillips poignantly document, DH
               colleagues who could be potential collaborators are frequently providing support without the resources 
               of a dedicated center, trying to balance complex research needs with administrative burdens of educating and
               persuading a C-suite to maintain funding for DH initiatives, and doing so under the professional burdens 
               of temporary positions <ptr target="#boyles2018"/>. Even at institutions with a higher level of commitment 
               to DH such as Bowdoin, this was Crystal's experience, starting as a postdoctoral fellow with the 
               expectation of building an undergraduate program, transitioning to a visiting assistant professorship 
               while generating institutional buy-in, and then undergoing promotion and tenure review in DH based on 
               teaching and scholarship in the field (in that order of priority). When funding ends for initiatives, or 
               when a person moves into a new, and hopefully less precarious, position, collaborations are difficult to 
               maintain, presuming that local interested colleagues took the risk of starting such projects under 
               circumstances of precarity. This status of DH practitioners is evident in the data about workshop instructors, 
               40% of whom were in non-tenure stream positions for liberal arts college workshops (compared with 60% at
               doctoral institutions). Building sustainable, long term DH pedagogy collaborations becomes nearly impossible 
               when the labor necessary for DHPSs is devalued.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Experimentation</head>
            <p>Reconsidering DHPSs as teaching also enables experimentation. In his oft-cited blog post, Tom Scheinfeldt 
               questioned the refrain, <quote rend="inline">Where's the beef?</quote> Those posing the question argued 
               that DH lacked arguments, which remains a popular debate from scholars, particularly in digital history. 
               While others have engaged in debates over the merit of the claim that DH does not make arguments, Scheinfeldt 
               questioned what was so wrong with experimenting as scholarly knowledge. <quote rend="inline">We need time 
               to experiment</quote>, he argued <ptr target="#scheinfeldt2012"/>. Experimentation, he argued, has long 
               been recognized as a way of knowing. Just ask a scientist, hacker, tinkerer, or maker. He's not alone.
            </p>
            <p>The idea of experimentation is so pervasive in DH, Lisa Spiro notes, that she offers it as one of the 
               six values that she suggests for the field. <quote rend="inline">As in the sciences, digital humanities 
               projects often use data, tools, and methods to examine particular questions</quote>, she writes, adding 
               that <quote rend="inline">the work supports interpretation and exploration</quote> <ptr target="#spiro2012"/>. 
               The same holds true for teaching and pedagogy. Experimenting with which DH methods to teach or utilize in a 
               course necessitates a space where one can learn these methods, hence the emergence of the DHPS.
            </p>
            <p>Yet, the ability to experiment in a DHPS is compromised when this teaching practice is framed as service. 
               Service is most often about sharing responsibility for maintenance and development of institutional structures
               and to perform administrative tasks within a defined timeline for completed components. Experimentation on the 
               other hand is as much about process as result. DHPSs therefore risk being assessed alongside maintaining a
               department and successfully carrying out administrative tasks. The assessment model of the institution can 
               then foreclose experimentation because service is measured by effectiveness and productivity. As a result,
               teaching a series of tools that one can numerically count as evidence of knowledge transfer, for example, 
               becomes appealing.
            </p>
            <p>Productive failure, therefore, is rarely an option. In a neoliberal effort to transfer as much knowledge 
               as <q>efficiently</q> as possible, the short duration and schedule of DHPSs create expectations for immediate 
               and quick results. This disincentivizes experimenting with a new method and its related tools. The stakes are 
               even higher for contingent and precarious colleagues. This is a particularly acute issue because the 
               instructors of on-campus DHPSs are frequently early career scholars, untenured, or term positions, according to
               our data. The person's position can preclude productive experimentation and failure, which is a continual part 
               of teacher development and central to DH.
            </p>
            <p>
            <table>
              <head>Campus Roles of DHPS Instructors</head>
                <row role="label">
                  <cell role="label">Instructor Role at Home Institution</cell>
                  <cell role="label">Number of DHPSs Instructed</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Other</cell>
                  <cell>82</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Assistant Professor</cell>
                  <cell>65</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Tenure Ineligible</cell>
                  <cell>58</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Professor</cell>
                  <cell>58</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Associate Professor</cell>
                  <cell>54</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Graduate Student</cell>
                  <cell>50</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Library Staff</cell>
                  <cell>28</cell>
                </row>
            </table>   
            </p>  
            <p>Reframing DHPSs as teaching shifts the stakes of experimentation while allowing the instructor to 
               model this DH value. Teaching brings pedagogy to the fore; therefore, process can be as important as 
               results. Modeling experimentation through productive failure is made possible because it can also be the 
               pedagogical goal of a DHPS. Particularly given the number of people leading a DHPS who are institutionally 
               precarious, acknowledging and raising the value of the work demonstrates to the institution the importance
               of the labor to the institution.
            </p>
            <p>This is particularly acute for those laboring in small liberal arts college settings where teaching is 
               often the most important aspect of their job and DH practitioners are performing the double duty of 
               community building around DH. These types of colleges are oriented toward undergraduate classroom
               instruction. Job descriptions for a number of positions, from faculty and librarians to technologists include 
               the role of supporting cutting edge classroom instruction. By framing all of this labor as also teaching, space
               is opened to engage in DH pedagogies as well as values such as experimentation.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Intersectional Feminism</head>
            <p>A third DH value that motivates defining DHPSs as teaching is intersectional feminism, a theory and 
               movement for gender equality with attention to how interconnected social categories such as race and 
               class shape gender inequality. An important aspect of this critical framework is addressing power structures 
               that produce gendered inequalities. The DHPS represents the very moment of training new members of the field. 
               That moment can either replicate existing, problematic power dynamics that are at odds with values
               of the field or resist those dynamics through modeling alternatives.
            </p>
            <p>Structural misogyny permeates the field of DH and institutions of higher education. As Elizabeth Losh 
               and Jacqueline Weirnemont point out in the introduction to their exciting volume on feminist DH, 
               <quote rend="inline">trivialization of feminist methodologies continues within the field</quote> and they 
               call for coalition building and communal care to resist the structural misogyny that marginalizes certain 
               aspects of the field. One area where structural misogyny permeates DH is the topic of DH pedagogy. At the 
               annual DH conferences 2105-2019, of the 400+ workshops, long papers, short papers, and posters each year, 
               contributions on pedagogy range from a minimum of 3 papers (2015) to a maximum of 11 (2016, 2018). Pedagogy 
               finds a marginalized home in the research space of the field. Examples abound including the programming of 
               the international DH conference, citation practices, and the language of <q>hard</q>, scientific research 
               versus <q>soft</q>, pedagogical work <ptr target="#losh2018"/>. Therefore, it is difficult to make compelling
               arguments to institutions to value DH pedagogical labor when hyper-visible and vocal aspects of DH marginalize 
               this labor.
            </p>
            <p>In an effort to challenge this misogyny, we want to center intersectional feminist pedagogies in DH and in 
               our institutions through DHPSs <ptr target="#park1996"/>. One way is to focus on process and not product, 
               which brings us back to centering collaboration and experimentation. The three values are interconnected and 
               mutually reinforcing. The combination moves the student-colleague, through DH pedagogy, into a space of 
               reflection on method and priorities in their field as well as ours. One way we model and convey these as DH 
               values is through the DHPS. For example, when we lead a DHPS, we don't identify a list of tools, but rather 
               discuss how we will be engaging in a set of methods in order to evaluate tools, process and outcomes.
               Experimentation and play become critical.
            </p>
            <p>Central to the discussions are which voices are represented (or not) in the data and materials being 
               tudied as well as what expressions are counted and emphasized (or not) by the tools. This necessitates 
               conversations about power structures in archives, histories and cultural contexts of tool development, and 
               responsible data creation. This work takes time, which is why we resist the call for a quick, one-time DHPS. 
               Quick, efficient, digestible knowledge transfer is capitalist and gendered logic that we seek to resist. 
               Rather, creating more stable, long term models for DHPSs that center intersectional feminist values through 
               collaboration and experimentation is one way that DHPSs can avoid replicating problematic power dynamics that 
               are at odds with values of the field. A more sustained model also gives us more space and time to argue and 
               demonstrate how this labor fits into the teaching logic of the Teaching-Research-Service model.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>III. Conclusion</head>
            <p>The root of the problem sits in three places: the pedagogical values that DH
                    practitioners represent, the status of instructors and their schools, and the
                    ways in which this labor is valued by those institutions. By juxtaposing the
                    values of the field against the form that our practice takes when inviting
                    others into the field through the DHPS, we hope to have articulated spaces for
                    intervention. We use these discrepancies and the proposed evaluative frameworks
                    for DH research to propose local and individual actions that can realign the
                    DHPS with values in the field while supporting their instructors. We suggest
                    changes that can be enacted by the DH community such that design and evaluation
                    can be based on something akin to Moya Bailey’s questions for researchers [2015]
                    and Graban et al.’s framework for research planning [2019]. 
            </p>
            <p>Bailey outlines three categories for planning a digital research project that can
                    be used for evaluation that ruptures this neoliberal, paternalistic definition
                    of success: connection (i.e. collaborators and benefits), creation (i.e.
                    multidirectional collaborative tools and methods, consent, pacing), and
                    transformation (i.e. the care of the self and others, new connections, and new
                    understandings). [Bailey, 34-36] Graban et al. also highlight care within
                    collaboration, adding the principles of identifying individual markers of
                    recognition, making labor visible through documentation, “acknowledging a
                    spectrum” of the acceptable outputs of DH work, and embracing the paradoxes
                    within DH. [2019] By making these ideological changes through a shift in our DH
                    practices and discourses, we can be a part of larger material changes in how
                    labor is assessed, credited, and compensated. With a majority of labor in higher
                    education actually working at teaching-intensive institutions of higher
                    education, even though much of our discourse is about research-intensive
                    institutions, elite teaching-intensive universities are well positioned to shift
                    the ideological and material conditions of DH and broader labor. 
            </p>
            <p>Given the dimensions of the DHPS that we observed and the institutional
                    restrictions to enacting the values of the field, we see the following actions
                    as ways to address the inequalities, particularly for having the DHPS considered
                    as Teaching for instructors who need it to be such, but also to assist in other
                    forms of credit:
            </p>
            <list rend="bulleted">
               <item>Design and advertise the DHPS with values-based language, activities, and
                        outcomes with a focus on methods. The tool-of-the-day can be the means to
                        that end, not the end in itself.</item>
               <item>Solicit evaluations after the DHPS that focus on these values and the
                        impact of the methods learned on a longer time-frame than immediately after
                        its conclusion. Special attention to how a member of the seminar may have
                        incorporated the methods into their own research and teaching will offer
                        further evidence of pedagogical impact, which can in turn also be a part of
                        showing impact for review processes. </item>
               <item>For DHPSs as Teaching in particular, craft a syllabus with reading lists
                        and track citations or reuses. A publication venue would be particularly
                        advantageous for this.</item>
               <item>Practice citation of DHPS material created by others and inform the
                        creator of its use. Aligning this with existing DH pedagogy publications
                        would facilitate this process of making visible the expertise of DHPS
                        instructors and making it count in through institutional assessment
                        metrics.</item>
               <item>Use internal hiring, promotion, and evaluation as moments to design for
                        and realign with sustainable values and practices in the face of changing
                        technology. The processes become a space to argue for this labor as
                        Teaching.</item>
               <item>Use external review as an opportunity to state how the DHPS reflects the
                        values of the field. If conducting an external review, ask the unit if there
                        are arguments about labor such as calling certain DH work teaching that
                        would help the department with internal advocacy such as FTEs and
                        compensation.</item>
            </list>
            <p>There are two major limits to our arguments, which we want to acknowledge. The
                    first is that this is not a fundamental challenge to the tripartite and
                    therefore problematic organization of labor in the U.S. academy. Rather, the call
                    to consider DHPSs as Teaching means continuing to work within the current
                    institutional stratification of labor. Since the current system for faculty
                    evaluation requires assigning all labor to one of these three categories,
                    another challenge arises. It is difficult to argue for “counting” a type of
                    labor as more than one part. Therefore, a DHPS in most settings will count as
                    either Teaching or Service much like all other forms of labor.
            </p>
            <p>As a result, depending on one’s position within the university, it may be
                    advantageous to “count” this labor as Service and for another person to “count”
                    it as Teaching. Our aim here is to demonstrate why labeling a DHPS as Teaching
                    can further DH values. We also hope that some of the structural considerations
                    that undergird our argument might frame how the field thinks about other forms
                    of DH labor such as support from DH lab staff, postdoctoral fellowships, and
                    visiting instructors.
            </p>
            <p>At the end of the day, we hope that moving to a values centered model may upend
                    the entire evaluation system. Shaped by important critiques about power from
                    fields such as cultural studies, work by groups such as the Humane Metrics
                    Initiative (HuMetricsHSS) is rethinking how we define and assess labor across
                    the Humanities and Social Sciences.[6] Models such as the one proposed by HuMetrics and Lisa Spiro offer
                    the possibility to tear down the Research, Teaching, Service tripartite that has
                    been in place over the past several decades. Our call to reassess how we
                    categorize DHPSs is a step in the direction, we hope, of a more radical and, dare
                    we say, “productive” future for DH and higher education.
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bailey2015" label="Bailey 2015"> Bailey, Moya. (2015) <title rend="quotes">#transform(ing)DH writing and 
             research: An autoethnography of digital humanities and feminist ethics</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 
             Quarterly</title>, 9(2). <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/2/000209/000209.html">
             http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/2/000209/000209.html</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bonds2017" label="Bonds and Gil 2017">Bonds, L., and Gil, A. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Introducing 
             the <q>miracle workers</q></title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Library Foundation</title>. Available at:
             <ref target="https://www.diglib.org/introducing-miracle-workers-working-group/">
             https://www.diglib.org/introducing-miracle-workers-working-group/</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="boyles2018" label="Boyles et al. 2018">Boyles, C. et al. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Precious labor and 
             the digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">American Quarterly</title>, 70(3), pp. 693–700.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bowdoincollege2019" label="Bowdoin College 2019">Bowdoin College (2019) <title rend="italic">Faculty Handbook 
             2019-20</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://www.bowdoin.edu/academic-affairs/pdf/19-20facultyhandbook.pdf">\
             https://www.bowdoin.edu/academic-affairs/pdf/19-20facultyhandbook.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="casselman2016" label="Casselman 2016">Casselman, B. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Shut up about Harvard</title>,
             <title rend="italic">Five Thirty Eight</title>, 20 March. 
             Available at: <ref target="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/shut-up-about-harvard/">
             https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/shut-up-about-harvard/</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dh2019" label="DH 2019"><title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2019 Conference Agenda</title>. 
             Available at <ref target="https://web.archive.org/web/20190824223442/https:/www.conftool.pro/dh2019/index.php?page=browseSessions&#x0026;path=adminSessions&#x0026;print=export&#x0026;presentations=show">
             https://web.archive.org/web/20190824223442/https:/www.conftool.pro/dh2019/index.php?page=browseSessions&#x0026;path=adminSessions&#x0026;print=export&#x0026;presentations=show</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="eder2016" label="Eder and Rybicki 2016">Eder, M., and Rybicki, J. (eds.) (2016) 
             <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2016 Conference Abstracts</title>. Available at
             <ref target="https://dh2016.adho.org/abstracts/static/dh2016_abstracts.pdf">
             https://dh2016.adho.org/abstracts/static/dh2016_abstracts.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gironpaulau2018" label="Girón Paulau and Galina Russell 2018">Girón Paulau, J., and Galina Russell, I.
             (eds.) (2018) <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2018 Puentes-Bridges Book of Abstracts</title>. 
             Available at: <ref target="https://dh2018.adho.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/dh2018_abstracts.pdf">
             https://dh2018.adho.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/dh2018_abstracts.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="graban2019" label="Graban et al. 2019">Graban, T.S. et al. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Introduction: 
             Questioning collaboration, labor, and visibility in digital humanities research</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital 
             Humanities Quarterly</title>, 13(2). <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/2/000416/000416.html">
             http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/2/000416/000416.html</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hall2016" label="Hall 2016">Hall, C. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Data set for North American colleges and 
             universities with Italian and digital humanities program</title>, <title rend="italic">DCS Faculty Publications</title>, 
             1. <ref target="https://digitalcommons.bowdoin.edu/dcs-faculty-publications/1">
             https://digitalcommons.bowdoin.edu/dcs-faculty-publications/1</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="indianauniversity2018" label="Indiana University 2018">Indiana University Center for Postsecondary Research (2018)
             <title rend="italic">The Carnegie classification of institutions of higher education</title>. Bloomington, IN: 
             Indiana University Center for Postsecondary Research.</bibl> 
          <bibl xml:id="klein2020" label="Klein and D'Ignazio 2020">Klein, L., and D'Ignazio, K. (2020) <title rend="italic">Data 
             feminism</title>. Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lewis2017" label="Lewis et al. 2017">Lewis, R. et al. (ed.) (2017) <title rend="italic">Digital 
             Humanities 2017 Conference Abstracts</title> Available at: 
             <ref target="https://dh2017.adho.org/abstracts/DH2017-abstracts.pdf">
             https://dh2017.adho.org/abstracts/DH2017-abstracts.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="losh2018" label="Losh and Wernimont 2018">Losh, E., and Wernimont, J. (2018) <title rend="italic">Bodies of 
             information: Intersection feminism and digital humanities</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota.
             <ref target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/projects/bodies-of-information">
             https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/projects/bodies-of-information</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mccarthy2016" label="McCarthy and Witmer 2016">McCarthy, S., and Witmer, M. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Notes 
             toward a values-driven framework for digital humanities pedagogy</title>, <title rend="italic">Hybrid Pedagogy</title>, 
             29 March. Available at: <ref target="https://hybridpedagogy.org/values-driven-framework-digital-humanities-pedagogy/">
             https://hybridpedagogy.org/values-driven-framework-digital-humanities-pedagogy/</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="park1996" label="Park 1996">Park, S. (1996) <title rend="quotes">Research, teaching, and service: Why shouldn't 
             women's work count?</title>, <title rend="italic">The Journal of Higher Education</title>, 67(1), pp. 46–84.
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/2943903">https://doi.org/10.2307/2943903</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="posner2016" label="Posner 2016">Posner, M. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Here and there: Creating DH 
             community</title>, in Gold, M.K. and Klein, L. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Debates in the digital humanities 
             2016</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press. 
             Available at: <ref target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled/section/c6b8f952-acfd-48b6-82bb-71580c54cad2">
             https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled/section/c6b8f952-acfd-48b6-82bb-71580c54cad2</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="proposal2014" label="Proposal 2014"><title rend="italic">Proposal for a graduate certificate in digital 
             humanities based in the Digital Humanities Summer Institute (DHSI) and its international network</title>. (2014)
             Available at: <ref target="http://web.uvic.ca/~siemens/DH(SI)GradCertificateProposal.pdf">
             http://web.uvic.ca/~siemens/DH(SI)GradCertificateProposal.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ramsay2011" label="Ramsay 2011">Ramsay, S. (2011) <title rend="quotes">Who's in and who's out</title>,
             <title rend="italic">Stephen Ramsay Blog</title>, 8 January. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://web.archive.org/web/20170426170232/http://stephenramsay.us:80/text/2011/01/08/whos-in-and-whos-out">
             https://web.archive.org/web/20170426170232/http://stephenramsay.us:80/text/2011/01/08/whos-in-and-whos-out</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="scheinfeldt2012" label="Scheinfeldt 2012">Scheinfeldt, T. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Where's the beef? 
             Does digital humanities have to answer questions?</title>, in Gold, M.K. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Debates in the 
             digital humanities 2012</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press. Available at:
             <ref target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled-88c11800-9446-469b-a3be-3fdb36bfbd1e/section/3c03ecdb-2dcf-4597-8fc4-e42f8dcc21e1">
             https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled-88c11800-9446-469b-a3be-3fdb36bfbd1e/section/3c03ecdb-2dcf-4597-8fc4-e42f8dcc21e1
             </ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="shuster2008" label="Shuster and Finkelstein 2008">Shuster, J.H, and Finkelstein, M.J. (2008)
             <title rend="italic">The American faculty: The restructuring of academic work and careers</title>. Baltimore, MD:
             Johns Hopkins University Press.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="spiro2012" label="Spiro 2012">Spiro, L. (2012) <title rend="quotes"><title rend="quotes">This is why we fight</title>: 
             Defining the values of the digital humanities</title>, in Gold, M.K. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Debates in the digital 
             humanities 2012</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press. Available at:
             <ref target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/13">http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/13</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="terras2016" label="Terras and Nyhan 2016">Terras, M., and Nyhan, J. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Father Busa's 
             female punch card operatives</title>, in Gold, M.K. and Klein, L. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Debates in the digital humanities 
             2016</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled/section/1e57217b-f262-4f25-806b-4fcf1548beb5">
                https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled/section/1e57217b-f262-4f25-806b-4fcf1548beb5</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tilton2018" label="Tilton et al. 2018">Tilton, L. et al. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Toward a critically engaged 
             digital practice: American studies and the digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">American Quarterly</title>, 
             70(3). <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1353/aq.2018.0026">https://doi.org/10.1353/aq.2018.0026</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="universityofrichmond2018" label="University of Richmond 2018">University of Richmond (2018) 
             <title rend="italic">Faculty handbook</title>. Available at:
             <ref target="https://facultyhandbook.richmond.edu/Handbook_022118rev_updated%20HR%20link%20for%20domestic%20part.pdf">
             https://facultyhandbook.richmond.edu/Handbook_022118rev_updated%20HR%20link%20for%20domestic%20part.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="wagner2019" label="Wagner2019">Wagner, J. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Digital collaborations: A survey analysis 
             of digital humanities librarians and other academics</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 
             13(4). <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/4/000441/000441.html">
             http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/4/000441/000441.html</ref></bibl>
        </listBibl>
     </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
