<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Researching Spanish
               Dance in Time and Space: A GIS for La Argentina's Ballets Espagnols</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Blanca <dhq:family>Gómez Cifuentes</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>Universidad Complutense de Madrid</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>blgomez@ucm.es</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Blanca Gómez Cifuentes is a doctoral student in Art History at the Universidad Complutense de Madrid (UCM). She is co-editor of <title rend="italic">Antonia Mercé, La Argentina. Epistolario</title> (1915-1936) (CDAEM, 2020) and author of articles on the relationship between dance and visual arts in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries. She has been awarded several internships and scholarships at the Université Paris 1 Panthéon-Sorbonne, the Fundación de Amigos del Museo del Prado, CSIC and the UCM. She is a member of the UCM-CSIC Seminar on Research in Dance History and Theory and R&amp;D projects at CSIC.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Carlos <dhq:family>Fernández Freire</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>Spanish National Research Council (CSIC)</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>carlos.ffreire@cchs.csic.es</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Geographic Information Systems and Remote Sensing Technician at the Spanish National Research Council (CSIC). Graduated in History in 2000, PhD in Prehistory in 2008. Member of the Geographic Information Systems and Digital Humanities Lab – CSIC since 2009. I have worked in issues regarding Data Modelling in UML, implementation and deployment of Spatial Databases, GIS and Remote Sensing Analysis, Spatial Data Infrastructures and Webmapping, in the context of Humanities Research Projects carried out within the Spanish National Resarch Council.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Isabel <dhq:family>del Bosque González</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>Spanish National Research Council (CSIC)</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>isabel.delbosque@csic.es</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Specialist in Cartography, Geographic Information Systems (GIS) and Spatial Data Infrastructures (SDI). She is a Engineer in Geodesy and Cartography from the Polytechnic University of Madrid (UPM) with Advanced Studies in Geographic Engineering from the UPM. She is officer career of Topographical Engineers (leave) and of Systems and Information Technologies of the State Administration (since 1992). She has developed her professional career at the National Geographic Institute of Spain (IGN) and since 2005, she is responsible for the GIS and Digital Humanities unit in the Spanish National Research Council (CSIC).</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Idoia <dhq:family>Murga Castro</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>Instituto de Historia, CSIC</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>idoia.murga@csic.es</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Idoia Murga Castro, PhD (History of Art) is Tenured Researcher at Instituto de Historia, CSIC, where she studies the relationships between dance and visual arts. She has a degree in Classical Dance from the RAD and the ISTD. She has worked in the field of museums as curator, adviser and coordinator of exhibitions; she is the author of various books and articles and directs several R&amp;D projects about dance history.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000625</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->3</idno>
         	<date when="2022-06-25">25 June 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2022-08-05" who="BRG">added teaser and resolved encoding errors</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>This study presents the results of the research project on the Ballets Espagnols de
               Antonia Mercé La Argentina, a dance company active between 1927 and 1929 that adapted
               the model of Diaghilev's Ballets Russes to a repertoire based on the construction of
               a national identity through the modern and avant-garde aesthetics of interwar Europe.
               The systematisation of the preserved sources and their visualisation in interactive
               maps permits research to be carried out on one of the most brilliant episodes in the
               history of Spanish dance and to collaborate in the recovery of a forgotten dance
               heritage.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
         	<p>Systematizing preserved sources of the Ballets Espagnols de Antonia Mercé La Argentina 
         	to create interactive maps which visualize their activity.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
   <div>
         <head>1. Introduction </head>
         <p> One of the difficulties encountered in research on Dance Studies, and especially in
            dance history, is the ephemeral condition of the object of study. Due to the
            impossibility of direct access to the primary source, which is the original performance
            of the dance work, it is necessary to trace its origin through the artistic, written,
            musical or audiovisual materials that have been preserved. The study of sketches of
            sets, costumes, scores, choreographic notation, films, sound recordings, librettos,
            newspaper reviews and documents, among others, will show the contribution made by each
            dance work when it was premiered. This information is the primary basis on which to
            establish the subsequent interpretive analysis. The frequent dispersion of these
            materials, as well as their poor preservation or loss, together with a short academic
            tradition and scarce research in certain contexts, mean that large gaps still exist in
            dance history. This is even more evident in the Spanish academic context in relation to
            dance research. Despite artistic manifestations such as flamenco, which was awarded
            UNESCO's World Heritage status in 2010, and other dance jewels, such as the bolero — a
            dance form legacy from the eighteenth century — Dance Studies are not established in the
            university system. Besides, research in dance history is still limited and depends on
            other humanistic and artistic disciplines. Therefore, the advance in the application of
            new methods in Digital Humanities and their open access offers great potential for
            research into the history of Spanish dance, increasing the level of interpretation of
            the preserved sources, and the possibilities of integration and impact on international
            art history narratives, from which it has traditionally been excluded. </p>
         <p> This article presents the case study of the research project <title rend="italic">Ballets
               Españoles (1927-1929): A Dance Company for the Internationalisation of Modern
               Art</title> (ref. ERC2018-092829), aimed at analysing the impact of transnational modern
            and avant-garde art and interdisciplinary creation that was disseminated through the
            Ballets Espagnols, the dance company founded by Antonia Mercé, aka La Argentina (Buenos
            Aires, 1890-Bordeaux, 1936). This group, which was active between 1927 and 1929, was the
            first to produce a <q>Spanish-style</q> version of the model of Sergei Diaghilev's successful
            Ballets Russes, which had dazzled Western audiences and critics since 1909 with its
            repertoire of ballets by the most outstanding creators and intellectuals, such as Igor
            Stravinsky, Pablo Picasso, Natalia Goncharova, Manuel de Falla, Vaslav and Bronislava
            Nijinska, among many others. </p>
      
      <figure>
         <head>Postcard of
            Antonia Mercé la Argentina, Teatro Barcelona. Private collection.</head>
         <graphic url="resources/images/image1.jpeg"/>
         <figDesc>Image of a woman</figDesc>
      </figure>
      
  
         <p> Diaghilev's previous success encouraged the foundation of other groups that examined
            their respective roots and national identities in order to propose modern pieces, which
            include the Ballets Suédois, Ballets Romantiques Russes, Ballets Russes de Monte Carlo
            and, in this case, the Ballets Espagnols. In these works, La Argentina surrounded
            herself with outstanding Spanish musicians, painters and writers in the creation of a
            repertoire based on Spanish cultural legacies. Some of her most outstanding works were
               <title rend="italic">El amor brujo, El fandango de candil, Au coeur de Seville (Cuadro
               flamenco), Juerga, Sonatina</title> and <title rend="italic">Triana.</title> Over the years
            she had the support of writers such as Cipriano de Rivas Cherif, Federico García Lorca
            and Tomás Borras; musicians such as Manuel de Falla, Ernesto Halffter, Julián Bautista,
            Joaquín Turina and Enrique Fernández-Arbós; stage designers such as Néstor, Gustavo
            Bacarisas, Manuel Fontanals and Mariano Andreu; and dancers such as Vicente Escudero,
            Carmita García, Pastora Imperio and Miguel de Molina. The transcendence of these names
            in their respective areas highlights the impact of the Russian model. Considering a
            ballet as a <q>total work of art</q> — derived from Richard Wagner's <title rend="italic"
               >gesamtkunswerg —</title> different elements were entrusted to outstanding personalities
            of their field with a certain innovative and modern outlook. Moreover, the company
            united examples of the most outstanding contributions of the arts and literature of the
            time, in what Spanish historiography considers the so-called Generations of 1898, 1914
            and 1927. These protagonists of the movement of cultural renewal would constitute the
            period know as the Silver Age, interrupted by the military uprising that started the
            Spanish Civil War on 18 July, 1936, the same day on which Antonia Mercé La Argentina
            died suddenly of a heart attack. </p>
         <p> The Ballets Espagnols were conceived mainly for a foreign audience and the ensemble
            never performed in Spain, making internationalisation a key element in understanding the
            acceptance of Spanish dance and its legacy in the memory of Western dance from then on.
            Despite the repercussion that both Antonia Mercé and her company had on Spanish dance,
            no monographic study of the Ballets Espagnols existed to date. Only some studies examine
            her biography and trajectory, and some articles and books propose readings of her
            context. <note> Some of the studies that recuperated the legacy of Antonia Mercé and
               mentioned the Ballets Espanols are: <ptr target="#rodrigo1990"/>; <ptr target="#manso1993"/>; <ptr target="#bennahum2000"/>; <ptr target="#murgacastro2017a"/>; <ptr target="#murgacastro2019"/>; <ptr target="#murgacastro2021"/>; <ptr target="#alberdi2018"/>.</note> Therefore, this research sought to
            locate, analyse and interpret the Ballets Espagnols repertoire in order to assess its
            impact on the definition of Spanish imaginaries through the modern interpretation of
            interwar Europe. </p>
         <p> It was therefore essential to have a tool that would enable the systematic examination
            of the preserved sources of diverse typology located in different countries. Besides, it
            was also possible to analyse the presence of this company in very specific sections
            using spatiotemporal coordinates. The research project was carried out between 2018 and
            2020 within the framework of the State Programme for the Promotion of Scientific and
            Technical Research of Excellence, under Europe Excellence Dynamization Actions of the
            Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation, at the Department of Art History and
            Heritage of the Institute of History of the Spanish National Research Council (CSIC), in
            collaboration with the Unit of Geographic Information Systems and Digital Humanities at
            the Centre for Human and Social Sciences. Part of this work has also been continued in a
            new research project, entitled <title rend="italic">Dance Studies and Digital
               Humanities</title> (ref. 202010E150), undertaken by the CSIC, which seeks to extend the
            development and application of these tools to research into Spanish dance history, and
            which is running from 2020 to 2023. The main aim is to share the results of this study
            in the application of Digital Humanities in dance, and specifically, for future research
            in the rich field of Spanish dance and its various aspects including flamenco, bolero,
            folk dances and stylised dance.</p></div>
         <div>
         <head>2. Dance Studies and Digital Humanities: a growing relationship</head>
         <p> The application of Digital Humanities to dance has become a fertile field for the
            advancement of knowledge in a discipline traditionally very attached to physical, oral
            and face-to-face transmission through body language techniques. Paradoxically, the
            context of extended reality is offering new advantages for areas of historical research,
            such as the recovery and reconstruction of dance heritage. </p>
         <p> Many initiatives along these lines are currently being carried out, such as the
            projects developed at Florida State University with the ViFlow augmented reality
            platform for dance <ptr target="#vvaa2016"/> or the completed <title rend="italic">WhoLoDance
               (Whole-body Interaction Learning for Dance Education)</title> <ptr target="#vvaa2018"/>, as well as
            various international conferences specialised in the relationship between the performing
            arts and technology: <title rend="italic">International Conference on Movement and
               Computing</title> (MOCO) and <title rend="italic">Conference for Research in Choreographic
               Interfaces</title> (CRCI). It is important to highlight the specialised spaces that host
            these interdisciplinary works, such as the Google Arts &amp; Culture Lab, New Frontier
            Artist Residency Programme (Sundance) or Advanced Computing Centre for the Arts and 
            Design (ACCAD, The Ohio State University).<note> <ref target="https://accad.osu.edu/">https://accad.osu.edu/</ref></note> In Spain,
            these spaces include the <title rend="italic">Aula de las Artes</title> Art and Science
            Platform of the Universidad Carlos III de Madrid and the Dance and New Media Lab (DANM)
            of the Etopia Art and Technology Centre in the city of Zaragoza.</p>
         <p> Regarding exploration of new software for performing arts research along the lines of
            <q>theatre analytics</q> <ptr target="#bardiot2020"/> and its assessment of the complexity of the
            associated data, different projects are exploring the relationships and exchanges that
            link the ephemeral with the permanent, the physical with the virtual. Some current
            initiatives are based on the development of digital archives, such as <title rend="italic"
               >Siobhan Davies Replay</title>:<title rend="italic"> The Archive of Siobhan Davies
                  Dance</title> 
            <note> <ref target="http://www.siobhandaviesreplay.com">http://www.siobhandaviesreplay.com</ref></note> or the Carmen Beuchat Archive.<note>
               <ref target="http.//carmenbeuchat.org">http.//carmenbeuchat.org</ref></note>
         </p>
         <p>Furthermore, Digital Humanities have provided fundamental tools for the assessment of
            the spatiotemporal coordinates in dance history research, focusing on the evidence
            preserved through interactive mapping. Of particular importance are the contributions of
            Harmony Bench (Ohio University) and Kate Elswit (Royal Central School of Speech and
            Drama) whose application of new digital research methodologies in conjunction with
            traditional tools have made it possible to manage, analyse and compare on a large scale
            the vast amount of data obtained on the different tours of dance companies in the
            twentieth century, giving rise to what has become known as <quote rend="inline">dynamic spatial histories of
               movement</quote> <ptr target="#bench2016"/>. <title rend="italic">Moving Bodies, Moving Culture</title>
            <note> <ref target="https://movingbodiesmovingculture.wordpress.com">https://movingbodiesmovingculture.wordpress.com</ref></note> follows the American 
            Ballet Caravan company on its tours of Latin America during the 1940s; <title rend="italic"
               >Mapping Touring</title> 
            <note> <ref target="https://movementonthemove.osu.edu/project-mapping-touring">https://movementonthemove.osu.edu/project-mapping-touring</ref></note> presents a
            database accessible through a map viewer containing the performances of various dancers,
            choreographers and companies from the turn of the century, such as Ruth Saint Denis, Ted
            Shawn, Erick Hawkins, Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo or Original Ballet Russe. Finally, the
            tours made by the African-American dancer and choreographer Katherine Dunham between the
            1930s and 1960s illustrate the recent project <title rend="italic">Dance in Transit and
               Dunham's Data: Katherine Dunham and Digital Methods for Dance Historical
               Inquiry.</title> 
            <note> <ref target="https://www.dunhamsdata.org">https://www.dunhamsdata.org</ref></note>
         </p>
         </div>
         <div>
         <head>3. Materials and methods</head>
         <p>The implementation of a Digital Humanities project of this nature requires addressing
            the systematisation of information by designing and creating <q>data models.</q> This is what
            is known, generically, as the description of the <q>universe of discourse</q> or the part of
            the real world we wish to study and represent <ptr target="#flanders2015"/>. The data
            modelling process involves identifying the most relevant entities or classes in our
            project and describing their main features and the connections between them.</p>
         <p>Data modelling is a current topic of discussion in Digital Humanities. Its definition,
            within this spectrum, is not very different from the one usually used in computer
            sciences. There are authors who believe that data modelling should be one of the main
            tasks of research projects in humanities <ptr target="#jannidis2013"/>. Nevertheless,
            neither a theory nor extensive scientific literature on the subject is apparent, perhaps
            because it is believed that there is already enough in the field of computer
            technologies. Data modelling, in Humanities, is understood as an <q>interpretation</q> of an
            object, both in the real and virtual world; a constructive and creative process in which
            the functions of digital technology determine which aspects should be modelled <ptr target="#flanders2015" loc="14"/>. Nowadays, data modelling is applied more and more frequently
            and is a prior and indispensable step in systematising information in Digital Humanities
            projects. This is well summarised in the work of Ciula &amp; Marras (<ref target="#ciula2016">2016</ref>), which
            highlights the upward trajectory of works that incorporate these technologies to develop
            their research. Two phases must be distinguished in data modelling: on the one hand,
            design modelling, which describes the entities from the universe of discourse with which
            we are going to work; and on the other hand, logical modelling, which is the
            implementation of the former in a database environment. </p>
         <p>Within the framework of our research project, we have undertaken a joint work process
            between the mentioned research group and the technology unit of Geographic Information
            Systems and Digital Humanities CCHS-CSIC, the latter having extensive experience in the
            modelling of scientific data <ptr target="#fernandezfreire2013"/>. </p>
         <p>Data systematisation involved designing a model containing the classes, possible
            relationships and properties of our information. The extensive collection was extracted
            from diverse sources, from national and international institutions, and will provide
            support for future consultations, studies, spatiotemporal analyses and visualisations to
            understand the contributions of the repertoire and the performances of the Ballets
            Espagnols and the individual recitals of Antonia Mercé La Argentina. </p>
         <p>The data modelling of our project has been carried out according to the UML (Unified
            Modelling Language) standard. Being an internationally used language, it enables our
            work to be understandable, scalable and reusable by any other researcher working on a
            related topic. Despite the potential of UML, its extension within the humanities is
            relatively limited. For several years, XML has been used for work in the field of text
            editing and analysis. There are therefore several examples of transformation of literary
            works to XML format <ptr target="#kimber2000"/>; <ptr target="#hayashi2001"/> and their storage in TEI
            format <ptr target="#teehan2010"/>; <ptr target="#portela2015"/>. These works have
            approached this technology from the perspective of text analysis, semantic web and
            ontologies, as well as extraction of annotations from ancient documents through a UML
            schema <ptr target="#luzzi2012"/>. More recently, there has been an updated volume <ptr target="#schraibman2016"/> dedicated exclusively to Digital Humanities that explores
            through authors, pioneers in research in this field, the infrastructures, creation,
            analysis, dissemination and future of Digital Humanities itself. </p>
         <p>The class diagram that describes our universe of discourse, within the framework of this
            art and dance history project, takes into account the georeferenced nature of the data
            and has been implemented in a database through an Entity-Relationship model using a free
            software management system, PostgreSQL and the PostGIS spatial extension. This "spatial"
            database structure offers not only the power of SQL queries, but also the possibility of
            integration in Geographic Information Systems (GIS) for subsequent spatiotemporal
            analysis and the generation of maps and dynamic visualisations.</p>
         <p>This potential also extends to the development of different forms of access, for example
            through a map viewer, and the reuse of the information generated by other researchers or
            a more general public. Thanks to the georeferenced nature of the data, web map services
            have been implemented that comply with the regulations and standardisation of spatial
            data (in particular with the specifications of the Open Geospatial Consortium), as well
            as other types of access to the data, still to be determined, always in an open science
            context <ptr target="#delbosquegonzalez2020" loc="36"/>, protecting their authorship as recommended for
            scientific research. Since 2017, and with the aim of enhancing and developing this
            philosophy, the European Commission has stipulated that all publicly funded projects
            guarantee free access to research data under the FAIR Principles (acronym for Findable,
            Accessible, Interoperable and Reusable). For data generated in scientific research
            <ptr target="#wilkinson2016"/>, the
            FAIR Principles are already an institutional mandate in some organisations such as the
            CSIC and a framework by which we intend to abide in this project.</p>
         <p>In order to fulfil those principles, the dataset<note>
               <ref target="http://sigyhd.cchs.csic.es/investigacionendanza-map/datos.php?ln=en"
                  >http://sigyhd.cchs.csic.es/investigacionendanza-map/datos.php?ln=en</ref>
            </note> generated within this project has been metadated according to ISO 19119 and
            incorporated into a public metadata catalogue, making data <q>findable</q> through web
            searches. Data are also <q>accessible</q> in an open spatial format such as GeoJSON and
            interoperable thanks to the above-mentioned Web Map Service, described in a standard
            language that enables linkage to other projects regardless of protocols, software or
            operating systems. The creative commons (by-nc-sa) licencing grants reuse to other
            researchers as long as terms such as attribution are observed. </p>
         <div>
         <head>3.1. Data model</head>
         <p>The data model of <title rend="quotes">Los Ballets Espagnols y los recitales individuales de Antonia Mercé,
            la Argentina</title> solves the integration of very diverse data, ranging from the
            georeferencing of theatres to the elements related to the scenography or the different
            recordings, including the authors and performers of the works. The whole set of data
            revolves around the primary information obtained through the programmes of the different
            performances, the central node that structures all the information that has been
            collected <note> A detailed description of the data model accesible at: <ref
                  target="https://digital.csic.es/handle/10261/261756"
                  >https://digital.csic.es/handle/10261/261756</ref>
            </note>:</p> 
         
         
            <figure>
               <head>Data model.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image2.jpeg"/>
               <figDesc>Image of a flowchart</figDesc>
            </figure>
         
         
         <p>As has been stated, the main sources are the shows’ handbills preserved from various
            locations. The information they contain has been broken down into many items to enable
            atomized database storage that ensures the implementation of complex queries and their
            versatility.</p>
         <p>The logic of the model starts from a show that takes place in a specific location and on
            specific dates. A show is made up of musical numbers in which a fragment of a play is
            enacted by a series of performers (dancers, musicians and conductor). Musical numbers
            may have been filmed by an author, and that footage may be kept in a private or public
            collection. Handbills and posters made for each show are also registered, along with
            their physical description, and location of known copies. The class <q>Play</q> registers all
            information regarding the original play: title, authors, and date. Each piece of
            information related to the show’s development is detailed as a specialization of the
            class <q>Component.</q> There are many components in a show: set design, models,
            choreographies, costumes, librettos and scores. Their authors, title (if applicable),
            current location, date and dimensions (if applicable) are registered, along with
            information about formats, techniques (if applicable) and, for scores, recordings if
            any. </p>
         <p>The following two aspects of the components of each show should be highlighted: whether
            it is possible to specify their current location (for example, in a museum or
            collection) and the existence of copies.</p>
         <p>The data model acknowledges two types of people: authors and performers. Basic biodata
            on both is registered, plus their specialty. The whole project is geographically pinned
            whenever the information can be spatialized: current location of the show’s components,
            handbills, posters, recordings, footage and most significantly, the location of theatres
            where the shows took place. Locations of all kinds are managed through the class
            "Place", where a point is stored in geographic WGS84 coordinates. All places are
            attached to the worldwide locations layer downloaded from Natural Earth’s ( <ref
               target="https://www.naturalearthdata.com/">https://www.naturalearthdata.com/</ref>)
            populated places and subsequently to a country. This way the spatial component enables
            future queries to be aggregated by country or locality.</p>
         <p>Despite the fact that many theatres no longer exist, thorough research has yielded an
            accurate position for almost all of them. In that case the generic locality’s
            coordinates taken from the Natural Earth layer are displayed in the map. Although this
            is a data model designed for this project, we believe that the development of
            sufficiently generic classes and the introspection carried out on the nature of the
            information make it an easily reusable model for any other project in the same field. </p>
         <p>The implementation of the model has consisted of the direct development of an
            Entity-Relationship model adjusted to the definition of classes. Given the need for a
            geographic data manager and the potential use of the database in online projects, it was
            decided to host the model in a PostgreSQL Database Management System (DBMS) with its
            PostGIS spatial extension. All coordinates have been defined in geographical WGS84.
            Access to basic Create, Read, Update and Delete (CRUD) operations has been enabled
            through the development of a web interface in PHP. This allows the project researchers
            to maintain and extend the database. </p> 
        
            <figure>
               <head>Interface
                  snapshot</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image3.png"/>
               <figDesc>screenshot of a table</figDesc>
            </figure>
        
        
         </div>
            <div>
         <head>3.2. Workflow</head>
         <p>The database has been completed with the help of the developed tools, adding plays,
            authors, performers, programmes, etc. The location of the theatres was first carried out
            using a geocoding service, but has finally required an exhaustive revision through
            searches on Google Maps and in some cases more specific revisions when the theatre has
            disappeared or its name has been altered. In any case, all theatre locations refer to a
            GIS layer of places, so that in cases where it has been impossible to obtain the exact
            location of a venue, the coordinates of the centroid of the place in which it is located
            are used (this is the case of 3 theatres out of a total of 115).</p>
         <p>The developed system (database + user interface) has been the tool to systematise the
            large amount of dispersed materials and documentation currently held in different
            international institutions, such as libraries, archives, museums and documentation
            centres. The collections held in the institutions listed below were consulted during the
            development of the project: </p>
         <table>
            <row role="label">
               <cell>Archives and documentation centres</cell>
               <cell></cell>
            </row>

            <row role="data">
               <cell>Archivo Carlos Manso (Buenos Aires, Argentina)</cell>
               <cell>A private collection by this relevant former dancer and researcher, author of
                     <hi rend="italic">La Argentina, fue Antonia Mercé</hi> (Buenos Aires, Devenir,
                  1993). It includes written and graphic sources. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>American Foundation for the Blind, Helen Keller Archive (New York, USA) </cell>
               <cell>The collection of this feminist, suffragist, social activist and pacifist
                  author contains some written sources related to La Argentina. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Archives de La Monnaie (Brussels, Belgium)</cell>
               <cell>It contains some materials related to the Ballets Espagnols tours in the
                  Théàtre de La Monnaie in 1928. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Archivo Fundación Zuloaga (Zumaia, Spain) </cell>
               <cell>One of the family archives related to the painter Ignacio Zuloaga contains
                  several written sources. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Archivo Histórico Nacional (Madrid, Spain) </cell>
               <cell>This state archive gathers written sources linked to Antonia Mercé and some
                  creators of her time. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Archivo Manuel de Falla (Granada, Spain)</cell>
               <cell> Focused on the collection of the musician, it conserves written, graphic and
                  musical sources, including letters, librettos, scores, photographs and other
                  documents. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Archivo Pablo Suero (Buenos Aires, Argentina)</cell>
               <cell> It conserves the private archive of this Spanish-born writer and journalist
                  established in Argentina, which contains several letters and articles linked to
                  Antonia Mercé. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Archivo Regional de la Comunidad de Madrid (Madrid, Spain)</cell>
               <cell> This archive conserves several written and graphic sources, including
                  programs, posters, photographs and scores, some of which are part of the Juan
                  María Martínez de Bourio collection. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Archivo Sáenz de Tejada (Laguardia, Spain): </cell>
               <cell>The private collection of the family of the painter Carlos Sáenz de Tejada, a
                  painter and scenographer of Antonia Mercé. Some of the consulted works during the
                  research were recently incorporated into the collections of the Museo Nacional
                  Centro de Arte Reina Sofía. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Centre de Documentació i Museu de les Arts Escèniques, Institut del Teatre
                  (Barcelona, Spain) </cell>
               <cell>One of the main research centres for performing arts in Spain, it contains one
                  of the principal collections about Antonia Mercé, including written and graphic
                  sources, original costumes and personal items. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Centro de Documentación de las Artes Escénicas y de la Música, INAEM (Madrid,
                  Spain) </cell>
               <cell> This state archive includes a significant number of publications and some
                  original written sources. </cell>
            </row>

            <row role="label">
               <cell>Libraries</cell>
               <cell></cell>
            </row>

            <row role="data">
               <cell>Biblioteca Fundación Juan March (Madrid, Spain) </cell>
               <cell>One of the main institutions that conserves the largest collection donated by
                  Antonia Mercé's niece, Carlota Mercé de Pavloff, "Fondo Antonia Mercé la
                  Argentina". It contains the original scrapbooks by the choreographer, as well as
                  photographs, letters, musical recordings, documents, and a wide range of
                  publications. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Biblioteca Nacional de Catalunya (Barcelona, Spain)</cell>
               <cell> It holds some written sources, mainly correspondence from Antonia Mercé and
                  her manager, Arnold Meckel. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Biblioteca Nacional de España (Madrid, Spain)</cell>
               <cell> It conserves original sketches, scores, librettos, footage, letters, press
                  clippings, and the most important bibliography about the choreographer. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Biblioteca Tomás Navarro Tomás, Centro de Ciencias Humanas y Sociales, CSIC
                  (Madrid, Spain) </cell>
               <cell> It contains a wide range of publications about performing arts, related to
                  dance research currently being undertaken at the History of Art and Heritage
                  Department at the History Institute. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Bibliothèque Nationale de France (Paris, France) </cell>
               <cell>The "Fonds Argentina" at the Bibliothèque-Musée de l'Opéra contain the most
                  important collection of materials about the choreographer, including: manuscripts,
                  programs, photographs, posters, costumes, other objects, paintings, and press
                  clippings. Besides, there are more materials conserved at the Département des Arts
                  du Spectacle, mainly costumes, personal souvenirs, portraits, sound recordings,
                  and other graphic sources. They were donations by the dancer's family, the
                  Association des Amis d'Argentina, Auguste Rondel and others. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Filipinas Heritage Library (Manila, Philippines) </cell>
               <cell>Bibliography related to Spanish colonial dances in the Philippines and the
                  context that Antonia Mercé experienced during her stay in Manila in 1929. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>New York Public Library (New York, USA)</cell>
               <cell> It contains a wide range of materials, including letters, programs, press
                  clippings, drawings of her dances by different artists, scores, and other
                  documents. </cell>
            </row>

            <row role="label">
               <cell>Museums and cultural institutions</cell>
               <cell></cell>
            </row>

            <row role="data">
               <cell>Institut Mémoires de l'Édition Contemporaine, Abbaye d'Ardenne
                  (Saint-Germain-la-Blanche-Herbe, France)</cell>
               <cell>It conserves some letters by Antonia Mercé addressed to writers. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Musée de l'Opéra de Vichy (Vichy, France)</cell>
               <cell>This archive contains essential graphic and written sources related to Antonia
                  Mercé’s performances at the Opéra, such as programs, posters and press clippings.
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Museo Mariemma (Íscar, Valladolid, Spain) </cell>
               <cell>This museum conserves the personal collection of the dancer Mariemma, who
                  received the donation of some of the costumes and castanets of the dancer from her
                  brother, and conserves some programs and written documents. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Museo Nacional Centro de Arte Reina Sofía (Madrid, Spain)</cell>
               <cell> The most important contemporary art museum in Spain, it contains graphic
                  materials by painters who collaborated with Antonia Mercé, such as Carlos Sáenz de
                  Tejada, some of which were recently incorporated from the painter’s private
                  collection. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Museo Nacional del Teatro (Almagro, Ciudad Real, Spain)</cell>
               <cell>The state museum of theatre conserves different art works linked to Antonia
                  Mercé, such as sketches and costumes, as well as written documents, photographs
                  and other objects such as castanets and one of the plaster copies of her mortuary
                  mask. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Museo Néstor (Las Palmas de Gran Canarias, Spain) </cell>
               <cell>This museum conserves the private collection of painter Nestor Martínez de la
                  Torre, one of the main artists who collaborated with Antonia Mercé. It contains a
                  wide variety of materials, such as costume and set designs, programs, letters,
                  etc., and specifically, the book <hi rend="italic">Néstor y el mundo del
                     teatro</hi> (1995) by Pedro Juan Almeida Cabrera, the first publication
                  dedicated to Néstor’s work on stage. </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>Residencia de Estudiantes (Madrid, Spain)</cell>
               <cell>This collection is focused on the so-called Spanish Silver Age, that is to say,
                  the flourishing culture of the first third of the 20th century. It comprises
                  several written sources, such as manuscripts, letters, musical scores, recordings,
                  a wide bibliography, and the donated collection of photographs of Antonia Mercé
                  that belonged to the former dancer and gallerist Elvira González. </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p> Among the large number of primary sources conserved in these institutions, programs,
            posters, press clippings and correspondence were essential as they provided the vital
            space-time information. Furthermore, it was necessary to contrast the data with other
            sources such as photographs, costume and set designs, wardrobe and video recordings.
            Other studies about Antonia Mercé and her Ballets Espagnols were equally important. </p>
         <p>At the same time, and in line with the <title rend="italic">gesamtkunstwerk</title> and the
            theoretical framework of the period, the project members considered it a priority to
            equate the importance of authorship in the different disciplines involved in Spanish
            dance work, and to highlight not only those responsible for choreography and music, as
            so often happens, but also to focus on the role of set and costume design — framed as a
            whole phenomenon of the time <ptr target="#murgacastro2012"/>; <ptr target="#murgacastro2017b"/> — , to reveal the authorship of
            the plays <ptr target="#coellohernandez2019"/>; <ptr target="#coellohernandez2020a"/> and to vindicate the contributions of the
            performers.</p>
         <p> Likewise, given the enormous number of performances that Antonia Mercé gave both with
            the Ballets Espagnols and in individual recitals, it was necessary to clarify the layout
            of her itineraries, separating both types of programmes, but offering an overall reading
            that would facilitate the comprehension the context of the collective and the individual
            pieces — both the newly created solos and those numbers taken from the ballets that
            ended up working better as solo performances by the choreographer <ptr target="#gomez2022"/>. </p></div>
            <div>
         <head>3.3. Web implementation: webmapping and WMS services</head>
         <p>The atomisation of the information collected allows it to be used in many ways,
            including analysis or visualisation. The development of a <q>made-to-measure</q> web 
            map<note> Webmap at: <ref target="http://sigyhd.cchs.csic.es/investigacionendanza-map/">http://sigyhd.cchs.csic.es/investigacionendanza-map/</ref></note> such
            as the one made for this project is a valuable tool as it offers an interactive
            interface to access all information on the project, thanks to the geographical nature of
            the central element of the model: the programmes. In this sense, it adds to the
            traditional thematic maps, which provide a concise and elegant representation of the
            data that led them to be a common resource for the illustration of scientific articles
            and books <ptr target="#delbosquegonzalez2012" loc="106"/>. </p>
         <p>The logic followed from the data model considers that the succession of programmes
            ordered by date generates a line that describes what could be called a <q>tour.</q> Lines
            have been generated by linking the performances of the Ballets Espagnols and Antonia
            Mercé for each of the years considered in the project: 1927, 1928 and 1929. The points
            of each theatre allow access to the rest of the information collected by the research
            group: performances, performers, authors of the works and elements. In addition, there
            is also the possibility of filtering all the content shown according to the start and
            end dates of the performances, using a time bar.</p> 
         
               <figure>
                  <head>Webmap
                     snapshots</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/image4.png"/>
                  <figDesc>screenshot of a map</figDesc>
               </figure>
         
               <figure>
                  <head>Webmap
                     snapshots</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/image5.png"/>
                  <figDesc>screenshot of a map</figDesc>
               </figure>

         <p> Interoperable services and metadata have also been generated for the project to adhere
            to the FAIR Principles mentioned above, following the specifications of the Open
            Geospatial Consortium (OGC) and the ISO standard for geographic data and data services
            (ISO 19100 series). Consequently, the Web Map Service (WMS) of "investigacionendanza"
            allows any user to consult the project data using desktop GIS software or to upload it
            to their online project.<note> Access to data and services from: 
               <ref target="http://sigyhd.cchs.csic.es/investigacionendanza-map/datos.php?ln=en">http://sigyhd.cchs.csic.es/investigacionendanza-map/datos.php?ln=en</ref></note> This
            service offers a GIS layer for each year, with information on the performance at each
            theatre. </p> 
         
         
               <figure>
                  <head>WMS charged in a
                     desktop GIS</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/image6.png"/>
                  <figDesc>screenshot of a map</figDesc>
               </figure>
         
         
         <p>From a technical point of view, the webmap has been developed entirely in JavaScript,
            using OpenLayers, and drivers written in PHP for database connections. The WMS service
            is generated from a Geoserver server provided by the Spatial Humanities project Imago
            Orbis <ptr target="#hermidajimenez2018"/> <note> Imago Orbis is the <title rend="italic">Spatial
                  Data Infrastructure (SDI)</title> of the CCHS-CSIC. <title rend="italic">Imago </title>
               <title rend="italic">Orbis</title>
               <title rend="italic"> SDI</title> makes georeferenced datasets generated in the various
               multidisciplinary Digital Humanities projects discoverable, accessible, combinable
               and shareable. In this framework, CCHS research groups can incorporate their
               georeferenced scientific data and be easily viewed with a single interface, according
               to open science standards and protocols, allowing users to combine, compare and reuse
               different information generated in different projects:
               <ref target="http://imagorbis.csic.es/">http://imagorbis.csic.es/</ref></note>.</p> </div>
         </div>
         <div>
         <head>4. Conclusions</head>
         <p> In short, the analysed case study illustrates how the methods employed by Digital
            Humanities, and specifically the Spatial Humanities, make it possible to extend and
            amplify the interpretative level of many different historical sources scattered in
            numerous locations. The consultation of an enormous amount of documentation, distributed
            among institutions in different countries, has been complemented, ordered and arranged
            for the reconstruction of the trajectories of the Ballets Espagnols de Antonia Mercé La
            Argentina, temporarily based in Paris in interwar Europe. The impact of this project can
            be seen especially in the interactive visualisation, the delimitation of the monthly
            time periods of the company's activities over the two years and the ability to
            distinguish between Antonia Mercé's individual recitals and the performances of the
            whole company. Moreover, the project has provided the opportunity to assess each
            performance in the context of the critical response and artistic production. </p>
         <p> In spatial terms, the georeferenced assessment of the dancer's performances in
            different theatres in the same city is particularly interesting, as it provides a better
            idea of the prestige that her shows were acquiring over time. The exact location of each
            performance also makes it possible to understand the type of audience that might attend
            the shows, depending on the district where the theatre was located, the distance from
            the city centre and the different categories of venues. Therefore, in the early days,
            the circuits in which the Ballets Espagnols were shown were somewhat peripheral — it is
            worth noting their world premiere in the German city of Krefeld. Their first steps were
            taken in Germany and Italy, but it was not until later, when the performers were more
            experienced on stage and familiar with a more refined repertoire, that the Ballets
            Espagnols premiered in Paris. </p>
         <p> However, it is noticeable that even Antonia Mercé did not dance on the first-class
            stages, such as the Paris Opera, until a few months before her death in 1936, after
            several attempts to revive her frustrated project of the Ballets Espagnols. The seasonal
            itineraries through numerous European cities between 1927 and 1929 confirm that Antonia
            Mercé's company had not yet achieved the prestige of other, more established
            international dance groups, who enjoyed a more constant and prolonged presence in
            leading cultural centres (Fig. 6). The Théâtre National de l'Opéra Comique (Paris) and
            Town Hall (New York) stand out as key centres in the dancer's career (Fig. 7). </p> 
        
            <figure>
               <head>Performance
                  locations in Paris (1927, 1928 and 1929)</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image7.jpeg"/>
               <figDesc>screenshot of a map</figDesc>
            </figure>
        
        
 
         <p>However, research into the period between 1929 and 1936 points to successive attempts to
            revive the company by touring other countries in America and Europe, including Spain. In
            this respect, it is also relevant to analyse the global dimension of the individual
            recitals of Antonia Mercé, who, in her tours outside Europe, set a precedent for the
            scope of Spanish dance in places such as Japan, Vietnam, the Philippines and the United
            States, with diverse connotations.</p>
       
            <figure>
               <head>Spatial evolution
                  of Ballets Espagnols and Antonia Mercé’s tours in 1927, 1928 and 1929.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image8.jpeg"/>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image9.jpeg"/>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image10.jpeg"/>
               <figDesc>screenshots of three maps illustrating show locations, one for 1927, one for 1928, and one for 1929</figDesc>
            </figure>
       
    
         <p>Another of the analysed issues was the internal development of the company, in
            particular its components. Although in-depth research into the composition of the corps
            de ballet of the Ballets Espagnols in its different seasons is still lacking, this
            qualitative approach yields some interesting indicators. Between 1927 and 1929, the
            group had a total of 91 dancers in its various performances, which varied each season.
            In 1927, there were 31, the following year 54 and the last season 43. Antonia Mercé
            starred in a total of 151 performances, accompanied mainly by the three most recurrent
            dancers: Irene Ibáñez (50 performances), Carmen Joselito (49 performances) and Carmen
            Juárez (46 performances). In a second group, other performers stand out, such as
            Mercedes Dalmau (39), Juan Relámpago (38), Otilio López (35), Lolita Mas (29), Blanca
            Minondo (28), Carmen Mora (27), and Pepita López (27). We must also point out the
            absolute prominence of Carmencita Pérez as piano accompanist (with 63 performances). </p>
         <p> In short, the possibility of visualising all these trajectories reconstructed step by
            step on the interactive map motivates new interpretations to be made of exchanges in
            European circuits, in the relationship with the Americas, and in East-West relations.
            Besides it proposes renewed interpretations of the role of dance as a vehicle for the
            construction and dissemination of cultural identities. Looking at Spanish dance from a
            Digital Humanities point of view helps to obtain a broader and deeper understanding of
            historical heritage and strengthen the dialogues between the virtual and the physical,
            the permanent and the ephemeral, the past and the future. The case study of the Ballets
            Espagnols can open the door to new ways of understanding the role of dance in the
            mapping of identities, aesthetics and ideologies from transnational and transcultural
            perspectives in the early 20th century.</p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Acknowledgements</head>
         <p>This study is supported by the R+D+I projects: <title rend="italic"> Ballets Españoles
               (1927-1929): Una compañía de danza para la internacionalización del arte moderno
            </title>(Acciones de Dinamización Europa Excelencia, Ministerio de Ciencia e
            Innovación/Agencia Estatal de Investigación, ref. ERC2018-092829) and <title rend="italic"
               >Dance Studies y Humanidades Digitales</title> (CSIC ref. 202010E150).</p>
         </div>
       
         
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="alberdi2018" label="Alberdi 2018"> Alberdi, A. <title rend="quotes">Los doce años de Mariemma y los Ballets Espagnols,</title> in R.
               Ruiz, A. Álvarez Cañibano and P. de Castro (ed.), <title rend="italic">Mariemma y su tiempo, Madrid, INAEM</title>
               (2018): 165-194.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bardiot2020" label="Bardiot 2020"> Bartiot, C. <title rend="quotes">Theatre analytics: developing software for theatre
               research,</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 14.3 (2020).
               <ref target="digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/3/000476/000476.html">digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/3/000476/000476.html</ref> </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bench2016" label="Bench y Elswit 2016"> Bench, H. and Elswit, K. <title rend="quotes">Mapping Movement on the Move: Dance
               Touring and Digital Methods,</title> <title rend="italic">Theatre Journal</title>, 68.4 (2016): 575-596.
               <ref target="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/645397">https://muse.jhu.edu/article/645397</ref> </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bennahum2000" label="Bennahum 2000"> Bennahum, N. D. <title rend="italic">Antonia Mercé, <title rend="quotes">La Argentina.</title></title> <title rend="italic">Flamenco and the Spanish
               Avant-Garde</title>, Hannover, University Press of New England (2000).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brockhoeft2016" label="Brockhoeft et al, 2016"> Brockhoeft, T. et al. <title rend="quotes">Interactive Augmented Reality for
               Dance.</title> In F. Pachet, A. Cardoso, V. Corruble and F. Ghedini, (eds). <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the
               Seventh International Conference on Computational Creativity</title>. Paris, France, June 27 –
               July 1, 2016. Sony CSL, Paris (2016): 396-403.
               <ref target="https://www.computationalcreativity.net/iccc2016/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Interactive-Augmented-Reality-for-Dance.pdf">https://www.computationalcreativity.net/iccc2016/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Interactive-Augmented-Reality-for-Dance.pdf</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ciula2016" label="Ciula and Marras, 2016"> Ciula, A. and Marras, C. <title rend="quotes">Circling around texts and language:
               towards 'pragmatic modelling' in Digital Humanities,</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 10.3
               (2016) <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/3/000258/000258.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/3/000258/000258.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="coellohernandez2019" label="Coello Hernández 2019"> Coello Hernández, A. <title rend="quotes">Sueños para una nueva danza española: la
               dramaturgia de <title rend="italic">El desertor </title>(1930), de Felipe Ximénez de
               Sandoval,</title> <title rend="italic">Diablotexto</title>, 6 (2019): 41-60.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="coellohernandez2020a" label="Coello Hernández 2020a"> Coello Hernández, A. <title rend="quotes">Antonia Mercé, la Argentina, y Cipriano
               Rivas Cherif en <title rend="italic">El fandango de candil </title>(1927): gestión y análisis
               dramatúrgico.</title> In <title rend="italic">La investigación en danza. Madrid Online 2020</title>. Mahali, Valencia
               (2020): 73-76.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="coellohernandez2020b" label="Coello Hernández 2020b"> Coello Hernández, A. <title rend="quotes">Imaginarios de lo español en el <title
               rend="italic">Quite</title> (1931): una dramaturgia de Tomás Borrás entre el ballet y la
               copla.</title> In E. Cabo Fernández and I. Matía Polo, (eds), <title rend="italic">Copla, ideología y poder.</title>
               Dykinson, Madrid (2020): 127-140.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="delbosquegonzalez2012" label="Del Bosque González et al., 2012"> Del Bosque González, I., Fernández Freire, C., Martín-Forero
               Morente, L. and Pérez Asensio, E. <title rend="italic">Los Sistemas de Información Geográfica y la
               Investigación en Ciencias Humanas y Sociales.</title> Madrid, <title rend="italic">CECEL-CSIC</title>
               (2012).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="delbosquegonzalez2020" label="Del Bosque González, 2020"> Del Bosque González, I. <title rend="quotes">Las tecnologías geomáticas en la
               investigación en ciencias humanas y sociales: Las humanidades espaciales,</title> <title rend="italic">Mapping</title>,
               29.200 (2020): 36-37. <ref
                  target="http://ojs.revistamapping.com/index.php?journal=MAPPING&amp;page=article&amp;op=view&amp;path%5B%5D=280"
                  >http://ojs.revistamapping.com/index.php?journal=MAPPING&amp;page=article&amp;op=view&amp;path%5B%5D=280</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fernandezfreire2013" label="Fernández Freire et al. 2013"> Fernández Freire, C. et al. <title rend="quotes">A cultural Heritage
               Application Schema: Achieving Interoperability of Cultural Heritage Data in INSPIRE,</title>
               <title rend="italic">International Journal of Spatial Data Infrastructures Research</title>, 8 (2013): 74-97. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="flanders2015" label="Flanders &amp; Jannidis, 2015"> Flanders, J. and Jannidis, F. <title rend="italic">Knowledge Organization and
               Data Modeling in the Humanities</title> (2015) <ref
                  target="http://www.wwp.northeastern.edu/outreach/conference/kodm2012/flanders_jannidis_datamodeling.pdf"
                  >http://www.wwp.northeastern.edu/outreach/conference/kodm2012/flanders_jannidis_datamodeling.pdf</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hayashi2001" label="Hayashi &amp; Hatton, 2001"> Hayashi L. and Hatton J. <title rend="quotes">Combining UML, XML and Relational
               Database Technologies,</title> <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the IRCS Workshop on Linguistic Databases</title>.
               University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia (2001).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hermidajimenez2018" label="Hermida Jiménez et al, 2018"> Hermida Jiménez, N., Fernández Freire, C., Martín-Forero
               Morente, L., and Del Bosque González, I. <title rend="quotes">IMAGO ORBIS: La Infraestructura de Datos de
               Investigación en Ciencias Sociales y Humanidades Espaciales del CSIC.</title> Paper presented
               at the <title rend="italic">IX Jornadas Ibéricas de la Infraestructuras de Datos Espaciales</title> (JIIDE). Menorca,
               España (2018) <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/10261/171823"
                  >http://hdl.handle.net/10261/171823</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jannidis2013" label="Jannidis &amp; Flanders, 2013"> Jannidis, F. and Flanders. J. <title rend="quotes">A Concept of Data
               Modeling for the Humanities.</title> Paper presented at <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities conference</title>, Lincoln,
               NE (2013), <ref target="http://dh2013.unl.edu/abstracts/ab-313.html"
                  >http://dh2013.unl.edu/abstracts/ab-313.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kimber2000" label="Kimber, 2000"> Kimber, W. E. <title rend="quotes">Using UML to define XML Document Types,</title> <title rend="italic">Markup languages:
               Theory &amp; Practice</title>, 2.3 (2000): 295-320. <ref
                  target="http://xml.coverpages.org/kimberUML-dtds20000115.pdf"
                  >http://xml.coverpages.org/kimberUML-dtds20000115.pdf</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="luzzi2012" label="Luzzi, 2012"> Luzzi, D. <title rend="quotes">Reperio 2014. A collaborative knowledge environment for Digital
               Humanities.</title> In C. Mills, M. Pidd and E. Ward. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Digital Humanities
               Congress</title> 2012. <title rend="italic">Studies in the Digital Humanities</title>. HRI Online Publications, Sheffield
               (2012) <ref target="https://www.hrionline.ac.uk/openbook/chapter/dhc2012-luzzi"
                  >https://www.hrionline.ac.uk/openbook/chapter/dhc2012-luzzi</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="manso1993" label="Manso 1993"> Manso, C. <title rend="italic"><title rend="quotes">La Argentina</title> fue Antonia Mercé,</title> Buenos Aires, Debate (1993). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="murgacastro2012" label="Murga Castro 2012">  Murga Castro, I. <title rend="italic">Pintura en danza. Los artistas españoles y el
               ballet.</title> Editorial CSIC, Madrid (2012).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="murgacastro2017a" label="Murga Castro 2017a"> Murga Castro, I. <title rend="italic">Escenografía de la danza en la Edad de Plata,</title> 2nd
               edition. Editorial CSIC, Madrid (2017). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="murgacastro2017b" label="Murga Castro 2017b"> Murga Castro, I. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Poetas del cuerpo. La danza de la Edad de
               Plata,</title> Madrid, Residencia de Estudiantes (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="murgacastro2019" label="Murga Castro 2019"> Murga Castro, I. <title rend="quotes">Embodying Spanishness: La Argentina and her
               Ballets Espagnols,</title> <title rend="italic">Conversations Across the Field of Dance
                  Studies</title>, (ed. A. Sethi and T. Sebro), xxxix (2019): 12-17.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="murgacastro2021" label="Murga Castro 2021"> Murga Castro, I. (dir.) <title rend='italic'>Antonia Mercé, la Argentina. Epistolario
               (1915-1936),</title> Madrid, Centro de Documentación de las Artes Escénicas y de la Música
               (2021). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="portela2015" label="Portela &amp; Rito Silva, 2015"> Portela M. and Rito Silva, A. <title rend="quotes">A model for a virtual
               LdoD,</title> <title rend="italic">Lit Linguist Computing</title>, 30.3 (2015): 354-370. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqu004">https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqu004</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rizzo2018" label="Rizzo et al, 2018"> Rizzo, A. et al. <title rend="quotes">WhoLoDance. Whole-body Interaction Learning for
               Dance Education.</title> In A. Antoniou and M. Wallace, (eds). <title rend="italic">Cultural Informatics</title>. <title rend="italic">CEUR
               Workshops Proceedings</title>, 2235 (2018): 41-50. <ref target="http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2235/"
                  >http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2235/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rodrigo1990" label="Rodrigo 1990"> Rodrigo, A. <title rend="quotes">Antonia Mercé <title rend="italic">Argentina</title>. El genio del
               baile español,</title> <title rend="italic">Cuadernos hispanoamericanos</title>, 484 (1990). 7-28. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schraibman2016" label="Schraibman, Siemens &amp; Unsworth, 2016"> Schraibman, S., Siemens, R. and Unsworth,
               John. <title rend="italic">A new companion to Digital Humanities.</title> Hoboken, New Jersey, John Wiley &amp; Sons,
               (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="teehan2010" label="Teehan &amp; Keating, 2010"> Teehan, A. and Keating, J. G. <title rend="quotes">Appropiate Use Case
               modelling for humanities documents,</title> <title rend="italic">Lit Linguist Computing</title>, 25.4 (2010): 381-391. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqq026">https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqq026</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vvaa2016" label="VVAA 2016"> VVAA, 2016. <title rend="quotes">Interactive Augmented Reality for Dance,</title> in F. Pachet, A. Cardoso, V. Corruble and F. Ghedini, eds. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Seventh International Conference on Computational Creativity</title>. Paris, France, June 27 – July 1, 2016. Sony CSL, Paris, 396-403. <ref target="https://www.computationalcreativity.net/iccc2016/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Interactive-Augmented-Reality-for-Dance.pdf">https://www.computationalcreativity.net/iccc2016/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Interactive-Augmented-Reality-for-Dance.pdf</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vvaa2018" label="VVAA 2018"> VVAA, 2018. <title rend="quotes">WhoLoDance. Whole-body Interaction Learning for Dance Education</title> in A. Antoniou and M. Wallace, eds. <title rend="italic">Cultural Informatics</title>. CEUR Workshops Proceedings, 2235, 41-50. <ref target="http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2235/">http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2235/</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wilkinson2016" label="Wilkinson et al, 2016"> Wilkinson, M., Dumontier, M., Aalbersberg, I. et al. <title rend="quotes">The FAIR
               Guiding Principles for scientific data management and stewardship,</title> <title rend="italic">Sci Data</title> 3, 160018.
               (2016) <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18</ref>
               <bibl xml:id="gomez2022" label="Gómez Cifuentes 2022"> Gómez Cifuentes, B. <title rend="quotes">Dance Studies and Digital Humanities: On Tour with Antonia Mercé La Argentina’s Ballets Espagnols (1927–1929),</title> in D. Romero López and J. Zamostny (eds), <title rend="italic">Towards the Digital Cultural History of the Other Silver Age Spain</title>. Berlin, Peter Lang (2022), 171-187.</bibl>
            </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
