<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Towards a Seamful Design of Networked Knowledge: Practical
                    Pedagogies in Collaborative Teams</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Aaron <dhq:family>Mauro</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Penn State Behrend</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>mauro@psu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Dr. Aaron Mauro is Assistant Professor of Digital Humanities and English
                            at Penn State Behrend. He is the director of the Penn State Digital
                            Humanities Lab and teaches on topics relating to digital culture,
                            computational text analysis, and scholarly communication. His articles
                            on U.S. literature and culture have appeared in Modern Fiction Studies,
                            Mosaic, and Symploke among others. He has also published on issues
                            relating to digital humanities in both Digital Studies and Digital
                            Humanities Quarterly.
                            <!-- writing, content analysis, project management, annotation, cleanup,
                            editing, commenting, designing, programming, web development, and
                            collaboration--></p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Daniel <dhq:family>Powell</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>daniel.j.powell@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>writing, content analysis, project management, annotation, cleanup,
                            editing, commenting, community building, and collaboration</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Sarah <dhq:family>Potvin</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Texas A&amp;M University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>spotvin@library.tamu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>discovering, gathering, writing, cleanup, editing, theorizing,
                            collaboration, commenting, and contextualizing</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Jacob <dhq:family>Heil</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>The Five Colleges of Ohio</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>jheil@wooster.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>writing, annotation, cleanup, editing, contextualizing, commenting, and
                            collaboration</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Eric <dhq:family>Dye</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Penn State Behrend</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>etdye6152@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Eric Dye is a photographer, graphics designer, and journalist. While
                            pursuing liberal studies at Penn State Behrend, he also worked at The
                            Behrend Beacon as the Creative Director and Opinion Editor. He is
                            currently a Projectionist at the Tom Ridge Environmental Center in Erie,
                            Pennsylvania.
                            <!--writing, imaging, content analysis, theorizing, and collaboration--></p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Bridget <dhq:family>Jenkins</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Penn State Behrend</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>bridgetj12@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Bridget Jenkins graduated from Penn State Behrend with a BA in English
                            and Professional Writing major in the spring of 2016. She also served as
                            the Managing Editor at her college newspaper, The Behrend Beacon. She is
                            currently a Technical Recruiter for All Lines Technology in West Palm
                            Beach, Florida.
                            <!--writing, content analysis, theorizing, and collaboration--></p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Dene <dhq:family>Grigar</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Washington State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>dgrigar@vancouver.wsu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>writing, content analysis, annotation, cleanup, editing, commenting,
                            teaching, and collaboration</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000322</idno>
                <idno type="volume">011<!-- volume number, with leading zeroes: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue">3<!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date when="2017-10-02">02 October 2017</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>digital pedagogy</item>
                        <item>collaboration</item>
                        <item>ethics</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="DD" when="2017-07-06">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>Collaboration is an ethically charged relationship that challenges traditional
                    modes of authorship attribution, institutional norms, and expectations of
                    teaching and learning. A careful reflection on the needs and expectations of
                    project participants demands an exposure of the seams and social dynamics
                    inherent in research-driven relationships. In this paper, we ask: How does
                    integrating digital scholarship into undergraduate pedagogy challenge systems of
                    evaluation and credit and affect collaboration in research environments tuned to
                    promotion and tenure? Emerging from our participation in the Scholarly
                    Communication Institute (2015) in the Research Triangle of North Carolina, this
                    article presents the findings of a team tasked with evaluating best practices
                    and better understanding how authorship and contributorship models emerge in
                    heterogeneous teams of students, faculty, staff, #alt-ac roles, librarians,
                    programmers, and community partners.<note>We have used the Taxonomy of Digital
                        Research Activities in the Humanities (TaDiRAH) to describe our
                        contributions to this article. Please find the full reference of activities
                        here: <ref target="https://github.com/dhtaxonomy/TaDiRAH/blob/master/reference/activities.md">https://github.com/dhtaxonomy/TaDiRAH/blob/master/reference/activities.md</ref>
                        This taxonomy was brought to our collective attention at the 2015 Scholarly
                        Communication Institute by the <title rend="quotes">Modeling contributorship
                            with TaDiRAH</title> team, comprised of Cassidy Sugimoto, J. Britt
                        Holbrook, Korey Jackson, Zach Coble, April Hathcock, and Micah
                        Vandegrift.</note></p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Ethics and best practices of collobaration in dh pedagogy</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>Digital scholarship is often a deeply collaborative and networked enterprise, one
                which involves multiple practitioners from a variety of academic, #altac, and
                non-academic contexts. This kind of socially oriented knowledge creation emerges
                from a community of practice that moves fluidly between curricular experiences and
                co-curricular research experiences, often hosted in DH labs, libraries, and
                    centers.<note> In <title rend="italic">Communities of Practice: Learning,
                        Meaning, and Identity</title>, Etienne Wenger posits a social theory of
                    learning advanced by the formation of communities of practice. Wegner argues for
                        <q>three dimensions of the relation by which practice is the source of
                        coherence of a community</q>: <q>mutual engagement… a joint enterprise … a
                        shared repertoire.</q>
                    <ptr target="#wenger1998"/></note> Neither formalised evaluative structures nor
                socio-cultural understandings of value and credit have kept pace with disciplinary
                and technological change in the humanities. In this context, scholarly work involves
                a mesh of potentially uneven relationships between many knowledge stakeholders and
                researchers with a range of technical capabilities. For example, student labor is
                paired awkwardly with faculty promotion and tenure, which is driven by faculty
                members’ ability to manage and mobilize large heterogeneous teams of researchers at
                all levels within the academic community. Credit, promotion, funding, and
                credentialing are more complex topics than ever, yet many individuals and
                institutions rely on often outdated structures to assess the value and insights made
                by these networked teams.</p>
            <p>Collaborative digital humanities projects present ethically charged relationships
                among non-tenure line and tenure line faculty, graduate and undergraduate students,
                staff, and community stakeholders. Spencer D. C. Keralis’s blog post <title rend="quotes">Milking the Deficit Internship</title> describes the power dynamic
                in this way: <cit>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#keralis2016">Student labor in the classroom is never not coerced</quote>
                    <ptr target="#keralis2016"/>
                </cit>. A range of knowledge stakeholders are now able to rethink the hierarchies
                imposed by academic rank and hollow notions of prestige by forming systems that
                emerge from new tools and methods. We believe this moment will allow humanities
                scholars to shape a collaborative practice by balancing pedagogy and labor through
                increased data collection within teams. </p>
            <p>We have determined that collaboration should be locally-determined,
                    <emph>seamfully</emph> designed, and mutually productive, regardless of standing
                within or without academic institutions; there must be an intentional ethics that is
                both transparent and adaptive to the needs of the team. We wish to expose the seams
                that knit technological infrastructure and academic assessment for both faculty and
                students working on DH projects. In doing so, we borrow language from Matt Ratto’s
                article <title rend="quotes">Ethics of Seamless Infrastructures</title> to think
                critically about our use of technology in humanities scholarship and our
                institutionalization of mentorship and credit allocation <ptr target="#ratto2007"/>.
                In an effort to best describe these relationships, we present a project-based
                pedagogy that realigns academic hierarchies of prestige and oversight and reflects
                the realities of scholarly labor: we suggest that, in the formation of collaborative
                teams, digital humanists must recognize and explicitly foreground the constraints,
                priorities, and shapes of our professional and institutional positions in order to
                affect a purposeful pedagogy aligned with research. We will present several case
                studies that cross between undergraduate and graduate pedagogies, public engagement,
                business partnerships, scholarly community formation, and #alt-ac roles toward a
                heterogeneous field of contributorship. We present, in other words, a species of
                networked knowledge in practice. Our objective is to link discussions of what we
                have come to call <soCalled>social knowledge creation</soCalled> with undergraduate
                education to produce new ways of measuring, evaluating, and validating digital
                    scholarship.<note> We have worked to extend John Maxwell’s definition of
                        <soCalled>open scholarship</soCalled> in <title rend="quotes">Beyond Open
                        Access to Open Content</title> to imagine open access publishing alongside
                    social media and collaborative practices <ptr target="#maxwell2015"/>.</note></p>
            <div>
                <head>Students Rethought</head>
                <p>Undergraduate digital scholarship in its current form can be a collaborative and
                    networked enterprise that involves multiple practitioners from a variety of
                    academic contexts. However, no great revolution in pedagogical practice is
                    needed; the tools and methods are before us. Socially oriented projects and
                    platforms within DH are evidence of this shift: Day of DH, Digital Humanities
                    Now, HASTAC, CenterNet, NINES, and DHSI are just a small sampling of community
                    minded approaches in DH. Efforts like these have sought to value social
                    knowledge creation by working to set the conditions for new discoveries in an
                    online social space.</p>
                <p>Community formation lies at the base of our model, and successful scholarly
                    communities grow best when fostered by effective mentorship and collaboration.
                    Beyond Marc Prensky’s much popularized but widely discredited description of
                    students as <soCalled>digital natives,</soCalled> faculty must be ready to link
                    interpretative priorities with employability and an enduring value of education
                    through transferable, durable, and authentic skills <ptr target="#prensky2001"/>.<note> Even as the term <soCalled>digital native</soCalled> became
                        anchored in common terminology, contemporary criticism of the coining
                        remains as clear and important then as now: Timothy VanSlyke’s <title rend="quotes">Some Thoughts from the Generation Gap</title> in <title rend="italic">The Technology Source</title> (2003) offers an even handed
                        rebuttal to the initial enthusiasm for the term. Somewhat tellingly, the
                        conversation about the term occurred largely in blogs, like that of Henry
                        Jenkins. His post <title rend="quotes">Reconsidering Digital Natives</title>
                        (2007), on his blog <title rend="italic">Confessions of an Aca-fan</title>,
                        does a remarkable job of laying bare the assumptions that Prensky uses to
                        form his rough analogy between digital nativists and immigrants. By 2011,
                        Michael Thomas was able to edit an anthology tasked with <title rend="italic">Deconstructing Digital Natives</title>. The term had
                        become myth and now required a more thorough rereading as a corrective to
                        the popular uptake of the term. </note> The canon and critical thinking
                    skills once served this language of extensibility in education. Students must be
                    ready to work alongside faculty and staff; in so doing, they undoubtedly benefit
                    from discipline-specific expertise and embrace methods and skills that may not
                    be validated by the very institution that grants their degrees. Therefore, the
                    connection between technology and content must not be missed. There must be an
                    integral and functional connection between the technology, teaching, and team
                    integration. In <title rend="quotes">Digital Pedagogy Unplugged</title>, Paul
                    Fyfe recounts his surprise upon learning that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#fyfe2011">Jerome McGann does not especially like
                            computers</quote>
                        <ptr target="#fyfe2011" loc="1"/>
                    </cit>. The affordances of a multimedia hypertext were simply required to build
                    the Rossetti Archive; the ability to set text and image in a discoverable
                    interface was made possible by the internet. There is an emerging tension
                    between research-specific computing needs and, as Fyfe puts it, <q>opening those
                        projects to questions he had yet to imagine</q> through computing <ptr target="#fyfe2011" loc="1"/>. The symbiotic relationship between
                    intellectual curiosity and skills-based training in the humanities requires a
                    community of concerns bound by an evolving culture of exploration and
                    experimentation through method. This is a dialogue that should occur between
                    faculty, staff, and students in an ongoing basis during the development and
                    dissemination of in-process scholarly work. In a curricular context, this
                    interdependent relationship between student and instructor means that curricular
                    models aimed at including DH methods may not keep perfect pace with the
                    development of consumer products, technical standards, or open source projects.
                    Providing access to long lasting technical standards and active communities
                    supporting open source technologies that will remain after graduation must be
                    the goal of our training.<note> Miriam Posner shares a similar sentiment in a
                        blog post entitled, <title rend="quotes"><ref target="http://miriamposner.com/blog/money-and-time/">Money and
                                Time</ref></title>: <q>We want to believe that we can be agile and
                            innovative, like Silicon Valley says it is, by making DH run with
                            short-term grants, app contests, and temporary labor. We want to have a
                            sort of Uber-style sharing economy for DH-research. But this is not how
                            one supports careful, enduring scholarship and teaching.</q>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Therefore, unlike a more global technical standard, we find that collaborative
                    models must be locally determined and agreed upon by local partners, often in an
                    ad hoc way. Bethany Nowviskie has described the <soCalled>human
                        factors</soCalled> of our <soCalled>scholarly machine</soCalled> and how,
                    even as we conceive of research in the humanities as operating at a great scale,
                    the collaborations themselves unfold on a closer, human scale: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#nowviskie2012">Despite all the focus on cyberinfrastructure and
                            scholarly workflows, we’re fashioning ever closer, more intimate and
                            personalized systems of production</quote>
                        <ptr target="#nowviskie2012"/>
                    </cit>. The argument for a greater appreciation of the human scale of research
                    and teaching is the basis for an ethics of collaboration and validating digital
                    scholarship. In this context, Nowviskie’s reminder of human scale of research
                    and teaching also highlights a fundamental inconsistency within university
                    structures, for both faculty and students, that are often more interested in
                    statistical metrics of success. </p>
                <p>For example, large archival and digitization projects across a range of
                    disciplines have outstripped the constraints of traditional tenure and promotion
                    timelines. Two notable examples of this disjunction between project development
                    and university standards could include The Map of Early Modern London (<ref target="http://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/">http://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/</ref>),
                    which has been in development for over 10 years, and The Orlando Project (<ref target="http://www.artsrn.ualberta.ca/orlando/">http://www.artsrn.ualberta.ca/orlando/</ref>), which has been in
                    development for over 20 years. In <title rend="quotes">Assessing the Future
                        Landscape of Scholarly Communication</title>, a report by The Center for
                    Studies in Higher Education, the authors seek to describe the pressures facing
                    faculty in collaborative digitally oriented teams and <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#harley2010">to understand the needs and practices of faculty for
                            in-progress scholarly communication</quote>
                        <ptr target="#harley2010" loc="2"/>
                    </cit>. Due to the increased time and collaboration required to create large
                    scale digital projects and the likelihood that these efforts may grow without
                    being <soCalled>finished,</soCalled> scholarly communication that occurs
                    in-progress is indeed becoming more prominent and bucks the traditional view
                    that knowledge is created when a monograph is printed and bound.<note>
                        <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Studies/Le champ numérique</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title>, and <title rend="italic">DH
                            Commons</title> all accept research that is in-progress. The expectation
                        of a completed project, as one would expect a completed and static
                        monograph, is simply not possible. Susan Brown et al., in <title rend="quotes">Published Yet Never Done,</title> describes this reality
                        in relation to the long development and evolution of the Orlando Project
                            <ptr target="#brown2009"/>.</note> The report surveys a handful of
                    disciplines–archaeology, astrophysics, biology, economics, history, music, and
                    political science–with a view to understanding the role of technology in
                    collaborative research and in-progress scholarly communication. The core concern
                    for the historians interviewed concerned the <q>crisis in monographic
                        publication,</q> which stems from both <q>cutting back the number of
                        books</q> published by high quality presses and the <q>glut of books</q>
                    produced by low market publishers in an attempt to satiate the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#harley2010">number of books required for advancement at competitive
                            universities</quote>
                        <ptr target="#harley2010" loc="436"/>
                    </cit>. In all of this, the report recognizes that university libraries, facing
                    squeezed budgets, are incapable of purchasing these monographs, which further
                    deflates demand. In <title rend="italic">Open Access</title>, Peter Suber has
                    even claimed that the rapid inflation of science based journal subscriptions has
                    caused a knock-on effect in humanities based monograph publishing because
                    university libraries are forced to maintain access to online subscriptions while
                    eroding the physical collection of books housed on campus <ptr target="#suber2012" loc="32"/>. The answer offered by the authors of the
                    report is in the successful collaborations revolving around <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#harley2010">online databases of archival materials or data sets
                            built collaboratively by scholars</quote>
                        <ptr target="#harley2010" loc="471"/>
                    </cit>. The crisis in scholarly publishing has been well documented in other
                        venues,<note> This is a well worn genre within scholarly communication, but
                        a range of concerns persist, from tenure and promotion committees,
                        institutional reform, and the economics of publishing: Jennifer Wolfe
                        Thompson’s <title rend="quotes">The Death of the Scholarly Monograph in the
                            Humanities? Citation Patterns in Literary Scholarship</title> details
                        the relationship between publications through tenure and promotion processes
                        in particular <ptr target="#thompson2007"/>, Blaise Cronin and Kathryn La
                        Barre’s <title rend="quotes">Mickey Mouse and Milton: book publishing in the
                            humanities</title>” has offered an analysis of institutional language
                        supporting the monograph <ptr target="#cronin2004"/>, and Carlos J. Alonso
                        et al., in a proceedings published by the American Council of Learned
                        societies, <title rend="quotes">Crises and Opportunities: The Futures of
                            Scholarly Publishing,</title> describe the problem as both an issue of
                        university self-governance, peer review, and economic factors <ptr target="#alonso2003"/>. </note> but the response to these pressures has
                    generated, by necessity, informal collaborations that have placed pressure on
                    students, staff, community partners, and other knowledge stakeholders. </p>
                <p> By describing some of the pressures facing researchers, we have begun with a
                    very pragmatic, perhaps pessimistic, view of what David Berry called the
                        <soCalled>computational turn</soCalled> across disciplines, wherein <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#berry2011">technologies [have shifted] the critical ground of
                            their concepts and theories</quote>
                        <ptr target="#berry2011" loc="11"/>
                    </cit>. Berry acknowledges that <q>... with card indexes dying a slow and
                        certain death… there remain few outputs for the non-digital scholar to
                        undertake research in the modern university,</q> but he extends the
                    consequences of this reality to the need to reimagine pedagogy and the social
                    function of a humanities education. No longer are the humanities tasked with
                    training students for civil participation through a national canon: students, he
                    suggests, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#berry2011">would need to be rethought</quote>
                        <ptr target="#berry2011" loc="6"/>
                    </cit>. Berry imagines a radical, deeply collaborative recentering that <q>...
                        would change our understanding of knowledge, wisdom and intelligence
                        itself,</q> a shift to <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#berry2011">... a method of thinking with eyes and screen</quote>
                        <ptr target="#berry2011" loc="10"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>In keeping with Berry’s vision of a <soCalled>collective intellect</soCalled>
                    spurred by <q>... a society or association of actors who can think critically
                        together, mediated through technology,</q> the academy must rethink both
                    undergraduate and graduate students through the lens of a technologically
                    literate, socially participatory community. By validating digital scholarship
                    throughout the university, all research participants by better conceptualize how
                    pedagogy, labor, and contributorship overlap. Likewise, students must reimagine
                    their relationships and expectations for training, professionalization, and
                    future employment. The social aspect of DH becomes the basis for a community of
                    practice that respects the realities of international, networked, and hybrid
                    identities and cultures. Akin to the communities of practitioners that gather
                    online to support open source projects, DH has the potential to become a
                    community of lifelong learning for our students as participation in the
                    workforce will require near perpetual retraining. We are proposing a third space
                    within the university that is both beyond and between the experiences of
                    teaching and research. Understanding the cultural and social realities of online
                    community formation is a relatively new social function of the humanities, and
                    our collaborative work must similarly engage with these realities that face our
                    students, their employers, and the university itself.</p>
                <p>Students require expertise that is adaptable, durable, and authentic.
                    Non-curricular experiences must thereby promote experimentation and open ended
                    play with technology. Skills acquisition should be part of a student’s outlook
                    toward any technical or cultural problem. Humanities students who embrace this
                    sensibility will, however, face an additional set of problems. The heterogeneous
                    nature of collaborative groups in the humanities means that competing values,
                    concerns, and responsibilities can result in tensions and misunderstandings
                    between Primary Investigators and funders, collaborating faculty and staff,
                    graduate and undergraduate students, and knowledge stakeholders and community
                    partners. Sheila Cavanagh observes in her recent article, <title rend="quotes">Living in a Digital World: Rethinking Peer Review, Collaboration, and Open
                        Access</title>, that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#cavanagh2012">collaborative work has a different history in the
                            humanities than in the sciences and conventional reward structures in
                            humanistic disciplines do not always easily accommodate mutual
                            efforts</quote>
                        <ptr target="#cavanagh2012"/>
                    </cit>. Similarly, Amy E. Earhart cautions us against <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#earhart2015">[romanticizing] the lab. Science labs emphasize
                            collaboration, but hierarchies may be apparent</quote>
                        <ptr target="#earhart2015" loc="393"/>
                    </cit>. Social knowledge creation may include geographically disparate
                    contributors or clusters coming together through social collaboration
                        platforms.<note> The drafting of this article was made possible by the Slack
                        platform. However, members of this team have used Yammer and Basecamp to
                        similar success in linking teams through the logic and interface of social
                        media. </note> The recent work by the digital humanities program at UCLA to
                    standardize student collaborator rights has helped to clarify the ethical
                    imperative for faculty who may be forced by the pressures of tenure and
                    promotion to emphasize scholarly output at the expense of sound pedagogy. Their
                        <title rend="quotes">Student Collaborators’ Bill of Rights</title> maintains
                    that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#dipressind">[c]ollaborations between students and more experienced
                            digital humanities practitioners should benefit everyone</quote>
                        <ptr target="#dipressind"/>
                    </cit>. Similarly, the efforts of the Modern Language Association (MLA) gesture
                    toward a bridge between the concerns of faculty with those of students working
                    in a research context. The <ref target="https://www.mla.org/About-Us/Governance/Committees/Committee-Listings/Professional-Issues/Committee-on-Information-Technology/Guidelines-for-Evaluating-Work-in-Digital-Humanities-and-Digital-Media">MLA’s Guidelines for Evaluating Work in Digital Humanities and Digital
                        Media</ref> (2012) recognises, for example, that digital scholarly
                    practitioners <q>engage in collaborative work</q> far more often than their
                    non-digital counterpart but stops short of recommending specific frameworks of
                    evaluation and peer review. Compounding the difficulties inherent in formally
                    evaluating digital research is the collaborative involvement of teaching
                    faculty, students, graduate researchers, cultural heritage professionals, etc.
                    The difficulties evaluators face is not limited to media type or form–archives,
                    blog posts, databases, and code bases are all up for consideration here–but also
                    encompasses disciplinary norms and shared authorship practices. Through the lens
                    of media and collaboration, we work to discuss and share guidelines that address
                    credit, mentorship frameworks, and scholarly merit for digital work in a
                    responsible way.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Non-mechanical Contributors</head>
                <p>Ethically-framed interventions have long been part and parcel of theorized
                    pedagogies. We position bell hooks’ Teaching to Transgress as a model for
                    classroom based community formation that negotiates class, race, and gender in
                    an inclusive and productive way <ptr target="#hooks1994"/>. Our goal is to
                    extend this kind of <soCalled>liberated classroom,</soCalled> as hooks describes
                    it, into the research space and into the public space. Social relationships
                    forged beyond the classroom have guided pedagogies that carry the structural
                    oppressions from society into the classroom and, in our current concerns,
                    collaborative teams. As Brett Hirsch puts it in the introduction to <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Pedagogy</title>,
                        <soCalled>bracketing</soCalled> teaching away from research is particularly
                    dangerous <ptr target="#hirsch2012" loc="5"/>. Whether we are thinking about
                    tenure and promotion, course design, research activities, or the critical
                    discussion of pedagogy or experimental design, we risk marginalizing digital
                    humanities by not fully integrating our research practice within our teaching.
                    Perhaps more subtly, we risk transferring the hierarchy between student and
                    instructor by artificially partitioning teaching from research. Paulo Freire
                    remains instructive on this point: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#freire2005">The pedagogy of the oppressed, as a humanist and
                            libertarian pedagogy, has two distinct stages. In the first, the
                            oppressed unveil the world of oppression and through the praxis commit
                            themselves to its transformation. In the second stage, in which the
                            reality of oppression has already been transformed, this pedagogy ceases
                            to belong to the oppressed and becomes a pedagogy of all people in the
                            process of permanent liberation.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#freire2005" loc="55"/>
                    </cit> We argue that theoretically informed interventions remain the source of
                    digital humanities work, but digital humanities must structure collaborative
                    work to reflect that ethics in a broader pedagogy. The slippage and breadth of
                    collective pronouns is a symptom of this broader problem of credit allocation.
                    As faculty, we must respect and include their behaviors, their view of the
                    world, and their own ethics. As students, we must work to liberate our education
                    from antiquated economic and institutional structures; we must liberate our
                    instructors from paper-based assessment that attempts to fix academic output as
                    a single assignment rather than a dynamic development process; by embracing a
                    collaborative, project based pedagogy, we must reject the simplistic
                            <q><soCalled>banking</soCalled> concept of education</q> that presumes
                    education is deposited in the heads of students from a teacher <ptr target="#freire2005" loc="72"/>; we must liberate ourselves from traditional
                    and conservative models of education that are predicated on rarified access to
                    resources and information. The banking concept of education is invalidated by
                    the Open Access model that makes content free. When paired with similar Open
                    Source and Open Data movements, access to open standards and data allows
                    non-traditional scholars to participate like never before. As Freire reminds us,
                    true liberation comes when the oppressors as well as the oppressed are liberated
                    from the structural inequalities that propagate and reward hierarchies of
                    control and dominance. Teaching our students to build digital projects will
                    validate digital scholarship for faculty and staff as well. Crossing between
                    these spaces should not carry with it the hierarchies of the university's own
                    evaluative procedures.</p>
                <p>Our ethics is split along the same discursive lines that divides the very term
                    digital humanities. Between the computational tools and the human understanding
                    of culture, there lies a split between the mechanical and the human that
                    animates our collaborative relationships. The UCLA <title rend="quotes">Student
                        Collaborators’ Bill of Rights</title> defines the necessity to pay students
                    for their work, arguing that an unpaid internship model should not merely
                    exchange experience or education for labor.<note> Sean Michael Morris and Jesse
                        Stommel have also drafted a <title rend="quotes">Bill of Rights and
                            Principles for Learning in the Digital Age</title> that works to
                        enshrine the quality and care of face-to-face education in an online
                        environment like MOOCs. While this Bill of Rights is critical for students
                        and faculty to enshrine pedagogical values like openness and inclusivity in
                        an online environment, this document does not focus directly on the
                        collaborative project based methods of many digital humanities. We also are
                        not concerned with politically motivated <soCalled>academic bills of
                            rights</soCalled> that seek <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#academicbill">to end the political abuse of the university and to
                                restore integrity to the academic mission as a disinterested pursuit
                                of knowledge</quote>
                            <ptr target="#academicbill"/>
                        </cit>. These rights are promoted by the David Horowitz Freedom Center, a
                        conservative think tank, which seeks to depoliticize education with the goal
                        of promoting racist, classist, and sexist policies <ptr target="#davidhorowitz"/>. We highlight these viewpoints to express how
                        politicised the <soCalled>rights</soCalled> of students has become and how
                        online environments are proving to be a point of contention from several
                        perspectives.</note> Work and education cannot enter into an economics of
                    exchange or gift because the value exchanged is simply too ephemeral, prone to
                    abuse, and reliant on hierarchies of authority between faculty, students, and
                    staff that are symptomatic of the old academy. The UCLA Bill of Rights explains
                    this division with a pragmatic sensibility: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#dipressind">If students have made substantive (i.e.,
                            non-mechanical) contributions to the project, their names should appear
                            on the project as collaborators, and they should be acknowledged in
                            subsequent publications that stem from the project</quote>
                        <ptr target="#dipressind"/>
                    </cit>. Student labor and education should not become merely an extension of the
                    computational tools researchers are taking up. Large scale XML/TEI projects may
                    well be the most susceptible research method because of the labor required. The
                    extensibility of the language may become extended uncomfortably into our
                    pedagogy; the structural demands of encoding text re-encodes personal
                    relationships and builds a human ethics through the demands of the machine.
                    Jaron Lanier’s <title rend="italic">You are Not a Gadget</title> does well to
                    describe how <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#lanier2010">the most important thing about technology is how it
                            changes people</quote>
                        <ptr target="#lanier2010" loc="4"/>
                    </cit>. While his argument is dystopian in tone and scope, Lanier rightly argues
                    that people sacrifice some portion of their intellect and their very humanity to
                    serve the limitations of computing. Teachers, as well as students, are
                    susceptible to the extensibility of this ethic. Digital humanities runs the
                    risks of translating the structural logic of the machine onto the human
                    experience of our students. People become the mere workings of the machines now
                    used for analysis and knowledge generation. For this reason, we suggest that
                    contributorship must be modeled on conditions and ethics that are inherited from
                    the humanities. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Narrative / History / Taxonomy</head>
                <p>We must be ready to radically rethink authorship attribution through a more
                    narrative style of contributorship. Models of attribution from other
                    disciplines, in which tacit rules governing order of authorship may privilege
                    the Primary Investigator as the originator of insight, signal the contributions
                    of graduate students or lab directors, or present a simple alphabetized list, do
                    not translate well into digital humanities. Insights offered by constituent
                    partners–who may include undergraduates, graduate research assistants, #altac
                    staff, librarians, computer IT professionals–are essential for the functioning
                    of digital projects for both faculty and institutions. Ideas in a multimedia
                    environment are dependent on layers of software, mentorship, and methodology.
                    The next great insight may come from a unique moment of discovery couched in
                    mentorship, direction, and dialogue. Heterogeneous collaborations within
                    academic contexts help to define the value of publishing digital projects and
                    communicating them to the public. </p>
                <p>Scholarly communication is bound up in several competing issues when done
                    collaboratively in a multimedia and multidisciplinary context. Authorship
                    occupies potentially-competing modes of credit and accountability. In
                    recognition of this tension, collaboration allows project contributors with
                    diverse expertise to define their roles and to apportion mutually-beneficial
                    responsibility. There are several models to document and attribute diverse
                    contributions made in a heterogeneous team. TaDiRAH and CrediT are two of the
                    most commonly discussed currently in digital humanities and scholarly
                        communication,<note> The CrediT project is an activity of Consortia
                        Advancing Standards in Research Administration Information (<ref target="http://casrai.org/CRediT">http://casrai.org/CRediT</ref>), and
                        TaDiRAH is a project initiated by DARIAH (<ref target="https://github.com/dhtaxonomy/TaDiRAH">https://github.com/dhtaxonomy/TaDiRAH</ref>).</note> though it is
                    unclear just how often these taxonomies are employed (Brand). TaDiRAH cites the
                    Digital Research Infrastructure for Arts and Humanities (DARIAH) and The Digital
                    Research Tools project (DiRT) as employing the framework. Collaboration disrupts
                    existing models of authorship and attribution. Greater transparency is possible
                    with these taxonomies; however, collaborative teams evolve as expertise
                    increases and roles shift as students or faculty come in and out of the project.
                    Activity definitions, like those used by <ref target="https://github.com/dhtaxonomy/TaDiRAH/blob/master/reference/activities.md">TaDiRAH</ref> represent just one side of the story that includes
                    contributor narrative statements and historical perspectives of the evolution of
                    roles as the overlap and shift over time. The humanities-specific logic of
                    history and narrative come to define our model.</p>
                <p>As we discussed at the opening, our perspective emerged during our participation
                    in the Mellon-funded Scholarly Communication Institute (SCI) hosted by the
                    Research Triangle of North Carolina from the 11th to the 15th of October, 2015.
                    Our discussions during this week centered on digital humanities work as a
                    community of practice, wherein the community is formed by the very methods and
                    techniques employed. TaDIRAH includes <soCalled>community_building</soCalled>
                    and <soCalled>teaching_and_learning</soCalled> in the taxonomy of activities,
                    but these roles do not map easily to student participation and define what
                    constitutes these acts. During the week at SCI, we were engaged on multiple
                    levels of community building and teaching and learning, but these activities
                    were difficult to capture in the current taxonomies. We turned to building a
                    timeline with Timeline.js to show how our thought evolved. We built a <ref target="http://www.personal.psu.edu/amm81/sci">project site</ref> to capture
                    our collaboratively written white paper, which used Google Docs to shape our
                    team’s discussions. We strove to have our project site reflect the fluidity of
                    born digital content, which evinces different issues related to credit, to
                    valuing varied contributions, and the articulation of participation in our
                    thinking. The romantic ideal of the solitary genius and the writer in his garret
                    was transparent to us as we worked in a multimedia environment, rapidly picking
                    up tasks, and sharing information. The taxonomies of contributorship faded as we
                    grappled with collecting our conversation. The timeline of our thinking includes
                    tweets from group members and digital photographs of our activity, many of which
                    were taken by Eric Dye. We argue for a radical inclusiveness that recognises the
                    very real labor of contributors that may manifest in a variety of ways. This is
                    a model of digital scholarship that is interested in the big picture of academia
                    intersecting with the public and of pedagogy existing as research. Knowledge is
                    a networked thing, and conceiving of scholarship as an inherently collaborative
                    venture enriches the people and the products of any given field. Having begun
                    in-depth discussion of theoretical issues, we realised that our key insights to
                    discussions of how to evaluate digital work emerged from extensive practical
                    knowledge. To expand on those insights, we developed a number of project-based
                    case studies that highlighted the collaboration behind them. These case studies
                    might serve as models for further study to gain information on more widespread
                    practices in digital scholarship.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Layered Dependencies: DH Case Studies</head>
                <p>With a desire to identify universal bridges between disciplines, we turned to
                    narrative case studies about four projects that involved our team members in a
                    range of capacities, including as facilitator, project manager, principal
                    investigator, and student collaborator. These case studies work from the
                    understanding that a granular approach to contribution, as would be captured in
                    a metric that simply counted GitHub commits, would not appreciate the
                    contributions of individuals who may have provided a critical insight or
                    discovery that shaped the evolution of our projects. We found that historical
                    accounting of activities helped lay bare the methodological decisions of each
                    group as they evolved. Our realization in our heterogeneous group was that there
                    are layers of dependences between technology and expertise that foregrounds
                    students, staff, and faculty roles in a highly variable way. We found that a
                    mentorship model that flattened hierarchies between participants allowed for a
                    fuller sense of participation and a holistic representation of the insights
                    offered by any one individual.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>12th Street Project</head>
                    <p><ref target="https://sites.psu.edu/12thstreetproject/">The 12th Street
                            Project</ref> is a collaborative effort of the students and faculty at
                        Penn State Behrend. 12th Street emerges from three needs arising from the
                        students and faculty at the college. Hosted by the Penn State Digital
                        Humanities Lab, 12th Street collects the history, culture, and contemporary
                        voices of those living in Erie, PA. The project takes its name from an
                        industrial corridor in Erie that has been lined with factories and
                        businesses throughout the region’s history. We take 12th Street as a
                        microcosm of the social, cultural, and economic forces that have shaped the
                        region since the mid-19th century. Together we are charting the history of
                        the region in an effort to imagine its potential futures. Developed on Omeka
                        and the Neatline add-on, 12th Street is a local geographical history of the
                        region that appeals to a global audience. The campus has recently developed
                        an undergraduate major program in Digital Media, Arts, and Technology,
                        otherwise known as DIGIT. The program positions undergraduate research
                        opportunities at the core of the curriculum and necessitates open and
                        dynamic collaboration. The major is organized around four media specific
                        concentrations that include text analysis, sound design and film production,
                        data visualization, and modeling and simulation. 12th Street is capable of
                        accommodating a wide range of multimedia contributions and maintain
                        coherence through its dedication to explaining the relationship between
                        space and place as well as culture and economy. The project is intended to
                        grow organically with the interests of participating faculty and students.
                        An emphasis on creative works may emerge with the contributions of
                        participating creative writing faculty, or an emphasis on visual history may
                        develop over time with the contributions of our arts and humanities faculty
                        and students. </p>
                    <p>For example, Eric Dye’s contributed a review and analysis of the history of
                        the locomotive industry in Erie through a juxtaposition of images from the
                        past and present. Local public library archives, as well as community and
                        company materials, have become resources to help frame the cultural impacts
                        of the 1853 Erie Gauge War or more recent attempts to move the engine
                        manufacturing industry to tax and labor friendly jurisdictions. This
                        contribution also includes interviews, newspapers, maps, and economic census
                        data. By contrast, <title rend="quotes">The Masonic Temple as a Microcosm of
                            Erie History</title> is another multimedia submission that Bridget
                        Jenkins has developed. It encompasses a visual and textual report that
                        detailed how the Erie Masonic Temple’s survival and development represents a
                        template for the evolution of the city and the region. Jenkins encountered
                        difficulties in finding a relevant original documentation, so she began
                        networking outside of the library system. Eventually, she connected with an
                        individual within one of the Temple’s Masonic bodies that had collected
                        documents throughout the years in an aim to have the Temple listed as a
                        historic site. This documentation, combined with the other minimal
                        information she had scrounged from the libraries and online, provided her
                        with the foundation for her project. She then contributed photographs and a
                        personal narrative of what the building looks like today. Joining the
                        historical documents with the present conditions enabled her to explain a
                        narrative of the broader social and cultural importance of the building.
                        Because Eric came to his contributions with a pre-existing expertise in
                        photography, his methodological focus embraced photography. Jenkins came to
                        her research with a robust background in journalism and public scholarship.
                        She was able to locate unique resources by directly engaging with knowledge
                        stakeholders and current users of the space. While Dye and Jenkins worked on
                        their own component of the project, they were able to chart each other’s
                        progress on Yammer and celebrate each other’s milestones. In this way, the
                        faculty lead, Aaron Mauro, describes himself as laying out the canvas that
                        will become the big-tent of DH at the undergraduate level. Students are
                        responsible for completing projects in a fluid and additive way. They each
                        pull up poles to support the larger structure. Through their individual
                        efforts, they build a community of practice that shifts and evolves with the
                        interests of the student contributors and the skills offered by faculty
                        teaching at Behrend.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Digital Scudéry</head>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="http://digitalscholarship.ohio5.org/scudery-digital-edition/">Digital Scudéry</ref> is an interdisciplinary, interdivisional
                        collaboration at the College of Wooster that will result in digitally
                        transcribed textual surrogates for five of Madelaine de Scudéry’s late
                        seventeenth- and early eighteenth-century books. The end result of the
                        project is not conceived as a digital edition per se, but as a version of de
                        Scudéry’s <title rend="italic">Conversations</title> that students can (1)
                        read more easily than they can images of the printed books and (2) encode
                        with research-based XML tags using Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) standards.
                        The project began with a pedagogical challenge: both the seventeenth-century
                        French and the unfamiliar typography offered challenges to Laura Burch’s
                        students, the latter of which was a distraction from the pedagogical
                        efficacy of the former. By bringing this pedagogical question to Jacob Heil,
                        then The Ohio Five’s Digital Scholar, working under the auspices of an
                        Andrew W. Mellon Foundation Grant to help faculty with digital pedagogical
                        projects, Prof. Burch kicked off a process that would come to involve
                        multiple faculty, staff, and student partners.</p>
                    <p>The first phase of the project involved four students’ transcriptions of the
                        first book of de Scudéry’s <title rend="italic">Conversations</title>,
                        comprised of two volumes, approximately 400 pages apiece. In attempts to
                        mitigate the tedium of transcription Burch designed revolving student
                        pairings so that they might practice their acquisition of French while
                        cross-checking their transcriptions by reading aloud to their partners over
                        Google Hangouts. The team of students–Shelby Stone (Wooster ‘15), Marie
                        Schroder (‘17), Jennifer Filak (‘16), and Grace Gamble (‘17)–also worked in
                        Basecamp so that they might raise questions about transcription publicly;
                        Burch, Heil, and Stephen Flynn (at the time, Wooster’s Emerging Technologies
                        LIbrarian) found in these questions opportunities to discuss editorial
                        practice, the idiosyncrasies of books made during the handpress period of
                        printing, and about structured markup. Regarding the latter of these, Flynn
                        designed a <soCalled>pre-TEI</soCalled> workflow so that students would have
                        a gentle introduction to angle brackets without getting in the way of the
                        transcription itself. The students were exposed to light markup that Flynn
                        then transformed into valid TEI via scripts and ported it into an interface
                        like TEI Boilerplate. Finally, a senior computer science student was hired
                        for a few weeks simply to explore TEI Boilerplate: Douglas Code was tasked
                        only with exploring creative, project-specific hacks to the Boilerplate code
                        and in his brief time on the project was able to create a table of contents
                        to facilitate ease of reading.</p>
                    <p>At its outset, then, Digital Scudéry was a partnership between student
                        editors transcribing the text, a librarian creating a technical framework, a
                        student coder/hacker, a faculty member, and the Five Colleges’ Digital
                        Scholar. To this point, Heil had been framing the project at the topmost
                        level by suggesting tools and frameworks like TEI and Basecamp, and by
                        guiding overall project timelines based on planning meetings, expressed
                        goals, and local resources. For his part the project was an experiment
                        designed to help us walk through the role of TEI in our transcription
                        projects on the Liberal Arts campus. Additionally, however, Heil was also
                        attempting to find partners in computer science who might save the project
                        from manual transcription by tailoring the optical character recognition
                        (OCR) workflows designed as a part of the Early Modern OCR Project (eMOP) at
                        Texas A&amp;M University. Professor Sofia Visa introduced an optional
                        assignment in her machine learning class and recruited Will Rial, a rising
                        senior at Wooster who worked over the summer tailor these workflows. (Rial
                        has presented talks and posters and has a forthcoming publication on his
                        design.) Next steps for the project will include close collaboration between
                        Rial and a French Language and Literature student to further refine the OCR
                        outputs so that the final four books in de Scudéry’s oeuvre can be OCR’d
                        effectively. The result of the project is not just machine- and
                        human-readable texts, but it will also contribute to the digital humanities
                        world’s knowledge base on the OCR technologies and processes that are
                        essentially to freeing the millions of pages of human cultural artifacts
                        from the digital images on which they are <title>preserved.</title>
                    </p>
                    <p>While <title rend="italic">Digital Scudéry</title> will result in digital,
                        pedagogically useful texts for Professor Burch to use in her courses–her
                        initial goal–it additionally demonstrates an ethically motivated and no less
                        expedient series of collaborations. In the aforementioned partnership
                        between libraries, students, faculty members, and an #altac facilitator,
                        each party brought their expertise to the table and, importantly, informed
                        the project’s processes in meaningful ways. Additionally, Heil sought an
                        opportunity for a <soCalled>coincidental collaboration</soCalled> in which
                        Visa and Rial could use data from Burch et al. to inform their project, the
                        result of which would benefit Burch’s original pedagogical goal without
                        rendering this goal dependent upon the results of the computer science
                        intervention. That is to say that two viable digital, pedagogical projects
                        worked along parallel paths, along which each stakeholder contributed her or
                        his creative and specialized solution to the research questions at hand.
                        Along the way, Digital Scudéry will have deliverables: preservation-quality
                        TEI documents, the potential for a digital edition of Scudéry’s work,
                        machine-readable text that can be utilized in the classroom for pedagogical
                        experiments in text mining, introductory TEI workflows for encoding
                        projects, OCR processes for printed seventeenth-century French books, and
                        post-processing scripts to clean the OCR output. The project also
                        exemplifies ethical interdisciplinary, interdivisional collaborations at two
                        different scales while it introduces more possibilities for collaboration in
                        the near term: Heil hopes to fold the lessons learned into processes that
                        can result in whole-campus collaborations that formally knit together
                        faculty teaching, student research, and library and educational
                        technologies’ technical acumen. It is a version of interdisciplinary
                        collaboration that is facilitated at the level of an academic
                        superstructure–here, the Ohio Five, the library, the Ed Tech division–rather
                        than at the level of individual faculty researcher(s).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>ReKN</head>
                    <p><ref target="http://rekn.itercommunity.org">The Renaissance Knowledge
                            Network</ref> (ReKN) is a major scholarly initiative designed to augment
                        digital scholarship in early modern studies by developing an integrated
                        research, analysis, and production environment. It is based at the
                        Electronic Textual Cultures Lab (University of Victoria) and has been
                        developed in partnership with Iter (University of Toronto Scarborough); ReKN
                        also works closely with the Implementing New Knowledge Environments Project
                        (Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council Major Collaborative
                        Research Initiative) and the Advanced Research Consortium (Texas A&amp;M
                        University). Led jointly by Dr Raymond G. Siemens (Canada Research Chair in
                        Humanities Computing and Distinguished Professor of English and Computer
                        Science at the University of Victoria) and Dr William R. Bowen (Director of
                        Iter: Gateway to the Middle Ages and Renaissance and Chair of the Department
                        of Arts, Culture and Media at the University of Toronto Scarborough), it is
                        a network of researchers, projects, and resources dedicated to sharing and
                        disseminating digital resources related to early modern studies.</p>
                    <p>ReKN, as both a potential scholarly platform and, more importantly, an
                        intellectual community, is devoted to understanding, critiquing, and
                        building digital projects for the study of the Renaissance. These aims
                        ensure that the scope and significance of individual and institutional
                        contributions are maximised across the scholarly community of interest. ReKN
                        directly addresses the growing challenge of diverse, isolated, and siloed
                        digital resources by building a scholarly environment explicitly tailored to
                        the needs of humanities scholars studying the Renaissance. ReKN seeks to
                        bring existing scholarly resources and methods into conversation by
                        integrating research, discovery, exploration, analysis, and visualisation.
                        ReKN will take shape at the intersection of the initiatives, projects, and
                        trends outlined above, providing a single point of entry into an entire
                        galaxy of scholarly activity, specialised for and oriented to scholars of
                        the Renaissance. It is a resource for searching and discovering, for
                        analysing and exploring, and for publishing and writing. And in all of these
                        diverse activities we are cognisant of the many ways the community is
                        formed, collaboration occurs, and research is shared and debated. ReKN is
                        being developed from its inception to encompass the ways that not only
                        researchers interact with each other, but the many ways in which digital
                        resources and tools benefit from interoperability and cross communication.
                        ReKN is at once a unique technological resource, a focal point for diverse
                        digital resources, and a community–of individuals, of practice, and of
                        scholarly work. It is a social, scholarly working environment and a
                        community of users, researchers, developers, the public, datasets, projects,
                        publications, and networks.</p>
                    <p>Over the past year, the ReKN team was distributed amongst several time zones
                        and institutions, with many members of the team frequently on the road for
                        conference travel. While this afforded some benefits, it also produced
                        difficulties in communication and decision making. Skype conferences, for
                        example, were difficult to schedule between Europe, Toronto, and Victoria,
                        and as a result were usually several hours in length when finally scheduled.
                        We also found that different work styles and personalities made project
                        coordination difficult at times, especially as concerned software and
                        platform deliverables. We also found that the local and individual needs of
                        the graduate students hired as research assistants often meant that they did
                        not want to intellectual <soCalled>own</soCalled> the project. The issues
                        faced by the project with regard to geographical distance and community
                        development is evidence of how a project, with the stated goal of community
                        formation, must actively work to shape that culture internally. The
                        collaborative cultures that we attempt to build on platforms like ReKN must
                        be echoed in the teams that develop the software as well. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Life Renewed</head>
                    <p>The Creative Media &amp; Digital Culture program at Washington State
                        University Vancouver (WSUV) has a strong outreach mission, due partly to the
                        WSUV’s status as a land grant institution and partly to the tight knit
                        community that helped to found the university a mere 26 years ago. Since the
                        introduction of the Senior Capstone course (DTC 497) to the curriculum in
                        summer 2007, graduating seniors have learned to apply their technological
                        and essential skills to the production of media objects for local non-profit
                        organizations and businesses. To date, students have produced websites,
                        apps, interactive exhibits, videos, digital marketing materials, and 2D and
                        3D animations for the Council of the Homeless, the Boys and Girls Club,
                        Ridgefield School District, Fort Vancouver National Historic Site, the <ref target="http://dtc-wsuv.org/projects/autovation/">Oregon Museum for
                            Science and Industry</ref>, <ref target="http://dtc-wsuv.org/projects/life-renewed/">Mount St. Helens
                            Science and Learning Center at Coldwater Station</ref>, the YWCA, <ref target="http://dtc-wsuv.org/projects/book-of-lists/index.html">Vancouver
                            Business Journal</ref>, <ref target="http://dtc-wsuv.org/projects/">iQ
                            Credit Union</ref>, and others. Of these <ref target="http://dtc-wsuv.org/projects/life-renewed/">Life Renewed</ref>,
                        the project produced in fall 2014 for the Mount St. Helens Science and
                        Learning Center at Coldwater Station, stands out as most representative of
                        the kind of project that best reflects the way digital humanities work
                        collaboratively with other fields to produce a meaningful experience aimed
                        at fostering learning through sound pedagogy. </p>
                    <p>Tasked with telling the story of the plants and animals that have returned to
                        Mount St. Helens since the 1980 eruption, the 23 students in this course
                        began, in August 2014, to research interactive installations relating to
                        environmental phenomena. Exploring science museums, educational facilities,
                        art galleries, and museums from around the world, they assembled a
                        collection of 50 exhibits. They studied these examples using the constraints
                        provided them by the scientists at the Station (e.g. size, portability, wide
                        audience interest) developing a comparative analysis that captured the
                        students’ observations. The next stage of the project’s development had them
                        creating their own exhibit. Using their research, students prepared a
                        proposal for the way in which their exhibit would look and function and
                        delivered this proposal to the scientists in a formal presentation. The end
                        product was the <title rend="quotes">Life Renewed,</title> an educational
                        environment that includes a mobile app and an interactive installation that
                        provides a 3D simulated flyover of the volcano, two augmented reality
                        banners that reveal 2D hand-made illustrations and 3D animation models, and
                        a touch screen interface for identifying plants and animals found on the
                        mountain. </p>
                    <p>Once the scientists accepted the students’ plan, production on the exhibit
                        began. The students assembled into four teams based on interests and skills:
                        1) Animation/Video/GIS, 2) Augmented Reality/Interface Design, 3) Web and
                        Mobile, and 4) Digital Marketing and Promotions. Each team worked to develop
                        their own portion of the project, interacting with the scientists and other
                        teams as they created their digital artifacts. Using GIS data, the Animation
                        Team mapped 289 square miles of the volcano in 3D and created a game
                        simulation in which visitors to the exhibit take the persona of a raven
                        flying over the various terrains of Mount St. Helens and observing the
                        animals and plants of that specific area of rebirth. Students also produced
                        hand-made 3D animations of the animals and 2D scientific illustrations of
                        the plants used for the augmented reality environment. The students on the
                        Web and Mobile team built the computer used to power the simulation and
                        produced a large screen and mobile version of it. The Design Team made the
                        augmented reality banners and produced the educational booklet that
                        accompanied the exhibit to be made available to visitors at the Station. The
                        Digital Marketing Team developed and maintained the website that documents
                        the production of the project and hosts many of its assets. Once completed,
                        the exhibit was installed at the Station in celebration of the 35th
                        anniversary of the eruption and remained on site until August 2015. So
                        successful was this project that it won two 1st place awards for
                        undergraduate research and has continued to be exhibited at events, like the
                        recent Portland mini-Maker Faire (Oregon Museum for Science and Industry,
                        September 2015) and Girlfest (Girl Scouts of Oregon and SW Washington,
                        October 2015). While students came to this project with strong technological
                        skills, what they learned in the process of producing the exhibit was how to
                        work collaboratively on teams, to communicate in both written and oral
                        contexts effectively to a variety of audiences––from students, to
                        scientists, to the public––and solve a real-world problem that came with a
                        healthy amount of responsibility and stress. These are the skill sets that
                        help them stand out on the job market and explains why the hiring rate for
                        the program stands at 90%. More importantly, students learn first hand what
                        it means to be part of a community. The team structure encourages this
                        understanding at a micro level as students working with other students, but
                        the collaboration with one another, the faculty, and the scientists to build
                        something of intellectual value for the public teaches students what it
                        means to be citizens of the world. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Revealing the Seams</head>
                <p>In large part, the challenges to new systems of evaluation and credit are not
                    technological or infrastructural per se. Instead, they are social, habituated by
                    longstanding disciplinary norms and expectations. They are deeply embedded in
                    administrative norms and processes, from informal expectations to the literal
                    paperwork used within universities. They find expression in tenure and promotion
                    guidelines or traditions that ignore or disincentivize collaborative work and
                    processes, frame digital scholarship as service, or overemphasize the
                        <soCalled>final product</soCalled> of digital scholarship. In evaluation
                    frameworks like the Research Excellence Framework in the United Kingdom or the
                    Excellence in Research for Australia, we can observe the nationalization of
                    these standards in an attempt to repatriate scholarship into the limited roles
                    of training a citizenry, which continue to overvalue monographs in rigid
                    point-based systems that determine funding. We see these disciplinary norms in
                    requirements for depositing dissertations as PDFs that often preclude digital
                    work outside that limiting file format. The habits of student evaluation and
                    curriculum development further disincentivize faculty from engaging their
                    students in collaborative teams and training undergraduates and graduates to
                    complete digital projects. Students see faculty trumpeting the arrival of their
                    new book and using it as a calling card for their expertise, while eliding the
                    pressures of tenure and promotion. Finally, students run the risk of emulating
                    these worn out modes of scholarly communication and sacrificing their education
                    to repeat the cycle. </p>
                <p> Through our case studies, we hope to narrativize how a project's processes,
                    participation patterns, and outcomes can cast these formally and informally
                    institutionalized values in relief. At its core, the approach is humanistic: we
                    tell the stories of our projects in an attempt to glimpse the connectedness that
                    holds true collaboration and ethical distribution of credit as a core value. Our
                    case studies bring to light our attempts at flattened hierarchies and, within
                    such a two-dimensional model, the sites of overlapping knowledge and abilities
                    that are sewn together into the fabric of our projects. To return to Ratto’s
                    terminology, our approach embraces its <soCalled>seamfulness</soCalled>
                    <ptr target="#ratto2007"/>. The seamlessness of contemporary consumer
                    electronics contains a rhetoric that elides the process of development, which we
                    argue is the key moment when new knowledge and insights are created. By
                    embracing the collaborative development as a core concern for digital humanities
                    pedagogy and research, we reject the consumerist privileging of a final product
                    and embrace an evolving model of social knowledge creation. As a development
                    ethos guiding projects, Chalmers and Galani describe an approach to interface
                    that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#chalmers2004">involves deliberately revealing seams to users, and
                            taking advantage of features usually considered as negative or
                            problematic</quote>
                        <ptr target="#chalmers2004" loc="1"/>
                    </cit>. For our purposes, the seam is not a failure but a redoubling that
                    results from layered, overlapping systems; our seams strengthen rather than
                    weaken interpersonal signals. Nevertheless, the seams are sites of contestation
                    in both Chalmers’s formulation and our adaptation thereof: in both instances,
                    the seam troubles the system and are <soCalled>negative or
                        problematic.</soCalled> Ratto pushes the logic of seam<emph>fulness</emph>
                    into an ethical domain by highlighting how consumers of seamless electronics
                    become <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ratto2007">passive agents</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ratto2007" loc="24"/>
                    </cit>, who are unable to modify or repair the technology they purchase. The
                    ethics of seamlessness is an ethic of disempowerment. When we elide the seams
                    between teaching and research, our students become passive agents and mere
                    consumers of education. Giving them the awareness of the seams between teaching
                    and research allows them to take agency of their education. </p>
                <p>As we think through the utility seamful design, there is a danger in adopting
                    tantalizingly figurative formulations: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#chalmers2004">Seamfully integrated tools would maintain the unique
                            characteristics of each tool, through transformations that retained
                            their individual characteristics</quote>
                        <ptr target="#chalmers2004" loc="2"/>
                    </cit>. While we certainly want to celebrate our <soCalled>unique
                        characteristics,</soCalled> the metaphor implies a problematic association
                    between the computational tools and those who use them. We want to continue to
                    push against that gadgetization of human contributorship that Lanier laments and
                    adapt a model that lays bare human networks of overlapping agency, displaying
                    the joints where our projects become knit together. Dean Rehberger, the Director
                    of Matrix at Michigan State University, has helpfully defined Digital Humanities
                    as quilting <ptr target="#rehberger2014"/>.<note> Dean Rehberger defined digital
                        humanities during the 2014 Day of DH in the following way: <q>Metaphorically
                            it is like making quilts: it takes many hands, it is about making, it is
                            about reuse &amp; remix, it is an art &amp; science, and while devalued
                            by some it is ultimately empowering and transformative</q> (<ref target="http://dayofdh2014.matrix.msu.edu/members/deanreh/">http://dayofdh2014.matrix.msu.edu/members/deanreh/</ref>). </note>
                    Perhaps, if we stretch the needlecraft metaphor even further, we might think of
                    it instead as a motley patchwork of projects that comprise the canvas for our
                    big tent view of DH. We can strengthen that fabric with intentional, ethically
                    designed knowledge networks that, when viewed through a humanistic lens, get us
                    closer (as a large community of practice) to evaluative structures that allow
                    for responsible, care-full accreditation and that foster intentional growth
                    rather than sprawl.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="academicbill" label="Academic Bill of Rights"><title rend="quotes">Academic Bill of Rights.</title> Wikipedia: The Free Encyclopedia.
                    Wikimedia Foundation, Inc. July 2015‎‎. Web.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="alonso2003" label="Alonso et al. 2003">Alonso, Carlos J.; Davidson,
                    Cathy N.; Unsworth, John M.; Withey, Lynne <title rend="quotes">Crises and
                        Opportunities: The Futures of Scholarly Publishing</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the American Council of Learned
                        Societies</title> Annual Meeting 57 (May 2003):1-55. Web. <ref target="http://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/ED503721.pdf">http://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/ED503721.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berry2011" label="Berry 2011">Berry, David M. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Computational Turn: Thinking About the Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Culture Machine</title> 12 (2011): 1–22. Web.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brand2015" label="Brand et al. 2015">Brand, Amy et al. <title rend="quotes">Beyond Authorship: Attribution, Contribution, Collaboration,
                        and Credit.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Learned Publishing</title> 28.2 (2015): 151–155.
                    Web.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brown2009" label="Brown et al. 2009">Brown, Susan, Patricia Clements,
                    Isobel Grundy, Stan Ruecker, Jeffery Antoniuk, and Sharon Balazs. <title rend="quotes">Published Yet Never Done: The Tension Between Projection and
                        Completion in Digital Humanities Research.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 3.2 (2009): 1–9.
                    Web.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cavanagh2012" label="Cavanagh 2012">Cavanagh, Sheila. <title rend="quotes">Living in a Digital World: Rethinking Peer Review,
                        Collaboration, and Open Access.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 1.4 (Fall 2012). Web.
                        <ref target="http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/1-4/living-in-a-digital-world-by-sheila-cavanagh/">http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/1-4/living-in-a-digital-world-by-sheila-cavanagh/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chalmers2004" label="Chalmers and Galani 2004">Chalmers, M. and
                    Galani, A. <title rend="quotes">Seamful inter-weaving: heterogeneity in the
                        theory and design of interactive systems.</title>
                    <title rend="italic"> Symposium on De-signing Interactive Systems. </title>
                    Cambridge, Massachusetts. (1-4 August 2004): 243-252. Web. <ref target="http://www.dcs.gla.ac.uk/~matthew/papers/ubicomp2003HCISystems.pdf">http://www.dcs.gla.ac.uk/~matthew/papers/ubicomp2003HCISystems.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cronin2004" label="Cronin and La Barre 2004">Cronin, Blaise and
                    Kathryn La Barre. <title rend="quotes">Mickey Mouse and Milton: book publishing
                        in the humanities</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Learned Publishing</title> 17. 2 (April 2004): 85-98. Web.
                        <ref target="http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/alpsp/lp/2004/00000017/00000002/art00003">http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/alpsp/lp/2004/00000017/00000002/art00003</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="davidhorowitz" label="David Horowitz Freedom Center"><title rend="quotes">David Horowitz Freedom Center.</title> Wikipedia: The Free
                    Encyclopedia. Wikimedia Foundation, Inc. 17 August 2015‎. Web.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dipressind" label="Di Pressi et al.">Di Pressi, Haley, Stephanie
                    Gorman, Miriam Posner, Raphael Sasayama, and Tori Schmitt, with contributions
                    from Roderic Crooks, Megan Driscoll, Amy Earhart, Spencer Keralis, Tiffany
                    Naiman, and Todd Presner. <title rend="quotes">A Student Collaborators’ Bill of
                        Rights.</title> Center for Digital Humanities at University of California at
                    Los Angeles. Web. <ref target="http://www.cdh.ucla.edu/news-events/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/">http://www.cdh.ucla.edu/news-events/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="earhart2015" label="Earhart 2015">Earhart, Amy E. <title rend="quotes">The Digital Humanities as a Laboratory.</title> In <title rend="italic">Between Humanities and the Digital</title>, ed. Patrik Svensson and David
                    Theo Goldberg. Cambridge: MIT Press, 2015. Print.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="freire2005" label="Freire 2005">Freire, Paulo. <title rend="italic">Pedagogy of the Oppressed</title>. Trans. Myra Bergman Ramos. New York:
                    Continuum, 2005. Print.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fyfe2011" label="Fyfe 2011">Fyfe, Paul. <title rend="quotes">Digital
                        Pedagogy Unplugged.</title>” <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</title> 5.3 (2011): 1-8. Web. <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/3/000106/000106.html">http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/3/000106/000106.html</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harley2010" label="Harley et al. 2010">Harley, Diane, et al. <title rend="quotes">Assessing the Future Landscape of Scholarly Communication: An
                        Exploration of Faculty Values and Needs in Seven Disciplines.</title> U of
                    California, Berkeley: Center for Studies in HIgher Education, Distributed in
                    associated with the U of California P. (2010). Web. <ref target="http://escholarship.org/uc/item/15x7385g">http://escholarship.org/uc/item/15x7385g</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hirsch2012" label="Hirsch 2012">Hirsch, Brett D. <title rend="quotes">&lt;/Parentheses&gt;: Digital Humanities and the Place of Pedagogy.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Pedagogy: Practices, Principles and
                        Politics.</title> United Kingdom: OpenBook, 2012. 3-30. Print. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hooks1994" label="hooks 1994">hooks, bell. <title rend="italic">Teaching to Transgress: Education as the Practice of Freedom. </title>New
                    York: Routledge, 1994. Print. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="keralis2016" label="Keralis 2016">Keralis, Spencer. <title rend="quotes">Milking the Deficit Internship.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Disrupting the Digital Humanities. </title> Blog. (2016).
                    Web. <ref target="http://www.disruptingdh.com/milking-the-deficit-internship/">http://www.disruptingdh.com/milking-the-deficit-internship/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lanier2010" label="Lanier 2010">Lanier, Jaron. <title rend="italic">You Are not a Gadget: A Manifesto.</title> New York: Knopf, 2010. Print. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="maxwell2015" label="Maxwell 2015">Maxwell, John. <title rend="quotes">Beyond Open Access to Open Content.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Scholarly and Research Communication 6.3</title> (2015).
                    Web. <ref target="http://src-online.ca/index.php/src/article/view/202">http://src-online.ca/index.php/src/article/view/202</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="morris2013" label="Morris and Stommell 2013">Morris, Sean Michael and
                    Jesse Stommell. <title rend="quotes">A Bill of Rights and Principles for
                        Learning in the Digital Age.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Hybrid Pedagogy</title> (January 22nd 2013). Web. <ref target="http://www.hybridpedagogy.com/journal/bill-rights-principles-learning-digital-age/">http://www.hybridpedagogy.com/journal/bill-rights-principles-learning-digital-age/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nowviskie2012" label="Nowviskie 2012">Nowviskie, Bethany. <title rend="quotes">Evaluating Collaborative Digital Scholarship (or, Where Credit
                        Is Due).</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 4.1 (Fall 2012). Web. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="prensky2001" label="Prensky 2001">Prensky, Marc. <title rend="quotes">Digital Natives, Digital Immigrants.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">On the Horizon</title> 9.5 (October 2001): 1-6. Web. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ratto2007" label="Ratto 2007">Ratto, Matt. <title rend="quotes">Ethics
                        of Seamless infrastructures: Resources and Future Directions.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">International Review of Information Ethics</title> 8
                    (December 2007): 21-25. Web. <ref target="http://www.i-r-i-e.net/inhalt/008/008_4.pdf">http://www.i-r-i-e.net/inhalt/008/008_4.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rehberger2014" label="Rehberger 2014">Rehberger, Dean. <title rend="quotes">[o]ral [h]istory and the [d]igital [h]umanities.</title> In
                        <title rend="italic">Oral History and Digital Humanities: Voice, Access, and
                        Engagement</title>, ed. Douglas A. Boyd and Mary A. Larson. New York:
                    Palgrave MacMillan, 2014. Print.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="suber2012" label="Suber 2012">Suber, Peter. <title rend="italic">Open
                        Access</title>. Cambridge: MIT Press, 2012. Print.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thomas2011" label="Thomas 2011">Thomas, Michael. Ed. <title rend="italic">Deconstructing Digital Natives: Young People, Technology, and
                        the New Literacies.</title> New York: Routledge, 2011. Print. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thompson2007" label="Thompson 2007">Thompson, Jennifer Wolfe. <title rend="quotes">The Death of the Scholarly Monograph in the Humanities?
                        Citation Patterns in Literary Scholarship</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Libri</title> 52.3 (December 2007): 121–136. Web. <ref target="http://www.degruyter.com/view/j/libr.2002.52.issue-3/libr.2002.121/libr.2002.121.xml">http://www.degruyter.com/view/j/libr.2002.52.issue-3/libr.2002.121/libr.2002.121.xml</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wenger1998" label="Wenger 1998">Wenger, Etienne. <title rend="italic">Communities of Practice: Learning, Meaning, and Identity</title>.
                    Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1998. Print. </bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>