<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Computational Paremiology: Charting the temporal, ecological dynamics of proverb use in books, news articles, and tweets</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
        

               <dhq:authorInfo>
                  <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
                  <dhq:author_name>Ethan <dhq:family>Davis</dhq:family>
                  </dhq:author_name>
                  <idno type="ORCID"
                     ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
                  <dhq:affiliation>Computational Story Lab, Vermont Complex Systems Center,
                     MassMutual Center of Excellence for Complex Systems and Data Science, Vermont
                     Advanced Computing Core, Watzek Library, Lewis &amp; Clark
                     College</dhq:affiliation>
                  <email>edavis@lclark.edu</email>
                  <dhq:bio>
                     <p>Ethan Davis is Digital and Data Science Specialist at Lewis &amp; Clark College. His research focuses on the use of proverbs across time. He is interested in computational approaches to the humanities, especially the use of metaphor and routine formulae in texts.</p>
                  </dhq:bio>
               </dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:authorInfo>
                  <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
                  <dhq:author_name>Christopher <dhq:family>Danforth</dhq:family>
                  </dhq:author_name>
                  
                  <dhq:affiliation>Computational Story Lab, Vermont Complex Systems Center,
                     MassMutual Center of Excellence for Complex Systems and Data Science, Vermont
                     Advanced Computing Core, Department of Mathematics &amp; Statistics, University
                     of Vermont</dhq:affiliation>
                  <email>chris.danforth@uvm.edu</email>
                  <dhq:bio>
                     <p>Christopher M. Danforth is Professor of Mathematics &amp; Statistics at the University of Vermont, and Director of the Vermont Advanced Computing Center. He is the co-inventor of <ref target="http://hedonometer.org">http://hedonometer.org</ref>, an instrument measuring daily happiness based on social media. Along with Peter Sheridan Dodds, Danforth runs the Computational Story Lab research group.</p>
                  </dhq:bio>
               </dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:authorInfo>
                  <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
                  <dhq:author_name>Wolfgang <dhq:family>Mieder</dhq:family>
                  </dhq:author_name>
                  
                  <dhq:affiliation>Department of German &amp; Russian, University of
                     Vermont</dhq:affiliation>
                  <email>wolfgang.mieder@uvm.edu</email>
                  <dhq:bio>
                     <p>Wolfgang Mieder is University Distinguished Professor Emeritus of German and Folklore at the University of Vermont, where he taught for fifty years and was the long-time chairperson of the Department of German and Russian. The author of well over one hundred books on fairy tales, folk songs, and legends, he is recognized internationally for his expertise in paremiology (proverb studies). Among his more recent books in English are: <title rend="italic"><q>Making a Way Out of No Way</q>: Martin Luther King’s Sermonic Proverbial Rhetoric</title> (2010), <title rend="italic"><q>Behold the Proverbs of a People</q>: Proverbial Wisdom in Culture, Literature, and Politics</title> (2014), <title rend="italic"><q>Right Makes Might</q>: Proverbs and the American Worldview</title> (2019), and <title rend="italic">Dictionary of Authentic American Proverbs</title>(2021).</p>
                  </dhq:bio>
               </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Peter Sheridan <dhq:family>Dodds</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
               
               <dhq:affiliation>Computational Story Lab, Vermont Complex Systems Center, MassMutual
                  Center of Excellence for Complex Systems and Data Science, Vermont Advanced
                  Computing Core, Department of Computer Science, University of
                  Vermont, Santa Fe Institute</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>peter.dodds@uvm.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Peter Sheridan Dodds is a Professor at the University of Vermont (UVM), Director of the Vermont Complex Systems Center, co-Director of the Computational Story Lab, and is appointed to the Department of Computer Science. Dodds maintains general research and teaching interests in complex systems with a focus on sociotechnical and psychological phenomena including contagion, language, meaning, and stories.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000676</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               >017</idno>
            <idno type="issue">2</idno>
            <date when="2023-05-26">26 May 2023</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000676/000676.xml"
               >GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>Proverbs are an essential component of language and culture, and though much attention
               has been paid to their history and currency, there has been comparatively little
               quantitative work on changes in the frequency with which they are used over time. With
               wider availability of large corpora reflecting many diverse genres of documents, it is
               now possible to take a broad and dynamic view of the importance of the proverb. Here, we
               measure temporal changes in the relevance of proverbs within four corpora, differing in
               kind, scale, and time frame: Millions of books over centuries; thousands of books over
               centuries; millions of news articles over twenty years; and billions of tweets over a
               decade. While similar methodologies abound lately, they have not yet been performed
               using comprehensive phraseological lexica (here, <title rend="italic">The Dictionary of
                  American Proverbs</title>). We show that beyond simple partitioning of texts into words,
               searches for culturally significant phrases can yield distinct insights from the same
               corpora. Comparative analysis between four commonly used corpora show that each reveals
               its own relationship to the phenomena being studied. We also find that the frequency
               with which proverbs appear in texts follows a similar distribution to that of individual
               words.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>This article measures temporal changes in the relevance of proverbs within four corpora,differing in
               kind, scale, and time frame: Millions of books over centuries; thousands of books over
               centuries; millions of news articles over twenty years; and billions of tweets over a
               decade.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>

         <div>
         
            <head>Introduction</head>
        
         <p>Our goal here is to advance <q>computational paremiology</q>: The data-driven study of
            proverbs, and in general to examine the utility of frequency-based studies of common
            phrases in large corpora. In particular, we hope to answer the following: Can a
            computational study of proverbs in large corpora offer unique insight in the study of
            those proverbs? And is this novel kind of approach appropriate to corpus linguistics and
            studies using corpora broadly? We first build a quantitative foundation by searching for
            and counting instances of an ecology of proverbs, and estimating their frequency of use
            over time in several large corpora from different domains. We then characterize basic
            temporal dynamics allowing us to address fundamental questions such as whether or not
            proverbs appear in texts according to a similar probability distribution to words <ptr target="#zipf2012"/>
            <ptr target="#balasubrahmanyan1996"/> <ptr target="#williams2015b"/> <ptr target="#cancho2001"/>.</p>
         <p>In studies of phraseology, data on frequency of use is often conspicuously absent
            <ptr target="#cermak2014"/>. The recent proliferation of large machine-readable corpora has enabled
            new frequency-informed studies of words and <emph>n</emph>-grams (phrases of
            length <emph>n</emph>) that have expanded our knowledge of language use in a
            variety of settings, from the Google Books <emph>n</emph>-gram Corpus and the
            introduction of <q>culturomics</q> <ptr target="#michel2011"/> <ptr target="#pechenick2015a"/>, to availability and
            analysis of Twitter data <ptr target="#alshaabi2020"/>. Routine formulae, or multi-word expressions
            that cannot be reduced to a literal reading of their semantic components, remain
            notoriously averse to reliable identification despite carrying high degrees of symbolic
            and indexical meaning <ptr target="#sag2002"/>. It is, for instance, much easier to chart a
            probability distribution of single words or <emph>n</emph>-grams than phrases
            like proverbs, conventional metaphors, or idioms, which must be associated with a
            lexicon – a set of meaningful linguistic units. </p>
         <p>Studies of words alone can generally assume that each word is lexically represented as
            such, but the study of phrases with a particular cultural use may require a lexicon in
            addition to the text being studied. Here, we use Mieder’s <title rend="italic">Dictionary
               of American Proverbs</title> as such a resource. Assuming words or <q>grams</q> as
            fundamental components of texts risks flattening the complex interrelations between
            common phrases that might place a text in a historical or literary context, by
            de-emphasizing or omitting altogether culturally significant phrases. We show a case
            (proverbs) in which established computational methods may be applied to a class of
            culturally meaningful phrases, with results that paint a valid and substantially unique
            picture of language use in the corpora studied. </p>
         <p>Perhaps the most recognizable routine formulae are proverbs and their close cousin,
            idioms. Centuries of the study of proverbs – paremiology – have shown their importance
            in language and culture, and that they are immensely popular among the folk (the people
            for whom these phrases are culturally relevant) <ptr target="#mieder2012"/>. Proverbs are generally
            metaphorical in their use, and map a generic situation described by the proverb to an
            immediate context. In light of challenges in developing reliable instruments for
            measurement and quantification of figurative language, research would greatly benefit,
            as it has with words, from a better understanding of the frequency and dynamics of
            proverb use in texts. By applying new methodologies in measuring frequency and
            probability distributions, this study seeks to contribute to this endeavor. </p>
         <p>Before going any further, we must detail a more precise definition of the proverb.
            Though there is still some debate, it is widely agreed that proverbs are popular sayings
            that offer general advice or wisdom. Naturally, not all such sayings are proverbs.
            Mieder’s definition is perhaps the most useful for our present purposes: <quote rend="inline">Proverbs [are]
            concise traditional statements of apparent truths with currency among the folk. More
            elaborately stated, proverbs are short, generally known sentences of the folk that
            contain wisdom, truths, morals, and traditional views in a metaphorical, fixed, and
            memorizable form and that are handed down from generation to generation</quote> <ptr target="#mieder2008"/>. </p>
         <p>Proverbs maintain a particular relationship with their context of use that provides a
            fruitful domain for frequency and probability analysis. An important part of the proverb
            is the context in which it is used. The metaphorical property of a proverb need not only
            have to do with the proverb itself (as in the proverb/metaphor <q>war is hell,</q> in which
            war is compared to hell within the proverb). In general, the use of a proverb is
            metaphorical in context, meaning that the proverb offers wisdom about a current
            situation via a metaphoric comparison to a proverbial one <ptr target="#mieder2008"/>. For instance,
            while the proverb <quote rend="inline">still waters run deep</quote> might be used to caution someone against
            taking a seeming calm for granted, as it may belie unseen dangers. As with many other
            proverbs, it is hard to imagine anyone using the proverb <quote rend="inline">you can’t put lipstick on a
            pig</quote> in any literal or pragmatic context. Rather, these phrases offer wisdom embodied in
            the culture as opposed to that of the speaker. In this way proverbs may be used
            generically without proffering personal expertise.</p>
         <p>Proverbs are necessarily ambiguous enough to offer wisdom in any number of situations.
            Michael Lieber argued that this ambiguity paradoxically gives proverbs the function of
            disambiguating situations in which they are used. In part due to their role as cultural
            rather than individual wisdom, they can be invoked impersonally as a way of clarifying a
            complex reality <ptr target="#lieber1994"/>. As such, part of Winick’s definition of the proverb is
            that they <quote rend="inline">address recurrent social situations in a strategic way</quote> <ptr target="#mieder2008"/>.</p>
         <p>It is important to note the distinction between proverbs and idioms. An example of an
            idiom would be the phrase <q>red herring</q> denoting a mislead. The meanings of idioms, like
            proverbs, often cannot be ascertained from the meanings of their component words. But
            unlike proverbs, idioms are often not complete sentences, require context, and need not
            reference a paradigmatic situation. Proverbs on the other hand represent a complete
            situation and offer some sort of general wisdom. The boundary between the two is rather
            fuzzy and contains many idioms and proverbial expressions. For instance, the proverb
            <quote rend="inline">every cloud has its silver lining</quote> is perhaps more well known by its idiomatic
            reduction <q>silver lining.</q> In fact, people may use an idiom without any knowledge of its
            proverbial context. Our intent here is to focus on expressions of full proverbs, and not
            their idiomatic uses. As previous work has shown, it is possible to investigate the
            manipulations and idiomizations of individual proverbs <ptr target="#cermak2014"/> <ptr target="#moon1998"/>. Our
            approach has limitations, and further research into flexible searches or other
            identification methods will be essential in future work.</p>
         <p>Metaphor and idiom identification and comprehension are an open area of research in
            machine learning and NLP (Natural Language Processing) <ptr target="#fazly2009"/> <ptr target="#shutova2010"/>. In
            general, metaphors and metaphorical speech are difficult to identify, and do not occur
            in consistent, repeated phrasings. Whereas in the study of individual words, one is
            allowed the tacit assumption that most of these words are represented in the lexicon of
            the language, in the search for routine formulae, one must access the lexicon as an
            essential step in verifying a phrase’s meaningfulness. Furthermore, the source and
            target domains of their metaphoric mapping are seldom explicit, as laid out by Lakoff
            and Johnson in their <title rend="italic">Conceptual Metaphor Theory</title> <ptr target="#lakoff1985"/> <ptr target="#andersson2013"/>. Proverbs
            generally appear in the same recognizable format, and in the form of a full,
            self-contained sentence. Prospectively, understanding of the conceptual mapping involved
            in proverb use may provide a useful step towards general understanding of metaphors in
            the above fields <ptr target="#ozbal2016a"/> <ptr target="#ozbal2016b"/>. </p>
         <p>Arguably, the proverb’s flexibility of use has helped make them an essential part of
            language and communication, literature, discourse, and media <ptr target="#mieder2012"/>. Interest in
            the collection and study of proverbs dates back to at least the ancient Greeks and
            Sumerians. Erasmus famously collected proverbs. In English literature, the proverb has
            been an important device for many famous authors, among them Geoffrey Chaucer, William
            Shakespeare, Oscar Wilde, and Agatha Christie <ptr target="#abrams1994"/> <ptr target="#obelkevich1994"/>. </p></div>
         <div>
         
            <head>Quantitative Approaches</head>
       
         <p>This is by no means the first quantitative study of proverb use. Permiakov called for
            demographic studies of proverb knowledge to gather an impression of which proverbs were
            being used by the folk, in the interest of establishing a paremiological minimum: A
            minimum lexicon of proverbs for understanding a language <ptr target="#permiakov1989"/>. Subsequent
            interest in proverb knowledge in psychology and folklore resulted in several studies
            conducted in the United States. Early studies by Albig and Bain in the 1930s found that
            American college students could recall on average between 25 and 27 distinct proverbs,
            many of which were common among participants <ptr target="#albig1931"/> <ptr target="#bain1939"/>. A more recent
            study by Haas observed proverb familiarity among college students in several regions of
            the US. They performed experiments in both proverb generation and proverb recognition.
            Notably, students could recognize more proverbs than they could recall on their own
            <ptr target="#haas2008"/>.</p>
         <p>Apart from the lexicographic collection of proverbs from texts, several attempts have
            been made to quantify and characterize their use. Whiting, in his assiduous collection
            of proverbs from texts in <title rend="quotes">Modern Proverbs and Proverbial Sayings</title> <ptr target="#whiting2014"/>, kept
            track of the frequency with which they were encountered. Norrick attempted a manual
            search for proverb frequency, though he was constrained to only using proverbs starting
            with the letter <emph>f</emph>, and used a relatively small text sample
            <ptr target="#norrick1985"/>. In the first serious computational analysis of proverb frequency, Lau
            searched for and counted instances of proverbs in newspapers in the Lexis/Nexis ALLNWS
            database <ptr target="#lau1996"/>. </p>
         <p>David Cram theorized that proverbs, acting as self-contained lexical units, were
            employed much in the same way that words are, and that their use involved a <q>lexical
            loop</q> where the speaker accesses the lexicon in addition to the syntax when forming a
            text. As such, in the case of proverbs (and phrasal idioms), one ought to <quote rend="inline">analyze a
               syntactic string as a single lexical item</quote> <ptr target="#cram1994"/>. </p>
         <p>Moon’s exhaustive early study of fixed expressions and idioms (denoted FEIs) in the
            Oxford Hector Pilot Corpus (OHPC) did just that <ptr target="#moon1998"/>. His study represents the
            first serious attempt to apply the new tools of computational linguistics to routine
            formulae. He searched the OHPC (a precursor to the British National Corpus or BNC) for
            instances of 6776 FEIs from the <title rend="italic">Collins Cobuild English Language Dictionary</title>. It is worth
            noting that at the time, there were few machine-readable English phraseological lexica.
            Though proverbs consisted of only 3.5% of the searched phrases (240), 19% of the
            expressions found in the corpus were proverbial expressions, the second most common
            subtype behind <q>simple expressions</q> (70%). Of the proverbs found, 59% were deemed
            metaphorical. Moon notes that exploitation of FEIs are easy to miss, and uses the
            proverb <quote rend="inline">a bird in the hand is worth two in the bush</quote> as an example. </p>
         <p>Significantly, Moon noted that journalism was over-represented in the corpus, and that
            the results did not represent the distributions of these FEIs in English as a whole.
            This and other similar caveats inspired the present study to observe genre-specific
            corpora separately, and compare after analysis.</p>
         <p>Čermák’s essay collection <title rend="italic">Proverbs: Their Lexical and Semantic Features</title> contains
            several essays that deal with the distribution of proverbs in the British National
            Corpus <ptr target="#cermak2014"/>. In Čermák’s pioneering essays, he searches for occurrences of
            English proverbs in the BNC corpus (100 million words) <ptr target="#bnc2001"/>.
            In his study, even the most common proverbs seem to occur relatively infrequently. For
            example, <quote rend="inline">easier said than done</quote> is the most common, appearing 62 times in the entire
            corpus. His study discusses the relevance of corpus occurrence to a paremiological
            minimum (he uses a limited proverb list from Wiktionary). Another study focuses on text
            introducers to various proverbs using collocation analysis. (Čermák notably
            created/spearheaded one of the first machine-readable phrasaeological lexica in the
            <quote rend="inline">Czech Idiom Dictionary</quote> (1994).)</p>
         <p>Čermák relates frequency dictionaries to discussions of a paremeological minimum. Should
            proverb frequency in large corpora be considered when judging that minimum? Of course,
            there are problems with this approach as well: proverbs rely heavily on oral tradition,
            and are prone to frequent corruptions and purposeful exploitations. As such there is no
            guarantee that a search of a given phrasing of a proverb will capture all, if any, of
            its occurrences in a text. There are ways around this on an individual basis, but it
            depends on the proverb: some employ parallel structures (like <q>good X make good Y</q>), or
            have popular idiomizations (like <q>silver lining</q>). Longer proverbs are more likely to
            appear in more than one form, as words and clauses can be swapped rearranged, or omitted
            without changing their overall meaning, which makes computational identification more
            difficult. Shorter proverbs will more reliably appear in a consistent form because there
            are fewer words to manipulate, and any manipulation is likely to change their meaning. </p>
         <p>In a recent introductory paremiology textbook, Steyer (2015) outlined a process general
            corpus linguistic method for studying proverbs, similar to Moon and Čermák. Most
            recently, Haas (2022) used Google Trends to analyze the frequency of Google searches of
            proverbs included in discourse around the COVID-19 pandemic. Here, we expand on the
            above literature, including much larger corpora and proverb data sets. </p>
         <p>Should the ambition be to find these distributions in English as a whole? We contend
            that there is no such universal corpus for any language. Clearly use of these phrases is
            context-dependent, it seems unlikely inter-contextual searches will yield greater
            insight than single-genre searches. Instead, frequency dynamics and distributions in
            separate corpora from differing contexts may be more informative.</p></div>
         <div>
         
            <head>From Data on Language to Culture</head>
       
         <p>Our present study of proverbs from a corpus linguistic point of view examines proverb
            frequency using several methods that are well established in the study of words, though
            rarely used in conjunction: namely the dynamics of frequency over time, and the
            relationship between frequency and relative popularity (rank). We illustrate that moving
            beyond words to the study of significant phrases provides worthwhile insight that cannot
            be captured by word-based methods, and yet reproduces some of the expected behavior of
            words.</p>
         <p>One of the foundational achievements in the study of complex systems was Zipf’s
            identification of scaling laws in language and other social phenomena <ptr target="#zipf2012"/>.
            Studies of scaling can help us understand the relationship between common and uncommon
            observations, and are particularly suited to studies of language, which relies both on
            the utility of some elements, and the specificity of others. A rank distribution
            describes the relationship between the frequency of a word’s appearance, and its
            resulting rank among all words in the text. Zipf’s law shows that there is an inverse
            relationship between the frequency and rank of words in a text, and that the most common
            20% of the unique words in a text account for 80% of overall word frequency. It was
            first observed by Zipf that the rank distribution of words in a text follows a <emph>power law</emph>
            <mml:math>
               <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">F</mi>
               <mfenced xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" separators="|">
                  <mrow>
                     <mi>r</mi>
                  </mrow>
               </mfenced>
               <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">=</mo>
               <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">c</mi>
               <msup xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                  <mrow>
                     <mi>r</mi>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow>
                     <mo>-</mo>
                     <mi mathvariant="normal">α</mi>
                  </mrow>
               </msup>
               <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">,</mo>
            </mml:math> where <mml:math>
               <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">r</mi>
            </mml:math> is a word’s rank, <mml:math>
               <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">F</mi>
               <mfenced xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" separators="|">
                  <mrow>
                     <mi>r</mi>
                  </mrow>
               </mfenced>
            </mml:math> is its frequency, with <mml:math>
               <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" mathvariant="normal">α</mi>
               <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">≃</mo>
               <mn xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">1</mn>
            </mml:math>. As early as 1996, natural language (in the context of computational
            linguistics) was cited explicitly as an example of the recently coined <quote rend="inline">complex adaptive
               systems</quote> <ptr target="#balasubrahmanyan1996"/>. </p>
         <p>While primary interest here is paid to its appearance and seeming ubiquity in language,
            the same class of distributions have been observed in phenomena across a wide range of
            fields including physics, biology, psychology, sociology, urban studies, and engineering
            <ptr target="#clauset2009"/> <ptr target="#martinezmekler2009"/>. </p>
         <p>One shortcoming noted in many evaluations of Zipf's law in text is that power law
            scaling breaks down toward the tails of these empirical distributions, meaning that the
            lowest ranked words do not seem to follow Zipf’s law. Recent work by Williams et al.
            <ptr target="#williams2015b"/> showed that power law scaling holds over more orders of magnitude when
            randomly partitioned phrases are used rather than individual words. That study also
            suggested a refocusing of corpus linguistic attention from words to phrases as essential
            elements of language. Further work by Williams et al. (<ref target="#williams2015a">2015a</ref>) suggested that changes in
            scaling in Zipf distributions of large corpora can be attributed to text mining. Few, if
            any, attempts have been made to apply Zipf's law to phraseological lexica.</p>
         <p>With large amounts of newly digitized text, corpus linguistics and
            lexicology/lexicography have seen renewed wider interest, and new results. Can these
            methods be used to tell new stories that are of interest to those working in the
            humanities? And in particular, how can that work embed itself into the existing wealth
            of knowledge accrued by those disciplines. In this case, how can computational work on
            proverbs situate itself in the existing knowledge-base of paremiology?</p>
         <p>In their seminal 2011 paper, Michel et al. discussed the newly created Google Books
            corpus, and coined the term <q>culturomics</q> to describe the nascent discipline concerned
            with observable trends in the use of <emph>n</emph>-grams over time <ptr target="#michel2011"/>. They present several case studies, among them trends in the use of “influenza”
            with historical outbreaks, and the use of geographical and antagonistic terms alongside
            the history of the American Civil War. These case studies make use of time series data
            and relative frequency to tell complex stories of interest from simple queries. </p>
         <p>Pechenick et al. note that there are serious issues with assertions that Google Books
            offers a reliable representation of culture. For one, books are not indexed by
            popularity, and each book appears only once. As a result, the linguistic contributions
            of the most popular books are weighted equally with the least popular <ptr target="#pechenick2015a"/>.
            Secondly, the increase in volume of scientific publications in the last century causes
            the last century of English as a whole to be relatively skewed towards that genre. For
            instance, enormously influential books like <title rend="italic">To Kill a
            Mockingbird</title>, <title rend="italic">I Know Why the Caged Bird Sings</title>, <title
               rend="italic">Mockingjay</title>, or <title rend="italic">Harry Potter and the Order of the
               Phoenix</title> are only represented once, and share the same weight as even the most
            obscure books. In the last century, the rise in volume of scientific and academic
            publication drastically increased the relative influence of this type of writing. Here,
            we examine only the English Fiction subset of the corpus, which is a less problematic
            subset <ptr target="#pechenick2015b"/>. </p>
         <p>Other work by Reagan et al. utilized the timelines <emph>within</emph> texts
            to evaluate the <q>emotional arc</q> of a text, given word valence (sentiment) data.
            Emotional arcs were created by plotting the changing sentiment of words in a text as it
            progresses: from beginning to end, how positive or negative is the overall languge in a
            given section? Inspired by Kurt Vonnegut's rejected Master's thesis (in anthropology) on
            the shapes of stories, they found that the emotional arcs of most stories in the
            Gutenberg corpus could be reduced to a handful of paradigmatic shapes <ptr target="#reagan2016"/>.</p>
         <p>Work by Underwood et al. used historical use of gendered names and words to reveal
            trends in gender representation in literature using data from the HathiTrust digital
            library <ptr target="#underwood2018"/>.</p>
         <p>StoryWrangler, a tool recently developed by Alshaabi et al. allows users to explore the
            temporal dynamics of <emph>n</emph>-grams found on Twitter <ptr target="#alshaabi2020"/>.
            Using a data set reflecting a random 10% of Twitter since 2008 (presently over 150
            billion tweets), Storywrangler tracks the prevalence of <emph>n</emph>-grams
            on a daily scale. <emph>n</emph>-grams are portrayed via rank by popularity,
            and convey the rise/dynamics of President Trump (further depicted in the PoTUSometer)
            <ptr target="#dodds2021"/>, or the meteoric rise, and continued influence of Justin Bieber (of
            surprising relevance to this work). Unlike the Google Books <emph
            >n</emph>-gram Corpus, StoryWrangler is notable in its ability to track phrases in both
            original tweets and retweets, conveying aspects of popularity through amplification. </p>
         <p>Beyond simple words and phrases, data have been used to track the progression of ideas.
            For instance, Leskovec et al.'s paper on <q>meme-tracking</q> tracked the progression and
            mutation of popular sayings as they proliferated through news reporting and blogging
            <ptr target="#leskovec2009"/>.</p>
         <p>Recently, <q>Computational Folkloristics</q> has gained recognition as an area of study, with
            a 2016 issue of the <title rend="italic">Journal of American Folklore</title> being devoted to
            the subject <ptr target="#tangherlini2016"/>. Using classification, networks, geographical data,
            temporal data, and digitized text, folklorists and other interested academics have
            explored new possibilities in understanding texts and cultural history. The <title rend="italic">Danish
            Folklore Nexus</title> developed by Abello et al. provides tools for large-scale analysis of
            Danish folk tales and stories, aiding in classification of stories, or mapping their
            similarity to others through networks. Tools like this can augment traditional methods
            of studying folklore, using data-driven methodology to guide future avenues of folklore
            research <ptr target="#abello2012"/>. This represents a paradigmatic example of a computational tool
            participating in the continued discourse around folklore, without being an end in and of
            itself.</p></div>
         <div>
   
            <head>Data and Methods</head>
        
         <p>In an effort to quantify the ecology of proverbial language, a list of over 14,000
            proverbs was obtained from Mieder's <title rend="italic">Dictionary of American
               Proverbs</title> <ptr target="#mieder1992"/>. Proverbs were stored in an SQL database for ease of
            access, and matched for frequency with four distinct corpora:</p>
         <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>The Gutenberg Corpus (English)</item>
            <item>
               The <title rend="italic">New York Times</title> (1988-2007)</item>
            <item>The Google Books <hi rend="italic">n</hi>-gram Corpus (1800-2000)</item>
            <item>Twitter (2008-2020)</item>
         </list>
         <p>For Google Books, the proverb <q>shit happens</q> was added to the set of proverbs to
            illustrate the emergence of a modern proverb.</p>
         <p>Individual corpora were collected as follows.</p>
         
         <div>
            <head>A. Gutenberg</head>
         
         <p>The Gutenberg corpus comprises over 60,000 collected published documents spanning
            several centuries. The present study restricts its use to the subset of documents in
            English. As the metadata for the Gutenberg corpus does not consistently encode the date
            of original publication, temporal data was collected using author birth dates (gathered
            from the gutenbergr library for R) <ptr target="#robinson2020"/>. These were used in place of
            publication dates, as the publication dates in the corpus seldom represent the original
            publication, instead they represent the digitized edition. For temporal analysis,
            documents without authors and their birth dates were omitted.</p>
         <p>The Gutenberg corpus comes with several caveats. Firstly, works were curated by
            perceived importance. Works also disproportionately represent the 18th and 19th
            centuries, and for this reason much of our work with Gutenberg focuses on this period.
            Several authors have much of their extensive oeuvre represented in the corpus (e.g.,
            Anthony Trollope, Mark Twain), which could compromise a more objective view of English
            writing tendencies of the period.</p></div>
            <div>
         
            <head>B. The <title rend="italic">New York Times</title></head>
         
         <p>Data from the <title rend="italic">New York Times</title> were gathered from the <title
               rend="italic">New York Times</title> Annotated Corpus of 1.8 million articles from
            1987-2007 [Sandhaus 2008]. The data are organized in NTIF (News Industry Text Format)
            formatted XML-readable documents. The corpus includes obituaries and other short pieces
            in addition to more traditional news articles.</p></div>
            <div>
         
            <head>C. Google Books</head>
         
         <p>The 2020 English Fiction Google <emph>n</emph>-grams corpus consists of every
               <emph>n</emph>-gram that appears at least 40 times in its set of millions
            of digitized books. For each <emph>n</emph>-gram the corpus provides on each
            year it appears in the data set, the frequency with which it appeared that year, and the
            number of documents it appeared in that year <ptr target="#michel2011"/>. Unlike Gutenberg and the <title
               rend="italic">New York Times</title>, Google Books does not contain the raw text of the
            concerned documents, rather it displays the counts for popular <title rend="italic"
            >n</title>-grams in the corpus, organized by <title rend="italic">n-</title>gram length. This
            creates an obvious limitation, where only phrases of the same length can be studied
            together. </p></div>
            <div>
      
            <head>Twitter</head>
         
         <p>Data from Twitter was accessed through the Vermont Complex Systems Center's
            StoryWrangler API <ptr target="#alshaabi2020"/>. StoryWrangler receives a randomly selected 1/10th of
            each day's tweets from Twitter's Decahose API (including retweets), and organizes <emph>n</emph>-grams by rank and frequency. Data for 2-gram and 3-gram proverbs
            were obtained though the tool, and were aggregated so the collection was case
            insensitive. Similar to Google Books, this corpus is organized by <emph
               >n-</emph>gram counts rather than full texts. </p></div>
            <div>
     
            <head>D. Data Processing and Visualization</head>
         
         <p>The data from all four corpora were processed using Python, and the libraries pandas and
            matplotlib were used for organization and visualization respectively <ptr target="#pandas2020"/>
            <ptr target="#hunter2007"/>. </p>
         <p>In our processing of Gutenberg and the <title rend="italic">New York Times</title>,
            punctuation in both proverbs and texts was removed. Twitter data were punctuation
            insensitive. Regular expressions were used to capture variations in punctuation when
            processing the Google Books <emph>n</emph>-gram Corpus. </p>
         <p>Estimating the frequency of a proverb’s use is essential to this work. Simple counts
            don’t lend themselves to comparing results between corpora of different sizes, and do
            not capture the frequency of the proverb in relation to the size of a single corpus.
            Relative frequency can be calculated simply by dividing the raw frequency by a quantity
            describing the size of a corpus (number of articles, number of <emph
            >n</emph>-grams, number of books, etc.) Expressed mathematically, it is calculated as: <mml:math>
               <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                  <mrow>
                     <mi>f</mi>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow>
                     <mi>r</mi>
                     <mi>e</mi>
                     <mi>l</mi>
                  </mrow>
               </msub>
               <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">=</mo>
               <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                  <mrow>
                     <mi>f</mi>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow>
                     <mi>t</mi>
                  </mrow>
               </msub>
               <maction xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" actiontype="lit">
                  <mo>/</mo>
               </maction>
               <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                  <mrow>
                     <mi>n</mi>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow>
                     <mi>t</mi>
                  </mrow>
               </msub>
            </mml:math> which is the frequency <mml:math>
               <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">f</mi>
            </mml:math> for time period <mml:math>
               <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">t</mi>
            </mml:math> divided by the number of documents <mml:math>
               <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">n</mi>
            </mml:math> found during time period <mml:math>
               <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">t</mi>
            </mml:math>. </p>
         <p>Zipf distributions were plotted using ranks of proverbs in a corpus, with rank 1 being
            the most frequent against their frequency. Zipf distribution plots are shown on a
            log-log scale as is standard, which displays less intuitive power law functions as more
            intuitive linear functions. For results and analysis, see Appendix A.</p>
         <p>A network approach will be useful in exploring how different books are connected by the
            proverbs they share. In this case, a connection is drawn between two books if they share
            at least one proverb. The resulting network emerges after this step is performed for
            each possible pair of books. In network analysis, an important metric is <emph>centrality</emph>, which in this case describes how well-connected a book
            is in the larger network. Specifically, we calculate <emph>betweenness
               centrality</emph>, which assesses how often a given book appears in the shortest path
            between any other two books in the network. A book with high betweenness centrality in
            this network appears in the path between many pairs of books in the network. For results
            and analysis, see Appendix B.</p>
         <p>Betweenness centrality in these networks is calculated as <mml:math>
               <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">b</mi>
               <mfenced xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" separators="|">
                  <mrow>
                     <mi>v</mi>
                  </mrow>
               </mfenced>
               <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">=</mo>
               <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                  <mo>∑</mo>
                  <mrow>
                     <mi>s</mi>
                     <mo>≠</mo>
                     <mi>v</mi>
                     <mo>≠</mo>
                     <mi>t</mi>
                  </mrow>
               </msub>
               <mrow xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                  <mfrac>
                     <mrow>
                        <msub>
                           <mrow>
                              <mi mathvariant="normal">σ</mi>
                           </mrow>
                           <mrow>
                              <mi>s</mi>
                              <mi>t</mi>
                           </mrow>
                        </msub>
                        <mfenced separators="|">
                           <mrow>
                              <mi>v</mi>
                           </mrow>
                        </mfenced>
                     </mrow>
                     <mrow>
                        <msub>
                           <mrow>
                              <mi mathvariant="normal">σ</mi>
                           </mrow>
                           <mrow>
                              <mi>s</mi>
                              <mi>t</mi>
                           </mrow>
                        </msub>
                     </mrow>
                  </mfrac>
               </mrow>
            </mml:math>,where <mml:math>
               <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                  <mrow>
                     <mi mathvariant="normal">σ</mi>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow>
                     <mi>s</mi>
                     <mi>t</mi>
                  </mrow>
               </msub>
               <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
            </mml:math>denotes the number of shortest paths between books <hi rend="italic">s</hi>
            and <hi rend="italic">t</hi>, and <mml:math>
               <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                  <mrow>
                     <mi mathvariant="normal">σ</mi>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow>
                     <mi>s</mi>
                     <mi>t</mi>
                  </mrow>
               </msub>
               <mfenced xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" separators="|">
                  <mrow>
                     <mi>v</mi>
                  </mrow>
               </mfenced>
               <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
            </mml:math>denotes the number of those paths that also pass through book <hi
               rend="italic">v</hi>.</p>
         <p>Most processing was performed using the Vermont Advanced Computing Core (VACC) located
            at the University of Vermont. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
        
            <head>Results</head>
        <div>
        
            <head>Gutenberg</head>
         
         <p>While the most popular entry in the Gutenberg corpus and the Google Books <emph>n</emph>-gram corpus was the phrase <quote rend="inline">hold your tongue,</quote> this phrase is
            classified as a proverbial expression rather than a proverb (its use requires outside
            context). For clarity of focus the phrase has been excluded from figures in this
            section. <q>Sink or swim,</q> another proverbial expression, has been left in. In light of
            the limitations of the Gutenberg corpus detailed in Methods, it is difficult to make
            claims about the trends of proverb use over time (Figure 1). It is clear from the data
            shown in Figure 1 that proverbs appear in a remarkable portion of the documents in the
            corpus. <quote rend="inline">The sooner the better</quote> for example, appears in nearly one in every ten
            documents in the early 1800s.</p> 
         <figure>
            <head>Time series for the 16 most popular proverbs in the Gutenberg corpus, ranked
               by overall count. These most common proverbs occur in a large portion of documents in
               the corpus for most of the period studied. For instance, <q>the sooner the better</q>
               regularly appeared in at least 5% of documents from the 19th century. Plots are ordered
               in the grid by rank first left to right, then top to bottom. Note that the vertical axis
               ranges vary across plots to highlight individual variation in time.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            <figDesc>sixteen frequency charts showing frequencies on the y axes and years on the x axes. The years go from 1800-1950</figDesc>
         </figure>
        </div>
            
            <div>
            <head>The <title rend="italic">New York Times</title></head>
         
         <p>Figure 2 shows time series plots for the 16 most common proverbs in The <title
               rend="italic">New York Times</title> Annotated Corpus. Shown are frequency binned by
            month and year, and normalized by article count. All articles are included in the count
            including smaller articles like obituaries (the average article count is 248 per issue).
            It is by no means a surprise that proverbs appear frequently in journalism; in fact
            Lau's study found as much <ptr target="#lau1996"/>. Not present in that work, is a temporal dimension
            (not to mention a different time period). It is clear in Figure 2 that the proverbs
            represented are used on a monthly or semi-monthly basis, and are rarely if ever absent
            in a year's publications. In these representations of proverb use, it is easier to
            identify use patterns and perhaps to extract narratives from their dynamics. The
            easiest, if somewhat trivial case is <quote rend="inline">to delay may mean to forget</quote> owes its yearly
            rhythm to its role as the NYT's charity tagline. Its frequency of use increased markedly
            over the period studied, though stayed confined to the winter holiday months. </p> 
         <figure>
            <head> Time series plots for the 16 most popular proverbs in the <title rend="italic">New York Times</title> from
               1997-2007 (ranked by overall count). The gray represent the data binned by month, and
               the orange represent the data binned by year. The proverb <q>to delay may mean to forget</q>
               owes its yearly rhythm to its role as the NYT's charity tagline. The frequencies are
               normalized by article count (obits, and non-body included). Plots are ordered in the
               grid by rank first left to right, then top to bottom.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            <figDesc>sixteen frequency charts showing frequency counts for key phrases over time. the y-axes show frequencies and the x-axes show years from 1988-2008</figDesc>
         </figure>
         
         <p>With the exception of <quote rend="inline">to delay may mean to forget,</quote> and consistent with accepted
            definitions of the proverb, the consistency with which proverbs are used in the <title
               rend="italic">New York Times</title> suggests they are employed widely for their utility
            in mapping general wisdom to a specific context. </p>
         <p>Nonetheless, prominent spikes in frequency can be associated with historical events. For
            instance, the brief several-fold increase in the use of <q>boys will be boys</q> around
            November of 1992 is likely attributed to a contentious and widely publicized sexual
            assault case at the time, which prompted additional discussion of rape culture. Before
            the trial, the president of the New Jersey chapter of the National Organization for
            Women was reported as saying, <quote rend="inline">We're going to stop this 'boys will be boys' attitude
            from continuing in this country.</quote> Meanwhile in the trial, the lawyer for the defense
            excused the rapists’ actions, telling the jury, <quote rend="inline">boys will be boys</quote> <ptr target="#glaberson1992"/> <ptr target="#hanley1992"/>.</p>
         <p>The maximum in use of <quote rend="inline">pay as you go</quote> in 2004 seems to correspond with discussion around
            President Bush and the Republican party’s budget plans, referencing the <quote rend="inline">pay as you go</quote>
            budget policy from the 1990's by which tax cuts and spending increases must not increase
            the defecit. Its increase in use in 1996 seems to owe to discussion of the Environmental
            Bond Act being proposed in New York at the time, which proponents argued would cause
            fewer delays than <quote rend="inline">pay as you go</quote> funding for environmental clean-up <ptr target="#voteyes1996"/> <ptr target="#henry1996"/>. </p></div>
            <div>
               
            <head>Google Books</head>
        
         <p>In Figure 3 are time series plots for the 12 most common 2-gram proverbs in the Google
               <emph>n</emph>-grams corpus. Here the gray represents yearly frequency
            (counted once per volume), and the orange represents the five-year rolling average,
            normalized by the number of volumes in a given year. One can see clearly from the figure
            the emergence of several more recent proverbs: <q>safety first,</q> <q>money talks,</q> and <q>shit
            happens.</q> </p>
               
               
               <figure>
                  <head>Time series plots for the 12 most popular 2-gram proverbs in the Google Books
                     n-gram Corpus (ranked by overall count). The gray represent the yearly frequency, while
                     the orange represent the five-year rolling average. The dramatic increase in use of the
                     proverbs <q>shit happens</q> and <q>safety first</q> correspond with previous scholarship on their
                     emergence. Plots are ordered in the grid by rank first left to right, then top to
                     bottom.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                  <figDesc>nine frequency charts showing the frequencies of key phrases over time. The y axes all show frequencies and the x axes show years from 1800-2000</figDesc>
               </figure>
         
         <p><q>Safety first</q> exhibits a precipitous rise in usage in the early 20th century.
            Specifically, in 1912, the National Safety Council (NSC) in the US adopted the phrase as
            its slogan to promote standards of worker safety, though the Safety First Movement was
            initiated by US Steel in 1906. Its origin has been traced back to at least 1818 <ptr target="#mieder2019"/>. The data shown in Figure 3 support the history of its popularization <ptr target="#swuste2010"/> <ptr target="#mieder1992"/>.</p>
         <p>Previous scholarship on the proverb <q>shit happens</q> (which does not appear in <title
               rend="italic">The Dictionary of American Proverbs</title>) traced its origin to the year
            1944, and its rise in popularity corresponds to its humorous use as a bumper sticker,
            and cultural controversy (and legal battles) associated with it <ptr target="#mieder2004"/> <ptr target="#georgia1991"/>. It’s increasing currency is illustrated in its appearance in Tom Clancy’s popular
            novel, <title rend="italic">Clear and Present Danger</title>: <quote rend="inline">Look, in field operations
               anything can go wrong … We are not immune. Shit happens, as they say</quote> <ptr target="#clancy1990"/>. It
            also famously appeared in the movie <title rend="italic">Forrest Gump</title> <ptr target="#zemeckis1994"/>.</p>
         <p>Figure 4 shows time series plots for the 16 most popular 3-gram proverbs in the Google
            Books <emph>n</emph>-gram corpus. Though the proverb <q>never say never</q>
            originated in 1887 <ptr target="#mieder1992"/>, it is evident that it gained far wider popularity in
            the late 1900s. Though the proverb <q>enough is enough</q> dates at least to 1546 <ptr target="#mieder1992"/>, its popularity seems to vastly increase throughout the 20th century. The proverb
            <q>divide and conquer</q> seems to have briefly gained popularity around the World War II
            era. </p>
               
               <figure>
                  <head>Time series plots for the 16 most popular 3-gram proverbs in the Google Books
                     Ngram Corpus (ranked by overall count). The gray represents the yearly frequency, while
                     the orange represents the 5 year rolling average. The rise in popularity of the proverb
                     <q>never say never</q> is shown. A period of increased usage of the proverb <q>divide and
                     conquer</q> corresponds with the World War II era. Plots are ordered in the grid by rank
                     first left to right, then top to bottom.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                  <figDesc>sixteen frequency charts showing the frequencies of key phrases over time. The y-axes show frequency counts and the x-axes show years from 1800 to 2000</figDesc>
               </figure>
               
               
         
            </div>
            <div>
               
            <head>Twitter</head>
         <p>On Twitter, the four most common 2-gram proverbs, on average, don't seem to exhibit much
            variability in their usage (Figure 5). The proverbs <q>be yourself</q> and <q>time flies</q> seem
            to remain above <mml:math>
               <msup xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                  <mrow>
                     <mn>10</mn>
                  </mrow>
                  <mrow>
                     <mo>-</mo>
                     <mn>6</mn>
                  </mrow>
               </msup>
            </mml:math>, or 1 in every million 2-grams on Twitter during the period studied. An
            increase in usage of “safety first” in early 2020 may be related to the onset of the
            coronavirus pandemic during the same period. </p>
               
               
               <figure>
                  <head>Time series plots for the nine most popular 2-gram proverbs on Twitter (ranked
                     by overall count). The gray represents the daily frequency, while the orange represents
                     the 30 day rolling average. The proverbs <q>be yourself</q> and <q>time flies</q> maintain
                     popularity over the period studied. Notably, the <q>safety first</q> shows an increase in
                     popularity in early 2020, possibly relating to the coronavirus pandemic. Plots are
                     ordered in the grid by rank first left to right, then top to bottom.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                  <figDesc>screenshot of nine frequency charts showing 2-grams of key phrases over time on Twitter. Charts are arranged by rank with <q>be yourself</q> ranking first. The graphs are colored with orange and gray to display frequiencies</figDesc>
               </figure>
         
         <p>Exhibited on Twitter (Figure 6), the convenience of proverbs as succinct narratives has
            made them useful in several titular media events in the past decade. Of note, Figure 6
            shows marked shifts in frequency of <q>never say never,</q> and <q>love is blind.</q> <q>Never say
            never</q> owes its initial attention in 2010 to Justin Bieber's single of the same title
               (<title rend="italic">Justin Bieber: Never Say Never</title>), repeated as his slogan and
            title of a biographical documentary. This was not the first film to utilize the proverb
            in its title; Sean Connery's final performance as James Bond was titled <title
               rend="italic">Never Say Never Again</title> (1983). </p>
               
               
               
               <figure>
                  <head>Time series plots for 3-gram proverbs on Twitter (ranked by overall count).
                     The gray represents the daily frequency, while the orange represents the 30 day rolling
                     average. The proverb <q>never say never</q> owes its meteoric rise in popularity in 2010 to
                     popular musician Justin Bieber's single and biographical documentary of the same name.
                     <q>never say never</q> remains the most popular proverb on Twitter until 2016, when it is
                     supplanted by <q>enough is enough</q> which has steadily gained popularity in the last
                     decade, owed in part to its constant use by Senator Bernie Sanders, and punctuated by
                     reactions to tragedies related to gun and police violence. Plots are ordered in the grid
                     by rank first left to right, then top to bottom.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                  <figDesc>screenshot of sixteen frequency charts showing 3-grams of key phrases over time on Twitter. Charts are arranged by rank with <q>never say never</q> ranking first. The graphs are colored with orange and gray to display frequiencies</figDesc>
               </figure>
               
        
         <p>Figure 7 shows the dynamics of <q>never say never</q> on Twitter in more detail. We observe
            first its meteoric rise in popularity at the time of <title rend="italic">Never Say
               Never</title>'s (song) release as the lead single off the soundtrack for a modern remake
            of the <title rend="italic">Karate Kid</title> movie (roughly two magnitudes in a single day).
            At the time of the single's official release on June 8th, 2010, <q>never say never</q> was
            the 63rd most used 3-gram on Twitter. When <title rend="italic">Justin Bieber: Never Say
               Never</title> was released on January 31, 2011, <q>never say never</q> was the 34th most
            common 3-gram on Twitter; for comparison, <q>I love you</q> was 22nd at the time. </p>
               
               
               
               <figure>
                  <head>Daily relative frequency of the 3-gram <q>never say never</q> on Twitter. While
                     <q>never say never</q> was already popular on Twitter as of 2008, its popularity was
                     amplified in 2010 by the release of Justin Bieber's single entitled <title rend="quotes">Never say never,</title>
                     and his subsequent biographical documentary of the same name. Remarkably, it remained
                     the most popular proverb on Twitter for almost six years, punctuated by anniversaries
                     and reruns of the movie, until it was surpassed by <q>enough is enough</q> in 2016.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                  <figDesc>screenshot of one frequency chart showing 3-grams of key phrases over time on Twitter. The chart shows the frequency of the phrase <q>never say never</q> with the highest peak in 2010. The graphs are colored with orange and gray to display frequiencies</figDesc>
               </figure>
        
         <p>Remarkably, the popularity of <q>never say never</q> on Twitter decayed so slowly that it did
            not reach its pre-Bieber frequency until 2016. The continued presence of the proverb in
            Twitter discourse suggests that in the wake of its initial rise, it was more frequently
            adopted to general non-Bieber usage. (A similarly popular 3-gram, non-proverbial song of
            that year, <title rend="quotes">Rock That Body</title> appeared and disappeared from the Twitter discourse in the
            span of a few months). While the enormity and fervor of Bieber's fanbase at the time (a
            period called <q>Bieber fever</q> <ptr target="#tweedle2012"/>) certainly contributed to its popularity,
            its continued use over a five-year period is compelling evidence that the proverb became
            a more integral part of the Twitter lexicon for a time. </p>
         <p>In 2020, <title rend="quotes">Love is Blind</title> became the title of a literally minded reality dating show in
            which participants were quarantined in private rooms, only communicating via audio
            interfaces. In this instance, the proverb was not only an apt description of the show's
            narrative, but a template for its formation. Additionally, it came to represent a
            narrative solution to the isolation imposed by the concurrent pandemic. The increase in
            the phrase's popularity seems only to have lasted for the month of the show's release,
            after which it seems to settle at its former rate of use. The proverb itself is ancient,
            and translations exist nearly every European language.</p>
         <p>While with <q>never say never</q> (the most popular proverb on Twitter), we see a sudden rise
            and slow decay, we see a different pattern in the second most popular proverb, <q>enough
            is enough.</q> </p>
         <p>From 2016 to the present, we see a steady increase in the frequency of <q>enough is
            enough</q> on Twitter (Figure 8). Recent work by Mieder attributes its renewed popularity
            in part to its constant use by Bernie Sanders <ptr target="#mieder2019"/>. Unlike <q>never say never</q>
            there does not seem to be a single event that precipitates this trend. An investigation
            into the several local maxima (brief spikes in occurrence) suggests a possible narrative
            correspondence. Many of these local maxima correspond to events related to either police
            violence or mass shootings.</p>
               
               
               <figure>
                  <head>Daily relative frequency of the 3-gram <q>enough is enough</q> on Twitter. The
                     popularity of <q>enough is enough</q> on Twitter grew steadily over the last decade, and it
                     has been the most popular proverb on Twitter since 2016, perhaps originating from its
                     consistent use by Senator Bernie Sanders <ptr target="#mieder2019"/>. It has since become associated
                     with growing protests against police brutality and gun violence. Annotations reflect
                     widely reported violent events and protests (with the exception of the 2018 US midterm
                     elections). The stark simplicity of this sixteenth century proverb evokes a narrative of
                     repetition past the point of tolerance <ptr target="#mieder1992"/>. In this instance, beginning as a
                     condemnation of the continued reaffirmation of the status quo in US politics by Senator
                     Sanders, it is now popular as collective outcry against political inaction in the wake
                     of regular mass shootings in the US, and a lack of accountability in the killing of
                     black Americans by police. The changing significance and popularity of the proverb in
                     the past decade displays the aptitude of proverbial speech to be successfully employed
                     in varying contexts, and its potential to illustrate narrative commonalities between
                     phenomena.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
                  <figDesc>screenshot of one frequency chart showing 3-grams of key phrases over time on Twitter. The chart shows the frequency of the phrase <q>enough is enough</q> steady useage from 2010-2020 and peaks around major international events such as the Pulse nightclub shooting and the Parkland school shooting. The graph is colored with orange and gray to display frequiencies</figDesc>
               </figure>
               
               
          
         <p>Famously, survivors of the Parkland shooting in 2018 appeared on the cover of <title
            rend="italic">Time</title> magazine with a simple title: <title rend="quotes">Enough.</title> <ptr target="#alter2018"/>.
            Coverage of the March for Our Lives against gun violence in the <title rend="italic">New
               York Times</title> included the title: <title rend="italic">March for Our Lives Highlights:
                  Students Protesting Guns Say <q>Enough Is Enough</q></title> <ptr target="#marchforourlives2018"/>. When
            protesters marched in DC in the wake of the murder of George Floyd, Politico's coverage
            was titled: <title rend="italic"><q>Enough is enough</q>: Thousands descend on D.C. for largest
               George Floyd protest yet</title> <ptr target="#semones2020"/>. Inasmuch as proverbs can create
            metaphorical mappings from a paradigmatic situation (or narrative) onto a present one,
            <q>enough is enough</q> represents a compelling narrative of continued injustice, and a
            critical point of retaliation. The data from Twitter display a narrative of repeated
            tragedy in spite of public outcry. The proverb was most popular during the 2018 US
            midterm elections, during which gun control was a major issue.</p></div></div>
         
         <div>
            
            <head>
         Concluding remarks</head>
            
            
         <p>In this study, four corpora reveal four markedly different patterns of proverb use,
            which taken each within the limits of their methods of collection, can offer piecemeal
            insight into the relationship between phrases and the written record. Observing all four
            side by side, it should become clear that generalizing linguistic tendencies from
            individual corpora may not be a good idea. Even among corpora with significant temporal
            overlap the results differ due to both the scope of each corpus, and the way in which
            data are collected from texts. The present approach of studying data from distinct
            domains allows for both a more limited and more useful interpretation of the results: We
            can only claim that results are representative of proverb use on Twitter for instance,
            rather than proverb use in English as a whole — an impossible achievement.</p>
         <p>So, rather than using the results to speak about <emph>all proverbs</emph> or
            all of language, we may use it as lens by which to identify areas (within a corpus) that
            warrant a closer look. In studies of common words, the concept the word represents is
            often dependent on its context, and evaluating context for each instance in a large
            corpus is generally not feasible. Proverbs carry with them a paradigmatic context</p>
         <p>Unlike studies of common words, whose interpretation is often dependent on their
            context, we show that proverbs allow us to perform a different kind of analysis that
            focuses on the historical use of a stable paradigmatic narrative.</p>
         <p>While much work up to this point uses computational methods to take a broader view of
            text than traditional methods of humanities scholarship, that broader view often
            necessarily obscures the context in which linguistic elements are used. A single word or
            short sequence of words may carry any number of meanings dependent on the words or
            concepts around it. Proverbs carry their own paradigmatic context which makes their
            meaning and use fairly consistent. While proverbs may be employed in many different
            practical situations, the paradigmatic situation they represent remains the same. In
            searching for proverbs, we are able to see how a paradigmatic context is applied to
            different practical contexts. The results of this search show not only the frequency of
            some sequence of words, but also the frequency with which a particular cultural concept
            is employed.</p>
         <p>
            <emph>N</emph>-gram based methods of analyzing common phrases in texts suffer
            from the inclusion of many sequences of words which do not have any self-contained
            meaning. Our work, in which phrases must be represented in the lexicon, ensures that
            each phrase studied is meaningful. In an analysis of all 3-grams in a text, a very
            common phrase without a fixed meaning, like <q>and this is</q> could obscure a far less
            common meaningful phrase like <q>love is blind,</q> even though it is common among phrases
            with fixed meanings. Our study of a specific cultural-linguistic phenomenon highlights
            the utility of using an extensive lexicon to isolate the phenomenon being studied. </p>
         <p>We demonstrate that lexically significant phrases (here proverbs), which are relatively
            stable and self-contained, can discern trends that words or <emph
            >n</emph>-grams would likely miss. In each corpus studied, evidence of proverbs’ changing
            use over time is shown to validate previous scholarship, reflect cultural events, and
            offer a quantitative, longitudinal perspective unable to be achieved by traditional
            methods in the study of proverbs.</p>
         <p>The study of common and flexible phrases seems to lend itself to this mode of inquiry.
            Through novel or context-specific words and phrases, we are able to observe discourse
            around specific phenomena (<q>pizzagate,</q> <q>pandemic,</q> or <q>Make America Great Again</q>). In
            contrast, through more generic culturally significant phrases, we may be able to observe
            how we organize specific phenomena into the paradigmatic narratives they represent.</p>
         <p>Much attention has been paid to the use of words and <emph>n</emph>-grams in
            general in large corpora, but it is difficult to extract from them instances of
            individual narrative or metaphorical language use. Proverbs, in their tendency to act as
            both narrative and metaphor, and in their often relatively fixed structure, are an ideal
            test case for our ability to observe broader cultural narratives through the piecemeal,
            routine stories employed by the folk. Studies of n-grams tend to organize their
            interpretation around n-grams which attain a specific historical use-case. In our study
            of proverbs, we are able to trace the progression of a paradigm and its varying
            application to historical changes and events. </p>
         <p>A natural limitation of this study, and any study that uses extant data to study
            language, is the issue of representativeness. In this study that limitation is twofold:
            Both the lexicon for directing the search, and the data being searched are inherently
            limited. While <title rend="italic">The Dictionary of American Proverbs</title> is extensive,
            and represents much that is known of proverbs in America, it naturally excludes new
            proverbs and does not account for many ways in which the structure of the proverbs it
            contains may be manipulated in their practical use. There are lexical resources that
            address recent proverbs, for example <title rend="italic">The Dictionary of Modern
               Proverbs</title>, and the methodology of this study may be readily applied to such
            lexica <ptr target="#doyle2012"/>. Previous studies on proverb frequency have relied on composite
            corpora, namely variations of the BNC (British National Corpus), which contains manually
            curated selections from several domains of text. As shown in this study, composite
            corpora may miss important differences in proverb usage between domains. </p>
         <p>Fieldwork (digital and otherwise) continues to be important in identifying new proverbs
            and changing structures of existing proverbs. This task may be aided in the future by
            tools like StoryWrangler, that track <emph>n</emph>-gram rank, likely
            capturing new proverbs in the process. The task then would be extracting likely proverbs
            from these data, which would require linguistic, cultural, and computational expertise. </p>
         <p>Much of proverb scholarship has been concerned with the idea of a <q>paremiological
            minimum</q>: A minimum proverbial lexicon for a language and culture. As shown by Lau
            (1996), and again in the present study, computational studies of the frequency of
            proverb use can contribute to the understanding of these minima, as those proverbs which
            seem ubiquitous in large corpora ought to be understood by speakers of a language.
            Temporal analysis of their frequency may further validate that their frequency is
            related to enduring currency among the folk, rather than correspondence with a specific
            occurrence. Another concern in paremiology and phraeseology is the origins of sayings.
            Work like the present study can serve to both validate and expand on previous
            scholarship on the history of phrases. </p>
         <p>In the study of the statistical distribution of natural language, there exists the idea
            of a kernel lexicon, a subset of words that are essential to communication using a given
            language. Much literature on the study of culture and education has focused on what one
            might consider a <q>minimum of cultural literacy</q>. Special attention has been paid to
            which proverbs constitute part of that minimum. It is clear from this study that the
            most common proverbs vary considerably between corpora. Given the prevalence of these
            popular proverbs in their respective contexts, we can posit that English learners would
            benefit in their comprehension of the language if they were familiar with these
            proverbs.</p>
         <p>Analyses of the frequency and rank of proverbs in this study (shown in Appendix A)
            verify that with ever increasing amounts of machine-readable textual data, we may
            produce longitudinal phraseological studies. </p>
         <p> Traditionally, the study of metaphor in language has relied on theoretical
            interpretations <ptr target="#lakoff1985"/>. This study opens up the possibility for new avenues in
            the study of metaphor that incorporate the currency of specific metaphors among the
            folk. A natural extension of this study would be employing a similar method to study
            idioms and conventional metaphors. </p>
         <p>As machine comprehension of natural language becomes increasingly important, this area
            too, would benefit from an expanded lexicon that includes proverbs and routine formulae,
            and understanding of metaphor may be assisted by a more basic understanding of the
            mapping from general to specific situations that exists in the use of proverbs.</p></div>
         
         <div>
         <head>Acknowledgements</head>
         <p>Thank you to David Dewhurst, Josh Minot, Michael Arnold, Nicholas Allgaier, Thayer
            Alshaabi for providing invaluable guidance in the writing of this paper. The authors are
            grateful for the computing resources provided by the Vermont Advanced Computing Core
            which was supported in part by NSF award No. OAC-1827314, and financial support from the
            Massachusetts Mutual Life Insurance Company to CMD and PSD.</p></div>
         
      <div>
         <head>Appendix A</head>
         <p>Figure 9 shows Zipf distributions for entries from Mieder's <title rend="italic"
               >Dictionary of American Proverbs</title> (1992) for each of the four corpora studied,
            using 3-gram proverbs for Google Books and Twitter. While the distributions exhibit some
            Zipf’s Law-like behavior (heavy tails), we do not observe robust power-law scaling for
            all proverbs. We find the largest number of distinct proverbs appearing in Gutenberg and
            the <title rend="italic">New York Times</title>, on the order of thousands, with the Google Books and Twitter
            examples showing many fewer. We note that Zipf's law for words does not itself extend
            over many orders of magnitude <ptr target="#williams2015a"/>, typically only 2 or 3, and that it is
            meaningful, mixed length phrases that present many orders of magnitude of scaling
            <ptr target="#williams2015b"/>. The Zipf distributions for proverbs are thus comparable to what we see
            for single words. </p>
         <p>With a more sophisticated method of proverb detection, one that captures minor
            variations in phrase structure, we would expect to see some adjustments to the Zipf
            distributions we have observed, though a priori it is not clear how. Short, robust
            proverbs (<q>time flies</q>) will be well counted, while longer ones for which, say,
            constituent function words might be changed based on context or era (<q>he/she/they who
            hesitates…</q>) would only see their apparent observed frequency of usage grow.</p>
       
         <figure>
         <head>Zipf distributions for entries from Mieder's <title rend="italic">Dictionary of American Proverbs</title>
            <ptr target="#mieder1992"/>. For each corpus, proverbs are enumerated and shown on logarithmic axes as
            a function of rank, with <q>hold your tongue,</q> to <q>delay may mean to forget,</q> <q>time will
            tell,</q> and <q>never say never</q> topping the charts in Gutenberg, NYT, Google, and Twitter
            respectively. Each distribution exhibits heavy-tailed behavior, more prominently for
            Gutenberg and NYT.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
            <figDesc>frequency charts for for the phrases <q>hold your tongue,</q> to <q>delay may mean to forget,</q> <q>time will
               tell,</q> and <q>never say never</q> in the Project Gutenberg, NYT, Google Books, and Twitter</figDesc>
         </figure>
      </div>
         
         <div>
         <head>Appendix B</head>
         <p>The data for proverbs in the Gutenberg corpus were used to construct a network with
            documents as nodes, connected if a given proverb appears in both documents. When
            betweenness centrality was calculated for nodes in the network, surprisingly James
            Joyce's <title rend="italic">Ulysses</title> had the 14th highest centrality, close to several
            dictionaries of proverbs and quotations, and the collected works of Mark Twain (Table
            B-1). Creasy (2008) documented Joyce's use of proverbs in <title rend="italic">Ulysses</title>
            from a critical perspective, noting that they are often altered, and blend high and low
            culture in the work. As Joyce uses many fewer proverbs than a comprehensive proverbial
            dictionary, the book's centrality in this network implies that Joyce's use of proverbs
            is far from arbitrary, and that his choice of proverbs is purposefully situated in the
            broader context of English proverbial knowledge. </p>
         <table>
            <head>The 20 most central books by betweenness centrality, from a network of books
               connected by shared proverbs in Gutenberg. Notably, James Joyce's <title rend="italic"
                  >Ulysses</title> appears alongside several proverb and quotations collections, and the
               collected works of Mark Twain.</head>
            <row role="label">
               <cell/>
               <cell>Book</cell>
               <cell>btwn centrality</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>1</cell>
               <cell>Dictionary of Quotations</cell>
               <cell>0.043048</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>2</cell>
               <cell>Familiar Quotations</cell>
               <cell>0.022821</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>3</cell>
               <cell>Dictionary of English Proverbs and Proverbial Phrases</cell>
               <cell>0.014274</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>4</cell>
               <cell>A Polyglot of Foreign Proverbs</cell>
               <cell>0.013061</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>5</cell>
               <cell>The Entire Project Gutenberg Works of Mark Twain</cell>
               <cell>0.013041</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>6</cell>
               <cell>French Idioms and Proverbs</cell>
               <cell>0.010083</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>7</cell>
               <cell>Roget's Thesaurus</cell>
               <cell>0.009785</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>8</cell>
               <cell>Webster's Unabridged Dictionary</cell>
               <cell>0.007978</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>9</cell>
               <cell>U.S. Copyright Renewals 1950 – 1977</cell>
               <cell>0.006709</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>10</cell>
               <cell>The Project Gutenberg Complete Works of Gilbert Parker</cell>
               <cell>0.006278</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>11</cell>
               <cell>Proverb Lore</cell>
               <cell>0.006028</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>12</cell>
               <cell>Complete Project Gutenberg John Galsworthy Works</cell>
               <cell>0.003897</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>13</cell>
               <cell>Complete Project Gutenberg Works of George Meredith</cell>
               <cell>0.003660</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>14</cell>
               <cell>Ulysses</cell>
               <cell>0.003184</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>15</cell>
               <cell>The Historical Romances of Georg Ebers</cell>
               <cell>0.003168</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>16</cell>
               <cell>Familiar Quotations</cell>
               <cell>0.003007</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>17</cell>
               <cell>The Circle of Knowledge</cell>
               <cell>0.002886</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>18</cell>
               <cell>The Complete Poetic and Dramatic Works of Robert Browning</cell>
               <cell>0.002749</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>19</cell>
               <cell>Complete Project Gutenberg Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr. Works</cell>
               <cell>0.002657</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>20</cell>
               <cell>Motion Pictures, 1960-1969: Catalog of Copyright Entries</cell>
               <cell>0.002578</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         </div>
         <div>
         <head>Appendix C</head>
         <p>Tables 2-4 show the total count of the 50 most popular proverbs in</p>
         <p>their respective corpora. <pb/>
         </p>

         <table>
            <head>The top 50 proverbs and proverbial expressions (from the <title rend="italic">Dictionary of
               American Proverbs</title>) in the entire Gutenberg Corpus.</head>
            <row role="label">
               <cell/>
               <cell>Proverb</cell>
               <cell>Count</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>1</cell>
               <cell>hold your tongue</cell>
               <cell>2,284</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>2</cell>
               <cell>the sooner the better</cell>
               <cell>1,536</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>3</cell>
               <cell>be yourself</cell>
               <cell>739</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>4</cell>
               <cell>let bygones be bygones</cell>
               <cell>685</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>5</cell>
               <cell>time flies</cell>
               <cell>603</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>6</cell>
               <cell>alls well that ends well</cell>
               <cell>588</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>7</cell>
               <cell>one thing at a time</cell>
               <cell>580</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>8</cell>
               <cell>business is business</cell>
               <cell>534</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>9</cell>
               <cell>sink or swim</cell>
               <cell>531</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>10</cell>
               <cell>forgive and forget</cell>
               <cell>477</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>11</cell>
               <cell>take it or leave it</cell>
               <cell>436</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>12</cell>
               <cell>nothing is impossible</cell>
               <cell>421</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>13</cell>
               <cell>better late than never</cell>
               <cell>419</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>14</cell>
               <cell>every man for himself</cell>
               <cell>414</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>15</cell>
               <cell>know thyself</cell>
               <cell>394</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>16</cell>
               <cell>share and share alike</cell>
               <cell>372</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>17</cell>
               <cell>slow but sure</cell>
               <cell>363</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>18</cell>
               <cell>live and let live</cell>
               <cell>356</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>19</cell>
               <cell>the more the merrier</cell>
               <cell>352</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>20</cell>
               <cell>the die is cast</cell>
               <cell>348</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>21</cell>
               <cell>honesty is the best policy</cell>
               <cell>339</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>22</cell>
               <cell>to be or not to be</cell>
               <cell>335</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>23</cell>
               <cell>do or die</cell>
               <cell>322</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>24</cell>
               <cell>never say die</cell>
               <cell>319</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>25</cell>
               <cell>extremes meet</cell>
               <cell>289</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>26</cell>
               <cell>art for arts sake</cell>
               <cell>286</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>27</cell>
               <cell>all men are created equal</cell>
               <cell>265</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>28</cell>
               <cell>let well enough alone</cell>
               <cell>260</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>29</cell>
               <cell>time is money</cell>
               <cell>250</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>30</cell>
               <cell>no accounting for taste</cell>
               <cell>249</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>31</cell>
               <cell>peace at any price</cell>
               <cell>244</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>32</cell>
               <cell>tastes differ</cell>
               <cell>241</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>33</cell>
               <cell>history repeats itself</cell>
               <cell>235</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>34</cell>
               <cell>boys will be boys</cell>
               <cell>235</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>35</cell>
               <cell>charity begins at home</cell>
               <cell>231</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>36</cell>
               <cell>love is blind</cell>
               <cell>228</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>37</cell>
               <cell>the end justifies the means</cell>
               <cell>227</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>38</cell>
               <cell>one good turn deserves another</cell>
               <cell>224</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>39</cell>
               <cell>blood is thicker than water</cell>
               <cell>221</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>40</cell>
               <cell>not wisely but too well</cell>
               <cell>219</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>41</cell>
               <cell>all things work together for good</cell>
               <cell>213</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>42</cell>
               <cell>first come first served</cell>
               <cell>201</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>43</cell>
               <cell>keep the wolf from the door</cell>
               <cell>196</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>44</cell>
               <cell>dead men tell no tales</cell>
               <cell>195</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>45</cell>
               <cell>the wages of sin is death</cell>
               <cell>191</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>46</cell>
               <cell>seeing is believing</cell>
               <cell>187</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>47</cell>
               <cell>keep a stiff upper lip</cell>
               <cell>186</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>48</cell>
               <cell>ignorance is bliss</cell>
               <cell>185</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>49</cell>
               <cell>where theres a will theres a way</cell>
               <cell>183</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>50</cell>
               <cell>murder will out</cell>
               <cell>179</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         
         <table>
            <head>The top 50 proverbs and proverbial expressions (from the <title rend="italic">Dictionary of
               American Proverbs</title>) in the <title rend="italic">New York Times</title> from 1987-2007.</head>
            <row role="label">
               <cell/>
               <cell>Proverb</cell>
               <cell>Count</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>1</cell>
               <cell>to delay may mean to forget</cell>
               <cell>1,075</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>2</cell>
               <cell>enough is enough</cell>
               <cell>891</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>3</cell>
               <cell>time will tell</cell>
               <cell>864</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>4</cell>
               <cell>pay as you go</cell>
               <cell>597</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>5</cell>
               <cell>take it or leave it</cell>
               <cell>565</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>6</cell>
               <cell>do or die</cell>
               <cell>528</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>7</cell>
               <cell>first come first served</cell>
               <cell>463</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>8</cell>
               <cell>be yourself</cell>
               <cell>348</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>9</cell>
               <cell>father knows best</cell>
               <cell>307</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>10</cell>
               <cell>never say never</cell>
               <cell>276</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>11</cell>
               <cell>live and let live</cell>
               <cell>272</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>12</cell>
               <cell>money talks</cell>
               <cell>244</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>13</cell>
               <cell>the sooner the better</cell>
               <cell>240</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>14</cell>
               <cell>better late than never</cell>
               <cell>224</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>15</cell>
               <cell>sink or swim</cell>
               <cell>218</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>16</cell>
               <cell>boys will be boys</cell>
               <cell>213</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>17</cell>
               <cell>time flies</cell>
               <cell>205</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>18</cell>
               <cell>time is of the essence</cell>
               <cell>204</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>19</cell>
               <cell>divide and conquer</cell>
               <cell>198</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>20</cell>
               <cell>gentlemen prefer blondes</cell>
               <cell>192</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>21</cell>
               <cell>to be or not to be</cell>
               <cell>187</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>22</cell>
               <cell>the show must go on</cell>
               <cell>185</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>23</cell>
               <cell>time is money</cell>
               <cell>174</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>24</cell>
               <cell>talk is cheap</cell>
               <cell>167</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>25</cell>
               <cell>every man for himself</cell>
               <cell>166</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>26</cell>
               <cell>leave well enough alone</cell>
               <cell>163</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>27</cell>
               <cell>put up or shut up</cell>
               <cell>161</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>28</cell>
               <cell>business is business</cell>
               <cell>159</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>29</cell>
               <cell>accentuate the positive</cell>
               <cell>157</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>30</cell>
               <cell>forgive and forget</cell>
               <cell>151</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>31</cell>
               <cell>you get what you pay for</cell>
               <cell>142</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>32</cell>
               <cell>safety first</cell>
               <cell>142</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>33</cell>
               <cell>too little and too late</cell>
               <cell>140</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>34</cell>
               <cell>there is no easy way</cell>
               <cell>132</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>35</cell>
               <cell>let the chips fall where they may</cell>
               <cell>131</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>36</cell>
               <cell>all men are created equal</cell>
               <cell>129</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>37</cell>
               <cell>the more the merrier</cell>
               <cell>128</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>38</cell>
               <cell>history repeats itself</cell>
               <cell>122</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>39</cell>
               <cell>let bygones be bygones</cell>
               <cell>117</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>40</cell>
               <cell>one thing at a time</cell>
               <cell>113</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>41</cell>
               <cell>let nature take its course</cell>
               <cell>106</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>42</cell>
               <cell>never say die</cell>
               <cell>106</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>43</cell>
               <cell>seeing is believing</cell>
               <cell>102</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>44</cell>
               <cell>nothing is impossible</cell>
               <cell>100</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>45</cell>
               <cell>war is hell</cell>
               <cell>95</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>46</cell>
               <cell>the worst is yet to come</cell>
               <cell>85</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>47</cell>
               <cell>actions speak louder than words</cell>
               <cell>82</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>48</cell>
               <cell>gone but not forgotten</cell>
               <cell>82</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>49</cell>
               <cell>to each his own</cell>
               <cell>80</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>50</cell>
               <cell>let the buyer beware</cell>
               <cell>80</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         
         <table>
            <head>The top 50 3-gram proverbs and proverbial expressions (from the <title rend="italic">Dictionary of
               American Proverbs</title>) in the Google Books Ngram Corpus.</head>
            <row role="label">
               <cell/>
               <cell>Proverb</cell>
               <cell>Count</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>1</cell>
               <cell>hold your tongue</cell>
               <cell>131,426</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>2</cell>
               <cell>time will tell</cell>
               <cell>65,640</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>3</cell>
               <cell>forgive and forget</cell>
               <cell>45,189</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>4</cell>
               <cell>enough is enough</cell>
               <cell>43,149</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>5</cell>
               <cell>business is business</cell>
               <cell>30,101</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>6</cell>
               <cell>sink or swim</cell>
               <cell>26,315</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>7</cell>
               <cell>nothing is impossible</cell>
               <cell>25,695</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>8</cell>
               <cell>easy does it</cell>
               <cell>23,655</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>9</cell>
               <cell>do or die</cell>
               <cell>21,672</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>10</cell>
               <cell>time is money</cell>
               <cell>18,856</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>11</cell>
               <cell>practice makes perfect</cell>
               <cell>17,469</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>12</cell>
               <cell>never say never</cell>
               <cell>16,649</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>13</cell>
               <cell>divide and conquer</cell>
               <cell>15,673</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>14</cell>
               <cell>love is blind</cell>
               <cell>14,439</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>15</cell>
               <cell>seeing is believing</cell>
               <cell>12,951</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>16</cell>
               <cell>never say die</cell>
               <cell>12,329</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>17</cell>
               <cell>ignorance is bliss</cell>
               <cell>11,838</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>18</cell>
               <cell>history repeats itself</cell>
               <cell>11,529</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>19</cell>
               <cell>fair is fair</cell>
               <cell>10,456</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>20</cell>
               <cell>slow but sure</cell>
               <cell>9,898</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>21</cell>
               <cell>forewarned is forearmed</cell>
               <cell>9,860</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>22</cell>
               <cell>love conquers all</cell>
               <cell>9,839</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>23</cell>
               <cell>misery loves company</cell>
               <cell>9,654</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>24</cell>
               <cell>facts are facts</cell>
               <cell>8,944</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>25</cell>
               <cell>time will pass</cell>
               <cell>8,389</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>26</cell>
               <cell>orders are orders</cell>
               <cell>7,620</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>27</cell>
               <cell>the truth hurts</cell>
               <cell>7,292</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>28</cell>
               <cell>blood will tell</cell>
               <cell>6,840</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>29</cell>
               <cell>father knows best</cell>
               <cell>6,783</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>30</cell>
               <cell>try anything once</cell>
               <cell>6,388</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>31</cell>
               <cell>murder will out</cell>
               <cell>6,349</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>32</cell>
               <cell>silence is golden</cell>
               <cell>6,278</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>33</cell>
               <cell>war is hell</cell>
               <cell>6,136</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>34</cell>
               <cell>business before pleasure</cell>
               <cell>5,811</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>35</cell>
               <cell>talk is cheap</cell>
               <cell>5,723</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>36</cell>
               <cell>revenge is sweet</cell>
               <cell>5,400</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>37</cell>
               <cell>familiarity breeds contempt</cell>
               <cell>5,095</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>38</cell>
               <cell>might makes right</cell>
               <cell>4,768</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>39</cell>
               <cell>consider the source</cell>
               <cell>4,677</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>40</cell>
               <cell>toe the mark</cell>
               <cell>4,549</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>41</cell>
               <cell>every little helps</cell>
               <cell>4,139</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>42</cell>
               <cell>time marches on</cell>
               <cell>4,019</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>43</cell>
               <cell>nothing is perfect</cell>
               <cell>4,007</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>44</cell>
               <cell>money is power</cell>
               <cell>3,757</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>45</cell>
               <cell>circumstances alter cases</cell>
               <cell>3,668</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>46</cell>
               <cell>respect your elders</cell>
               <cell>3,644</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>47</cell>
               <cell>gentlemen prefer blondes</cell>
               <cell>2,922</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>48</cell>
               <cell>mother knows best</cell>
               <cell>2,908</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>49</cell>
               <cell>love never fails</cell>
               <cell>2,848</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>50</cell>
               <cell>nobody is perfect</cell>
               <cell>2,801</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
        
         <table>
            <head>The top 50 proverbs and proverbial expressions (from the <title rend="italic">Dictionary of
               American Proverbs</title>) on Twitter from 2008-2021.</head>
            <row role="label">
               <cell/>
               <cell>Proverb</cell>
               <cell>Count</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>1</cell>
               <cell>never say never</cell>
               <cell>2,549,095</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>2</cell>
               <cell>enough is enough</cell>
               <cell>2,182,460</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>3</cell>
               <cell>nothing is impossible</cell>
               <cell>978,533</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>4</cell>
               <cell>time will tell</cell>
               <cell>869,662</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>5</cell>
               <cell>the truth hurts</cell>
               <cell>748,285</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>6</cell>
               <cell>forgive and forget</cell>
               <cell>557,294</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>7</cell>
               <cell>talk is cheap</cell>
               <cell>465,608</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>8</cell>
               <cell>love is blind</cell>
               <cell>426,010</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>9</cell>
               <cell>practice makes perfect</cell>
               <cell>405,635</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>10</cell>
               <cell>nobody is perfect</cell>
               <cell>399,324</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>11</cell>
               <cell>time is money</cell>
               <cell>383,632</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>12</cell>
               <cell>ignorance is bliss</cell>
               <cell>377,037</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>13</cell>
               <cell>do or die</cell>
               <cell>316,328</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>14</cell>
               <cell>history repeats itself</cell>
               <cell>307,467</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>15</cell>
               <cell>love never fails</cell>
               <cell>255,795</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>16</cell>
               <cell>misery loves company</cell>
               <cell>226,217</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>17</cell>
               <cell>divide and conquer</cell>
               <cell>94,085</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>18</cell>
               <cell>facts are facts</cell>
               <cell>90,513</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>19</cell>
               <cell>respect your elders</cell>
               <cell>89,372</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>20</cell>
               <cell>seeing is believing</cell>
               <cell>86,169</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>21</cell>
               <cell>time will pass</cell>
               <cell>84,432</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>22</cell>
               <cell>silence is golden</cell>
               <cell>82,346</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>23</cell>
               <cell>love conquers all</cell>
               <cell>80,964</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>24</cell>
               <cell>revenge is sweet</cell>
               <cell>69,820</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>25</cell>
               <cell>health is wealth</cell>
               <cell>66,274</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>26</cell>
               <cell>never say die</cell>
               <cell>65,115</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>27</cell>
               <cell>prayer changes things</cell>
               <cell>63,757</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>28</cell>
               <cell>iron sharpens iron</cell>
               <cell>57,065</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>29</cell>
               <cell>sink or swim</cell>
               <cell>50,361</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>30</cell>
               <cell>tomorrow never comes</cell>
               <cell>50,297</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>31</cell>
               <cell>business is business</cell>
               <cell>39,525</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>32</cell>
               <cell>hold your tongue</cell>
               <cell>34,344</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>33</cell>
               <cell>nothing is perfect</cell>
               <cell>34,050</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>34</cell>
               <cell>try anything once</cell>
               <cell>33,370</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>35</cell>
               <cell>mother knows best</cell>
               <cell>26,848</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>36</cell>
               <cell>every little helps</cell>
               <cell>23,672</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>37</cell>
               <cell>never waste time</cell>
               <cell>22,244</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>38</cell>
               <cell>fair is fair</cell>
               <cell>18,125</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>39</cell>
               <cell>slow but sure</cell>
               <cell>14,404</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>40</cell>
               <cell>consider the source</cell>
               <cell>14,201</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>41</cell>
               <cell>justice is blind</cell>
               <cell>11,604</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>42</cell>
               <cell>money is power</cell>
               <cell>10,186</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>43</cell>
               <cell>time works wonders</cell>
               <cell>10,079</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>44</cell>
               <cell>time changes everything</cell>
               <cell>9,512</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>45</cell>
               <cell>like attracts like</cell>
               <cell>8,320</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>46</cell>
               <cell>familiarity breeds contempt</cell>
               <cell>8,166</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>47</cell>
               <cell>war is hell</cell>
               <cell>7,439</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>48</cell>
               <cell>easy does it</cell>
               <cell>6,071</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>49</cell>
               <cell>gentlemen prefer blondes</cell>
               <cell>5,273</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
               <cell>50</cell>
               <cell>courtesy costs nothing</cell>
               <cell>3,890</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="abello2012" label="Abello 2012"> Abello, J., Broadwell, P. and Tangherlini, T. R. (2012a) <title rend="quotes">Computational
               folkloristics,</title> <title rend="italic">Communications of the ACM</title>, 55(7), pp. 60–70. doi:
               <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1145/2209249.2209267"
                  >10.1145/2209249.2209267</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="abrams1994" label="Abrams 1994"> Abrams, R. D. and Babcock, B. A. (1994) <title rend="quotes">The literary use of proverbs,</title> in
               Mieder, W. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Wise words: Essays on the Proverb</title>. New York:
               Garland (Garland reference library of the humanities, vol. 1638), pp. 415–437.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="albig1931" label="Albig 1931"> Albig, W. (1931) <title rend="quotes">Proverbs and social control,</title> <title rend="italic">Sociology
               and Social Research</title>, (15), pp. 527–535.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="alshaabi2020" label="Alshaabi 2020"> Alshaabi, T. <title rend="italic">et al.</title> (2020) <title rend="quotes">Storywrangler: A
               massive exploratorium for sociolinguistic, cultural, socioeconomic, and political
               timelines using Twitter,</title> <title rend="italic">arXiv:2007.12988 [physics]</title>. Available
               at: <ref target="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.12988">http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.12988</ref>
               (Accessed: 7 December 2020).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="alter2018" label="Alter 2018"> Alter, C. (2018) <title rend="quotes">The Young and the Relentless,</title> <title rend="italic"
               >TIME</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://time.com/magazine/us/5210502/april-2nd-2018-vol-191-no-12-u-s/"
                  >https://time.com/magazine/us/5210502/april-2nd-2018-vol-191-no-12-u-s/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="andersson2013" label="Andersson 2013"> Andersson, D. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Understanding figurative proverbs: A model based
               on conceptual blending,</title> <title rend="italic">Folklore</title>, 124(1), pp. 28–44. doi: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1080/0015587X.2012.734442"
                  >10.1080/0015587X.2012.734442</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bain1939" label="Bain 1939"> Bain, R. (1939) <title rend="quotes">Verbal stereotypes and social control,</title> <title rend="italic"
               >Sociology and Social Research</title>, (23), pp. 431–446.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="balasubrahmanyan1996" label="Balasubrahmanyan 1996"> Balasubrahmanyan, V. K. and Naranan, S. (1996) <title rend="quotes">Quantitative
               linguistics and complex system studies,</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of Quantitative
                  Linguistics</title>, 3(3), pp. 177–228. doi: <ref
                     target="https://doi.org/10.1080/09296179608599629"
                     >10.1080/09296179608599629</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bnc2001" label="British National Corpus 2001"> <title rend="quotes">British National Corpus,</title> (2001). Available at: <ref
               target="http://www.natcorp.ox.ac.uk">http://www.natcorp.ox.ac.uk</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cancho2001" label="Cancho 2001"> Cancho, R. F. i. and Solé, R. V. (2001) <title rend="quotes">Two regimes in the frequency of
               words and the origins of complex lexicons: Zipf’s law revisited,</title> <title rend="italic"
                  >Journal of Quantitative Linguistics</title>, 8(3), pp. 165–173.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cancho2003" label="Cancho 2003"> Cancho, R. F. i. and Sole, R. V. (2003) <title rend="quotes">Least effort and the origins of
               scaling in human language,</title> <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the National Academy of
                  Sciences</title>, 100(3), pp. 788–791. doi: <ref
                     target="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0335980100">10.1073/pnas.0335980100</ref>.</bibl>
       
            <bibl xml:id="cermak2014" label="Čermák 2014"> Čermák, F. (2014) <title rend="italic">Proverbs: their lexical and semantic
               features</title>. Burlington, Vermont: The University of Vermont (Supplement series of
               Proverbium Yearbook of International Proverb Scholarship, volume 36).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="clancy1990" label="Clancy 1990"> Clancy, T. (1990). <title rend="italic">Clear and present danger</title>. Berkley mass-market edition.
               ed. Berkley Books, New York.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="clauset2009" label="Clauset 2009"> Clauset, A., Shalizi, C. R. and Newman, M. E. J. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Power-law
               distributions in empirical data,</title> <title rend="italic">SIAM Review</title>, 51(4), pp.
               661–703. doi: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1137/070710111"
                  >10.1137/070710111</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="corominasmurtra2010" label="Corominas-Murtra 2010"> Corominas-Murtra, B. and Solé, R. V. (2010) <title rend="quotes">Universality of
               Zipf’s law,</title> <title rend="italic">Physical Review E</title>, 82(1), p. 011102. doi: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.82.011102"
                  >10.1103/PhysRevE.82.011102</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="corral2015" label="Corral et al. 2015"> Corral, A., Boleda, G. and Ferrer-i-Cancho, R. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Zipf’s law for word
               frequencies: Word forms versus lemmas in long texts,</title> <title rend="italic">PLOS ONE</title>,
               10(7), p. e0129031. doi: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0129031"
                  >10.1371/journal.pone.0129031</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cram1994" label="Cram 1994"> Cram, D. (1994) <title rend="quotes">The linguistic status of the Proverb,</title> in Mieder, W. (ed.)
               <title rend="italic">Wise Words: Essays on the Proverb</title>. New York: Garland (Garland
               reference library of the humanities), pp. 73–97.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="creasy2008" label="Creasy 2008"> Creasy, M. (2008) <title rend="quotes">'To vary the timehonoured adage': Ulysses and the
               Proverb,</title> <title rend="italic">English</title>, 57(217), pp. 65–81. doi: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1093/english/efn008">10.1093/english/efn008</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dodds2017" label="Dodds 2017"> Dodds, P. S. et al. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Simon’s fundamental
               rich-get-richer model entails a dominant first-mover advantage,</title> <title rend="italic"
                  >Physical Review E</title>, 95(5), p. 052301. doi: <ref
                     target="https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.95.052301"
                     >10.1103/PhysRevE.95.052301</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dodds2021" label="Dodds 2021"> Dodds PS, Minot JR, Arnold MV, Alshaabi T, Adams JL, Reagan AJ, et al.
               (2021) <title rend="quotes">Computational timeline reconstruction of the stories surrounding Trump: Story
               turbulence, narrative control, and collective chronopathy,</title> PLoS ONE 16(12): e0260592.
               <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0260592">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0260592</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="doyle2012" label="Doyle 2012"> Doyle, C. C., Mieder, W. and Shapiro, F. R. (2012) <title rend="italic">The
               Dictionary of Modern Proverbs</title>. New Haven: Yale University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dundes1965" label="Dundes 1965"> Dundes, A. (1965) <title rend="quotes">The study of folklore in literature and culture:
               Identification and interpretation,</title> <title rend="italic">The Journal of American
                  Folklore</title>, 78(308), p. 136. doi: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/538280"
                     >10.2307/538280</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fazly2009" label="Fazly 2009"> Fazly, A., Cook, P. and Stevenson, S. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Unsupervised Type and Token
               Identification of Idiomatic Expressions,</title> <title rend="italic">Computational
                  Linguistics</title>, 35(1), pp. 61–103. doi: <ref
                     target="https://doi.org/10.1162/coli.08-010-R1-07-048"
                     >10.1162/coli.08-010-R1-07-048</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="georgia1991" label="Georgia 1991"> Georgia, S. C. of (1991) <title rend="quotes">Cunningham v. State 1991.</title></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="glaberson1992" label="Glaberson 1992"> Glaberson, W. (1992) <title rend="quotes">Assault case renews debate on rape shield law,</title>
               <title rend="italic">The New York Times</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="haas2008" label="Haas 2008"> Haas, H. A. (2008) <title rend="quotes">Proverb familiarity in the United States: Cross-regional
               comparisons of the paremiological minimum,</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of American
                  Folklore</title>, 121(481), pp. 319–347. doi: <ref
                     target="https://doi.org/10.2307/20487611">10.2307/20487611</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="haas2022" label="Haas 2022"> Haas, H. A. (2022) <title rend="quotes">The Proverbs of a Pandemic: The Early Months of the
               COVID-19 Pandemic Viewed through the Lens of Google Trends,</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of American
               Folklore</title>, 135 (535), pp. 26–48. Doi: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.5406/15351882.135.535.02"
                  >https://doi.org/10.5406/15351882.135.535.02</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hanley1992" label="Hanley 1992"> [Hanley, R. (1992) <title rend="quotes">Jury chosen in Glen Ridge assault trial,</title> <title
               rend="italic">The New York Times</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="henry1996" label="Henry 1996"> Henry, J. (1996) <title rend="quotes">How the money was spent in previous environmental Bond
               Acts,</title> <title rend="italic">The New York Times</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hunter2007" label="Hunter 2007"> Hunter, J. D. (2007) <title rend="quotes">Matplotlib: A 2D graphics environment,</title> <title
               rend="italic">Computing in Science &amp; Engineering</title>, 9(3), pp. 90–95. doi: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1109/MCSE.2007.55">10.1109/MCSE.2007.55</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="koplenig2018" label="Koplenig 2018"> Koplenig, A. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Using the parameters of the Zipf–Mandelbrot law to
               measure diachronic lexical, syntactical and stylistic changes — a large-scale corpus
               analysis,</title> <title rend="italic">Corpus Linguistics and Linguistic Theory</title>, 14(1), pp.
               1–34. doi: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1515/cllt-2014-0049"
                  >10.1515/cllt-2014-0049</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lakoff1985" label="Lakoff 1985"> Lakoff, G. and Johnson, M. (1985) <title rend="italic">Metaphors We Live
               By</title>. Chicago, Ill.: Univ. of Chicago Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lau1996" label="Lau 1996"> Lau, K. J. (1996) <title rend="quotes">'It’s About Time': The ten proverbs most frequently used
               newspapers and their relation to American values,</title> <title rend="italic">Proverbium</title>,
               13, pp. 135–59.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="leskovec2009" label="Leskovec 2009"> Leskovec, J., Backstrom, L. and Kleinberg, J. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Meme-tracking and
               the dynamics of the news cycle,</title> in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 15th ACM SIGKDD
                  international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining - KDD ’09</title>.
               Paris, France: ACM Press, p. 497. doi: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1145/1557019.1557077">10.1145/1557019.1557077</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lieber1994" label="Lieber 1994"> Lieber, M. D. (1994) <title rend="quotes">Analogic ambiguity: A paradox of proverb usage,</title> in
               Mieder, W. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Wise Words: Essays on the Proverb</title>. New York:
               Garland (Garland reference library of the humanities, vol. 1638), pp. 99–126.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="loveisblind2020" label="Love is Blind 2020"> <title rend="quotes">Love Is Blind</title> (2020). Netflix.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mandelbrot1953" label="Mandelbrot 1953"> Mandelbrot, B. (1953) <title rend="quotes">An informational theory of the statistical
               structure of languages,</title> in Jackson, W. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Communication
                  Theory</title>. Academic Press, Princeton, pp. 486–502.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="marchforourlives2018" label="March for Our Lives 2018"> <title rend="quotes">March for Our Lives Highlights: Students Protesting Guns Say
               'Enough Is Enough'</title> (2018) <title rend="italic">The New York Times</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="martinezmekler2009" label="Martínez-Mekler 2009"> Martínez-Mekler, G. <title rend="italic">et al.</title> (2009)
               <title rend="quotes">Universality of rank-ordering distributions in the arts and sciences,</title> <title
                  rend="italic">PLoS ONE</title>. Edited by M. Costa, 4(3), p. e4791. doi: <ref
                     target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0004791"
                     >10.1371/journal.pone.0004791</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mechling2004" label="Mechling 2004"> Mechling, J. (2004) <title rend="quotes">“Cheaters Never Prosper” and other lies adults tell
               kids: Proverbs and the culture wars over character,</title> in Lau, K. J., Tokofsky, P., and
               Winick, S. D. (eds) <title rend="italic">What goes around comes around: the circulation of
                  proverbs in contemporary life: Essays in Honor of Wolfgang Mieder</title>. Logan: Utah
               State University Press, pp. 107–126.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="michel2011" label="Michel 2011"> Michel, J.-B. <title rend="italic">et al.</title> (2011) <title rend="quotes">Quantitative analysis
               of culture using millions of digitized books,</title> <title rend="italic">Science</title>,
               331(6014), pp. 176–182. doi: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1199644"
                  >10.1126/science.1199644</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mieder2004" label="Mieder 2004"> Mieder, W. (2004) <title rend="italic">Proverbs: a handbook</title>. Westport,
               Conn: Greenwood Press (Greenwood folklore handbooks).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mieder2005" label="Mieder 2005"> Mieder, W. (2005) <title rend="italic">Proverbs are the best policy: Folk
               wisdom and American politics</title>. Logan, Utah: Utah State University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mieder2008" label="Mieder 2008"> Mieder, W. (2008) <title rend="italic">'Proverbs speak louder than words':
               Folk wisdom in art, culture, folklore, history, literature and mass media</title>. New
               York: P. Lang.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mieder2012" label="Mieder 2012"> Mieder, W. (2012) <title rend="italic">Proverbs are never out of season:
               Popular wisdom in the modern age</title>. New York: Peter Lang (International
               folkloristics, v. 7).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mieder2019" label="Mieder 2019"> Mieder, W. (2019) <title rend="italic">“Right makes Might”: Proverbs and the
               American worldview</title>. Bloomington, Indiana: Indiana University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mieder1992" label="Mieder 1992"> Mieder, W., Kingsbury, S. A. and Harder, K. B. (eds) (1992) <title
               rend="italic">A Dictionary of American Proverbs</title>. New York: Oxford University
               Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="moon1998" label="Moon 1998"> Moon, R. (1998) <title rend="italic">Fixed expressions and idioms in English: A
               corpus-based approach</title>. Oxford : New York: Clarendon Press ; Oxford University
               Press (Oxford studies in lexicography and lexicology).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="norrick1985" label="Norrick 1985"> Norrick, N. R. (1985) <title rend="italic">How Proverbs Mean: Semantic
               Studies in English Proverbs</title>. Berlin, New York: DE GRUYTER MOUTON. doi: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110881974">10.1515/9783110881974</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="obelkevich1994" label="Obelkevich 1994"> Obelkevich, J. (1994) <title rend="quotes">Proverbs and social history,</title> in Mieder, W.
               (ed.) <title rend="italic">Wise Words: Essays on the Proverb</title>. New York: Garland
               (Garland reference library of the humanities, vol. 1638), pp. 211–252.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ozbal2016a" label="Özbal 2016a"> Özbal, G. <title rend="italic">et al.</title> (2016) <title rend="quotes">Learning to identify
               metaphors from a corpus of proverbs,</title> in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2016
                  Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing</title>. Austin, Texas:
               Association for Computational Linguistics, pp. 2060–2065. doi: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/D16-1220">10.18653/v1/D16-1220</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ozbal2016b" label="Özbal 2016b"> Özbal, G., Strapparava, C. and Sinem Tekiroglu, S. (2016) <title rend="quotes">PROMETHEUS: A
               corpus of proverbs annotated with metaphors,</title> <title rend="italic">LREC, Proceedings
               of the Tenth International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation</title> (LREC’16),
               pp. 3787–3793.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pechenick2015a" label="Pechenick 2015a"> Pechenick, Eitan Adam, Danforth, C. M. and Dodds, P. S. (2015)
               <title rend="quotes">Characterizing the Google Books corpus: Strong limits to inferences of socio-cultural
               and linguistic evolution,</title> <title rend="italic">PLOS ONE</title>. Edited by A. Barrat, 10(10),
               p. e0137041. doi: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0137041"
                  >10.1371/journal.pone.0137041</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pechenick2015b" label="Pechenick 2015b"> Pechenick, Eitan A., Danforth, C. M. and Dodds, P. S. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Is
               language evolution grinding to a halt? The scaling of lexical turbulence in English
               fiction suggests it is not.</title></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="permiakov1989" label="Permiakov 1989"> Permiakov, G. L. (1989) <title rend="quotes">On the question of a Russian paremiological
               minimum.,</title> <title rend="italic">Proverbium</title>, 6, pp. 91–102.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="reagan2016" label="Reagan 2016"> Reagan, A. J. <title rend="italic">et al.</title> (2016) <title rend="quotes">The emotional arcs of
               stories are dominated by six basic shapes,</title> <title rend="italic">EPJ Data Science</title>,
               5(1), p. 31. doi: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1140/epjds/s13688-016-0093-1"
                  >10.1140/epjds/s13688-016-0093-1</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="robinson2020" label="Robinson 202"> Robinson, D. (2020) <title rend="italic">Gutenbergr</title>. Available at:
               <ref target="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/gutenbergr/index.html"
                  >https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/gutenbergr/index.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sag2002" label="Sag 2002"> Sag, I. A. <title rend="italic">et al.</title> (2002) <title rend="quotes">Multiword expressions: A
               pain in the neck for NLP,</title> in Goos, G. et al. (eds) <title rend="italic">Computational
                  Linguistics and Intelligent Text Processing</title>. Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer Berlin
               Heidelberg, pp. 1–15. doi: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/3-540-45715-1_1"
                  >10.1007/3-540-45715-1_1</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sandhaus2008" label="Sandhaus 2008"> Sandhaus, E. (2008) <title rend="quotes">The New York Times Annotated Corpus,</title> <title rend="italic">Linguistic
               Data Consortium</title>. doi: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.35111/77BA-9X74"
                  >10.35111/77BA-9X74</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="semones2020" label="Semones 202"> Semones, E. (2020) <title rend="quotes">'Enough is enough': Thousands descend on D.C. for
               largest George Floyd protest yet,</title> <title rend="italic">POLITICO</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shutova2010" label="Shutova 2010"> Shutova, E. (2010) <title rend="quotes">Models of metaphor in NLP,</title> in <title rend="italic"
               >Proceedings of the 48th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational
               Linguistics</title>. Uppsala, Sweden: Association for Computational Linguistics, pp.
               688–697. Available at: <ref target="https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/P10-1071"
                  >https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/P10-1071</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="simon1960" label="Simon 1960"> Simon, H. A. (1960) <title rend="quotes">Some further notes on a class of skew distribution
               functions,</title> <title rend="italic">Information and Control</title>, 3(1), pp. 80–88. doi: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0019-9958(60)90302-8"
                  >10.1016/S0019-9958(60)90302-8</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="steyer2015" label="Steyer 2015"> Steyer, K. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Proverbs from a corpus linguistic point of view,</title> in
               Hrisztova-Gotthardt, H. and Aleksa Varga, M. (eds) <title rend="italic">Introduction to
                  Paremiology: A Comprehensive Guide to Proverb Studies</title>. Warsaw, Poland: DE
               GRUYTER OPEN, pp. 206–228. doi: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.2478/9783110410167"
                  >10.2478/9783110410167</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="swuste2010" label="Swuste 2010"> Swuste, P., Gulijk, C. van and Zwaard, W. (2010) <title rend="quotes">Safety metaphors and
               theories, a review of the occupational safety literature of the US, UK and The
               Netherlands, till the first part of the 20th century,</title> <title rend="italic">Safety
                  Science</title>, 48(8), pp. 1000–1018. doi: <ref
                     target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ssci.2010.01.020"
                     >10.1016/j.ssci.2010.01.020</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tangherlini2016" label="Tangherlini 2016"> Tangherlini, T. R. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Big folklore: A special issue on
               computational folkloristics,</title> <title rend="italic">The Journal of American Folklore</title>,
               129(511), p. 5. doi: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5406/jamerfolk.129.511.0005"
                  >10.5406/jamerfolk.129.511.0005</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pandas2020" label="pandas 2020"> The pandas development team (2020) <title rend="italic">pandas-dev/pandas:
               Pandas</title>. Zenodo. doi: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3509134"
                  >10.5281/zenodo.3509134</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tweedle2012" label="Tweedle 2012"> Tweedle, V. and Smith, R. J. (2012) <title rend="quotes">A mathematical model of Bieber
               Fever: The most infectious disease of our time?,</title> in.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="underwood2018" label="Underwood 2018"> Underwood, T., Bamman, D. and Lee, S. (2018) <title rend="quotes">The transformation of
               gender in English-language fiction,</title> p. 25.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="voteyes1996" label="Vote Yes on the Bond Act 1996"> <title rend="quotes">Vote Yes on the Bond Act,</title> (1996) <title rend="italic">The
               New York Times</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whiting2014" label="Whiting 2014"> Whiting, B. J. (2014) <title rend="italic">Modern Proverbs and Proverbial
               Sayings</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://0-doi-org.pugwash.lib.warwick.ac.uk/10.4159/harvard.9780674864153"
                  >https://0-doi-org.pugwash.lib.warwick.ac.uk/10.4159/harvard.9780674864153</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="williams2015a" label="Williams 2015a"> Williams, J. R. <title rend="italic">et al.</title> (2015a) <title rend="quotes">Text mixing
               shapes the anatomy of rank-frequency distributions,</title> <title rend="italic">Physical Review
                  E</title>, 91(5), p. 052811. doi: <ref
                     target="https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.91.052811"
                     >10.1103/PhysRevE.91.052811</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="williams2015b" label="Williams 2015b"> Williams, J. R. et al. (2015b) <title rend="quotes">Zipf’s law holds
               for phrases, not words,</title> <title rend="italic">Scientific Reports</title>, 5(1), p. 12209. doi:
               <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1038/srep12209">10.1038/srep12209</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zemeckis1994" label="Zemeckis 1994"> Zemeckis, R. (1994) <title rend="italic">Forrest Gump</title>. Paramount Pictures.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zipf2012" label="Zipf 2012"> Zipf, G. K. (2012) <title rend="italic">Human behavior and the principle of
               least effort: An introduction to human ecology.</title> Mansfield Centre, Conn: Martino
               Publishing [u.a.].</bibl>
          
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
