<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">The Digital Future of Humanities through the Lens of DIY
                    Culture</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Henriette
                        <dhq:family>Roued-Cunlife</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Copenhagen</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>roued@hum.ku.dk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Assistant Professor at The Royal School of Library and Information
                            Science</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000277</idno>
                <idno type="volume">010</idno>
                <idno type="issue">4</idno>
                <date when="2016-11-08">8 November 2016</date>
                <dhq:articleType>editorial</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>Digital Humanities future</item>
                        <item>DIY culture</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="DD" when="2016-10-26">Created</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This paper asks the question: Do the humanities by necessity have a digital
                    future? It argues that the answer to this question is both yes and no. The
                    argument looks through the lens of DIY culture as an attempt to try and
                    understand the future for the humanities in terms of both cultural material and
                    processes. The argument is made first by examining the case of information
                    sharing within DIY culture as an expression of current day cultural material.
                    Secondly, it illustrated how traditional humanities scholarship, such as reading
                    ancient documents, compares to it’s DIY equivalent within family history
                    circles, and how both will continue to use digital and non-digital methods.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Henriette Roued-Cunliffe analyzes the future of the digital humanities from the
                    lens of DIY culture.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>

        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Do the humanities by necessity have a digital future? This question is answered
                    by understanding the humanities as the study of human culture and cultural
                    material, both on and off the Internet. This paper will use <term>DIY</term>
                    (Do-It-Yourself) cultural material and practises as a way to understand this. </p>
                <p>First the phrase and concept of DIY culture will be unpacked: </p>
                <p>DIY culture is here defined as the social world of people engaged in DIY
                    activities, which can be anything from building a shed or knitting a sweater to
                    running a food co-op, with the prerequisite that the practitioner has no
                    relevant formal education or training. DIY culture can, in many ways, be seen as
                    simultaneously an online and an offline culture, with a complex relationship
                    between digital and non-digital activity and interaction. Due to its rising
                    relevance, particularly on the internet, it is important that the humanities
                    include the study of DIY culture and its cultural products - digital,
                    non-digital and everything in between. </p>
                <p>The humanities are generally defined as the disciplines that examine human
                    culture, or in other words the products of the human mind, both tangible and
                    intangible, such as music, arts, crafts, rituals, literature and linguistics.
                    The humanities have a long history of attempting to understand these different
                    products of the past and the present. The methods with which these attempts have
                    been made often strongly depend on the formats of the material as well as on the
                    technology that is available to the scholars in question <ptr target="#bod2014"/>. </p>
                <p>This paper suggests that cultural material produced by DIY practicioners should
                    be the subject of much future research in the humanities, and through examining
                    both products and practices from DIY culture, we can understand the future of
                    humanities scholarship as both digital and non-digital, online and offline. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>DIY culture</head>
                <p>DIY culture constitutes an important part of human culture today. Gelber (1999)
                    portrays productive leisure activities (<term>hobbies</term>) as an antidote to
                    more problematic leisure activities (e.g. drinking or gambling) and idleness
                    following in the wake of the separation of work and leisure brought on by
                    industrialisation. An antidote supported by authorities:<cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#gelber1999">Teachers, recreation directors, journalists, and other
                            voices of authority have felt free to encourage the autonomy and
                            creativity of hobbies because even if they sensed that hobbies could
                            critique regular work, they also recognized that hobbies’ triumph over
                            idleness was a victory for the values of a market economy.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#gelber1999" loc="3"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>In other words: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#gelber1999"> Hobbies have been a way to confirm the verities of
                            work and the free market inside the home so long as remunerative
                            employment has remained elsewhere.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#gelber1999" loc="4"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Gelber uses the existing term <term>hobbies</term> (which after 1880 came to be
                    known as a productive use of free time rather than a dangerous obsession) to
                    talk about productive leisure activities such as collecting, handicrafts,
                    husbandry, amateurism and volunteerism. Stebbins, on the other hand, has
                    hobbies, amateurism and volunteerism side by side as different types of serious
                    leisure pursuits <ptr target="#stebbins2007"/>. In Gelber’s view, DIY (which
                    includes crafts and maintenance) is a less creative and more productive hobby
                    focussing on producing something useful and perhaps necessary to the household.
                    Matchar, on the other hand, focuses on the household aspects in the term
                        <term>new domesticity</term> - returning to productivity in the home: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#matchar2013">Our nostalgia for old-fashioned home and hearth has
                            transformed our food culture as well. Who hasn’t tried canning jam or
                            making their own pickles? Young women who, had they been of age in the
                            1990s, might have been boozing it up in the Meatpacking District [New
                            York neighbourhood] are now spending Saturday nights baking cupcakes and
                            photographing them for their food blogs. The kinds of kitchen work once
                            associated with Depression-era farmwives - making curds and whey,
                            preserving sauerkraut, grinding flour - are now thoroughly unremarkable
                            pastimes for young people flush with today’s DIY back-to-basics
                            spirit.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#matchar2013" loc="3"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Both note that times of recession and economic crises give rise to more work-like
                    and productive leisure activities supported by a media focus on <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#gelber1999">good-things-to-do when there was nothing to do</quote>
                        <ptr target="#gelber1999" loc="41"/>
                    </cit>. Matchar particularly notes the spread of anti-authoritarian
                    disillusionment and this could be seen as a result of the ease of which ideas
                    and information can and has spread on the internet during the latest recession.
                    The internet furthermore plays a large role in the aspects of DIY and DIY
                    culture.</p>
                <p>DIY culture is here defined as a social world surrounding DIY practitioners.
                    Unruh uses social worlds to refer to a social organisation that cannot be
                    defined by spatial, territorial, formal or membership boundaries <ptr target="#unruh1980"/>. Instead, a social world is defined through
                    interaction and communication. DIY culture exists worldwide and varieties of DIY
                    culture can be seen in most societies. There are no rules on how you engage with
                    DIY culture and anyone can be part of it. Although there are no spatial,
                    territorial, formal or membership boundaries of DIY culture, it exists through
                    interaction and communication.</p>
                <p>When examining DIY culture it is not the DIY activities as such that are the
                    focus. How a sweater is knitted or how the shed is built is secondary here. In
                    fact, the act of knitting a sweater or building a shed is not in itself a DIY
                    activity as these tasks can also be accomplished by professionals with the
                    relevant formal education or training. The focus lies instead on how information
                    is gathered that enables people to build sheds, or the social setting in which
                    someone is motivated and gathers knowledge that enables them to knit the
                    sweater, when they have had no formal training to do so. Thus, it is the
                    autodidact information behaviour, which is the foundation of DIY activities,
                    that is of interest here.</p>
                <p>DIY practitioners have no formal training or education in this particular
                    activity. To <soCalled>do it yourself</soCalled> in the rawest form implies
                    being completely self-taught. However, instead of the word self-taught, Solomon
                    suggest using the term autodidactism: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#solomon2003"> So <soCalled>self-taught</soCalled> will not quite do
                            as a complete description of the autodidact. We need a word to describe
                            a range of people who prefer to teach themselves or to pick up knowledge
                            from non-teaching situations, in one way or another.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#solomon2003" loc="3"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Solomon further argues that from the time they are born humans are constantly
                    being taught, or allowing themselves to be taught: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#solomon2003">Every time someone speaks, or points out a bird doing
                            something strange on the lawn, or reconfigures the computer slowly
                            enough for us to follow - if we want to, we are being taught.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#solomon2003" loc="3"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Solomon’s understanding of autodidact learning is not one of solitude, but rather
                    one where we are seeking out learning and knowledge from other people. This is
                    closely related to research in Human Information Behaviour, especially that in
                    our everyday life: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#wilson2000">Information Behaviour is the totality of human behaviour
                            in relation to sources and channels of information, including both
                            active and passive information seeking, and information use. Thus, it
                            includes face-to-face communication with others, as well as the passive
                            reception of information as in, for example, watching TV advertisements,
                            without any intention to act on the information given.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#wilson2000" loc="49"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Information behaviour <ptr target="#fisher2006"/> typically focussed more on
                    one-way access to information and the ways in which the individual can use this
                    information. However, the field of Everyday Life Information Seeking <ptr target="#savolainen1995"/> (ELIS) has lead to a more rounded understanding
                    of information behaviour, which includes the social and collaborative nature of
                    human interaction with information (i.e. the field of CIB - Collaborative
                    Information Behaviour) <ptr target="#talja2006"/>. Thus, information behaviour
                    is a complex area of seeking, finding, sharing, creating new and remixing old
                    information. In everyday life this information behaviour becomes even more
                    complex in a world of overlapping tasks for which information is sought, found,
                    shared, presented and even ignored or discarded <ptr target="#karlova2013"/>.
                    Therefore, most ELIS studies tend to focus on a certain task or activity for
                    which it is easier to identify a group of participants. This could, for example,
                    be parenting <ptr target="#mckenzie2003"/> or health issues <ptr target="#yeoman2010"/> as well as DIY activities such as genealogy <ptr target="#yakel2004"/>, knitting <ptr target="#prigoda2007"/>, gourmet
                    cooking <ptr target="#hartel2010"/> or heritage <ptr target="#skov2013"/>. </p>
                <p>Nevertheless, I would argue that there is a general aspect in all DIY activities
                    that usually require a certain amount of autodidact information behaviour in
                    order to engage with the activity. This has been the case since the first
                    mentions of a DIY movement in the 1950s <ptr target="#mead1957"/> where there
                    was an increase in instructions on how-to do it yourself experienced a boom.
                    This how-to genre has developed into a DIY activity in itself and this type of
                    material is ever growing on the Internet and in print. The enormous amounts of
                    information sharing currently going on between DIY practitioners around the
                    world is creating a new type of cultural material that we in the humanities need
                    to understand in order to understand current culture. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>On and offline</head>
                <p>DIY culture can in many ways be seen as simultaneously an online and an offline
                    culture, with a complex relationship between digital and non-digital activity
                    and interaction. In order to make this argument we will begin by looking at the
                    relationship between time spent on and off the internet, for people of all age
                    groups.</p>
                <p>Sigman argues that time spent online displaces face-to-face contact, and he
                    explains how in turn this lack of face-to-face interaction has been shown to
                    relate to increased illness and premature mortality <ptr target="#sigman2009"/>.
                    While the connection between lack of social interaction and health issues is
                    strong, it seems to be more difficult to find specific connections between
                    internet use and health issues. Findings here are more mixed, with some studies
                    showing a more positive correlation. As an example, Cotton and colleagues showed
                    how internet use among older adults (50 years or older) reduced depression
                    categorization by 33%<ptr target="#cotten2012"/>.</p>
                <p>This is furthermore an area where it is important to keep in mind the differences
                    between correlation and causality. If we make the assumption that there is a
                    correlation between a high degree of loneliness and a large amount of time spent
                    online, do people who spend much time online become lonely as a result of less
                    face-to-face contact or is it the case that people who are lonely spend more
                    time online, perhaps in order to achieve more social contact via a digital
                    media? Another suggestion is that there is a third factor involved which causes
                    a high degree of both loneliness and spending time online, for example bullying
                    or a general lack of closeness in one’s social network. It is not an easy
                    question to answer and findings seem to depend on the groups of people that are
                    studied. Staying with the example of loneliness, which can take different shapes
                    (e.g. social or emotional loneliness), the size of social networks can for
                    example have a larger impact on the social loneliness of young adults, while the
                    lack of closeness to other members of a social network can have a larger impact
                    on the social loneliness on older adults <ptr target="#green2001" loc="281"/>. </p>
                <p>Nevertheless, the internet does provide an opportunity to connect with
                    like-minded people or those with similar interests across large physical as well
                    as social distances.</p>
                <p>In an attempt to teach the elderly to use computers with the prospect of enabling
                    connectivity, as shown above, it made sense to change the focus of the syllabus
                    towards teaching them to use the internet rather than the computer
                        itself<note>The class <soCalled>IT for beginners</soCalled> taught by the
                        author took place through the community learning programme AOF in Denmark,
                        Autumn 2013</note>. Through this experience I identified the three most
                    important things to teach them about the internet:</p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>How to access information on the internet,</item>
                    <item>How to communicate and interact socially on the internet, and</item>
                    <item>How to express themselves and share information on the internet. </item>
                </list>
                <p>Each step led small groups of elderly individuals to a new level of motivation to
                    use the internet. Despite their expectations at the beginning of the course, at
                    no point were they taught anything particularly technical.</p>
                <p>The tech industry, amongst others, despairs over the lack of understanding of
                    technology <ptr target="#bt2015"/> among children, of which 71% (of 5-15 year
                    olds in the UK) <ptr target="#ofcom"/> have access to tablet computers at home,
                    and I am sympathetic to their plight. The future of the tech industry relies on
                    young people interested in working within that discipline and industry. However,
                    we need to consider the following difficult and troubling suggestion: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#bt2015">even though young people grow up surrounded by
                            technology, many of them don’t understand the basic concepts of how it
                            works – which will leave them unable to fully participate in
                            society</quote>
                        <ptr target="#bt2015"/>
                    </cit>. Statements like this assume that an understanding of how the internet
                    and the technology behind the internet works is necessary for participation in
                    society. But does technology shape society or culture, or is it culture and
                    society that shape technology?</p>
                <p> Technology is a product of the human mind, not the other way around. So perhaps
                    the issue with young people's understanding of the internet is that they
                    understand it differently from those who did not grow up with it. For the older
                    generation a computer is still technology, it is apart from us. For the younger
                    generation, on the other hand, it is perhaps not. For them the computer provides
                    opportunities to connect - the internet an abstraction which they only
                    experience when it is not available. </p>
                <p>Another pertinent question is <soCalled>will their future necessarily be
                        digital?</soCalled> Will the younger generation experience very little
                    face-to-face or in-real-life interaction with other people? Mcclure suggests
                    that even babies can differentiate between real live interaction via screen on
                    the one hand and pre-recorded video on the other <ptr target="#mcclure2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#lafrance2015"/>. This could mean that for the younger generation
                    communication mediated via screen bears a closer resemblance to physical
                    socialising than to screen entertainment. Thus there is no need to understand
                    technology, in order to socially interact with others via digital media. It is
                    just a means for us as humans to connect, to access information, to express
                    ourselves and of course to be entertained. </p>
                <p>Many people use the internet to express themselves creatively (a large part of
                    DIY culture), some use it to express other very human sentiments, with varying
                    degrees of sympathy. It is intriguing to see how connecting via the internet
                    increasingly opens up to connecting in the physical world. From blogger meetups
                    of the 00’s to finding on Ravelry<note> Online knitting and crochet community
                            (<ref target="www.ravelry.com/">www.ravelry.com/</ref>)</note> a fellow
                    knitter that lives in your own neighbourhood. The internet is giving us the
                    opportunity to find and connect with people who have similar values and
                    interests; connections that pre-internet would have been very difficult to make. </p>
                <p>The internet has a great influence on DIY culture as much as DIY culture
                    certainly has a great influence on the internet. As mentioned above, a large
                    part of DIY culture is the use of autodidact information behaviour. It does not
                    seem so much to be a question of whether the internet plays a large role in this
                    information behaviour or, if not, in fact autodidact information behaviour lays
                    the foundation for the internet, but rather if the internet would be as
                    widespread as it is today (and continually growing), if we humans did not in the
                    first place engage in autodidact information behaviour?</p>
                <p>But what about the non-digital world - the offline, the physical world? Most DIY
                    activities are in some way very firmly grounded in the physical world. Knitting
                    a sweater is a very physical activity. As is building a shed and running a food
                    co-op. Running a food co-op is particularly physical and social in its very
                    nature. Therefore, while a large part of autodidact information behaviour in DIY
                    culture happens online, there is still a very large part of it that does
                        not.<note>Based on preliminary conclusions from wider empirical study of
                        self-reported use of these autodidact information situations which the
                        author is currently conducting.</note> This illustrates that in DIY
                    activities and DIY culture, the digital and the physical, being online and being
                    offline, more often than not go hand in hand. The relationship between digital
                    and physical material and immaterial culture is an interesting new area for the
                    humanities to study, not only within media and information studies but also
                    within arts, crafts, literature, music, heritage, and more. This would in many
                    cases traditionally have been analysed among professional cultural practitioners
                    and their cultural products. However, this paper argues that it may be just as
                    relevant to examine this among DIY practitioners and DIY products. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Humanities in a digital world</head>
                <p>An important part of DIY culture today is autodidact information behaviour, much
                    of which (but far from all) is conducted on the internet. One of the results of
                    this is an enormous amount of information, of both high and low quality,
                    flooding the internet. It is generally very difficult to preserve this
                    information <ptr target="#kasioumis2014"/>, let alone understand it. Attempting
                    to understand products of culture and the human mind produced today is
                    challenging because these materials are very diverse and have increased so
                    immensely in number, particularly within DIY culture. New methods for analysing
                    large amounts of data are currently in focus under the heading of Big Data
                    analysis. However, any analysis of cultural products requires an understanding
                    of the culture and the material <ptr target="#boyd2012"/>. There are masses of
                    cultural products out there that we have not yet even begun to consider. At the
                    same time new formats and producers appear every single day, both digital and
                    non-digital, from the 25-year-old DIY music artist with a new single out on
                    vinyl, to the 75 year old DIY gardener with a popular Youtube channel. </p>
                <p>Understanding these cultural products is a great challenge for humanities
                    research and will continue to be so in the future. Therefore the answer to the
                    question, <soCalled>Do the humanities by necessity have a digital
                        future?</soCalled> must be a resounding <soCalled>yes and no.</soCalled>
                    Yes, humanities research must attempt to understand cultural productions that
                    are digital. No, because if we look at DIY culture we will see that there most
                    likely will continue to be many cultural productions of non-digital material,
                    which humanities researchers must continue to study and understand. Perhaps the
                    future of the humanities is instead to learn from DIY practitioners and no
                    longer distinguish so sharply between the digital and the non-digital. </p>
                <p>Furthermore, while the internet itself relies on technology, I argue that we
                    should not understand the contents of the internet as technological products,
                    but rather the products of the human mind or as cultural products. Historian Roy
                    Rosenzweig made this same point in relation to Wikipedia, saying that it was <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#rosenzweig2006">the most important application of the principles of the
                            free and open-source software movement to the world of cultural, rather
                            than software, production</quote>
                        <ptr target="#rosenzweig2006" loc="118"/>
                    </cit>. The information shared, the opinions expressed, the communication about
                    common interests and the social interactions stem from humans and not machines.
                    Understanding machines or technology may give us some tools to study the
                    internet, but it will never give us the ability to understand the content. For
                    this we need methods developed for the understanding of cultural products, in
                    other words humanities methods. So, to answer the question again; yes, the
                    humanities do have a necessary digital future in that it will be necessary to
                    use digital tools to study both digital and non-digital material, and no,
                    because without traditional methods for understanding cultural products we
                    simply will not be able to understand either digital or non-digital material. </p>
                <p>The implications of this <soCalled>yes and no</soCalled> answer can be understood
                    through the following two examples. The first is an example of computer
                    technology aiding humanities scholarship. The premise here was to examine how
                    technology could <emph>aid</emph> a scholar during the <emph>scholar's</emph>
                    reading of ancient documents <ptr target="#rouedcunliffe2010"/>. The italics are
                    added to emphasise that the scholar’s humanities-based methods for reading
                    stayed the same and that technology merely added speed or ease to certain
                    aspects of the process. For example the speed of finding parallel readings in
                    the same or other corpora or the ease with which evidence that supported certain
                    readings is remembered <ptr target="#rouedcunliffe2013"/>. In this example the
                    materials studied (i.e. ancient documents from the Roman fort of Vindolanda in
                    the North of England<note>
                        <ref target="http://vto2.classics.ox.ac.uk/">http://vto2.classics.ox.ac.uk/</ref></note>) are cultural products that
                    at first were not digital. However, the fragile state of most of these documents
                    as well as the physical location of the scholars was such that the documents
                    studied were often in fact digital photographs. Here scholars moved from the
                    study of physical objects to the study of digital objects. The methods for
                    studying the documents were very traditional for the field of papyrology. Terras
                    describes the complex and cyclical process in the following way: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#terras2005">An expert reads an ancient document by identifying
                            visual features, and then incrementally building up knowledge about the
                            document’s characters, combinations of characters, words, grammar,
                            phrases, and meaning, continually proposing hypotheses, and checking
                            those against other information, until s/he finds that this process is
                            exhausted</quote>
                        <ptr target="#terras2005" loc="54"/>
                    </cit>. </p>
                <p>Along the way there are aspects of this process that are typically done by
                    non-digital means but which can alternatively be <emph>aided</emph> by digital
                    technology. First is the identification of visual features where the scholars,
                    in the case of quite illegible incised texts, would typically use a light source
                    to cast a shadow on the document and by tipping the document to and fro this
                    enables the scholar to make out the incisions <ptr target="#brady2005"/>. This
                    is a cumbersome and unreliable method and therefore the project attempted to aid
                    this task with digital image processing techniques <ptr target="#terras2012"/>. </p>
                <p>The second part of the process is the building up of knowledge about the
                    characters, words and phrases in the document. Typically, this will happen today
                    by keeping digital and non-digital notes about the different interpretations and
                    decisions made along the way. Therefore, attempts were made at showing how a
                    digital <soCalled>Decision Support System</soCalled> would enable the scholar to
                    organise and remember these interpretations and the basis on which they were
                    made <ptr target="#rouedcunliffe2013"/>.</p>
                <p>The final part of the process, as described here, is checking against other
                    information. This traditionally required access to copies of published editions
                    that could contain relevant parallels to the documents being studied. Potential
                    parallels would be found by trawling through indices. This is a part of the
                    process of reading ancient documents where digital technology and the internet
                    has had a great influence. By digitally publishing interpreted editions online
                    (using XML), and by making them accessible through search engines this task has
                    become much lighter and has made the texts more easily accessible by scholars
                    around the world. As the example shows, even a traditional digital humanities
                    project that works with digital tools for the reading of handwritten texts
                    continually oscillates between digital and non-digital tools, methods and
                    material.</p>
                <p>However, as this second example will show, the reading of handwritten texts is
                    not a method used only by scholars in academia. Genealogy is probably the most
                    well-known DIY activity in which the skill of reading old handwritten texts is
                    quite essential. My own experience of working with family history and engaging
                    with other genealogists has led to a few observations in relation to this
                    skill:</p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>Genealogists, depending on their level of experience, usually have some
                        skills in reading handwritten texts, ranging from beginners to experts. </item>
                    <item>These experts are able to read Latin texts, written in a very illegible
                        Gothic script.</item>
                    <item>Experts and beginners alike usually collaborate on the reading of texts
                        that are related to their own family history and they do this both online
                        and offline.</item>
                    <item>Genealogists usually gather the skills and knowledge needed for this task
                        through the different autodidact information situations mentioned
                        above.</item>
                    <item>Genealogists use a greater variety of different digital tools and
                        platforms depending on their level of digital literacy, than I have
                        experienced among scholars.</item>
                </list>
                <p>For these skills particularly, genealogists and other amateur historians are
                    regularly used as volunteer transcribers in museums and archives. With digital
                    media and the internet, GLAM institutions (i.e. galleries, libraries, archives
                    and museums) are now able to structure these skills and use them more
                    efficiently to transcribe material in their collections; in other words, to use
                    these skills in crowdsourcing projects <ptr target="#ridge2013"/>.</p>
                <p>This second example suggests that perhaps the skills involved are not what
                    separates the DIY practitioner from the professional practitioner, neither is
                    the need for social networking or collaboration. The motivations for reading
                    handwritten documents are most likely the same, namely recognition and
                    furthering their understanding of the subject at hand. Perhaps what really
                    divides the waters is the information behaviour and whether this is taught or it
                    is autodidact. The consequence of this difference is often that DIY
                    practitioners are in a position to be more adaptable and innovative in their use
                    of digital technology in a way that can be difficult within the organisational
                    structures surrounding the humanities.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, one lesson that can be learned from both examples is that the very
                    traditional humanities method of reading handwritten texts, whether or not it is
                    done as a DIY activity, will involve digital tools in one way or another. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>DIY culture is a social world of people engaging in DIY activities, which have in
                    common that they are activities undertaken without any formal education or
                    training. Information behaviour in DIY culture is autodidact and information
                    sharing is informal and outside of organisational structures. Furthermore, it is
                    rarely dependant on funding and thus has the potential to incorporate innovative
                    solutions at a higher speed than we typically see in the humanities. This is why
                    on the one hand it is important for the Digital Humanities to look towards DIY
                    culture and learn from the methods and practises that occur here. </p>
                <p>On the other hand, the information sought, created and shared within DIY culture,
                    both on– and offline, is a product of the human mind and can, along with more
                    traditional cultural products, be understood by humanities scholars. The
                    Internet is currently exploding with this material, alongside more frivolous
                    entertainment content. If we in the humanities want to understand our current
                    culture, now and in the future, we need to study DIY culture, both off- and
                    online to a much higher degree than is currently the case. </p>
                <p>Therefore, the answer to the question whether the humanities by necessity have a
                    digital future is two-fold. Yes, the humanities need to employ digital tools in
                    order to understand culture and cultural products on the internet However,
                    humanities does not have a solely digital future as culture and cultural
                    products will continue to blossom offline and traditional humanities methods are
                    needed in order to understand these too. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bod2014" label="Bod 2014">Bod, Rens. <title rend="italic">A New
                        History of the Humanities, the Search for Principles and Patterns from
                        Antiquity to the Present</title>. Oxford: Oxford University Press,
                    2014.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boyd2012" label="Boyd and Crawford 2012">Boyd, Danah, and Kate
                    Crawford. <title rend="quotes">CRITICAL QUESTIONS FOR BIG DATA: Provocations for
                        a Cultural, Technological, and Scholarly Phenomenon.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Information, Communication &amp; Society</title> 15, no. 5
                    (2012): 662–79. doi:10.1080/1369118X.2012.678878.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brady2005" label="Brady et al 2005">Brady, Michael, X. Pan, Veit U. B.
                    Schenk, Melissa Terras, Paul Robertson, and N. Molton. <title rend="quotes">Shadow Stereo, Image Filtering and Constraint Propagation.</title> In
                        <title rend="italic">Images and Artefacts of the Ancient World</title>,
                    edited by Alan K. Bowman and Michael Brady, 4:15–30. British Academy British
                    Academy Occasional Paper. Oxford University Press/British Academy, 2005.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bt2015" label="BT 2015">BT. <title rend="quotes">The Tech Literacy
                        Challenge: Building a Culture of Tech Literacy for the Nation,</title> 2015.
                        <ref target="http://home.bt.com/pages/techliteracy/BT_Tech_Literacy.pdf">http://home.bt.com/pages/techliteracy/BT_Tech_Literacy.pdf</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cotten2012" label="Cotten et al 2012">Cotten, Shelia R., George Ford,
                    Sherry Ford, and Timothy M. Hale. <title rend="quotes">Internet Use and
                        Depression among Older Adults.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Computers in Human Behavior</title> 28, no. 2 (2012):
                    496.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fisher2006" label="Fisher et al 2006">Fisher, Karen E, Sanda Erdelez,
                    and Lynne E.F McKechnie. <title rend="italic">Theories of Information
                        Behavior</title>. Medford, N.J: Published for the American Society for
                    Information Science and Technology by Information Today, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gelber1999" label="Gelber 1999">Gelber, Steven M. <title rend="italic">Hobbies : Leisure and the Culture of Work in America</title>. New York:
                    Columbia University Press, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="green2001" label="Green et al 2001">Green, Laura R., Deborah S.
                    Richardson, Tania Lago, and Elizabeth C. Schatten-Jones. <title rend="quotes">Network Correlates of Social and Emotional Loneliness in Young and Older
                        Adults.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Personality &amp; Social Psychology Bulletin</title> 27,
                    no. 3 (2001): 281.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hartel2010" label="Hartel 2010">Hartel, Jenna. <title rend="quotes">Managing Documents at Home for Serious Leisure: A Case Study of the Hobby
                        of Gourmet Cooking.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title> 66, no. 6 (2010):
                    847–74.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="karlova2013" label="Karlova and Fisher 2013">Karlova, Natascha A., and
                    Karen E. Fisher. <title rend="quotes">A Social Diffusion Model of Misinformation
                        and Disinformation for Understanding Human Information Behaviour.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Information Research</title> 18, no. 1 (2013). <ref target="http://www.informationr.net/ir/18-1/paper573.html#.VZUGDhOqpBc">http://www.informationr.net/ir/18-1/paper573.html#.VZUGDhOqpBc</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kasioumis2014" label="Kasioumis et al 2014">Kasioumis, Nikos, Vangelis
                    Banos, and Hendrik Kalb. <title rend="quotes">Towards Building a Blog
                        Preservation Platform.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Internet and Web Information Systems</title> 17, no. 4
                    (2014): 799–825.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lafrance2015" label="LaFrance 2015">LaFrance, Adrienne. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Do Babies Know When They’re Skyping?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Atlantic</title>, September 10. <ref target="http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2015/09/do-babies-know-when-theyre-skyping/404650/">http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2015/09/do-babies-know-when-theyre-skyping/404650/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="matchar2013" label="Matchar 2013">Matchar, Emily. <title rend="italic">Homeward Bound: Why Women Are Embracing the New Domesticity</title>. Simon
                    &amp; Schuster, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcclure2013" label="Macclure 2013">Mcclure, Elisabeth. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Infant Emotional Engagement in Video Mediated
                        Interactions.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">IDC ’13</title>, 655–58.
                    doi:10.1145/2485760.2485874.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mckenzie2003" label="McKenzie 2003">McKenzie, Pamela J. <title rend="quotes">A Model of Information Practices in Accounts of Everyday-Life
                        Information Seeking.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title> 59, no. 1 (2003):
                    19–40.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mead1957" label="Mead 1957">Mead, M. (1957). <title rend="quotes">The
                        Pattern of Leisure in Contemporary American Culture.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social
                        Science</title>, 313, 11–15.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ofcom" label="Ofcom n.d.">Ofcom. <title rend="quotes">Children and
                        Parents: Media Use and Attitudes Report,</title> 2014. <ref target="http://stakeholders.ofcom.org.uk/binaries/research/media-literacy/media-use-attitudes-14/Childrens_2014_Report.pdf">http://stakeholders.ofcom.org.uk/binaries/research/media-literacy/media-use-attitudes-14/Childrens_2014_Report.pdf</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="prigoda2007" label="Prigoda and McKenzie 2007">Prigoda, Elena, and
                    Pamela J. McKenzie. <title rend="quotes">Purls of Wisdom</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title> 63, no. 1 (2007):
                    90–114.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ridge2013" label="Ridge 2013">Ridge, Mia. <title rend="quotes">From
                        Tagging to Theorizing: Deepening Engagement with Cultural Heritage through
                        Crowdsourcing.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Curator: The Museum Journal</title> 56, no. 4 (2013):
                    435–50.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rouedcunliffe2013" label="Roued-Cunliffe 2013">Roued-Cunliffe,
                    Henriette. <title rend="quotes">A Decision-Support System for the Reading of
                        Ancient Documents.</title> Doctoral thesis, University of Oxford,
                    2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rouedcunliffe2015" label="Roued-Cunliffe 2015">Roued-Cunliffe,
                    Henriette. <title rend="quotes">Archiving Online Do-It-Yourself Culture.</title>
                    Aarhus, Danmark, 2015. <ref target="http://events.netlab.dk/conference/index.php/resaw/june2015/paper/view/38">ref
                        target="http://events.netlab.dk/conference/index.php/resaw/june2015/paper/view/38</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rouedcunliffe2010" label="Roued-Cunliffe 2010">Roued-Cunliffe,
                    Henriette. <title rend="quotes">Towards a Decision Support System for Reading
                        Ancient Documents.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 25, no. 4 (2010):
                    365–79. doi:10.1093/llc/fqq020.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rosenzweig2006" label="Rosenzweig 2006">Rosenzweig, R. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Can History Be Open Source? Wikipedia and the Future of the
                        Past.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of American History</title>, 93(1), 117–146.
                    http://doi.org/10.2307/4486062</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="savolainen1995" label="Savolainen 1995">Savolainen, Reijo. <title rend="quotes">Everyday Life Information Seeking: Approaching Information
                        Seeking in the Context of <soCalled>way of Life</soCalled></title>. <title rend="italic">Library and Information Science Research</title> 17, no. 3
                    (1995): 259–94.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sigman2009" label="Sigman 2009">Sigman, Aric. <title rend="quotes">Well Connected?: The Biological Implications of <soCalled>Social
                            Networking</soCalled>.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Biologist</title> 56, no. 1 (2009). <ref target="http://www.aricsigman.com/IMAGES/Sigman_lo.pdf">http://www.aricsigman.com/IMAGES/Sigman_lo.pdf</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="skov2013" label="Skov 2013">Skov, Mette. <title rend="quotes">Hobby-Related Information-Seeking Behaviour of Highly Dedicated Online
                        Museum Visitors.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Information Research</title> 18, no. 4 (2013). <ref target="http://www.informationr.net/ir/18-4/paper597.html#.U_B7fUhDLw0">http://www.informationr.net/ir/18-4/paper597.html#.U_B7fUhDLw0</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="solomon2003" label="Solomon 2003">Solomon, Joan. <title rend="quotes">Theories of Learning and the Range of Autodidactism.</title> In <title rend="italic">The Passion to Learn : An Inquiry into Autodidactism</title>,
                    edited by Joan Solomon, 3–23. London: RoutledgeFalmer, 2003.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stebbins2007" label="Stebbins 2007">Stebbins, Robert A. <title rend="italic">Serious Leisure: A Perspective for Our Time</title>. New
                    Brunswick, N.J: Transaction Publishers, 2007.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="talja2006" label="Talja and Hansen">Talja, Sanna, and Preben Hansen.
                        <title rend="quotes">Information Sharing.</title> In <title rend="italic">New Directions in Human Information Behavior</title>, edited by Amanda
                    Spink and Charles Cole, 113–34. Dordrecht, the Netherlands: Springer,
                    2006.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="terras2005" label="Terras 2005">Terras, Melissa. <title rend="quotes">Reading the Readers: Modelling Complex Humanities Processes to Build
                        Cognitive Systems.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 20 (2005):
                    41–59.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="terras2012" label="Terras 2012">Terras, Melissa. <title rend="quotes">Image Processing in the Digital Humanities.</title> In <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities in Practice</title>, edited by Claire Warwick, Melissa
                    Terras, and Julianne Nyhan. London: Facet Publishing, 2012. <ref target="https://www-dawsonera-com.ep.fjernadgang.kb.dk/abstract/9781856049054">https://www-dawsonera-com.ep.fjernadgang.kb.dk/abstract/9781856049054</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="unruh1980" label="Unruh 1980">Unruh, David R. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Nature of Social Worlds.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Pacific Sociological Review</title> 23, no. 3 (1980):
                    271–96.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wilson2000" label="Wilson 2000">Wilson, Tom D. <title rend="quotes">Human Information Behaviour.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Informing Science</title> 3, no. 2 (2000). <ref target="https://www.ischool.utexas.edu/~i385e/readings/Wilson.pdf">https://www.ischool.utexas.edu/~i385e/readings/Wilson.pdf</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="yakel2004" label="Yakel 2004">Yakel, Elizabeth. <title rend="quotes">Seeking Information, Seeking Connections, Seeking Meaning: Genealogists and
                        Family Historians. Genealogy, Family History, Information Seeking, Archives,
                        Personal Information Management.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Information Research: An International Electronic
                        Journal</title> 10, no. 1 (2004): 205 – .</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="yeoman2010" label="Yeoman 2010">Yeoman, Alison. <title rend="quotes">Applying McKenzie’s Model of Information Practices in Everyday Life
                        Information Seeking in the Context of the Menopause Transition.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Information Research</title> 15, no. 4 (2010).</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>