<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">

  <!-- BEGIN TEI HEADER ELEMENTS -->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Books Aren't Dead: Resurrecting Audio Technology and
          Feminist Digital Humanities Approaches to Publication and Authorship</title>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Emily <dhq:family>Edwards</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>Bowling Green State University</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>eledwar@bgsu.edu</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Emily Edwards is a doctoral student in Bowling Green State University’s American
              Culture Studies Program and serves as co-producer of the Fembot Collective podcast,
                <title rend="italic">Books Aren’t Dead</title>. She received her Master’s of Arts
              from New York University's Center for European and Mediterranean Studies where she
              served as the Max Weber Research Assistant. She is concerned with topics of
              nationalism, race, and digital media and has most recently explored these issues in
              Germany as a Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst (DAAD) visiting researcher at the
              University of Leipzig’s Department of Sociology.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Robin <dhq:family>Hershkowitz</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>Bowling Green State University</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>robinh@bgsu.edu</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Robin Hershkowitz is a doctoral student in Bowling Green State University’s American
              Culture Studies Program and serves as co-producer of the Fembot Collective podcast
                <title rend="italic">Books Aren’t Dead</title>. She received her Masters of Arts
              from Bowling Green State University in Popular Culture. Her dissertation research is
              about performance rituals in comedy roasts.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
        <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
        <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000527</idno>
        <idno type="volume">015</idno>
        <idno type="issue">1</idno>
        <date when="2021-03-05">05 March 2021</date>
        <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
        <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
          <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
          <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at<ref
              target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
              >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
          <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2020-09-18" who="Taylor Arnold">Created file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <!-- END TEI HEADER ELEMENTS -->

  <!-- BEGIN TEXT -->
  <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
    <!-- FRONT TEXT -->
    <front>
      <dhq:abstract>
        <p>This article explores how the podcast medium as a form of audio technology has
          facilitated the reimagining of academic publication and feminist praxis. In this case
          study, we situate the podcast <title rend="italic">Books Aren’t Dead (BAD)</title>, an
          affiliate of the Fembot Collective, within a broader context of digital humanities
          scholarship and the field's potential to utilize audio technology to realize feminist
          approaches. <title rend="italic">BAD</title>, as a podcast, serves as an open-access
          medium that brings authors and reviewers together in a collaborative context. Audiobook
          reviews allow for a conversation between author and interviewer, whereby the author can
          place the work in a broader scholastic and contemporary context for listeners as well as
          actively engage with constructive critique and questions. The result is a dynamic
          scholarly communication rather than the static textual product of a book review. We
          discuss the unique role of audio technology within the knowledge production process from a
          performance studies and archival point of view. Additionally, in the spirit of the project
            <title rend="italic">BAD</title>, we also provide an addendum to our textual discussion
          by including a podcast where we discuss these themes as co-producers, graduate students,
          and young academics, exploring how audio technology can break down barriers to publication
          and authorship.</p>
      </dhq:abstract>
      <dhq:teaser>
        <p>This article explores how the podcast medium as a form of audio technology has
          facilitated the reimagining of academic publication and feminist praxis.</p>
      </dhq:teaser>
    </front>

    <!-- BODY TEXT -->
    <body>
      <p>Podcast Audio: <ref target="resources/audio/audio01.mp3">audio01.mp3</ref>
        <lb/>This podcast is an audio supplement to the article.</p>
      <div>
        <head/>
        <p>As an audio medium, podcasts are undergoing a renaissance in both consumption and
          production <ptr target="#bech2014"/>. Alternatively, as some writers have noted <ptr
            target="#hempel2015"/>, today's podcast market is saturated with content. Although the
          mutable form of a podcast may be situated in the historical context of radio broadcasting
            <ptr target="#berry2016"/>
          <ptr target="#menduni2007"/>, a podcast is distinctively different from the radio
          broadcast medium in modes of delivery, archiving, and function. Podcasting is a more
          accessible audio format that has increasingly enabled a broad public to record
          conversations, interviews, and fictional narratives as well as disseminate audio
          recordings on various digital platforms rather than commercial airwaves. This article
          explores the podcast medium as a form of audio technology within the dynamic field of
          digital humanities (DH). We argue that the podcast as an audio format has the potential to
          facilitate the reimagining of an academic publication as feminist praxis. As co-producers
          of the podcast <title rend="italic">Books Aren't Dead</title> (<title rend="italic"
            >BAD</title>), an affiliate of the <title rend="italic">Fembot Collective,</title> we
          offer <title rend="italic">BAD</title> as a case study to discuss how the podcast embodies
          feminist and critical approaches in the field of DH publication and project creation.</p>
        <p><title rend="italic">BAD</title> features interviews of authors and creators of books,
          academic works, and games that are at the intersection of feminism, new technology, new
          media, and digital spaces <ptr target="#fembot2019"/>. <title rend="italic">BAD</title>
          was relaunched in the fall of 2018 as part of its mother organization, the <title
            rend="italic">Fembot Collective</title>. The Fembot Collective was founded in 2009 at
          the University of Oregon <ptr target="#fembot2019"/>. Today, the Fembot Collective is a
          vibrant, scholarly community and an open-access publishing platform, supported by
          Manifold, that is home to the peer-reviewed journal <title rend="italic">Ada: Journal of
            Gender, New Media, and Technology,</title> featuring the involvement of staff from
          universities across the country <ptr target="#fembot2019"/>. As a part of the Fembot
          Collection, the <title rend="italic">BAD</title> podcast does not simply mediate and
          produce content about feminism, technology, and media, but rather, <title rend="italic"
            >BAD</title> directly intervenes in existing debates in the field of DH by producing a
          feminist audio archive and foregrounding audio interviews as alternatives to written book
          reviews.</p>
        <p>To demonstrate how the podcast format expands our definitions of text and therefore, what
          counts as scholarship in DH, this article begins by examining the <title rend="italic"
            >BAD</title> podcast in the context of feminist DH and the archival preservation of
          feminist scholarship. We outline how podcasting as a medium and genre allows for the
          expression and centralization of feminist values and forms of knowledge production. We
          then recount how podcasting permits the preservation of feminist voices and the curation
          of an archive of feminist knowledge evidenced by two recent <title rend="italic"
            >BAD</title> interviews. We discuss the significance of performance and mediation
          between producer, listener, and interviewee in the podcast format. Next, we contextualize
          how <title rend="italic">BAD</title> subverts and problematizes existing hierarchies in
          academic publishing and models a feminist praxis. We conclude with encouragement for other
          DH practitioners interested in utilizing this audio format through small-scale feminist DH
          projects and publications.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>(Critical) Digital Humanities: Debates, Tensions, and Approaches</head>
        <p><title rend="italic">BAD</title> is situated within emerging debates in DH scholarship,
          specifically the potential for DH projects to be transformative, feminist, and
          intersectional. Today we witness the increased prominence of technological devices in the
          toolbox of humanities scholars <ptr target="#dobson2019"/>, which is situated within a
          broader trend of the new <soCalled>datafied</soCalled> ways of reading, analyzing, and
          deconstructing texts. These trends privilege a <soCalled>big data</soCalled> approach to
          information <ptr target="#dobson2019" loc="3"/>
          <ptr target="#kitchin2014"/>
          <ptr target="#van2017"/>. This <soCalled>big data</soCalled> turn marginalizes feminist
          and critical methods and deprivileges close readings, situated case studies, and the
          subjective and contingent position of knowledge <ptr target="#leurs2017"/>. Scholars have
          noted the propensity of DH projects to at best fetishize digital technologies that curate
          and catalog mass amounts of information <ptr target="#dobson2019" loc="68"/>, or at worst,
          that inadvertently reproduce dominant, oppressive structures and ideologies onto texts and
          archives <ptr target="#risam2015" loc="4"/>. The field of DH has been critiqued as
          male-dominated and aligned with the neoliberal corporatization of academic knowledge <ptr
            target="#allington2016"/>
          <ptr target="#wernimont2018"/>.</p>
        <p>Despite these important critiques of the field of DH, we situate <title rend="italic"
            >BAD</title> as a DH project in the context of a vibrant tradition of feminist DH
          scholarship, and we draw attention to how <title rend="italic">BAD</title> actualizes what
          we view as the main goal of feminist DH work, to <quote rend="inline">...expand our
            notions of text and context, archive and canon, and code and program</quote>
          <ptr target="#wernimont2018" loc="xii"/>. Our intervention in this project of expansion is
          the reimagining of the academic book review as a podcast, which falls within a longer
          trajectory of feminist scholarship in DH. As Alexis Lothian and Amanda Phillips have
          noted, <quote rend="inline">archives may be the most legible form of digital humanities
            production</quote>
          <ptr target="#lothian2013" loc="6"/>. Our DH project produces the necessary historical
          archives of feminist scholarship, but also expands upon the use and content of an archive
          in the podcast format <ptr target="#wernimont2013"/>. We take a broader view of archives,
          moving away from the primacy of written texts and draw particular attention to how audio
          recordings serve as living archives. Therefore, in addition to the technology of the
          feminist archive, <title rend="italic">BAD</title> also draws upon the affordances of
          audio technology to expand the definition of text, thereby embracing feminist forms of
          knowledge production that characterize a feminist DH approach.</p>
        <p>Along with the expansion of texts, the importance of affective or mediated connection,
          collaborative labor arrangements, and centralization of ethical values also shape
          intersectional feminist DH <ptr target="#wernimont2018" loc="xiii"/>. Following this call,
            <title rend="italic">BAD</title> ultimately seeks to produce scholarly knowledge through
          a transparent, collaborative process, via audio rather than textual means. We host <title
            rend="italic">BAD</title> in an open-access format — available to stream on Anchor,
          Spotify, Apple Podcasts, and our website <title rend="italic">Books Aren't Dead</title>
          <ptr target="#hershkowitz2020"/> — to bring authors and reviewers together in a
          collaborative context to reimagine the traditional concept of a book review. As a podcast,
          the book review interview facilitates connectivity and collaboration between author and
          interviewer that is not possible through the process of writing a traditional textual book
          review.</p>
        <p>Our approach is in stark contrast to dominant publication models. Book reviews, in the
          traditional textual format, often appear in academic peer-reviewed journals, with little
          interaction between the reviewer and the author. Furthermore, book reviews are often
          pay-walled and thus inaccessible to a broader public <ptr target="#brienza2012"/>
          <ptr target="#logan2017"/>. Increasingly, academics at smaller institutions and
          independent scholars struggle to pay for institutional or individual access to expensive
          journal subscriptions <ptr target="#logan2017"/>
          <ptr target="#sample2012"/>. As a result, both the production and consumption of book
          reviews alienates the reviewer, author, and audience from one another. As Alexis Lothian
          and Amanda Phillips note, the <title rend="italic">Fembot Collective</title> — through its
          commitment to collaborative, open peer review and an open-access platform — has <quote
            rend="inline">expanded [the] notion of what <q>article</q> means</quote> and more
          broadly serves as an <quote rend="inline">innovator in scholarly communicative
            possibilities</quote> within the field of DH <ptr target="#lothian2013" loc="19"/>.
          Podcasting, therefore, offers an exciting approach that addresses critiques of DH and
          models how the field can challenge structures and hierarchies of power in the academy.</p>
        <p>Additionally, <title rend="italic">BAD</title> attempts to go beyond an additive approach
          to feminist knowledge production by emphasizing the scholarly value of podcast interviews
          not as addendums to textual book reviews, but as an alternative format. Roopika Risam, in
          problematizing Western biases in existing DH scholarship, notes that for scholars
          committed to principles of social justice, including feminism, such scholars must <quote
            rend="inline">challenge the exclusions in the record of digital knowledge</quote>
          <ptr target="#risam2018" loc="140"/>. Risam further argues that the simple inclusion of
          marginalized voices is not enough; rather, we must <quote rend="inline">seize control over
            the means of digital knowledge production</quote>
          <ptr target="#risam2018" loc="141"/>. In <title rend="italic">BAD</title>, we not only
          include feminist voices in the digital culture record, but we also seize the microphone.
          We create a new archive for a new era of DH scholarship that is feminist and
          intersectional. In terms of content, this includes the preservation of feminist voices; in
          terms of structure, this includes the facilitation of mediated connection between
          listener, producer, and interviewee; finally, in terms of practice, this project revises
          exclusive definitions of authorship within academic publishing. Therefore, <title
            rend="italic">BAD</title> functions as an intervention by sharing and preserving
          feminist voices through its interview format that expands DH's notions of text and context
          as well as archive and canon.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Books Aren't Dead: Archiving Feminist Voices Through Interviews</head>
        <p>In line with feminist calls for context and close analysis, we turn to the feminist work
          of two podcasts. One of <title rend="italic">BAD's</title> key aims is to curate an
          audible archive of feminist voices. Risam, in discussing the possibility of intersectional
          approaches in the field of DH, emphasizes that the <quote rend="inline">relationship
            between theory and praxis is integral to the digital humanities. Connections between the
            two appear in the archives built, corpora analyzed, oral histories recorded, and
            geographies mapped</quote>
          <ptr target="#risam2015" loc="4"/>. Our interview with <title rend="italic">Fembot
            Collective</title> founder Carol Stabile in <title rend="italic">BAD</title>'s inaugural
          relaunch interview demonstrates such feminist digital humanities praxis; Stabile is a
          feminist media scholar and the Associate Dean for Strategic Initiatives of the College of
          Arts and Sciences at the University of Oregon. Archiving Stabile's work as a key figure in
          feminist media studies <ptr target="#stabile1992"/>
          <ptr target="#stabile1994"/>
          <ptr target="#stabile2006"/>, makes the knowledge in Stabile's scholarly monographs
          accessible through the podcast format. The connection between feminist theory and praxis
          is realized in the content of <title rend="italic">BAD's</title> archives, and
          specifically through our interview with Stabile.</p>
        <p>In this interview, we discussed Stabile's most recent work, <title rend="italic">The
            Broadcast 41: Women and the Anti-Communist Blacklist</title>
          <ptr target="#stabile2018"/>, which focuses on how forty-one progressive women writers,
          performers, and creators working in the American television industry between the 1930s and
          1940s were forced out of their professions as targets of the <soCalled>Red
            Scare.</soCalled> Stabile's book illustrates how this resulted in a television landscape
          with a profound absence of progressive, feminist voices that we recognize in the
          white-washed, conservative <title rend="quotes">Golden Age of Television</title> of the
          1950s. In the interview, we connect contemporary forms of exclusion and marginalization
          within audio and visual industries, such as the #MeToo movement to the early 20th century,
          as explored in Stabile's work.</p>
        <p>In the podcast conversation, we were interested in Stabile's process of connecting the
          early age of television production to the contemporary media landscape. Stabile noted that
            <quote rend="inline">moments when new media get introduced [are] really important
            moments for studying the history of struggle</quote>
          <ptr target="#edwards2019a"/>. She situates the marginalization and disenfranchisement of
          progressive women writers in the 1930s and 1940s concerning contemporary trends of racial
          bias and conservative capture of media institutions, which we have most recently witnessed
          through the prominence of media figures such as President Donald Trump and
          conspiracy-theorist Alex Jones <ptr target="#edwards2019a"/>. Stabile spoke about the
          importance of highlighting the legacy of progressive women writers in the television
          industry during the blacklist. She noted that by archiving the underexplored contributions
          of progressive women in television, this <quote rend="inline">makes you understand that
            you're not the first person to fight against the structures, but that you're part of a
            history of resistance. And I think that that can be inspiring and sustaining to people
            who struggle today</quote>
          <ptr target="#edwards2019a"/>.</p>
        <p>By curating these conversations with feminist authors such as Stabile, we highlight the
          existence of a community of feminist media scholars, emphasize the critical work that is
          being done in our own field, and underscore that resistance scholarship exists, even if
          not in one's home institution or department. Wernimont and Losh note that within the field
          of DH, feminist, antiracist work and scholarship are often actively minimized or viewed as
          superfluous to the field <ptr target="#wernimont2018" loc="ix–xi"/>. In this scholarly
          landscape where there are active questions of whether feminist, critical, antiracist, and
          postcolonial approaches are welcome in the field DH scholarship <ptr
            target="#mcpherson2012"/>
          <ptr target="#risam2015"/>, interviewing feminist scholars working in the fields of media,
          technology, and science is an active response to the erasure of these approaches. Building
          our archive, we explicitly seek contributions that centralize feminist perspectives to
          counter institutional and field erasure <ptr target="#hershkowitz2019"/>. Additionally, we
          structure the interview process to create an open network of scholarly discussions
          accessible to those who may not have departmental structures that support feminist
          research. By archiving interviews with authors writing within this intersection of
          feminism, media, and technology, we create a new community of feminist scholars who are
          able to listen and engage.</p>
        <p>In our second interview with Polina Kroik about her book <title rend="italic">Cultural
            Production and the Politics of Women's Work in American Literature and Film</title>
          <ptr target="#kroik2019"/>, we discussed the legacy of women who are cultural producers
          between the 1920s and 1950s. Kroik emphasized the relationship between changes in
          technology, such as typewriters and the physical structures of offices, and how these
          material changes inaugurated new modes and forms of authorship, which forced women to
          engage in forms of affective, emotional labor. These changes continue to inform emerging
          power imbalances in the workplace that reverberate in cultural industries, such as
          Hollywood, with Kroik also highlighting the #MeToo movement <ptr target="#edwards2019b"/>.
          With this interview, we emphasize the significance of not only the preservation of Kroik's
          voice as a feminist scholar, but the possibility of <title rend="italic">BAD</title> to
          emphasize the historical marginalization and exclusion of female media producers,
          creators, and writers in cultural industries.</p>
        <p>While we agree with Risam that an additive approach to critical DH is not enough <ptr
            target="#risam2018"/>, the addition of podcast interviews serve as potential models for
          alternative recording and publishing of feminist histories. The curation of a feminist
          digital archive through podcasts is only one aspect of the significance of this type of DH
          work. The interview does not merely comprise a static archive; rather, the interview can
          be read beyond its status as a text and publication. The connections produced through the
          mediated performance of producer, interviewee, and listener also underscore the value of
          podcasts as an alternative form of book review publication that privileges connectivity
          and affect, key principles in our feminist approach <ptr target="#wernimont2018"
            loc="xiii"/>.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Podcaster, Guest, and Listening Audience: A Mediation of Performances</head>
        <p>Podcasts can be a site of performance whereby the interviewer and interviewee share
          affective, aural, and interpersonal intimacy that shapes knowledge creation and
          circulation. Thus, we consider performance studies an important context with which to
          locate podcasting in feminist praxis. In one of the first edited academic collections on
          podcasting, <title rend="italic">Podcasting: New Aural Cultures and Digital Media</title>
          (2018), the editors note that podcasts represent <quote rend="inline">the possibility, in
            one <q>space,</q> to create a considered yet engaging conversation that merges
            criticality, scholarship, fandom, and practice, not to mention the possibility of
            attracting an audience that found value in our conversations</quote>
          <ptr target="#llinares2018" loc="1"/>. Here, the podcast is more than the mp3 file or an
          audio recorded sound. The space is one of performance, invention, and even resistance. As
          performance studies scholars Richard Schechner and Sara Brady state, <quote rend="inline"
            >performance must be construed as a broad spectrum or continuum of human actions,
            ranging from ritual, play, popular entertainments, performing arts and everyday life
            performances and to the enactment of professional, gender, race, and class roles</quote>
          <ptr target="#schechner2013" loc="2"/>. As such, we emphasize how the various performances
          within the production of podcasting underscore the potential for feminist DH praxis.</p>
        <p>Regardless of genre, podcasts are a type of performance where podcasters and guests are
          performing a certain version of themselves in collaborative communication. In emphasizing
          the performance aspects of podcasting, we draw attention to the possibility of co-creation
          through performance, which facilitates forms of affective, dynamic communication outside
          of the removed and supposedly objective tone of the written book review. Podcasting has
          the potential for collaborative knowledge production between author and interviewee
          through the shared experience of performance in the audio conversation. Additionally,
          podcasts provide a staging ground for feminist conversations through the ease of podcast
          production and distribution on digital platforms. Using the lens of performance studies,
          we argue for the possibility of viewing podcasts as a medium that allows for the
          centralization of feminist DH praxis.</p>
        <p>As an affective form of communication, the act of podcasting a book review connects to
          feminist DH praxis. The surplus information that the affect of podcasting invites
          transforms the value of a book review to align with feminist approaches. Podcasts, such as
            <title rend="italic">BAD</title>, reveal previously hidden elements of academic
          knowledge, such as the conditions of production, ethics, relationships, and the
          socio-political context of the work. In our interviews, we are interested not simply in
          the content of the text but the authors' experience in producing the text. We particularly
          want to emphasize the fluidity of a podcast performance that facilitates feminist forms of
          communicative engagement. The audience, while listening rather than reading, experiences a
          form of affective connection that allows for identification with the voices and the
          centralization of feminist themes. The audience's experience of listening is now included
          in the creation of knowledge. Each individualized listeners' decoding allows for and
          encourages different places of entry and departure within the podcast.</p>
        <p>Just as the listener has the opportunity to engage with the podcast, the author or
          interviewee has the potential to perform the self as an authoritative voice via
          co-scriptive interactions and discussions. Typically, the accessibility of an academic
          publication creates the scholarly authority, specifically if it is behind a paywall and
          situated within a vocabulary only understood by other academics. However, we contend that
          this type of scholarly authority is determined by institutional methods that are arbitrary
          and prohibitive to a broader public. In <title rend="italic">BAD</title>, the interviewer
          and the interviewee are not just performing scholarly inquiry but also engaging in dynamic
          communication throughout the interview that redefines scholarly authority. The interviewer
          prepares written questions, but the conversation may change as she switches her line of
          inquiry to the author. Additionally, the author can lead the conversation in various
          directions as part of an ongoing dialogue. Stacy Copeland emphasizes that in podcasts, the
          changing emotional tone of voice and other background audio allows for the podcast to
          become a form of affective media. Copeland states that in podcasts, <quote rend="inline"
            >the material voice becomes a sticky surface to be stuck with multiple decodings,
            re-workings and affect</quote>
          <ptr target="#copeland2018" loc="220"/>. An interview between two people can become
            <soCalled>sticky</soCalled> in the sense that emotional changes in voice, laughter, and
          unexpected moments can produce the possibility for multiple points of engagement.
          Stickiness, then, produces surplus affect and creates the conditions for greater dynamic,
          dialogic engagement, thus providing a facet of connection that goes beyond the formulaic
          structure of a book review.</p>
        <p>While Stabile and all the authors interviewed on <title rend="italic">BAD</title> are
          experienced scholars, the relationship between interviewee and interviewer produces a more
          equitable relational dynamic compared to the structure of the book review in which the
          reviewer comments on and critiques a text from afar. The ability to ask questions of
          authors in real-time through the podcast performance for clarification, expansion of
          concepts, or even constructive critique, produces new knowledge and information about the
          monographs through dialogue and partnership. The interview not only produces a dynamic
          product but through the process of the interview performance, the interviewer engages in
          authorship through performance. This method is directly aligned with feminist emphasis on
          collaborative forms of knowledge production outside of the confines of the academy and the
          exclusive academic publishing apparatus <ptr target="#lothian2013" loc="22"/>.</p>
        <p>Our framing of podcasting as performance is an important contribution to feminist DH
          praxis. To be included within feminist DH praxis, the podcast ought to produce a unique
          space for dialogue and engagement that was previously limited in the current state of
          academic publishing. We situate <title rend="italic">BAD</title> to serve as an aural
          space for feminist scholarly engagement in the field of DH that is, at times, exclusionary
          to feminist concerns, projects, and critiques <ptr target="#wernimont2018"/>. Another way
          in which podcasting as performance establishes feminist DH praxis is that podcasts
          ultimately represent active possibilities. These possibilities include performance,
          affective connection, staging, learning, and the extension of the professional
          relationship beyond the interview. Podcasts have the potential to directly archive
          emotions and experiences, and therefore feminist ways of knowing, thus serving as both
          affective as well as physical archives. Affective archives preserve performances,
          experiences, emotions, and interactions. Thus, the performance of podcasting is crucial to
          subverting academic hierarchies by creating archives beyond the physical and written
          form.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Subverting Academic Publishing Hierarchies and Podcasting Feminist Futures</head>
        <p>Subverting academic hierarchies through podcasting offers dynamic new opportunities for
          feminist DH practitioners. In our professionalization, we have been informed that in the
          hierarchy of publishing, book reviews may be lower in prestige and often serve as a way
          for graduate students to ease into publishing. Therefore, the individuals that do engage
          with book reviews may find their labor delegitimized and seen as <soCalled>knowing their
            place</soCalled> and <soCalled>doing their time.</soCalled> However, we see engaging
          with the labor of other people's work as incredibly important to elevate and legitimize
          one another's research, especially for marginalized authors in academia. This is important
          since the work of individuals who identify as Black scholars, indigenous scholars,
          scholars of color, and female-identified and non-binary scholars, is underrepresented in
          academic literature and within the academic publishing industry <ptr target="#mirza2015"/>
          <ptr target="#roh2016"/>
          <ptr target="#souto2007"/>. A feminist perspective shifts the focus on padding the
          reviewer's CV to supporting the author in the interview space and amplifying feminist
          scholarship.</p>
        <p>Another intervention is using sound. Podcasting can facilitate a more feminist use of the
          idea of voice, both literally and figuratively. Like many women, we were socialized into
          thinking our voices were not authoritative both in content and delivery. Just as
          marginalized scholars confront an academic publishing apparatus that is biased towards
          white, male forms of authorship and knowledge production <ptr target="#mirza2015"/>
          <ptr target="#roh2016"/>
          <ptr target="#souto2007"/>, feminine voices are audibly policed. This can manifest in the
          characterization of <soCalled>vocal fry</soCalled> as unprofessional and unattractive <ptr
            target="#anderson2014"/>, or a preference among men to listen to higher-pitched
          femininized voices over average pitched tones <ptr target="#feinberg2008"/>. However, we
          maintain that a podcast's performative authorship breaks down barriers to knowledge such
          as paywalls, and also creates spaces for diverse voices to emerge and claim authority.
          Podcasts become a way to intervene in the politics of sound.</p>
        <p>Along with amplifying voices, the form of podcasting itself challenges existing
          hierarchies. The technical and financial barriers to entry are lower than many other DH
          methods. On the distribution side, platforms for producing and distributing podcasts, such
          as Anchor, have become increasingly user-friendly. Unlike most academic journals that are
          behind steep paywalls, listeners can access and download podcasts with financial and
          technical ease. As a result, one can bypass expensive and narrow publishing models while
          increasing access and discovery of, in our case, feminist scholarship.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, DH projects should not be viewed as alternatives to traditional academic
          practices; rather, the academic hierarchies must be changed to accommodate new ways of
          knowledge production. One example that both incorporates and challenges existing academic
          frameworks is <title rend="italic">Reviews of Digital Humanities</title>, a journal
          founded by Jennifer Guiliano and Roopika Risam in 2019. The goal of this open-access
          journal <quote rend="inline">is to foster critical discourse about scholarship in a format
            useful to other scholars,</quote> publishing <quote rend="inline">project overviews
            written by project directors alongside peer reviews written by members of digital
            humanities communities</quote>
          <ptr target="#guiliano2020"/>. This project takes the form of incorporating previous
          academic standards by existing as a peer-reviewed journal but expands upon the idea of
          what is considered eligible and credible to academic archives. Guiliano and Risam's
          initiative demonstrates how creators of DH projects can still be legitimized by their
          peers through rigorous reviews and evaluation, but with DH projects and publications
          considered on their own terms, rather than trying to fit into the very evaluative
          structure of academic journal publishing that DH practitioners are trying to subvert.
            <title rend="italic">BAD</title>, therefore, synthesizes traditional academic publishing
          conventions, such as the book review, with the podcasting format to realize the potential
          of feminist scholarly engagement. The project models how small-scale feminist DH audio
          projects can realize a different future for DH.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Conclusion</head>
        <p>In conclusion, we have emphasized the significance and transformative potential of
          utilizing audio technology to produce alternative forms of knowledge. We have situated
            <title rend="italic">BAD</title> within the scholarly conversation of feminist DH
          practice, drawing attention to expanding definitions of scholarly texts and the
          possibility of creating a dynamic archive. <title rend="italic">BAD</title> utilizes
          podcasting to highlight and preserve the work of feminist scholars writing within spheres
          of media and technology. Additionally, we have suggested the importance of drawing on
          performance studies to understand the mediated connection between audience, interviewee,
          and producer, which is a form of collaborative connection unique to the podcast format.
          Ultimately, in this article, we have demonstrated how podcasting can allow feminist DH
          practitioners to produce and publish scholarly knowledge in a way that effectively
          challenges the hierarchical practices of academic publishing.</p>
        <p>This case study contributes to the feminist field of DH and serves as a call to action
          for other feminist and critical DH scholars to engage with the audio medium of podcasting.
          There is a burgeoning field of academic podcasts that demonstrate the exciting possibility
          of producing knowledge from a variety of interdisciplinary perspectives using audio
          technology, including the podcast <title rend="italic">Rocking the Academy</title> from
          Mary Churchill and Roopika Risam, the <title rend="italic">MFAngle Podcast</title> from
          Mirna Palacio Ornelas, Bessie F. Zaldívar, and Blessing Christopher et al., and the
          podcast <title rend="italic">Alt! Ack!</title> from Robin Hershkowitz and Patrick Felton.
          These are just a few examples of some exciting additions to the field of critical
          podcasting.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, as a truly interdisciplinary field, DH includes ways of knowing that reject
          arbitrary disciplinarily divisions of knowledge and structures of hierarchy within the
          academy. Technical knowledge has been streamlined by accessible programs and applications.
          Thus, the opportunity to create is increasingly available to the public and individuals
          with beginner levels of technical acumen. We believe that podcasting can be a radical
          interdisciplinary intervention that challenges not only the textual form of scholarly
          discourse but also its content. We have seized the mic at Bowling Green State University
          as <title rend="italic">BAD</title> co-producers, and we hope this article serves as an
          impetus to pass the mic to other DH scholars invested in feminist and critical
          approaches.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <!-- BACK TEXT -->
    <back>
      <listBibl>
        <bibl xml:id="allington2016" label="Allington et al. 2016">Allington, D., S. Brouillette,
          and D. Golumbia. <title rend="quotes">Neoliberal Tools (and Archives): A Political History
            of Digital Humanities</title> (2016). <title rend="italic">Los Angeles Review of
            Books</title>. Retrieved from: <ref
            target="https://lareviewofbooks.org/article/neoliberal-tools-archives-political-history-digital-humanities/"
            >https://lareviewofbooks.org/article/neoliberal-tools-archives-political-history-digital-humanities/</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="anderson2014" label="Anderson et al. 2014">Anderson, R.C., C.A. Klofstad, W.J.
          Mayew, and M. Venkatachalam. <title rend="quotes">Vocal Fry May Undermine the Success of
            Young Women in the Labor Market,</title>
          <title rend="italic">PLOS ONE </title>9.5 (2014).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="bennett2015" label="Bennett 2015">Bennett, L. <title rend="quotes">The
            First-Person Industrial Complex,</title>
          <title rend="italic">Slate</title> (2015). Retrieved from: <ref
            target="http://www.slate.com/articles/life/technology/2015/09/the_first_person_industrial_complex_how_the_harrowing_personal_essay_took.html"
            >http://www.slate.com/articles/life/technology/2015/09/the_first_person_industrial_complex_how_the_harrowing_personal_essay_took.html</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="bech2014" label="Bech 2014">Bech, L. <title rend="quotes">Is This the Golden
            Age of Podcasts?,</title>
          <title rend="italic">Columbia Journalism Review</title> (2014). Retrieved from: <ref
            target="https://archives.cjr.org/behind_the_news/is_this_the_golden_age_of_podc_1.php"
            >https://archives.cjr.org/behind_the_news/is_this_the_golden_age_of_podc_1.php</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="berry2016" label="Berry 2016">Berry, R. <title rend="quotes">Podcasting:
            Considering the Evolution of the Medium and Its Association with the Word
            <q>Radio,</q></title><title rend="italic">Radio Journal: International Studies in
            Broadcast &amp; Audio Media</title> 14.1 (2016): 7–22.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="brienza2012" label="Brienza 2012">Brienza, C. <title rend="quotes">Opening the
            Wrong Gate? The Academic Spring and Scholarly Publishing in the Humanities and Social
            Sciences,</title>
          <title rend="italic">Publishing Research Quarterly</title> 28.3 (2012): 159–171.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="churchill" label="Churchill et al.">Churchill, M., Risam. R. Rocking the
          Academy, (n.d.). Retrieved from: <ref target="https://rocking-the-academy.simplecast.com"
            >https://rocking-the-academy.simplecast.com</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="copeland2018" label="Copeland 2018">Copeland, S. <title rend="quotes">A
            Feminist Materialisation of Amplified Voice: Queering Identity and Affect in <title
              rend="italic">The Heart.</title></title> In Llinares, D., Fox N., and R. Berry (eds.),
            <title rend="italic">Podcasting New Aural Cultures and Digital Media.</title> Palgrave
          McMillan, New York (2018): 209-225.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="dobson2019" label="Dobson 2019">Dobson, J.E. <title rend="italic">Critical
            Digital Humanities: The Search for a Methodology</title>. University of Illinois Press,
          Champaign (2019).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="edwards2019a" label="Edwards and Hershkowitz 2019a">Edwards, E., and R.
          Hershkowitz. <title rend="quotes">Carol Stabile Interview,</title>
          <title rend="italic">Books Aren't Dead</title> (2019). Retrieved from: <ref
            target="https://fembotcollective.manifoldapp.org/projects/books-aren-t-dead/resource/carol-stabile-interview"
            >https://fembotcollective.manifoldapp.org/projects/books-aren-t-dead/resource/carol-stabile-interview</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="edwards2019b" label="Edwards and Hershkowitz 2019b">Edwards, E., and R.
          Hershkowitz. <title rend="quotes">Polina Kroik Interview,</title><title rend="italic"
            >Books Aren't Dead</title> (2019). Retrieved from: <ref
            target="https://fembotcollective.manifoldapp.org/projects/books-aren-t-dead/resource/polina-kroik-interview"
            >https://fembotcollective.manifoldapp.org/projects/books-aren-t-dead/resource/polina-kroik-interview</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="everett2003" label="Everett 2003">Everett, A., and J.T. Caldwell. <title
            rend="italic">New Media: Theories and Practices of Digitextuality</title>. Routledge,
          New York (2003).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="feinberg2008" label="Feinberg et al. 2008">Feinberg, D.R., L.M. DeBruine, B.C.
          Jones, and D.I. Perrett. <title rend="quotes">The Role of Femininity and Averageness of
            Voice Pitch in Aesthetic Judgments of Women's Voices,</title>
          <title rend="italic">Perception</title> 37.4 (2008): 615–623.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="fembot2019" label="Fembot 2019">Fembot Collective<title rend="quotes"
            >Home.</title>(2019). Retrieved from: <ref
            target="https://fembotcollective.manifoldapp.org/"
            >https://fembotcollective.manifoldapp.org</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="guiliano2020" label="Guiliano and Risam 2020">Guiliano, J., and R. Risam.
            <title rend="quotes">Welcome to Reviews in Digital Humanities</title>, <title
            rend="italic">Reviews in Digital Humanities</title> (2020)<title rend="italic">.</title>
          Retrieved from: <ref target="https://reviewsindh.pubpub.org"
            >https://reviewsindh.pubpub.org</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="hershkowitz2019" label="Hershkowitz 2019">Hershkowitz, R. Call for
          Submissions: Books Aren't Dead Podcast. (2019).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="hershkowitz2020" label="Hershkowitz and Edwards 2020">Hershkowitz, R., and E.
          Edwards. <title rend="quotes">Books Aren't Dead,</title>
          <title rend="italic">Books Aren't Dead</title> (2020). Retrieved from: <ref
            target="https://anchor.fm/booksarentdead/"
          >https://anchor.fm/booksarentdead/</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="hershkowitzNA" label="Hershkowitz and Felton">Hershkowitz, R. and P. Felton.
            <title rend="italic">Alt! Ack!</title> n.d. Retrieved from: <ref
            target="https://anchor.fm/altack">https://anchor.fm/altack</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="hempel2015" label="Hempel 2015">Hempel, J. <title rend="quotes">If Podcasts
            Are the New Blogs, Enjoy the Golden Age While It Lasts,</title>
          <title rend="italic">Wired</title> (2015) Retrieved from: <ref
            target="https://www.wired.com/2015/12/if-podcasts-are-the-new-blogs-enjoy-the-golden-age-while-it-lasts/"
            >https://www.wired.com/2015/12/if-podcasts-are-the-new-blogs-enjoy-the-golden-age-while-it-lasts/</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="kitchin2014" label="Kitchin 2014">Kitchin, R. <title rend="quotes">Big Data,
            new epistemologies and paradigm shifts,</title>
          <title rend="italic">Big Data &amp; Society</title> 1, (2014): 1–12.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="kuntsman2012" label="Kuntsman 2012">Kunstman, A. <title rend="quotes"
            >Introduction: Affective Fabrics of Digital Cultures.</title> In Karatzogianni, A. and
          A. Kuntsman, (eds), <title rend="italic">Digital Cultures and the Politics of Emotion:
            Feelings, Affect and Technological Change,</title> Palgrave Macmillan, London
          (2012).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="kroik2019" label="Kroik 2019">Kroik, P. <title rend="italic">Cultural
            Production and the Politics of Women's Work in American Literature and Film</title>.
          Routledge, New York (2019).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="leurs2017" label="Leurs 2017">Leurs, K. <title rend="quotes">feminist data
            studies: using digital methods for ethical, reflexive and situated socio-cultural
            research,</title>
          <title rend="italic">Feminist Review</title> 115, (2017): 130–154.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="llinares2018" label="Llinares and Fox 2018">Llinares, D., and N. Fox.
            Eds<title rend="italic">. Podcasting: New Aural Cultures and Digital Media</title>.
          Palgrave Macmillan, New York (2018).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="logan2017" label="Logan 2017">Logan, C. J. <title rend="quotes">We Can Shift
            Academic Culture through Publishing Choices,</title>
          <title rend="italic">F1000 Research</title> 6.518 (2017).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="lothian2013" label="Lothian and Phillips 2013">Lothian, A. and A. Phillips.
            <title rend="quotes">Can Digital Humanities Mean Transformative Critique?,</title>
          <title rend="italic">Journal of E-Media Studies</title> 3.1 (2013).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="mann2019" label="Mann 2019">Mann, R. <title rend="quotes">22. Paid to Do but
            Not to Think: Reevaluating the Role of Graduate Student Collaborators.</title>In M. K.
          Gold and L.F. Klein (eds.), <title rend="italic">Debates in Digital Humanities
            2019</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2019).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2012" label="McPherson 2012">McPherson, T. <title rend="quotes">9:
            Why Are the Digital Humanities So White? or Thinking the Histories of Race and
            Computation.</title> In M.K Gold (ed.), <title rend="italic">Debates in Digital
            Humanities,</title> University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis, MN (2012).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="menduni2007" label="Menduni 2007">Menduni, E. <title rend="quotes">Four Steps
            in Innovative Radio Broadcasting: From QuickTime to Podcasting,</title>
          <title rend="italic">Radio Journal: International Studies in Broadcast &amp; Audio
            Media</title> 5.1 (2007): 9–18.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="mirza2015" label="Mirza 2015">Mirza, H. S. <title rend="quotes">Decolonizing
            Higher Education: Black Feminism and the Intersectionality of Race and Gender,</title>
          <title rend="italic">Journal of Feminist Scholarship,</title> 7–8 (2015): 1–12.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="palacio" label="Palacio et al.">Palacio Ornelas, M., B.F. Zaldívar, B.
          Christopher, H. Ankong, S. Jones, S. Boudreau, D. Carrera, J. Forte, and T. Thompson.
            <title rend="italic">MFAngle Podcast</title> (n.d.). Retrieved from: <ref
            target="https://sites.google.com/vt.edu/mfanglepodcast/about?authuser=0"
            >https://sites.google.com/vt.edu/mfanglepodcast/about?authuser=0</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="risam2015" label="Risam 2015">Risam, R. <title rend="quotes">Beyond the
            Margins: Intersectionality and the Digital Humanities,</title>
          <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly,</title> 9.2 (2015).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="risam2018" label="Risam 2018">Risam, R. <title rend="italic">New Digital
            Worlds Postcolonial Digital Humanities in Theory, Praxis, and Pedagogy</title>.
          Northwestern University Press, Evanston (2018).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="roh2016" label="Roh 2016">Roh, C. <title rend="quotes">Inequalities in
            Publishing,</title>
          <title rend="italic">Urban Library Journal</title> 22. 2 (2016): 1-16.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="sample2012" label="Sample 2012">Sample, I. <title rend="quotes">Harvard
            University Says It Can't Afford Journal Publishers' Prices,</title>
          <title rend="italic">The Guardian</title>, (2012). Retrieved from: <ref
            target="http://wavelets.ens.fr/BOYCOTT_ELSEVIER/ARTICLES/2012_04_24_The_Guardian.pdf"
            >http://wavelets.ens.fr/BOYCOTT_ELSEVIER/ARTICLES/2012_04_24_The_Guardian.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="schechner1985" label="Schechner 1985">Schechner, R. <title rend="italic"
            >Between theater &amp; anthropology</title>. University of Pennsylvania Press,
          Philadelphia (1985).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="schechner2013" label="Schechner and Brady 2013">Schechner, R. and S. Brady.
            <title rend="italic">Performance studies: an introduction</title>. Routledge, London
          (2013).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="souto2007" label="Souto and Ray 2007">Souto-Manning, M. and N. Ray. <title
            rend="quotes">Beyond Survival in the Ivory Tower: Black and Brown Women's Living
            Narratives,</title>
          <title rend="italic">Equity &amp; Excellence in Education</title> 40.4 (2007):
          280–90.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="spinelli2019" label="Spinelli and Dann 2019">Spinelli, M. and L. Dann. <title
            rend="italic">Podcasting. The Audio Media Revolution</title>, Bloomsbury Academic,
          London (2019).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="stabile2018" label="Stabile 2018">Stabile, C.A. <title rend="italic">The
            Broadcast 41: Women and the Anti-Communist Blacklist</title>. Goldsmiths Press, London
          (2018).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="stabile1994" label="Stabile 1994">Stabile, C. A. <title rend="italic">Feminism
            and the Technological Fix.</title> Manchester University Press, Manchester, UK
          (1994).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="stabile1992" label="Stabile 1992">Stabile, C.A. <title rend="quotes">Shooting
            the Mother: Fetal Photography and the Politics of Disappearance.</title>
          <title rend="italic">Camera Obscura Feminism, Culture, Media Studies</title> 10, (1992):
          178–205.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="stabile2006" label="Stabile 2006">Stabile, C. A. <title rend="italic">White
            victims, black villains: gender, race, and crime news in US culture,</title> Routledge,
          New York, NY (2006).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="van2017" label="van Es and Schäfer 2017">van Es, K. and M. T. Schäfer. <title
            rend="italic">The Datafied Society. Studying Culture through Data</title>. Amsterdam
          University Press, Amsterdam (2017).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="wernimont2018" label="Wernimont and Losh 2018">Wernimont, J. and E. Losh.
            <title rend="quotes">Introduction.</title>In J. Wernimont and E. Losh (eds.), <title
            rend="italic">Bodies of Information Intersectional Feminism and the Digital
            Humanities.</title> University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis and London, (2018):
          ix–xxvi.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="wernimont2013" label="Wernimont 2013">Wernimont, J. <title rend="quotes"
            >Whence Feminism? Assessing Feminist Interventions in Digital Literary
            Archives.</title><title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 7.1
          (2013).</bibl>
      </listBibl>
    </back>
  </text>
  <!-- END TEXT -->

</TEI>
