<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Linked data from TEI (LIFT): A Teaching Tool for
                    TEI to Linked Data Transformation</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Francesca
                        <dhq:family>Giovannetti</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6007-9118</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Bologna</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>francesc.giovannett6@unibo.it</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Francesca Giovannetti is a Ph.D. candidate in Digital Humanities at the
                            University of Bologna's Department of Classical Philology and Italian
                            Studies. Her current research focuses on the use of semantic web
                            technologies for the representation of writers' archives. She
                            collaborates to the <ref
                                target="http://projects.dharc.unibo.it/bufalini-notebook/">Paolo
                                Bufalini's notebook semantic digital edition</ref> project.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Francesca <dhq:family>Tomasi</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6631-8607</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Bologna</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>francesca.tomasi@unibo.it</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Francesca Tomasi is a Professor in Archival Science, Bibliography and
                            Librarianship at the Department of Classical Philology and Italian
                            Studies of the University of Bologna, where, since 2006, she has been
                            engaged in Digital Humanities research and teaching, expecially in the
                            context of Semantic Web technologies. She is currently the head of: a
                            research center (Digital Humanities Advanced Research Centre - /DH.arc),
                            an international master degree (Digital Humanities and Digital Knowledge
                            - DHDK) and a PhD programme (Cultural Heritage in the Digital Ecosystem
                            - CHeDE). She has written about 100 papers in the field of Digital
                            Humanities and she is the scientific leader of a number of research
                            projects and digital environments or applications. Among her last
                            publications, the book: F. Tomasi, <title rend="italic">Organizzare la
                                conoscenza: Digital Humanities e Web semantico. Un percorso tra
                                archivi, biblioteche e musei</title>, Milano, Editrice
                            Bibliografica, 2022.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">
                    <!-- including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110 -->000605 </idno>
                <idno type="volume"
                    ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->2</idno>
                <date when="2022-04-01">01 April 2022</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Produced by pandoc.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>digital scholarly editions</item>
                        <item>linked open data</item>
                        <item>TEI</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2022-08-03" who="BRG">resolved encoding errors and revised xml:id naming
                structure</change>
            <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
                    target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000605/000605.xml"
                    >GitHub </ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="original" xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>The purpose of this paper is to introduce <title rend="italic">Linked data from
                        TEI</title> (LIFT), an open source tool written as a set of Python scripts
                    for generating linked data from TEI-encoded texts. LIFT’s goal is to walk users
                    through the transformation process from TEI to linked data step by step, as well
                    as to promote a better understanding of the theoretical and methodological
                    aspects that underpin the transformation. LIFT was created in the context of the
                    University of Bologna’s Master Degree in Digital Humanities and Digital
                    Knowledge as a teaching tool for students encountering linked open data for the
                    first time as a method of organizing and publishing cultural knowledge and,
                    specifically, digital scholarly editions on the web in a perspective of data
                    integration.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>Linked data from TEI (LIFT) is an open source tool for generating linked data
                    from TEI-encoded texts.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="introduction">
                <head>1. Introduction<note> This paper is the result of a collaborative work. In
                        particular, Francesca Tomasi is responsible for sections 1, 5 and 6, while
                        Francesca Giovannetti is responsible for sections 2, 3 and 4.</note>
                </head>
                <p>Many and diverse scientific communities, including digital textual scholars, have
                    shown increasing interest in semantic web technologies and linked open data
                    (LOD) as a means of knowledge representation since the early 2000s, when Tim
                    Berners-Lee coined the concept of a web of interconnected data rather than
                    simply documents (see <ptr target="#spadini2021"/>). Nonetheless, there is a
                    lack of user-friendly tools for working with digital scholarly editions and
                    LOD.</p>
                <p>
                    <title rend="italic">Linked data from TEI</title> (LIFT) is a Digital Humanities
                    tool for generating linked open data (LOD) from TEI-encoded texts. LIFT, which
                    is accessible at <ref target="https://projects.dharc.unibo.it/lift"
                        >https://projects.dharc.unibo.it/lift</ref>, provides a set of TEI-to-LOD
                    transformation scripts written in Python. The scripts, addressing the
                    transformation of different types of entities to LOD, are thoroughly documented
                    to facilitate their understanding and reuse. The purpose of this paper is to
                    introduce LIFT as a teaching tool for supporting the adoption of linked open
                    data in digital scholarly editing. Our plan is to use LIFT as part of a
                    laboratory activity for the University of Bologna’s Master Degree in Digital
                    Humanities and Digital Knowledge, which will combine the knowledge and skills
                    acquired by the students from different modules: text encoding with the TEI,
                    ontology development, Python programming, and linked open data for cultural
                        heritage.<note> The modules are Digital Text in the Humanities: Theories,
                        Methodologies and Applications; Knowledge representation and extraction;
                        Computational thinking and programming, and Knowledge organization and
                        cultural heritage (see the full descriptions at <ref
                            target="https://corsi.unibo.it/2cycle/DigitalHumanitiesKnowledge"
                            >https://corsi.unibo.it/2cycle/DigitalHumanitiesKnowledge</ref>).
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>This paper first provides a brief background on linked open data and their use in
                    digital text representation (see <ref target="#background">Section 2</ref>). It
                    then goes on to consider related work in the field of TEI to LOD transformation
                    (see <ref target="#relatedWork">Section 3</ref>) as well as to introduce LIFT
                    from both a technical and methodological perspective (see <ref
                        target="#linkedDataFromTeiLift">Section 4</ref>). Finally, it discusses the
                    potential application of LIFT in digital humanities learning contexts (see <ref
                        target="#LiftInTheClassroom">Section 5</ref> and <ref
                        target="#conclusionAndNextSteps">Section 6</ref>).</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="background">
                <head>2. Background</head>
                <p>The concept of linked open data refers to a method of publishing structured data
                    – as well as organizing knowledge – on the web in such a way that they can be
                    semantically interlinked to form open clouds of integrated information. As is
                    already well known, LOD are based on the Resource Description Framework (RDF), a
                    graph data model used for making statements about resources. Each RDF statement
                    contains a subject, a predicate, and an object, represented by unique URIs. The
                    subject is the resource being described, the object is either a characteristic
                    of the subject (such as its type) or a resource related to the subject, and the
                    predicate expresses the relationship between the subject and the object (see
                        <ref target="#example1">example 1 below</ref>). The meaning of RDF data is
                    defined by machine-readable ontologies, formal descriptions of specific concepts
                    within a domain and the relationships holding between them.</p>
                <dhq:example xml:id="example1">
                    <head>An RDF representation of the statement <title rend="quotes">Alexander the
                            Great has parent Philip II of Macedon</title> (extracted from
                        DBpedia).</head>
                    <eg lang="xml">
                        <![CDATA[
<http://dbpedia.org/resource/Alexander_the_Great> # Alexander the Great
<http://dbpedia.org/ontology/parent> # has parent
<http://dbpedia.org/resource/Philip_II_of_Macedon> # Philip II of Macedon

                    ]]>
                    </eg>
                </dhq:example>

                <p>RDF statements can be used to represent information in digital scholarly editions
                    as linked open data.<note> For a definition of digital scholarly edition, see
                            <ptr target="#sahle2016"/>.</note> To cite just a few examples, the <ref
                        target="https://finerollshenry3.org.uk/">Henry III Fine Rolls edition</ref>
                    experiments with linked data to express complex relationships between people in
                    historical documents (see <ptr target="#ciula2008"/>). The <ref
                        target="https://ancientwisdoms.ac.uk/">Sharing Ancient Wisdoms
                    project</ref>, on the other hand, uses linked data to reconstruct text
                    interaction (see <ptr target="#jordanous2012"/>), while the <ref
                        target="https://projects.dharc.unibo.it/bufalini-notebook">Paolo Bufalini’s
                        Notebook edition</ref> uses linked data to represent the interconnections
                    between the various types of fragments – quotations, translations, and
                    annotations – that make up the text (see <ptr target="#daquino2019"/>). Similar
                    information extracted from texts, in addition to administrative, structural, and
                    descriptive metadata, can make a significant contribution to the development of
                    a cultural heritage linked open data cloud: texts do indeed occupy a prominent
                    space in cultural heritage representation. However, in order to reuse and
                    integrate texts into LOD systems, information must first be expressed in RDF
                    according to widely used ontologies in the digital humanities and cultural
                    heritage domains.</p>
                <p>The Text Encoding Initiative (TEI), an XML vocabulary for encoding texts in the
                    humanities, is the de facto standard for digital scholarly editing.<note> On the
                        role of the TEI standard in digital scholarly editing, see <ptr
                            target="#mla2016"/>, <ptr target="#price2008"/>, and <ptr
                            target="#sahle2014"/>.</note> The standard defines terms for
                    representing a wide range of textual entities, including personal names, place
                    names, dates, concepts, and events. Unlike RDF, the TEI has traditionally taken
                    a document-centric approach to representing such entities, with texts processed
                    as ordered hierarchies of content objects nesting neatly one inside the other
                    (see <ptr target="#derose1990"/> and <ptr target="#renear1993"/>). However,
                    transitioning from a document-centric paradigm to a data-centric paradigm, such
                    as LOD, is not an easy task: converting TEI editions into graphs of RDF
                    statements necessitates a conceptual shift in which texts are no longer viewed
                    as documents but as collections of interconnected entities (see <ptr
                        target="#tomasi2012"/>).</p>
                <p>The movement beyond TEI towards linked open data began in 2004, when a TEI
                    Special Interest Group on Ontologies was formed with the goal of investigating
                    the feasibility of encoding information about persons, dates, events, places and
                    objects outside the text, in parallel with the steps taken by the Museum
                    community, which was working on the development of CIDOC CRM, an ontological
                    vocabulary for the description of museum collections (see <ptr
                        target="#teiontologies"/>). The new P5 release of the TEI in 2007 introduced
                    new elements for distinguishing real-world entities from their in-text
                    occurrences <ptr target="#wittern2009"/>. This change, along with the addition
                    of new attributes that could be used to link an entity to external authority
                    records (see <ref target="#example2">example 2 below</ref>), made it easier to
                    express relationships between entities in TEI and extract them as RDF
                    statements.</p>


                <dhq:example xml:id="example2">
                    <head>The attribute @sameAs encode an equivalence between the person <title
                            rend="quotes">Alexander the Great</title> in the TEI document and the
                        personal entity identified by the VIAF URI <ref
                            target="http://viaf.org/viaf/101353608"
                            >http://viaf.org/viaf/101353608</ref>.</head>
                    <eg lang="xml">
                        <![CDATA[
<person sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/101353608">Alexander the Great</person>

                    ]]>
                    </eg>
                </dhq:example>


                <p>Despite these meaningful developments, there are very few user-friendly tools for
                    working with TEI editions and LOD <ptr loc="121" target="#pierazzo2016"/>. The
                    fact that the TEI guidelines are not intended to be strictly followed
                    complicates matters: annotators can encode the same textual features in
                    different ways, depending on the project. Because no two texts or editions are
                    identical, this flexibility is required; however, the unavoidable drawback is a
                    certain loss of interoperability (see <ptr loc="2" target="#andrews2013"/>).
                    Enhancing TEI-encoded texts with linked open data represents a possible way of
                    overcoming this limitation.</p>
                <p>Being willing to introduce DHDK students to the extraction of linked open data
                    from TEI-encoded texts, we ran into a lack of user-friendly tools capable of
                    raising awareness about both the methodology and the technology that underpin
                    such operation. LIFT was created to fill this gap.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="relatedWork">
                <head>3. Related work</head>
                <p>As digital humanities practitioners know, XSLT (Extensible Stylesheet Language
                    Transformations) is a language for transforming XML documents into other XML
                    documents. Because the TEI is an XML vocabulary, digital textual scholars have
                    naturally adopted XSLT as their primary transformation language from TEI to
                    other formats including RDF/XML, which is one of the possible serializations of
                    LOD graphs. The TEI Consortium develops and maintains the <ref
                        target="https://tei-c.org/tools/stylesheets/">TEI Stylesheets</ref>, a
                    collection of ready-for-use XSL Transformations scripts that includes a
                    TEI-to-RDF transformation. Despite providing a relatively simple method of
                    extracting RDF statements from TEI documents, the Stylesheets have several
                    shortcomings, particularly when used as a teaching tool. The Stylesheets were
                    not, in fact, designed with a didactic aim in mind and do not offer TEI-to-RDF
                    transformation guidelines: users need to possess good XSLT skills to prepare the
                    TEI document, gain insight into the rationale of the transformation, and adapt
                    it to their specific needs. Also, RDF can be serialized in a variety of ways,
                    with Turtle being by far the most widely used due to its legibility. Since the
                    TEI-to-RDF Stylesheet was created, more powerful methods of linked data
                    production have been released. <ref target="https://rdflib.readthedocs.io"
                        >RDFLib</ref>, a Python package for working with RDF, is one of these. The
                    key difference between using XSLT and RDFLib to create RDF triples is that the
                    former requires developers to hardcode RDF triples into the transformation
                    stylesheet (i.e., the developer must choose ahead of time a specific
                    serialization and adhere to its syntax), resulting in a significant loss of
                    flexibility and an increase in human errors. RDFLib, on the other hand,
                    automatically serializes RDF triples, allowing you to add properties to an
                    entity at any point along the way without worrying about syntax and structure
                    (see <ref target="#example3">example 3</ref>, which shows a comparison between
                    XSLT and RDFLib as two different methods of generating RDF statements). Finally,
                    while the TEI-to-RDF Stylesheet reuse some concepts from the <ref
                        target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org/">CIDOC</ref> Conceptual Reference Model
                    (see <ptr target="#crofts2011"/>) and the <ref
                        target="http://purl.org/dc/terms/">Dublin Core</ref> (see <ptr
                        target="#weibel2000"/>), it does not make use of the expressive potential of
                    ontologies such as <ref target="http://iflastandards.info/ns/fr/frbr/frbroo/"
                        >FRBRoo</ref> (see <ptr target="#bekiari2015"/>) and <ref
                        target="http://purl.org/spar/pro/">PRO</ref> (see <ptr target="#peroni2012"
                    />), which have recently gained attention and application in both text and
                    cultural heritage representation (see <ptr target="#daquino2019"/>).</p>
                <p>Another tool we considered is <ref target="http://xtriples.spatialhumanities.de/"
                        >XTriples</ref>. XTriples is a webservice-based infrastructure for
                    extracting RDF statements from collections of XML documents <ptr
                        target="#gruntgens2016"/>. Unlike the Stylesheets, XTriples can produce
                    multiple serializations of the resulting RDF graph and comes with a
                    documentation. The transformation is customizable via an XPath-based
                    configuration file. LOD beginners, however, may find this operation difficult
                    and the tool not immediately usable or replicable.</p>
                <p>There are also tools, such as <ref target="https://recogito.pelagios.org/"
                        >Recogito</ref>, that enable the extraction of specific features from
                    TEI-encoded texts. Recogito, developed by the Pelagios Network, allows users to
                    add annotations to specific passages of text, which they can then download as
                    RDF statements (see <ptr target="#simon2017"/>). The transformation is not
                    configurable nor explained as this is not the focus of the tool.</p>


                <dhq:example xml:id="example3">
                    <head>XSLT versus RDFLib TEI-to-LOD transformation; the second method offers a
                        more flexible and less error-prone way of creating RDF statements.</head>
                    <eg lang="xml">
                        <![CDATA[
                    TEI to RDF/XML with XSLT                 
                    
<rdf:Description rdf:about="{$person_uri}">
    <rdf:type rdf:resource="http://schema.org/Person"/>
    <owl:sameAs rdf:resource="{$same_as_uri}"/>
    <rdfs:label>
        <xsl:attribute name="xml:lang">
        	<xsl:value-of select="{$label_lang}"/>
        </xsl:attribute>
        <xsl:value-of select="{$label}"/>
    </rdfs:label>
</rdf:Description>


                    TEI to RDF/XML with RDFLib

g.add((person_uri, RDF.type, schema.Person))
g.add((person_uri, OWL.sameAs, same_as_uri))
g.add((person_uri, RDFS.label, Literal(label, lang=label_lang)))
g.serialize(format="xml")

                    ]]>
                    </eg>
                </dhq:example>


            </div>
            <div xml:id="linkedDataFromTeiLift">
                <head>4. <title rend="italic">Linked data from TEI</title> (LIFT)<note> A Github
                        repository containing all of LIFT’s components can be found at <ref
                            target="https://github.com/fgiovannetti/lift"
                            >https://github.com/fgiovannetti/lift</ref>. The web application can be
                        found at <ref target="https://projects.dharc.unibo.it/lift/"
                            >https://projects.dharc.unibo.it/lift/</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <p>Based on the shortcomings discussed above, we decided to develop a TEI-to-LOD
                    transformation tool for our students that would simplify the transformation
                    process while also openly and transparently documenting the workflow, with the
                    goal of making such workflow modifiable and adaptable to new contexts. <title
                        rend="italic">Linked data from TEI</title> (LIFT) is a Python-based,
                    open-source application for creating graphs of RDF statements from TEI
                    documents. LIFT targets digital humanities students as well as textual scholars
                    experimenting for the first times with linked open data in digital scholarly
                    editing. The main component of LIFT is a collection of TEI-to-LOD transformation
                    scripts. The scripts, written in Python, take as input a TEI document and
                    generate an RDF graph. Each script addresses the transformation of specific TEI
                    entities including persons, personal relations, places, and events. A
                    transformation script for the TEI critical apparatus is also available (see <ref
                        target="#transformationScripts">Section 4.2</ref>). The application is
                    extensively documented in order to facilitate the reuse and adaptation of the
                    transformation workflow. The documentation walks users through the process of
                    preparing their TEI document for transformation, describes the expected RDF
                    graph, and provides step-by-step explanations of the transformation scripts in
                    the form of an interactive Jupyter notebook (see <ref target="#documentation"
                        >Section 4.3</ref>).</p>
                <p>Users can access LIFT through a browser or download the collection of scripts for
                    local use. A basic understanding of the TEI and RDF is recommended (the ideal
                    target audience are digital humanities students who are already familiar with
                    digital scholarly editions, the TEI, RDF and ontologies, and basic Python
                    programming).</p>
                <p>LIFT’s web interface has a straightforward design. When using a browser to access
                    LIFT, users are directed to the homepage, which contains instructions for
                    getting started with the transformation (see <ref target="#figure01">Figure
                        1</ref>): by clicking on the 'Quick start' tab, an upload bar for the input
                    TEI document becomes available (see <ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref>).
                    After uploading the TEI document into LIFT, users are directed to another page
                    where they can select a transformation option (see <ref target="#figure03"
                        >Figure 3</ref>). If the transformation is successful, multiple
                    serializations of the resulting RDF graph become available for download (see
                        <ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>).</p>
                <div xml:id="methodology">
                    <head>4.1 Methodology</head>
                    <p>The creation of linked open data from TEI documents is more than a technical
                        operation. While digital scholarly editions based solely on the TEI standard
                        are document-centric, LOD-based resources are data-centric: the
                        transformation of the information conveyed by the TEI markup into RDF
                        statements forming a graph necessitates careful methodological reflection as
                        the edition is disassembled to form a dataset of interconnected entities,
                        each represented by a URI or a literal.</p>
                    <p>In addition to reorganizing tree-structured information into a graph data
                        structure, the transition from TEI to linked data necessitates assigning a
                        formal semantics to the entities by reusing existing ontologies whenever
                        possible. As of today, there is no TEI-specific ontology, so all elements
                        and attributes must be mapped to classes and properties from arbitrary
                        ontologies (see <ptr target="#eide2014"/> and <ptr target="#ciotti2016"/>).
                        There are two major challenges to performing such mapping. First, the chosen
                        ontologies assign a formal semantics to the data, influencing how
                        information is accessed and reused in the future. Users should be aware of
                        the implications of using ready-to-use conversion tools like LIFT: the
                        information conveyed by the original encoding may change when moving from
                        one vocabulary, e.g. the TEI, to another, e.g. FRBRoo, CIDOC CRM, PROV-O,
                        etc. Second, a knowledge graph is composed of entities (i.e. concepts), and
                        links between entities (i.e. relationships between concepts). The
                        distinction between what will become a concept and what will become a
                        relationship is not inconsequential. In TEI, there are at least two ways to
                        represent a relationship. The first approach is to make use of an attribute.
                        The line <code>&lt;rdg wit=&quot;#A&quot;&gt;liber&lt;/rdg&gt;</code>, for
                        example, indicates that the reading 'liber' is witnessed by manuscript 'A',
                        where 'is witnessed by' is the relationship between the reading and the
                        manuscript. A second method is to nest elements within each another. The
                        encoding <code>&lt;app&gt;&lt;rdg
                            wit=&quot;#A&quot;&gt;liber&lt;/rdg&gt;&lt;rdg
                            wit=&quot;#B&quot;&gt;libellus&lt;/rdg&gt;&lt;/app&gt;</code>, for
                        example, indicates that 'libellus' is a variant of 'liber'. Although
                        interpreting the meaning of the relationships in the preceding examples is
                        simple and without ambiguity, this is not always the case.</p>
                    <p>When developing LIFT, we decided to set some predefined requirements for the
                        encoding of the input TEI document so to ensure a meaningful, error-free
                        restructuring and formalization of the information (see <ref
                            target="#transformationScripts">Section 4.2</ref>). The encoding
                        prerequisites can be adjusted locally by modifying the scripts. As of
                        semantics, we decided to reuse a set of ontologies that are widely adopted
                        in the fields of cultural heritage and text representation: the CIDOC
                        Conceptual Reference Model (CIDOC CRM) to represent people, places and
                        events; the <ref target="https://d-nb.info/standards/elementset/agrelon"
                            >Agent Relationship Ontology</ref> (AgRelOn) (see <ptr
                            target="#litz2012"/>) to describe personal relationships; the Functional
                        Requirements for Bibliographic Records object-oriented (FRBRoo) for texts;
                        the Dublin Core Metadata Terms (DCMI Metadata Terms) to describe
                        bibliographic resources; PROV-O to link the account of an event to its
                        source; the Publishing Roles Ontology (PRO), which enables the reification
                        of roles in such a way that each role is bounded to a specific context (e.g.
                        the role of 'bride' in the context of a particular ceremony); the <ref
                            target="http://www.essepuntato.it/2012/04/tvc/">Time-indexed Value in
                            Context</ref> (TVC) (see, again, <ptr target="#peroni2012"/>) to
                        represent time; the property owl:sameAs from the Web Ontology Language (OWL)
                        to interconnect the entities to semantically equivalent resources outside
                        the edition; the property rdfs:label and rdf:value from the Resource
                        Description Framework Schema (RDF Schema), which are used to include
                        human-readable labels and TEI snippets in the graph, respectively. Finally,
                        the <ref target="https://w3id.org/cao">Critical Apparatus Ontology</ref>
                        (CAO) is leveraged to represent critical apparatus entries (see <ptr
                            target="#giovannetti2021"/>). </p>
                    <p>A combination of multiple ontologies is required to express the various
                        concepts and relationships underpinning editions, as well as to demonstrate
                        to students how multiple ontologies can be used in the same knowledge
                        graph.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="transformationScripts">
                    <head>4.2 The transformation scripts</head>
                    <p>LIFT’s collection of transformation scripts include:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Persons only</item>
                        <item>Persons and events</item>
                        <item>Persons and relations</item>
                        <item>Places only</item>
                        <item>Persons, events, relations, and places</item>
                        <item>Critical apparatus</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>We decided to write multiple scripts because we wanted the transformation to
                        be modular and the resulting RDF graph’s complexity to be incremental.
                        Script 5 combines the previous four into a single transformation option. For
                        the scripts to work, the input TEI document must follow specific guidelines.
                        The TEI, as previously stated, allows for multiple ways to encode the same
                        textual features. For example, in order to markup a personal name, one can
                        use the tag <code>&lt;persName&gt;</code> , the tag
                            <code>&lt;name&gt;</code> , or even the tag <code>&lt;rs&gt;</code> (see
                            <ref
                            target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ND.html"
                            >https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ND.html</ref>)
                        This is an important feature in terms of flexibility, but it makes creating
                        a universal TEI-to-RDF transformation script difficult. As a result, LIFT’s
                        documentation includes a set of encoding guidelines intended to ensure a
                        smooth TEI-to-LOD transformation (<ref target="#example4">example 4
                            below</ref> juxtaposes the input TEI encoding and the resulting RDF
                        statements). In particular, the input TEI document must conform to the
                        following indications:<note> Further requirements apply when transforming a
                            critical apparatus (see, again, <ptr target="#giovannetti2021"/>).
                        </note> 1. Any TEI element being transformed must be assigned a unique
                        identifier within an @xml:id attribute; 2. The TEI document must contain a
                        TEI header, even if minimal; the <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> element must be
                        used to describe people in the TEI header, and the
                            <code>&lt;persName&gt;</code> element must be used to markup in-text
                        occurrences of such people; 3. In a similar way, the
                            <code>&lt;place&gt;</code> element must be used to describe places in
                        the TEI header, and the <code>&lt;placeName&gt;</code> element must be used
                        to markup in-text occurrences of such places; 4. People and places described
                        in the TEI header should be assigned a <code>@sameAs</code> attribute
                        containing links to external authority records (e.g. VIAF); 5. Any
                        relationship between people should be described in the TEI header within
                            <code>&lt;listRelation&gt;</code> ; 6. Similarly, events should be
                        described using the <code>&lt;event&gt;</code> element within
                            <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> or <code>&lt;place&gt;</code>. An example
                        input file is also provided when accessing LIFT from the browser. If
                        modifying the TEI encoding to meet the requirements of LIFT is not possible,
                        the documentation in general, and the interactive Jupyter notebook in
                        particular, will help users gain the understanding needed to adapt the
                        transformation to a different input.</p>


                    <dhq:example xml:id="example4">
                        <head>The input TEI encoding and the corresponding RDF output.</head>
                        <eg lang="xml">
                            <![CDATA[
             Input (TEI)
             
             
<person xml:id="socr" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/88039167">
   <persName xml:lang="en">Socrates</persName>
</person>
[...]
<p xml:id="para01">An example of paragraph mentioning <persName ref="#socr">Socrates</persName>.</p>

Output (RDF)
@prefix crm:<http://www.cidoc-crm.org/cidoc-crm/> .
@prefix dcterms: <http://purl.org/dc/terms/> .
@prefix frbroo: <http://iflastandards.info/ns/fr/frbr/frbroo/> .
@prefix owl: <http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#> .
@prefix rdf: <http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#> .
@prefix rdfs: <http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#> .

<https://example.org/person/socr> a crm:E21_Person ;
   rdfs:label "Socrates"@en ;
   dcterms:isReferencedBy <https://example.org/text/para01> ;
   owl:sameAs <http://viaf.org/viaf/88039167> .

<https://example.org/text/para01> a frbroo:F23_Expression_Fragment ;
   frbroo:R15i_is_fragment_of <https://example.org/example_v1> ;
   rdf:value """An example of paragraph mentioning Socrates."""^^rdf:Literal .

                    ]]>
                        </eg>
                    </dhq:example>


                    <p>LIFT, as stated earlier in the introduction, uses Python as its
                        transformation language. Python, which is increasingly being taught in
                        digital humanities courses around the world, offers more efficient and
                        error-free ways of working with RDF and linked open data than XSLT (see <ref
                            target="#relatedWork">Section 3 above</ref>).</p>
                    <p>RDFLib is a Python library that specializes in RDF triple creation and
                        management (see the documentation at <ref
                            target="https://rdflib.readthedocs.io"
                            >https://rdflib.readthedocs.io</ref>). Using RDFLib to create RDF
                        triples is very simple, and the amount of human effort required is minimal.
                        URIs can be saved as variables, and RDF statements can be written on
                        separate lines. RDFLib then generates a single graph with no repetitions.
                        Multiple serializations are possible, including XML, Turtle, N-Triples, and
                        JSON-LD.</p>
                    <p>LIFT uses another Python library, lxml, in conjunction with RDFLib to parse
                        TEI documents (see the documentation at <ref target="https://lxml.de"
                            >https://lxml.de</ref>). When using XSLT to process XML files, one must
                        be familiar with the structure of the document to be processed. However,
                        using lxml and Python, it is possible to work with less well-known
                        inputs.</p>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="#example4">example 4 above</ref> shows a portion of a TEI
                        document and the corresponding RDF graph in LIFT. <ref target="#example5"
                            >example 5 below</ref> provides some components of the transformation
                        script used for generating such output. LIFT searches the TEI document for
                        all occurrences of <code>&lt;person&gt;</code>. The value of the
                            <code>@xml:id</code> attribute associated with the person is then
                        obtained and used to generate the URI representing that person. LIFT looks
                        also for any in-text reference to the person. To do so, it searches the TEI
                        document for all occurrences of <code>&lt;persName&gt;</code> featuring a
                        @ref attribute linking to the person. Each person is assigned to the CIDOC
                        CRM class E21 Person. If a <code>@sameAs</code> attribute is provided in the
                        TEI document for the <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> element, LIFT leverages its
                        value or values to create interconnections to external authority records
                        (using the OWL property owl:sameAs). All data used for building the RDF
                        graph are extracted from the TEI document. The content of the
                            <code>&lt;persName&gt;</code> element provided within
                            <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> is used to generate a human-readable label
                        for the entity. The language is specified by the <code>@xml:lang</code>
                        attribute. As the reader can see from this example, LIFT uses a predefined
                        set of ontologies to describe the text (see <ref target="#methodology"
                            >Section 4.1</ref>). In order to modify this behaviour, users must
                        modify the scripts. To facilitate this effort, as already anticipated, LIFT
                        provides a Jupyter notebook that guides users through the scripts
                        step-by-step and interactively (see <ref target="#documentation">Section
                            4.3</ref> ).</p>

                    <dhq:example xml:id="example5">
                        <head>An excerpt of one of LIFT’s transformation script creating RDF triples
                            about persons.</head>
                        <eg lang="python">
                            <![CDATA[
for person in root.findall('.//tei:person', tei):
    person_id = person.get('{http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace}id')
    person_uri = URIRef(base_uri + '/person/' + person_id)
    person_ref = '#' + person_id
    g.add( (person_uri, RDF.type, crm.E21_Person))
    
    same_as = person.get('sameAs').split()
    if same_as is not None:
        same_as = same_as.split()
        i = 0
        while i < len(same_as):
            same_as_uri = URIRef(same_as[i])
            g.add( (person_uri, OWL.sameAs, same_as_uri))
            i += 1
 
    persname = person.find('./tei:persName', tei)
    if persname is not None:
        label = persname.text
        label_lang = persname.get('{http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace}lang')
        if label_lang is not None:
            g.add( (person_uri, RDFS.label, Literal(label, lang=label_lang)))
        else:
            g.add( (person_uri, RDFS.label, Literal(label)))

                    ]]>
                        </eg>
                    </dhq:example>




                </div>
                <div xml:id="documentation">
                    <head>4.3 The documentation</head>
                    <p>In developing LIFT as a tool for supporting the adoption of linked open data
                        in digital scholarly editing, we followed the principle that no tool should
                        be used as a black box. Students/users of LIFT must be provided with the
                        knowledge required to understand the methodology and the technology
                        informing the conversion. LIFT is accompanied by an extensive documentation
                        available at <ref target="http://linked-data-from-tei.rtfd.io/"
                            >http://linked-data-from-tei.rtfd.io/</ref> presenting the full
                        Python-based workflow for TEI-to-LOD transformation. LIFT’s documentation is
                        divided into four main sections:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <title rend="italic">Prepare your TEI document</title>, which
                                explains the encoding requirements for the input TEI document;</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <title rend="italic">The RDF graph</title>, illustrating the
                                structure and semantics of the generated knowledge graph by
                                comparing the TEI input with the corresponding RDF output (this
                                section also discusses why and how users might choose different
                                ontologies for their projects or modify the scripts to work with
                                different input data);</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <title rend="italic">How the scripts work</title>, where users can
                                access an interactive Jupyter notebook containing LIFT’s scripts
                                with instructions and line-by-line explanations that are meant to
                                help users develop the skills required to write their own
                                transformation scripts;<note> An online, read-only version of the
                                    notebook is available at <ref
                                        target="https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/fgiovannetti/lift/blob/master/jupyter_nb/TEItoRDF.ipynb"
                                        >https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/fgiovannetti/lift/blob/master/jupyter_nb/TEItoRDF.ipynb</ref>
                                    .</note>
                            </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <title rend="italic">Further readings and resources</title>, which
                                lists relevant publications and provides examples of TEI digital
                                scholarly editions which have been enriched by means of linked open
                                data.</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>In addition to the documentation, each semantic statement of the resulting
                        RDF graph is accompanied by the original TEI construct that generated it
                        facilitating the comparison between the TEI input and the RDF output: this
                        provides users with indirect support as they can view the input TEI encoding
                        and the output RDF graph side by side and go back to adjust the input TEI
                        document to resolve any transformation issues that may arise (see <ref
                            target="#example4">example 4 above</ref>).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="LiftInTheClassroom">
                <head>5. LIFT in the classroom</head>
                <p>Digital humanities, as a discipline, lie at the crossroads of theory and
                    practice. The learning-by-example paradigm, which entails presenting existing
                    models that can be adapted to address new problems, is particularly effective in
                    similar interdisciplinary contexts (see <ptr target="#tomasi2020"/>). LIFT was
                    created in response to a perceived lack of teaching tools for TEI to LOD
                    transformation based on such paradigm.</p>
                <p>LIFT will be used in a text representation laboratory activity for the University
                    of Bologna’s Master Degree in Digital Humanities and Digital Knowledge. As
                    anticipated at the beginning of this paper, the activity aims to combine the
                    knowledge and skills acquired by the students from various modules and,
                    particularly, text encoding with the TEI, ontology development, Python
                    programming, and linked open data for cultural heritage. The plan for the
                    activity involves gathering the students in 3-member groups. Each group will
                    choose an existing digital scholarly edition and work on the underlying TEI
                    document to ensure that the encoding requirements of LIFT are met.<note> Patrick
                        Sahle’s and Greta Franzini’s catalogues of digital scholarly editions (<ref
                            target="https://v3.digitale-edition.de/"
                            >https://v3.digitale-edition.de/</ref> ; <ref
                            target="https://dig-ed-cat.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/"
                            >https://dig-ed-cat.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/</ref>) will be provided as a
                        starting point, along with RIDE (<ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/"
                            >https://ride.i-d-e.de/</ref>).</note> The groups will then use LIFT,
                    either via browser or locally, to produce an RDF graph. Finally, each group will
                    present their findings to the class, highlighting challenges and solutions in
                    transforming each type of entity. Following activities will shift the emphasis
                    away from the input TEI document as students will focus on modifying the
                    transformation scripts to adapt them to the existing digital scholarly editions
                    rather than the other way around. By experimenting with the shift from
                    tree-structured to graph-structured data, and from the TEI vocabulary to RDF
                    using multiple ontologies, students will gain a better understanding of the
                    implications of annotating a text in one way versus another within the context
                    of a real-world task that requires them to combine different skills and
                    competencies that are typically taught separately. Furthermore, because the
                    activity is structured as group work on a specific problem to be solved,
                    students will be able to strengthen their ability to collaborate as a team,
                    which is one of the pillars of digital humanities scholarship and, by extension,
                    should be one of digital humanities pedagogy (see <ptr target="#licastro2020"
                    />).</p>
                <p>The laboratory activity will also allow us to evaluate the clarity and
                    effectiveness of LIFT as a teaching tool both directly through an
                    end-of-activity questionnaire and indirectly through the students’
                    presentations.</p>

            </div>
            <div xml:id="conclusionAndNextSteps">
                <head>6. Conclusion and next steps</head>
                <p>This paper introduced LIFT, an open-source tool written as a set of Python
                    scripts for generating linked data from TEI-encoded texts. The use of linked
                    open data for text representation facilitates interoperability with other
                    cultural resources on the web and opens up editions to new areas of cultural
                    heritage research. LIFT’s goal is to walk users through the transformation
                    process from TEI to linked data step by step, as well as to promote a better
                    understanding of the theoretical and methodological aspects that underpin the
                    transformation.</p>
                <p>Some of the key characteristics of the evolving web of data include open-source
                    tools, well-documented applications, and shared ontologies. User-friendly
                    resources that reduce the complexity of transforming digital scholarly editions
                    from a document-centric to a data-centric model are also critical in the
                    development and expansion of a linked open data cloud of cultural heritage. We
                    envisage LIFT both as a teaching tool and a ready-for-use resource for
                    TEI-to-LOD transformation, hoping it will serve as an example of a digital
                    humanities teaching tool that raises awareness about the methodological and
                    theoretical implications of the structural and semantic shift that occurs when
                    transitioning from a TEI-based text representation to LOD.</p>
                <p>With LIFT, we also aim to encourage further research into the development of
                    open-source, user-friendly tools aiding the mutual integration of digital
                    scholarly editions and the cultural heritage linked open data cloud. Such tools
                    have the potential to make digital humanities, and especially knowledge
                    representation, a more inclusive field of study and research. In order to test
                    this idea, we will use LIFT in the context of the University of Bologna’s Master
                    Degree in Digital Humanities and Digital Knowledge, as a teaching tool for
                    students encountering linked open data for the first time as a method of
                    publishing digital scholarly editions on the web in a data integration
                    perspective. We expect that LIFT will help students understand the process not
                    only practically but also, and primarily, in terms of methodology and
                    theory.</p>
                <p>LIFT is under active development. Features that will be provided in the near
                    future include a transformation script for bibliographic references encoded
                    using specialized elements from the <ref
                        target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#COBI"
                        >TEI</ref> model.bibLike class. Furthermore, the documentation will be
                    expanded with new sections on ontologies for text representation as well as
                    useful resources, particularly examples of digital scholarly editions enhanced
                    through the use of linked open data.</p>
            </div>
            <figure>
                <head>Homepage</head>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure01(1).png" style="height: 500px;"/>
                <figDesc>A screenshot of the homepage</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <head>Quick start</head>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure02(1).png" style="height: 500px;"/>
                <figDesc>A screenshot of the Quick start page</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <head>Choosing a transformation</head>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure03(1).png" style="height: 500px;"/>
                <figDesc>A screenshot of the page example the transformation options</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <head>Downloading the resulting knowledge graph according to different
                    serializations</head>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure04(1).png" style="height: 500px;"/>
                <figDesc>A screenshot of the download button producing different serializations of
                    the knowledge graph</figDesc>
            </figure>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="andrews2013" label="Andrews 2013">Andrews, Tara L. 2013. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Third Way: Philology and Critical Edition in the Digital
                        Age</title>. Application/pdf. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.7892/BORIS.43071"
                        >https://doi.org/10.7892/BORIS.43071</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bekiari2015" label="Bekiari et al. 2015">Bekiari, Chryssoula, Martin
                    Doerr, Patrick Le Boeuf, and Pat Riva. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Definition of
                        FRBRoo: A Conceptual Model for Bibliographic Information in Object-Oriented
                        Formalism</title>. 2.4. IFLA.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ciotti2016" label="Ciotti and Tomasi 2016">Ciotti, Fabio, and
                    Francesca Tomasi. 2016. <title rend="quotes">Formal Ontologies, Linked Data, and
                        TEI Semantics</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding
                        Initiative</title>, no. Issue 9 (September). <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.4000/jtei.1480"
                        >https://doi.org/10.4000/jtei.1480</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ciula2008" label="Ciula et al. 2008">Ciula, A., P. Spence, and J. M.
                    Vieira. 2008. <title rend="quotes">Expressing Complex Associations in Medieval
                        Historical Documents: The Henry III Fine Rolls Project</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 23 (3): 311–25. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqn018"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqn018</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="crofts2011" label="Crofts et al. 2011">Crofts, Nick, Martin Doerr,
                    Tony Gill, Stephen Stead, and Matthew Stiff, eds. 2011. <title rend="quotes"
                        >CIDOC CRM: CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model</title>, November. <ref
                        target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org/cidoc-crm/"
                        >http://www.cidoc-crm.org/cidoc-crm/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="daquino2019" label="Daquino et al. 2019">Daquino, Marilena, Francesca
                    Giovannetti, and Francesca Tomasi. 2019. <title rend="quotes">Linked Data per le
                        edizioni scientifiche digitali. Il workflow di pubblicazione dell edizione
                        semantica del quaderno di appunti di Paolo Bufalini</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Umanistica Digitale</title>, December, No 7 (2019). <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.6092/ISSN.2532-8816/9091"
                        >https://doi.org/10.6092/ISSN.2532-8816/9091</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="daquino2014" label="Daquino et al. 2014">Daquino, Marilena, Silvio
                    Peroni, Francesca Tomasi, and Fabio Vitali. 2014. <title rend="quotes">Political
                        Roles Ontology (PRoles): Enhancing Archival Authority Records through
                        Semantic Web Technologies</title>. <title rend="italic">Procedia Computer
                        Science</title> 38: 60–67. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.procs.2014.10.012"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1016/j.procs.2014.10.012</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="derose1990" label="DeRose et al. 1990">DeRose, Steven J., David G.
                    Durand, Elli Mylonas, and Allen H. Renear. 1990. <title rend="quotes">What Is
                        Text, Really?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Computing in Higher Education</title> 1 (2):
                    3–26. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02941632"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02941632</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eide2014" label="Eide 2014">Eide, Øyvind. 2014. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Ontologies, Data Modeling, and TEI</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of
                        the Text Encoding Initiative</title>, no. Issue 8 (December). <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.4000/jtei.1191"
                        >https://doi.org/10.4000/jtei.1191</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="giovannetti2021" label="Giovannetti 2021">Giovannetti, Francesca.
                    2021. <title rend="quotes">The Critical Apparatus Ontology (CAO): Modelling the
                        TEI Critical Apparatus as a Knowledge Grap</title>. In <title rend="italic"
                        >Graph Data-Models and Semantic Web Technologies in Scholarly Digital
                        Editing</title>, edited by Elena Spadini, Francesca Tomasi, and Georg
                    Vogeler, 125–39. Schriften Des Instituts Für Dokumentologie Und Editorik, Band
                    15. Norderstedt: BoD – Books on Demand.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gruntgens2016" label="Gruntgens and Torsten 2016">Gruntgens, Max, and
                    Torsten Schrade. 2016. <title rend="quotes">Data Repositories in the Humanities
                        and the Semantic Web: Modelling, Linking, Visualising</title>, 12.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jordanous2012" label="Jordanous et al. 2012">Jordanous, Anna, K. Faith
                    Lawrence, Mark Hedges, and Charlotte Tupman. 2012. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Exploring Manuscripts: Sharing Ancient Wisdoms across the Semantic
                        Web</title>. In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2nd International
                        Conference on Web Intelligence, Mining and Semantics - WIMS </title>12, 1.
                    Craiova, Romania: ACM Press. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1145/2254129.2254184"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1145/2254129.2254184</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="licastro2020" label="Licastro et al. 2020">Licastro, Amanda, Katina
                    Rogers, and Danica Savonick, eds. 2020. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Collaboration</title>. In <title rend="italic">Digital Pedagogy in the
                        Humanities: Concepts, Models, and Experiments</title>. Modern Language
                    Association. <ref
                        target="https://digitalpedagogy.hcommons.org/keyword/Collaboration"
                        >https://digitalpedagogy.hcommons.org/keyword/Collaboration</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="litz2012" label="Litz et al. 2012">Litz, Berenike, Aenne Löhden, Jan
                    Hannemann, and Lars Svensson. 2012. <title rend="quotes">AgRelOn – An Agent
                        Relationship Ontology</title>. In <title rend="italic">Metadata and
                        Semantics Research</title>, edited by Juan Manuel Dodero, Manuel
                    Palomo-Duarte, and Pythagoras Karampiperis, 343:202–13. Communications in
                    Computer and Information Science. Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer Berlin
                    Heidelberg. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-35233-1_21"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-35233-1_21</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mla2016" label="MLA 2016">MLA Commettee on Scholarly. n.d. <title
                        rend="quotes">MLA Statement on the Scholarly Edition in the Digital
                        Age</title>. Modern Language Association. Accessed 29 September 2019. <ref
                        target="https://www.mla.org/Resources/Research/Surveys-Reports-and-Other-Documents/Publishing-and-Scholarship/Reports-from-the-MLA-Committee-on-Scholarly-Editions/MLA-Statement-on-the-Scholarly-Edition-in-the-Digital-Age"
                        >https://www.mla.org/Resources/Research/Surveys-Reports-and-Other-Documents/Publishing-and-Scholarship/Reports-from-the-MLA-Committee-on-Scholarly-Editions/MLA-Statement-on-the-Scholarly-Edition-in-the-Digital-Age</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="peroni2012" label="Peroni et al. 2012">Peroni, Silvio, David Shotton,
                    and Fabio Vitali. 2012. <title rend="quotes">Scholarly Publishing and Linked
                        Data: Describing Roles, Statuses, Temporal and Contextual Extents</title>.
                    In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 8th International Conference on
                        Semantic Systems - I-SEMANTICS </title>12, 9. Graz, Austria: ACM Press. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1145/2362499.2362502"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1145/2362499.2362502</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pierazzo2016" label="Pierazzo 2016">Pierazzo, Elena. 2016. <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Scholarly Editing</title>. 0 ed. Routledge. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.4324/9781315577227"
                        >https://doi.org/10.4324/9781315577227</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="price2008" label="Price 2008">Price, Kenneth M. 2008. <title
                        rend="quotes">Electronic Scholarly Editions</title>. In <title rend="italic"
                        >A Companion to Digital Literary Studies</title>, edited by Susan Schreibman
                    and Ray Siemens.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="renear1993" label="Renear 1993">Renear, Allen H., Elli Mylonas, and
                    David G. Durand. 1993. <title rend="quotes">Refining Our Notion of What Text
                        Really Is: The Problem of Overlapping Hierarchies</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Computer Science</title>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sahle2014" label="Sahle 2014">Sahle, Patrick. 2014. <title
                        rend="quotes">Criteria for Reviewing Scholarly Digital Editions</title>.
                    2014. <ref
                        target="https://www.i-d-e.de/publikationen/weitereschriften/criteria-version-1-1/"
                        >https://www.i-d-e.de/publikationen/weitereschriften/criteria-version-1-1/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sahle2016" label="Sahle 2016"> Sahle, Patrick. 2016. <title
                        rend="quotes">2. What Is a Scholarly Digital Edition?</title> In <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories and Practices</title>,
                    edited by Matthew James Driscoll and Elena Pierazzo, 19–40. Open Book
                    Publishers. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0095.02"
                        >https://doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0095.02</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="simon2017" label="Simon et al. 2017">Simon, Rainer, Elton Barker, Leif
                    Isaksen, and Pau De Soto CaÑamares. 2017. <title rend="quotes">Linked Data
                        Annotation Without the Pointy Brackets: Introducing Recogito 2</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Journal of Map &amp; Geography Libraries</title> 13
                    (1): 111–32. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/15420353.2017.1307303"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1080/15420353.2017.1307303</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="spadini2021" label="Spadini et al. 2021">Spadini, Elena, Francesca
                    Tomasi, and Georg Vogeler, eds. 2021. <title rend="italic">Graph Data-Models and
                        Semantic Web Technologies in Scholarly Digital Editing</title>. Schriften
                    Des Instituts Für Dokumentologie Und Editorik, Band 15. Norderstedt: BoD – Books
                    on Demand.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="teiconsortium2019" label="TEI Consortium 2019">TEI Consortium. 2019.
                        <title rend="quotes">P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                        Interchange</title>. 3.6.0. TEI Consortium. <ref
                        target="https://tei-c.org/guidelines/"
                    >https://tei-c.org/guidelines/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="teiontologies" label="TEI 2019"><title rend="quotes">TEI: Ontologies
                        SIG</title>. 2019. Text Encoding Initiative. 2019. <ref
                        target="https://tei-c.org/activities/sig/ontologies"
                        >https://tei-c.org/activities/sig/ontologies</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tomasi2012" label="Tomasi 2012">Tomasi, Francesca. 2012. <title
                        rend="quotes">Ledizione Digitale e La Rappresentazione Della Conoscenza. Un
                        Esempio: Vespasiano Da Bisticci e Le Sue Lettere</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Ecdotica</title> 9 (1): 264–86.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tomasi2020" label="Tomasi 2020"> Tomasi, Francesca. 2020. <title
                        rend="quotes">Digital Humanities e Organizzazione Della Conoscenza: Una
                        Pratica Di Insegnamento Nel LODLAM</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Aibstudi</title> 60 (2): 1–15. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.2426/aibstudi-12068"
                        >https://doi.org/10.2426/aibstudi-12068</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weibel2000" label="Weibel and Traugott 2000">Weibel, Stuart L., and
                    Traugott Koch. 2000. <title rend="quotes">The Dublin Core Metadata Initiative:
                        Mission, Current Activities, and Future Directions</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine</title> 6 (12). <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1045/december2000-weibel"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1045/december2000-weibel</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wittern2009" label="Wittern et al. 2009">Wittern, C., A. Ciula, and C.
                    Tuohy. 2009. <title rend="quotes">The Making of TEI P5</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 24 (3): 281–96. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqp017"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqp017</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
