<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Linked data from TEI (LIFT): A Teaching Tool for
                    TEI to Linked Data Transformation</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Francesca
                        <dhq:family>Giovannetti</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6007-9118</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Bologna</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>francesc.giovannett6@unibo.it</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Francesca <dhq:family>Tomasi</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6631-8607</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Bologna</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>francesca.tomasi@unibo.it</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">
                    <!-- including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110 -->000605 </idno>
                <idno type="volume">
                    <!-- volume number, with leading zeroes: e.g. 006 -->
                </idno>
                <idno type="issue">
                    <!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 -->
                </idno>
                <date/>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Produced by pandoc.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>digital scholarly editions</item>
                        <item>linked open data</item>
                        <item>TEI</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="original" xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>The purpose of this paper is to introduce <title rend="italic">Linked data from
                        TEI</title> (LIFT), an open source tool written as a set of Python scripts
                    for generating linked data from TEI-encoded texts. LIFT’s goal is to walk users
                    through the transformation process from TEI to linked data step by step, as well
                    as to promote a better understanding of the theoretical and methodological
                    aspects that underpin the transformation. LIFT was created in the context of the
                    University of Bologna’s Master Degree in Digital Humanities and Digital
                    Knowledge as a teaching tool for students encountering linked open data for the
                    first time as a method of organizing and publishing cultural knowledge and,
                    specifically, digital scholarly editions on the web in a perspective of data
                    integration.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>Linked data from TEI (LIFT) is an open source tool for generating linked data
                    from TEI-encoded texts.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction <note>
                        This paper is the result of a collaborative work. In particular,
                            Francesca Tomasi is responsible for sections 1, 5 and 6, while Francesca
                            Giovannetti is responsible for sections 2, 3 and 4.</note>
                </head>
                <p>Many and diverse scientific communities, including digital textual scholars, have
                    shown increasing interest in semantic web technologies and linked open data
                    (LOD) as a means of knowledge representation since the early 2000s, when Tim
                    Berners-Lee coined the concept of a web of interconnected data rather than
                    simply documents (see <ptr target="#spadini2021"/> ). Nonetheless, there is a
                    lack of user-friendly tools for working with digital scholarly editions and
                    LOD.</p>
                <p>
                    <title rend="italic">Linked data from TEI</title>(LIFT) is a Digital Humanities tool
                    for generating linked open data (LOD) from TEI-encoded texts. LIFT, which is
                    accessible at <ref target="https://projects.dharc.unibo.it/lift"
                        >https://projects.dharc.unibo.it/lift</ref> , provides a set of TEI-to-LOD
                    transformation scripts written in Python. The scripts, addressing the
                    transformation of different types of entities to LOD, are thoroughly documented
                    to facilitate their understanding and reuse. The purpose of this paper is to
                    introduce LIFT as a teaching tool for supporting the adoption of linked open
                    data in digital scholarly editing. Our plan is to use LIFT as part of a
                    laboratory activity for the University of Bologna’s Master Degree in Digital
                    Humanities and Digital Knowledge, which will combine the knowledge and skills
                    acquired by the students from different modules: text encoding with the TEI,
                    ontology development, Python programming, and linked open data for cultural
                    heritage. <note>
                         The modules are Digital Text in the Humanities: Theories, Methodologies
                            and Applications; Knowledge representation and extraction; Computational
                            thinking and programming, and Knowledge organization and cultural
                            heritage (see the full descriptions at <ref
                                target="https://corsi.unibo.it/2cycle/DigitalHumanitiesKnowledge"
                                >https://corsi.unibo.it/2cycle/DigitalHumanitiesKnowledge</ref>
                            ).
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>This paper first provides a brief background on linked open data and their use in
                    digital text representation (see <ref target="#2_background">Section 2</ref> ).
                    It then goes on to consider related work in the field of TEI to LOD
                    transformation (see <ref target="#3_related-work">Section 3</ref> ) as well as
                    to introduce LIFT from both a technical and methodological perspective (see <ref
                        target="#4_linked-data-from-tei-lift">Section 4</ref> ). Finally, it
                    discusses the potential application of LIFT in digital humanities learning
                    contexts (see <ref target="#5_lift-in-the-classroom">Section 5</ref> and <ref
                        target="#6_conclusion-and-next-steps">Section 6</ref> ).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="level1" xml:id="2_background">
                <head>Background</head>
                <p>The concept of linked open data refers to a method of publishing structured data
                    – as well as organizing knowledge – on the web in such a way that they can be
                    semantically interlinked to form open clouds of integrated information. As is
                    already well known, LOD are based on the Resource Description Framework (RDF), a
                    graph data model used for making statements about resources. Each RDF statement
                    contains a subject, a predicate, and an object, represented by unique URIs. The
                    subject is the resource being described, the object is either a characteristic
                    of the subject (such as its type) or a resource related to the subject, and the
                    predicate expresses the relationship between the subject and the object (see
                        <ref target="#listing1">Listing 1 below</ref> ). The meaning of RDF data is
                    defined by machine-readable ontologies, formal descriptions of specific concepts
                    within a domain and the relationships holding between them.</p>
                <eg xml:id="listing1">&lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Alexander_the_Great&gt; #
                    Alexander the Great &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/parent&gt; # has parent
                    &lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Philip_II_of_Macedon&gt; # Philip II of Macedon </eg>
                <dhq:caption>
                    <head>Listing 1</head>
                    <p>An RDF representation of the statement ‘Alexander the Great has parent Philip
                        II of Macedon’ (extracted from DBpedia).</p>
                </dhq:caption>
                <p>RDF statements can be used to represent information in digital scholarly editions
                    as linked open data. <note>
                       For a definition of digital scholarly edition, see <ptr
                                target="#shale2016"/> .
                    </note>To cite just a few examples, the <ref
                        target="https://finerollshenry3.org.uk/">Henry III Fine Rolls edition</ref>
                    experiments with linked data to express complex relationships between people in
                    historical documents (see <ptr target="#ciula2008"/> . The <ref
                        target="https://ancientwisdoms.ac.uk/">Sharing Ancient Wisdoms project</ref>
                    , on the other hand, uses linked data to reconstruct text interaction (see <ptr
                        target="#jordanous2012"/> ), while the <ref
                        target="https://projects.dharc.unibo.it/bufalini-notebook">Paolo Bufalini’s
                        Notebook edition</ref> uses linked data to represent the interconnections
                    between the various types of fragments – quotations, translations, and
                    annotations – that make up the text (see <ptr target="#daquino2019"/> ). Similar
                    information extracted from texts, in addition to administrative, structural, and
                    descriptive metadata, can make a significant contribution to the development of
                    a cultural heritage linked open data cloud: texts do indeed occupy a prominent
                    space in cultural heritage representation. However, in order to reuse and
                    integrate texts into LOD systems, information must first be expressed in RDF
                    according to widely used ontologies in the digital humanities and cultural
                    heritage domains.</p>
                <p>The Text Encoding Initiative (TEI), an XML vocabulary for encoding texts in the
                    humanities, is the de facto standard for digital scholarly editing. <note>
                        On the role of the TEI standard in digital scholarly editing, see <ptr
                                target="#mla2016"/> , <ptr target="#price2008"/> , and <ptr
                                target="#sahle2014"/> .
                    </note>The standard defines terms for representing a wide range of textual
                    entities, including personal names, place names, dates, concepts, and events.
                    Unlike RDF, the TEI has traditionally taken a document-centric approach to
                    representing such entities, with texts processed as ordered hierarchies of
                    content objects nesting neatly one inside the other (see <ptr
                        target="#derose1990"/> and <ptr target="#renear1993"/> ). However,
                    transitioning from a document-centric paradigm to a data-centric paradigm, such
                    as LOD, is not an easy task: converting TEI editions into graphs of RDF
                    statements necessitates a conceptual shift in which texts are no longer viewed
                    as documents but as collections of interconnected entities (see <ptr
                        target="#tomasi2012"/> ).</p>
                <p>The movement beyond TEI towards linked open data began in 2004, when a TEI
                    Special Interest Group on Ontologies was formed with the goal of investigating
                    the feasibility of encoding information about persons, dates, events, places and
                    objects outside the text, in parallel with the steps taken by the Museum
                    community, which was working on the development of CIDOC CRM, an ontological
                    vocabulary for the description of museum collections (see <ptr
                        target="#tei_ontologies_sig2019"/> ). The new P5 release of the TEI in 2007
                    introduced new elements for distinguishing real-world entities from their
                    in-text occurrences ( <ptr target="#wittern2009"/> ). This change, along with
                    the addition of new attributes that could be used to link an entity to external
                    authority records (see <ref target="#listing2">Listing 2 below</ref> ), made it
                    easier to express relationships between entities in TEI and extract them as RDF
                    statements.</p>
                <eg xml:id="listing2">&lt;person
                    sameAs=&quot;http://viaf.org/viaf/101353608&quot;&gt;Alexander the
                    Great&lt;/person&gt; </eg>
                <dhq:caption>
                    <head>Listing 2</head>
                    <p>The attribute @sameAs encode an equivalence between the person ‘Alexander the
                        Great’ in the TEI document and the personal entity identified by the VIAF
                        URI <ref target="http://viaf.org/viaf/101353608"
                            >http://viaf.org/viaf/101353608</ref> .</p>
                </dhq:caption>
                <p>Despite these meaningful developments, there are very few user-friendly tools for
                    working with TEI editions and LOD ( <ptr loc="121" target="#pierazzo2016"/> ).
                    The fact that the TEI guidelines are not intended to be strictly followed
                    complicates matters: annotators can encode the same textual features in
                    different ways, depending on the project. Because no two texts or editions are
                    identical, this flexibility is required; however, the unavoidable drawback is a
                    certain loss of interoperability (see <ptr loc="2" target="#andrews2013"/> ).
                    Enhancing TEI-encoded texts with linked open data represents a possible way of
                    overcoming this limitation.</p>
                <p>Being willing to introduce DHDK students to the extraction of linked open data
                    from TEI-encoded texts, we ran into a lack of user-friendly tools capable of
                    raising awareness about both the methodology and the technology that underpin
                    such operation. LIFT was created to fill this gap.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="level1" xml:id="3_related-work">
                <head>Related work</head>
                <p>As digital humanities practitioners know, XSLT (Extensible Stylesheet Language
                    Transformations) is a language for transforming XML documents into other XML
                    documents. Because the TEI is an XML vocabulary, digital textual scholars have
                    naturally adopted XSLT as their primary transformation language from TEI to
                    other formats including RDF/XML, which is one of the possible serializations of
                    LOD graphs. The TEI Consortium develops and maintains the <ref target="https://tei-c.org/tools/stylesheets/">TEI Stylesheets</ref>, a
                    collection of ready-for-use XSL Transformations scripts that includes a
                    TEI-to-RDF transformation. 
                </p>
                <p>Despite providing a relatively simple method of extracting RDF statements from
                    TEI documents, the Stylesheets have several shortcomings, particularly when used
                    as a teaching tool. The Stylesheets were not, in fact, designed with a didactic
                    aim in mind and do not offer TEI-to-RDF transformation guidelines: users need to
                    possess good XSLT skills to prepare the TEI document, gain insight into the
                    rationale of the transformation, and adapt it to their specific needs.</p>
                <p>Also, <ref target="https://rdflib.readthedocs.io">RDF</ref> can be serialized in a variety of ways, with Turtle being by far the
                    most widely used due to its legibility. Since the TEI-to-RDF Stylesheet was
                    created, more powerful methods of linked data production have been released.
                    RDFLib, a Python package for working with RDF, is one of these. The key difference between using XSLT and RDFLib to create RDF triples is
                    that the former requires developers to hardcode RDF triples into the
                    transformation stylesheet (i.e., the developer must choose ahead of time a
                    specific serialization and adhere to its syntax), resulting in a significant
                    loss of flexibility and an increase in human errors. RDFLib, on the other hand,
                    automatically serializes RDF triples, allowing you to add properties to an
                    entity at any point along the way without worrying about syntax and structure
                    (see <ref target="#listing3">Listing 3</ref> , which shows a comparison between
                    XSLT and RDFLib as two different methods of generating RDF statements).</p>
                <p>Finally, while the TEI-to-RDF Stylesheet reuse some concepts from the <ref target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org/">CIDOC</ref>
                    Conceptual Reference Model (see <ptr target="#crofts2011"/> ) and the <ref target="http://purl.org/dc/terms/">Dublin Core</ref> (see <ptr target="#weibel2000"/> ), it does not make use of the expressive potential of ontologies such as
                    <ref target="http://iflastandards.info/ns/fr/frbr/frbroo/">FRBRoo</ref> (see <ptr
                        target="#bekiari2015"/> ) and <ref target="http://purl.org/spar/pro/">PRO</ref> (see <ptr target="#peroni2012"/>
                    ), which have recently gained attention and application in both text and
                    cultural heritage representation (see <ptr target="#daquino2019"/> ).</p>
                <p>Another tool we considered is <ref target="http://xtriples.spatialhumanities.de/">XTriples</ref> (see <ptr
                    target="#gruntgens2016"/> ). XTriples is a webservice-based infrastructure for extracting RDF
                    statements from collections of XML documents ( <ptr target="#gruntgens2016"/> ).
                    Unlike the Stylesheets, XTriples can produce multiple serializations of the
                    resulting RDF graph and comes with a documentation. The transformation is
                    customizable via an XPath-based configuration file. LOD beginners, however, may
                    find this operation difficult and the tool not immediately usable or
                    replicable.</p>
                <p>There are also tools, such as Recogito, that enable the extraction of specific
                    features from TEI-encoded texts. <ref target="https://recogito.pelagios.org/">Recogito</ref>, developed by the Pelagios Network,
                    allows users to add annotations to specific passages of text, which they can
                    then download as RDF statements (see <ptr target="#simon2017"
                    /> ). The transformation is not configurable nor explained as this is not the
                    focus of the tool.</p>
                <eg xml:id="listing3">TEI to RDF/XML with XSLT &lt;rdf:Description
                    rdf:about=&quot;{$person_uri}&quot;&gt; &lt;rdf:type
                    rdf:resource=&quot;http://schema.org/Person&quot;/&gt; &lt;owl:sameAs
                    rdf:resource=&quot;{$same_as_uri}&quot;/&gt; &lt;rdfs:label&gt;
                    &lt;xsl:attribute name=&quot;xml:lang&quot;&gt; &lt;xsl:value-of
                    select=&quot;{$label_lang}&quot;/&gt; &lt;/xsl:attribute&gt; &lt;xsl:value-of
                    select=&quot;{$label}&quot;/&gt; &lt;/rdfs:label&gt; &lt;/rdf:Description&gt;
                    TEI to RDF/XML with RDFLib g.add((person_uri, RDF.type, schema.Person))
                    g.add((person_uri, OWL.sameAs, same_as_uri)) g.add((person_uri, RDFS.label,
                    Literal(label, lang=label_lang))) g.serialize(format=&quot;xml&quot;) </eg>
                <dhq:caption>
                    <head>Listing 3</head>
                    <p>XSLT versus RDFLib TEI-to-LOD transformation; the second method offers a more
                        flexible and less error-prone way of creating RDF statements.</p>
                </dhq:caption>
            </div>
            <div type="level1" xml:id="4_linked-data-from-tei-lift">
                <head>
                    <title rend="italic">Linked data from TEI</title>(LIFT) <note>
                         A Github repository containing all of LIFT’s components can be found at
                                <ref target="https://github.com/fgiovannetti/lift"
                                >https://github.com/fgiovannetti/lift</ref> . The web application
                            can be found at <ref target="https://projects.dharc.unibo.it/lift/"
                                >https://projects.dharc.unibo.it/lift/</ref> .
                    </note>
                </head>
                <p>Based on the shortcomings discussed above, we decided to develop a TEI-to-LOD
                    transformation tool for our students that would simplify the transformation
                    process while also openly and transparently documenting the workflow, with the
                    goal of making such workflow modifiable and adaptable to new contexts.</p>
                <p>
                    <title rend="italic">Linked data from TEI</title>(LIFT) is a Python-based, open-source
                    application for creating graphs of RDF statements from TEI documents. LIFT
                    targets digital humanities students as well as textual scholars experimenting
                    for the first times with linked open data in digital scholarly editing.</p>
                <p>The main component of LIFT is a collection of TEI-to-LOD transformation scripts.
                    The scripts, written in Python, take as input a TEI document and generate an RDF
                    graph. Each script addresses the transformation of specific TEI entities
                    including persons, personal relations, places, and events. A transformation
                    script for the TEI critical apparatus is also available (see <ref
                        target="#4-2_the-transformation-scripts">Section 4.2</ref> ).</p>
                <p>The application is extensively documented in order to facilitate the reuse and
                    adaptation of the transformation workflow. The documentation walks users through
                    the process of preparing their TEI document for transformation, describes the
                    expected RDF graph, and provides step-by-step explanations of the transformation
                    scripts in the form of an interactive Jupyter notebook (see <ref
                        target="#4-3_the-documentation">Section 4.3</ref> ).</p>
                <p>Users can access LIFT through a browser or download the collection of scripts for
                    local use. A basic understanding of the TEI and RDF is recommended (the ideal
                    target audience are digital humanities students who are already familiar with
                    digital scholarly editions, the TEI, RDF and ontologies, and basic Python
                    programming).</p>
                <p>LIFT’s web interface has a straightforward design. When using a browser to access
                    LIFT, users are directed to the homepage, which contains instructions for
                    getting started with the transformation (see <ref target="#figure01">Figure
                        1</ref> ): by clicking on the 'Quick start' tab, an upload bar for the input
                    TEI document becomes available (see <ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref> ).
                    After uploading the TEI document into LIFT, users are directed to another page
                    where they can select a transformation option (see <ref target="#figure03"
                        >Figure 3</ref> ). If the transformation is successful, multiple
                    serializations of the resulting RDF graph become available for download (see
                        <ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref> ).</p>
                <div type="level2" xml:id="4-1_methodology">
                    <head>Methodology</head>
                    <p>The creation of linked open data from TEI documents is more than a technical
                        operation. While digital scholarly editions based solely on the TEI standard
                        are document-centric, LOD-based resources are data-centric: the
                        transformation of the information conveyed by the TEI markup into RDF
                        statements forming a graph necessitates careful methodological reflection as
                        the edition is disassembled to form a dataset of interconnected entities,
                        each represented by a URI or a literal.</p>
                    <p>In addition to reorganizing tree-structured information into a graph data
                        structure, the transition from TEI to linked data necessitates assigning a
                        formal semantics to the entities by reusing existing ontologies whenever
                        possible. As of today, there is no TEI-specific ontology, so all elements
                        and attributes must be mapped to classes and properties from arbitrary
                        ontologies (see <ptr target="#eide2014"/> and <ptr target="#ciotti2016"/>
                        ).</p>
                    <p>There are two major challenges to performing such mapping. First, the chosen
                        ontologies assign a formal semantics to the data, influencing how
                        information is accessed and reused in the future. Users should be aware of
                        the implications of using ready-to-use conversion tools like LIFT: the
                        information conveyed by the original encoding may change when moving from
                        one vocabulary, e.g. the TEI, to another, e.g. FRBRoo, CIDOC CRM, PROV-O,
                        etc.</p>
                    <p>Second, a knowledge graph is composed of entities (i.e. concepts), and links
                        between entities (i.e. relationships between concepts). The distinction
                        between what will become a concept and what will become a relationship is
                        not inconsequential. In TEI, there are at least two ways to represent a
                        relationship. The first approach is to make use of an attribute. The line
                            <code>&lt;rdg wit=&quot;#A&quot;&gt;liber&lt;/rdg&gt;</code> , for
                        example, indicates that the reading 'liber' is witnessed by manuscript 'A',
                        where 'is witnessed by' is the relationship between the reading and the
                        manuscript. A second method is to nest elements within each another. The
                        encoding <code>&lt;app&gt;&lt;rdg
                            wit=&quot;#A&quot;&gt;liber&lt;/rdg&gt;&lt;rdg
                            wit=&quot;#B&quot;&gt;libellus&lt;/rdg&gt;&lt;/app&gt;</code> , for
                        example, indicates that 'libellus' is a variant of 'liber'. Although
                        interpreting the meaning of the relationships in the preceding examples is
                        simple and without ambiguity, this is not always the case.</p>
                    <p>When developing LIFT, we decided to set some predefined requirements for the
                        encoding of the input TEI document so to ensure a meaningful, error-free
                        restructuring and formalization of the information (see <ref
                            target="#4-2_the-transformation-scripts">Section 4.2</ref> ). The
                        encoding prerequisites can be adjusted locally by modifying the scripts. As
                        of semantics, we decided to reuse <ref target="https://d-nb.info/standards/elementset/agrelon">a set of ontologies</ref> that are widely
                        adopted in the fields of cultural heritage and text representation: the
                        CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model (CIDOC CRM) to represent people, places and
                        events; the Agent Relationship Ontology (AgRelOn) (see <ptr
                            target="#litz2012"/> ) to describe personal relationships; the Functional Requirements for
                        Bibliographic Records object-oriented (FRBRoo) for texts; the Dublin Core
                        Metadata Terms (DCMI Metadata Terms) to describe bibliographic resources;
                        PROV-O to link the account of an event to its source; the Publishing Roles
                        Ontology (PRO), which enables the reification of roles in such a way that
                        each role is bounded to a specific context (e.g. the role of 'bride' in the
                        context of a particular ceremony); the <ref target="http://www.essepuntato.it/2012/04/tvc/">Time-indexed Value in Context</ref> (TVC) (see, again, <ptr
                            target="#peroni2012"/> ) to represent time; the property owl:sameAs from the Web Ontology
                        Language (OWL) to interconnect the entities to semantically equivalent
                        resources outside the edition; the property rdfs:label and rdf:value from
                        the Resource Description Framework Schema (RDF Schema), which are used to
                        include human-readable labels and TEI snippets in the graph, respectively.
                        Finally, the <ref target="https://w3id.org/cao">Critical Apparatus Ontology</ref> (CAO) is leveraged to represent
                        critical apparatus entries (see
                        <ptr target="#giovannetti2021"/> ). 
                    </p>
                    <p>A combination of multiple ontologies is required to express the various
                        concepts and relationships underpinning editions, as well as to demonstrate
                        to students how multiple ontologies can be used in the same knowledge
                        graph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="level2" xml:id="4-2_the-transformation-scripts">
                    <head>The transformation scripts</head>
                    <p>LIFT’s collection of transformation scripts include:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Persons only</item>
                        <item>Persons and events</item>
                        <item>Persons and relations</item>
                        <item>Places only</item>
                        <item>Persons, events, relations, and places</item>
                        <item>Critical apparatus</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>We decided to write multiple scripts because we wanted the transformation to
                        be modular and the resulting RDF graph’s complexity to be incremental.
                        Script 5 combines the previous four into a single transformation option.</p>
                    <p>For the scripts to work, the input TEI document must follow specific
                        guidelines. The TEI, as previously stated, allows for multiple ways to
                        encode the same textual features. For example, in order to markup a personal
                        name, one can use the tag <code>&lt;persName&gt;</code> , the tag
                            <code>&lt;name&gt;</code> , or even the tag <code>&lt;rs&gt;</code> (see
                            <ref
                            target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ND.html"
                            >https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ND.html</ref> )
                        This is an important feature in terms of flexibility, but it makes creating
                        a universal TEI-to-RDF transformation script difficult. As a result, LIFT’s
                        documentation includes a set of encoding guidelines intended to ensure a
                        smooth TEI-to-LOD transformation ( <ref target="#listing4">Listing 4
                            below</ref> juxtaposes the input TEI encoding and the resulting RDF
                        statements). In particular, the input TEI document must conform to the
                        following indications: <note>
                             Further requirements apply when transforming a critical apparatus
                                (see, again, <ptr target="#giovannetti2021"/> ).
                        </note>1. Any TEI element being transformed must be assigned a unique
                        identifier within an @xml:id attribute; 2. The TEI document must contain a
                        TEI header, even if minimal; the <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> element must be
                        used to describe people in the TEI header, and the
                            <code>&lt;persName&gt;</code> element must be used to markup in-text
                        occurrences of such people; 3. In a similar way, the
                            <code>&lt;place&gt;</code> element must be used to describe places in
                        the TEI header, and the <code>&lt;placeName&gt;</code> element must be used
                        to markup in-text occurrences of such places; 4. People and places described
                        in the TEI header should be assigned a <code>@sameAs</code> attribute
                        containing links to external authority records (e.g. VIAF); 5. Any
                        relationship between people should be described in the TEI header within
                            <code>&lt;listRelation&gt;</code> ; 6. Similarly, events should be
                        described using the <code>&lt;event&gt;</code> element within
                            <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> or <code>&lt;place&gt;</code> . An example
                        input file is also provided when accessing LIFT from the browser. If
                        modifying the TEI encoding to meet the requirements of LIFT is not possible,
                        the documentation in general, and the interactive Jupyter notebook in
                        particular, will help users gain the understanding needed to adapt the
                        transformation to a different input.</p>
                    <eg xml:id="listing4">Input (TEI) &lt;person xml:id=&quot;socr&quot;
                        sameAs=&quot;http://viaf.org/viaf/88039167&quot;&gt; &lt;persName
                        xml:lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;Socrates&lt;/persName&gt; &lt;/person&gt; [...]
                        &lt;p xml:id=&quot;para01&quot;&gt;An example of paragraph mentioning
                        &lt;persName ref=&quot;#socr&quot;&gt;Socrates&lt;/persName&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
                        Output (RDF) @prefix crm:&lt;http://www.cidoc-crm.org/cidoc-crm/&gt; .
                        @prefix dcterms: &lt;http://purl.org/dc/terms/&gt; . @prefix frbroo:
                        &lt;http://iflastandards.info/ns/fr/frbr/frbroo/&gt; . @prefix owl:
                        &lt;http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#&gt; . @prefix rdf:
                        &lt;http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#&gt; . @prefix rdfs:
                        &lt;http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#&gt; .
                        &lt;https://example.org/person/socr&gt; a crm:E21_Person ; rdfs:label
                        &quot;Socrates&quot;@en ; dcterms:isReferencedBy
                        &lt;https://example.org/text/para01&gt; ; owl:sameAs
                        &lt;http://viaf.org/viaf/88039167&gt; .
                        &lt;https://example.org/text/para01&gt; a frbroo:F23_Expression_Fragment ;
                        frbroo:R15i_is_fragment_of &lt;https://example.org/example_v1&gt; ;
                        rdf:value &quot;&quot;&quot;An example of paragraph mentioning
                        Socrates.&quot;&quot;&quot;^^rdf:Literal . rdf:value &quot;&quot;&quot;&lt;p
                        xml:id=&quot;para01&quot;&gt;An example of paragraph mentioning &lt;persName
                        ref=&quot;#socr&quot;&gt;Socrates&lt;/persName&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&quot;&quot;&quot;^^rdf:XMLLiteral
                        . </eg>
                    <dhq:caption>
                        <head>Listing 4</head>
                        <p>The input TEI encoding and the corresponding RDF output.</p>
                    </dhq:caption>
                    <p>LIFT, as stated earlier in the introduction, uses Python as its
                        transformation language. Python, which is increasingly being taught in
                        digital humanities courses around the world, offers more efficient and
                        error-free ways of working with RDF and linked open data than XSLT (see <ref
                            target="#3_related-work">Section 3 above</ref> ).</p>
                    <p>RDFLib is a Python library that specializes in RDF triple creation and
                        management (see the documentation at <ref
                            target="https://rdflib.readthedocs.io"
                            >https://rdflib.readthedocs.io</ref> ). Using RDFLib to create RDF
                        triples is very simple, and the amount of human effort required is minimal.
                        URIs can be saved as variables, and RDF statements can be written on
                        separate lines. RDFLib then generates a single graph with no repetitions.
                        Multiple serializations are possible, including XML, Turtle, N-Triples, and
                        JSON-LD.</p>
                    <p>LIFT uses another Python library, lxml, in conjunction with RDFLib to parse
                        TEI documents (see the documentation at <ref target="https://lxml.de"
                            >https://lxml.de</ref> ). When using XSLT to process XML files, one must
                        be familiar with the structure of the document to be processed. However,
                        using lxml and Python, it is possible to work with less well-known
                        inputs.</p>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="#listing4">Listing 4 above</ref>shows a portion of a TEI
                        document and the corresponding RDF graph in LIFT. <ref target="#listing5"
                            >Listing 5 below</ref> provides some components of the transformation
                        script used for generating such output. LIFT searches the TEI document for
                        all occurrences of <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> . The value of the
                            <code>@xml:id</code> attribute associated with the person is then
                        obtained and used to generate the URI representing that person. LIFT looks
                        also for any in-text reference to the person. To do so, it searches the TEI
                        document for all occurrences of <code>&lt;persName&gt;</code> featuring a
                        @ref attribute linking to the person. Each person is assigned to the CIDOC
                        CRM class E21 Person. If a <code>@sameAs</code> attribute is provided in the
                        TEI document for the <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> element, LIFT leverages its
                        value or values to create interconnections to external authority records
                        (using the OWL property owl:sameAs). All data used for building the RDF
                        graph are extracted from the TEI document. The content of the
                            <code>&lt;persName&gt;</code> element provided within
                            <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> is used to generate a human-readable label
                        for the entity. The language is specified by the <code>@xml:lang</code>
                        attribute.</p>
                    <p>As the reader can see from this example, LIFT uses a predefined set of
                        ontologies to describe the text (see <ref target="#4-1_methodology">Section
                            4.1</ref> ). In order to modify this behaviour, users must modify the
                        scripts. To facilitate this effort, as already anticipated, LIFT provides a
                        Jupyter notebook that guides users through the scripts step-by-step and
                        interactively (see <ref target="#4-3_the-documentation">Section 4.3</ref>
                        ).</p>
                    <eg xml:id="listing5">for person in root.findall('.//tei:person', tei):
                        person_id = person.get('{http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace}id')
                        person_uri = URIRef(base_uri + '/person/' + person_id) person_ref = '#' +
                        person_id g.add( (person_uri, RDF.type, crm.E21_Person)) same_as =
                        person.get('sameAs').split() if same_as is not None: same_as =
                        same_as.split() i = 0 while i &lt; len(same_as): same_as_uri =
                        URIRef(same_as[i]) g.add( (person_uri, OWL.sameAs, same_as_uri)) i += 1
                        persname = person.find('./tei:persName', tei) if persname is not None: label
                        = persname.text label_lang =
                        persname.get('{http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace}lang') if label_lang is
                        not None: g.add( (person_uri, RDFS.label, Literal(label, lang=label_lang)))
                        else: g.add( (person_uri, RDFS.label, Literal(label))) </eg>
                    <dhq:caption>
                        <head>Listing 5</head>
                        <p>An excerpt of one of LIFT’s transformation script creating RDF triples
                            about persons.</p>
                    </dhq:caption>
                </div>
                <div type="level2" xml:id="4-3_the-documentation">
                    <head>The documentation</head>
                    <p>In developing LIFT as a tool for supporting the adoption of linked open data
                        in digital scholarly editing, we followed the principle that no tool should
                        be used as a black box. Students/users of LIFT must be provided with the
                        knowledge required to understand the methodology and the technology
                        informing the conversion. LIFT is accompanied by an extensive documentation
                        available at <ref target="http://linked-data-from-tei.rtfd.io/"
                            >http://linked-data-from-tei.rtfd.io/</ref> presenting the full
                        Python-based workflow for TEI-to-LOD transformation. LIFT’s documentation is
                        divided into four main sections:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <title rend="italic">Prepare your TEI document</title>, which explains the
                                encoding requirements for the input TEI document;</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <title rend="italic">The RDF graph</title>, illustrating the structure and
                                semantics of the generated knowledge graph by comparing the TEI
                                input with the corresponding RDF output (this section also discusses
                                why and how users might choose different ontologies for their
                                projects or modify the scripts to work with different input
                                data);</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <title rend="italic">How the scripts work</title>, where users can access
                                an interactive Jupyter notebook containing LIFT’s scripts with
                                instructions and line-by-line explanations that are meant to help
                                users develop the skills required to write their own transformation
                                scripts; <note>
                                    An online, read-only version of the notebook is available at
                                            <ref
                                            target="https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/fgiovannetti/lift/blob/master/jupyter_nb/TEItoRDF.ipynb"
                                            >https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/fgiovannetti/lift/blob/master/jupyter_nb/TEItoRDF.ipynb</ref>
                                        .
                                </note>
                            </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <title rend="italic">Further readings and resources</title>, which lists
                                relevant publications and provides examples of TEI digital scholarly
                                editions which have been enriched by means of linked open data.</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>In addition to the documentation, each semantic statement of the resulting
                        RDF graph is accompanied by the original TEI construct that generated it
                        facilitating the comparison between the TEI input and the RDF output: this
                        provides users with indirect support as they can view the input TEI encoding
                        and the output RDF graph side by side and go back to adjust the input TEI
                        document to resolve any transformation issues that may arise (see <ref
                            target="#listing4">Listing 4 above</ref> ).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="level1" xml:id="5_lift-in-the-classroom">
                <head>LIFT in the classroom</head>
                <p>Digital humanities, as a discipline, lie at the crossroads of theory and
                    practice. The learning-by-example paradigm, which entails presenting existing
                    models that can be adapted to address new problems, is particularly effective in
                    similar interdisciplinary contexts (see <ptr target="#tomasi2020"/> ). LIFT was
                    created in response to a perceived lack of teaching tools for TEI to LOD
                    transformation based on such paradigm.</p>
                <p>LIFT will be used in a text representation laboratory activity for the University
                    of Bologna’s Master Degree in Digital Humanities and Digital Knowledge. As
                    anticipated at the beginning of this paper, the activity aims to combine the
                    knowledge and skills acquired by the students from various modules and,
                    particularly, text encoding with the TEI, ontology development, Python
                    programming, and linked open data for cultural heritage.</p>
                <p>The plan for the activity involves gathering the students in 3-member groups.
                    Each group will choose an existing digital scholarly edition and work on the
                    underlying TEI document to ensure that the encoding requirements of LIFT are
                    met. <note>
                         Patrick Sahle’s and Greta Franzini’s catalogues of digital scholarly
                            editions ( <ref target="https://v3.digitale-edition.de/"
                                >https://v3.digitale-edition.de/</ref> ; <ref
                                target="https://dig-ed-cat.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/"
                                >https://dig-ed-cat.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/</ref> ) will be provided as a
                            starting point, along with RIDE ( <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/"
                                >https://ride.i-d-e.de/</ref> ).
                    </note>The groups will then use LIFT, either via browser or locally, to produce
                    an RDF graph. Finally, each group will present their findings to the class,
                    highlighting challenges and solutions in transforming each type of entity.
                    Following activities will shift the emphasis away from the input TEI document as
                    students will focus on modifying the transformation scripts to adapt them to the
                    existing digital scholarly editions rather than the other way around.</p>
                <p>By experimenting with the shift from tree-structured to graph-structured data,
                    and from the TEI vocabulary to RDF using multiple ontologies, students will gain
                    a better understanding of the implications of annotating a text in one way
                    versus another within the context of a real-world task that requires them to
                    combine different skills and competencies that are typically taught
                    separately.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, because the activity is structured as group work on a specific
                    problem to be solved, students will be able to strengthen their ability to
                    collaborate as a team, which is one of the pillars of digital humanities
                    scholarship and, by extension, should be one of digital humanities pedagogy (see
                        <ptr target="#frost2020"/> ).</p>
                <p>The laboratory activity will also allow us to evaluate the clarity and
                    effectiveness of LIFT as a teaching tool both directly through an
                    end-of-activity questionnaire and indirectly through the students’
                    presentations.</p>

            </div>
            <div type="level1" xml:id="6_conclusion-and-next-steps">
                <head>Conclusion and next steps</head>
                <p>This paper introduced LIFT, an open-source tool written as a set of Python
                    scripts for generating linked data from TEI-encoded texts. The use of linked
                    open data for text representation facilitates interoperability with other
                    cultural resources on the web and opens up editions to new areas of cultural
                    heritage research. LIFT’s goal is to walk users through the transformation
                    process from TEI to linked data step by step, as well as to promote a better
                    understanding of the theoretical and methodological aspects that underpin the
                    transformation.</p>
                <p>Some of the key characteristics of the evolving web of data include open-source
                    tools, well-documented applications, and shared ontologies. User-friendly
                    resources that reduce the complexity of transforming digital scholarly editions
                    from a document-centric to a data-centric model are also critical in the
                    development and expansion of a linked open data cloud of cultural heritage.</p>
                <p>We envisage LIFT both as a teaching tool and a ready-for-use resource for
                    TEI-to-LOD transformation, hoping it will serve as an example of a digital
                    humanities teaching tool that raises awareness about the methodological and
                    theoretical implications of the structural and semantic shift that occurs when
                    transitioning from a TEI-based text representation to LOD.</p>
                <p>With LIFT, we also aim to encourage further research into the development of
                    open-source, user-friendly tools aiding the mutual integration of digital
                    scholarly editions and the cultural heritage linked open data cloud. Such tools
                    have the potential to make digital humanities, and especially knowledge
                    representation, a more inclusive field of study and research. In order to test
                    this idea, we will use LIFT in the context of the University of Bologna’s Master
                    Degree in Digital Humanities and Digital Knowledge, as a teaching tool for
                    students encountering linked open data for the first time as a method of
                    publishing digital scholarly editions on the web in a data integration
                    perspective. We expect that LIFT will help students understand the process not
                    only practically but also, and primarily, in terms of methodology and
                    theory.</p>
                <p>LIFT is under active development. Features that will be provided in the near
                    future include a transformation script for bibliographic references encoded
                    using specialized elements from the <ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#COBI">TEI</ref> model.bibLike class. Furthermore, the documentation will be expanded with new sections on
                    ontologies for text representation as well as useful resources, particularly
                    examples of digital scholarly editions enhanced through the use of linked open
                    data.</p>
            </div>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="images/figure01.png"/>
                <figDesc>A screenshot of the homepage</figDesc>
                <head>Homepage</head>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="images/figure02.png"/>
                <figDesc>A screenshot of the Quick start page</figDesc>
                <head>Quick start</head>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="images/figure03.png"/>
                <figDesc>A screenshot of the page listing the transformation options</figDesc>
                <head>Choosing a transformation</head>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="images/figure04.png"/>
                <figDesc>A screenshot of the download button producing different serializations of
                    the knowledge graph</figDesc>
                <head>Downloading the resulting knowledge graph according to different
                    serializations</head>
            </figure>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/GSFKJVW7"
                    label="Licastro, Rogers and Savonick 2020" type="bookSection" xml:id="frost2020">
                    <title level="a">Collaboration</title>
                    <editor>
                        Amanda
                        <surname>Licastro</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Katina</forename>
                        <surname>Rogers</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Danica</forename>
                        <surname>Savonick</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <title level="m">Digital Pedagogy in the Humanities: Concepts, Models, and
                        Experiments</title>
                    <idno type="ISBN">978-3-7543-4369-2</idno>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Rebecca</forename>
                        <surname>Frost Davis</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Matthew K.</forename>
                        <surname>Gold</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Katherine D.</forename>
                        <surname>Harris</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Jentery</forename>
                        <surname>Sayers</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <publisher>Modern Language Association</publisher>
                    <date>2020</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-21T12:27:27Z</note>
                    <note type="url"
                        >https://digitalpedagogy.hcommons.org/keyword/Collaboration</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/XBECBBB8"
                    label="TEI Ontologies SIG 2019" type="webpage" xml:id="tei_ontologies_sig2019">
                    <title level="a">TEI: Ontologies SIG</title>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>contributor</resp>
                        <persName>
                            <name>TEI Ontologies SIG</name>
                        </persName>
                    </respStmt>
                    <title level="m">Text Encoding Initiative</title>
                    <date>2019</date>
                    <note type="url">https://tei-c.org/activities/sig/ontologies</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/J7K8ZJHT"
                    label="Crofts et al. 2011" type="journalArticle" xml:id="crofts2011">
                    <title level="a">CIDOC CRM: CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model</title>
                    <title type="short">CIDOC CRM</title>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Nick</forename>
                        <surname>Crofts</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Martin</forename>
                        <surname>Doerr</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Tony</forename>
                        <surname>Gill</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Stephen</forename>
                        <surname>Stead</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Matthew</forename>
                        <surname>Stiff</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <date>2011</date>
                    <note type="url">http://www.cidoc-crm.org/cidoc-crm/</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/SZZW6NEL" label="Sahle 2014"
                    type="blogPost" xml:id="sahle2014">
                    <title level="m">Criteria for Reviewing Scholarly Digital Editions</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Patrick</forename>
                        <surname>Sahle</surname>
                    </author>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>contributor</resp>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Georg</forename>
                            <surname>Vogeler</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </respStmt>
                    <date>2014</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2019-09-28T12:27:27Z</note>
                    <note type="url"
                        >https://www.i-d-e.de/publikationen/weitereschriften/criteria-version-1-1/</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/N8CLLVZY" label="Price 2008"
                    type="bookSection" xml:id="price2008">
                    <title level="a">Electronic scholarly editions</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Kenneth M.</forename>
                        <surname>Price</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="m">A companion to digital literary studies</title>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Susan</forename>
                        <surname>Schreibman</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Ray</forename>
                        <surname>Siemens</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <date>2008</date>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/QJ6N3RUF"
                    label="Gruntgens and Schrade 2016" type="journalArticle" xml:id="gruntgens2016">
                    <title level="a">Data repositories in the Humanities and the Semantic Web:
                        modelling, linking, visualising</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Max</forename>
                        <surname>Gruntgens</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Torsten</forename>
                        <surname>Schrade</surname>
                    </author>
                    <biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/ZDJP8PYZ"
                    label="MLA Commettee on Scholarly Editions 2016" type="webpage" xml:id="mla2016">
                    <title level="a">MLA Statement on the Scholarly Edition in the Digital
                        Age</title>
                    <author>
                        <name>MLA Commettee on Scholarly Editions</name>
                    </author>
                    <title level="m">Modern Language Association</title>
                    <date>2016</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2019-09-29T15:52:03Z</note>
                    <note type="url"
                        >https://www.mla.org/Resources/Research/Surveys-Reports-and-Other-Documents/Publishing-and-Scholarship/Reports-from-the-MLA-Committee-on-Scholarly-Editions/MLA-Statement-on-the-Scholarly-Edition-in-the-Digital-Age</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/6UN62N3F" label="Andrews 2013"
                    type="journalArticle" xml:id="andrews2013">
                    <title level="a">The Third Way: Philology and Critical Edition in the Digital
                        Age</title>
                    <idno type="DOI">10.7892/BORIS.43071</idno>
                    <title type="short">The Third Way</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Tara L.</forename>
                        <surname>Andrews</surname>
                    </author>
                    <date>2013</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-02T19:40:57Z</note>
                    <note type="url">http://boris.unibe.ch/43071/</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/UL3SHNRN"
                    label="Ciotti and Tomasi 2016" type="journalArticle" xml:id="ciotti2016">
                    <title level="a">Formal Ontologies, Linked Data, and TEI Semantics</title>
                    <idno type="DOI">10.4000/jtei.1480</idno>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Fabio</forename>
                        <surname>Ciotti</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Francesca</forename>
                        <surname>Tomasi</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
                    <idno type="ISSN">2162-5603</idno>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">Issue 9</biblScope>
                    <date>2016</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-02T19:41:23Z</note>
                    <note type="url">http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1480</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/5MAXPKCH"
                    label="Ciula, Spence and Vieira 2008" type="journalArticle" xml:id="ciula2008">
                    <title level="a">Expressing complex associations in medieval historical
                        documents: the Henry III Fine Rolls Project</title>
                    <idno type="DOI">10.1093/llc/fqn018</idno>
                    <title type="short">Expressing complex associations in medieval historical
                        documents</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Arianna</forename>
                        <surname>Ciula</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Paul</forename>
                        <surname>Spence</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>José Miguel</forename>
                        <surname>Vieira</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                    <idno type="ISSN">0268-1145, 1477-4615</idno>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="page">311-325</biblScope>
                    <date>2008</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-02T19:41:38Z</note>
                    <note type="url"
                        >https://academic.oup.com/dsh/article-lookup/doi/10.1093/llc/fqn018</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/VX9DYENP"
                    label="Daquino, Giovannetti and Tomasi 2019" type="journalArticle"
                    xml:id="daquino2019">
                    <title level="a">Linked Data per le edizioni scientifiche digitali. Il workflow
                        di pubblicazione dell’edizione semantica del quaderno di appunti di Paolo
                        Bufalini</title>
                    <idno type="DOI">10.6092/ISSN.2532-8816/9091</idno>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Marilena</forename>
                        <surname>Daquino</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Francesca</forename>
                        <surname>Giovannetti</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Francesca</forename>
                        <surname>Tomasi</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="j">Umanistica Digitale</title>
                    <biblScope unit="page">No 7 (2019)</biblScope>
                    <date>2019</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-02T19:42:13Z</note>
                    <note type="url">https://umanisticadigitale.unibo.it/article/view/9091</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/H3J5ZUPG"
                    label="Daquino et al. 2014" type="journalArticle" xml:id="daquino2014">
                    <title level="a">Political Roles Ontology (PRoles): Enhancing Archival Authority
                        Records through Semantic Web Technologies</title>
                    <idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.procs.2014.10.012</idno>
                    <title type="short">Political Roles Ontology (PRoles)</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Marilena</forename>
                        <surname>Daquino</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Silvio</forename>
                        <surname>Peroni</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Francesca</forename>
                        <surname>Tomasi</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Fabio</forename>
                        <surname>Vitali</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="j">Procedia Computer Science</title>
                    <idno type="ISSN">18770509</idno>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="page">60-67</biblScope>
                    <date>2014</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-02T19:45:07Z</note>
                    <note type="url"
                        >https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S1877050914013726</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/BL456XVI"
                    label="DeRose et al. 1990" type="journalArticle" xml:id="derose1990">
                    <title level="a">What is text, really?</title>
                    <idno type="DOI">10.1007/BF02941632</idno>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Steven J.</forename>
                        <surname>DeRose</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>David G.</forename>
                        <surname>Durand</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Elli</forename>
                        <surname>Mylonas</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Allen H.</forename>
                        <surname>Renear</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="j">Journal of Computing in Higher Education</title>
                    <idno type="ISSN">1042-1726</idno>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="page">3-26</biblScope>
                    <date>1990</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-02T19:45:41Z</note>
                    <note type="url">http://link.springer.com/10.1007/BF02941632</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/WYDZXJYU" label="Eide 2014"
                    type="journalArticle" xml:id="eide2014">
                    <title level="a">Ontologies, Data Modeling, and TEI</title>
                    <idno type="DOI">10.4000/jtei.1191</idno>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Øyvind</forename>
                        <surname>Eide</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
                    <idno type="ISSN">2162-5603</idno>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">Issue 8</biblScope>
                    <date>2014</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-02T19:45:53Z</note>
                    <note type="url">http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1191</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/XTCB5BAK"
                    label="Jordanous et al. 2012" type="conferencePaper" xml:id="jordanous2012">
                    <title level="a">Exploring manuscripts: sharing ancient wisdoms across the
                        semantic web</title>
                    <idno type="DOI">10.1145/2254129.2254184</idno>
                    <title type="short">Exploring manuscripts</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Anna</forename>
                        <surname>Jordanous</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>K. Faith</forename>
                        <surname>Lawrence</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Mark</forename>
                        <surname>Hedges</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Charlotte</forename>
                        <surname>Tupman</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="m">Proceedings of the 2nd International Conference on Web
                        Intelligence, Mining and Semantics - WIMS '12</title>
                    <title type="conferenceName">the 2nd International Conference</title>
                    <idno type="ISBN">978-1-4503-0915-8</idno>
                    <pubPlace>Craiova, Romania</pubPlace>
                    <biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
                    <publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
                    <date>2012</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-02T19:49:23Z</note>
                    <note type="url">http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?doid=2254129.2254184</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/2ABWXPH5"
                    label="Litz et al. 2012" type="bookSection" xml:id="litz2012">
                    <title level="a">AgRelOn – An Agent Relationship Ontology</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Berenike</forename>
                        <surname>Litz</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Aenne</forename>
                        <surname>Löhden</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Jan</forename>
                        <surname>Hannemann</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Lars</forename>
                        <surname>Svensson</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="m">Metadata and Semantics Research</title>
                    <idno type="ISBN">978-3-642-35232-4 978-3-642-35233-1</idno>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Juan Manuel</forename>
                        <surname>Dodero</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Manuel</forename>
                        <surname>Palomo-Duarte</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Pythagoras</forename>
                        <surname>Karampiperis</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <pubPlace>Berlin, Heidelberg</pubPlace>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">343</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="page">202-213</biblScope>
                    <publisher>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher>
                    <date>2012</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-02T19:49:53Z</note>
                    <note type="url">http://link.springer.com/10.1007/978-3-642-35233-1_21</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/RMJTD8WF"
                    label="Peroni, Shotton and Vitali 2012" type="conferencePaper"
                    xml:id="peroni2012">
                    <title level="a">Scholarly publishing and linked data: describing roles,
                        statuses, temporal and contextual extents</title>
                    <idno type="DOI">10.1145/2362499.2362502</idno>
                    <title type="short">Scholarly publishing and linked data</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Silvio</forename>
                        <surname>Peroni</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>David</forename>
                        <surname>Shotton</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Fabio</forename>
                        <surname>Vitali</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="m">Proceedings of the 8th International Conference on Semantic
                        Systems - I-SEMANTICS '12</title>
                    <title type="conferenceName">the 8th International Conference</title>
                    <idno type="ISBN">978-1-4503-1112-0</idno>
                    <pubPlace>Graz, Austria</pubPlace>
                    <biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
                    <publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
                    <date>2012</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-02T19:50:52Z</note>
                    <note type="url">http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?doid=2362499.2362502</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/WUS62H6M" label="Pierazzo 2016"
                    type="book" xml:id="pierazzo2016">
                    <title level="m">Digital Scholarly Editing</title>
                    <idno type="ISBN">978-1-317-15067-1</idno>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Elena</forename>
                        <surname>Pierazzo</surname>
                    </author>
                    <edition>0</edition>
                    <publisher>Routledge</publisher>
                    <date>2016</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-02T19:51:03Z</note>
                    <note type="url">https://www.taylorfrancis.com/books/9781317150671</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/3HBDNDR3" label="Sahle 2016"
                    type="bookSection" xml:id="sahle2016">
                    <title level="a">2. What is a Scholarly Digital Edition?</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Patrick</forename>
                        <surname>Sahle</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="m">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories and Practices</title>
                    <idno type="ISBN">978-1-78374-238-7 978-1-78374-239-4 978-1-78374-240-0
                        978-1-78374-241-7 978-1-78374-242-4</idno>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Matthew James</forename>
                        <surname>Driscoll</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Elena</forename>
                        <surname>Pierazzo</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <biblScope unit="page">19-40</biblScope>
                    <publisher>Open Book Publishers</publisher>
                    <date>2016</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-02T19:55:26Z</note>
                    <note type="url">http://www.openbookpublishers.com/product/483</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/T8CKA9JN"
                    label="Giovannetti 2021" type="bookSection" xml:id="giovannetti2021">
                    <title level="a">The Critical Apparatus Ontology (CAO): Modelling the TEI
                        Critical Apparatus as a Knowledge Grap</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Francesca</forename>
                        <surname>Giovannetti</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="m">Graph data-models and semantic web technologies in scholarly
                        digital editing</title>
                    <idno type="ISBN">978-3-7543-4369-2</idno>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Elena</forename>
                        <surname>Spadini</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Francesca</forename>
                        <surname>Tomasi</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Georg</forename>
                        <surname>Vogeler</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <pubPlace>Norderstedt</pubPlace>
                    <biblScope unit="page">125-139</biblScope>
                    <publisher>BoD – Books on Demand</publisher>
                    <date>2021</date>
                    <series>
                        <title level="s">Schriften des Instituts für Dokumentologie und
                            Editorik</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">Band 15</biblScope>
                    </series>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/3PJNJWGZ"
                    label="Weibel and Koch 2000" type="journalArticle" xml:id="weibel2000">
                    <title level="a">The Dublin Core Metadata Initiative: Mission, Current
                        Activities, and Future Directions</title>
                    <idno type="DOI">10.1045/december2000-weibel</idno>
                    <title type="short">The Dublin Core Metadata Initiative</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Stuart L.</forename>
                        <surname>Weibel</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Traugott</forename>
                        <surname>Koch</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="j">D-Lib Magazine</title>
                    <idno type="ISSN">1082-9873</idno>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
                    <date>2000</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-02T19:59:20Z</note>
                    <note type="url">http://www.dlib.org/dlib/december00/weibel/12weibel.html</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/C9FJH8SY"
                    label="Wittern, Ciula and Tuohy 2009" type="journalArticle" xml:id="wittern2009">
                    <title level="a">The making of TEI P5</title>
                    <idno type="DOI">10.1093/llc/fqp017</idno>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Christian</forename>
                        <surname>Wittern</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Arianna</forename>
                        <surname>Ciula</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Conal</forename>
                        <surname>Tuohy</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                    <idno type="ISSN">0268-1145, 1477-4615</idno>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="page">281-296</biblScope>
                    <date>2009</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-02T19:59:29Z</note>
                    <note type="url"
                        >https://academic.oup.com/dsh/article-lookup/doi/10.1093/llc/fqp017</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/K8DM7K3G"
                    label="Bekiari et al. 2015" type="report" xml:id="bekiari2015">
                    <title level="m">Definition of FRBRoo: A conceptual model for bibliographic
                        information in object-oriented formalism</title>
                    <title type="short">Definition of FRBRoo</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Chryssoula</forename>
                        <surname>Bekiari</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Martin</forename>
                        <surname>Doerr</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Patrick</forename>
                        <surname>Le Boeuf</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Pat</forename>
                        <surname>Riva</surname>
                    </author>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/N7265R87"
                    label="TEI Consortium 2019" type="report" xml:id="tei_consortium2019">
                    <title level="m">P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                        Interchange</title>
                    <title type="short">TEI P5 Guidelines</title>
                    <author>
                        <name>TEI Consortium</name>
                    </author>
                    <date>2019</date>
                    <note type="url">https://tei-c.org/guidelines/</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/GPDYAI99"
                    label="Spadini, Tomasi and Vogeler 2021" type="book" xml:id="spadini2021">
                    <title level="m">Graph data-models and semantic web technologies in scholarly
                        digital editing</title>
                    <idno type="ISBN">978-3-7543-4369-2</idno>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Elena</forename>
                        <surname>Spadini</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Francesca</forename>
                        <surname>Tomasi</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <editor>
                        <forename>Georg</forename>
                        <surname>Vogeler</surname>
                    </editor>
                    <pubPlace>Norderstedt</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>BoD – Books on Demand</publisher>
                    <date>2021</date>
                    <series>
                        <title level="s">Schriften des Instituts für Dokumentologie und
                            Editorik</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">Band 15</biblScope>
                    </series>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/CIV45Z5C"
                    label="Simon et al. 2017" type="journalArticle" xml:id="simon2017">
                    <title level="a">Linked Data Annotation Without the Pointy Brackets: Introducing
                        Recogito 2</title>
                    <idno type="DOI">10.1080/15420353.2017.1307303</idno>
                    <title type="short">Linked Data Annotation Without the Pointy Brackets</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Rainer</forename>
                        <surname>Simon</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Elton</forename>
                        <surname>Barker</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Leif</forename>
                        <surname>Isaksen</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Pau</forename>
                        <surname>De Soto CaÑamares</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="j">Journal of Map &amp; Geography Libraries</title>
                    <idno type="ISSN">1542-0353, 1542-0361</idno>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="page">111-132</biblScope>
                    <date>2017</date>
                    <note type="accessed">2021-12-02T20:14:52Z</note>
                    <note type="url"
                        >https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/15420353.2017.1307303</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/H2GBYDRP" label="Tomasi 2012"
                    type="journalArticle" xml:id="tomasi2012">
                    <title level="a">L’edizione digitale e la rappresentazione della conoscenza. Un
                        esempio: Vespasiano da Bisticci e le sue lettere</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Francesca</forename>
                        <surname>Tomasi</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="j">Ecdotica</title>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="page">264-286</biblScope>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/B4KMFBGC" label="Tomasi 2020"
                    type="journalArticle" xml:id="tomasi2020">
                    <title level="a">Digital humanities e organizzazione della conoscenza: una
                        pratica di insegnamento nel LODLAM</title>
                    <idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.2426/aibstudi-12068</idno>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Francesca</forename>
                        <surname>Tomasi</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="j">Aibstudi</title>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="page">1-15</biblScope>
                    <date>2020</date>
                </bibl>
                <bibl corresp="http://zotero.org/users/2075931/items/AMM4NMWB"
                    label="Renear, Mylonas and Durand 1993" type="journalArticle"
                    xml:id="renear1993">
                    <title level="a">Refining our Notion of What Text Really Is: The Problem of
                        Overlapping Hierarchies</title>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Allen H.</forename>
                        <surname>Renear</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>Elli</forename>
                        <surname>Mylonas</surname>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <forename>David G.</forename>
                        <surname>Durand</surname>
                    </author>
                    <title level="j">Computer Science</title>
                    <date>1993</date>
                </bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
