<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article">Introduction to Feminisms and DH special issue</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
               <dhq:author_name>Jacqueline <dhq:family>Wernimont</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Arizona State University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>jwernimo@asu.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>I am an assistant professor of English at Arizona State University, where I
                     specialize in literary history, feminist digital media, histories of
                     quantification, and technologies of commemoration. Currently a Fellow of the
                     Lincoln Center for Applied Ethics, I work on new civil rights in digital
                     cultures with a particular emphasis on the long histories of our technologies
                     and practices. </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000217</idno>
            <idno type="volume">009</idno>
            <idno type="issue">02</idno>
            <date when="2015-08-26">26 August 2015</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>feminism</item>
                  <item>gender and women's studies</item>
                  <item>queer studies</item>
                  <item>text encoding</item>
                  <item>game studies</item>
                  <item>library and information sciences</item>
                  <item>literary studies</item>
                  <item>social editing</item>
                  <item>ethnography</item>
                  <item>post-colonial studies</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
         <change who="EH" when="2015-08-20">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
            <p>Introduction to the special issue of <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                  Quarterly</title> on Feminisms and DH, which offers both background on the origins
               of the special issue and an overview of the pieces therein.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
            <p>Introduction to the special issue on DH and Feminisms</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>Special issues often capture a moment in time, an efflorescence of critical engagement,
            or an urgent and timely shift in a field. If most special issues are snapshots, <title
               rend="quotes">Feminisms and DH</title> is something more like a long-exposure
            photograph, a surreal composite that is simultaneously fiction and fact.</p>
         <p>Let me indulge in a bit of scene-setting to help elucidate what I mean about the
            surrealism of this issue and as way of practicing the kind of self-disclosure that Chris
            Bourg and Bess Sadler argue is an important design and accessibility feature in feminist
            work <ptr target="#bourg2015"/>. Katherine D. Harris and I first proposed this special
            issue to the editorial board of <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> in January of 2012. We
            had been part of ongoing discussions about <q>silences</q> in archives and were
            relatively fresh off of a challenging roundtable titled <title rend="quotes">Editing
               Digital Feminisms</title> at the 2011 meeting of the Society of Textual Scholarship
            (STS), which also included Marilee Lindeman and Martha Nell Smith. The roundtable was
            great; what was challenging from my perspective was the clear gender profile of those in
            attendance – ours was a room full of women. While it was (is) disheartening to imagine
            that our male colleagues weren’t interested in feminist DH work, it struck us as
            particularly strange given the history of the field. As Harris and I noted in our call
            for this special issue, <quote rend="inline" source="#undocumented">several of the major
               DH projects that are now at the forefront of the field had feminist imperatives at
               the outset (for example: Women Writers Project, the Orlando Project, and the
               Dickenson Archive), but it does not seem to us that there has been a sustained
               inquiry into the evolving relationships between feminist theory and DH
            work.</quote></p>
         <p>In calling for a more sustained consideration of relationships between feminist theories
            and digital humanities, we were calling for engagements that helped enrich our sense of
            why feminisms mattered to DH, beyond simply getting more women in the rooms. In addition
            to issues of equity and access, at stake in the conception of this special issue were
            the ethics and commitments in digital humanities scholarship and teaching. Within a
            12-month span leading up to the proposal, there were discussions at the Modern Language
            Association meeting about who was in and who was out of DH,<note> see Stephen Ramsay’s
               write up of the MLA Roundtable <ref
                  target="http://stephenramsay.us/text/2011/01/08/whos-in-and-whos-out/"
                  >http://stephenramsay.us/text/2011/01/08/whos-in-and-whos-out/</ref></note> Jamie
            Skye Bianco’s <title rend="quotes">This Digital Humanities Which is Not One</title> and
            Tara McPherson’s <title rend="quotes">Why is the Digital Humanities So White?</title>
            came out in print, and the seeds of the three-site THATCamp Feminisms were sown by
            debates about coding, gender, and the politics of DH. In response, the creative and
            critical pieces in this special issue work to think not just about gender parity and
            recovery, modes central to second wave feminisms, but also about intersectional
            identities, labor, affect, and materiality in ways aligned with third-wave and
            decolonizing feminisms. Several of the pieces also reach outside of the admittedly
            porous boundaries of DH to include Library and Information Studies, Postcolonial
            Studies, Ethnography, and Game Studies as explicitly feminist interventions in a field
            that can feel dominated by literary and textual studies.</p>
         <p>By invoking the surreality of long-exposure photography I mean to point to the ways the
            interventions here are as necessary and fresh as they might have been in 2012 or 2013.
            Given the production time, this should be a blurry photograph, but the lack of sustained
            engagement with feminist theory within DH makes it still rather clear. Rather than being
            superseded, the interventions of each piece, and of the collection as a whole, have only
            become more urgent and it is striking that the field has not yet seen another special
            issue on feminisms and digital humanities. As I write this introduction the annual ADHO
            Digital Humanities conference is taking place in Sydney, Australia. In some ways it
            seems as if nothing has changed. As Scott Weingart has observed is his series of blog
            posts on the ADHO conference, while 46% of DH2015 attendees are women, they make up only
            35% of authors with accepted papers.<note><ref target="http://www.scottbot.net/HIAL/"
                  >http://www.scottbot.net/HIAL/</ref></note> What’s more, his analysis suggests
            that part of what makes DH so white (to paraphrase McPherson) is that <q>there’s a very clear bias against submissions by people
               with names non-standard to the US.</q><note>ibid.</note> Now, it is worth noting
            that a single year does not a trend make (although he sees stable numbers over three
            years with respect to gender) and that the ADHO conference is not necessarily
            representative of the entirety of digital humanities scholarship. Nevertheless, the
            questions we posed in the call for this issue about the presence of a masculinized
            research/tools track and a feminized pedagogy track, the elided histories of feminist
            intervention, and exclusionary cultures within DH are as urgent today as they were in
            2012 </p>
         <p>
            <title rend="quotes">Feminisms and DH</title> confronts a number of methodological and
            topical biases that continue to haunt the field according to Weingart’s analysis. Jamie
            Skye Bianco’s <title rend="quotes">Man and His Tool, Again?: Queer and Feminist Notes on
               Practices in the Digital Humanities and Object Orientations Everywhere</title> uses a
            performative mode, previously theorized in her 2012 <title rend="quotes">This Digital
               Humanities Which is Not One,</title> to critique heteropatriarchal biases in a
            textual studies dominated digital humanities. Her piece exemplifies the <quote
               rend="inline" source="#kember2013">socially engaged critical creativity</quote>
            advocated by feminist scholars like Sarah Kember and Joanna Zylenska; a thinking with
            and through the tools that we critique <ptr target="#kember2013"/>. Her piece and the
            companion teaching reflection by Nicole Starosielski push the boundaries of traditional
            academic argument by insisting that <q>creative critique</q> is central to how we
            communicate amongst ourselves as scholars and with and to our students. </p>
         <p>Equally critical, argues Roopika Risam, is intersectionality as <q>a lens for scholarship in the digital humanities [that] resists binary
               logic, encourages complex analysis, and foregrounds difference.</q> This is an
            important corrective that we have seen recently emerge in projects like the Digital
            Diversity Timeline, Amy Earhart’s Diverse Histories of DH, and Global Outlook DH to tell
            more diverse histories of digital humanities work and thereby imagine alternative
            futures. Risam draws on Sandra Harding’s work in feminist and postcolonial Science and
            Technology Studies (STS), to foreground the relationships between difference and
            technology. In addition to suggesting the value of alternative histories, Risam does the
            difficult work of charting theoretical foundations for alternative digital humanities
               <q>methods that advocate inclusion and critical
               analysis but are situated in the materiality of technologies.</q> In ways that
            blend the kind of theoretical and historiographic work of both Risam and Bianco,
            Gabrielle Dean’s <title rend="quotes">The Shock of the Familiar: Three Timelines about
               Gender and Technology in the Library</title> offers a set of provocations about not
            only the history of librarianship and information technology, but also about its
            possible futures. Like Bianco, Dean plays with argumentative form, drawing on the
            timeline as both a critical and speculative genre. Both Dean and Tanya Clement draw on
            Library and Information Science disciplines to push digital humanists to grapple with
            both the physical and epistemological sites of DH work, which is very often housed in
            libraries and archives either literary, metaphorically, or both.</p>
         <p>Clement’s <title rend="quotes">The Information Science Question in DH Feminism</title>
            brings the question of infrastructure and its situated relations to the fore
            specifically through Information Science and architectures and systems of knowledge.
            Like Bianco, Risam, and Losh, Clement is interested the ways that a feminist insistence
            on situated knowledge and <q>technologies of
               self-consciousness</q> draws attention to technocultures and their underlying
            epistemic commitments. Drawing on her own work on the Baroness von Freytag, Clement
            deftly demonstrates how tools and subject become entangled as she pursues the social
            text/body/network. The social body/network is central as well to Moya Bailey’s <q>#transform(ing)DH Writing and Research: An Autoethnography
               of Digital Humanities and Feminist Ethics.</q> Bailey further expands the
            question of how we communicate amongst ourselves when undertaking research by blurring
            the boundaries between the researcher and her <q>subjects.</q> Prioritizing
               <q>collaborative connections</q> in order to enact a praxis of care that she sees at
            work in Black trans women’s use of Twitter, Bailey’s autoethnography charts a different
            mode of scholarly engagement than that envisioned by standard protocols in the social
            sciences. </p>
         <p>Elizabeth Losh looks to feminist Media and Game Studies and STS to suggest that it is
            critical to move networks and power formations from ground to figure in feminist digital
            humanities. Citing the example of the Ludica collective (Celia Pearce, Jacki Morie,
            Tracy Fullerton and Janine Fron), she also imagines new ways for collaborative, communal
            feminist work to unfold within DH. Collaboration and social networks might be keywords
            for this special issue. Bailey and Losh both point us to scholarly practitioners who act
            as and within communities. Similar modalities have histories within scholarly and
            activist communities of women of color, trans, and queer folks. Work like that of the
            Crunk Feminist Collective (<ref target="http://crunkfeministcollective.tumblr.com/"
               >http://crunkfeministcollective.tumblr.com/</ref>), Electronic Disturbance Theater
            2.0/b.a.n.g lab (<ref target="http://bang.transreal.org/about/"
               >http://bang.transreal.org/about/</ref>), the LatiNegrxs Project (<ref
               target="http://lati-negros.tumblr.com/">http://lati-negros.tumblr.com/</ref>) and
            GO::DH (<ref target="http://www.globaloutlookdh.org/"
               >http://www.globaloutlookdh.org/</ref> demonstrate that interdisciplinary and
            inclusive collaborative communities have long been present if not centered in digital
            humanities work. They also illuminate how powerful community-driven mixed-media
            scholarship can be — both as models of scholarly practice and as arguments that
            illuminate technologies and practices of oppression. </p>
         <p>Constance Crompton, Ray Siemens, Alyssa Arbuckle, and the DMSEG team use <title
               rend="quotes">Enlisting 'Vertues Noble &amp; Excelent' Across Scholarly Cultures:
               Digital Collaboration and the Social Edition</title> to reflect on the affordances
            and limitations of social editing for the Devonshire Manuscript, a text that is itself
            deeply social and networked. The team sought to create an inclusive, visible editorial
            process as a way of prioritizing the processes of editing and social networking over a
            traditional model of consumption. In this they are perhaps the most conventional of all
            of the projects discussed here, in so far as they are producing a digital edition of an
            early modern text. But their efforts to expand beyond traditional scholarly platforms
            and communities place their work firmly in line with the other feminist interventions in
            this special issue. These efforts were repaid with insights on the ways that wiki
            platforms might enact social support functions akin to early modern marginalia and, as
            if responding to Losh and Clement, they foreground their own feminist epistemological
            commitments through both their processes and their platform. But they also had to
            grapple with the presence of trolls in their open edition, making it clear that digital
            platforms are always <q>contact zones</q> of the kind discussed by Mary Louis Pratt <ptr
               target="#pratt1991"/>. Spaces where difference, dissensus, and even abuse can mingle
            in the social text.</p>
         <p>I began this introduction by invoking the analogy of long-exposure photography, which
            produces surreal images in part because it obscures differences across time. Streaky
            starry night images preserve the traces of celestial bodies that appear at the beginning
            of an evening, but are no longer visible by morning. We don’t have a good equivalent of
            this in academic publishing. The contributors to this volume are doing the hard work of
            bringing feminist theories and practice together, each in her/their own way and their
            important work is preserved here in this issue. Process — the additions, deletions,
            revisions evoked by the social edition of the Devonshire Manuscript project — is far
            less visible. Perhaps this is a way in which the special issue is more surreal that the
            long-exposure photograph; in advancing itself as a snapshot it erases the long arc,
            privileging just the final product. Without this introduction, <title rend="quotes"
               >Feminisms and DH</title> could well appear to be the labor of a single issue editor
            when it was inaugurated by two and significantly supported by <title rend="italic"
               >DHQ</title> staff. It could look like a collection of eleven authors across eight
            pieces, instead of an issue that contains within it the traces and published work of
            seventeen authors across fourteen pieces.</p>
         <p>As feminist theory has long known, our work is embodied and this embodiment manifests in
            this issue as institutional and professional limits, geographic moves, pregnancies,
            illnesses, and self-determining redirections. In some instances this has left gaps in
            the final product – spaces where voices were to be heard, but aren’t for a variety of
            reasons. These absent voices register for me as faded streaks in the long exposure
            image. Harris and I invited more experimental pieces for an <q>assemblage</q> section in
            our original call, which is realized in Bailey, Bianco, and Dean’s pieces but was
            envisioned to be larger and more experimental still. A vibrant discussion of the
            distance between the representation of women in the profession and feminist agendas is
            absent and much needed. Engagement with queer theories and praxis are similarly limited
            despite the great work being done in venues like <ref
               target="http://adanewmedia.org/issues/issue-archives/issue5/"><title rend="italic"
                  >ada: the journal of gender, new media, and technology</title></ref> (see for
            example issue #5 on Queer Feminist Media Praxis).</p>
         <p>The pieces herein are working to redefine DH and they all point to larger, often
            marginalized fields of creative and critical work. Bailey and Rissam’s articles function
            as entrée points to the work being done by women and feminists of color both in the U.S.
            and internationally that has too often had to find home outside of DH as such but is
            nevertheless transforming both how scholarship is done and on what terms. Crompton et
            al.’s chapter similarly points to the rich vein of work being done and still to be done
            on the various affordances and risks of social media and open platforms for feminist
            digital production and scholarship. As suggested by Bianco, Dean, and Clement, a more
            robust theorization of feminist digital humanities requires understanding the ways in
            which academic structures subsume feminist innovation and critique, appropriating both
            the insights and power of subversive work. Finally, as nearly every piece herein
            demonstrates, if we are to have a more just feminist digital humanities, we must attend
            to the ways that academic practices and digital spaces and tools are being leveraged by
            those with power — very often to limit marginalized people and at the most extreme in
            order to consume or promote violence against women, people of color, and trans people. </p>
         <p>Gaps and silences aren’t unique to this special issue – there are always declined
            invitations, rejected articles, pieces withdrawn or delayed or never written – but
            having had the privilege of watching the process, they strike me as important traces.
            Affect, another feminist keyword, was everywhere present in struggles over and in
            reviews, anxieties about timelines, celebrations of new directions, and the mourning of
            losses. Anger, frustration, sorrow, and joy are co-present on these pages and in the
            margins of this issue, and yet are nearly absent from the reader’s perspective. From the
            privileged position of editor, I am acutely aware of how disciplinary, technical, and
            personal constraints have shaped this volume.</p>
         <p>I draw attention to this as a way of testifying obliquely to the challenges that
            continue to shape feminist engagements within digital humanities (probably within
            academia more generally as well). I want to observe openly that this volume is shaped in
            ways that may well be inarticulable but are at the heart of feminist commitments to
            seeing knowledge production as material, embodied, affective, situated, and labor. bell
            hooks writes about citing gaps in archives and histories as a way to <quote
               rend="inline" source="#hooks2004">let the reader know that something has been
               missed</quote> and I want to mark that the pressures that come to bear on women’s
            bodies, lives, and work mean that there are known gaps here <ptr target="#hooks2004"/>.
            One of the great insights, I think, of the contributions to this volume is that there
            are also many unknown gaps and that intersectional, interdisciplinary, and multimodal
            work is essential to that process of seeing what we do not yet know is missing. Ellen
            Rooney argues that <soCalled>feminist address</soCalled> is a performative, critical act
            that creates constituencies and brings feminist positions into being – it is a
            generative, poetic process through which alternative futures are created <ptr
               target="#rooney2006"/>. Herein are eight different modes of feminist address and they
            are powerful but partial beginnings.</p>
         <p>- Jacqueline Wernimont</p>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label="Bourg and Sadler 2015" xml:id="bourg2015">Chris Bourg and Bess Sadler,
                  <title rend="quotes">Feminism and the Future of Library Discovery</title>
               <title rend="italic">code{4}lib</title> Issue 28 (April), 2015. Stable URL: <ref
                  target="http://journal.code4lib.org/articles/10425"
                  >http://journal.code4lib.org/articles/10425</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="hooks 2004" xml:id="hooks2004">bell hooks, <title rend="quotes">Choosing
                  the Margin as a Space of Radical Openness,</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Feminist Standpoint Theory Reader: Intellectual and
                  Political Controversies</title>, Sandra G. Harding (ed.), (Routledge, 2004),
               154.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Kember and Zylinska 2013" xml:id="kember2013"> Sarah Kember and Joanna
               Zylinska, <title rend="italic">Life After New Media</title> (MIT, 2013), 177.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Pratt 1991" xml:id="pratt1991"> Mary Louise Pratt <title rend="quotes">Arts
                  of the Contact Zone,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Profession</title> (1991), pp. 33-40. Published by: Modern
               Language Association. Stable URL: <ref target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/25595469"
                  >http://www.jstor.org/stable/25595469</ref></bibl>
            <bibl label="Rooney 2006" xml:id="rooney2006">Ellen Rooney, <title rend="quotes"
                  >Introduction,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Cambridge Companion to Feminist Literary Theory</title>
               (Cambridge, 2006), 16.</bibl>
         </listBibl>

      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
