<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
	xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
	xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
				<title type="article" xml:lang="en">Cross-codex Learning for Reliable Scribe Identification in Medieval
					Manuscripts</title>
				<!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Julius <dhq:family>Weißmann</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7086-941X</idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>Media and Digital Technologies, St. Pölten University of Applied Sciences</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>weissmann.julius@gmail.com</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Julius Weißmann, is a Data Scientist at Destatis (Germany). Already in his bachelor’s program at the
							Goethe University, Frankfurt am Main (2015 – 2019), he was interested in big data and implemented in his
							thesis deep neural networks in archaeological image detection. In his Digital Humanities master at the
							Johannes Gutenberg-University Mainz (2019 – 2022), he focused on Machine learning and researched in his
							thesis on deep neural networks in scribe identification. He then worked as a junior researcher at the
							University of St. Pölten University of Applied Sciences.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Markus <dhq:family>Seidl</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7966-3602</idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>Media and Digital Technologies, St. Pölten University of Applied Sciences</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>markus.seidl@fhstp.ac.at</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Markus Seidl is an expert for Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition and professor at the St. Pölten
							University of Applied Sciences. He has gained extensive experience in scientific collaboration with other
							disciplines in various Digital Heritage projects, e.g. from 2010-2016 he was working intensively with an
							international group of archaeologists on digital documentation and analysis methods for rock art. The
							collaboration was awarded the Europa Nostra award for Cultural Heritage 2016. Currently Markus is working
							on Scribe identification in mediaeval manuscripts. In a second strand of scientific work, Markus Seidl
							works on digital artifacts that enhance the museum experience.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Anya <dhq:family>Dietrich</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8564-1055</idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>MEG Unit, Brain Imaging Center</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>a.dietrich@med.uni-frankfurt.de</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Anya Dietrich is a Neuroscientist, Biologist and Laboratory Manager in Frankfurt am Main, Germany. In her
							doctoral thesis, she researched on the neurobiological underpinnings of the interaction of emotion and
							cognition. She was trained as a neurobiologist and cognitive neuroscientist at the Ernst Strüngmann
							Institute, Frankfurt, the Georg-August University, Göttingen and the University of Bayreuth, Germany.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Martin <dhq:family>Haltrich</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2585-7188</idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>Library, Klosterneuburg Abbey</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>m.haltrich@stift-klosterneuburg.at</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Martin Haltrich studied German Studies and History at the University of Vienna. His doctoral thesis dealt
							with late-medieval writing and practices of administration in the Chartusian monastery of Gaming (Lower
							Austria). He worked at the Department of Palaeography and Codicology at the Austrian Academy of Sciences
							and was librarian and archivist at the monastery in Zwettl. At present he is head of the library in
							Klosterneuburg Abbey. His research involve paleographical and codicological analyses of medieval
							manuscripts and late medieval administrative source material. Currently he is interested in the emergence
							of knowledge spaces in high medieval Central European monasteries.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
				<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
				<!--This information will be completed at publication-->
				<idno type="DHQarticle-id">000738<!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
				<idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
				<idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
				<date/>
				<dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
				<availability status="CC-BY-ND">
					<!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
					<cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>This is the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
					<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en" extent="original"/>
				<!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
					<!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
					<!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
					<term corresp="#machine_learning"/>
					<term corresp="#cs"/>
					<term corresp="#data_analytics"/>
					<term corresp="#manuscripts"/>
					<term corresp="#medieval"/>
					<term corresp="#digital_libraries"/>
					<term corresp="#history"/>
					<term corresp="#images"/>
					<term corresp="#informatics"/>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
					<!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
					<list type="simple">
						<item>scribe identification</item>
						<item>deep learning</item>
						<item>computer vision</item>
						<item>Carolingian miniscule</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
			<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
					target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000738/000738.xml"
					>GitHub</ref>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en" type="original">
		<front>
			<dhq:abstract>
				<p>Historic scribe identification is a substantial task for obtaining information about the past. Uniform script
					styles, such as the Carolingian minuscule, make it a difficult task for classification to focus on meaningful
					features. Therefore, we demonstrate in this paper the importance of cross-codex training data for CNN based
					text-independent off-line scribe identification, to overcome codex dependent overfitting. We report three main
					findings: First, we found that preprocessing with masked grayscale images instead of RGB images clearly
					increased the F1-score of the classification results. Second, we trained different neural networks on our
					complex data, validating time and accuracy differences in order to define the most reliable network
					architecture. With AlexNet, the network with the best trade-off between F1-score and time, we achieved for
					individual classes F1-scores of up to 0,96 on line level and up to 1.0 on page level in classification. Third,
					we could replicate the finding that the CNN output can be further improved by implementing a reject option,
					giving more stable results. We present the results on our large scale open source dataset – the Codex
					Claustroneoburgensis database (CCl-DB) – containing a significant number of writings from different scribes in
					several codices. We demonstrate for the first time on a dataset with such a variety of codices that
					paleographic decisions can be reproduced automatically and precisely with CNNs. This gives manifold new and
					fast possibilities for paleographers to gain insights into unlabeled material, but also to develop further
					hypotheses.</p>
			</dhq:abstract>
			<dhq:teaser>
				<!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
				<p>Unveiling the secrets of the monastery library with AI based technology! Our latest research explores the
					power of cross-codex learning for reliable scribe identification in medieval manuscripts.</p>
			</dhq:teaser>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div>
				<head>1 Introduction</head>
				<p>In recent years, there has been a notable surge in the digitization of historical documents, allowing for
					machine processing and providing unprecedented opportunities for researchers, including palaeographers. A
					pivotal challenge lies in the identification of scribes, recognizing the hands responsible for manuscript
					creation. However, this task is inherently time-intensive for researchers like palaeographers and
					codicologists, constraining its scope.</p>
				<p>Simultaneously, the differentiation and recognition of scribal hands represent an essential methodology. This
					capability facilitates the determination of dates, specific scribal hands, or the geographic origins, enabling
					the formulation of insights into the trajectories of medieval scribes across diverse monasteries and
					scriptoria. Such information contributes significantly to our understanding of dating, place of origin, and
					insights into the scribes themselves and their organizational structures <ptr target="#kluge2019"/>, <ptr
						target="#landau2004"/>, <ptr target="#powitz2007"/>.</p>
				<p>In European scriptoria the script <term>Carolingian minuscule</term> was used until the second half of 12th
					century for writing and copying books (codices). This Latin script was the first standardized script in the
					medieval period. Although codices typically lack specific notations regarding which scribe wrote particular
					sections, the identification of scribes across various codices is invaluable for understanding scriptoria
					organization and the movement of codices and scribes between monasteries.</p>
				<p>The historic auxiliary science of paleography addresses, among other aspects, the identification of scribes
					based on distinct, scribe-typical features in their writing. However, given the sheer volume of codex pages,
					this task remains tedious and time-consuming, demanding a high level of domain expertise. Automation through
					machines holds promise for expediting and enhancing the assignment of scribal hands, thereby relieving
					palaeographers from laborious and repetitive tasks, making the process faster and more comprehensive.</p>
				<p>For instance, the library of Stift Klosterneurburg, amassed over the past 900 years, boasting nearly 300,000
					copies. This remarkable collection, dating back to the 12th century, exemplifies the potential of automated
					techniques in efficiently identifying scribes within the vast repository of codex pages <ptr
						target="#haltich2014"/>.</p>
				<p>Consequently, only a limited amount of medieval codices has been investigated with a focus on scribe
					identification. The automation utilizing pattern recognition and machine learning allows for larger amounts of
					material. However, to the best of our knowledge data of most automation-based approaches are either limited to
					even only one <ptr target="#destefano_etal2011"/>, <ptr target="#cilia_etal2020a"/>, <ptr
						target="#cilia_etal2020b"/> or a few different codices or include material from way larger time periods
					(e.g. <ptr target="#fiel_etal2017"/>, <ptr target="#chammas_etal2020"/>).</p>
				<p>To overcome these shortcomings, we investigate automated scribe identification on a large dataset we
					compiled: The CCl-DB <ptr target="#seidl_etal2014"/>. This dataset contains 51 individual codices with a total
					amount of 17071 pages. These codices originate from the library of Klosterneuburg Abbey and were written in
					the late 12th century in Carolingian minuscule <ptr target="#schneider2014"/>, <ptr target="#bischoff2004"/>.
					The scarcity of information about the scribes underscores the significant value of this new dataset and its
					associated processing capabilities.</p>
				<p>We are aiming to answer two central questions:<list type="ordered">
						<item>Can the scribe assignments coming from decades of work by paleographic experts <ptr
								target="#haidinger1983"/>, <ptr target="#haidinger1991"/>, <ptr target="#lackner2012"/> be successfully
							modelled and predicted?</item>
						<item>If so, can we use the models to predict scribes for codex pages that have unclear scribe assignments
							or no scribe assignments at all?</item>
					</list>A substantial potential data specific risk seen in work by others that could render our work useless is
					that we could model not only script specific features but also book specific features such as the parchment
					and page margins. To mitigate this risk, we identified scribes that have been found in at least 3 codices. The
					subset we use contains 25200<note>A typical single column page contains 31 or 32 lines. The vast majority of
						our books is in single column layout, hence we can roughly estimate that the 25200 lines correspond to 800
						pages.</note> random lines uniformly distributed over 7 scribes in 31 different historic codices, in order
					to train the models to recognize the scribe without codex specific features.</p>
				<p>In the last decade, convolutional neural networks<note>Recently, artificial neural networks have demonstrated
						remarkable efficiency in handling unstructured data, including images, text, and speech. Convolutional
						Neural Networks (CNNs), as a specialized architecture, have proven highly beneficial in image processing by
						adeptly learning spatial hierarchies of features.</note> (CNNs) have proven to efficiently classify writers
					in modern and historic context and other tasks such as segmentation <ptr target="#oliveira_etal2018"/>,
					optical character recognition <ptr target="#islam_etal2016"/>, and writer identification <ptr
						target="#xing_etal2016"/>, <ptr target="#destefano_etal2011"/>.</p>
				<p>For our classification model we compared several general purpose object and concept detection CNNs as well as
					specific architectures for scribe identification (<ref target="#table03">see Table 3</ref>). Surprisingly, the
					classic AlexNet <ptr target="#krizhevsky_etal2012"/> provided the best trade-off between F1-score and time. We
					show that we can distinguish the scribes described by paleographic experts and even identify potential wrong
					scribe assignments. Furthermore, in combination with the reject option introduced by Cilia et al. (<ref
						target="#cilia_etal2020a">2020a</ref>) we demonstrate that we can reliably predict the scribes for codices
					with unclear or missing scribe assignments.</p>
				<figure xml:id="figure01">
					<head>Examples from the CCl-DB <ptr target="#seidl_etal2014"/> of three lines of different codices from one
						scribe. The ink and parchment appearance differs, although it’s written from the same scribe (class A 30)
							<ptr target="#haidinger1991"/>, <ptr target="#lackner2012"/>. Top: CCl 206, middle: CCl 197, bottom: CCl
						217.</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
					<figDesc>Three differing lines of handwritten Carolingian miniscule</figDesc>
				</figure>
				<p>In this paper, we focus on three major issues:</p>
				<list type="unordered">
					<item>the importance of cross-codex based training data for automatic scribe identification</item>
					<item>the feasibility of training a model based on scribe assignments by the paleographers Haidinger (<ref
							target="#haidinger2010">2010</ref>, <ref target="#haidinger1983">1983</ref>, <ref target="#haidinger1991"
							>1991</ref>) and Lackner (<ref target="#lackner2012">2012</ref>)</item>
					<item>the necessity of exploiting the confidence in scribe predictions to reveal uncertainties in the
						dataset.</item>
				</list>
				<p>The latter is a central requirement, as there is no objective ground truth for scribe assignments for the
					medieval codices we are using. Our contribution in this paper is threefold:</p>
				<p>Firstly, we demonstrate the necessity of book independent training of scribe models, which has been neglected
					in other studies. Secondly, we demonstrate that contrary to the results of Xing and Qiao (<ref
						target="#xing_etal2016">2016</ref>) standard architectures are sufficiently accurate to reliably identify
					medieval scribes in a classification pipeline. Thirdly, our work consequently facilitates comprehensive and
					convincing studies on large datasets and allows new insights into the historic monastic life and the
					relationships between the monasteries.<note>The code for the experiments is publicly accessible: <ref
							target="https://gitlab.rlp.net/studiengang-digitale-methodik/abschlussarbeiten/ma-repo/-/tree/main/experiments"
							>https://gitlab.rlp.net/studiengang-digitale-methodik/abschlussarbeiten/ma-repo/-/tree/main/experiments</ref></note>
				</p>
				<p>The paper is structured as follows: after an overview about related work in <ref target="#section02">Section
						2</ref> we outline the dataset in <ref target="#section03">Section 3</ref>. In <ref target="#section04"
						>Section 4</ref> we explain the applied methods for scribe identification. We show and discuss the results
					in <ref target="#section05">Section 5</ref> and finally conclude the paper in <ref target="#section06">Section
						6</ref>.</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="section02">
				<head>2 Related work</head>
				<p>Computer-aided historic handwritten document analysis includes segmentation, text recognition, dating and
					writer identification as well as verification. Segmentation usually separates the written or drawn content
					from the carrier material (such as parchment or paper) <ptr target="#oliveira_etal2018"/>, <ptr
						target="#tensmeyer_etal2017"/>. Based on this, a possible next step is handwritten text recognition (HTR)
						<ptr target="#chammas_etal2018"/>. Either the segments or the written content alone or a combination of both
					modalities allow further investigations like dating, writer verification <ptr target="#shaikh_etal2020"/>,
						<ptr target="#dey_etal2017"/> and identification <ptr target="#chammas_etal2020"/>, <ptr
						target="#xing_etal2016"/>, <ptr target="#fiel_etal2017"/>.</p>
				<p>Different processes for scribe identification can be used, such as text-dependent and text-independent.
					Text-dependent <ptr target="#said_etal1998"/> methods allow identifying the writer on particular characters or
					words, whereas text-independent <ptr target="#yang_etal2016"/> approaches can be applied on new unseen
					content. Two kinds of handwritten text patterns can be used: on-line and offline writer identification.
					On-line <ptr target="#yang_etal2016"/> systems work with time series of the formation process, while off-line
						<ptr target="#xing_etal2016"/> solutions are limited to the images of the written text document.</p>
				<p>Writer identification is a strong topic in document analysis and therefore much discussed. In the last years,
					a variety of solutions have been provided. These methods can be grouped into codebook-based and codebook-free
					methods. Codebook-based refer to a codebook that serves as a background model. This model is based on
					statistical features like in <ptr target="#maaten_etal2005"/>. The codebook-free methods include for example
					the width of ink traces, which was used from Brink et al. (<ref target="#brink_etal2012">2021</ref>) to
					predict the writer in medieval and modern handwritten documents, or the hinge feature provided by <ptr
						target="#he_etal2014"/> in order to identify writers in handwritten English text in the IAM-dataset <ptr
						target="#marti_etal2002"/>. Further, there have been strong results in using the Scale-Invariant Feature
					Transform (SIFT) for writer identification <ptr target="#xiong_etal2015"/>, <ptr target="#fiel_etal2012"/>,
						<ptr target="#wu_etal2014"/>.</p>
				<p>In recent years, the number of Deep Learning<note>Deep learning is a subset of machine learning that involves
						neural networks with multiple layers (deep neural networks) to model and process complex patterns in
						data.</note> (DL) based studies in document analysis increased drastically <ptr target="#chammas_etal2020"
					/>, <ptr target="#cilia_etal2020b"/>, <ptr target="#xing_etal2016"/>. As mentioned in the introduction, the
					interest in using such techniques is due to their ability to provide powerful state-of-the-art solutions in an
					efficient and reliable way. During the training, the DL model learns the best fitting features for the
					classification. Therefore, no handcrafted features are required.</p>
				<p>In Fiel and Sablatnig (<ref target="#fiel_etal2015">2015</ref>) presented the strong performance of CNN’s for
					scribe identification on modern data sets.</p>
				<p>Xing and Qiao (<ref target="#xing_etal2016">2016</ref>) performed a writer identification on the modern IAM
					and the HWDB1.1 dataset. They developed a special multi-stream CNN architecture based on AlexNet and
					outperformed previous approaches on handcrafted features.</p>
				<table xml:id="table01">
					<head>Subset of the CCl-DB. The dataset for our experiments is a subset of the seven common scribes of the
						CCl-DB <ptr target="#seidl_etal2014"/>. We generated a dataset, with two groups of codices – the <q>Training
							Codices</q> and the <q>Separate Codices</q>. From the <q>Training Codices</q> we choose for every class
						3600 random lines, that are uniformly distributed over all books. In total these are 25200 lines that are
						separated into training, validation and test data (Test A) according to the ratio of 60%, 20% and 20%
						respectively. The separate books are used for an extra test set Test B. There are up to 3000 lines of one
						class, depending on the codex-size.</head>
					<row role="label">
						<cell rows="2">Class</cell>
						<cell cols="3">Training codices (Test A and Test B)</cell>
						<cell cols="3">Separate codices (Test B only)</cell>
					</row>
					<row role="label">
						<cell>Lines per codex</cell>
						<cell>#Codices</cell>
						<cell>Codices</cell>
						<cell>Lines per codex</cell>
						<cell>#Codices</cell>
						<cell>Codices</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell role="label">A 30</cell>
						<cell>450</cell>
						<cell>8</cell>
						<cell>30, 31, 197, 206, 226, 246, 256, 257</cell>
						<cell>1500</cell>
						<cell>2</cell>
						<cell>32217</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell role="label">A 259</cell>
						<cell>1200</cell>
						<cell>3</cell>
						<cell>209, 259, 949</cell>
						<cell>1754</cell>
						<cell>1</cell>
						<cell>706</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell role="label">B 259</cell>
						<cell>720</cell>
						<cell>5</cell>
						<cell>259, 622, 706, 212, 671</cell>
						<cell>1439</cell>
						<cell>1</cell>
						<cell>246</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell role="label">A 20</cell>
						<cell>1200</cell>
						<cell>3</cell>
						<cell>21, 28, 39</cell>
						<cell>3000</cell>
						<cell>1</cell>
						<cell>20</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell role="label">B 20</cell>
						<cell>900</cell>
						<cell>4</cell>
						<cell>22, 195, 216, 764</cell>
						<cell>119</cell>
						<cell>1</cell>
						<cell>20</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell role="label">A 215</cell>
						<cell>1200</cell>
						<cell>3</cell>
						<cell>215, 219, 703</cell>
						<cell>3000</cell>
						<cell>1</cell>
						<cell>245</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell role="label">A 258</cell>
						<cell>1800</cell>
						<cell>2</cell>
						<cell>258, 707</cell>
						<cell>3000</cell>
						<cell>1</cell>
						<cell>203</cell>
					</row>
				</table>
				<p>Cilia et al. (<ref target="#cilia_etal2020a">2020a</ref>) demonstrated a comparison between deep learning and
					handcrafted features on the Avila Bible that is written in <term>Carolingian minuscule</term>. These classical
					features, as Cilia et al. call them, are handcrafted features, that have been developed in cooperation with
					paleographers. The results of their studies emphasize the effectiveness of deep learning features in contrast
					to the handcrafted features.</p>
				<p>In our research, we investigate <term>scribe</term> identification in contrast to <emph>writer</emph>
					identification, since the specific individual of the writing is generally not known for our material. Scribe
					identification is discussed in a medieval context only in a very limited range, like at the International
					Conference on Document Analysis and Recognition (ICDAR) competitions <ptr target="#fiel_etal2017"/> or in
					conjunction with the Avila bible <ptr target="#cilia_etal2020a"/>. However, the aforementioned datasets are of
					limited use for our goals. The Avila bible is literally only one codex and consequently does not allow
					cross-codex scribe identification. The datasets used in the historical ICDAR competitions <ptr
						target="#fiel_etal2017"/>, <ptr target="#christlein_etal2019"/> span time periods of many centuries, and
					hence include different scripts and carrier materials. Thus, scribe identification in the large amounts of
					medieval codices in Europe’s libraries is still a challenge and our approach allows novel insights as it
					focuses on a wide range of codices of several scribes in the short period of the late 12th century.</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="section03">
				<head>3 Dataset</head>
				<p>We perform experiments on a subset (<ref target="#table01">see Table 1</ref>) of seven scribes provided by
					the CCl-DB <ptr target="#seidl_etal2014"/>. We selected the scribes which have contributed to as many books as
					possible to allow cross-codex evaluation. Samples in the dataset were handwritten on parchment in
						<term>Carolingian minuscule</term> (see <ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref> and <ref target="#figure02"
						>Figure 2</ref>) on one- and two-column pages. These codices have been written down in the scriptorium of
					Klosterneuburg in the last third of the 12th century. The data is provided by the Scribe ID AI<note>See: <ref
							target="https://research.fhstp.ac.at/en/projects/scribe-id-ai"
							>https://research.fhstp.ac.at/en/projects/scribe-id-ai</ref>
					</note> project and has been labelled by paleographic experts based on the activity of the paleographers
					Haidinger (<ref target="#haidinger2010">2010</ref>, <ref target="#haidinger1983">1983</ref>, <ref
						target="#haidinger1991">1991</ref>) and Lackner (<ref target="#lackner2012">2012</ref>). 52 labelled codices
					are provided in the CCl-DB. This database enables new possibilities within document analysis and especially in
					handwriting recognition.</p>
				<figure xml:id="figure02">
					<head>Image data of the CCl-DB <ptr target="#seidl_etal2014"/> (CCl 20, S. 3r, hand A 20 <ptr
							target="#haidinger1983"/>). The CCl-DB provides the codices page by page (left) and on line-level
						(right-top). The line-level images are produced automatically by the segmentation of Transkribus <ptr
							target="#kahle_etal2017"/>. The neural network classification works with squared images, therefore we
						cropped the line images into squares and resized them into the network input size.</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpeg"/>
					<figDesc>A page of text divided into lines, then into individual glyphs</figDesc>
				</figure>
				<p>To the best of our knowledge, there is no comparable database available that provides the workings of many
					medieval scribes in various codices and in such a short period of time.</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="section04">
				<head>4 Methods for Scribe Identification</head>
				<p>This section will introduce the pipeline of our line-based scribe identification approach. The pipeline is
					grouped into three main parts (<ref target="#figure03">see Figure 3</ref>). In the first part – the image
					preprocessing – we focus on providing the following network input images that are reduced to their scribe
					specific information. The second part presents the neural network classification approach. Here we compare
					different CNNs as image classifiers for scribe identification. Finally, the third part covers the
					post-processing which generates the final score. This is where we introduce the computation of the line score
					and the reject option – a method to improve the prediction. All parts will be detailed in the following.</p>
				<div>
					<head>4.1 Image preprocessing</head>
					<p>The dataset contains not only the codex pages, but also the extracted lines. The line data is usually
						correctly extracted from the pages, however there are some small snippets with no noticeable content in the
						dataset. As image lines are generally of wide aspect ratio, we use a simple heuristic <formula
							notation="tex" rend="inline">\(\text{width}/\text{height}\leq5\)</formula> to skip these uninformative
						snippets already in the step of preprocessing.</p>
					<figure xml:id="figure03">
						<head>Overall procedure of the proposed scribe recognition system. The rounded boxes symbolize data, whereas
							the angular boxes show processes.</head>
						<graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpeg"/>
						<figDesc>Flowchart of image processing steps resulting in page and line scores</figDesc>
					</figure>
					<p>For studying the optimal input image data we generated grayscale images and masked grayscale images
						additionally to the RGB data (<ref target="#figure04">see Figure 4</ref>). When we masked<note>Image masking
							is a technique of selectively concealing or revealing specific portions of an image. In this example,
							masking is done by removing the parchment/background in the image, to focus the model's attention on the
							features of the handwriting.</note> the images we followed the example of De Stefano et al. (<ref
							target="#destefano_etal2018">2018</ref>). We applied their fixed threshold value, equal to 135, to
						separate the ink and the parchment of the grayscale images (<ref target="#figure04">see Figure 4</ref>). In
						related work <ptr target="#cilia_etal2020a"/>, <ptr target="#fiel_etal2017"/>, <ptr target="#fiel_etal2015"
						/>, <ptr target="#cloppet_etal2016"/>, binarization is often applied to text images. However, since our
						masking does not work reliably enough to produce meaningful binarization, we omit this step in this
						work.</p>
					<figure xml:id="figure04">
						<head>Example for the preprocessing (CCl 212, S. 1r, hand B 259 <ptr target="#lackner2012"/>). The lines of
							the CCl-DB <ptr target="#seidl_etal2014"/> are provided as RGB images (top). From these, we converted the
							images to grayscale (middle). The masked grayscaled images are produced by removing the background from
							the ink.</head>
						<graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpeg"/>
						<figDesc>The three-step preprocessing sequence for scribe identification</figDesc>
					</figure>
					<p>As already mentioned, the lines of the CCl-DB are of different aspect ratio, but the networks we
						implemented are working with a fixed input size. In order to handle the different lengths of the lines, we
						followed the patch scanning strategy of Xing and Qiao (<ref target="#xing_etal2016">2016</ref>). First, the
						images have been resized in height to the specific network input image height, while maintaining the aspect
						ratio of the line. Afterwards, we cropped the lines from left to right into patches (<ref target="#figure02"
							>see Figure 2</ref>). This sliding window comprises the network specific input image width. Due to the
						large dataset (<ref target="#table01">see Table 1</ref>), there is no need for data augmentation.<note>Data
							augmentation can be used to enlarge the dataset. In image classification it involves applying various
							transformations (such as rotation, flipping, and scaling) to the existing training dataset to create
							additional diverse samples, enhancing the model's ability to generalize to different variations of the
							input images.</note> Hence, we generated patches with no overlap. Only one overlap occurs at the last
						image of each line, as the last patch of the line is generated by positioning the sliding window at the end
						of the line. Finally, we scaled and normalized the patches.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>4.2 Patch level classification</head>
					<p>Xing and Qiao (<ref target="#xing_etal2016">2016</ref>) achieved high identification accuracies with their
						customized CNN’s on the line level data of the IAM <ptr target="#marti_etal2002"/> dataset. They optimized
						AlexNet to the task of writer identification on the IAM dataset and denoted the architecture Half
						DeepWriter. Next, they developed the DeepWriter architecture, which is an improvement of Half DeepWriter
						that enables the computation of two sequential image patches in a single pass with a multi-stream
						architecture. Xing and Qiao showed that DeepWriter produces the best results on the line level data of the
						IAM dataset. Therefore, we implemented these three auspicious architectures as per description of Xing and
						Qiao (<ref target="#xing_etal2016">2016</ref>), when we tested the potential of preprocessed images on our
						data (<ref target="#table01">see Table 1</ref>).</p>
					<p>Additionally, we compared several other general-purpose object and concept detection architectures in our
						study to find the best one suited to our specific data. For this purpose, we used models provided by
						Torchvision <ptr target="#marcel_etal2010"/> (<ref target="#table03">see Table 3</ref>) and only adapted the
						input layer to the grayscale images and the output layer to the seven classes.</p>
					<p>As shown in different studies, pre-training and fine-tuning a CNN can lead to better results <ptr
							target="#xing_etal2016"/> , <ptr target="#studer_etal2019"/>. Xing and Qiao (<ref target="#xing_etal2016"
							>2016</ref>) demonstrated this on the IAM <ptr target="#marti_etal2002"/> and the HWDB <ptr
							target="#liu_etal2011"/> dataset. Therefore, we trained the described models on the IAM dataset,
						fine-tuned them on our data and compared the results with the from scratch trained weights.</p>
					<p>The models have been trained with a batch size of 32 over 10 epochs with a learning rate of <formula
							notation="tex" rend="inline">\(1∗10^{−5}\)</formula> on ADAM. The error was calculated with the cross
						entropy. Over all ten epochs, the instance of the model that performed best on the validation data has been
						saved for the next steps of the experiments.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>4.3 Postprocessing</head>
					<p>We pursue a patch, line and page level classification, but as already described, the network classification
						is on patch level. To compute the line and page score, we follow the example of Xing and Qiao (<ref
							target="#xing_etal2016">2016</ref>). They calculate the final score vector <formula notation="tex"
							rend="inline">\(f_i\)</formula> for the <formula notation="tex" rend="inline">\(j^{th}\)</formula> writer,
						of all patches <formula notation="tex" rend="inline">\(N\)</formula> of one line: <formula notation="tex"
							rend="inline">\(f_i=\frac{1}{N}\sum{^N_{i=1}}f_{ij}\)</formula>. This averaged Softmax output serves as
						the basis for the final step of the post-processing – the reject option.</p>
					<p>Cilia et al. (<ref target="#cilia_etal2020a">2020a</ref>) proposed the reject option to generate more
						reliable results for the writer identification on the Avila bible. They showed that sometimes it is better
						to withdraw a precarious decision than accepting all predictions. In such a case, they reject the prediction
						with the reject option.</p>
					<p>We used the line score as a probability distribution to check the probabilities for all writers. As Cilia
						et al. explained, the error-reject curve shows the impact of the reject rate to the wrong predictions and
						allows finding the optimal threshold for rejecting a prediction. Our reject rate is given by the line score
						of one writer. The reject rate corresponds to the wrong predictions.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="section05">
				<head>5 Results</head>
				<p>The purpose of this study was to train a model that classifies reliable and efficiently scribes in
					cross-codex data. We want to enable the automatic continuation of the work of paleography experts following
					their example, in order to allow research in large scale. In this study we would like to find a model that is
					not only reliable but also fast in processing, as it is the basis for research on active learning.</p>
				<p>In <ref target="#table02">Table 2</ref> we show the importance of cross-codex test data and the risk of
					overfitting.</p>
				<p>In the evaluation of our scribe classification pipeline, we found: <list type="ordered">
						<item>Image preprocessing plays a key role in cross-codex scribe identification. In comparison to RGB
							images, masked grayscale images roughly doubled the F1-score in the classification task.</item>
						<item>Further, we showed that AlexNet provides very fast, and among the most reliable predictions in
							classifying the scribes of our data set.</item>
						<item>Contrary to expectations, pre-training the network on the IAM database leads to worse results, which
							is why we omitted this step.</item>
					</list></p>
				<p>Applying the best fitting trained model, it turned out that it is very effective and even indicates incorrect
					data.</p>
				<p>Moreover, we introduce the reject option on our dataset in order to get rid of precarious classifications and
					found that it underlines the results.</p>
				<p>Finally, we deployed the pipeline to processes open paleographic topics.</p>
				<div>
					<head>5.1 Cross-codex data</head>
					<p>The CCl-DB provides handwritings of several scribes in different codices. Therefore, we compared two test
						sets (<ref target="#table02">see Table 2</ref>) to check if the networks tend to learn codex-specific
						features. For this experiment we trained the architectures AlexNet, Half Deep Writer and DeepWriter.
						Referring to Xing and Qiao (<ref target="#xing_etal2016">2016</ref>) these networks are suitable for
						handwriting identification. We found, that the test set Test B which contains test samples from books which
						have not been used for training (<ref target="#table01">see Table 1</ref>) is more comprehensive than Test A
						because all three trained networks performed better on Test A whether the input images have been RGB
						grayscale or masked. We conclude, that the networks learned codex-specific features in Test A. Therefore, we
						used the test set Test B for further experiments to obtain more reliable results.</p>
					<table xml:id="table02">
						<head>F1-score for image preprocessing on patch level. Preprocessed input images and their impact on the
							classification of the test data. The experiment was performed on the three different networks AlexNet,
							Half DeepWriter and Deepwriter. As a result, the averaged F1-score is given. We provide two F1-scores of
							separate test sets (<ref target="#table01">see Table 1</ref>).</head>
						<row role="label">
							<cell>Data</cell>
							<cell>Network</cell>
							<cell>RGB</cell>
							<cell>GS</cell>
							<cell>GS mask</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell rows="4" role="label">Test A</cell>
							<cell>AlexNet</cell>
							<cell>0.25</cell>
							<cell>0.56</cell>
							<cell>0.64</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>Deep Writer</cell>
							<cell>0.25</cell>
							<cell>0.44</cell>
							<cell>0.57</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>Half Deep Writer</cell>
							<cell>0.25</cell>
							<cell>0.41</cell>
							<cell>0.54</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>∅</cell>
							<cell>0.25</cell>
							<cell>0.47</cell>
							<cell>0.58</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell rows="4" role="label">Test B</cell>
							<cell>AlexNet</cell>
							<cell>0.30</cell>
							<cell>0.53</cell>
							<cell>0.60</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>Deep Writer</cell>
							<cell>0.26</cell>
							<cell>0.32</cell>
							<cell>0.42</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>Half Deep Writer</cell>
							<cell>0.35</cell>
							<cell>0.30</cell>
							<cell>0.38</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell>∅</cell>
							<cell>0.30</cell>
							<cell>0.38</cell>
							<cell>0.47</cell>
						</row>
					</table>
					<table xml:id="table03">
						<head>Network performance on patch level. Nine different CNN architectures are trained on the data of <ref
								target="#table01">Table 1</ref> to compare their performance on patch level. The weighted averaged
							F1-Score we use, is measured on Test B (<ref target="#table01">see Table 1</ref>) and rounded to two
							decimal places. The training-time is given in rounded minutes. The models marked by * originate from the
							torchvision library.</head>
						<row role="label">
							<cell>Network</cell>
							<cell>F1 Test B</cell>
							<cell>Time</cell>
							<cell>Image (height, width)</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">Densenet*</cell>
							<cell>0.61</cell>
							<cell>503</cell>
							<cell>224, 224</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">AlexnetNet</cell>
							<cell>0.60</cell>
							<cell>115</cell>
							<cell>227, 227</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">ResNet18*</cell>
							<cell>0.56</cell>
							<cell>164</cell>
							<cell>224, 224</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">Inception v3*</cell>
							<cell>0.55</cell>
							<cell>683</cell>
							<cell>299, 299</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">VGG*</cell>
							<cell>0.53</cell>
							<cell>610</cell>
							<cell>224, 224</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">SqueezeNet*</cell>
							<cell>0.50</cell>
							<cell>135</cell>
							<cell>224, 224</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">MNASNet*</cell>
							<cell>0.43</cell>
							<cell>196</cell>
							<cell>224, 224</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">DeepWriter</cell>
							<cell>0.42</cell>
							<cell>66</cell>
							<cell>113, 226</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">Half DeepWriter</cell>
							<cell>0.38</cell>
							<cell>62</cell>
							<cell>113, 113</cell>
						</row>
					</table>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>5.2 Classification pipeline</head>
					<p><list type="ordered">
							<item>To find the best type of input image for the CNN classification, we preprocessed the dataset in
								three different ways. We compared RGB images with grayscale and masked grayscale images and found that
								masked grayscale images produce the best F1-score in the test data (<ref target="#table02">see Table
									2</ref>). Consequently, the following experiments are based on this powerful image preprocessing. The
								masking has proven to be effective enough even though we used a simple threshold-based algorithm that
								sometimes does not reliably distinguish between ink and parchment. Hence, we could replace it in further
								studies by a better learning-based solution.</item>
							<item>As there are different networks available for image classification, we compare in <ref
									target="#table03">Table 3</ref> nine powerful architectures. AlexNet achieves with an F1-score of 0.60
								on patch level and 115 minutes training time the best trade-off between F1-score and time. Only DenseNet
								achieved a small improvement of 0.01 in comparison to AlexNet but with a training time of 503 minutes it
								is much less time efficient. Even though latest state-of-the-art models performed better, with a growing
								number of parameters, the processing time would be impractical for our purpose, and as already shown
									(<ref target="#table02">see Table 2</ref>) data-centric approaches such as masked grayscale images are
								more influential. Given these F1 and training time results, we claim AlexNet to be best suited for our
								purposes and thus used it for all further experiments.</item>
							<item>To understand whether pre-training is beneficial, we follow the example of Xing and Qiao (<ref
									target="#xing_etal2016">2016</ref>). Accordingly, we pre-trained AlexNet on 301 writers of the IAM
								dataset and fine-tuned the model on the CCl-DB data. The pre-trained and fine-tuned model generates an
								F1-score of 0.58 whereas the from scratch trained model outperformed this result with an F1-score of
								0.60 on page level. Because of the lower F1-score of the pre-trained and finetuned model model, we
								assume that there are not enough shared features between the CCl-DB and the IAM dataset. However, as
								shown by Studer et al. (<ref target="#studer_etal2019">2019</ref>), models in general benefit from
								pre-training. We assume, that larger and more comprehensive datasets than the IAM handwriting database
								could improve our model.</item>
						</list></p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>5.3 Automatic paleographic classification</head>
					<p>To figure out, which reliability values can be reached by the trained AlexNet, we evaluated the data of
						Test B. The main experiments are performed on line level (<ref target="#figure07">see Figure 7</ref>), but
						we also provide test results on patch and page level (<ref target="#table04">see Table 4</ref>).
						Furthermore, we show the confusion matrix of the same test data on page level in <ref target="#figure05"
							>Figure 5</ref>. We observe, that the line level classification generally reinforces the patch level
						results and the page level classification generally reinforces the line level results.</p>
					<p>Another particularity in <ref target="#table04">Table 4</ref> and <ref target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref>
						are the dichotomous scores. Five of seven classes are predicted well, such as F1-scores up to 1.0 on page
						level and 0.96 on line level in the case of A20 (<ref target="#table04">see Table 4</ref>). Only the two
						classes B 20 and A 215 seem to be less precisely predicted on the test data. We observe low F1-Scores of 0.0
						on page level as well as 0.24 and 0.06 on line level respectively. However, the low predictions for the two
						classes B 20 and A 215 strengthen the hypothesis of a powerful model as investigations of our paleographic
						partners revealed the labelling of these classes to be most probably incorrect. The paleographers actually
						labeled this test data as several not defined classes. Thus, the classification of the two classes proposed
						by the network might indeed correspond to the correct scribes and could therefore give new insight. However,
						confirmation by future research using our approach would be needed.</p>
					<table xml:id="table04">
						<head>Results of Test B. F1-score on Test B(<ref target="#table01">see Table 1</ref>). The F1-score is
							measured on patch- (p) and line- (l) and page-level (pg). The weighted averaged test data are random lines
							of unseen books, as these lines are of various length, they result in a different number of patches. Due
							to the image preprocessing the total of samples is slightly lower than in <ref target="#table01">Table
								1</ref>.</head>
						<row role="label">
							<cell>Scribe</cell>
							<cell>F1-p</cell>
							<cell>F1-l</cell>
							<cell>F1-pg</cell>
							<cell>#-p</cell>
							<cell>#-l</cell>
							<cell>#-pg</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">B 259</cell>
							<cell>0.60</cell>
							<cell>0.76</cell>
							<cell>0.85</cell>
							<cell>31309</cell>
							<cell>1340</cell>
							<cell>42</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">A 259</cell>
							<cell>0.79</cell>
							<cell>0.94</cell>
							<cell>0.98</cell>
							<cell>34004</cell>
							<cell>1672</cell>
							<cell>52</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">A 30</cell>
							<cell>0.62</cell>
							<cell>0.76</cell>
							<cell>0.74</cell>
							<cell>56173</cell>
							<cell>2805</cell>
							<cell>66</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">A 20</cell>
							<cell>0.90</cell>
							<cell>0.96</cell>
							<cell>1.00</cell>
							<cell>71565</cell>
							<cell>2814</cell>
							<cell>72</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">B 20</cell>
							<cell>0.05</cell>
							<cell>0.24</cell>
							<cell>0.00</cell>
							<cell>1957</cell>
							<cell>111</cell>
							<cell>3</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">A 215</cell>
							<cell>0.07</cell>
							<cell>0.06</cell>
							<cell>0.00</cell>
							<cell>65689</cell>
							<cell>2897</cell>
							<cell>92</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell role="label">A 258</cell>
							<cell>0.68</cell>
							<cell>0.79</cell>
							<cell>0.83</cell>
							<cell>67520</cell>
							<cell>2893</cell>
							<cell>96</cell>
						</row>
					</table>
					<p/>
					<figure xml:id="figure05">
						<head>Confusion matrix of the data of Test B on page level (<ref target="#table03">see Table
							3</ref>).</head>
						<graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
						<figDesc>a matrix showing truth vs prediction where light colors represent higher scores</figDesc>
					</figure>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>5.4 Reject Option</head>
					<p> To investigate whether implementing a reject option improves results we tested the five classes (B 259, A
						259, A 30, A 20, A 258) on it. These are the classes shown previously without conflicts in the test data of
						Test B. <ref target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref> shows that increasing the reject rate minimizes the error.
						The reject curves of <ref target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref> drop quickly, indicating a strong influence of
						the threshold. As Cilia et al. (<ref target="#cilia_etal2020a">2020a</ref>) explained, the reject option is
						therefore suitable for the scribe identification on the CCl-DB. Therefore, we choose a reject option based
						on the threshold of 40 %, as it ensures low error with high sample rate. As class B 20 and A 215 are
						difficult to evaluate from the test data, the threshold is adapted to 60%.</p>
					<figure xml:id="figure06">
						<head>Error-reject curves for five different scribes on the data of Test B on line level (<ref
								target="#table01">see Table 1</ref>).</head>
						<graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
						<figDesc>a line graph where high steady y-values drop sharply after 40%</figDesc>
					</figure>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>5.5 Into the wild: Using our model on data with unknown scribes</head>
					<p>The central aim of our approach is to contribute new insights for paleography. Therefore, we examined
						sections from the codices that the experts limited to one scribe, although they could not determine the
						exact individual. As shown in <ref target="#figure07">Figure 7</ref> the trained model contributes
						meaningful classifications for these parts. The first plot can be considered as reference, this is the part
						of CCl 214 written by A 30. In this example, the model recognizes class A 30 as main class. The remaining
						six plots can be differentiated into two groups. On the one hand there are plots b, d and f which give
						significant results that refer to one scribe class B 20, A 30 and A 215 respectively. On the other hand,
						there are plots like in c, e and g that produce diffuse classification, not focused on one class. We
						conclude that these less significant predictions are caused either by scribes the model hasn’t learned yet
						or by more than one scribe.</p>
					<figure xml:id="figure07">
						<head>Scribe identification on line level and with reject option. All figures are based on the parts of one
							scribe. These new codices are labeled with one given (a) and six unknown scribes (b-g).</head>
						<graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
						<figDesc>7 comparative bar graphs where the "reject option" yields more favorable results</figDesc>
					</figure>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="section06">
				<head>6 Conclusion</head>
				<p>In this paper, we want to study the question of how to train a reliable and efficient model that allows
					cross-codex scribe identification in the strongly standardized medieval Carolingian minuscule of the CCl-DB.
					To this aim, we first figured out the risk of codex specific overfitting and showed the importance of
					cross-codex data to overcome this issue. We also found, that the reduction of RGB-images to grayscale masked
					images helps the network to focus on scribe specific features and leads to significantly better results.</p>
				<p>After comparing several networks, AlexNet was used in our pipeline to generate a classification on patch,
					line and page level. Finally, we improved the final score by implementing the reject option.</p>
				<p>One of the limitations of the proposed method is the basic segmentation, which is challenging on the historic
					parchment. This limitation leads to a natural direction of future work, focusing on improving the segmentation
					method that also allows binarization. The outcomes of these investigations currently form the foundation for
					advancing automated scribe identification. The recognition system described in this paper has been integrated
					into the backend of an active learning application, while concurrently, we are collaboratively developing an
					intuitively accessible application with continuous annotations in close cooperation with paleographers. The
					inclusion of a visual interface will empower experts to scrutinize and refine predictions, facilitating an
					iterative process of retraining our model and validating it against new scribe hypotheses. These findings aim
					to unlock novel possibilities and analytical tools, fostering a more profound comprehension of diverse
					medieval scriptoria. Going forward, this research endeavors to bring researchers closer to addressing open
					questions regarding the organizational aspects of scriptoria in the high medieval monasteries of (Lower)
					Austria, with additional evidence and interpretations serving as valuable support.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="appendix">
				<head/>
				<div>
					<head>Funding</head>
					<p>This work has received funding from the Lower Austrian FTI-Call 2018 under grant agreement No FTI18-004
						(project Active Machine Learning for Automatic Scribe Identification in 12th Century Manuscripts). Moreover,
						the work was supported by Erasmus+ from the German Academic Exchange Service (DAAD).</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>Acknowledgments</head>
					<p>We would like to thank the team of the Klosterneuburg abbey library, as well as the team of the institute
						of Creative\Media/Technologies of the St. Polten University of Applied Sciences for their help.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<listBibl>
				<bibl xml:id="bischoff2004" label="Bischoff 2004"> Bischoff, B. (2004) <title rend="italic">Paläographie des
						römischen Altertums und des abendländischen Mittelalters</title>, E. Schmidt, Berlin.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="brink_etal2012" label="Brink et al 2012"> Brink, A., Smit, J., Bulacu, M. and Schomaker, L. (2012)
						<title rend="quotes">Writer identification using directional ink-trace width measurements</title>, <title
						rend="italic">Pattern Recognition</title> 45(1), 162–171. Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0031320311002810"
						>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0031320311002810</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="chammas_etal2018" label="Chammas et al 2018"> Chammas, E., Mokbel, C. and Likforman-Sulem, L.
					(2018) <title rend="quotes">Handwriting recognition of historical documents with few labeled data</title>, in
						<title rend="italic">2018 13th IAPR International Workshop on Document Analysis Systems (DAS)</title>, IEEE
					Computer Society, Los Alamitos, CA, USA, pp. 43–48. Available at: <ref
						target="https://doi.ieeecomputersociety.org/10.1109/DAS.2018.15"
						>https://doi.ieeecomputersociety.org/10.1109/DAS.2018.15</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="chammas_etal2020" label="Chammas et al 2020"> Chammas, M., Makhoul, A. and DEMERJIAN, J. (2020)
						<title rend="quotes">Writer identification for historical handwritten documents using a single feature
						extraction method</title>, in <title rend="italic">19th International Conference on Machine Learning and
						Applications (ICMLA 2020)</title>, Miami (on line), United States. Available at: <ref
						target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-03017586"
					>https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-03017586</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="christlein_etal2019" label="Christlein et al 2019"> Christlein, V., Nicolaou, A., Seuret, M.,
					Stutzmann, D. and Maier, A. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Icdar 2019 competition on image retrieval for
						historical handwritten documents</title>, in <title rend="italic">2019 International Conference on Document
						Analysis and Recognition</title>. IEEE, pp. 1505–1509.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="cilia_etal2020a" label="Cilia et al 2020a"> Cilia, N. D., De Stefano, C., Fontanella, F.,
					Marrocco, C., Molinara, M. and Freca, A. S. d. (2020a), <title rend="quotes">An experimental comparison
						between deep learning and classical machine learning approaches for writer identification in medieval
						documents</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Imaging</title> 6(9). Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.mdpi.com/2313-433X/6/9/89">https://www.mdpi.com/2313-433X/6/9/89</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="cilia_etal2020b" label="Cilia et al 2020b"> Cilia, N., De Stefano, C., Fontanella, F., Marrocco,
					C., Molinara, M. and Freca, A. (2020b), <title rend="quotes">An end-to-end deep learning system for medieval
						writer identification</title>, <title rend="italic">Pattern Recognition Letters</title> 129, 137–143.
					Available at: <ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0167865519303460"
						>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0167865519303460</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="cloppet_etal2016" label="Cloppet et al 2016"> Cloppet, F., Eglin, V., Kieu, V. C., Stutzmann, D.
					and Vincent, N. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Icfhr2016 competition on the classification of medieval
						handwritings in latin script</title>, in <title rend="italic">2016 15th International Conference on
						Frontiers in Handwriting Recognition (ICFHR)</title>, pp. 590–595.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="destefano_etal2011" label="De Stefano et al 2011"> De Stefano, C., Fontanella, F., Maniaci, M. and
					Scotto di Freca, A. (2011) <title rend="quotes">A method for scribe distinction in medieval manuscripts using
						page layout features</title>, in <title rend="italic">Image Analysis and Processing–ICIAP 2011: 16th
						International Conference Proceedings</title>, pp. 393–402.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="destefano_etal2018" label="De Stefano et al 2018"> De Stefano, C., Maniaci, M., Fontanella, F. and
					Scotto di Freca, A. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Layout measures for writer identification in mediaeval
						documents</title>, <title rend="italic">Measurement</title> 127, 443–452. Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0263224118305359"
						>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0263224118305359</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="dey_etal2017" label="Dey et al 2017"> Dey, S., Dutta, A., Toledo, J., Ghosh, S., Llados, J. and
					Pal, U. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Signet: Convolutional siamese network for writer independent offline
						signature verification</title>, <title rend="italic">CoRR</title> abs/1707.02131. Available at: <ref
						target="http://arxiv.org/abs/1707.02131">http://arxiv.org/abs/1707.02131</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="fiel_etal2017" label="Fiel et al 2017"> Fiel, S., Kleber, F., Diem, M., Christlein, V., Louloudis,
					G., Nikos, S. and Gatos, B. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Icdar 2017 competition on historical document writer
						identification (historical-wi)</title>, in <title rend="italic">2017 14th IAPR International Conference on
						Document Analysis and Recognition (ICDAR)</title>, Vol. 01, IEEE, pp. 1377– 1382. Available at: <ref
						target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/8270156"
						>https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/8270156</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="fiel_etal2012" label="Fiel and Sablatnig 2012"> Fiel, S. and Sablatnig, R. (2012) <title
						rend="quotes">Writer retrieval and writer identification using local features</title>, <title rend="italic"
						>Proceedings - 10th IAPR International Workshop on Document Analysis Systems, DAS 2012</title>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="fiel_etal2015" label="Fiel and Sablatnig 2015"> Fiel, S. and Sablatnig, R. (2015) <title>Writer
						identification and retrieval using a convolutional neural network</title>, in G. Azzopardi and N. Petkov,
					eds, <title rend="italic">Computer Analysis of Images and Patterns</title>, Springer, Springer International
					Publishing, Cham, pp. 26–37.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="haidinger1983" label="Haidinger 1983"> Haidinger, A. (1983) <title rend="italic">Katalog der
						Handschriften des Augustiner Chorherrenstiftes Klosterneuburg</title>, Vol. 2 of <title rend="italic"
						>Veröffentlichungen der Kommission für Schrift- und Buchwesen des Mittelalters</title>, Wien.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="haidinger1991" label="Haidinger 1991"> Haidinger, A. (1991) <title rend="italic">Katalog der
						Handschriften des Augustiner Chorherrenstiftes Klosterneuburg</title>, Vol. 2 of <title rend="italic"
						>Veröffentlichungen der Kommission für Schrift- und Buchwesen des Mittelalters</title>, Wien.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="haidinger2010" label="Haidinger 2010"> Haidinger, A. (2010) <title rend="quotes">manuscripta.at –
						ein webportal zu mittelalterlichen handschriften in österreichischen bibliotheken</title>, <title
						rend="italic">Schriften der Vereinigung Österreichischer Bibliothekarinnen und Bibliothekare (VÖB)</title>
					pp. 53–61. Available at: <ref target="https://manuscripta.at/">https://manuscripta.at/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="haltich2014" label="Haltich 2014"> Haltich M. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Die
						Stiftsbibliothek</title>, in: <title rend="italic">Das Stift Klosterneuburg : wo sich Himmel und Erde
						begegnen</title>. Hrsg. von Wolfgang Huber. Doessel: Janos Stekovics Verlag, 2014, p. 216–229.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="he_etal2014" label="He and Schomaker 2014"> He, S. and Schomaker, L. (2014) <title rend="quotes"
						>Delta-n hinge: Rotation-invariant features for writer identification</title>, in <title rend="italic">2014
						22nd International Conference on Pattern Recognition</title>, pp. 2023–2028.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="islam_etal2016" label="Islam et al 2016"> Islam, N., Islam, Z. and Noor, N. (2016) <title
						rend="quotes">A survey on optical character recognition system</title>, <title rend="italic">ITB Journal of
						Information and Communication Technology</title>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="kahle_etal2017" label="Kahle et al 2017"> Kahle, P., Colutto, S., Hackl, G. and Mühlberger, G.
					(2017) <title rend="quotes">Transkribus - a service platform for transcription, recognition and retrieval of
						historical documents</title>, in <title rend="italic">2017 14th IAPR International Conference on Document
						Analysis and Recognition (ICDAR)</title>, Vol. 04, pp. 19–24.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="kluge2019" label="Kluge 2019"> Kluge M. (2019) <title rend="italic">Handschriften des
						Mittelalters: Grundwissen Kodikologie und Paläographie</title>. Thorbecke Jan Verlag. Available at: <ref
						target="https://books.google.de/books?id=unFHwgEACAAJ"
					>https://books.google.de/books?id=unFHwgEACAAJ</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="krizhevsky_etal2012" label="Krizhevsky et al 2012"> Krizhevsky, A., Sutskever, I. and Hinton, G.
					E. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Imagenet classification with deep convolutional neural networks</title>, in F.
					Pereira, C. J. C. Burges, L. Bottou and K. Q. Weinberger, eds, <title rend="italic">Advances in Neural
						Information Processing Systems</title>, Vol. 25, Curran Associates, Inc. Available at: <ref
						target="https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper/2012/file/c399862d3b9d6b76c8436e924a68cPaper.pdf"
						>https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper/2012/file/c399862d3b9d6b76c8436e924a68cPaper.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="lackner2012" label="Lackner 2012"> Lackner, F. (2012) <title rend="italic">Katalog der
						Handschriften des Augustiner Chorherrenstiftes Klosterneuburg</title>, Vol. 2 of <title rend="italic"
						>Veröffentlichungen der Kommission für Schrift- und Buchwesen des Mittelalters</title>, Wien.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="landau2004" label="Landau 2004"> Landau P. (2004) <title rend="quotes">Die Lex Baiuvariorum.
						Entstehungszeit, Entstehungsort und Charakter von Bayerns ältester Rechts- und Geschichtsquelle</title>;
						<title rend="itlaic">vorgetragen in der Gesamtsitzung</title> vom 6. Juni 2003. München. Available at: <ref
						target="http://publikationen.badw.de/de/019366060">http://publikationen.badw.de/de/019366060</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="liu_etal2011" label="Liu et al 2011"> Liu, C.-L., Yin, F., Wang, D.-H. and Wang, Q.-F. (2011)
						<title rend="quotes">Casia online and offline chinese handwriting databases</title>, pp. 37 – 41.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="maaten_etal2005" label="Maaten and Postma 2005"> Maaten, L. V. D. and Postma, E. (2005) <title
						rend="quotes">Improving automatic writer identification</title>, in <title rend="italic">PROC. OF 17TH
						BELGIUM-NETHERLANDS CONFERENCE ON ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE (BNAIC 2005</title>, pp. 260–266.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="marcel_etal2010" label="Marcel and Rodriguez 2010"> Marcel, S. and Rodriguez, Y. (2010) <title
						rend="quotes">Torchvision the machine-vision package of torch</title>, in <title rend="italic">Proceedings
						of the 18th ACM International Conference on Multimedia</title>, MM ’10, Association for Computing Machinery,
					New York, NY, USA, p. 1485–1488. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1145/1873951.1874254"
						>https://doi.org/10.1145/1873951.1874254</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="marti_etal2002" label="Marti and Bunke 2002"> Marti, U. and Bunke, H. (2002) <title rend="quotes"
						>The iam-database: an english sentence database for offline handwriting recognition</title>, <title
						rend="italic">International Journal on Document Analysis and Recognition</title> 5(1), 39–46.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="oliveira_etal2018" label="Oliveira et al 2018"> Oliveira, S. A., Seguin, B. and Kaplan, F. (2018)
						<title rend="quotes">dhsegment: A generic deeplearning approach for document segmentation</title>, <title
						rend="italic">2018 16th International Conference on Frontiers in Handwriting Recognition (ICFHR)</title> pp.
					7–12.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="powitz2007" label="Powitz 2007"> Powitz G. (2007) “Was vermag Paläographie?”, in: Urkundensprachen
					im germanisch-romanischen Grenzgebiet: Beiträge zum Kolloquium am 5./6. Oktober 1995 in Trier, hrsg. von K.
					Gärtner und G. Holtus (Trierer historische Forschungen, 35), p. 223–251.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="said_etal1998" label="Said et al 1998"> Said, H., Baker, K. and Tan, T. (1998) <title
						rend="quotes">Personal identification based on handwriting</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings.
						Fourteenth International Conference on Pattern Recognition (Cat. No.98EX170)</title> 2, 1761–1764.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="schneider2014" label="Schneider 2014"> Schneider, K. (2014) <title rend="italic">Paläographie und
						Handschriftenkunde für Germanisten</title>, De Gruyter, Berlin/Boston.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="seidl_etal2014" label="Seidl and Haltrich 2014"> Seidl, M., Haltrich, M. (2014) <title
						rend="quotes">Codex claustroneoburgensis-datenbank (ccl-db)</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://phaidra.fhstp.ac.at/view/o:4631">https://phaidra.fhstp.ac.at/view/o:4631</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="shaikh_etal2020" label="Shaikh et al 2020"> Shaikh, M. A., Duan, T., Chauhan, M. and Srihari, S.
					N. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Attention based writer independent verification</title>, <title rend="italic"
						>2020 17th International Conference on Frontiers in Handwriting Recognition (ICFHR)</title> pp.
					373–379.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="studer_etal2019" label="Studer et al 2019"> Studer, L., Alberti, M., Pondenkandath, V., Goktepe,
					P., Kolonko, T., Fischer, A., Liwicki, M. and Ingold, R. (2019) <title rend="quotes">A comprehensive study of
						imagenet pre-training for historical document image analysis</title>, <title rend="italic">2019
						International Conference on Document Analysis and Recognition (ICDAR)</title> pp. 720–725.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="tensmeyer_etal2017" label="Tensmeyer et al 2017"> Tensmeyer, C., Davis, B., Wigington, C., Lee, I.
					and Barrett, B. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Pagenet: Page boundary extraction in historical handwritten
						documents</title>, in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 4th International Workshop on Historical
						Document Imaging and Processing</title>, HIP2017, Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, p.
					59–64. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1145/3151509.3151522"
						>https://doi.org/10.1145/3151509.3151522</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="wu_etal2014" label="Wu et al 2014"> Wu, X., Tang, Y. and Bu, W. (2014) <title rend="quotes"
						>Offline text-independent writer identification based on scale invariant feature transform</title>, <title
						rend="italic">Information Forensics and Security, IEEE Transactions on 9</title>, pp. 526–536.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="xing_etal2016" label="Xing and Qiao 2016"> Xing, L. and Qiao, Y. (2016) <title rend="quotes"
						>Deepwriter: A Multi-stream Deep CNN for Text-Independent Writer Identification</title>, in <title
						rend="italic">2016 15th International Conference on Frontiers in Handwriting Recognition (ICFHR)</title>,
					IEEE Computer Society, Los Alamitos, CA, USA, pp. 584–589. Available at: <ref
						target="https://doi.ieeecomputersociety.org/10.1109/ICFHR.2016.0112"
						>https://doi.ieeecomputersociety.org/10.1109/ICFHR.2016.0112</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="xiong_etal2015" label="Xiong et al 2015"> Xiong, Y.-J., Wen, Y., Wang, P. S. P. and Lu, Y. (2015)
						<title rend="quotes">Text-independent writer identification using sift descriptor and contour-directional
						feature</title>, in <title rend="italic">2015 13th International Conference on Document Analysis and
						Recognition (ICDAR)</title>, pp. 91–95.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="yang_etal2016" label="Yang et al 2016"> Yang, W., Jin, L. and Liu, M. (2016) <title rend="quotes"
						>Deepwriterid: An end-to-end online text-independent writer identification system</title>, <title
						rend="italic">IEEE Intelligent Systems</title> 31(2), 45–53. Available at: <ref
						target="https://doi.org/10.1109/MIS.2016.22">https://doi.org/10.1109/MIS.2016.22</ref>.</bibl>
			</listBibl>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
