<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Fingerprints of British Book History: A Feminist Labor History of EEBO</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Ana<dhq:family>Quiring</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID"><!-- if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000 --></idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Washington University in St. Louis</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>quiring@wustl.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio><p></p></dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!-- including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110 -->000718</idno>
                <idno type="volume"><!-- volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date></date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->                    
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    
                    <!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new <term> element for each -->
                    <term corresp="#digitization"/> 
                    <term corresp="#gender"/>
                    <term corresp="#glam"></term>
                    <term corresp="#race"></term>
                    <term corresp="#gender"></term>
                    <term corresp="#materialisms"></term>
                    <term corresp="#data_curation"></term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>invisible labor</item>
                        <item>World War II</item>
                        <item>Lucia Moholy</item>
                        <item>microfilm</item>
                        <item>EEBO
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item></item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Replace "XXXXXX" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
            <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000718/000718.xml">GitHub
            </ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
               <p> In this essay, I give a labor history of the commonly used database Early English Book Online. EEBO began its life as a mirofilm archive produced beginning in 1940: a massive book-copying project was undertaken during World War II to protect rare books from German bombs. These reproductions were made largely by unnamed woman archivists and led by a team of woman photographers, academics, and secretaries. In this essay, I draw on existing theories and histories of EEBO while highlighting these women's work, which manifests in the photographs through the shadows of the fingertips they used to pin down the fragile books. This archive of reproductive labor exemplifies the artificial divide between auteur and stenographer, artist and secretary, that animated many of the early twentieth century’s avant-garde movements, including ones in which EEBO photographers were intimately involved. The fingers represent the custodial labor of women working across artistic and administrative modes during World War II and the decades that followed. 
</p>            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p></p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>
Upon its founding in 2002, Google Books promised its users the world  <ptr target="#hoffman2016"/>.
                    “Imagine,” wrote then-CEO Eric Schmitt, “the cultural impact of putting tens of
                    millions of previously inaccessible volumes into one vast index, every word of
                    which is searchable by anyone, rich and poor, urban and rural, First World and
                    Third, <hi rend="italic">en toute langue</hi>—and all, of course, entirely for
                    free”  <ptr target="#schmidt2005"/>. Nearly twenty years later, the service has
                    indeed become a ubiquitous online resource, one with a mixed reputation among
                    digital humanists  <ptr target="#noble2018"/>, <ptr target="#newman2011"/>, <ptr
                        target="#grimmelmann2009"/>. Its errors—evidence of imperfect human
                    mediation—are also commonplace. In 2011, artist and writer Krissy Wilson began
                    collecting these errors on her blog <title rend="italic">The Art of Google
                        Books</title>. Wilson’s archive, which includes submissions from readers,
                    catalogues the ephemeral flaws made before and during the copying process: a
                    forgotten library slip with check-out dates spanning thirty years; a blurred
                    page, photographed as it is turned; rips in the paper; ink stains. However, the
                    most common and most eloquent error captured by  <title rend="italic">The Art of
                        Google Books</title> concerns the trace of human labor in the archive’s
                    production. Google’s scanning cameras often capture the fingers and hands of the
                    low-wage workers who hold open each book. They often wear pink or blue finger
                    rubbers, minimizing the wear and tear book-handling exerts on the skin. The
                    images largely depict Black and brown hands, suggesting the demographics of this
                    low-paid work <ref target="#figure01">(Figure 1)</ref>. The bad scans capture the process of unspectacular labor as it occurs. In consequence, they are an artful and poignant visible record of the work that digital humanists have recently sought to recover  <ptr target="#klein2020"/>, <ptr target="#nyhan2020"/>
                    </p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure01">
                            <head> This worker’s hand obscures the book plate and check-out slip
                                for Edward Young’s <title rend="italic">The Complaint; or,
                                    Night-thoughts on Life, Death, and Immortality</title> (1750).
                                The original is held by Oxford University and was digitized by an
                                anonymous worker on August 2, 2007.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                            <figDesc>alt text</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                <p>
                    <title rend="italic">The Art of Google Books</title> demonstrates the continuity between contemporary digitization practices and a longer history of archival touch. Scholars have examined the abuses of Google’s digital practices and their implications for both archival labor and intellectual property [Noble 2018, Hoffman and Bloom 2016, Segev 2010]. In this essay, I extend this work to trace a cultural history of the photographed finger. I do so through a focus on the labor history embedded in one literary database: Early English Books Online (EEBO). Several critics have catalogued the palimpsestic nature of this digital archive, which reveals the circumstances in which the database was produced, beginning during the crucible of World War II, in an international scramble to photograph every extant early modern book as the threat of German occupation increased [Schmitt 2003, Peiss 2019, Mak 2014, Kichuk 2007]. Less known are the experiences of the photographers and librarians who created the archive. Teams of women in the backrooms of universities and museums made thousands of microfilm reels during the war and continuing afterward. The evidence of their labor is anything but invisible. The images they created include stunning and mundane traces of their work, cluttering the lower margins of manuscript pages, their fingertips a silent motif that persists into the Google Books era (Figure 2). 
                </p>
                <figure xml:id="figure02">
                    <head>The first page of a 1595 copy of Sir Philip Sidney’s <title rend="italic">The Defence of Poesie</title> has been photographed with the fingers of the photographer visible in the lower corners of each page. © British Library Board. STC 2nd edition 22535 reel 904:16. Images published with permission of ProQuest. Further reproduction is prohibited without permission. Images produced by ProQuest as part of Early Modern Books. www.proquest.com.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    <figDesc>alt text</figDesc>
                </figure>         
                 <p>
                     This essay centers EEBO’s photographed fingertips as interventions in the archive, analyzing not only their historical significance but also the conceptual import of their visual mark on images of the English literary canon. Reading EEBO’s fingers focalizes the digital object as distinct from print, and acknowledges the feminized labor needed to produce it. This reading practice also activates a centuries-long material and conceptual history of interaction between hand and page, one that spans a series of technological evolutions. EEBO and its fingers mark the transition from analog to digital, through the intimate technology of the digit—the index finger. This archive of reproductive labor exemplifies the artificial divide between auteur and stenographer, artist and secretary, that animated many of the early twentieth century’s avant-garde movements, including ones in which EEBO, then called Early English Books (EEB), photographers were intimately involved. In what follows, I chronicle the women who lived this divide, including secretary Margaret Harwick, librarian-spy Adele Kibre, and Bauhaus photographer Lucia Moholy, whose work in both microfilm and avant-garde photography theorized “the invisible hand of the artist-as-reproducer” [Troeller 2020, 86]. The largely untold stories of these artists throw into relief the self-hagiography of the archive’s presumed architect, Eugene Power. Read in this context, the signature contribution of the EEB images is that they render reproductive labor literally visible, in the form of a fingernail imprinted at the edge of a textual artifact. The fingers represent the custodial labor of women working across artistic and administrative modes during World War II and the decades that followed. At the same time, they render visible the text’s transition into a new form of commodity, repackaged for new sites of purchase and distribution, their specific visual arrangement testifying to the text’s valuation and evaluation at a key moment in literary history.    
                 </p>           
                <p>
                    <head>A Note on Methodology: Piercing the Digital Veil</head>
                    Studying the production history of EEBO places my work in conversation with a growing tradition of feminist digital humanists. Integrating feminist practices into the digital humanities has required its practitioners to, as Catherine D’Ignazio and Lauren Klein write, “show [their] work.” Their book, Data Feminism [2020], argues that digital spaces depend on invisible labor forces. In fact, “invisible labor” has become a central formulation in digital studies. The predicament is a feminist one, Klein writes elsewhere, because women have traditionally been tasked with myriad forms of uncredited work, from cleaning and child-rearing to editing, typesetting, data entry, and archive maintenance [Klein 2020]. An important example of this shift is recent scholarship on digital humanities pioneers like Josephine Miles, who invented a form of quantitative reading while teaching at UC Berkeley in the 1950s [Sagner Buurma and Heffernan 2021, Pasanek 2019]. Julianne Nyhan has illuminated the work of the 65 keypunch operators, many of them woman, who worked with Roberto Busa, the so-called father of the digital humanities [Nyhan 2020]. Still more scholars have traced extensive histories of digitized archives of newspapers [Fyfe 2016, Beals and Bell 2020, Bingham 2010, Fafinski 2022, Hauswedell et al 2022]. We can also draw inspiration from the emerging field of production studies, begun in film and media studies and now borrowed by many feminist digital humanists.  Production studies attends to the quotidian and collective labor of making art. The field, Miranda Banks writes, is profoundly “anti-auterist,” deflating the cults of personality that often define filmmaking in favor of cataloguing the many tasks that bring a film to life. This is a feminist methodology in large part because it “highlights production at the margins” [Banks 2018, 157]. The microfilmed EEBO archive provides an apt opportunity for a production studies approach, its margins quite literally highlighted by the cluttered residue of its production.  
                </p>            
                 <p>
                     Methodologically, production studies contends with the occlusions of reproductive labor. Jordan Troeller articulates the challenge this insight poses for studying artists such as Lucia Moholy, whose work in the Bauhaus school during the 1920s and ‘30s was often overshadowed and outright stolen by her husband, the more famous László Moholy-Nagy. Troeller writes, “Coded as ‘reproductive,’ in distinction to the ‘productive’ work of her male colleagues, Moholy’s photography was not maliciously ignored so much as it was naturalized as a labor of love on the part of a devoted wife, whose status as an artist was never seriously considered” [Troeller 2020, 75]. Troeller describes a hierarchy of labor that separates the original from the reproduced, and, importantly, the artistic from the technical. While Moholy-Nagy shot the camera, it was most often his wife who actually produced his images in the darkroom. According to Moholy, her husband viewed technical knowledge as “derivative… in comparison to the more consequential work of the painter and architect” [Troeller 2020, 82]. This divide, which characterized the artistic philosophy of the Bauhaus more generally, mirrors the gendered hierarchies in literary modernism between authors and midwife-editors and in bibliographic societies between male museum and library directors and female secretaries, treasurers, and copyists, the so-called “handmaidens of history.” The first several decades of the twentieth century, which saw women gain access to the professions in growing numbers, not to mention the loss of thousands of men from the workforce due to two world wars, are prime territory for interrogating the ever-flimsier divide between artistic and reproductive labor, as research in art history and literary studies has demonstrated [Troeller 2020, Richards 2020, Delsandro 2020, Otto and Rössler 2019, Micir 2019, Wagner 1998, Marek 1995]. 
</p>
<p>
Putting production studies in conversation with existing histories of EEBO leads to new feminist insights into theories of digitized archives and book history. Bonnie Mak, Ryan Cordell, Ian Gadd, Stephen H. Gregg, and Diana Kichuk have argued for emphasizing the particularity, even materiality of each digital text, which becomes a new object rather than a failed reproduction of another one. As Gregg writes, “Transform the book into another medium (‘remediation’) and you change the meanings of the book” [Gregg 2020]. Cordell argues that “we must reckon with mass digitized historical texts as new and discrete bibliographic objects, which is to say as objects worthy of and available for source criticism” [Cordell 2017, 190]. This is a difficult task, as readers most often come to EEBO in search of early modern originals, albeit with an awareness of those originals’ mediations. The insistent virtuality of an online database—which can, for instance, block a viewer out of the archive if her browser window has remained inactive too long—makes it even more difficult to conceive of a digital object as discrete and unique. The crux of this challenge, Cordell argues, is that “of apprehending: of seeing the digital object as such, as an artifact with a distinct materiality and sociology” [Cordell 2017, 192]. Cordell articulates the need for a more granular and attentive digital history, an expectation of the medium that mirrors the enthusiasm many early modernists express for book history. And yet these forms of history often work at cross purposes. Kichuk, who gives an extensive history and theory of the “remediations” of EEBO, points out that most of the database’s users “[gaze] through [the] veil, seduced by the transformations wrought by remediation, [and suspend] disbelief in order to advance the study of the text” [Kichuk 2007, 299]. In response, feminist production studies insists upon the materiality of the veil. 
</p>
<p>
    This method articulates how digitized texts preserve multiple moments of history in a palimpsestic form. This is especially important for EEBO, which purports to represent the relatively distant early modern past. Its digitization catalogues the intermediary forces that have stewarded that past. As Mak writes, “As a product of human labor, a digitization transmits clues in its very instantiation about the circumstances of its manufacture and dissemination” [Mak 2014, 1515]. Mak argues that the best way to glimpse the materiality of a digitization is to know its history: its legacies of labor and touch. In this way, she contradicts the first early modernist responses to the archive, like that of reviewer John P. Schmitt, who wrote that using EEBO was “a little like waking up in the British Library after closing time” [Schmitt 2003]. Informed by production studies, my reading of EEBO redirects attention from the simulated experience of the reader to those of the women who actually worked in the British Museum and Victoria and Albert Museum during the 1940s. 
</p>        
<p>
    In what follows, I begin by tracing the trajectory of EEBO’s construction, focusing on the women who gathered its holdings, managed correspondence and translation, and photographed each page. First, I sketch a history of the EEBO archive, including details of its creation, daily operations, and equipment; I also give a thick description of the fingered images themselves. Second, I describe the women who served as administrators and secretaries for the copying project, analyzing both their appearances in and absences from important historical records. I pay special attention to the writing and photography of Lucia Moholy, whose art photography provides artistic referents for a visual analysis of the microfilmed fingers. The presence of these digits in the margins reflects a set of interlocking historical developments: the dawn of [digit]ization, the role of reproductive labor in both avant-garde art and archive-keeping, and the increasing power of American corporations to maintain and control data. Contextualizing these developments leads to a new theorization of the finger as a shifting transhistorical signal of embodied reading, from the early modern manicule to the digital cursor. Finally, I argue that the fingers in these images point toward a labor tradition that has permeated late capitalism into the present: the human mediation—often labor performed by underpaid women in the Global South—required to prop up all forms of automated work that benefit mega-corporations.  
</p>
 <p>
     <head>The British Museum at War: Eugene B. Power’s Modern Renaissance Archive</head>
     The history of EEBO is a war history; it begins not with the Second World War but with the first. Archivists from the Bibliographical Society at the British Museum compiled a volume entitled The Short Title Catalogue of Books Printed in English, Scotland, and Ireland and of English Books Printed Abroad (STC) beginning in 1918 as a response to “the potential for air raids during World War I and [their] fear that future wars might jeopardize the collections within Britain” [Martin 2007, 160]. This volume attempted to list every extant book published between 1471 and 1640, found largely at the British Museum, the Bodleian Library, and the Huntington Library. Archivists A. W. Pollard and G. R. Redgrave published the STC in 1926. As anticipation of another war intensified, the curation of this body changed hands, and its preservation became an industry unto itself. The vast conservation mission undertaken to protect English books and manuscripts marks only part of a frenzy of collection at work in the years immediately preceding the war.  Kathy Peiss’s Information Hunters [2019] catalogues this international scramble by “librarians, soldiers, and spies” to protect archives, often with cinematic flair. She argues that books came to represent the bastions of European culture and anti-Nazi principles that must be preserved during the German onslaught. “Even more important,” she writes, “wartime mobilization [of archive technologies] encouraged new aspirations among major libraries to achieve national leadership and international prominence through the development of foreign holdings” [Peiss 2019, 8]. The most obvious of these aspirations originated in the United States, whose acquisition of myriad European archives mirrors its ascension to unqualified global superpower in the post-war years. 
 </p>
 <p>
     According to Pamela Spence Richards, after attending the first World Congress of Documentation, organized by the League of Nations Institute of Intellectual Cooperation in Paris in March 1937, H.G. Wells called microfilm “a preserver of ‘the brain of mankind, the race brain’” [Richards 1988, 302]. At the same Congress, it became clear to many attendees that American microfilm technology was the most advanced in the world. By 1938, an American scholarly journal, The Journal of Documentary Reproduction, and corporation, University Microfilms International (UMI), had been created to sustain that reputation. In that year, UMI’s founder, entrepreneur Eugene B. Power, offered the services of his newly created company to make microfilm copies of every book listed in The Short Title Catalogue (Figure 3), a photography archive known as Early English Books (EEB). As preserved on EEBO today, this collection is known as STC I to distinguish it from the microfilm collection of works published 1641-1700 by bibliographer Donald Wing. A second edition with additions and corrections was published in three volumes in 1976, 1986, and 1991. The STC images included in this essay were part of Power’s original collection, which we can discern by their early reel numbers and their canonical status in the Short Title Catalogue published in 1927. 
 </p>
 <p>
     Power consistently describes his work as an emergency preservation project. “The Nazis,” he writes with signature mildness, “had the reputation of being book burners” [Power 1990, 117]. Considering libraries on the besieged continent a lost cause, Power focused his attention on England. As suggested by the title of his autobiography Edition of One, Power takes the vast majority of the credit for the preservation of EEB. In this account of himself as a singular innovator, Power resembles Roberto Busa, who has been depicted, Noëlle Schon claims, “as a lone scholar whose work marked a sharp break with the past” [Schon 2020]. We might think of Power as a Busa-like figure in the history of digitized early modern archives.  However, Power goes beyond Busa by making brief reference to the staff of women working in numerous archives to make microfilm copies of rare books. Nearly 900,000 pages of EEB were photographed in 1940-41 alone. This work was performed largely by women, as Power alludes, because so many young and junior male workers, including bus drivers and drill press operators, were at war. Of his hastily trained staff Power writes, “Too much cannot be said in praise of those who have done so well despite the handicaps of unfamiliar equipment and a strange technique” [Power 1944, 28]. Ironically, given his performed deference, Power mentions their leaders only briefly, and the team members not at all, requiring us to examine the literal and metaphorical perimeters of the archive to discern their contributions. 
 </p> 
 <p>
     The literal perimeters were shaped by the technology available to Power’s teams. The imaging process begun in 1940 predates cradle technology, a more advanced copying method that protects old books’ delicate spines while producing a complete photograph. The microfilm camera used during this period, the Kodak Recordak Microfile Model D, featured an adjustable camera that faced down on the document, which rested on a flat plate. As a result, the book had to be pinned flat against the plate in order to prevent page curvature and a black galley down the binding (Figure 3 and 4).     
 </p>               
                <figure xml:id="figure04">
                    <head>Aemelia Lanyer’s <title rend="italic">Salue Dues Rex Iudæorum</title> (1611) features the shadows of steadying features on every page. © British Library Board. STC 2nd 15227.5 reel 803:11. Images published with permission of ProQuest. Further reproduction is prohibited without permission. Images produced by ProQuest as part of Early Modern Books. www.proquest.com.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure4.png"/>
                    <figDesc>alt text</figDesc>
                </figure>     
             
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="banks2018" label="Banks 2018"> Banks, M. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Production Studies</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Feminist Media Histories</title>, 4.2 (2018): 157-161.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barker2013" label="Barker 2013"> Barker, J. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Be-Hold: Touch, Temporality, and the Cinematic Thumbnail Image.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Discourse: Journal for Theoretical Studies in Media and Culture</title>, 35:2 (2013): 194–211.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="beals2020" label="Beals, et al. 2020"> Beals, M. and Bell, E. (2020)
                    <title rend="quotes">The Atlas of Digitised Newspapers and Metadata: Reports
                        from Oceanic Exchanges.</title> <title rend="italic">Discourse: Journal for
                            Theoretical Studies in Media and Culture</title>, https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.11560059.v2.</bibl>        
                <bibl xml:id="bingham2010" label="Bingham 2010">Bingham, A. (2010) <title
                    rend="quotes">The Digitization of Newspaper Archives: Opportunities and
                    Challenges for Historians,</title><title rend="italic">Twentieth Century British
                        History</title>, 21:2 (2010): 225–231.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="conrad2019" label="Conrad 2019"> Conrad, E. (2019) <title rend="quotes">The Poet as Printer’s Fist: Walt Whitman’s Indicative Hand</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Nineteenth-Century Literature</title>, 74:1 (2019): 54–86.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cordell2017" label="Cordell 2017"> Cordell, R. (2017) <title
                    rend="quotes">’Q i-jtb the Raven’: Taking Dirty OCR Seriously,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Book History</title>, 20 pp. 188-225 (2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="delsandro2020" label="Delsandro 2020"> Delsandro, E., editor (2020)
                    <title rend="italic">Women Making Modernism</title>, University of Florida Press, Gainesville, FL, 2020.</bibl> 
                <bibl xml:id="dignazio2020" label="D’Ignazio and Klein 2020">D’Ignazio, K. and Klein, L.F., (2020) <title
                    rend="italic">Data Feminism</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Book History</title>, Massachusetts Institute of Technology Press, Boston, MA (2020).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fafinski2022" label="Fafinski 2022">Fafinski, M. (2022) <title
                    rend="quotes">Facsimile narratives: Researching the past in the age of digital reproduction</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 37:1 (2022): 94–108. (2022).</bibl>     
                <bibl xml:id="flint2011" label="Flint 2011">Flint, C. (2011) <title
                    rend="italic">The Appearance of Print in Eighteenth-century Fiction</title>,
                    Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="freeman2010" label="Freeman 2010">Freeman, E. (2010) <title rend="italic">Time Binds: Queer Temporalities, Queer Histories.</title>Duke University Press, Durham, NC (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fyfe2016" label="Fyfe 2016">Fyfe, P. (2016) <title rend="quotes">An Archaeology of Victorian Newspapers</title>, <title rend="italic">Victorian Periodicals Review</title>, 49:4 (2016): 546–77. Available at https://doi.org/10.1353/vpr.2016.0039.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gavin2017" label="Gavin 2017">Gavin, M. (2017) <title rend="quotes">How to Think About EEBO</title>, <title rend="italic">Textual Cultures</title>, 11:1/2 (2017): 70-105.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="goldsmith2013" label="Goldsmith 2013"> Goldsmith, K. (2013) <title rend="quotes">The Artful Accidents of Google Books</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The New Yorker</title>, December 4, 2013. DOI: https://www.newyorker.com/books/page-turner/the-artful-accidents-of-google-books</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gray2019" label="Gray and Suri 2019"> Gray and Suri (2019) <title rend="italic">Ghost Work: How to Stop Silicon Valley from Building a New Global Underclass</title>.  Houghton Mifflin Harcourt, Boston, MA, 2019. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gregg2020" label="Gregg 2020">Gregg, S. <title rend="italic">Old Books and Digital Publishing: The History of Eighteenth-Century Collections Online.</title> Cambridge, Cambridge University Press (2020). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="grimmelmann2009" label="Grimmelmann 2009">Grimmelmann, J. <title rend="quotes">The Google Book Search Settlement: Ends, Means, and the Future of Books,</title> <title rend="italic">The American Constitution Society for Law and Policy</title>. https://www.acslaw.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Grimmelman_Issue_Brief.pdf</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hauswedell2020" label="Hauswedell et al 2020">Hausewedell T., Nyhan, J., Beals, M.H. et al. <title rend="quotes">Of global reach yet of situated contexts: an examination of the implicit and explicit selection criteria that shape digital archives of historical newspapers.</title> <title rend="italic">Arch Sci</title> 20 (2020): 139–165.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="heffernan2020" label="Heffernan and Sagner Buurma 2020">Heffernan, L, and Sagner Buurma, R. <title rend="italic">The Teaching Archive: A New History for Literary Study.</title> Chicago, University of Chicago Press (2020).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hoffman2016" label="Hoffman and Bloom 2016">Hoffman, A. L. and Raina Bloom. <title rend="quotes">Digitizing Books, Obscuring Women’s Work: Google Books, Librarians, and Ideologies of Access.</title>  <title rend="italic">ADA: A Journal of Gender, New Media, and Technology</title> 9 (2016), https://adanewmedia.org/2016/05/issue9-hoffmann-and-bloom/.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="houston2013" label="Houston 2013">Houston, K. <title rend="italic">Shady Characters: The Secret Life of Punctuation, Symbols, and Other Typographical Marks.</title> Norton, New York (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="irani2015" label="Irani 2015">Irani, L. <title rend="quotes">Justice for Data Janitors,</title>  Public Books (2015) https://www.publicbooks.org/justice-for-data-janitors/</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jacob2020" label="Jacob 2020">Jacob, A. <title rend="quotes">Punching Holes in the International Busa Machine Narrative</title>. <title rend="italic">IDEAH</title>, 1:1 (2020) https://doi.org/10.21428/f1f23564.d7d097c2</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kichuk2007" label="Kichuk 2007">Kichuk, D. <title rend="quotes">Metamorphosis: Remediation in Early English Books Online (EEBO)</title>, <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 23.2 (2007): 291-303.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="klein2020" label="Klein 2020">Kichuk, D. <title rend="quotes">Dimensions of Scale: Invisible Labor, Editorial Work, and the Future of Quantitative Literary Studies</title>, <title rend="italic">PMLA/Publications of the Modern Language Association of America</title> 135.1 (2020): 23–39.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lesser2019" label="Lesser 2010">Lesser, Z. <title rend="quotes">Xeroxing the Renaissance: The Material Text of Early Modern Studies</title>, <title rend="italic">Shakespeare Quarterly</title>, 70.1 (2019): 2-31.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="make2014" label="Mak 2014">Mak, B. <title rend="quotes">Archeology of a Digitization</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology</title> 6.8 (2014): 1515-1526.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="marek1996" label="Marek 1996">Marek, J. <title rend="italic">Women Editing Modernism: ‘Little’ Magazines and Literary History.</title> The University Press of Kentucky, Lexington, KY, 1996.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="martin2007" label="Martin 2007">Martin, S. <title rend="quotes">EEBO, Microfilm, and Umberto Eco: Historical Lessons and Future Directions for Building Electronic Collections</title>, <title rend="italic">Microform and Imaging Review</title>, 36.4 (2007): 159-164.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="meuel2016" label="Meuel 2016">Meuel, D. <title rend="italic">Women Film Editors: Unseen Artists of the American Cinema</title>. McFarland and Company, Inc., Jefferson, North Carolina, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="micir2019" label="Micir 2019">Micir, M. <title rend="italic">The Passion Projects: Modernist Women, Intimate Archives, Unfinished Live.</title>. Princeton University Press, Princeton, NJ, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moholy1939" label="Moholy 1939">Moholy, L. <title rend="italic">A Hundred Years of Photography, 1839-1938</title>. Pelican, London, 1939.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moholy1942" label="Moholy 1942">Moholy, L. <title rend="quotes">Microfilm Services in War</title>. <title rend="italic">Full Report of the Year’s Work and Accounts of Aslib</title>, (1942): 7-10.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moholy1946" label="Moholy 1946">Moholy, L. <title rend="quotes">The New Microfilm Project for Disabled Persons</title>. <title rend="italic">The Work of ASLIB 1945-1946</title>, (1946): 82-84.</bibl>
                
                
                
                
                
                <bibl></bibl>
            </listBibl>
            
             
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
