<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Fingerprints of British Book History: A Feminist Labor History of EEBO</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Ana<dhq:family>Quiring</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID"><!-- if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000 --></idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Author's School Affiliation</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email></email>
                    <dhq:bio><p></p></dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!-- including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110 -->000718</idno>
                <idno type="volume"><!-- volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date></date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->                    
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    
                    <!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new <term> element for each -->
                    <term corresp=""/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item></item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item></item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Replace "XXXXXX" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
            <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target=
                "https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000718/000718.xml">GitHub
            </ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
               <p> In this essay, I give a labor history of the commonly used database Early English Book Online. EEBO began its life as a mirofilm archive produced beginning in 1940: a massive book-copying project was undertaken during World War II to protect rare books from German bombs. These reproductions were made largely by unnamed woman archivists and led by a team of woman photographers, academics, and secretaries. In this essay, I draw on existing theories and histories of EEBO while highlighting these women's work, which manifests in the photographs through the shadows of the fingertips they used to pin down the fragile books. This archive of reproductive labor exemplifies the artificial divide between auteur and stenographer, artist and secretary, that animated many of the early twentieth century’s avant-garde movements, including ones in which EEBO photographers were intimately involved. The fingers represent the custodial labor of women working across artistic and administrative modes during World War II and the decades that followed. 
</p>            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p></p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>
Upon its founding in 2002, Google Books promised its users the world  <ptr target="#hoffman2016"/>. “Imagine,” wrote then-CEO Eric Schmitt, “the cultural impact of putting tens of millions of previously inaccessible volumes into one vast index, every word of which is searchable by anyone, rich and poor, urban and rural, First World and Third, <hi rend="italic">en toute langue</hi>—and all, of course, entirely for free”  <ptr target="#schmidt2005"/>. Nearly twenty years later, the service has indeed become a ubiquitous online resource, one with a mixed reputation among digital humanists  <ptr target="#noble2018"/>, <ptr target="#newman2011"/>, <ptr target="#grimmelmann2009"/>. Its errors—evidence of imperfect human mediation—are also commonplace. In 2011, artist and writer Krissy Wilson began collecting these errors on her blog  <title rend="italic">The Art of Google Books</title>. Wilson’s archive, which includes submissions from readers, catalogues the ephemeral flaws made before and during the copying process: a forgotten library slip with check-out dates spanning thirty years; a blurred page, photographed as it is turned; rips in the paper; ink stains. However, the most common and most eloquent error captured by  <title rend="italic">The Art of Google Books</title> concerns the trace of human labor in the archive’s production. Google’s scanning cameras often capture the fingers and hands of the low-wage workers who hold open each book. They often wear pink or blue finger rubbers, minimizing the wear and tear book-handling exerts on the skin. The images largely depict Black and brown hands, suggesting the demographics of this low-paid work (Figure 1). The bad scans capture the process of unspectacular labor as it occurs. In consequence, they are an artful and poignant visible record of the work that digital humanists have recently sought to recover  <ptr target="#klein2020"/>, <ptr target="#nyhan2020"/>
                    </p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure01">
                            <figDesc> This worker’s hand obscures the book plate and check-out slip for Edward Young’s <I>The Complaint; or, Night-thoughts on Life, Death, and Immortality</I> (1750). The original is held by Oxford University and was digitized by an anonymous worker on August 2, 2007.</figDesc>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure1.png"/>
                        </figure>
                <p>
                        The Art of Google Books demonstrates the continuity between contemporary digitization practices and a longer history of archival touch. Scholars have examined the abuses of Google’s digital practices and their implications for both archival labor and intellectual property [Noble 2018, Hoffman and Bloom 2016, Segev 2010]. In this essay, I extend this work to trace a cultural history of the photographed finger. I do so through a focus on the labor history embedded in one literary database: Early English Books Online (EEBO). Several critics have catalogued the palimpsestic nature of this digital archive, which reveals the circumstances in which the database was produced, beginning during the crucible of World War II, in an international scramble to photograph every extant early modern book as the threat of German occupation increased [Schmitt 2003, Peiss 2019, Mak 2014, Kichuk 2007]. Less known are the experiences of the photographers and librarians who created the archive. Teams of women in the backrooms of universities and museums made thousands of microfilm reels during the war and continuing afterward. The evidence of their labor is anything but invisible. The images they created include stunning and mundane traces of their work, cluttering the lower margins of manuscript pages, their fingertips a silent motif that persists into the Google Books era (Figure 2). 
                </p>
                            
                            
                            
                            
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="author name year"> lastname. (year) <title rend="quotes">quouted text</title>
                    <title rend="italic">italics</title>, <ref target="">url plain text</ref>. Accessed... </bibl>
                <bibl></bibl>
            </listBibl>
            
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
