<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
	xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
	xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
				<title type="article" xml:lang="en">Fingerprints of British Book History: A Feminist Labor
					History of EEBO</title>
				<!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
					<dhq:author_name>Ana <dhq:family>Quiring</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID"
						><!-- if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000 --></idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>Washington University in St. Louis</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>quiring@wustl.edu</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p/>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
				<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
				<!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
				<idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!-- including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110 -->000718</idno>
				<idno type="volume"
					><!-- volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006 --></idno>
				<idno type="issue"><!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
				<date/>
				<dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
				<availability status="CC-BY-ND">
					<!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->
					<cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>This is the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
					<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en" extent="original"/>
				<!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
					<!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
					<!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new <term> element for each -->
					<term corresp="#digitization"/>
					<term corresp="#gender"/>
					<term corresp="#glam"/>
					<term corresp="#race"/>
					<term corresp="#gender"/>
					<term corresp="#materialisms"/>
					<term corresp="#data_curation"/>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
					<!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
					<list type="simple">
						<item>invisible labor</item>
						<item>World War II</item>
						<item>Lucia Moholy</item>
						<item>microfilm</item>
						<item>EEBO </item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!-- Replace "XXXXXX" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
			<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
					target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000718/000718.xml"
					>GitHub </ref></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
	<text xml:lang="en" type="original">
		<front>
			<dhq:abstract>
				<p>In this essay, I give a labor history of the commonly used database Early English Books
					Online. EEBO began its life as a mirofilm archive produced beginning in 1940: a massive
					book-copying project was undertaken during World War II to protect rare books from German
					bombs. These reproductions were made largely by unnamed woman archivists and led by a team
					of woman photographers, academics, and secretaries. In this essay, I draw on existing
					theories and histories of EEBO while highlighting these women's work, which manifests in
					the photographs through the shadows of the fingertips they used to pin down the fragile
					books. This archive of reproductive labor exemplifies the artificial divide between auteur
					and stenographer, artist and secretary, that animated many of the early twentieth
					century’s avant-garde movements, including ones in which EEBO photographers were
					intimately involved. The fingers represent the custodial labor of women working across
					artistic and administrative modes during World War II and the decades that followed. </p>
			</dhq:abstract>
			<dhq:teaser>
				<!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
				<p/>
			</dhq:teaser>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div>
				<head/>
				<p>Upon its founding in 2002, Google Books promised its users the world <ptr
						target="#hoffman_etal2016"/>. <quote rend="inline" source="#hoffman_etal2016"
						>Imagine,</quote> wrote then-CEO Eric Schmitt, <quote rend="inline">the cultural
						impact of putting tens of millions of previously inaccessible volumes into one vast
						index, every wor)d of which is searchable by anyone, rich and poor, urban and rural,
						First World and Third, <foreign xml:lang="fr">en toute langue</foreign> — and all, of
						course, entirely for free</quote>
					<ptr target="#schmidt2005"/>. Nearly twenty years later, the service has indeed become a
					ubiquitous online resource, one with a mixed reputation among digital humanists <ptr
						target="#noble2018"/>, <ptr target="#newman2011"/>, <ptr target="#grimmelmann2009"/>.
					Its errors — evidence of imperfect human mediation — are also commonplace. In 2011, artist
					and writer Krissy Wilson began collecting these errors on her blog <title rend="italic"
						>The Art of Google Books</title>. Wilson’s archive, which includes submissions from
					readers, catalogues the ephemeral flaws made before and during the copying process: a
					forgotten library slip with check-out dates spanning thirty years; a blurred page,
					photographed as it is turned; rips in the paper; ink stains. However, the most common and
					most eloquent error captured by <title rend="italic">The Art of Google Books</title>
					concerns the trace of human labor in the archive’s production. Google’s scanning cameras
					often capture the fingers and hands of the low-wage workers who hold open each book. They
					often wear pink or blue finger rubbers, minimizing the wear and tear book-handling exerts
					on the skin. The images largely depict Black and brown hands, suggesting the demographics
					of this low-paid work (<ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>). The bad scans capture the
					process of unspectacular labor as it occurs. In consequence, they are an artful and
					poignant visible record of the work that digital humanists have recently sought to recover
						<ptr target="#klein2020"/>, <ptr target="#nyhan2020"/></p>
				<figure xml:id="figure01">
					<head> This worker’s hand obscures the book plate and check-out slip for Edward Young’s
							<title rend="italic">The Complaint; or, Night-thoughts on Life, Death, and
							Immortality</title> (1750). The original is held by Oxford University and was
						digitized by an anonymous worker on August 2, 2007.</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
					<figDesc>A composite of two hands each holding a book flat</figDesc>
				</figure>
				<p><title rend="italic">The Art of Google Books</title> demonstrates the continuity between
					contemporary digitization practices and a longer history of archival touch. Scholars have
					examined the abuses of Google’s digital practices and their implications for both archival
					labor and intellectual property <ptr target="#noble2018"/>, <ptr
						target="#hoffman_etal2016"/>, <ptr target="#segev2010"/>. In this essay, I extend this
					work to trace a cultural history of the photographed finger. I do so through a focus on
					the labor history embedded in one literary database: Early English Books Online (EEBO).
					Several critics have catalogued the palimpsestic nature of this digital archive, which
					reveals the circumstances in which the database was produced, beginning during the
					crucible of World War II, in an international scramble to photograph every extant early
					modern book as the threat of German occupation increased <ptr target="#schmitt2003"/>,
						<ptr target="#peiss2019"/>, <ptr target="#mak2014"/>, <ptr target="#kichuk2007"/>.
					Less known are the experiences of the photographers and librarians who created the
					archive. Teams of women in the backrooms of universities and museums made thousands of
					microfilm reels during the war and continuing afterward. The evidence of their labor is
					anything but invisible. The images they created include stunning and mundane traces of
					their work, cluttering the lower margins of manuscript pages, their fingertips a silent
					motif that persists into the Google Books era (<ref target="#figure02">Figure
					2</ref>).</p>
				<figure xml:id="figure02">
					<head>The first page of a 1595 copy of Sir Philip Sidney’s <title rend="italic">The
							Defence of Poesie</title> has been photographed with the fingers of the
						photographer visible in the lower corners of each page. © British Library Board. STC
						2nd edition 22535 reel 904:16. Images published with permission of ProQuest. Further
						reproduction is prohibited without permission. Images produced by ProQuest as part of
						Early Modern Books. <ref target="http://www.proquest.com"
						>www.proquest.com</ref>.</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
					<figDesc>A black and white scan of a page with fingers visible</figDesc>
				</figure>
				<p>This essay centers EEBO’s photographed fingertips as interventions in the archive,
					analyzing not only their historical significance but also the conceptual import of their
					visual mark on images of the English literary canon. Reading EEBO’s fingers focalizes the
					digital object as distinct from print, and acknowledges the feminized labor needed to
					produce it. This reading practice also activates a centuries-long material and conceptual
					history of interaction between hand and page, one that spans a series of technological
					evolutions. EEBO and its fingers mark the transition from analog to digital, through the
					intimate technology of the digit — the index finger. This archive of reproductive labor
					exemplifies the artificial divide between auteur and stenographer, artist and secretary,
					that animated many of the early twentieth century’s avant-garde movements, including ones
					in which EEBO, then called Early English Books (EEB), photographers were intimately
					involved. In what follows, I chronicle the women who lived this divide, including
					secretary Margaret Harwick, librarian-spy Adele Kibre, and Bauhaus photographer Lucia
					Moholy, whose work in both microfilm and avant-garde photography theorized <cit><quote
							rend="inline">the invisible hand of the artist-as-reproducer</quote><ptr
							target="#troeller2020" loc="86"/></cit>. The largely untold stories of these
					artists throw into relief the self-hagiography of the archive’s presumed architect, Eugene
					Power. Read in this context, the signature contribution of the EEB images is that they
					render reproductive labor literally visible, in the form of a fingernail imprinted at the
					edge of a textual artifact. The fingers represent the custodial labor of women working
					across artistic and administrative modes during World War II and the decades that
					followed. At the same time, they render visible the text’s transition into a new form of
					commodity, repackaged for new sites of purchase and distribution, their specific visual
					arrangement testifying to the text’s valuation and evaluation at a key moment in literary
					history.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>A Note on Methodology: Piercing the Digital Veil</head>
				<p>Studying the production history of EEBO places my work in conversation with a growing
					tradition of feminist digital humanists. Integrating feminist practices into the digital
					humanities has required its practitioners to, as <name>Catherine D’Ignazio</name> and
						<name>Lauren Klein</name> write, <quote rend="inline" source="#dignazio_etal2020">show
						[their] work.</quote> Their book, Data Feminism <ref target="#dignazio_etal2020"
						>2020</ref>, argues that digital spaces depend on invisible labor forces. In fact,
						<quote rend="inline" source="#dignazio_etal2020">invisible labor</quote> has become a
					central formulation in digital studies. The predicament is a feminist one,
						<name>Klein</name> writes elsewhere, because women have traditionally been tasked with
					myriad forms of uncredited work, from cleaning and child-rearing to editing, typesetting,
					data entry, and archive maintenance <ptr target="#klein2020"/>. An important example of
					this shift is recent scholarship on digital humanities pioneers like <name>Josephine
						Miles</name>, who invented a form of quantitative reading while teaching at UC
					Berkeley in the 1950s <ptr target="#heffernan_etal2020"/>, <ptr target="#pasanek2019"/>.
						<name>Julianne Nyhan</name> has illuminated the work of the 65 keypunch operators,
					many of them woman, who worked with <name>Roberto Busa</name>, the so-called father of the
					digital humanities <ptr target="#nyhan2020"/>. Still more scholars have traced extensive
					histories of digitized archives of newspapers <ptr target="#fyfe2016"/>, <ptr
						target="#beals_etal2020"/>, <ptr target="#bingham2010"/>, <ptr target="#fafinski2022"
					/>, <ptr target="#hauswedell_etal2020"/>. We can also draw inspiration from the emerging
					field of production studies, begun in film and media studies and now borrowed by many
					feminist digital humanists. Production studies attends to the quotidian and collective
					labor of making art. The field, <name>Miranda Banks</name> writes, is profoundly <quote
						rend="inline" source="#banks2018">anti-auterist,</quote> deflating the cults of
					personality that often define filmmaking in favor of cataloguing the many tasks that bring
					a film to life. This is a feminist methodology in large part because it <cit><quote
							rend="inline">highlights production at the margins</quote><ptr target="#banks2018"
							loc="157"/></cit>. The microfilmed EEBO archive provides an apt opportunity for a
					production studies approach, its margins quite literally highlighted by the cluttered
					residue of its production.</p>
				<p>Methodologically, production studies contends with the occlusions of reproductive labor.
						<name>Jordan Troeller</name> articulates the challenge this insight poses for studying
					artists such as <name>Lucia Moholy</name>, whose work in the <term>Bauhaus school</term>
					during the 1920s and 1930s<!-- regularized to 1930s from '30s in original --> was often
					overshadowed and outright stolen by her husband, the more famous <name>László
						Moholy-Nagy</name>. <name>Troeller</name> writes, <cit><quote rend="inline">Coded as
								<q>reproductive,</q> in distinction to the <q>productive</q> work of her male
							colleagues, Moholy’s photography was not maliciously ignored so much as it was
							naturalized as a labor of love on the part of a devoted wife, whose status as an
							artist was never seriously considered</quote><ptr target="#troeller2020" loc="75"
						/></cit>. Troeller describes a hierarchy of labor that separates the original from the
					reproduced, and, importantly, the artistic from the technical. While Moholy-Nagy shot the
					camera, it was most often his wife who actually produced his images in the darkroom.
					According to Moholy, her husband viewed technical knowledge as <cit><quote rend="inline"
							>derivative... in comparison to the more consequential work of the painter and
							architect</quote><ptr target="#troeller2020" loc="82"/></cit>. This divide, which
					characterized the artistic philosophy of the Bauhaus more generally, mirrors the gendered
					hierarchies in literary modernism between authors and midwife-editors and in bibliographic
					societies between male museum and library directors and female secretaries, treasurers,
					and copyists, the so-called <q>handmaidens of history.</q> The first several decades of
					the twentieth century, which saw women gain access to the professions in growing numbers,
					not to mention the loss of thousands of men from the workforce due to two world wars, are
					prime territory for interrogating the ever-flimsier divide between artistic and
					reproductive labor, as research in art history and literary studies has demonstrated <ptr
						target="#troeller2020"/>, <ptr target="#richards2020"/>, <ptr target="#delsandro2020"
					/>, <ptr target="#otto_etal2019"/>, <ptr target="#micir2019"/>, <ptr target="#wagner1998"
					/>, <ptr target="#marek1996"/>.</p>
				<p>Putting production studies in conversation with existing histories of EEBO leads to new
					feminist insights into theories of digitized archives and book history. Bonnie Mak, Ryan
					Cordell, Ian Gadd, Stephen H. Gregg, and Diana Kichuk have argued for emphasizing the
					particularity, even materiality of each digital text, which becomes a new object rather
					than a failed reproduction of another one. As Gregg writes, <cit><quote rend="inline"
							>Transform the book into another medium (<q>remediation</q>) and you change the
							meanings of the book</quote><ptr target="#gregg2020"/></cit>. Cordell argues that
							<cit><quote rend="inline">we must reckon with mass digitized historical texts as
							new and discrete bibliographic objects, which is to say as objects worthy of and
							available for source criticism</quote><ptr target="#cordell2017" loc="190"
					/></cit>. This is a difficult task, as readers most often come to EEBO in search of early
					modern originals, albeit with an awareness of those originals’ mediations. The insistent
					virtuality of an online database — which can, for instance, block a viewer out of the
					archive if her browser window has remained inactive too long — makes it even more
					difficult to conceive of a digital object as discrete and unique. The crux of this
					challenge, Cordell argues, is that <cit><quote rend="inline">of apprehending: of seeing
							the digital object as such, as an artifact with a distinct materiality and
							sociology</quote><ptr target="#cordell2017" loc="192"/></cit>. Cordell articulates
					the need for a more granular and attentive digital history, an expectation of the medium
					that mirrors the enthusiasm many early modernists express for book history. And yet these
					forms of history often work at cross purposes. Kichuk, who gives an extensive history and
					theory of the <quote rend="inline" source="#kichuk2007">remediations</quote> of EEBO,
					points out that most of the database’s users <cit><quote rend="inline">[gaze] through
							[the] veil, seduced by the transformations wrought by remediation, [and suspend]
							disbelief in order to advance the study of the text</quote><ptr
							target="#kichuk2007" loc="299"/></cit>. In response, feminist production studies
					insists upon the materiality of the veil.</p>
				<p>This method articulates how digitized texts preserve multiple moments of history in a
					palimpsestic form. This is especially important for EEBO, which purports to represent the
					relatively distant early modern past. Its digitization catalogues the intermediary forces
					that have stewarded that past. As Mak writes, <cit><quote rend="inline">As a product of
							human labor, a digitization transmits clues in its very instantiation about the
							circumstances of its manufacture and dissemination</quote><ptr target="#mak2014"
							loc="1515"/></cit>. Mak argues that the best way to glimpse the materiality of a
					digitization is to know its history: its legacies of labor and touch. In this way, she
					contradicts the first early modernist responses to the archive, like that of reviewer John
					P. Schmitt, who wrote that using EEBO was <cit><quote rend="inline">a little like waking
							up in the British Library after closing time</quote><ptr target="#schmitt2003"
						/></cit>. Informed by production studies, my reading of EEBO redirects attention from
					the simulated experience of the reader to those of the women who actually worked in the
					British Museum and Victoria and Albert Museum during the 1940s.</p>
				<p>In what follows, I begin by tracing the trajectory of EEBO’s construction, focusing on the
					women who gathered its holdings, managed correspondence and translation, and photographed
					each page. First, I sketch a history of the EEBO archive, including details of its
					creation, daily operations, and equipment; I also give a thick description of the fingered
					images themselves. Second, I describe the women who served as administrators and
					secretaries for the copying project, analyzing both their appearances in and absences from
					important historical records. I pay special attention to the writing and photography of
					Lucia Moholy, whose art photography provides artistic referents for a visual analysis of
					the microfilmed fingers. The presence of these digits in the margins reflects a set of
					interlocking historical developments: the dawn of [digit]ization, the role of reproductive
					labor in both avant-garde art and archive-keeping, and the increasing power of American
					corporations to maintain and control data. Contextualizing these developments leads to a
					new theorization of the finger as a shifting transhistorical signal of embodied reading,
					from the early modern manicule to the digital cursor. Finally, I argue that the fingers in
					these images point toward a labor tradition that has permeated late capitalism into the
					present: the human mediation — often labor performed by underpaid women in the Global
					South — required to prop up all forms of automated work that benefit mega-corporations.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>The British Museum at War: Eugene B. Power’s Modern Renaissance Archive</head>
				<p>The history of EEBO is a war history; it begins not with the Second World War but with the
					first. Archivists from the Bibliographical Society at the British Museum compiled a volume
					entitled The Short Title Catalogue of Books Printed in English, Scotland, and Ireland and
					of English Books Printed Abroad (STC) beginning in 1918 as a response to <cit><quote
							rend="inline">the potential for air raids during World War I and [their] fear that
							future wars might jeopardize the collections within Britain</quote><ptr
							target="#martin2007" loc="160"/></cit>. This volume attempted to list every extant
					book published between 1471 and 1640, found largely at the British Museum, the Bodleian
					Library, and the Huntington Library. Archivists A. W. Pollard and G. R. Redgrave published
					the STC in 1926. As anticipation of another war intensified, the curation of this body
					changed hands, and its preservation became an industry unto itself. The vast conservation
					mission undertaken to protect English books and manuscripts marks only part of a frenzy of
					collection at work in the years immediately preceding the war. Kathy Peiss’s <title
						rend="italic">Information Hunters</title>
					<ref target="#peiss2019">2019</ref> catalogues this international scramble by <quote
						rend="inline" source="#peiss2019">librarians, soldiers, and spies</quote> to protect
					archives, often with cinematic flair. She argues that books came to represent the bastions
					of European culture and anti-Nazi principles that must be preserved during the German
					onslaught. <quote rend="inline" source="#peiss2019">Even more important,</quote> she
					writes, <cit><quote rend="inline">wartime mobilization [of archive technologies]
							encouraged new aspirations among major libraries to achieve national leadership
							and international prominence through the development of foreign
							holdings</quote><ptr target="#peiss2019" loc="8"/></cit>. The most obvious of
					these aspirations originated in the United States, whose acquisition of myriad European
					archives mirrors its ascension to unqualified global superpower in the post-war years.</p>
				<p>According to Pamela Spence Richards, after attending the first World Congress of
					Documentation, organized by the League of Nations Institute of Intellectual Cooperation in
					Paris in March 1937, H.G. Wells called microfilm <cit><quote rend="inline">a preserver of
							the brain of mankind, the race brain</quote><ptr target="#richards1988" loc="302"
						/></cit>. At the same Congress, it became clear to many attendees that American
					microfilm technology was the most advanced in the world. By 1938, an American scholarly
					journal, The Journal of Documentary Reproduction, and corporation, University Microfilms
					International (UMI), had been created to sustain that reputation. In that year, UMI’s
					founder, entrepreneur Eugene B. Power, offered the services of his newly created company
					to make microfilm copies of every book listed in The Short Title Catalogue (<ref
						target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref>), a photography archive known as Early English Books
					(EEB). As preserved on EEBO today, this collection is known as STC I to distinguish it
					from the microfilm collection of works published 1641-1700 by bibliographer Donald Wing. A
					second edition with additions and corrections was published in three volumes in 1976,
					1986, and 1991. The STC images included in this essay were part of Power’s original
					collection, which we can discern by their early reel numbers and their canonical status in
					the Short Title Catalogue published in 1927.</p>
				<p>Power consistently describes his work as an emergency preservation project. <quote
						rend="inline" source="#power1990">The Nazis,</quote> he writes with signature
					mildness, <cit><quote rend="inline">had the reputation of being book burners</quote><ptr
							target="#power1990" loc="117"/></cit>. Considering libraries on the besieged
					continent a lost cause, Power focused his attention on England. As suggested by the title
					of his autobiography Edition of One, Power takes the vast majority of the credit for the
					preservation of EEB. In this account of himself as a singular innovator, Power resembles
					Roberto Busa, who has been depicted, Noëlle Schon claims, <cit><quote rend="inline">as a
							lone scholar whose work marked a sharp break with the past</quote><ptr
							target="#schon2020"/></cit>. We might think of Power as a Busa-like figure in the
					history of digitized early modern archives. However, Power goes beyond Busa by making
					brief reference to the staff of women working in numerous archives to make microfilm
					copies of rare books. Nearly 900,000 pages of EEB were photographed in 1940-41 alone. This
					work was performed largely by women, as Power alludes, because so many young and junior
					male workers, including bus drivers and drill press operators, were at war. Of his hastily
					trained staff Power writes, <cit><quote rend="inline">Too much cannot be said in praise of
							those who have done so well despite the handicaps of unfamiliar equipment and a
							strange technique</quote><ptr target="#power1944" loc="28"/></cit>. Ironically,
					given his performed deference, Power mentions their leaders only briefly, and the team
					members not at all, requiring us to examine the literal and metaphorical perimeters of the
					archive to discern their contributions.</p>
				<p>The literal perimeters were shaped by the technology available to Power’s teams. The
					imaging process begun in 1940 predates cradle technology, a more advanced copying method
					that protects old books’ delicate spines while producing a complete photograph. The
					microfilm camera used during this period, the Kodak Recordak Microfile Model D, featured
					an adjustable camera that faced down on the document, which rested on a flat plate. As a
					result, the book had to be pinned flat against the plate in order to prevent page
					curvature and a black galley down the binding (<ref target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref> and
						<ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>).</p>
				<figure xml:id="figure03">
					<head><name>Aemelia Lanyer’s</name>
						<title rend="italic">Salue Dues Rex Iudæorum</title> (1611) features the shadows of
						steadying features on every page. © British Library Board. STC 2nd 15227.5 reel
						803:11. Images published with permission of ProQuest. Further reproduction is
						prohibited without permission. Images produced by ProQuest as part of Early Modern
						Books. <ref target="http://www.proquest.com">www.proquest.com</ref>.</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
					<figDesc>Grayscale scan of a book with dark area between pages</figDesc>
				</figure>
				<p>Many of the books that feature these marks have them on every page, suggesting that the way
					a book is bound and the person who photographed a particular book play a role in the
					circumstances of its reproduction. In photographs made in later decades, during
						<name>Donald Wing</name>’s tenure as chief bibliographer, the finger markings
					significantly decrease and photo quality increases. On the original microfilm reels, which
					in most cases feature between ten and twenty books, sometimes several consecutive books
					feature consistent finger markings, but just as often these are interrupted by unmarred
					images, suggesting that entire reels were not photographed successively or simultaneously.
					Despite the fact that a long roll of film gives the impression of linearity, each reel is
					a collage, patching together texts that do not share author, publication date, or even
					library of origin.</p>
				<p>At the start, Power planned for the reels to be produced and organized chronologically and
					alphabetically by author, and indeed the first 100 reels or so focus exclusively on late
					medieval manuscripts, including printings of Chaucer made in the late fifteenth
					century<!--
					(Figure 6) No figure exists-->. But shortly afterward, access to different libraries
					and the urgency of the bombings made the organization of the reels grow more haphazard,
					with Shakespeare’s plays included on reel 353, 675, 783, 904, 2403, and many more. The
					best explanation for this haphazardness is the decentered and overlapping groups doing
					preservation work during the war, especially given the varied locations of rare books,
					which were sometimes shipped to London or to the United States, and sometimes remained in
					place. According to Lucia Moholy, a committee under the direction of Dr. H. A. Kellar of
					the American Historical Association made inquiries and ultimate decisions about which
					books to document first. Copying projects under Kellar’s authority were carried out in
					London, Oxford, Cambridge, and Wales <ptr target="#moholy1942" loc="9"/>.</p>
				<p>These wartime efforts have had a long afterlife in both analog and digital archives, and
					thus remain relevant to contemporary users of online databases. Zachary Lesser has
					chronicled the 1950s and 60s initiative at the University of Pennsylvania to make Xerox
					reproductions of EEB microfilm texts, despite the fact that the university already owned
					the microfilm collection <ptr target="#lesser2019" loc="12"/>. According to Lesser,
					internal records show that Penn librarians viewed a Xerox archive of printed, codex books
					— unlike the technical struggle of microfilm — would establish the university’s holdings
					as a major force in early modern archives. A few decades later, when archivists began
					Early English Books Online in 1998, Proquest staff digitzed these microfilms rather than
					re-photographing the fragile books. These digitizations, like the Xeroxes, reverse the
					unending scroll of the microfilm reel in favor of mimicking the codex. However, these
						<emph>updated</emph> forms, which contribute their own original errors, depend on the
					microfilm as the <emph>original</emph> source of the material. As a result, the fingers of
					the photographers, alongside many other imperfections, remain preserved in the widely
					accessed online database. That database is fundamentally shaped by the wartime context of
					its creation — in effect, the first and last time all of these books would be
						<emph>together</emph> in order to be copied.</p>
				<p>These images, poignant on their own, are made even more striking by a knowledge of their
					production. But Power elides some of the most valuable information about this process in
					his autobiography, not least the central contributions of his staff and the wide array of
					bibliographic societies contributing to the photography effort. Although most of the
					photography was performed by unnamed laborers, several women working in administrative
					roles have left impressions on the microfilm’s history.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Secretaries, Photographers, and Spies: Microfilm’s Women Architects</head>
				<p>Power originally hired his eventual right-hand woman and CFO Margaret Harwick, whose
					corporate headshot is printed in Power’s book, as a secretary; she had recently lost her
					job at the Michigan Crippled Children’s Society <!--(Figure 7) No figure exists-->. <quote
						rend="inline" source="#power1990">I will never forget the look on Margaret’s face —
						she had been on the job all of one week — when I told her I was going to England on an
						important microfilming project and said, <said>You will be in charge,</said></quote>
					he writes <ptr target="#power1990" loc="37"/>. Power represents her as guileless and
					femininely competent, a tool for his genius, writing, <cit><quote rend="inline">If I were
							compiling a book of lessons for entrepreneurs based on my experience, a major
							point would be; Find someone like Margaret Harwick to be your right hand, and hire
							her as soon as you can</quote><ptr target="#power1990" loc="38"/></cit>. He frames
					Harwick’s capacity to run the entire corporation and oversee a great deal of microfilm
					photography when Power was abroad as a testament to his own sensibilities, but he also
					suggests the importance of her administrative labor in reproducing a vast intellectual
					archive.</p>
				<p>Another woman central to establishing UMI’s international reach was the American scholar
					and photographer Adele Kibre. Before the war, she traveled across Europe and made a living
					photographing rare manuscripts for scholars at the University of Chicago, where she had
					earned her PhD in medieval studies in 1930 <ptr target="#peiss2019" loc="121"/>. At the
					Vatican, she discovered microphotography and first met Eugene Power, who hired her to do
					freelance translation and photography work. Power described her as <cit><quote
							rend="inline">a real Mata Hari type</quote><ptr target="#power1990" loc="138"
						/></cit>, referencing her expatriate lifestyle and proficiency in several languages.
					Her relationship with the American government is shadowy; Peiss reports that her personnel
					file at the National Archives comprises one page. Once the United States entered the war,
					Kibre became an agent for the American Interdepartmental Committee for the Acquisition of
					Foreign Publications (IDC). She made the clandestine trip to Stockholm under the cover of
					bad weather, and remained stationed in Sweden, a neutral nation that could receive German
					periodicals embargoed in Britain and the United States, until the end of the war <ptr
						target="#peiss2019" loc="132"/>. While there, she collaborated with the British
					Ministry of Information to ship 192 reels of microfilm to London. Richards writes that
					Kibre, among other IDC agents, ordered subscriptions to the periodicals through
					cooperative or made-up Swedish citizen subscribers, and Peiss suggests that Kibre may have
					cultivated a friendship with Nazi party member Rolf Hoffman in order to receive his
					private mailings <ptr target="#peiss2019" loc="133"/>.</p>
				<p>In appropriate Mata Hari style, few photos of Kibre exist. While she <quote rend="inline"
						>was supposed to be terrific… at translating ancient inscriptions,</quote> she was
					also, according to Power, <cit><quote rend="inline">all thumbs mechanically. She simply
							could not operate the camera</quote><ptr target="#power1990" loc="139"/></cit>.
					Power’s account of Kibre’s skill, which unwittingly parodies the thumbs in the images
					themselves, contradicts Peiss’s research; she documents many recipients praising Kibre’s
					skill, although perhaps it developed over time. Kibre was certainly famous for her
					scrupulous recordkeeping, which could verge on the fanatical. As many microfilming
					missions <quote rend="inline" source="#peiss2019">scrambled,</quote> according to Peiss,
					to film everything in sight with somewhat haphazard methods, Kibre kept detailed lists of
					everything she photographed, including relatively insignificant periodicals and newspapers
						<ptr target="#peiss2019" loc="45"/>. In Power’s and Peiss’s renderings, Kibre is a
					marginal historical figure but nevertheless an ideal innovator for archive studies. As a
					librarian hero, her wartime bravery was outstripped only by her attention to detail.</p>
				<p>While Kibre made secret inroads in Stockholm, and Harwick managed daily operations in Ann
					Arbor, the book-photographing mission was conducted primarily in Britain, with Power
					making frequent visits. The urgency of photographing rare manuscripts and printed books
					increased as the war progressed, with Power acknowledging that the Blitz played a central
					part in the project’s decision to focus on the British Museum and other British holdings
						<ptr target="#power1944" loc="28"/>. At the outset, the British Museum did not warmly
					receive the intervention of this newly formed American corporation. According to Power,
					Sir John Forsdyke, the museum’s director, replied <quote rend="inline" source="#power1990"
						>frostily</quote> to their offer: <cit><quote rend="inline">Thank you very much, but
							the British Museum can take care of their own holdings</quote><ptr
							target="#power1990" loc="123"/></cit>. Early in the war, documentation efforts
					were decentralized, with government entities like the United States Office of Special
					Services, the German Society of Documentation, the British Association of Special
					Libraries and Information Bureaux (styled Aslib or ASLIB), and individual interests like
					UMI, the British Museum, and many public and university libraries, all pursuing their own
					archival projects. As bombing continued and libraries lost hundreds of thousands of
					volumes, these efforts were centralized under Power’s and Aslib’s administration. A great
					number of women worked as administrators and secretaries for Aslib, including treasurer
					Irene Shrigley and archivist and writer Edith M. R. Ditmas. In addition, Eleanor Cavanaugh
					and Ruth S. Leonard, employees of the American Special Library Association, visited London
					to give talks at Aslib’s annual conference. These women’s names almost exclusively appear
					in the archived Report of Proceedings for Aslib’s Annual Conference, held at the British
					Library. The most prominent Aslib employee was the director of its microfilm division:
					Lucia Moholy. During her tenure, Moholy oversaw Aslib’s photography efforts in Britain,
					which included not only many early modern books but hundreds of thousands of German
					scientific publications and classified government information.</p>
				<p>Moholy had first moved to London in 1933, after many years spent as part of the Bauhaus
					school in Dessau, Germany. She was never formally a student or instructor at the school,
					but a frequent collaborator with her husband on photography and writing projects for which
					she was rarely credited <ptr target="#schuldenfrei2013" loc="185"/>. After her exile to
					England and divorce from Moholy-Nagy, Moholy published a book, A Hundred Years of
					Photography, 1839-1939, in 1939. Her contributions to the modernist and sachlich
					(objective) photography movements have been partially recovered in art historical
					scholarship on photography, including work by Rolfe Sassche, Mercedes Valdivieso, Ulrike
					Müller, Robin Schuldenfrei, and Jordan Troeller, but a great deal of this criticism, as
					well as Moholy’s own writing, remains available only in German. Moholy’s underappreciated
					contributions to the history of photography run in illustrative parallel to the
					development of the EEB microfilm.</p>
				<p>In 1943, the Aslib Microfilm Service (AMS) moved from the Science Museum Library to the
					flat of the superintendent of the nearby Victoria and Albert Museum for more space <ptr
						target="#richards1989" loc="283"/>. Once there, Moholy oversaw a set of five Kodak
					Recordak Microfile Model D cameras manufactured in Rochester, New York, the highest
					quality available at the time. According to Moholy’s report on Aslib’s work during the
					war, published in the Journal of Documentation in 1946, the cameras were movable up and
					down their stands, and <cit><quote rend="inline">fitted with voltmeter, exposure meter,
							film footage counter, exposure counter, framing light, focusing device, a release
							for operation by hand or by foot, and an indicator showing the reduction which can
							be varied from 8 to 30 diameters</quote><ptr target="#moholy1946a" loc="150"
						/></cit>. The unit also made use of a Recordak Microfile Reader, Model C, and a Depue
					Printer, which transferred photo negatives to
					positives<!-- (Figure 8) No figure exists -->. Once a document was delivered to AMS
					headquarters, Moholy’s team of camera operators, largely women, had 24 hours to photograph
					and develop them <ptr target="#peiss2019" loc="46"/>. AMS’s total output during the war
					amounted to 5.5 million pages, and they indexed microfilms from other centers to the
					extent of 7 million more. Because Moholy had an existing relationship with the American
					Council of Learned Societies, where she had photographed <quote rend="inline"
						source="#peiss2019">valuable manuscripts and early printed books,</quote> AMS
					continued to oversee the photography of rare book material in addition to scientific
					publishing and classified government documents <ptr target="#moholy1946a" loc="158"/>. It
					is unclear how much of this photography overlapped or corresponded with the archive Power
					claimed as his own, although they had a lengthy collaboration. Neither in Moholy’s own
					account of her activities, nor in scholarly retellings, are the camera operators
					enumerated or named.</p>
				<p>In her contributions to Aslib’s Annual Conference and in published essays after the war,
					Moholy made clear that she considered evangelism about microfilm a large part of her role.
					Because Britain lagged behind the United States in manufacturing both cameras and readers,
					the technology had been less completely embraced, and her photography could be used by
					fewer customers. She was eager to expand this industry, which could respond to book
					shortages by serving <quote rend="inline" source="#moholy1946a">the intellectual needs of
						people in liberated countries</quote>, where micro-copies could supplement printed
					books that were not always available <ptr target="#moholy1946a" loc="159"/>. But Moholy
					was also invested in more innovative uses of the technology. In 1946, she introduced to
					Aslib the possibility of a microfilm reader designed for disabled people, especially
					wounded soldiers, using hospital beds. The mechanism would reflect the magnified image of
					the page onto the ceiling, so patients lying on their backs could read without moving in
					bed. Moholy mentioned that adaptions were in the works for patients who could not use
					their hands, or whose hands were in plaster casts <ptr target="#moholy1946b" loc="82"/>.
					This product was already under construction in the United States and not an invention of
					Moholy’s, but her presentation at Aslib’s annual conference demonstrates her holistic
					approach to the microfilm medium, which allowed for the preservation of enemy periodicals
					and rare English books, supplementing book shortages for hobby readers, and accommodation
					of disabled readers.</p>
				<p>In Power’s account, Moholy’s credentials are primarily technical. He writes that his
					project was <cit><quote rend="inline">advanced considerably when I discovered Lucia Moholy
							in London…. She was well versed in the techniques of microfilming. I hired her,
							and she recruited a crew of women to help her. At that time, of course, one saw
							women doing all kinds of work in England, from driving buses to running drill
							presses</quote><ptr target="#power1990" loc="135–136"/></cit>. Power describes
					Moholy as a capable technician, a shift leader who worked in the trenches of wartime
					preservation in the absence of more esteemed male colleagues. In this depiction, Power,
					perhaps unwittingly, reproduces the hierarchy of artistry that characterized the Bauhaus
					school. In a short statement entitled <quote rend="inline"
						>Production-Reproduction,</quote> Moholy’s husband Moholy-Nagy makes a strict division
					between creation and reproduction, writing, <cit><quote rend="inline">reproduction
							(reiteration of already existing relations) can be regarded for the most part as
							mere virtuosity</quote><ptr target="#moholynagy1922" loc="289"/></cit>. Power’s
					praise of Moholy alights upon her <quote rend="inline" source="#power1990">mere
						virtuousity</quote> as the force that will make her a good employee. He had no need
					for a creative artist, although the ultimate result of her work was more layered than he
					expected.</p>
				<p>A productive continuity emerges between Moholy’s art photography and her work with Aslib,
					considering Moholy’s personal photography of disembodied hands (<ref target="#figure04"
						>Figure 4</ref>). As Troeller writes, <cit><quote rend="inline">Moholy fragmented the
							body, identifying it with its parts and then again with its various forms of
							domestic (i.e., reproductive) labor — labor that was, like her own act of taking
							the image, maligned as artistically unmeaningful, <q>merely</q>
							reproductive</quote><ptr target="#troeller2020" loc="102"/></cit>. Moholy’s
					photography work takes on the character of the domestic work it depicts; both are
					unspectacular, <quote rend="inline" source="#troeller2020">idle,</quote> and repetitive.
					Moholy chooses the hands as the bodily fragment responsible for reproductive labor:
					precision tools that can depress the shutter release button on a camera as well as wring
					out wet laundry. The photography project she would oversee on an entirely different scale
					at the Victoria and Albert Museum also depicted hands at work. Like Moholy’s work in the
					darkroom for her husband, and like her own objective photography, the fingered EEB
					microfilms trouble the boundary between productive and reproductive, artistic and
					technical.</p>
				<figure xml:id="figure04">
					<head>Lucia Moholy, <title rend="italic">Hands Pinning Cloth</title>. 1930.</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
					<figDesc>A person's hands pin clothing at the waist</figDesc>
				</figure>
				<p>Despite working as an arm of Power’s corporation and the British government, the archive
					under Moholy’s supervision disrupts the legacy of early modern great masters that it
					claims to preserve. Its reproductive history is sutured to the <quote rend="inline"
						>original</quote> text. Considering the shared preoccupation with the hands and
					fingers between these two bodies, representing Moholy’s work during the 1920s and 1940s,
					it is possible to understand the EEB microfilm as an art historical archive, and her
					personal art photography as a digital humanist one. Both insist upon the importance of
					mundane human touch in the creation — and more importantly recreation — of art.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>From Digit to Digitization: Tracking the Technology of the Index Finger</head>
				<p>Parsing the visual significance of EEBO’s photographed fingers necessitates attention not
					only to art history but to its intersections with book history. Visual representations of
					fingers appeared in the margins of rare books long before they were being photographed.
					Beginning as early as the <title rend="italic">Domesday Book</title> in 1086, authors,
					scribes, and readers included drawings of hands with pointing index fingers to emphasize
					specific passages <ptr target="#houston2013" loc="167"/>. Much later, these hands would
					recur in a digital remnant: the point and click mouse. At first glance EEBO’s fingers and
					the hands recorded in The Art of Google Books appear functionally opposed to these
					pointing images; after all, they appear randomly within the texts that they frame, rather
					than highlighting specific passages. However, like the manicule, they inflect the text
					with a new layer of meaning, marking its encounter with specific bodies, institutions, and
					readerships. The spatial arrangement of the fingers recorded on the page visually
					represents the precise nature of this encounter, its mediation through the hands of women
					workers and the emergent technology of the camera. While the photographer’s marks make
					meaning in a fashion distinct from the pointing finger, to read these images back into the
					visual tradition of the manicule recognizes EEBO’s anonymous photographers as co-producers
					of textual meaning and physical agents of a pivotal transition in literary history.</p>
				<p>Until recently, no codified name for bibliographic finger markers existed, and book
					historian William Sherman turned up more than 10 alternate names, including pointer,
					digit, index, indicator, and fist <ptr target="#sherman2008" loc="25"/>. He follows
					manuscript experts in his choice of the currently used term, <term>manicule,</term> from
					the Latin <term xml:lang="la">maniculum</term>, or <term>little hand</term>. Manicules
					were used both by printers and in handwritten manuscripts, meaning that they bridge the
					gap between the literal work of a text created <emph>by hand</emph> and that of emergent
					print technology. Manicule use peaked during the Renaissance, when readers continued to
					insert them into already printed books. Although they are most associated with this
					period, the image of the gesturing hand has continued to populate literary history. In the
					eighteenth century, printed versions joined the handwritten ones, and the device appeared
					in letter-writing manuals and printed novels by Samuel Richardson and Lawrence Sterne <ptr
						target="#williams2013"/>. In Richardson’s <title rend="italic">Clarissa</title>
					(1748), Christopher Flint writes, the appearance of the printed manicule demonstrates
							<cit><quote rend="inline">the degree to which the fiction is enmeshed in its mode
							of production</quote><ptr target="#flint2011" loc="650"/></cit>. A century later,
					Walt Whitman would use a pointing finger, topped with a butterfly, as his icon for the
					first printings of <title rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</title> (1855) and use handwritten
					manicules in his manuscripts and notes.</p>
				<p>In the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, the indexing finger also became associated with
					advertising. Readers of Whitman’s work would have recognized the pointing hand, Eric
					Conrad writes, from its use in countless newspapers, periodicals, and hand-bills <ptr
						target="#conrad2019" loc="64"/>, <ptr target="#mcpharlin1942" loc="61"/>. These
					fingers express contradictory implications; on one hand, they imply an embodied reading
					practice, intimate, focused, and particular. Sherman writes that manuscript manicules in
					particular are often <cit><quote rend="inline">intentionally made to look as though they
							extend inwards from a now-invisible reader’s body off the edge of the
							margin</quote><ptr target="#sherman2008" loc="32"/></cit> (<ref target="#figure05"
						>Figure 5</ref>). On the other hand, their mass production created ever-more distant
					facsimiles of readerly intimacy. Even when disseminated by the growing print industry in
					the eighteenth century, the presence of the hand or finger points to the suturing of
					mechanized and human technology. Their adoption by corporate advertising quite literally
					illustrates the ongoing analog labor required in capitalism-driven mass-printed archives,
					from the advertising flyer to the microfilm reel. The work of individual hands is required
					to mass produce print and digital ephemera.</p>
				<figure xml:id="figure05">
					<head>Aemelia Lanyer’s This manicule, which can be found in a book by fifteenth century
						Archbishop William Scheves, features an extended index finger and a sleeved arm
						disappearing off the edge of the page. Courtesy of the University of St Andrews
						Libraries and Museums.</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
					<figDesc>A long pencil finger points from the margins to a specific line</figDesc>
				</figure>
				<p>The fingers captured at the margins of EEB, and now digitally preserved on EEBO, represent
					a pivotal moment in the history of the pointing finger. Like the manicule that advertises
					a product, EEB’s fingers indicate the creation of a consumer good: the Early English Books
					Microfilm Collection, which Eugene Power’s UMI would sell to university libraries across
					the United States. They represent the moment of intimate touch between embodied reading
					and mass production. These images capture the manicule’s detachment from the content of
					individual passages and from its historical role as the record of a reading. Instead,
					EEBO’s scans manifest a different mode of literary valuation, which selected a corpus of
					texts for reproduction according to twin standards of English national heritage and
					American literary taste. And this, too, by the happy coincidence of technological error:
					EEB records the custodial touch, neither authorial nor readerly but belonging to the
					worker, enlisted in a vast institutional project of reshaping the practice of reading.
					Like Richardson’s manicules, EEB’s digital afterlife is indeed <quote rend="inline"
						>enmeshed in its mode of production,</quote> and richer for it <ptr
						target="#flint2011" loc="650"/>.</p>
				<p>The visual flaws left by the fingers evoke the immediacy and tactility of a very particular
					moment in a document’s history — a single now of touch and collective readership that
					bears a durable poignancy. In so doing, these fingers also offer a preliminary method for
					the digital humanities’ quest to articulate the materiality of distinct digital artifacts.
					This materiality, especially in the form of the finger, has gendered and even erotic
					implications. In her book <title rend="italic">Time Binds: Queer Temporalities, Queer
						Histories</title>, Elizabeth Freeman draws attention to the cheeky finger metaphors
					present throughout Virginia Woolf’s 1928 novel Orlando, including an allusion to a hole in
					a manuscript <quote rend="inline">big enough to put your finger through</quote>
					<ptr target="#woolf1973" loc="119"/>. In a sense, Freeman suggests, Woolf invites us to
						<quote rend="inline" source="#freeman2010">finger history,</quote> indicating that,
						<quote rend="inline">History is a hole to penetrate, but not with the usual
						instruments</quote>
					<ptr target="#freeman2010" loc="109"/>. As read by Freeman, Woolf imagines a
					historiography that makes itself available to the playful, erotic prodding of a queer
					historian. The finger is <quote rend="inline" source="#freeman2010">not the usual
						instrumen[t]</quote> for penetrating history; it is not a phallic tool for domination.
					Instead, its investigation is gentle, sensual, and curious; it explores the <quote
						rend="inline" source="#freeman2010">holes</quote> in history that make the archive
					inscrutable. Freeman figures this exploration as both deconstructive and reparative. The
					queer finger, she writes, <cit><quote rend="inline">pokes and caresses the holes in the
							archival text even as it sutures them</quote><ptr target="#freeman2010" loc="110"
						/></cit>. Orlando instantiates a symbolics of the finger that is indebted to the
					indexical history of the manicule but adds a defiant emphasis on sex in all senses. The
					finger is the nonphallic amateur’s tool for reaching toward the archive. Despite Power’s
					corporate credentials, his archive is covered with the inappropriate touches of femininity
					— those made by Moholy, Kibre, and Harwick, as well as the staff they directed. As
					Moholy’s art photography shows, modernist-era avant-gardes understood the intimate touch
					of the finger as the point where mechanized labor and high art intersected.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Exploitation in the Margins: Touching Texts in Late Capitalism</head>
				<p>The women fingering EEBO's archive belong to a labor history of digitization that
					stretches forward to include contemporary projects such as Google Books. To recognize the
					agency of these women workers as participants in the creation of meaningful visual texts
					is not to negate their status as workers, operating on the lower rungs of a vast
					institutional collaboration. The labor of digitization still consistently falls to
					anonymous workers. <title rend="italic">The Art of Google Books</title> belongs to a
					growing body of work that illuminates hidden and undervalued labor in digital archive
					production, particularly Google Books. Artist Andrew Norman Wilson worked for a time on
					the Google campus and noted that the vast majority of the workers in the
						<term>ScanOps</term> division were people of color, working ten-hour days at low
					wages. He later made a work of video art entitled <cit><quote rend="inline">Workers
							Leaving the Googleplex</quote><ptr target="#goldsmith2013"/></cit>. The imperfect
					Google scans demonstrate how the totalizing information technology available to large
					corporations requires constant and underpaid labor that depends on intimacies of touch.
					Lilly Irani calls these workers <quote rend="inline" source="#irani2015">data
						janitors,</quote> a massive invisible labor force that props up corporate power while
					reaping none of the benefits. She writes, <cit><quote rend="inline">These moderators and
							scan workers never showed up in the lavish, celebrated spaces where Googlers
							drank, ate, and brainstormed…. In fact, Google’s abundantly productive,
							nonhierarchical, and playful workplace seemed to rely on hidden layers of human
							data work</quote><ptr target="#irani2015"/></cit>. I take Krissy Wilson’s blog as
					an especially eloquent instance of the hierarchal system Norman Wilson and Irani
					describe.</p>
				<p>This system is also at work in the ongoing corporate interests that govern EEBO. The EEBO
					Text Creation Partnership (TCP) has sponsored transcriptions of the EEBO images, making
					them searchable by keyword and thus useful for many early modern quantitative projects,
					albeit not infallibly. The digital era of the database reproduces the labor circumstances
					of its earliest instantiations. The transcription work was outsourced by Proquest to
					third-party vendors, Apex CoVantage and SPi Global, whose workers, anonymous coders in
					India, actually created the inscriptions <ptr target="#gavin2017" loc="98n54"/>. Every
					technological era of EEBO is also an era of labor practices, as the University Microfilms
					International, later Proquest, corporation immerses itself in global capitalism. The
					anonymity of the Indian coders is even more complete than that of Power’s women
					photographers; their presence, stripped back by the digital mode, is not represented by an
					errant finger; they are what Mary L. Gray and Siddarth Suri call <quote rend="inline"
						>ghost workers,</quote> representatives of a developing global underclass that props
					up information and technology corporate wealth <ptr target="#gray_etal2019"/>. Another
					example that underlines the contours of racial capitalism is Amazon’s <quote rend="inline"
						>Mechanical Turk</quote> platform, which relies on human workers to produce <quote
						rend="inline" source="#stephens2023">artificial artificial intelligence,</quote> using
					a racialized referent to an automation hoax that dates back to the 18th century. According
					to one study, only 4% of <quote rend="inline" source="#stephens2023">Turkers</quote> make
					above minimum wage, and their numbers disproportionately include those for whom disability
					or weak local economies make gainful employment difficult to access. Their underpaid labor
					perpetuates the hoax of artificial intelligence as a truly autonomous technological marvel
						<ptr target="#stephens2023"/>.</p>
				<p>Placing the EEB microfilm in historical continuity with corporations like Google, Amazon,
					and Proquest allows us to recognize the longer history of this exploitative labor and its
					entanglement with the American superpower that World War II fostered. Gavin points out
					that Eugene Power <quote rend="inline" source="#gavin2017">in many ways…represents the
						ideal of twentieth-century masculine subjectivity,</quote> observing that even his
					name seems plucked from the work of Ayn Rand <ptr target="#gavin2017" loc="78"/>. Power
					made no apologies for his corporate interests and their calibration to make the United
					States the universal custodian of British and European rare books. He wrote in one memo,
							<cit><quote rend="inline">The collections listed are not complete. Only those
							portions of particular interest to American scholars were microfilmed</quote><ptr
							target="#power1990" loc="385"/></cit>. Power’s intervention represents a watershed
					moment in the intersection of book history and capitalism. As war and new technologies
					converged to create great opportunity, he seized it in order to make an immense profit in
					the name of book preservation. I have argued that the images of EEBO bear the marks of
					this literary revolution, not in Power’s own hand but through the hands of the women hired
					to conduct the physical labor of the project. The images they generated testify to his
					ambitions and those of the institutions with which he collaborated, but they also invoke
					contemporaneous women’s photography, such as the work of Lucia Moholy, which celebrated
					the artistry of reproductive labor and challenged its dismissal as derivative, unskilled,
					or merely technical. Knowing the labor history of this capitalist archive, which makes
					itself insistently known through errorful fingers, should enjoin us to observe the
					increased custodianship of corporate interests in our archives. This custodianship is, and
					has always been, built on the work of women. As readers of these digital sources, we bear
					the responsibility to attend to the ghostly presence of anonymous workers and to study
					their work in continuity with the literary work they preserved.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<listBibl>
				<bibl xml:id="banks2018" label="Banks 2018">Banks, M. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Production
						Studies</title>, <title rend="italic">Feminist Media Histories</title>, 4(2), pp.
					157–161.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="barker2013" label="Barker 2013">Barker, J. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Be-Hold:
						Touch, Temporality, and the Cinematic Thumbnail Image</title>, <title rend="italic"
						>Discourse: Journal for Theoretical Studies in Media and Culture</title>, 35(2), pp.
					194–211.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="beals_etal2020" label="Beals and Bell 2020">Beals, M. and Bell, E. (2020) <title
						rend="italic">The Atlas of Digitised Newspapers and Metadata: Reports from Oceanic
						Exchanges</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.11560059.v2"
						>https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.11560059.v2</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="bingham2010" label="Bingham 2010">Bingham, A. (2010) <title rend="quotes">The
						Digitization of Newspaper Archives: Opportunities and Challenges for
						Historians</title>, <title rend="italic">Twentieth Century British History</title>,
					21(2), pp. 225–231.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="conrad2019" label="Conrad 2019">Conrad, E. (2019) <title rend="quotes">The Poet
						as Printer's Fist: Walt Whitman’s Indicative Hand</title>, <title rend="italic"
						>Nineteenth-Century Literature</title>, 74(1), pp. 54–86.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="cordell2017" label="Cordell 2017">Cordell, R. (2017) <title rend="quotes">'Q
						i-jtb the Raven': Taking Dirty OCR Seriously</title>, <title rend="italic">Book
						History</title>, 20, pp. 188–225.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="delsandro2020" label="Delsandro 2020">Delsandro, E. (ed.) (2020) <title
						rend="italic">Women Making Modernism</title> Gainesville, FL: University of Florida
					Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="dignazio_etal2020" label="D’Ignazio and Klein 2020">D’Ignazio, K. and Klein,
					L.F. (2020) <title rend="italic">Data Feminism</title> Boston, MA: Massachusetts Institute
					of Technology Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="fafinski2022" label="Fafinski 2022">Fafinski, M. (2022) <title rend="quotes"
						>Facsimile narratives: Researching the past in the age of digital
					reproduction</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>,
					37(1), pp. 94–108.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="flint2011" label="Flint 2011">Flint, C. (2011) <title rend="italic">The
						Appearance of Print in Eighteenth-century Fiction</title> Cambridge, UK: Cambridge
					University Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="freeman2010" label="Freeman 2010">Freeman, E. (2010) <title rend="italic">Time
						Binds: Queer Temporalities, Queer Histories</title> Durham, NC: Duke University
					Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="friedrich" label="Friedrich n.d.">Friedrich, S. (n.d.) <title rend="italic"
						>Edited by — Women Film Editors</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="http://womenfilmeditors.princeton.edu/"
						>http://womenfilmeditors.princeton.edu/</ref> (Accessed: 23 August 2023.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="fyfe2016" label="Fyfe 2016">Fyfe, P. (2016) <title rend="quotes">An Archaeology
						of Victorian Newspapers</title>, <title rend="italic">Victorian Periodicals
						Review</title>, 49(4), pp. 546–77. Available at: <ref
						target="https://doi.org/10.1353/vpr.2016.0039"
						>https://doi.org/10.1353/vpr.2016.0039</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="gavin2017" label="Gavin 2017">Gavin, M. (2017) <title rend="quotes">How to Think
						About EEBO</title>, <title rend="italic">Textual Cultures</title>, 11(1), pp.
					70–105.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="goldsmith2013" label="Goldsmith 2013">Goldsmith, K. (2013) <title rend="quotes"
						>The Artful Accidents of Google Books</title>, <title rend="italic">The New
						Yorker</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.newyorker.com/books/page-turner/the-artful-accidents-of-google-books"
						>https://www.newyorker.com/books/page-turner/the-artful-accidents-of-google-books</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="gray_etal2019" label="Gray and Suri 2019">Gray, M. and Suri, S. (2019) <title
						rend="italic">Ghost Work: How to Stop Silicon Valley from Buildingg a New Global
						Underclass</title> Boston, MA: Houghton Mifflin Harcourt.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="gregg2020" label="Gregg 2020">Gregg, S. (2020) <title rend="italic">Old Books
						and Digital Publishing: The History of Eighteenth-Century Collections Online</title>
					Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="grimmelmann2009" label="Grimmelmann 2009">Grimmelmann, J. (2009) <title
						rend="quotes">The Google Book Search Settlement: Ends, Means, and the Future of
						Books</title>. <title rend="italic">The American Constitution Society for Law and
						Policy</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.acslaw.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Grimmelman_Issue_Brief.pdf"
						>https://www.acslaw.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Grimmelman_Issue_Brief.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="hauswedell_etal2020" label="Hauswedell et al 2020">Hausewedell T., Nyhan, J.,
					Beals, M.H. et al. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Of global reach yet of situated contexts: an
						examination of the implicit and explicit selection criteria that shape digital
						archives of historical newspapers</title>, <title rend="italic">Arch Sci</title>, 20,
					pp. 139–165.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="heffernan_etal2020" label="Heffernan and Sagner Buurma 2020">Heffernan, Sagner
					Buurma 2020]. Heffernan, L. and Sagner Buurma, R. (2020) <title rend="italic">The Teaching
						Archive: A New History for Literary Study</title> Chicago, University of Chicago
					Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="hoffman_etal2016" label="Hoffman and Bloom 2016">Hoffman, A.L. and Bloom, R.
					(2016) <title rend="quotes">Digitizing Books, Obscuring Women's Work: Google Books,
						Librarians, and Ideologies of Access</title>, ADA: A Journal of Gender, New Media, and
					Technology, 9. Available at: <ref
						target="https://adanewmedia.org/2016/05/issue9-hoffmann-and-bloom/"
						>https://adanewmedia.org/2016/05/issue9-hoffmann-and-bloom/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="houston2013" label="Houston 2013">Houston, K. (2013) <title rend="italic">Shady
						Characters: The Secret Life of Punctuation, Symbols, and Other Typographical
						Marks</title>. Norton, New York.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="irani2015" label="Irani 2015">Irani, L. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Justice for
						Data Janitors</title>, <title rend="italic">Public Books</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.publicbooks.org/justice-for-data-janitors/"
						>https://www.publicbooks.org/justice-for-data-janitors/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="jacob2020" label="Jacob 2020">Jacob, A. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Punching
						Holes in the International Busa Machine Narrative</title>, <title rend="italic"
						>IDEAH</title>, 1(1). Available at: <ref
						target="https://doi.org/10.21428/f1f23564.d7d097c2"
						>https://doi.org/10.21428/f1f23564.d7d097c2</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="kichuk2007" label="Kichuk 2007">Kichuk, D. (2007) <title rend="quotes"
						>Metamorphosis: Remediation in Early English Books Online (EEBO)</title>, <title
						rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 23(2), pp. 291–303.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="klein2020" label="Klein 2020">Klein, L.F. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Dimensions
						of Scale: Invisible Labor, Editorial Work, and the Future of Quantitative Literary
						Studies</title>, <title rend="italic">PMLA/Publications of the Modern Language
						Association of America</title>, 135(1), pp. 23–39.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="lesser2019" label="Lesser 2010">Lesser, Z. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Xeroxing
						the Renaissance: The Material Text of Early Modern Studies</title>, <title
						rend="italic">Shakespeare Quarterly</title>, 70(1), pp. 2–31.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="mak2014" label="Mak 2014">Mak, B. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Archeology of a
						Digitization</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of the Association for Information
						Science and Technology</title>, 6(8), pp. 1515–1526.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="marek1996" label="Marek 1996">Marek, J. (1996) Women Editing Modernism: <title
						rend="italic">'Little' Magazines and Literary History</title>. Lexington, KY: The
					University Press of Kentucky.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="martin2007" label="Martin 2007">Martin, S. (2007) <title rend="quotes">EEBO,
						Microfilm, and Umberto Eco: Historical Lessons and Future Directions for Building
						Electronic Collections</title>, <title rend="italic">Microform &amp; Imaging
						Review</title>, 36(4), pp. 159–164.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="mcpharlin1942" label="McPharlin 1942" sortKey="Mcpharlin">McPharlin, P. (1942)
						<title rend="italic">Roman numerals, typographic leaves and pointing hands: some notes
						on their origin, history and contemporary use</title>. New York: Typophiles.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="meuel2016" label="Meuel 2016">Meuel, D. (2016) <title rend="italic">Women Film
						Editors: Unseen Artists of the American Cinema</title> Jefferson, North Carolina:
					McFarland and Company, Inc.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="micir2019" label="Micir 2019">Micir, M. (2019) <title rend="italic">The Passion
						Projects: Modernist Women, Intimate Archives, Unfinished Lives</title> Princeton, NJ:
					Princeton University Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="moholy1939" label="Moholy 1939">Moholy, L. (1939) <title rend="italic">A Hundred
						Years of Photography, 1839-1938</title> London: Pelican.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="moholy1942" label="Moholy 1942">Moholy, L. (1942) <title rend="quotes">Microfilm
						Services in War</title>, in <title rend="italic">Full Report of the Year’s Work and
						Accounts of Aslib</title>, pp. 7–10.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="moholy1946a" label="Moholy 1946a">Moholy, L. (1946) <title rend="quotes">The
						ASLIB Microfilm Service: The Story of its Wartime Activities</title>, <title
						rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title>, 2: 3, pp. 147–173.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="moholy1946b" label="Moholy 1946b">Moholy, L. (1946) <title rend="quotes">The New
						Microfilm Project for Disabled Persons</title>, <title rend="italic"> The Work of
						ASLIB 1945-1946</title>, pp. 82–84.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="moholynagy1922" label="Moholy 1922"><title rend="quotes">Moholy-Nagy, L.
						“Production-Reproduction</title> (1922) <title rend="italic">De Stijl</title>, 5(7),
					pp. 97–100.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="muller_etal2009" label="Müller 2009" sortKey="Muller">Müller (2009). <title
						rend="italic">Bauhaus Women: Art, Handicraft</title>. New York: Rizzoli.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="newman2011" label="Newman 2011">Newman, J. (2011) <title rend="quotes">The
						Google Books Settlement: A Private Contract in the Absence of Adequate Copyright
						Law</title>, <title rend="italic">Scholarly and Research Communication</title>, 2: 1,
					pp. 3–75.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="noble2018" label="Noble 2018">Noble, S.U. (2018) <title rend="italic">Algorithms
						of Oppression: How Search Engines Reinforce Racism</title> New York: New York
					University Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="nyhan2020" label="Nyhan 2020">Nyhan, J. (2020) <title rend="quotes">New findings
						and new questions about the origins of Digital Humanities: on the state of the art of
						histories of the Index Thomisticus project of Fr Roberto Busa S.J</title>, <title
						rend="italic">Luxembourg Center for Contemporary and Digital History</title> lecture
					and interview.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="otto_etal2019" label="Otto and Rössler 2019" sortKey="Otto">Otto, E. and
					Rössler, P.(2019) <title rend="italic">Bauhaus Women: A Global Perspective</title> London:
					Herbert Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="overholt2015" label="Overholt 2015">Overholt, J. (2015) <title rend="quotes"
						>Together, We Can FrEEBO</title>, <title rend="italic">medium.com</title>. Available
					at: <ref
						target="https://medium.com/@john_overholt/together-we-can-freebo-b33d39618f8#.92z68geno"
						>https://medium.com/@john_overholt/together-we-can-freebo-b33d39618f8#.92z68geno</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="pasanek2019" label="Pasanek 2019">Pasanek, B. (2019) <title rend="quotes"
						>Extreme Reading: Josephine Miles and the Scale of the Pre-Digital Digital
						Humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">ELH</title>, 86(2), pp. 355–385.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="peiss2019" label="Peiss, K. 2019">Peiss, K. (2019) <title rend="italic"
						>Information Hunters: When Librarians, Soldiers, and Spies Banded Together in World
						War II Europe</title> New York: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="power1938" label="Power 1938">Power, E. (1938) <title rend="quotes">Report on
						Progress on Filming English Books Issued Before 1550</title>, <title rend="italic">The
						Journal of Documentary Reproduction</title>, 1(1), pp. 45–49.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="power1944" label="Power 1944">Power, E. (1944) <title rend="quotes">The
						Manuscript Copying Program in England</title>, <title rend="italic">The American
						Archivist</title>, 7(1), pp. 28–32.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="power1990" label="Power 1990">Power, E. (1990) <title rend="italic">Edition of
						One: The Autobiography of Eugene B</title> Power, Founder of University Microfilms
					with Robert Anderson. Ann Arbor, MI: University Microfilms International.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="richards2020" label="Richards 2020">Richards, J. (2020) <title rend="italic">The
						Fury Archives: Female Citizenship, Human Rights, and the International
						Avant-Gardes</title> New York: Columbia University Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="richards1988" label="Richards 1988">Richards, P.S. (1988) <title rend="quotes"
						>Historical Note - Information Science in Wartime: Pioneer Documentation Activities in
						World War II</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of the American Society for
						Information Science</title>, 39(5), pp. 301–306.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="richards1989" label="Richards 1989">Richards, P.S. (1989) <title rend="quotes"
						>Aslib at War: The Brief but Intrepid Career of a Library Organization as a Hub of
						Allied Scientific Intelligence 1942-1945</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of
						Education for Library and Information Science</title>, 29(4), pp. 279–296.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="sachsse1985" label="Sachsse 1985">Sachsse, R. (1985) <title rend="quotes">Lucia
						Moholy</title>. Düsseldorf, Marzona.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="schmidt2005" label="Schmidt 2005">Schmidt, E. (2005) <title rend="quotes">Books
						of Revelation</title>, <title rend="italic">The Wall Street Journal</title>. Available
					at: <ref target="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB112958982689471238.html"
						>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB112958982689471238.html</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="schmitt2003" label="Schmitt 2003">Schmitt, J. (2003) <title rend="quotes">Early
						English Books Online</title>, <title rend="italic">The Charlestone Advisor</title>,
					4(4). Available at: <ref target="http://charlestonco.com/review/cfm?id=141"
						>http://charlestonco.com/review/cfm?id=141</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="schon2020" label="Schon 2020">Schon, N. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Lecture by
						Julianne Nyhan: New findings and new questions about the origins of Digital
						Humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Luxenbourg Center for Contemporary and
						Digital History</title>. Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.c2dh.uni.lu/data/lecture-julianne-nyhan-new-findings-and-new-questions-about-origins-digital-humanities"
						>https://www.c2dh.uni.lu/data/lecture-julianne-nyhan-new-findings-and-new-questions-about-origins-digital-humanities</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="schuldenfrei2013" label="Schuldenfrei 2013">Schuldenfrei, R. (2013) <title
						rend="quotes">Images in Exile: Lucia Moholy</title>s Bauhaus Negatives and the
					Construction of the Bauhaus Legacy’, History of Photography, 37(2), pp. 182–203.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="segev2010" label="Segev 2010">Segev, E. (2010) <title rend="quotes">Google and
						the Digital Divide: The Bias of Online Knowledge</title>. Oxford: Chandros.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="sherman2008" label="Sherman 2008">Sherman, W. (2008) <title rend="italic">Used
						Books: Marking Readers in Renaissance England</title>. Philadelphia: University of
					Pennsylvania Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="stallybrass2002" label="Stallybrass 2002">Stallybrass, P. (2002) <title
						rend="quotes">Books and Scrolls: Navigating the Bible</title> in Jennifer Andersen,
					and Elizabeth Sauer, (eds), <title rend="italic">Books and Readers in Early Modern
						England: Material Studies</title>. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania
					Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="stephens2023" label="Stephens 2023">Stephens, E. (2023) <title rend="quotes">The
						mechanical Turk: a short history of ‘artificial artificial intelligence’</title>,
						<title rend="italic">Cultural Studies</title>, 37(1), pp. 65–87. Available at: <ref
						target="https://doi-org.ezproxy.neu.edu/10.1080/09502386.2022.2042580"
						>https://doi-org.ezproxy.neu.edu/10.1080/09502386.2022.2042580</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="troeller2020" label="Troeller 2020">Troeller, J. (2020) <title rend="quotes"
						>Lucia Moholy’s Idle Hands</title>, <title rend="italic">October</title> 172, pp.
					68-108.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="valdivieso2000" label="Valdivieso 2000">Valdivieso, M. (2000) <title
						rend="quotes" xml:lang="de">Eine ‘symbiotische Arbeitsgemeinschaft’: Lucia and László
						Moholy-Nagy</title>, in Renate Berger (ed.)<title rend="italic" xml:lang="de">Liebe
						Macht Kunst: Künstlerpaare im 20. Jahrhundert</title>. Cologne: Böhlau, pp. 65–85. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="wagner1998" label="Wagner 1998">Wagner, A. (1998) <title rend="italic">Three
						Artists (Three Women): Modernism and the Art of Hesse, Krasner, and O’Keefe</title>.
					Berkeley: University of California Press. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="williams2013" label="Williams 2013">Williams, H. (2013) <title rend="italic"
						>Sterne's Manicules: Hands, Handwriting and Authorial Property in Tristram
						Shandy</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</title>,
					36, pp. 209-223. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="wilson" label="Wilson n.d.">Wilson, K. (n.d.) <title rend="quotes"
					>Guide</title>, <title rend="italic">The Art of Google Books</title>, Available at: <ref
						target="https://theartofgooglebooks.tumblr.com/guide"
						>https://theartofgooglebooks.tumblr.com/guide</ref>. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="woolf1973" label="Woolf 1973">Woolf, V. (1973) <title rend="italic"
						>Orlando</title>. London: Harcourt Brace.</bibl>
			</listBibl>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
