<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Digital Humanities as Epistemic Cultures: How DH
                    Labs Make Knowledge, Objects, and Subjects</title>
                <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
                    <dhq:author_name>James W. <dhq:family>Malazita</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>malazj@rpi.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>James W. Malazita is an Assistant Professor in Science &amp; Technology
                            Studies and in Games &amp; Simulation Arts &amp; Sciences at Rensselaer
                            Polytechnic Institute in Troy, NY. He holds a Ph.D. in Communication,
                            Culture, and Media from Drexel University. His research brings feminist
                            technoscience studies into the analysis of game engines, computer
                            science, and digital culture. He is the founder and director of
                            Rensselaer's <ref target="https://tactical.wp.rpi.edu/">Tactical
                                Humanities Lab</ref>, a research space for combining technical
                            practice with critical thought and social justice.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
                    <dhq:author_name>Ezra J. <dhq:family>Teboul</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>teboue@rpi.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Ezra J. Teboul is an artist, researcher and organizer whose work focuses
                            on making accessible the human and non-human labor in electric sound. He
                            holds a PhD in electronic arts from Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute,
                            has published various chapters and articles between hacking, history and
                            sound art, and released records under the name <title rend="italic"
                                >Passive Tones</title> with Karl Hohn. Various re/construction
                            projects of electronic music systems can be found at <ref
                                target="https://redthunderaudio.com/">redthunderaudio.com</ref>.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
                    <dhq:author_name>Hined <dhq:family>Rafeh</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>rafehh@rpi.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Hined A. Rafeh is a PhD candidate in Science &amp; Technology Studies and
                            a Humanities, Arts, and Social Sciences Research Fellow at Rensselaer
                            Polytechnic. Her research explores genetic testing, technoidentities and
                            critical scientific engagement. Her dissertation is on the regulation
                            and commercialization of genetic health tests, and how genetic tests
                            construct and are shaped by notions of risk, diagnosis, and
                            identity.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000465</idno>
                <idno type="volume">014</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2020-09-25">25 September 2020</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
            <change who="BRG" when="2022-07-27">Updated encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
                <p>This essay develops a conceptual framework for examining and practicing digital
                    humanities (DH) and DH labs from the perspective of science and technology
                    studies and laboratory studies. We argue that the
                        <soCalled>situatedness</soCalled> of DH labs extends beyond
                    physical/institutional space and includes also epistemic, political,
                    sociological, and disciplinary issues. To explore this, we first outline the
                    constructivist model of laboratory knowledge practices developed through
                    feminist laboratory studies, and how that model’s focus on the laboratory as a
                    producer of research subjects, rather than a container for them, runs counter to
                    narratives about laboratories in DH. We then show how DH labs produce research
                    objects, research subjects, epistemic context, and disciplinary legitimacy.
                    Finally, we present the case of the Tactical Humanities Lab (THL) at Rensselaer,
                    a DH lab situated through Science &amp; Technology Studies and housed within an
                    engineering-centered institute. Through the highlighting of two student-led
                    projects, we show how THL knowledge workers navigate issues of our own identity,
                    the boundaries of STS and DH, the practice of social justice through DH, and the
                    social construction of the boundaries of laboratory work.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
                <p>This article explores the <soCalled>situatedness</soCalled> of DH labs.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>1. Introduction</head>
                <p> How we as digital humanities (DH) scholars construct the laboratory — as a
                    space, as a culture, as an imaginary, as a process, as an apparatus —
                    contributes to the material and epistemic production of DH labs, their spaces,
                    cultures, practices, and products. Our foci in this essay are the disciplinary
                    constructions of the laboratory and its products as epistemic cultures <ptr
                        target="#knorrcetina1999"/>, and the expansion of the
                        <soCalled>situatedness</soCalled> of DH labs beyond physical/institutional
                    space to include epistemic, political, sociological, and disciplinary concerns.
                    Rather than narrowly framing labs as spaces of technical production and inquiry,
                    we begin from the premise that laboratory structures and cultures produce
                    specific kinds of knowledge practitioners. These practitioners in turn produce
                    and police the boundaries of legitimate and recognizable knowledge work —
                    including in the Digital Humanities. All of these productions are, in part,
                    results of particular institutional and disciplinary positions, even as they can
                    sometimes be presented as <soCalled>matters of fact</soCalled>
                    <ptr target="#latour2004"/>. An <soCalled>opening up</soCalled> of the
                    imaginations of how DH situates itself and of how DH practices configure and
                    reconfigure researchers can, in turn, serve as an opening up of new
                    disciplinary, institutional, and political formations of DH knowledge work.</p>
                <p>We will make this case by using Science &amp; Technology Studies’ (STS) <title
                        rend="quotes">Laboratory Studies</title> literature to examine DH labs and
                    their practices, and through illustrations of how the Tactical Humanities Lab
                    (THL), an STS-situated DH lab at Rensselaer, grapples with its own identity, the
                    constructed boundaries of STS and DH, and the social construction of the
                    boundaries of laboratory work. The THL is in many ways an improvised space,
                    operating out of shared spaces and funded by a new professor's startup fund,
                    contrasting with more institutionally supported labs (e.g. <ptr
                        target="#foka2017"/>). With this spirit of relative outsider, the THL
                    operates as an inverse of the typical imagination of the relationship between DH
                    theory and practice. Rather than asking how technical tools can be applied to
                    humanities questions, the THL focuses on how method and inquirer are mutually
                    shaped through research practices, and on how the <soCalled>divide</soCalled>
                    between technical and interpretive scholarship and methods is a historical and
                    contingent one. This flipped model encourages faculty, graduate students, and
                    undergraduate students in the THL to co-theorize about the multiple social
                    constructions of the digital and the virtual in humanistic and social scientific
                    cultures, and to experiment with using DH to produce new situations for social
                    justice. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. Laboratory Studies and the Production of Subjects and Objects</head>
                <p> Laboratory Studies of the late 1970s/early 1980s represented a seismic shift in
                    the then-still-emerging field of STS. While work in the Sociology of Scientific
                    Knowledge (SSK) had been present in British STS circles since the late 1960s
                        <ptr target="#bloor1976"/>
                    <ptr target="#collins1975"/>, SSK had largely focused on the relationships among
                    macro-social and historical narratives and events upon scientific enterprise,
                    particularly in terms of how scientific controversies are created, debated, and
                    resolved. The social, ideological, and historical were either treated as
                    external factors that potentially led to the <soCalled>incorrect</soCalled>
                    interpretation of work generated by scientific research, or were constructed as
                    variables that intersect with scientific knowledge <ptr target="#bloor1983"
                    />.</p>
                <p>Through the use of ethnographic method, Laboratory Studies focused on scientific
                    work as <emph>in situ</emph> practice, where the wider results of
                        <soCalled>science</soCalled> were negotiated and produced through the
                    everyday activities of scientific practitioners and knowledge workers. Perhaps
                    the most broadly recognizable early Lab Studies work was Bruno Latour and Steve
                    Woolgar’s tracing of knowledge production in Roger Guilleman’s Salk Institute
                    labs in <title rend="italic">Laboratory Life </title>(1979). The book would
                    build the foundations for Latour’s later work on Actor-Network Theory (ANT),
                    whose <soCalled>flattening</soCalled> of the agency of non-humans and things in
                    daily life would become majorly influential both inside and outside of STS
                    circles. The presence of ANT can be seen in DH work <ptr target="#bianco2012"/>,
                    flat ontology <ptr target="#bogost2012"/>, object-oriented <ptr
                        target="#bryant2011"/>, speculative <ptr target="#harman2011"/>, and media
                    archeological <ptr target="#parikka2016"/> literatures.</p>
                <p>While ANT’s highlighting of the agency of objects and <quote rend="inline">the
                        missing masses</quote>
                    <ptr target="#latour1992"/> is often positioned as a <quote rend="inline"
                        >counter</quote> to social constructivist critique of science <ptr
                        target="#bloor1999"/>, STS has tended to treat these approaches as dual
                    components of a broader <soCalled>both/and</soCalled> analysis of scientific
                    practice <ptr target="#winner1980"/>. Object-oriented fans of Latour’s later ANT
                    work may be surprised reading <title rend="italic">Laboratory Life</title>,
                    which uses a clearly social constructivist interpretation of scientific
                    practice. Latour and Woolgar conceive of the scientific fact as constructed —
                    not only in terms of the processes of interpretive, interpersonal, and
                    methodological negotiations that occur during research practices, but also in
                    terms of the need for political and social institutions to legitimate scientific
                    knowledge. Though this argument is accused by some of radical postmodernism or
                    correlationism <ptr target="#harman2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#bryant2011"/> or of denying reality <ptr target="#eidin2004"/>,
                    its analytic power has been made even more evident during the US Trump
                    administration. The <quote rend="inline">production of ignorance</quote>
                    <ptr target="#kleinman2013"/> about global warming, for example, is more than
                    just the spread of misinformation and deletion of data. It is also the
                    systematic undermining of the institutions that give scientific facts their
                    legitimacy and political power — universities, government agencies, grant
                    agencies, congressional commissions, educational systems, and the media. From
                    this more relational perspective of ANT/social constructivist approaches, the
                    networks of humans, non-humans, institutions, and infrastructures that produce
                    knowledge appear less like antagonistic or collaborative forces pushing against
                    one another, and more like a mapping of the contingent material and social
                    forces that <soCalled>lash-up</soCalled> the realities and practices we believe
                    to be concretized <ptr target="#bijker2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#molotch2003"/>.</p>
                <p> Further, Latour and Woolgar argue that the construction of scientific knowledge
                    — and in particular, of <soCalled>facts</soCalled> — socially produces
                    neutrality and objectivity. While the scientific method is far from neutral, and
                    while scientific knowledge workers spend large amounts of time debating and
                    negotiating interpretations of experimental results, these results tend to be
                    reported as objective fact in scientific publications; the rhetorical and
                    epistemological frame of <quote rend="inline">facts which speak for
                        themselves.</quote> In this way, Laboratory Studies scholars argue that the
                    broader institutional, cultural, and political milieus of scientific practice
                    are not the <emph>contexts</emph> of laboratory practices, they are
                        <emph>productions</emph> of those practices. The results, methods,
                    interpretations, and political impact of scientific research are thus
                    co-produced and co-legitimized through the practices of scientific knowledge
                    workers.</p>
                <p> The Laboratory Studies of the 1990s would extend the analysis of the laboratory
                    as a site of multi-modal production. Among the most vital work of this era was
                    that of Karin Knorr Cetina, which culminated in the publication of <title
                        rend="italic">Epistemic Cultures</title> in 1999. Knorr Cetina’s research, a
                    comparative analysis of ethnographic experiences at a molecular biology lab and
                    at the CERN High-Energy Physics (HEP) lab, served as a major blow to the <title
                        rend="quotes">Unity of Science</title> epistemological frame — the idea that
                    all scientific practices are united under a grander methodological and empirical
                    truth, and therefore that all scientific practices, properly arranged, can
                    contribute to an unbroken, consistent accounting for the natural and social
                    world <ptr target="#knorrcetina1999"/>. Rather, Knorr Cetina argues that
                    different scientific disciplines — and even different localized scientific
                    research apparatuses — produce different epistemic cultures: different ways that
                    knowledge is produced and disseminated, facts and research are legitimized, the
                        <soCalled>empirical</soCalled> and the <soCalled>theoretical</soCalled> are
                    defined and related, laboratory apparatuses and equipment are socially
                    constructed, and institutions and structures are built and maintained.
                        <soCalled>Science,</soCalled> then, is radically disunified — the practices
                    and epistemic frameworks of different scientific knowledge spaces are not
                    interoperable without further interpretive, constructive, and political work,
                    and do not <soCalled>add up</soCalled> to a unified view of the world. The
                    production of a unified Science is more institutional than it is epistemic, with
                    the separation of the <soCalled>objective and neutral</soCalled> disciplines
                    from <soCalled>softer and interpretive</soCalled> ones providing political and
                    ideological legitimacy, often accompanied by larger funding streams and
                    infrastructural support <ptr target="#malazita2018b"/>.</p>
                <p>Earlier Lab Studies work tended to make agential cuts between the labor of
                    laboratory practitioners and the outcomes of laboratories; i.e., the material
                    and social productions of laboratory work were the results of the collective
                    action of lab workers and the actor-networks of which they were a part. Knorr
                    Cetina, however, argued that the lab workers themselves, subjectively and
                    epistemically, were also products of the laboratory apparatus. The intra-actions
                        <ptr target="#barad2007"/> of discursive, material, and institutional
                    networks produce laboratory researchers as <quote rend="inline">epistemic
                        subjects</quote>
                    <ptr target="#knorrcetina1999"/>, or practitioners attuned to particular ways of
                    knowing, of ways of bounding internal and external disciplinary knowledge, and
                    ways of producing the institutions and infrastructures needed to legitimize that
                    knowledge and its boundaries. Latour and Woolgar’s observations of the
                    production of the <soCalled>neutrality</soCalled> of a scientific fact can be
                    extended through Knorr Cetina: scientific knowledge workers also co-produce
                    themselves as knowers of <soCalled>neutral</soCalled> research.</p>
                <p> As the identities and subjectivities of scientific practitioners are not
                    pre-given, neither are their objects of study, which Knorr Cetina calls <quote
                        rend="inline">epistemic objects</quote> (1999). Epistemic objects are
                    produced through the boundaries drawn around what makes an object knowable.
                    These boundaries are material and social. Global Warming, for example, can be
                    produced as a scientific object, an economic object, a social object, a
                    political object, and/or a synthesis of any of the prior through the apparatuses
                    enrolled <ptr target="#callon1982"/> to know and bound it, through the practices
                    of scientists, journalists, politicians, and their interests, and through the
                    theories and technologies of knowing capable or chosen to be deployed. The
                    co-productions of epistemic subjects and objects are not
                        <soCalled>just</soCalled> rhetorical or framing moves; how we construct the
                    formation of our objects of study and our relationships to them produces lasting
                    and durable infrastructures and institutions of knowledge.</p>
                <p> The production of epistemic objects, subjects, and infrastructures transverses
                    and co-produces the boundaries of applied and theoretical work, as well as the
                    boundaries of the physical and the virtual. For example, in her studies of HEP,
                    Knorr Cetina describes how the laboratory apparatus is designed through the
                    co-constructions of the physical high-energy particles and their digital
                    representations: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block">The experiment designs and builds the apparatus in which
                            the particles register. Physicists, however, do not start with the
                            particles, they start with representations of the detector, that is,
                                <quote rend="inline">offline</quote> manipulations of the signals
                            extracted from detectors after data have been taken. This level of
                            representation reconstructs the events in the detector and slowly molds
                            these signals into a form that echoes the particles of interest to
                                physicists.<ptr target="#knorrcetina1999" loc="49"
                    /></quote></cit></p>
                <p> The typical rhetoric of the physical/virtual divide is complicated in laboratory
                    knowledge practices. Rather than the digital representations of particles being
                        <soCalled>results</soCalled> of physical particles, they are embedded among
                    physical particles and among the epistemic objects of particles, made
                    perceptible by laboratory researchers as epistemic subjects and by the apparatus
                    of which they are a part. The relationship between the laboratory apparatus, the
                    researchers, the material, the discursive, and the virtual, is thus not one of
                    transition between multiple layers, or of a causal chain, but rather is a
                    co-constitutive relationship; they all produce each other, participating in one
                    another’s existence.</p>
                <p> 1990s Laboratory Studies’ use of ANT and social constructivist models of
                    knowledge production, blended with the concurrent emergence of feminist,
                    cybernetic, and posthuman configurations of subjectivity <ptr
                        target="#haraway1991"/>
                    <ptr target="#braidotti1994"/>, signaled a shift from first-order cybernetic
                    models of the laboratory, where humans were observers and manipulators of
                    large-scale systems, to second-order cybernetic models <ptr target="#mead1968"
                    />, where the actants within systems, including humans, are always part of the
                    system itself, and where the <soCalled>bounds</soCalled> of the system are
                    always under negotiation. Though <title rend="italic">Epistemic Cultures</title>
                    is generally considered to be the last <soCalled>mega</soCalled> Laboratory
                    Studies work from an empirical perspective — it synthesized over a decade of
                    comparative ethnographic research across multiple laboratories and continents —
                    more recent work in and around Lab Studies has continued its synthetic work on
                    the production of materiality, subjectivity, and epistemology in scientific
                    spaces. Feminist Science Studies and its subset, Feminist New Materialism, have
                    been particularly prominent in the decades since, including the quantum and
                    intra-active theories of Karen Barad <ref target="#barad2007">(2007)</ref> and
                    the multiply-produced ontologies of Annemarie Mol <ref target="#mol2002"
                        >(2002)</ref>.</p>
                <p>While there has been scholarship bridging STS literature with DH practices <ptr
                        target="#boeva2018"/>
                    <ptr target="#hamraie2018"/>
                    <ptr target="#parikka2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#resch2018"/>, much of this writing has focused on labs as
                    imaginaries and as spaces of material and speculative production. More
                    connections can be built between DH’s acknowledgement of the cultural qualities
                    of laboratories and Laboratory Studies’ examinations of the social and material
                    processes that practice those qualities into being. These connections include:
                        <list type="unordered">
                        <item>An interrogation into methodological and epistemological disunity of
                            Science</item>
                        <item>The laboratory as a site of social construction of facts, and</item>
                        <item>The co-production of laboratories, researchers, research
                            objects/subjects, and institutional legitimization</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>We want to highlight these potential connections for two reasons. First, we argue
                    that lack of attention to laboratory practices leads to the stereotyping of
                    scientific and computational practices by DH scholars. In turn, this
                    stereotyping reinforces hegemonic institutions that thrive on the constructed
                    neutrality, rationality, and unity of Science. It can also limit imaginations of
                    when, where, and how DH can intervene in and subvert hegemonic institutions.
                    Second, the social, subjective, political, and epistemological work found in
                    scientific laboratories happens in DH labs as well. The acknowledgement of this
                    work can allow for the reflexive proliferation of more diverse models of DH
                    labs.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3. Producing Digital Humanities Laboratories</head>
                <p>How does the construction of Science and scientific laboratories shape DH
                    identity and practices? How do DH Labs produce Digital Humanists as epistemic
                    subjects, and our objects of inquiry as epistemic objects? To begin, the DH Lab
                    produces and is produced by a network of scholars, practices, institutions,
                    epistemologies, ideologies, and cultures of STEM, the Humanities, higher
                    education, and society writ large. And although <quote rend="inline">analytic
                        cuts</quote>
                    <ptr target="#barad2007"/> are part of the process of making knowable the
                    epistemic object of DH Labs, critically evaluating these cuts can help us to
                    understand how the epistemic subjectivities of DH researchers take part in are
                    co-produced through broader narratives about DH and Science.</p>
                <p>Though the genre of <soCalled>defining DH</soCalled> articles and essays <ptr
                        target="#kirschenbaum2012"/> has been criticized as <quote rend="inline"
                        >absurdly self-referential</quote>
                    <ptr target="#raley2014"/>, work from Laboratory Studies suggests that the
                    absence of these public debates does not mean that disciplinary boundary
                    constructions are settled. Rather, the lack definitional discourse is a product
                    of the <quote rend="inline">making invisible</quote>
                    <ptr target="#garforth2012"/> of the debates, interpretations, and legitimizing
                    and de-legitimizing practices that always occur in knowledge production. </p>
                <p>Rita Raley describes common attacks on DH as part of a broader criticism of the
                    metrically-oriented university, including arguments that <quote rend="inline"
                        >quantitative analysis is unthinking and its investments in <q>precise
                            measurement</q> hopelessly naive; the epistemological certainty that
                        data visualization seems to offer is equally fantastic</quote>
                    <ptr target="#raley2014"/>. While these critiques of quantitative and data
                    cultures are certainly legitimate, they also reinforce the social construction
                    of science as an interpretively naive, yet empirically neutral, knowledge
                    system. We can see some of the issues of this reproduction even in definitional
                    work that supports DH scholarship. James Smithies and Alan Liu have each written
                    about the usefulness — when paired with caution — of scientific and
                    computational methodologies applied to humanities research <ptr
                        target="#liu2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#smithies2017"/>. Similarly, David M. Berry and Anders Fagerjord
                    write: <quote rend="inline">There is clearly also a danger for the humanities
                        when their work is seen through the optic of computational approaches.
                        Hence, it is important that digital humanities remains focused on the
                        research questions that are drawn from the humanities, even whilst working
                        in and through computational approaches</quote>
                	<ptr target="#berry2017" loc="¶50"/>.</p>
                <p>This position, that DH practices represent the <soCalled>application</soCalled>
                    of tools to Humanities questions, is a common one. However, in the co-productive
                    model of knowledge construction, there can never be a separation between the
                    methods we use and the questions we ask. Rather, they are embedded within one
                    another and co-produce each other. Use of these methodologies enrolls broader
                    institutional and epistemological apparatuses when defining
                        <soCalled>computational approaches</soCalled> or <soCalled>humanities
                        questions.</soCalled> As a case, we can take the Introduction to Jentery
                    Sayers’s DH course <title rend="quotes">Unlearning the Internet</title> at the
                    University of Victoria (2018). In the introductory course notes, Sayers explains
                    to his students that: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block"> [This] is not a computer science course. The only
                            technical competencies I assume are that you know how to send an email
                            and also check this website. [It] is not about defining
                                <soCalled>digital humanities.</soCalled> We will treat digital
                            humanities not as a field but as a collection of strategies for
                            conducting humanities research with and through digital technologies. We
                            will emphasize techniques and practices over the use of specific tools
                            and software. <ptr target="#sayers2018"/></quote></cit></p>
                <p>Note the epistemological and identity work performed in this syllabus. The
                    descriptor of <quote rend="inline">not a computer science course</quote> is
                    clearly not intended as a disclaimer about the institutional location of the
                    course, but rather as an epistemic claim. Computer Science is constructed as a
                    set of <soCalled>technical competencies,</soCalled> presumably
                    difficult-to-master ones, in opposition to, or at least orthogonal to, the kinds
                    of knowledge that will be valued in Sayers’s class. The claim of non-definition
                    of DH is followed by a reasonable frame of DH, but one that constructs DH as a
                    collection of practices rather than as a discrete epistemic culture. Finally,
                    the class is positioned as focused on technique and practice rather than on
                    particular digital tools; presumably in opposition to more
                        <soCalled>instrumental</soCalled> STEM classroom cultures <ptr
                        target="#cordell2015"/>.</p>
                <p>The syllabus produces a particular construction of identity, epistemic
                    subjectivity, and disciplinary difference. This production enrolls a variety of
                    constructed facts, including particular imaginations of Computer Science,
                    internal narratives of the strengths of the Humanities, and an anticipation that
                    Humanities students will be intimidated by what they construct as heavily
                    technical work. These facts may be incommensurable with facts from another
                    epistemic culture. For example, despite the common association of Computer
                    Science with toolsets by DH scholars, it would be very outside the norm for
                    Computer Science faculty to frame their course as focused on <quote
                        rend="inline">specific tools and software</quote> rather than on <quote
                        rend="inline">techniques and practices</quote>
                    <ptr target="#malazita"/>. Similarly, the construction of Computer Science as a
                    technical or instrumental discipline also makes invisible the deeply political
                    and historically contingent dimensions of computer science research practices
                        <ptr target="#dourish2004"/>
                    <ptr target="#mcpherson2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#malazita2019b"/>.</p>
                <p> Constructing external disciplinary situatedness such as Computer Science as
                    overly technical and naively instrumental gives other,
                        <soCalled>alternative</soCalled> technical practices, such as DH, internal
                    social capital. It also serves to construct humanist subjectivity as
                        <soCalled>non-technical,</soCalled> and therefore erects barriers around
                    what kinds of educational or scholarly practices are imagined as practical or
                    possible. Raley, for example, dismisses a course or curriculum that <quote
                        rend="inline">satisfactorily train[s] students in different modes of text
                        analysis… visualization techniques, and GIS, along with… literature and a
                        philosophical approach to informatics</quote> as <quote rend="inline"
                        >difficult to imagine.</quote>
                    <ptr target="#raley2014"/>. Ryan Cordell and Rafael Alvarado too argue that the
                    epistemic boundaries of DH are too varied to ever be counted as a discipline, as
                    only a select few polymaths could ever hope to teach or learn such a hybrid
                    cannon <ptr target="#alvarado2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#cordell2015"/>. The construction of a premade humanist or
                    scientific subjectivity thus forecloses the imagination of what can be produced,
                    sustained, and institutionalized through DH practices.</p>
                <p>Digital Humanities labs too can rhetorically reproduce the bounding of technical
                    method and interpretive inquiry. For example, Katy Kavanagh Webb describes a DH
                    lab as: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block">a space that includes technology such as multimedia
                            software and high-powered computers. Some hybrid spaces, such as Georgia
                            State’s CURVE (Collaborative University Research and Visualization
                            Environment) lab, also have visualization screens. Another important
                            aspect of DH labs is the types of meeting and work spaces they can offer
                            to scholars. Duke University even offers lockers where faculty can store
                            research materials. Most DH labs have a strong web presence that
                            showcases the projects that researchers have created. The websites vary
                            from blogs to digital collections (many of them created with Omeka
                            software). <ptr target="#webb2018"/></quote>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Similarly, UMass Amherst describes their DH lab as <quote rend="inline"
                        >contain[ing] necessary hardware and software to facilitate the research
                        agendas of the DHI faculty</quote>
                    <!-- source? -->(University of Massachusetts). Harvard’s East Asian Digital
                    Humanities Lab <quote rend="inline">exhibits ongoing or completed DH projects
                        that can be used as models and provides information about databases, tools
                        and methods that are used in creating these projects,</quote> and <quote
                        rend="inline">... is arranged according to the usual workflow of digital
                        humanists, starting from finding and managing data and moving subsequently
                        to analysis and presentation</quote>
                    <!-- source? -->(Harvard).</p>
                <p>Across all of these examples is the reproduction of a practical construction of
                    DH laboratories, and of laboratories in general: as physical or virtual
                    infrastructures that provide equipment or collaboration spaces for researchers.
                    Again, the technical method and inquiry are reproduced as separate: the lab is
                    the site of technology and method, the humanities researcher is the locus of
                    interpretation and inquiry. In this construction, the lab and its technical
                    apparatus becomes framed as passive; as a necessary holding ground for
                    technology and technique, but one that is ultimately a tool at the service of
                    rotating groups of researchers. Laboratory Studies scholars have shown this is
                    not the case. Labs are active spaces, their very presence on campus reshapes
                    expectations for research, the identities of researchers, the imaginations of
                    objects of inquiry, and the legitimization practices for making knowable those
                    objects. A lab space does not emerge out of an epistemically neutral position.
                    The choices to have a DH lab on campus in the first place, how to staff it, how
                    to outfit it, and which faculty and students are imagined as its audience all
                    contribute to broader constructions of scientific and humanistic knowledge work. </p>
                <p>DH labs are also responsible for producing their outcomes as
                        <soCalled>knowable.</soCalled> Labs must contribute to the legitimization of
                    lab practices and material products for particular epistemic cultures in the
                    Humanities. The <title rend="quotes">Kits for Cultural History,</title> products
                    of Sayers’s University of Victoria Maker Lab <ptr target="#sayers2015"/>, serve
                    as models for thinking through the construction of an epistemic object of DH.
                    Designed as enticing artifacts that allow their users to materially experience
                    media history, each kit contains incomplete reconstructions, archival documents,
                    hidden materials, making tutorials, and reflections about an extant or
                    speculative object. One of the earliest disseminated of these kits was a
                    speculative recreation of Victorian era electro-jewelry, personal wearable
                    technologies, which the authors describe as evoking a sense of wonder and
                    alterity in contemporary viewers. In writeups the kits are described as <quote
                        rend="inline">foreground[ing] how the past is interpreted through present
                        conditions… Hidden compartments point to absences in the scholarly record,
                        implying more omissions exist somewhere beyond the container….</quote>
                    <ptr target="#sayers2015"/>. Jussi Parikka argues that the kits become a <quote
                        rend="inline">disjuncture on a time-axis and [work] to enrich the sense of
                        the contemporary as an overlapping set of temporal layers.</quote>
                    <ptr target="#parikka2016" loc="85"/>.</p>
                <p>However, if we assume a non-universality of audience and the general existence of
                    multiple, competing epistemic subjectivities, we must ask: for whom are these
                    kits built, and for whom do they do the critical historical work of interpreting
                    the past, implying omission, and disjuncturing time? The audience who can know
                    the kits as doing this work must be produced; the material arrangements of wood,
                    plastic, and paper of the kits themselves are not enough. The kits are
                    co-produced and situated by their write-ups and their journeys through media.
                    The subjects for whom they are intended, humanities scholars and students, must
                    be produced as epistemic subjects through the interactions of their education,
                    the objects, the field, and the documentary and critical writings about the
                    objects. The lab practitioners at the Maker Lab must be produced as epistemic
                    subjects capable of translating their historical and material negotiations to an
                    imagined external audience. The kits as material artifacts must be co-produced
                    alongside the validity of their interpretive operation. If any of these
                    productions do not occur, the kits do not function; at least, not in the way
                    described by the Parikka and by the Maker Lab. The <soCalled>results</soCalled>
                    of DH labs are more than virtual and physical objects. Labs produce
                    documentation, contextualization, and subjectification. DH scholars, DH
                    journals, and DH audiences are as much an outcome of laboratory work as any
                    artifact.</p>
                <p>DH Labs are therefore not just institutionally or materially situated; they
                    produce situations, and from there, situatedness. Researchers do not interact
                    with lab equipment and personnel and leave unchanged. Rather, researchers become
                    epistemically and subjectively reconfigured within labs, even as they
                    reconfigure and extend the lab. They are produced as a different kind of
                    epistemic subject capable of knowing the world in different ways. DH labs thus
                    operate not only as knowledge structures <ptr target="#knorrcetina1999"/>,
                    structuring the methods through which research is conducted and circulated, but
                    also as epistemic infrastructures <ptr target="#malazita"/>, producing how
                    researchers ask questions and bound their identities.</p>
                <p>DH knowledge workers have constructed a particular onto-epistemic model of their
                    own scholarship and practice, one of the application of
                        <soCalled>technology,</soCalled> broadly understood, to humanities
                    questions. Acknowledgement of this boundary work is not intended as an attack on
                    DH; <emph>all</emph> knowledge practices create subjects, objects, and
                    boundaries. Rather, we want this critique to serve as an <emph>opening up</emph>
                    of DH practices, and thus of DH labs. As DH labs create situatedness, Humanities
                    scholars can use laboratory spaces and practices as modes of intervention across
                    diverse institutional, epistemological, and disciplinary contexts. These
                    interventions do not have to be constructed as instrumental, as in bringing
                    tools and techniques to <soCalled>non-technical</soCalled> spaces; nor as
                    evangelical, as in bringing the light of critical inquiry to naive technical
                    practitioners. STS argues that the Sciences should not be constructed as a
                    monolithic, anti-interpretive technical enterprise, but rather a collection of
                    diverse, at times contestational and agonistic, persons, networks, and knowledge
                    practices. What can a similar articulation of DH as contestational, diverse sets
                    of epistemic spaces open up? </p>
                <p>Articulating a Disunity of DH alongside the Disunity of Science would impact both
                    the subjectivities of DH practitioners and the situatedness of the DH labs
                    through which we are produced. While the DH work this essay has thus far
                    addressed manifests in more textually-oriented Humanities programs — or, as
                    Kirschenbaum puts it, <quote rend="inline">in English Departments</quote> (2012)
                    — DH could also be constructed as a vehicle for producing knowledge in
                    non-textually dominated humanities fields, or as tactical reconfiguration of
                    non-Humanities fields, including in STEM <ptr target="#malazita2018a"/>
                    <ptr target="#malazita"/>. In the case of synthesizing DH and STS, this would
                    mean undoing some of the present boundary work which has positioned STS as a
                    separate, though allied, disciplinary arena from DH <ptr target="#liu2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#resch2018"/>.</p>
                <p>The Tactical Humanities Lab (THL) at Rensselaer is our effort to epistemically
                    and institutionally produce DH and DH labs as within the boundaries of STS <ptr
                        target="#malazita2019a"/>. The word <soCalled>tactical</soCalled> has for us
                    a double meaning. First, it is a recognition of the deployment of the term
                    already in DH, used somewhat flippantly as a way to <quote rend="inline">get
                        things done</quote>
                    <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2012"/> in the contemporary university. While we
                    certainly do not support the managerialization of higher education, we believe
                    that <soCalled>tactical</soCalled> in this sense can be more than just a way of
                        <quote rend="inline">accepting [our] parasitic relationship to the
                        host</quote> of academic administration <ptr target="#raley2014"/>.
                    Tactical-as-instrumental can also a way of making humanities and social science
                    research knowable to administrative systems, funding systems, and broader
                    cultural narratives of academic research. In this way,
                        <soCalled>tactical</soCalled> DH operates as an intra-institutional
                    translational platform <ptr target="#malazita2018a"/>, in similar ways that
                    translational medicine practices have been constructed as ways of empathetically
                    bridging biomedical research and diagnostic practices with patients and the
                    public <ptr target="#wang2012"/>. The lab must always acknowledge our
                    situatedness in an engineering-centered institute, where laboratory practices
                    and technoscientific innovation are the major knowable genres for framing social
                    and political change. Our lab meetings consistently evolve into discussions and
                    venting sessions about being humanists and critical theorists in the context of
                    an engineering-centered institute. As such, the THL must be made readable as
                    legitimate knowledge practice to STS and Humanities scholars, and within the
                    framework of a technical university. </p>
                <p>Second, we use <soCalled>tactical</soCalled> in de Certeau's form, as the
                    practice of small-scale, everyday resistances to larger systems of power <ptr
                        target="#certeau1980"/>. Part of this commitment is disciplinary; STS
                    scholars tend to construct the field as strongly oriented with social justice
                    and normative approaches to scientific, technological, and knowledge practices.
                    We aim not just to change the Humanities and the social sciences, but to change
                    computer science, design, information technology, and biotechnology. This means
                    not only working with self-identified STEM practitioners, but also
                    highlighting–and holding accountable–the epistemic and political frameworks that
                    underpin disciplinary and technical work across STEM and the humanities. </p>
                <p>To accomplish these twin goals, the THL takes a bottom-up approach to DH
                    laboratory practices. Rather than having one or two longer-term projects
                    administered through the lab director, graduate and undergraduate students
                    propose semester-long projects to the lab, and are free to work individually or
                    in groups. Though projects can continue for multiple semesters, every
                    semester-length segment is structured via a particular development and
                    dissemination plan. The lab assumes no prior expertise in technical work or
                    critical inquiry; students and faculty share readings, run discussions and
                    workshops, and skillshare throughout the semester. The topics of these workshops
                    and reading groups vary depending on the projects pursued in a given semester.
                    The lab has no formal funding model or physical space — students and student
                    projects are funded through a combination of scrapped-together internal and
                    external sources, including bits and pieces of grants from the National
                    Endowment for the Humanities, Rensselaer-based internal
                        <soCalled>accelerator</soCalled> funds, faculty startup funds, Independent
                    Study credits, and preexisting institutional research infrastructures available
                    for supporting undergraduates. Our physical lab presence manifests through
                    distributed temporary spaces, generally either in a conference room outside of
                    Malazita’s office, or throughout various electronics, fabrication, and computer
                    labs on a campus designed for STEM students. In addition to enrolling students
                    from the Humanities, Arts, Sciences, and Engineering across Rensselaer, THL
                    members have also worked to embed themselves back into their home-frameworks
                    with the explicit purpose of bringing this attention to epistemic cultures to
                    research endeavors which may not have initially explicitly valued it. In <quote
                        rend="inline">broadening and opening</quote> our research output <ptr
                        target="#golub2019"/> we have embraced the shapeshifting nature of our work
                    as evidenced by this attention to the epistemic and brought this internalized
                    understanding of <soCalled>tactical</soCalled> knowledge production along with
                    us.</p>
                <p>The above may sound familiar to many DH laboratory practitioners — especially the
                    contingent funding, space shifting, and sweat equity involved in holding a
                    physically situated research practice together. Building momentum towards
                    continuous operation is also complicated by the term-to-term, student-driven
                    nature of the lab’s research foci. The structure of the lab leads to the
                    production of a wide variety of epistemic subjects and objects. The students and
                    faculty represent multiple disciplines, including STS, Arts, Computer Science,
                    Computer Engineering, Sustainability Studies, and Game Design. The project
                    topics range across critical technical education, data visualization,
                    reverse-engineering and hacking hardware, web-based media production, game
                    production, bioart, installation design, and furniture design. </p>
                <p>While the array of projects and disciplines can sometimes lead to a feeling of
                    disjointedness at the beginning of the semester, all projects are united by two
                    lab requirements: the projects must be oriented toward a social or political
                    goal, and the research teams should be interested in making their object
                    knowable by DH and STS audiences. Our collective starting point is that
                        <soCalled>the digital</soCalled> is not a set of tools to be deployed to get
                    social justice done. Rather, the digital, as a coagulation of material,
                    symbolic, and epistemic apparatuses, is entangled with histories of justice,
                    appropriation, resistance, oppression, knowledge-making, agonism, and power.
                    Similarly, the digital is not just a set of material and semiotic systems. It is
                    a pattern of thought that exists as cultural, philosophical, and material
                    practices before and beyond computational systems. As such, it is always
                    ideological, always political, always multiple. Most of our projects are in some
                    way oriented toward deconstructing the digital as an epistemic, ideological, and
                    material concept; building spaces that grapple with translating diverse ways of
                    knowing; hacking existing digital networks to privilege women, PoC, and LGBTQIA+
                    persons; and re-configuring when, where, and how <soCalled>technical</soCalled>
                    and <soCalled>humanistic</soCalled> work happens.</p>
                <p>The discussion of making a THL project knowable to diverse epistemic and personal
                    subjectivity is often the most compelling inter-group activity for lab members.
                    Not only does the articulation of a wide variety of activities <quote
                        rend="inline">as DH</quote> and/or <quote rend="inline">as STS</quote> help
                    to build common identity for lab participants, it also gives participants the
                    space to reflect upon how knowledge is produced, bounded, and legitimized in
                    their own fields. This reflective action, ideally, can lead to reflexive action,
                    where THL members can not only better articulate their projects and their
                    impacts to outside audiences, but also imagine the broader array of facts and
                    results that laboratory work produces. In the following sections, we will
                    articulate two of the projects that have emerged from the THL, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Arbitrary Waveform Generator</hi> and <title rend="italic"
                        >Politicizing DNA</title>. The <title rend="italic">Arbitrary Waveform
                        Generator</title> sees students hacking, re-wiring, and designing musical
                    synthesizers to better understand the relations between mathematics, history,
                    culture, and sound lashed up in their construction. <title rend="italic"
                        >Politicizing DNA</title> uses “the digital” as a metaphor to explore how
                    DNA testing services are rhetorically constructing race and genetic risk in
                    object-oriented ways. Though each project is topically, materially,
                    methodologically, and disciplinarily divergent, each also aims to challenge the
                    epistemic boundaries of digital and non-digital objects, the split between
                    making and interpretive practices, and the epistemic subjectivities of STS and
                    DH knowledge workers.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4. An Arbitrary Waveform Generator</head>
                <p>The <title rend="italic">Arbitrary Waveform Generator</title> develops prior
                    theoretical work by Teboul, who, discussing the history of homemade electronic
                    music instruments, argues that <quote rend="inline">if most audio devices are a
                        new take on an old concept, then acknowledging lineage is ethically
                        preferable to claiming originality</quote>
                    <ptr target="#teboul2018"/>. What can we learn from a technical project where
                    the specifications are cultural and contextual in nature, rather than scientific
                    and measurable? Can we design a usable electronic music instrument that doubles
                    as a lesson in music technology history and open source research? With
                    contributions from Emily Yan and Caoilin Ramsay, computer science and electrical
                    engineering undergraduates at Rensselaer, the project explores the use of
                    alternative design parameters in the design and prototyping process of
                    electronic synthesizers. Synthesizers, widely construed, are the electronic
                    devices that generate sound to help today's musician develop their work. They,
                    along with their users, are responsible for a significant portion of
                    contemporary musical production. While most synthesizer designs follow a <quote
                        rend="inline">Kit-of-Parts</quote> approach <ptr target="#pernerwilson2011"
                    />, where a set of electronic components enable specific sounds at a
                    pre-determined price point, we are building ours to make users reflect upon
                    their own potential as artists, hackers, historians, and anarchivists <ptr
                        target="#striegl2019"/>.</p>
                <p>Why attend to social histories when developing a device that assists in musical
                    composition and performance? Audio electronics often combine otherwise
                        <soCalled>obsolete</soCalled> technologies with newer developments in
                    digital signal processing and integrated circuit designs <ptr
                        target="#paradiso2017"/>. Modular synthesizers, introduced commercially in
                    the US by Moog and Buchla in the mid 1960's <ptr target="#pinch2004"/> now
                    operate in updated forms alongside software-based synthesizers, themselves
                    descendents of Max Mathews' computer music paradigm from the same era <ptr
                        target="#mathews1964"/>
                    <ptr target="#roads1980"/>, <ptr target="#park2009"/>. These digital relatives
                    for live performance include Max/MSP, Pure Data or Supercollider. </p>
                <p>Interfaces that enable the side-by-side, coordinated use of hardware and software
                    devices are, notwithstanding their common origins, relatively rare and
                    expensive. All use proprietary code which makes them relatively expensive and
                    difficult to study. In these technical limitations, related to the historical
                    developments of related inventions, we see an opportunity for productive
                    cultural reflection. We acknowledge that the audio interface we are putting
                    together will encourage some modes of music-making before others. In wondering
                    what the <soCalled>best</soCalled> way to implement a cheaper, more open source,
                    more versatile and most <soCalled>self-aware</soCalled> way to do so, we were
                    drawn to two recent devices. The Bela enables a small Linux computer to process
                    many channels of digital audio with no noticeable lag <ptr
                        target="#mcpherson2016"/>. In complement, the arduino-based "arbitrary
                    function generator" designed by Lawson et al (2016) offers a template for an
                    innovative <soCalled>multi-tool</soCalled> of sound synthesis. Using the Bela
                    allows us to use Pure data, a visual programming environment for music
                    composition and performance <ptr target="#puckette1997"/>. Pure Data is
                    relatively more accessible and user-readable than C++, the other coding language
                    native to the Bela platform. With those, we are able to interface any computer
                    connected to a local network to any eurorack-format modular synthesizer with a
                    user-editable and performable platform. </p>
                <p>Functionally, waveform generator is effectively a programmable oscillator.
                    Because of the physical properties of semiconductors and the history of
                    synthesizers, some waveforms are more common than others: the sine wave, for
                    example, is considered to be the mathematical basis by which all other sound can
                    be reconstructed <ptr target="#helmholtz1954"/>, whereas the square wave is
                    constructed as the basis of digital communication. These waves’ ubiquity in
                    electronics means they are also responsible for a number of the musical timbres
                    reoccurring in popular music; for example, a very distorted guitar approximates
                    the timbre of a square wave. We play with these norms and expectations in two
                    ways: first, by allowing smooth fades between any pair of those canonical
                    waveforms. Second, by implementing a wavetable, a memory space where the value
                    of each audio sample can be rewritten arbitrarily by the user, for the
                    generation of non-standard waveforms. The choice of coding our audio system with
                    Pure Data, which is almost as easy to modify as it is to use, is made in hopes
                    that future experimenters will feel invited to adapt the system to their needs. </p>
                <p>This practical and constructive process is complemented by a deconstructive
                    theory: a <quote rend="inline">critical and practical reverse
                        engineering</quote> that highlights how different devices and different
                    abstractions of devices can be analyzed side-by-side to extract or represent
                    meaning from/in technical decisions. Making is here seen as a lossy type of
                    compression, because less can be retrieved from an artifact than the
                    intellectual and physical resources that have been put into it. History, then,
                    is a process of dealing with the inaccuracies produced in the decompression of
                    this lossy encoding. This dealing is deeply ingrained in the technological
                    archives dear to the project of the humanities. Here, perspectives from critical
                    readings of electronic music and electronic music technology force both a wide
                    construction of the text as including the technological <ptr
                        target="#parikka2011"/>, as well as a reminder that what cannot be encoded
                    has a frictional relationship with text. The Arbitrary Waveform generator is
                    about rendering a multimodal archive operational as a space for lab-based work. </p>
                <p>To that end, Ramsay's work has focused on developing the circuits that allow our
                    device to interact with eurorack format modular synthesizers. A first stage
                    involved breadboarded prototypes, in which electronic components are arranged in
                    temporary circuits without soldering, and we are currently moving to a more
                    permanent <soCalled>protoboard</soCalled> stage for which the functioning
                    circuit is more permanently soldered together. Yan's work has consisted of
                    designing audio programs for composition and performance in Pure Data. These are
                    inspired by the features of Lawson et. al.'s original device (2016), that also
                    enabled a connection between software and hardware synthesizers but uses an
                    Arduino and a wavetable with high-resolution samples rather than function calls
                    to iterate the values of a waveform. Yan's software design allows the user to
                    select pairs of the aforementioned <quote rend="inline">canonical
                        waveforms</quote> and either blend them dynamically, affecting timbre. In
                    addition to that, and a wavetable, we are also implementing a sequencer to
                    automate arbitrary changes of these oscillator settings. Teboul's work,
                    expanding from a role of mentoring the undergraduates on technical and interface
                    design requirements of each component, also consists of linking the team's
                    technical decisions to the musical affordances of the prototype, developing
                    documentation of each of these connections and framing them within a critical
                    perspective inspired by Rodgers and Sterne (2011) or Mills (2011) through the
                    extensive use of system diagrams and code commenting. In doing so we develop a
                    practical understanding of electronic music's technoculture <ptr
                        target="#haring2007"/>. </p>
                <p>Group technical work as a method for history is both the concern of STS <ptr
                        target="#boeva2018"/> and of media archeology <ptr target="#hertz2012"/>,
                    but this is also where we build our primary connection to digital humanities
                    generally, and the THL specifically: by operating in the rarefied design space
                    of electronic music, we have a privileged avenue to talk about how arbitrary
                    technical decisions can or should be leveraged to impart meaning to our
                    political artifacts. This is why we complement technical experimentation with
                    critical and cultural research. Each homemade synthesizer is the local
                    reification of the large technocultural system <ptr target="#hughes1983"/>
                    <ptr target="#wittje2016"/> of electronics and musical production, a fragment
                    through which we can see a partial record of these worlds and what they mean to
                    us. We see this project as offering something new in the context of the digital
                    humanities because although digital tools and associated cultures are an
                    essential aspect, the <term>arbitrary waveform generator</term>makes obvious
                    that any advantage software and digital signal processing may be able to offer
                    in this context is deeply dependent on both the materiality of the hardware at
                    hand and the sociotechnical context within which it is used. </p>
                <p>Reinventing traditional parts of synthesizers in this specifically musical
                    context is a tactic for exposing the politics inherent in every prior instance
                    of these ideas. As such, we do not expect our final prototype to clarify the
                    rich history of do it yourself electronic music instruments through the design
                    of an <soCalled>archetypical</soCalled> or <soCalled>Rosetta Stone</soCalled>
                    device; rather, we hope to hint at the complexity of the practice of electronic
                    music, the hundreds of arbitrary or materially-derived decisions in influential
                    past devices as reifications of compositional ideas, and the potential for
                    future technical work to address its own supposedly apolitical nature. In other
                    words, synthesizers, because of their post-optimal nature <ptr
                        target="#dunne2005"/>
                    <ptr target="#teboul2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#teboul2017"/>
                    <ptr target="#teboul2018"/> offer a unique, variably coupled <ptr
                        target="#perrow2011"/> environment for us to make statements through
                    technical work. The modes of interaction with the device are the result of
                    wondering how material choices help challenge the <soCalled>natural</soCalled>
                    aspect of our traditional musical assumptions. Helmholtz's theory of sound and
                    of the sine as the basic building block of all complex signals <ptr
                        target="#helmholtz1954"/>, is not just the premise for communication theory,
                    but also a significant portion of electronic music making <ptr
                        target="#jackson2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#hui2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#hankins1999"/>; we are constantly aware that although biases can
                    be challenged in our theories of instrument making, it is in practical use that
                    power relationship are most re-established. </p>
                <p>We construe our arbitrary waveform as an ideological object. Wittje <ref
                        target="#wittje2016">(2016)</ref> and Patteson <ref target="#patteson2016"
                        >(2016)</ref> made clear that the political underpinnings of scientistic
                    approaches to sound most clearly exemplified by Helmholtz' work have deep roots
                    in the scientization of acoustic and electrical phenomena in interwar Germany or
                    Europe. Keeping precedents such as those in mind, our work as a team contributes
                    to the slowly growing practice of synthesis as an explicitly political space of
                    experimentation, with the development that statements can be made with
                    technological decisions alongside cultural ones <ptr target="#sterne2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#rodgers2015"/>. </p>
                <p>This project sits at an uneasy crossroads. We feel the pressure outlined by Brian
                    Massumi in <title rend="quotes">On The Superiority of The Analog</title>
                    <ref target="#massumi2002">(2002)</ref>, acknowledging that ultimately we are
                    making a machine for still-analog humans and their perceptual fields. On the
                    other we are equally unsettled by what may seem as a contemporary focus on the
                    digital. This is visible from digital humanities to digital music instruments
                        (<soCalled>DMI</soCalled>, see <ptr target="#jorda2005"/>
                    <ptr target="#calegario2017"/>
                    <ptr target="#magnusson2017"/>
                    <ptr target="#armitage2017"/>, the latter of which have come to dominate
                    contemporary instrument making dialog in academia. At no point does our project
                    indicate a clear preference for hardware or software, for computation over
                    critique or vice-versa.</p>
                <p>Our status as relative amateurs (this is effectively our first digital music
                    interface project, let alone as a research group) is viewed as a motivation more
                    than a hindrance: the technical issues at hand aren't more difficult than the
                    critical questions we are asking, and therefore we are able to avoid
                    prioritization based on comfort. Echoing the <title rend="italic">Kits for
                        Cultural History </title>
                    <ptr target="#sayers2015"/>, we hope to smash the archival and anarchival <ptr
                        target="#striegl2019"/> together, picking up the pieces and documenting them
                    for future reiteration, offering a robust template and solidified framework for
                    a method in the process. In this work, textual commentary emerges as an
                    undertheorized mode of operationalizing both diagrams and interactive visual
                    programming software such as Pure Data. Inspired by this digital culture
                    technique of the <emph>comment</emph>, we are in dialog with DH and its
                    artificial boundaries: between analog and digital, between human and nonhuman,
                    between media archeology and platform studies <ptr target="#apperley2015"/>,
                    between engineering and music studies, but always in <emph>practice,</emph>and
                    in service of<emph>a functional result.</emph>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5. Politicizing DNA</head>
                <p>The<title rend="italic"> Politicizing DNA </title>project analyzes how seemingly
                    objective scientific and genetic data has profound political and social effects
                    on current and future conceptions of race. With the rise of direct-to-consumer
                    (DTC) genetic testing, social conceptions of race are brought back into
                    question. By re-inserting the politics of science back into DNA, this project
                    aims to deconstruct the attempts at presenting DNA as unpolitical or neutral.
                    This project seeks to answer how race is constructed within these genetic test
                    kits by reviewing the mission statements, products, and classifications of
                    racial identity of direct-to-consumer genetic testing companies such as 23andMe
                    and the Genographic Project. The project takes a stance of active refusal: the
                    construction of DTC testing as a political knowledge practice rather than as a
                    material practice allows us to engage with DTC without subjecting our own DNA to
                    the laboratories that house and process these genetic tests, and the legal
                    policies that regulate these laboratories.</p>
                <p>Given our refusal to take and materially manipulate DTC tests, why are we
                    constructing this project as DH? DNA is constructed as informational in popular
                    culture <ptr target="#nelkin2010"/> and in the laboratory <ptr
                        target="#thacker2003"/>
                    <ptr target="#chun2011"/>, both of which borrow rhetoric from computational
                    knowledge practices. These constructive practices are common in laboratory
                    settings, where scientific knowledge workers seek to translate their objects of
                    inquiry into information, and in so doing make the objects knowable by the
                    laboratory apparatus <ptr target="#knorrcetina1999"/>. For genetics researchers,
                    this construction produces metaphorical, methodological, and ideological
                    assumptions, with the assumption that DNA can be read, coded, and re-coded, and
                    that the relationship between DNA, the body, and the environment is a discrete
                    and networked one, rather than a discursive and ecological one. Though these
                    assumptions have been increasingly challenged <ptr target="#bolnick2007"/>, they
                    have produced decades of research agendas and laboratory infrastructures,
                    including $2.7 billion in public funds dedicated to the Human Genome Project
                    alone <ptr target="#tripp2011"/>.</p>
                <p> As genetic testing rapidly moves from-and-through research labs to consumer
                    spaces, DTC technologies seek to enroll the public in biopolitical practices
                    akin to mass data sousveillance <ptr target="#nelkin1999"/>, packaging and
                    selling our genetic material back to ourselves. DTC testing services reconfigure
                    mass <soCalled>data scraping</soCalled> practices into mass <soCalled>data
                        swabbing</soCalled> practices. Consumers choosing to not take a genetic test
                    or engage with the broader apparatus of genetic testing are making political
                    decisions to deviate from the new normal of circulating and commercially
                    operationalizing genetic data. These choices intersect with gendered and
                    racialized systems of digital and genetic surveillance, including onto-epistemic
                        <ptr target="#barad2007"/> systems of classification, identity, and
                    belonging that structure the lives and digital experiences of marginalized
                    people <ptr target="#tallbear2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#mcpherson2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#noble2018"/>.</p>
                <p> Spearheaded by Rafeh and undergraduate researchers Paloma Alonso and Hannah
                    Lightner, the <title rend="italic">Politicizing DNA </title>project has thus far
                    centered the mediated constructions of DNA, race, and identity with-and-through
                    digital infrastructures. The <title rend="italic">Politicizing DNA</title> team
                    is comprised of women and women of color, particularly rare in an institute like
                    Rensselaer that is majority white and male. This intentional structuring of the
                    project team produces a unique situatedness for the lab, as it recognizes that
                    the positionality of the researchers in a lab co-constructs the kinds of
                    questions asked, the ways in which the epistemic object is bounded, and what
                    counts as legitimate discourse. That women and women of color are investigating
                    DTC genetics is particularly important, due to the history of exclusionary,
                    exploitative, and oppressive practices in medicine and healthcare <ptr
                        target="#braun2002"/>
                    <ptr target="#roberts2011"/>. This type of politically situated lab structure
                    reinforces the research group's work of politicizing formerly depoliticized
                    scientific processes.</p>
                <p>Of primary analysis was the construction of the relationships between genetics
                    and identity through DTC’s public-facing documents. These documents primarily
                    included websites (including <ref target="http://www.23andme.com"
                        >23andme.com</ref>, <ref target="https://www.ancestry.com/"
                        >ancestry.com</ref>, <ref
                        target="https://genographic.nationalgeographic.com/"
                        >genographic.nationalgeographic.com/</ref>, and africanancestry.com), but
                    also included archival materials such as FDA regulatory decisions,
                    Terms-of-Service contracts, and popular coverage of DTC tests in media. Public
                    understandings of the gene cyclically influence, and are influenced by,
                    scientific understanding of the gene <ptr target="#bates2005"/>
                    <ptr target="#savard2013"/>. At the same time, the epistemic object of the gene
                    known by the public is a different artefact than the gene as multiply
                    constructed by the scientific community <ptr target="#nelkin2010"/>
                    <ptr target="#torgersen2009"/>. These differences include how scientific
                    achievements are promoted in the public as more significant or advanced than
                    stated in publications. </p>
                <p>These different meanings continue to disassemble the idea that
                        <soCalled>science</soCalled> is apolitical, or separate from social
                    influence. The public fascination with DNA orients the scientific community just
                    as much as the scientific community orients public fascination. For example,
                    when a lab does publicly engage with the politics of DNA, it is often done in a
                    way that leverages Enlightenment narratives of the public good of scientific
                    enterprise, rather than addressing genetic sciences’ history of oppression and
                    abuse, particularly of women and women of color. This follows the prioritization
                    of scientific research over the understanding of the political and social
                    meanings it has in the world for multiple epistemic subjectivities. </p>
                <p>Contrary to much DH research, the <title rend="italic">Politicizing DNA</title>
                    project employs close reading rather than distant reading to develop hermeneutic
                    analyses of the digital object of DNA as constructed through corporate websites.
                    The researchers weren't just tasked to look at language frequency or
                    presence/absence, but also to interpret how each company chose to publicly
                    engage with the intersections of race, identity, and DNA. This included both a
                    rhetorical analysis, how these concepts were deployed or not deployed in text,
                    and also a situational analysis, such as whether or not identity content was
                    included in advertising materials, terms and conditions, or legal documentation.
                    Each of these digital-textual formats are governed by different legal standards,
                    giving implied and explicit meanings behind the words companies chose to
                    use.</p>
                <p>Given the lingering presence of the <soCalled>hack vs. yack</soCalled> debates of
                    the mid-2010s in DH research communities <ptr target="#nowviskie2014"/>, the
                    lack of technical sophistication or use of manual analysis over programming may
                    lead to some scholars to construct <title rend="italic">Politicizing DNA</title>
                    as outside the bounds of DH. However, we argue that the project’s methodology
                    deeply engages <soCalled>the digital,</soCalled> deploying a rhetorical and
                    archeological trancing of a digital object across multiple digital media, and as
                    it intersects with legal apparatuses, identity, and materiality. After the
                    initial swabbing test kit that consumers receive and return to DTC genetics
                    companies, the entirety of the consumer-facing genetic test experience is
                    digital. The materiality of DNA has been transformed into a digital
                    experience.</p>
                <p>While Berry and Fagerjord argue that <quote rend="inline">the question of whether
                        something is or is not <q>digital</q> will be increasingly secondary as many
                        forms of culture become mediated, produced, accessed, distributed or
                        consumed through digital devices and technologies</quote>
                    <ptr target="#berry2017" loc="2"/>, the <title rend="italic">Politicizing DNA
                    </title>project provides an alternative critique of the humanities/technology
                    divide. Further, by constructing this project as DH, we are arguing that asking
                    whether something <soCalled>is digital</soCalled> is not a question of
                    technicity or mediation. Rather, it is an ideological and political question,
                    one whose answer enrolls an array of knowledge systems, normative concerns,
                    market logics, and institutional apparatuses. Claiming DNA as digital subsumes
                    it into a larger infrastructures of data processing and computational culture.
                    Similarly, claiming the analysis of DTC DNA testing and its rhetoric as DH
                    allows us to enroll larger systems of analysis and interpretation that highlight
                    DNA as a transitory object among wet and digital bodies.</p>
                <p>Lab work has thus far uncovered ill-defined terminology and unfeasible promises
                    of ancestry on these companies’ websites. The websites of DTC genetic test
                    companies do not explicitly discuss race, and instead use wording such as
                        <soCalled>ancestry</soCalled> or <soCalled>population groups</soCalled>. Our
                    results have shown how race and ethnicity are subjective terms exploited by DTC
                    genetic testing websites. This exploitation has been evident through websites’
                    ill-defined terminology and unfeasible promises of ancestry. For example,
                    instead of using race, the three genetic companies use the terms <quote
                        rend="inline">ethnic groups and tribes,</quote>
                    <quote rend="inline">populations,</quote> and <quote rend="inline">ethnic
                        populations.</quote></p>
                <p>Even though the companies don’t talk about race, DTC genetic tests are used to
                    confirm, deny, or discover racial identities. DTC tests have direct
                    ramifications among several groups of people, including white nationalists <ptr
                        target="#panofsky2019"/>, African Americans <ptr target="#nelson2016"/>, and
                    Native Americans <ptr target="#tallbear2013"/>, engaging with popular
                    conceptions of what it means to be Black, white or Native. Incidentally, the
                    only website to explicitly discuss race was AfricanAncestry. In their FAQ
                    section of their website, they answer the question <quote rend="inline">Can a
                        DNA analysis identify my racial or ethnic identity?</quote> with: <quote
                        rend="inline">There is no test for racial identification. Race is a social
                        construct, not genetically determined. Similarly, ethnicity is more cultural
                        than biological</quote> (<ref target="https://africanancestry.com/home/"
                        >africanancestry.com</ref>). Not only is it poignant that a DTC genetic
                    ancestry company provides this kind of answer that reflects scholarship in
                    social studies of science, but it is also interesting that the only company that
                    centers itself on ethnic identity also provides information on the social
                    construct of race. </p>
                <p>Though <title rend="italic">Politicizing DNA</title> is still in early stages, we
                    hope that our findings will contribute to the public understanding of genetics
                    by analyzing the accessibility and representation of genetic information as it
                    affects the public’s perceptions of genetics and race. The ultimate goal of this
                    study was to examine the portrayal of race and ancestry in DTC genetic tests by
                    asking how do DTC genetic testing companies classify people into different
                    groups based on ancestry, ethnicity, and race. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p> Constructing laboratories as epistemic infrastructures that produce epistemic
                    subjects, objects, and cultures destabilizes current imaginations of DH
                    practice. While DH labs are often framed as semi-passive resource spaces, where
                    students and faculty can access equipment, trained staff, and research
                    infrastructures, we have argued that labs are instead epistemically active
                    spaces. DH labs produce the epistemic subjectivities of researchers, the
                    textures and boundaries of the objects made knowable by the lab, and the
                    material-discursive practices that make legitimate DH research. </p>
                <p>This reconstruction of laboratories, and of DH labs in particular, brings with it
                    epistemic opportunities. If the boundaries of DH work are produced through
                    particular imaginations of science and scientific practice, through imaginations
                    of the abstracted <soCalled>user</soCalled> of DH spaces, then the shifting of
                    that imaginative landscape can have tremendous impact upon the shapes and
                    structures of DH labs. These impacts may include alternative models of
                    laboratory work, alternative disciplinary spaces where DH work can be practiced,
                    and alternative objects of DH research. Alternative knowledge practices lead to
                    alternative epistemic subjects, new bodies of theory, shifting infrastructural
                    and institutional terrain, and may move us toward a more <quote rend="inline"
                        >radical, unrealized potential</quote>
                    <ptr target="#posner2016"/> of DH. </p>
                <p>For the Tactical Humanities Lab, this potential includes the expansion of
                    disciplinary and epistemic situatedness beyond textually-based humanities into
                    the humanistic social sciences, cultural studies, and STEM. The THL is one
                    possible configuration of DH that could emerge, one that focuses on the
                    construction of the boundaries of technical and interpretive work, and on the
                    production of DH knowledge and subjectivity through technical work, written
                    argumentation, and labor practices. While this is certainly not the only form DH
                    could take when reading-through STS knowledge practices, and while there are
                    countless other disciplines through which DH could be co-constructed, we offer
                    the THL as an alternative to the tool/application centeredness that dominates
                    contemporary narratives of the digital humanities, and as an alternative for
                    imagining when, where, and for whom DH knowledge practices can happen.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="africanancestry" label="AfricanAncestry.com">
                    <title rend="quotes">Trace Your DNA. Find Your Roots. Today.</title> Accessed
                    January 30, 2020. <ref target="https://africanancestry.com/home/"
                        >https://africanancestry.com/home/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="alvarado2012" label="Alvarado 2012">Alvarado, Rafael C. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Digital Humanities Situation.</title> In <title
                        rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, 50–55. Minneapolis:
                    University of Minnesotta Press, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="apperley2015" label="Apperley and Parikka 2015">Apperley, Thomas, and
                    Jussi Parikka. <title rend="quotes">Platform Studies’ Epistemic
                        Threshold.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Games and Culture</title> 13, no. 4 (2015): 349–69. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1555412015616509"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/1555412015616509</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="armitage2017" label="Armitage et al. 2017">Armitage, Jack, Fabio
                    Morreale, and Andrew McPherson. <title rend="quotes"><q>The Finer the Musician,
                            the Smaller the Details</q>: NIMEcraft under the Microscope.</title> In
                        <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the International Conferences on New
                        Interfaces for Musical Expression</title>, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barad2007" label="Barad 2007">Barad, Karen Michelle. <title
                        rend="italic">Meeting the Universe Halfway: Quantum Physics and the
                        Entanglement of Matter and Meaning</title>. Durham: Duke University Press,
                    2007.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bates2005" label="Bates 2005">Bates, Benjamin R. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Public Culture and Public Understanding of Genetics: A Focus Group
                        Study.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Public Understanding of Science</title> 14, no. 1 (2005):
                    47–65.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berry2017" label="Berry and Fagerjord 2017">Berry, David M., and
                    Anders Fagerjord. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities: Knowledge and
                        Critique in a Digital Age</title>. John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bianco2012" label="Bianco 2012">Bianco, Jamie
                        <soCalled>Skye</soCalled>. <title rend="quotes">The Digital Humanities Which
                        Is Not One.</title> In <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities</title>, 96–112. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press,
                    2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bijker2012" label="Bijker et al. 2012">Bijker, Wiebe E., Thomas P.
                    Hughes, Trevor J. Pinch, and Deborah G. Douglas, eds. <title rend="italic">The
                        Social Construction of Technological Systems: New Directions in the
                        Sociology and History of Technology</title>. Second Edition. Cambridge: MIT
                    Press, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bloor1999" label="Bloor 1999">Bloor, David. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Anti-Latour.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Studies in History and Philosophy of Science Part A</title>
                    30, no. 1 (March 1999): 81–112. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0039-3681(98)00038-7"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1016/S0039-3681(98)00038-7</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bloor1976" label="Bloor 1976">Blood, David. <title rend="italic"
                        >Knowledge and Social Imagery</title>. Routledge Direct Editions. London ;
                    Boston: Routledge &amp; K. Paul, 1976.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bloor1983" label="Bloor 1983">Bloor, David. <title rend="italic"
                        >Wittgenstein: A Social Theory of Knowledge</title>. New York: Columbia
                    University Press, 1983.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boeva2018" label="Boeva et al. 2018">Boeva, Yana, Devon Elliot, Edward
                    Jones-Imhotep, Shezan Muhammedi, and William J. Turkel. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Doing History By Reverse Engineering Electronic Devices.</title> In <title
                        rend="italic">Making Things And Drawing Boundaries: Experiments In The
                        Digital Humanities</title>, edited by Jentery Sayers, 163–76. Minneapolis:
                    University of Minnesota Press, 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bogost2012" label="Bogost 2012">Bogost, Ian. <title rend="italic"
                        >Alien Phenomenology, or, What It’s Like to Be a Thing</title>. Minneapolis:
                    University of Minnesota Press, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bolnick2007" label="Bolnick et al. 2007">Bolnick, Deborah A., Duana
                    Fullwiley, Troy Duster, Richard S. Cooper, Joan H. Fujimura, Jonathan Kahn, Jay
                    S. Kaufman, et al. <title rend="quotes">The Science and Business of Genetic
                        Ancestry Testing.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Science</title> 318, no. 5849 (October 19, 2007): 399–400.
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1150098"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1150098</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="braidotti1994" label="Braidotti 1994">Braidotti, Rosi. <title
                        rend="italic">Nomadic Subjects: Embodiment and Sexual Difference in
                        Contemporary Feminist Theory</title>. Gender and Culture. New York: Columbia
                    University Press, 1994.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="braun2002" label="Braun 2002">Braun, Lundy. <title rend="quotes">Race,
                        Ethnicity, and Health: Can Genetics Explain Disparities?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Perspectives in Biology and Medicine</title> 45, no. 2 (May
                    1, 2002): 159–74. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1353/pbm.2002.0023"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1353/pbm.2002.0023</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bryant2011" label="Bryant 2011">Bryant, Levi R. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Democracy of Objects</title>. 1. ed. New Metaphysics. Ann Arbor, Mich:
                    Open Humanities Press, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="calegario2017" label="Calegario et al. 2017">Calegario, Filipe,
                    Marcelo M. Wanderley, Stephane Huot, Giordano Cabral, and Geber Ramalho. <title
                        rend="quotes">A Method and Toolkit for Digital Musical Instruments:
                        Generating Ideas and Prototypes.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">IEEE MultiMedia</title> 24, no. 1 (2017): 63–71.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="callon1982" label="Callon and Law 1982">Callon, Michel, and John Law.
                        <title rend="quotes">On Interests and Their Transformation: Enrolment and
                        Counter-Enrolment.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Social Studies of Science</title> 12, no. 4 (November 1,
                    1982): 615–25. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/030631282012004006"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/030631282012004006</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="certeau1980" label="Certeau 1980">Certeau, Michel de. <title
                        rend="italic">The Practice of Everyday Life</title>. Berkeley, Calif.: Univ.
                    of California Press, 1980.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chun2011" label="Chun 2011">Chun, Wendy Hui Kyong. <title
                        rend="italic">Programmed Visions: Software and Memory</title>. Cambridge,
                    Mass.: MIT Press, 2011</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="collins1975" label="Collins 1975">Collins, Harry M. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Seven Sexes: A Study in the Sociology of a Phenomenon, or
                        the Replication of Experiments in Physics.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Sociology</title> 9, no. 2 (1975): 205–224.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cordell2015" label="Cordell 2015">Cordell, Ryan. <title rend="quotes"
                        >How Not to Teach Digital Humanities,</title> 2015. <ref
                        target="https://ryancordell.org/teaching/how-not-to-teach-digital-humanities/"
                        >https://ryancordell.org/teaching/how-not-to-teach-digital-humanities/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dourish2004" label="Dourish 2004">Dourish, Paul. <title rend="italic"
                        >Where the Action Is: The Foundations of Embodied Interaction</title>. 1.
                    MIT Press paperback ed. A Bradford Book. Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press,
                    2004.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dunne2005" label="Dunne 2005">Dunne, Anthony. <title rend="italic"
                        >Hertzian Tales: Electronic Products, Aesthetic Experience, and Critical
                        Design</title>. 2005 ed. Cambridge, Mass: MIT Press, 2005.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eidin2004" label="Eidin 2004">Eidlin, Fred. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Ideology, Objectivity, and Reality in Natural Science, Social Science, and
                        Politics.</title> SSRN Scholarly Paper. Rochester, NY: Social Science
                    Research Network, 2004. <ref target="https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=1963404"
                        >https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=1963404</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="foka2017" label="Foka et al. 2017">Foka, Anna, Anna Misharina, Viktor
                    Arvidsson, and Stefan Gelfgren. <title rend="quotes">Beyond Humanities Qua
                        Digital: Spatial and Material Development for Digital Research
                        Infrastructures in Humlabx.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> 33, no. 2
                    (2017): 264–278.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="garforth2012" label="Garforth 2012">Garforth, Lisa. <title
                        rend="quotes">In/Visibilities of Research: Seeing and Knowing in
                        STS.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values</title> 37, no. 2
                    (2012): 264–85.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="golub2019" label="Golub et al. 2019">Golub, Koraljka, Elisabet
                    Göransson, Anna Foka, and Isto Huvila. <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities
                        in Sweden and Its Infrastructure: Status Quo and the Sine qua Non.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hamraie2018" label="Hamraie 2018">Hamraie, Aimi. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Mapping Access: Digital Humanities, Disability Justice, and Sociospatial
                        Practice.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">American Quarterly</title> 70, no. 3 (2018): 455–82. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1353/aq.2018.0031"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1353/aq.2018.0031</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hankins1999" label="Hankins and Silverman 1999">Hankins, Thomas L, and
                    Robert J Silverman. <title rend="italic">Instruments and the
                    Imagination</title>. Princeton University Press, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="haraway1991" label="Haraway 1991">Haraway, Donna Jeanne. <title
                        rend="italic">Simians, Cyborgs, and Women: The Reinvention of
                    Nature</title>. New York: Routledge, 1991.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="haring2007" label="Haring 2007">Haring, Kristen. <title rend="italic"
                        >Ham Radio’s Technical Culture</title>. Cambridge: MIT Press, 2007.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harman2011" label="Harman 2011">Harman, Graham. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Quadruple Object</title>. Winchester, U.K. Washington, USA: Zero Books,
                    2011.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harvardeast" label="Harvard East Asian Digital Scholarship Lab"
                    >Harvard East Asian Digital Scholarship Lab. <title rend="quotes">Research
                        Guides: East Asian Digital Scholarship Lab: Get Started.</title> Accessed
                    January 30, 2020. <ref
                        target="https://guides.library.harvard.edu/c.php?g=608708&amp;p=4224591"
                        >https://guides.library.harvard.edu/c.php?g=608708&amp;p=4224591</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="helmholtz1954" label="Helmholtz 1954">Helmholtz, H. <title
                        rend="italic">On the Sensations of Tone</title>. Dover Books on Music
                    Series. New York: Dover, 1954.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hertz2012" label="Hertz and Parikka 2012">Hertz, Garnet, and Jussi
                    Parikka. <title rend="quotes">Zombie Media: Circuit Bending Media Archaeology
                        into an Art Method.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Leonardo</title> 45, no. 5 (2012): 424–30.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hughes1983" label="Hughes 1983">Hughes, Thomas Parke. <title
                        rend="italic">Networks of Power: Electrification in Western Society,
                        1880-1930</title>. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1983.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hui2013" label="Hui et al. 2013">Hui, Alexandra, Julia Kursell, and
                    Myles W Jackson. <title rend="quotes">Music, Sound, and the Laboratory from 1750
                        to 1980.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Osiris</title> 28, no. 1 (2013): 1–11.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jackson2011" label="Jackson 2011">Jackson, Myles W. <title
                        rend="quotes">From Scientific Instruments to Musical Instruments: The Tuning
                        Fork, the Metronome, and the Siren.</title> In <title rend="italic">The
                        Oxford Handbook of Sound Studies</title>, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jorda2005" label="Jorda 2005">Jorda, Sergi. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Digital Lutherie: Crafting Musical Computers for New Musics’ Performance
                        and Improvisation.</title> PhD Thesis, Universitat Pompeu Fabra,
                    2005.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2012" label="Kirschenbaum 2012">Kirschenbaum, Matthew.
                        <title rend="quotes">What Is Digital Humanities and What’s It Doing in
                        English Departments?</title> In <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities</title>, 3–11. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press,
                    2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kleinman2013" label="Kleinman et al. 2013">Kleinman, Daniel Lee, and
                    Sainath Suryanarayanan. <title rend="quotes">Dying Bees and the Social
                        Production of Ignorance.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values</title> 38, no. 4
                    (July 1, 2013): 492–517. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243912442575"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243912442575</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="knorrcetina1999" label="Knorr Cetina 1999">Knorr Cetina, K. <title
                        rend="italic">Epistemic Cultures: How the Sciences Make Knowledge</title>.
                    Cambridge, Mass: Harvard University Press, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="knorrcetina2007" label="Knorr Cetina 2007">Knorr Cetina, Karin. <title
                        rend="quotes">Culture in Global Knowledge Societies: Knowledge Cultures and
                        Epistemic Cultures.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</title> 32, no. 4
                    (December 1, 2007): 361–75. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1179/030801807X163571"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1179/030801807X163571</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="latour1992" label="Latour 1992">Latour, Bruno. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Where Are the Missing Masses? The Sociology of a Few Mundane
                        Artifacts.</title> In <title rend="italic">Shaping Technology/Building
                        Society; Studies in Sociotechnical Change</title>, 225–58. Cambridge: MIT
                    Press, 1992.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="latour2004" label="Latour 2004">— — — . <title rend="quotes">Why Has
                        Critique Run Out of Steam? From Matters of Fact to Matters of
                        Concern.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Critical Inquiry</title> 30, no. 2 (2004): 225–48.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="latour1986" label="Latour and Woolgar 1986">Latour, Bruno, and Steve
                    Woolgar. <title rend="italic">Laboratory Life: The Construction of Scientific
                        Facts</title>. Princeton, N.J: Princeton University Press, 1986.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lawson2016" label="Lawson et al. 2016">Lawson, Shawn, Ryan Ross Smith,
                    and Frank Appio. <title rend="quotes">Closing the Circuit: Live Coding the
                        Modular Synthesizer,</title> 2016, 6.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2012" label="Liu 2012">Liu, Alan. <title rend="quotes">Where Is the
                        Cultural Criticism in the Digital Humanities?</title> In <title
                        rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, 490–509.
                    Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="magnusson2017" label="Magnusson 2017">Magnusson, Thor. <title
                        rend="quotes">Contextualizing Musical Organics: An Ad-Hoc Organological
                        Classification Approach.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                        International Conference on New Interfaces for Musical Expression</title>,
                    6, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="malazita2019a" label="Malazita 2019">Malazita, James. <title
                        rend="quotes">About – Tactical Humanities Lab,</title> 2019. <ref
                        target="https://tactical.wp.rpi.edu/about/"
                        >https://tactical.wp.rpi.edu/about/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="malazita" label="Malazita Forthcoming">Malazita, James. <title
                        rend="quotes">Epistemic Infrastructures, the Instrumental Turn, and the
                        Digital Humanities.</title> In <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities: Institutions, Infrastructures at the Interstices</title>.
                    Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, Forthcoming.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="malazita2018a" label="Malazita 2018a">Malazita, James W. <title
                        rend="quotes">Re: Configurations — A Shared Project for Literature and
                        Science.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Configurations</title> 26, no. 3 (July 11, 2018): 269–75.
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1353/con.2018.0021"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1353/con.2018.0021</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="malazita2018b" label="Malazita 2018b">Malazita, James W. <title
                        rend="quotes">Translating Critical Design: Agonism in Engineering
                        Education.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Design Issues</title> 34, no. 4 (2018): 96–109.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="malazita2019b" label="Malazita and Resetar 2019">Malazita, James W.,
                    and Korryn Resetar. <title rend="quotes">Infrastructures of Abstraction: How
                        Computer Science Education Produces Anti-Political Subjects.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Creativity</title> 30, no. 4 (October 2, 2019):
                    300–312. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/14626268.2019.1682616"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1080/14626268.2019.1682616</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="massumi2002" label="Massumi 2002">Massumi, Brian. <title rend="quotes"
                        >On the Superiority of the Analog.</title> In <title rend="italic">Parables
                        for the Virtual</title>, 2002.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mathews1964" label="Mathews and Miller 1964">Mathews, Max V, and Joan
                    E Miller. <title rend="italic">Music IV Programmer’s Manual</title>. Murray
                    Hill: Bell Telephone Laboratories, Incorporated, 1964.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2016" label="McPherson et al 2016">McPherson, Andrew P,
                    Robert H Jack, and Giulio Moro. <title rend="quotes">Action-Sound Latency: Are
                        Our Tools Fast Enough?</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                        International Conference on New Interfaces for Musical Expression</title>,
                    6, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2014" label="McPherson 2014">McPherson, Tara. <title
                        rend="quotes">Designing for Difference.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Differences</title> 25, no. 1 (May 1, 2014): 177–88. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1215/10407391-2420039"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1215/10407391-2420039</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2011" label="McPherson 2011">McPherson, Tara. <title
                        rend="quotes">US Operating Systems at Mid-Century: The Intertwining of Race
                        and UNIX.</title> In <title rend="italic">Race After The Internet</title>,
                    21–37. New York: Routledge, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mead1968" label="Mead 1968">Mead, Margaret. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Cybernetics of Cybernetics.</title> In <title rend="italic">Purposive
                        Systems</title>, 1–11. New York: Spartan Books, 1968.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mills2011" label="Mills 2011">Mills, Mara. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Hearing Aids and the History of Electronics Miniaturization.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</title> 33, no. 2
                    (2011): 24–45.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mol2002" label="Mol 2002">Mol, Annemarie. <title rend="italic">The
                        Body Multiple: Ontology in Medical Practice</title>. Science and Cultural
                    Theory. Durham: Duke University Press, 2002.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="molotch2003" label="Molotch 2003">Molotch, Harvey. <title
                        rend="italic">Where Stuff Comes From: How Toasters, Toilets, Cars, Computers
                        and Many Other Things Come To Be As They Are.</title> 2003. <ref
                        target="http://ebookcentral.proquest.com/lib/qut/detail.action?docID=214526"
                        >http://ebookcentral.proquest.com/lib/qut/detail.action?docID=214526</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nelkin1999" label="Nelkin and Andrews 1999">Nelkin, Dorothy, and Lori
                    Andrews. <title rend="quotes">DNA Identification and Surveillance Creep.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Sociology of Health &amp; Illness</title> 21, no. 5 (1999):
                    689–706.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nelkin2010" label="Nelkin and Lindee 2010">Nelkin, Dorothy, and M.
                    Susan Lindee. <title rend="italic">The DNA Mystique: The Gene as a Cultural
                        Icon</title>. University of Michigan Press, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nelson2016" label="Nelson 2016">Nelson, Alondra. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Social Life of DNA: Race, Reparations, and Reconciliation after the
                        Genome</title>. Boston: Beacon Press, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="noble2018" label="Noble 2018">Noble, Safiya Umoja. <title
                        rend="italic">Algorithms of Oppression: How Search Engines Reinforce
                        Racism</title>. New York: New York University Press, 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nowviskie2014" label="Nowviskie 2014">Nowviskie, Bethany. <title
                        rend="quotes">On the Origin of <q>Hack</q> and <q>Yack.</q></title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 3, no. 2 (2014):
                    3–2.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="panofsky2019" label="Panofsky and Donovan 2019">Panofsky, Aaron, and
                    Joan Donovan. <title rend="quotes">Genetic Ancestry Testing Among White
                        Nationalists: From Identity Repair to Citizen Science.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Social Studies of Science</title> 49, no. 5 (October 1,
                    2019): 653–81. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0306312719861434"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/0306312719861434</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="paradiso2017" label="Paradiso 2017">Paradiso, Joseph A. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Modular Explosion - Deja Vu or Something New?,</title> 13,
                    2017.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="parikka2011" label="Parikka 2011">Parikka, Jussi. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Operative Media Archaeology: Wolfgang Ernst’s Materialist Media
                        Diagrammatics.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Theory, Culture &amp; Society</title> 28, no. 5 (September
                    2011): 52–74. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0263276411411496"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/0263276411411496</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="parikka2016" label="Parikka 2016">— — — . <title rend="quotes">The Lab
                        Imaginary: Speculative Practices In Situ.</title> In <title rend="italic"
                        >Across and Beyond - A Transmediale Reader on Post-Digital Practices,
                        Concepts, and Institutions</title>, 78–91. Berlin: Sternberg Press,
                    2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="park2009" label="Park and Mathews 2009">Park, Tae Hong and Max
                    Mathews. <title rend="quotes">An Interview with Max Mathews.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Computer Music Journal</title> 33, no. 3 (2009):
                    9–22.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="patteson2016" label="Patteson 2016">Patteson, Thomas. <title
                        rend="italic">Instruments for New Music: Sound, Technology, and
                        Modernism</title>. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pernerwilson2011" label="Perner-Wilson 2011">Perner-Wilson, Hannah
                    Hannah Rosamonde. <title rend="quotes">A Kit-of-No-Parts.</title> Master’s
                    Thesis, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="perrow2011" label="Perrow 2011">Perrow, Charles. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Fukushima and the Inevitability of Accidents.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists</title> 67, no. 6 (2011):
                    44–52.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pinch2004" label="Pinch and Trocco 2004">Pinch, Trevor, and Frank
                    Trocco. <title rend="italic">Analog Days: The Invention and Impact of the Moog
                        Synthesizer</title>. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2004.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="posner2016" label="Posner 2016">Posner, Miriam. <title rend="quotes"
                        >What’s Next: The Radical, Unrealized Potential of Digital
                        Humanities.</title> In <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities 2016</title>, 32–41. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press,
                    2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="puckette1997" label="Puckette 1997">Puckette, Miller. <title
                        rend="quotes">Pure Data,</title> 1997.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="raley2014" label="Raley 2014">Raley, Rita. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Digital Humanities for the Next Five Minutes.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Differences</title> 25, no. 1 (May 1, 2014): 26–45. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1215/10407391-2419991"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1215/10407391-2419991</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="resch2018" label="Resch et al 2018">Resch, Gabby, Dan Southwick, I.
                    Record, M. Ratto, and J. Sayers. <title rend="quotes">Thinking as Handwork:
                        Critical Making with Humanistic Concerns.</title> In <title rend="italic"
                        >Making Things and Drawing Boundaries. Experiments in the Digital
                        Humanities</title>, 149–61. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press,
                    2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="roads1980" label="Roads and Mathews 1980">Roads, C., and Max Mathews.
                        <title rend="quotes">Interview with Max Mathews.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Computer Music Journal</title> 4, no. 4 (1980): 15. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.2307/3679463"
                        >https://doi.org/10.2307/3679463</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="roberts2011" label="Roberts et al 2011">Roberts, Maegan E., Douglas L.
                    Riegert-Johnson, Brittany C. Thomas. <title rend="quotes">Self diagnosis of
                        lynch syndrome using direct to consumer genetic testing: A case
                        study.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Genetic Counseling. </title>20, no. 4 (2011):
                    327-329</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rodgers2015" label="Rodgers 2015">Rodgers, Tara. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Cultivating Activist Lives in Sound.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Leonardo Music Journal</title> 25 (2015): 79–83.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="savard2013" label="Savard 2013">Savard, Jacqueline. <title
                        rend="quotes">Personalised Medicine: A Critique on the Future of Health
                        Care.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Bioethical Inquiry</title> 10, no. 2 (2013):
                    197–203.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sayers2015" label="Sayers 2015">Sayers, Jentery. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Kits for Cultural History, or Fluxkits for Scholarly Communication.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Hyperrhiz: New Media Cultures</title> 13 (2015). <ref
                        target="http://hyperrhiz.io/hyperrhiz13/workshops-kits/early-wearables-essay.html"
                        >http://hyperrhiz.io/hyperrhiz13/workshops-kits/early-wearables-essay.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sayers2018" label="Sayers 2018">— — — . <title rend="quotes"
                        >Unlearning the Internet.</title> Unlearning the Internet, 2018. <ref
                        target="http://jentery.github.io/150/"
                    >http://jentery.github.io/150/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="smithies2017" label="Smithies 2017">Smithies, James. <title
                        rend="italic">The Digital Humanities and the Digital Modern</title>. London,
                    United Kingdom: Palgrave Macmillan, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sterne2011" label="Sterne 2011">Sterne, Jonathan, and Tara Rodgers.
                        <title rend="quotes">The Poetics of Signal Processing.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Differences</title> 22, no. 2–3 (2011): 31–53.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="striegl2019" label="Striegl and Emerson 2019">Striegl, Libi, and Lori
                    Emerson. <title rend="quotes">Anarchive as Technique in the Media Archaeology
                        Lab | Building a One Laptop Per Child Mesh Network.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">International Journal of Digital Humanities</title>, April
                    1, 2019. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s42803-019-00005-9"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1007/s42803-019-00005-9</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tallbear2013" label="TallBear 2013">TallBear, Kimberly. <title
                        rend="italic">Native American DNA: Tribal Belonging and the False Promise of
                        Genetic Science</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press,
                    2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="teboul2018" label="Teboul 2018">Teboul, Ezra J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Electronic Music Hardware and Open Design Methodologies for Post-Optimal
                        Objects.</title> In <title rend="italic">Making Things and Drawing
                        Boundaries: Experiments in the Digital Humanities</title>, edited by Jentery
                    Sayers, 177–84. Minneapolis: University of Minnesotta Press, 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="teboul2015" label="Teboul 2015">Teboul, Ezra J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Silicon Luthiers: Contemporary Practices in Electronic Music
                        Hardware.</title> Master’s Thesis, Dartmouth College, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="teboul2017" label="Teboul 2017">Teboul, Ezra J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Transgressive Practices of Silicon Luthiers.</title> In <title
                        rend="italic">Guide to Unconventional Computing for Music</title>, edited by
                    Eduardo Miranda, 85–120. New York: Springer, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thacker2003" label="Thacker 2003">Thacker, Eugene. <title
                        rend="quotes">Data Made Flesh: Biotechnology and the Discourse of the
                        Posthuman</title></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="culturalcritique" label="Cultural Critique">
                    <title rend="italic">Cultural Critique</title> No. 53, Posthumanism (Winter,
                    2003), pp. 72-97</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="torgersen2009" label="Torgersen 2009">Torgersen, Helge. <title
                        rend="quotes">Fuzzy Genes: Epistemic Tensions in Genomics.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Science as Culture</title> 18, no. 1 (2009): 65–87.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tripp2011" label="Tripp and Grueber 2011">Tripp, Simon, and Martin
                    Grueber. <title rend="quotes">Economic Impact of the Human Genome
                        Project.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Battelle Memorial Institute</title>, 2011, 1–58.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wang2012" label="Wang 2012">Wang, Xiangdong. <title rend="quotes">A
                        New Vision of Definition, Commentary, and Understanding in Clinical and
                        Translational Medicine.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Clinical and Translational Medicine</title> 1, no. 1 (May
                    3, 2012): 5. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1186/2001-1326-1-5"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1186/2001-1326-1-5</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="webb2018" label="Webb 2018">Webb, Katy Kavanagh. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Digital Humanities Lab: A Dedicated Space to Support Faculty’s Creative
                        Endeavors.</title> Library Connect, June 11, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://libraryconnect.elsevier.com/articles/digital-humanities-lab-dedicated-space-support-faculty-s-creative-endeavors"
                        >https://libraryconnect.elsevier.com/articles/digital-humanities-lab-dedicated-space-support-faculty-s-creative-endeavors</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="winner1980" label="Winner 1980">Winner, Langdon. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Do Artifacts Have Politics?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Daedalus</title>, 1980, 121–36.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wittje2016" label="Wittje 2016">Wittje, Roland. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Age of Electroacoustics: Transforming Science and Sound</title>. The
                    MIT Press, 2016.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
