<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
	xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
	xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
				<title type="article" xml:lang="en">A Review of James Little’s <title rend="italic">The Making of Samuel Beckett’s
						Not I / Pas moi, That Time / Cette Fois and Footfalls / Pas</title> (2021)</title>
				<!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Céline <dhq:family>Thobois</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
					<!--<idno type="ORCID"
						><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
					<dhq:affiliation>Trinity College Dublin</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>cthobois@tcd.ie</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Céline Thobois is a PhD researcher in the Department of Drama at Trinity College Dublin. Her thesis –
							supervised by Nicholas Johnson and funded by the Irish Research Council – investigates the interactions between
							the human, technology and the environment in Samuel Beckett’s drama. Her publications have appeared in <title
								rend="italic">Samuel Beckett Today/Aujourd’hui</title>, <title rend="italic">Beckett and Technology</title>
							and <title rend="italic">Theatre Journal</title>. She is currently co-editing <title rend="italic">Samuel
								Beckett and Ecology</title> (Bloomsbury, 2024) and the Anthropocene issue of the <title rend="italic">Journal
								of Beckett Studies</title> (Edinburgh University Press, 2024). She co-convenes the Samuel Beckett Working
							Group of the International Federation for Theatre Research with Trish McTighe.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
				<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
				<!--This information will be completed at publication-->
				<idno type="DHQarticle-id">000492</idno>
				<idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
				<idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
				<date/>
				<dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
				<availability status="CC-BY-ND">
					<!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
					<cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>This is the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
					<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en" extent="original"/>
				<!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
					<!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
					<!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
					<term corresp="#digital"/>
					<term corresp="#elit"/>
					<term corresp="#literary_studies"/>
					<term corresp="#performance"/>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
					<!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
					<list type="simple">
						<item>Samuel Beckett</item>
						<item>genetic criticism</item>
						<item>mind theory</item>
						<item>Beckett Digital Manuscript Project</item>
						<item>performance</item>
						<item>theatre</item>
						<item>translation</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
			<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
					target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000492/000492.xml">GitHub
				</ref>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en" type="original">
		<front>
			<dhq:abstract>
				<!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
				<p>This review highlights the main achievements of James Little’s <title rend="italic">The Making of Samuel Beckett’s
					Not I / Pas moi, That Time / Cette Fois and Footfalls / Pas</title> (2021).</p>
			</dhq:abstract>
			<dhq:teaser>
				<!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
				<p>Reviewing James Little's book, <title rend="italic">The Making of Samuel Beckett’s
					Not I / Pas moi, That Time / Cette Fois and Footfalls / Pas</title></p>
			</dhq:teaser>
		</front>
		<body>
			<epigraph>
				<figure>
					<head>This activation piece is composed with materials drawn from existing sources. Researcher’s dialogue is taken
						from Opener’s lines in Beckett’s <title rend="italic">Cascando</title> (1963) <ptr target="#beckett2006"
							loc="297–298"/>. Book’s lines are excerpts from James Little’s <title rend="italic">The Making of Samuel
							Beckett's Not I / Pas moi, That Time / Cette Fois and Footfalls / Pas</title>
						<ptr target="#little2021" loc="126"/>. Manuscript’s cues are from <title rend="none">MS–TCD–4664, module 10,
							Samuel Beckett: Digital Manuscript Project</title>
						<ptr target="#beckett2022" loc="17r"/>.<note>Editorial Note: This is an accessibly formatted version of the
							activation piece in the figure above. While not a perfect model of the piece, we hope it gives a greater number
							of our readers a version of the piece they can access.
							<lb/><sp>
								<speaker>RESEARCHER</speaker>
								<p>I open.</p>
							</sp>
							<sp>
								<speaker>BOOK</speaker>
								<p>There is no spoken text on this page, but a set of stage directions describe a situation of observed
									speaking, whereby the two women each give a ‘statement’, during which their upraised faces are picked out
									by a spot and the other figures are in darkness (17r).</p>
							</sp>
							<sp>
								<speaker>RESEARCHER</speaker>
								<p>And I close.
									<lb/><stage>Silence.</stage>
									<lb/>I open the other.</p>
							</sp>
							<sp>
								<speaker><hi style="color:gray;">DIGITAL MANUSCRIPT</hi></speaker>
								<p><hi style="color:gray;"><hi rend="strikethrough">x</hi> 1. General light. All 3 seated. B &amp; C plain
										chairs, A armchair. B &amp; C bowed heads. A head up looking at them. 2. General light gradually down,
										all light on C’s face, <hi rend="superscript">her head lifts</hi>, rest darkness. 3. <hi
											rend="strikethrough">C’s statement</hi> C’s statement 4. <hi rend="strikethrough">x</hi> Gradual return
										to gener, C’s head down, B’s still down, A’s still up looking.</hi></p>
							</sp>
							<sp>
								<speaker>RESEARCHER</speaker>
								<p>And I close.
									<lb/><stage>Silence.</stage>
									<lb/>I open both.</p>
							</sp>
							<stage>Together.</stage>
							<sp>
								<speaker>BOOK</speaker>
								<p>While Beckett would have difficulties with the Auditor of <title rend="italic">Not I</title>, he was also
									unsure as to how many listeners should be on the stage of this draft play. He added another (silent) female
									figure (D) to the bottom of his stage directions along with the word ‘Possible’, and also added – </p>
							</sp>
							<sp>
								<speaker><hi style="color:gray;">DIGITAL MANUSCRIPT</hi></speaker>
								<p><hi style="color:gray;">5. General light gradually down, all light on B’s face, her head lifts, rest
										darkness. 6. B’s statement. 7. Gradual return to general light, B’s head down, <hi rend="strikethrough"
											>A</hi>C’s still down, A’s now down. Curtain. Possible: D – woman, armchair. 1. Looking at B &amp; C.
										4. Head down. 7. Head still down</hi></p>
							</sp>
							<sp>
								<speaker>RESEARCHER</speaker>
								<p><stage>With BOOK and DIGITAL MANUSCRIPT</stage> And I close.
									<lb/><stage>Silence.</stage>
									<lb/>I start again.</p>
							</sp></note>
					</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
					<figDesc>Dramatic prose in the style of Samuel Beckett</figDesc>
				</figure>
			</epigraph>
			<div>
				<head/>
				<p>Dialogue and its failure underpin Samuel Beckett’s (1906–1989) oeuvre not only as a narrative or as a dramatic
					structure, but also as an epistemological approach. In the Irish artist’s practice, verbal dialogue is often
					reworked to generate non-anthropocentric interactions. Amongst the agents that are put into conversation, one can
					think of a number of everyday-life objects, technological devices, dust or even mud. It is in the radio plays that
					Beckett achieved intermedial dialogue to the most powerful effect with <title rend="italic">Words and Music</title>
					(1961) and <title rend="italic">Cascando</title> (1962). The experimenters – respectively Croak and Opener –
					attempt to tease out a theme or to tell a story by regulating dialogue between two media: words (in <title
						rend="italic">Words and Music</title>) / voice (in <title rend="italic">Cascando</title>) and music (in the two
					plays). In both cases, the result is not the one anticipated by the experimenters, whose control is challenged by
					the agency of the non-human characters. The dialogue orchestrated by James Little between <title rend="italic">The
						Making of Samuel Beckett’s Not I / Pas moi, That Time / Cette Fois and Footfalls / Pas</title> and the
					corresponding archival documents on the Beckett Digital Manuscript Project is a well-mastered and productive one,
					but beware: both the book and the original manuscripts may take you off the prescribed track.</p>
				<p>Over the past eleven years, the Samuel Beckett Digital Manuscript Project (BDMP) – <ref
						target="https://www.beckettarchive.org/">https://www.beckettarchive.org/</ref> – led by Dirk Van Hulle and Mark
					Nixon – has transformed the approach to Samuel Beckett’s oeuvre by publishing digitised facsimiles of the
					manuscripts that led to the publication of texts both in English and in French. The digital archive is extended by
					an array of features that facilitate the reading of the manuscripts and their comparison. This contribution has
					been so potent that it has been acknowledged as the genetic turn in Beckett studies, influencing the ways in which
					Beckett’s texts are received, researched and reused.<note>For instance, Pan Pan Theatre’s 2019 production of <title
							rend="italic">Endgame</title> placed process at the heart of its project. The set itself was made out of
						recycled opera sets, hence acknowledging the palimpsestic nature of all art. The script ultimately performed by
						the creative team was informed by an in-depth study of the play’s endogenesis, exogenesis and epigenesis. Thanks
						to the <title rend="italic">Fin de partie / Endgame</title> module of the BDMP, in conjunction with Shane Weller
						and Dirk Van Hulle’s <title rend="italic">The Making of Fin de partie / Endgame</title> (2018) and <title
							rend="italic">The Theatrical Notebooks of Samuel Beckett, Volume II: Endgame, edited by S.E. Gontarski</title>
						(2019), dramaturg Nicholas Johnson indexed all variables in the text and compiled them in a rehearsal script with
						a hundred and seven annotations. This working volume facilitated director Gavin Quinn’s and actors’ – Andrew
						Bennett (Hamm), Des Keogh (Nagg), Rosaleen Linehan (Nell) and Antony Morris (Clov) – experimentation in studio
						and ultimate choice of versions of the text they would perform.</note> In 2018, the BDMP was awarded the eleventh
					Modern Language Association of America (MLA) Prize for a Bibliography, Archive, or Digital Project, thereby gaining
					formal recognition for its transformative impact beyond Beckett studies as a digital practice that: tackles the
					problem of accessibility to archival material, challenges the ontological status of text itself as fixed, and
					augments the epistemology of literary studies. </p>
				<p>James Little’s <title rend="italic">The Making of Samuel Beckett’s Not I / Pas moi, That Time / Cette Fois and
						Footfalls / Pas</title> represents a landmark in the history of the BDMP, for it is their tenth genetic edition.
					While it follows <title rend="italic">The Making of</title> series’ traditions, it also innovates by ambitiously
					reconstructing the genesis of three texts in the same volume: other series monographs focus solely on a single
					text, with the exception of Dirk Van Hulle’s <title rend="italic">The Making of Samuel Beckett’s Stirrings Still /
						Soubresauts and Comment dire / what is the word</title> (2016) – which examines the genesis of Beckett’s
					penultimate text and his last poem – and Olga Beloborodova’s <title rend="italic">The Making of Samuel Beckett’s
						Play / Comédie and Film</title> (2019) – which studies the genesis of the theatre and television plays and
					illustrates best how Beckett had become a multimedial artist. When working with <title rend="italic">Not I</title>
					(1973) and <title rend="italic">Footfalls</title> (1976), critics and artists alike have often included <title
						rend="italic">Rockaby</title> (1982) in the grouping of texts or performances. Little’s genetic edition hence
					reconfigures the triad by leaving out <title rend="italic">Rockaby</title> and instead including <title
						rend="italic">That Time</title> (1976). While the former association has proven useful to explore gender,
					embodiment and space, Little’s innovative combination spotlights Beckett’s cognition-based dramaturgy in this
					cluster of plays. The volume then can be read in line with Dirk Van Hulle’s <title rend="italic">The Making of
						Samuel Beckett’s Krapp’s Last Tape / La Dernière Bande</title> (2017) which unveils how Beckett’s thinking of the
					mind informed the composition of this poignant dramatic piece staging <quote rend="inline">the [decaying] workings
						of a person’s mind</quote>
					<ptr target="#vanhulle2015" loc="21"/>. </p>
				<p>The genesis of each text is presented in a separate section of the book, themselves divided into two sub-sections: </p>
				<list type="unordered">
					<item><title rend="quotes">Documents:</title> the chronological presentation and the description of English and
						French manuscripts, typescripts, setting copies, galleys and proofs that led to the published texts, as well as
						their first editions across languages and the playscripts and production notes. This sub-section is illustrated
						with a genetic map, which provides a visual summary of the genetic process; a gesture that both fosters
						accessibility and facilitates navigation between the documents of each module on the BDMP;</item>
					<item><title rend="quotes">Genesis:</title> an analytic and interpretative narrative of the genesis of the texts
						and their translation. </item>
				</list>
				<p>This review will highlight the main discoveries and achievements of each section without following their internal
					structure.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>A Hybrid Journey through the Narrative and Performance of Beckett’s Enactive Mind </head>
				<p>The general introduction locates Beckett’s artistic creation of the three plays within the scope of his life-long
					interest in cognition, mind theory, psychology, psychoanalysis and neuroscience. Little argues that Beckett’s
					research into, and critical engagement with, those areas not only nourished his aesthetic, but also informed his
					thinking of the <quote rend="inline">breakdown between subject and object</quote>
					<ptr target="#little2021" loc="28"/>, as Beckett initially formulated it in the 1934 essay <title rend="quotes"
						>Recent Irish Poetry.</title> The author therefore delineates his own intervention in Beckett Studies as
					bridge-building between Beckett’s early philosophical and aesthetic statement and his late dramaturgical practice
					in the triad <title rend="italic">Not I / Pas moi</title>, <title rend="italic">That Time / Cette fois</title> and
						<title rend="italic">Footfalls / Pas</title>. A short case study of <title rend="italic">Footfalls</title>
					operates as an effective demonstration of the value of genetic criticism to uncover Beckett’s staging of the
						<q>breakdown</q> through psychological images, such as May’s enactive mind in this case. </p>
				<p>Drawing on past research around Beckett’s creative process and by analogy with archaeological discoveries that led
					to the reframing of the mind as an interactive process between the subject, their environment and objects
					populating it, Little simultaneously demonstrates how the study of manuscripts – and therefore of the creative
					process – bears witness to Beckett’s own enactive mind. In other words, Beckett’s texts must be understood as the
					product of a multi-layered process that is embodied and situated. This point is transformative for practice, since
					the performance of these texts then needs to function as a synaptic space between Beckett’s creative spaces (that
					of when he created the play and that for which he created the play) and the audiences’ own environments. </p>
				<p>In a surprising move towards performance theory and theatre history, Little proceeds to argue that this effect can
					only be achieved in Cartesian Theatres with a proscenium arch framing the action (aesthetic object) and separating
					it from the observing spectator (subject), such as the Royal Court Theatre in London, where Beckett directed the
					three plays. This separation is challenged in performance, Little explains, by the aesthetic of the stage image
					that emerges out of darkness. The restrained use of light generates metaphysical uncertainty as to the material
					conditions of the agent onstage and consequently epistemological uncertainty for the spectator. Little contends
					that it is in the planned failure to seize the onstage mind that the breakdown between subject and object occurs.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head><title rend="quotes">Kilcool</title> Drafts and <title rend="quotes">Petit Odéon</title> Fragments: Strata of
					Beckett’s Oeuvre Before and Beyond Not I </head>
				<p>As the genetic map of <title rend="italic">Not I / Pas moi</title> clearly shows, the French and English published
					editions are the top layers of a stratified maturation process that compares to that of <title rend="italic"
						>Endgame / Fin de partie</title>, due to the nature of its <term>avant-texte</term>, split between texts written
					before <title rend="italic">Not I</title> (which are not versions of the play, but experiments that paved the way
					to <title rend="italic">Not I</title>) and those written towards <title rend="italic">Not I</title> (as versions of
					play). The first English manuscript that qualifies as <term>avant-texte</term> towards <title rend="italic">Not
						I</title> is dated from March 1972, and the last English typescript was produced in January 1973. That text was
					translated into French between 1973 and 1974. However, some of the dramaturgical and thematic ideas underpinning
					the play emerged as early as 1963 with <title rend="quotes">J. M. Mime</title> and the <title rend="quotes"
						>Kilcool</title> drafts, and others four years later in the <title rend="quotes">Petit Odéon</title> fragments
					written between April 1967 and April 1968. Little’s narrative of the genesis of <title rend="italic">Not I / Pas
						moi</title> effectively segregates the study of those abandoned works from that of the versions and drafts of
						<title rend="italic">Not I</title>, highlighting their connection – particularly that of <title rend="quotes"
						>Kilcool</title> – to the oeuvre as a whole rather than to <title rend="italic">Not I</title> alone. Little’s
					vision, which appears as a slight stretch, still shows that those abandoned texts function as experiments both
					fertilised by the previous works and fertilising the ones to follow. In other words, the rhizomatic structure of
					Beckett’s oeuvre is dynamically mapped out by Little’s genetic criticism of <title rend="quotes">Kilcool</title>
					and the <title rend="quotes">Petit Odéon</title> fragments. </p>
				<p>Conversely, Little’s analysis of the four <title rend="quotes">Kilcool</title> drafts and the ten <title
						rend="quotes">Petit Odéon</title> fragments sheds more light on Beckett’s composition process, informed by his
					readings, his other artistic activities (rehearsals, directing, translation, etc.), his creative engagement with
					other media and genres (mostly film, mime, and prose in those instances), his collaborations with particular
					theatre practitioners (such as Alan Schneider, Patrick Magee, Jocelyn Herbert, Madeleine Renaud and Jean-Louis
					Barrault amongst others) and theatre spaces (notably the Petit Odéon in Paris). The <quote rend="inline">vast
						stretch of time</quote>
					<ptr target="#beckett2012"/>Beckett 2012] and colossal range of materials covered by Little in this prologue-like
					subsection is indicative of the depth and breadth of the volume as a whole, and the scholarship presented under the
					heading <title rend="quotes">Before <title rend="italic">Not I / Pas moi</title></title> creates an authoritative
					timeline of those abandoned works, situating them with outstanding precision as nodes on Beckett’s creative map. </p>
				<p>The focus on the subject/object breakdown recedes in the analysis of the <title rend="quotes">Kilcool</title>
					drafts, where Little excavates as many thematic and structural connections as possible between this abandoned piece
					and <title rend="italic">Not I</title>, <title rend="italic">That Time</title>, <title rend="italic"
						>Footfalls</title> and beyond. Nevertheless, in this experimental series of drafts, the first one stands out, for
					it shows that Beckett’s idea of a lit, speaking woman’s face was always designed for the Cartesian Theatre with the
					frame of the proscenium arch. Little does not lose sight of his focus, and the breakdown is more prominent in the
					analysis of the <title rend="quotes">Petit Odéon</title> fragments, where he also underscores Beckett’s creative
					and critical use of medical history. </p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Not I / Pas moi: <quote rend="inline">…what?.. the buzzing?.. yes… all the time the buzzing… so-called…</quote>
				</head>
				<p>Little’s analysis of the geneses of Not I and Pas moi sheds light on versions and drafts of the texts as
					interfaces between the author’s mind, Mouth’s mind, the Auditor’s mind, Billie Whitelaw’s mind and the spectators’
					minds. He seizes every opportunity to sketch out Beckett’s creative process, whether it is via the layout of text
					on the page, the chronology of ideas and textual edits or their interaction with his correspondence. While the
					playwright himself questioned his own abilities as a theatre practitioner, Little demonstrates that by the time
					Beckett wrote Not I, the stage image and the script were profoundly shaped by his experience of being physically in
					the theatre auditorium and of rehearsing with actors, as well as by his personal engagement with the visual arts.
					Little’s scholarship contributes to establishing the centrality of embodied cognition in Beckett’s drama and its
					subsequent impact on twentieth-century theatre: with Not I, the breakdown between subject and object is not to be
					witnessed or understood; it is to be felt. </p>
				<p>At the beginning of the <title rend="quotes">Genesis</title> subsection, the image of the synopsis of Not I, taken
					from the eighth English typescript, illustrates the structure that Beckett had in mind for the play – so to speak –
					and the omnipresence of cognition at thematic and structural levels. Little adopts Beckett’s outline as a guide for
					his own archaeological journey through the English drafts of Not I. The strategy proves efficient to dig through
					most of the main furrows opened by Beckett and to unearth the underlying systems on, and against which, the
					cognitive environment of the play is built from Otto Rank and Ernest Jones to Sigmund Freud and Max Nordeau, from
					Gestalt psychology and behaviourist theories to the significance of William James’ <quote rend="inline">big
						blooming buzzing confusion</quote> [James, quoted in <ref target="#little2021" loc="168">Little 2021</ref>, 168].
					Navigating the digitised manuscripts with this section of the book is a rich experience, but the multiplicity of
					themes and the wide range of perspectives, theories, and intertextual links marshalled by Little in blocks built by
					Beckett for narrative and rehearsal purposes pulls the reader in many directions, which may result in temporary
					cognitive overload. </p>
				<p>As oxymoronic as the proposition may be, darkness then appears as an illuminating path to follow for a steady
					journey through the making of Not I / Pas moi. Working from the Éditions de Minuit’s 2014 publication of Pour finir
					encore et autres foirades, Little aptly defines darkness as a Beckettian topos of memory and imagination, but also
					as a mechanistic cognitive space. He traces the creation of Mouth’s automatic mind in the darkness of the stage by
					contrast with the evolving role of the light as an inquisitor reminiscent of the spotlight in Play. By focusing on
					Beckett’s addition of the verb <word>flash</word> in the second English typescript onwards – to express the mode of
					appearance of Mouth’s thoughts – Little argues that thoughts operate as disruptions of the darkened mind space.
					Turning to language, sounds, rhythms and silences, he brilliantly analyses the function of the ellipses in the
					script and the discarding of certain words as Beckett’s boring of holes in language and therefore as the painting
					of epistemological darkness at a linguistic level. The analysis of the French documents moves away from darkness,
					but it explores related processes such as dehumanizing, vaguening, syllabic un- and re-doing and unending. Little’s
					genetic criticism of Not I / Pas moi will undoubtedly bear considerable influence on future performances of both
					Mouth and Auditor alike and on the scenography of future stagings of Not I.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>That Time / Cette fois: <quote rend="inline">something like that come and gone come and gone no one come and gone in no time
						gone in no time</quote></head>
				<p>Little’s study of the <term>avant-texte</term> of <title rend="italic">That Time / Cette fois</title> invites the
					reader to follow him in a fascinating intertextual and autotextual journey. By exploring time both at thematic and
					structural level in this play, Beckett goes back to one of his early metaphysical interests and necessarily to some
					of his classics: Marcel Proust and Dante Alighieri. However, as Little demonstrates, Beckett’s focus on
					consciousness and memory is also informed by past readings of, or about, Friedrich Hölderlin, Rank, Lao Tzu, George
					Berkeley and Henri Bergson and by Beckett’s own work on those notions in pieces such as <title rend="italic"
						>Krapp’s Last Tape</title> (1958), <title rend="italic">Comment c’est</title> (1961), and <title rend="italic"
						>Lessness</title> (1970). In particular, Little’s identification and analysis of the potential intertextual links
					with Proust’s work and Proust’s own composition process is a tour de force that enables the reader, on the one
					hand, to trace the lexical, conceptual, dramaturgical and translational connections between <title rend="italic"
						>That time</title>, <title rend="italic">Cette fois</title> and <title rend="italic">À la recherche du temps
						perdu</title> (1913–1927), unlocking new potential interpretations of the nexus of memory/time in the playscript
					and in the stage image of the play. On the other hand, it exemplifies once more Beckett’s rhizomatic and
					palimpsestic creative process and his strategy of <q>vaguening,</q> supplemented with elements of serialism and
					imagism in the creation of <title rend="italic">That Time</title>, which rather illustrate Beckett’s intermedial
					practice, as Little convincingly argues. The originality of Little’s approach also lies in his study of autotextual
					connections, as a means to show how the sonic quality of the text takes precedence over references in the creation
					process, hence reinforcing the thesis that Beckett wrote his play text for performance. </p>
				<p>The study of the breakdown in <title rend="italic">That Time</title> is multi-layered and goes from strength to
					strength: starting from processes in common with <title rend="italic">Not I</title>, Little moves to the
					specificity of the breakdown in <title rend="italic">That Time</title> that pertains to memory. It is through the
					intertextual link with several of Hölderlin’s texts that Little first traces how memory is enacted as a process of
					self-fragmentation in the play. Little supports the reader’s exploration of this argument by featuring the
					hyperlinks to the digitised facsimile of Beckett’s copy of Hölderlin’s <title rend="italic">Sämtliche Werke</title>
					(Leipzig: Insel Verlag, 1926) that can be consulted on the Beckett Digital Library, another section of the BDMP.
					Little then interprets Beckett’s division of A, B and C’s monologues (the three voices that Listener hears) into
					smaller units (lexia), their sequencing and their reordering during the composition of the play both as a process
					of entanglement of the three voices and as a thematization of the breakdown, simultaneously making it visible on
					the page. Additionally, the author highlights how the play articulates a breakdown between subject and object
					through the failure of communication. Most importantly, Little’s analysis of the lexical field of business in lexia
					C10 reveals that the subject-object breakdown is not purely psychological but also social. After studying the
					ossification of the remembered self, Little shifts his attention to the contrasting narratives of the same memory
					by the three voices, which buttresses the thesis according to which the subject breakdown also happens in the
					foregrounding of the constructiveness of memory and of the remembered self. Little’s inquiry into the
					subject/memory breakdown through a reworked version of Beckett’s own analytic structure is most effective to create
					a clear picture of the mechanisms, themes and structures of the breakdown in <title rend="italic">That
					Time</title>, providing an unprecedented and near-exhaustive study of this Beckettian trope and aesthetic quest in
					the play under examination.</p>
				<p>Eventually, it is worth noting that Little’s description and chronology of the documents that are part of the
						<title rend="italic">That Time / Cette fois</title> module and his study of the French translation frame the
					genetic criticism of the play, but they also perform other fundamental roles. The description of the documents
					sheds light on, and pays tribute to, the work of archivists through the analysis of foliation and the cataloguing
					history of the two loose leaves of the manuscript UoR MS 1639. Moreover, the study of font sizes, paper quality and
					Sellotape marks on the typescripts informs the reader’s understanding of Beckett’s material composition process and
					will be of particular interest to scholars and artists investigating the materiality of manuscripts and Beckett’s
					extended mind. Little concludes the genetic criticism of <title rend="italic">Cette fois</title> with a list of the
					orthographic, conjugational and grammatical errors that Beckett made in the process of translation. A short
					quantitative analysis of the errors in the first full handwritten manuscripts of <title rend="italic">Not
					I</title>, <title rend="italic">Pas moi</title>, <title rend="italic">That Time</title>, <title rend="italic">Cette
						fois</title> and <title rend="italic">Footfalls</title> (a footnote indicates that this document is missing for
						<title rend="italic">Pas</title>) reveals the discrepancy between <title rend="italic">Cette fois</title> and
					other plays. Little suggests that the significantly higher number of errors in that manuscript could be another
					indication of Beckett’s translation struggles, but he warns the reader against the temptation of drawing any
					further conclusion and instead advocates for the <quote rend="inline">perform[ance of] an act of
							<emph>recovery</emph> by publishing Beckett’s play in a bilingual critical edition</quote>
					<ptr target="#little2021" loc="347"/>. This final gesture speaks for the integrity and generosity with which Little
					disseminates his research, acknowledging all colleagues who helped him during the research and writing process,
					facilitating access to the most minute, hidden or intricate details of the documents under study and overtly
					sharing ideas for further research into the three texts and their translations. The book then is not only a
					precious resource for experts, but it is an ethical model and a source of inspiration for undergraduate and
					postgraduate students alike.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Footfalls / Pas: <quote rend="inline">Will you never have done… revolving it all? [Pause.] It? [Pause.] It all. [Pause.] In
						your poor mind.</quote></head>
				<p>As one makes their way through the third section of the book (the genetic criticism of <title rend="italic"
						>Footfalls/Pas</title>), they encounter several salient concepts to categorise the play – a play about ageing, a
					play about birth, a pacing play, a painkiller play, a wintery play – thematically linking this text to other works
					in Beckett’s oeuvre, while singularly articulating <q>revolving,</q> the core dynamic in <title rend="italic"
						>Footfalls</title>. But it is perhaps the label <term>complex play</term> that may summarise best the composition
					process and the practical aspects of performance for this text, since Little emphasises the complexity of the
					foliation system, the play’s structure, its title, the naming of characters, the number of voices, the calculations
					of May’s pacing, the width of the strip, subplots, and instrumentation. Little shows that <title rend="italic"
						>Footfalls</title> kept evolving significantly even post-publication, and he kindly points the reader toward the
						<q>Compare Sentences</q> tool on the BDMP, to trace the changes in the texts and navigate the complexity
					of the creation process. This function enables the user to track variants across the composition process and in the
					various editions of the text, and in this case, it can be used not for the sole purpose of genetic criticism, but
					also for practitioners to understand how both pacing and voicing operate, especially since the stage directions
					related to pacing are more specific in the French text, being enriched by Beckett’s experience of directing the
					play.</p>
				<p>While the play’s filiation with others of Beckett is highlighted through themes, Little rather suggests to view
						<title rend="italic">Footfalls</title> as a <quote rend="inline">textual orphan</quote> by comparison with W. B.
					Yeats’ <title rend="italic">At the Hawk’s Well</title>
					<ptr target="#little2021" loc="401"/>. The scholar argues that the former explores the ungraspable nature of
					theatre, a vision also traceable in the latter, the illusive dramaturgy of <title rend="italic">Footfalls</title>
					then setting the play in sharp contrast with the clear tableaux of <title rend="italic">Not I</title> and <title
						rend="italic">Footfalls</title>. Instead of reassessing Beckett’s conflicted relationship to Yeats’ theatre,
					Little sticks to the compositional process: he uses this intertextual instance as a means to dig further into
					Beckett’s own understanding of the mechanics of writing and the role of memory in the composition and translation
					processes, which is further investigated in the section <title rend="quotes">The Genesis of Pas</title> with the
					analysis of <word xml:lang="fr">Fatalement</word> (a replacement for <word xml:lang="fr">Inévitablement</word>), as
					a potential reference to Beckett’s interest in Atropos. Such focus is an opportunity to articulate how the play
					intrinsically queries the relationship between textuality and performance, but Little also pays attention to the
					deeply collaborative nature of the creation of this play; his narrative and analysis of Beckett and Billie Whitelaw
					working through posture and pacing in a Parisian restaurant is one of the highlights of the book. Additionally,
					through the study of the initial stage direction, Little demonstrates that the composition of the play was driven
					by pacing, Beckett presenting text as only secondary. But as far as text is concerned, one of the main achievements
					of Little’s analysis of Beckett’s compositional process is to go beyond <q>vaguening</q> or <q>undoing</q> alone by
					suggesting that it is only possible to achieve a <q>vaguened</q> stage image with precise stage directions, and
					Little introduces other compositional practices, such as correction as improvisation, the presence of textual scars
					or weakening. Such strategies, Little contends, exemplify how Beckett’s creation process had evolved towards an
					approach that is both text-oriented and stage-oriented. So what steps, after all, is Beckett asking his audiences
					to take with this play? </p>
				<p>As Little demonstrates, the spectator is again thrown into the pit of the subject-object breakdown, but this time
					through revolving. Indeed, the intertextuality with Yeats’ play is also a locus for the breakdown: Little
					identifies that, while Beckett was working on <title rend="italic">Footfalls</title>, he also attempted to write
					the prose piece <title rend="quotes">Long Observation of the Ray,</title> in which Beckett referenced the eye and
					mind of <title rend="italic">The Hawk’s Well</title> and explored the themes of self-observation and
					self-perception without a subject. In <title rend="italic">Footfalls</title>, however, it is the clear separation
					between subjects that is at stake, whether it is at the plot or linguistic level. Furthermore, Little shows that
					Beckett edited woman’s voice’s (V) text to augment the seemingly endless revolution of May’s thoughts without
					locating them in the mind, as it is the case in <title rend="italic">Not I</title>. And in so doing, Beckett
					extended May’s mind to her environment, hence challenging the subject-world divide. In translation, Beckett
					heightened the sense of breakdown with the polysemous French word <word xml:lang="fr">pas</word> as the title for
					the piece. <word xml:lang="fr">Pas</word> operates both as the signifier for steps and the marker of negation in
					French grammar. As a result, it negates subjectivity, and as Little demonstrates, it enhances the breakdown of the
					subject onstage, while presenting Beckett’s oeuvre as <quote rend="inline">work in regress</quote> [Beckett, quoted
					in <ref target="#little2021" loc="462">Little 2021</ref>, 462]. That entropic movement is reinforced by what Little
					identifies as the weakening of dialogues and stage directions, which, he argues, intensifies the breakdown of the
					character’s subjectivity. In short, Little’s genetic criticism of <title rend="italic">Footfalls</title> reveals
					how the breakdown had become inherent to Beckett’s experimental theatre, not only as an exploration of changing
					modes of subjectivity and new cognitive paradigms, but also – and even more fundamentally – as a performance
					practice and ethics, challenging the role (and place) of spectators.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>After <title rend="italic">The Making of Samuel Beckett’s Not I / Pas moi, That Time / Cette Fois and Footfalls
						/ Pas</title></head>
				<p>Through Little’s thorough descriptions and analyses of the archival artefacts that bear witness to the genesis of
						<title rend="italic">Not I / Pas moi</title>, <title rend="italic">That Time / Cette fois</title> and <title
						rend="italic">Footfalls</title> / <title rend="italic">Pas</title> and the digital access to the facsimiles,
					reader-users are offered a privileged vantage point on Beckett’s creative, revision, translation, and publication
					processes over the span of a dozen years. Little’s book represents a significant addition to the branches of
					Beckett studies looking at the mind and cognitive processes on their own and in/for performance, but it also
					operates as a fast track to research the digitised facsimile of those three plays on the BDMP. For optimal study,
					it is preferable to have access to both the book and the BDMP; however, the book also functions as a stand-alone
					piece, and it contains numerous visuals of the archival documents, which provide readers with useful insights into
					the manuscripts. Beyond the field, it is a key publication for interdisciplinary research that puts performance and
					epistemology in dialogue, and it will also be of interest to theatre historians of modernism. The spotlight that it
					directs at this set of plays calls for new performances of those demanding pieces and provides invaluable tools to
					reimagine those plays in twenty-first century ecosystems. The final product of this hybrid research therefore
					invites more academic and creative work on the same material, as the author clearly states in the introduction. The
					editors also acknowledge that manuscript edition is an open process, and readers are invited to propose alternative
					transcriptions by using the <q>Your Comments</q> function on the BDMP’s website: digitally-assisted dialogue goes
					on. All in all, Little’s monograph is yet another proof of the ground-breaking affordances of genetic criticism and
					digital humanities combined at the service of other disciplines and practices. </p>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<listBibl>
				<bibl xml:id="beckett2006" label="Beckett 2006">Beckett, S. (2006) <title rend="quotes">Cascando</title> in <title
						rend="italic">The Complete Dramatic Works</title>. London: Faber and Faber.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="beckett2012" label="Beckett 2012">Beckett, S. (2012) <title rend="italic">How It Is</title>. London:
					Faber and Farber. Ebook.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="beckett2022" label="Beckett 2022">Beckett, S. (2022) <title rend="italic">Not I / Pas moi, That Time /
						Cette fois and Footfalls / Pas: a genetic edition</title> (Series <title rend="quotes">The Beckett Digital
						Manuscript Project</title>, module 10). Edited by James Little and Vincent Neyt. Brussels: University Press
					Antwerp. Available at: <ref target="http://www.beckettarchive.org">http://www.beckettarchive.org</ref>
				</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="little2021" label="Little 2021">Little, J. (2021) <title rend="italic">The Making of Samuel Beckett’s
						Not I / Pas moi, That Time / Cette Fois and Footfalls / Pas</title>. Antwerp and London: University Press Antwerp
					and Bloomsbury.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="vanhulle2015" label="Van Hulle 2015">Van Hulle, D. (2015) <title rend="italic">The Making of Samuel
						Beckett’s Krapp’s Last Tape / La Dernière Bande</title>. Antwerp and London: University Press Antwerp and
					Bloomsbury.</bibl>
			</listBibl>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
