<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Organic and Locally Sourced: Growing a Digital
               Humanities Lab with an Eye Towards Sustainability</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Rebekah <dhq:family>Cummings</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Utah</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>rebekah.cummings@utah.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Rebekah Cummings is the Digital Matters Librarian at the University of Utah J.
                     Willard Marriott Library. Prior to her work as a digital humanities and data
                     management librarian at the Marriott Library, Rebekah was the Assistant
                     Director of the Mountain West Digital Library, one of the inaugural service
                     hubs for the Digital Public Library of America. She holds an MLIS from the
                     University of California, Los Angeles with a specialization in data
                     curation.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>David S. <dhq:family>Roh</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Utah</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>david.roh@utah.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>David S. Roh is Associate Professor of English and Director of the Digital
                     Matters Lab at the University of Utah, where he specializes in Digital
                     Humanities and Asian American literature. He is the author of <title
                        rend="italic">Illegal Literature</title> (University of Minnesota Press),
                     and coeditor of <title rend="italic">Techno-Orientalism</title> (Rutgers
                     University Press). His current book project, <title rend="italic">Mediating
                        Empire</title>, is under advance contract with Stanford University Press.
                     His work has appeared in <title rend="italic">Law &amp; Literature, Journal of
                        Narrative Theory</title>, <title rend="italic">MELUS</title>, and <title
                        rend="italic">Verge</title>.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Elizabeth <dhq:family>Callaway</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Utah</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>elizabeth.callaway@utah.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Elizabeth Callaway is an assistant professor in the Department of English at
                     the University of Utah and affiliated faculty with the Environmental Humanities
                     Graduate Program. She has published articles on biodiversity, climate change,
                     and the speculative ecosystems of science fiction. Her current book project,
                     titled <title rend="italic">Eden’s Endemics: Narratives of Biodiversity on
                        Earth and Beyond</title>, is forthcoming at University of Virginia
                     Press.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000470</idno>
            <idno type="volume">014</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2020-09-25">25 September 2020</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2020-06-06" who="jmurel">began and finished encoding</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>In 2016, the Digital Matters Lab at the University of Utah launched a temporary
                  <q>pop-up</q> space in the Marriott Library, the culmination of eighteen months of
               discussions between the College of Humanities, the College of Fine Arts, the College
               of Architecture+Planning, and the Marriott Library. After a previously unsuccessful
               attempt at creating a digital scholarship center in the late 2000s, our second
               attempt was rooted in skepticism. Why would this version be any more successful than
               the last? This paper chronicles how, learning from our mistakes, the Digital Matters
               Lab negotiated between a loose community of scholars and administrative stakeholders
               to navigate complex institutional legacies and bear a formal center with a
               cross-campus partnership, mission, and identity. The Lab’s focus on environmental,
               financial, and technological sustainability emerged in response to the situated
               environment of Utah where water rights, public lands, and air quality are critical
               concerns. As a second iteration digital humanities/scholarship center, the Digital
               Matters Lab’s emphasis on sustainability also reflects awareness of its vulnerability
               to the vicissitudes of administrative temperament or shifts in budgetary priorities.
               This case study concludes by looking to the future of the Digital Matters Lab in
               terms of scalability and permanence.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>This article presents the case study of the Digital Matters Lab at the University of
               Utah as an example of the creation of a digital scholarship center.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction: First Tracks, Again</head>
            <p>In the fall of 2016, the University of Utah launched the Digital Matters Lab<note>In
                  2019 the Digital Matters Advisory Board dropped the word <quote rend="inline"
                     >Lab</quote> from our official title, making the Digital Matters Lab simply
                     <title rend="quotes">Digital Matters.</title> The rationale behind this
                  decision was that Digital Matters had evolved beyond a space into a community, set
                  of services, and opportunities like the Digital Matters Fellowship Program and
                  Digital Matters Speaker and Workshop Series.</note> within a temporary
                  <q>pop-up</q> space in the Marriott Library. However tenuous, it was nevertheless
               the culmination of eighteen months of meetings and policy writing sessions, and
               represented the first step toward future plans to build a permanent home — a 3,000
               square foot lab complete with virtual reality studio, 3D printing, collaborative
               workspace, and classrooms. But the ghost of failure haunted these conversations, for
               this was the University of Utah’s second attempt to build a Digital Humanities (or,
               depending on discipline, Digital Scholarship) lab. Reminders of efforts past emerged
               in unexpected ways throughout the process. For example, the Digital Matters
               exploratory working group discovered early on that we had a predecessor. A small
               group of librarians had led a similar group several years before, yet we had no
               record or knowledge of their efforts, accomplishments, and missteps. The challenge
               was two-fold: how could we track down the lessons learned from our first attempt if
               little institutional memory remained, and how could we persuade hesitant stakeholders
               that a second attempt would be worthwhile?</p>
            <p>This paper outlines the process through which we formed the Digital Matters Lab at
               the University of Utah in the face of the aforementioned challenges, and the factors
               that contributed to its launch. First, we recognized that the compulsion to bridge
               the humanities and arts with technology and computing was, is, and always will be,
               present on campus, albeit in unfocused and disparate forms. Regardless of whether the
               university pursued a DH initiative or not, these efforts would persist; and by
               dedicating a space, funds, and personnel to the Digital Matters Lab, the university
               would coalesce these efforts under a singular identity and focus. Second, due to a
               confluence of elements that we later describe in detail, several colleges — led by
               the Marriott Library — came together to agree to a cost-sharing scheme mitigating
               risk and easing financial burden. And third, Digital Matters staff agreed that the
               lab’s focus and mission would be grounded in critical scholarship and engage locally
               with projects of significance to Utah and the broader Mountain West region. Building
               on that mission, we adopted a four year theme of <q>sustainability,</q> which allowed
               us to think through concerns about digital humanities itself while also casting an
               eye toward our specific environmental challenges in Utah. Most importantly, we
               embraced the legacy of failure and adopted a skeptical framework to guide our
               approach. That is, we recognized ongoing campus DH research and avoided hyperbolic
               promises of the <q>new,</q> eagerly collaborated both within and outside of the four
               partner colleges, and constantly refined the DML's identity and mission to reflect
               local interests and character.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Digital Humanities in Libraries: Three Subgenres</head>
            <p>Creating a library-based digital humanities center is a now well-worn path of both
               success and struggle (<title rend="quotes">Registry of DH sites with library
                  participation</title>, 2018). Though several early digital humanities centers
               started in English departments, in recent decades there has been a migration to
               library-based models that range from a <quote rend="inline">virtual suite of
                  services</quote> to full-fledged digital humanities centers <ptr
                  target="#anne2017"/>
               <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2010"/>
               <ptr target="#zhang2015"/>.</p>
            <p>There are distinct advantages in placing DH centers in libraries. Libraries provide
               an inherently interdisciplinary space where faculty from across campus feel
               comfortable taking advantage of technology and services. Libraries have high-traffic
               physical spaces, technical infrastructure (server space, software, collections), and
               human expertise (metadata, copyright, data management, digital preservation, project
               management) that are potentially beneficial to digital humanities efforts. Many
               high-profile digital scholarship and digital humanities efforts are based in
               libraries such as HathiTrust at the University of Michigan Library, the Women Writers
               Project at Northeastern University Library, Chronicling America at the Library of
               Congress, and countless digital archives. Moreover, as libraries evolve from sites of
               knowledge circulation to knowledge production, an intimate relationship with a DH
               center is strategically and mutually beneficial <ptr target="#vandegrift2013"/>.</p>
            <p>Despite a natural fit, in practice the majority of libraries tend to offer DH
               services in an ad hoc manner with many libraries struggling to find an optimal
               approach for DH engagement <ptr target="#schaffner2014"/>. Digital humanities in a
               library might be subsumed under a broader category of digital scholarship, digital
               publishing, digital library, or data management. Often there is a single librarian
               responsible for supporting or leading digital humanities efforts in addition to their
               core job duties. </p>
            <p>These issues are well-documented in a growing body of <q>DH+Lib</q> literature, which
               we see as consisting of three subgenres. The first chronicles strategies for building
               a DS/DH center or lab in resource-challenged environments. A. Miller, in <title
                  rend="quotes">DH Start-Ups: A Library Model for Advancing Scholarship through
                  Collaboration</title>, details how Middle Tennessee State University's library was
               able to establish its Digital Scholarship lab in its library by forming strategic
               partnerships, co-opting faculty lines, and narrowing its mission and scope <ptr
                  target="#miller2016"/>. Articles such as these are useful for visualizing the
               processes and steps required to formulate a digital humanities lab, particularly
               during financially challenged times. The various case studies in this corpus often
               focus on one or two main areas of strengths that bred success such as campus
               collaboration <ptr target="#bayer2014"/>
               <ptr target="#gerber2017"/>
               <ptr target="#miller2016"/>
               <ptr target="#rosenblum2016"/>, community engagement <ptr target="#sweeney2017"/>,
               innovation <ptr target="#nowviskie2013"/>, or evidence-based service design <ptr
                  target="#lindquist2016"/>.</p>
            <p>A second genre of DH and library literature focuses on paradigmatic digital
               humanities projects produced either solely from libraries or as the result of
               library/campus partnerships. For example, in their book chapter, <title rend="quotes"
                  >Digital Public History in the Library</title>, Battle, Mobley, and Gilbert
               chronicle their workflow and editorial process in curating the Lowcountry Digital
               History Initiative at the College of Charleston <ptr target="#battle2016"/>. Our own
               contribution to the genre, <quote rend="inline">Kindles, card catalogs, and the
                  future of libraries: a collaborative digital humanities project</quote> highlights
               a topic modeling project initiated by two librarians, Anna Neatrour and Rebekah
               Cummings, and a digital humanities researcher, Dr. Elizabeth Callaway, at the
               University of Utah <ptr target="#neatrour2018"/>. These contributions to the digital
               humanities and libraries corpus model a useful roadmap for other librarians to
               undertake similar projects. </p>
            <p>A third and final subgenre of DH+Lib articles focuses on the broader role that
               libraries can and should play in advancing and supporting digital humanities. The
               tone of these articles generally range from cautiously optimistic to openly skeptical
               regarding the investment that libraries make in digital humanities infrastructure. In
                  <title rend="quotes">Evolving in Common: Creating Mutually Supportive
                  Relationships Between Libraries and the Digital Humanities</title>, Vandegrift and
               Varner focus on the strengths that libraries bring to DH and see academic librarians
               as valuable intellectual partners <ptr target="#vandegrift2013"/>. Schaffer and
               Erway, on the other hand, believe that only rarely should an academic library invest
               in a robust DH center and that, for most libraries, lower levels of support are a
               better use of resources <ptr target="#schaffner2014"/>. Other articles advocate
               caution and list items for consideration when investing in digital humanities <ptr
                  target="#kamada2010"/>
               <ptr target="#millson-martula2017"/>.</p>
            <p>The aforementioned subgenres are not exhaustive nor are they mutually exclusive.
               Nearly every <q>Building a DH Center</q> paper highlights a successful project and
               reflects, at least implicitly, on the role libraries should play in digital
               humanities. Moreover, these articles frequently rely upon the experiences of the
               author in building a DH center or engaging in digital scholarship projects.</p>
            <p>While this article fits squarely in the <q>Building a DH Center</q> genre, our aim is
               to do more than simply summarize our experience. Rather, by reflecting on our history
               and process, we identify the local, structural, and cultural factors shaping the
               Digital Matters Lab as well as generalizable lessons for building and sustaining a
               digital humanities center. For example, sustained engagement with digital humanities
               literature through biweekly reading groups informed our early decisions in setting a
               course for the Digital Matters Lab and helped us think critically about how our
               burgeoning lab fit into the larger ecosystem of DH Centers.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Boom and Bust: The History of DH Centers at the University of Utah
               (2007-2018)</head>
            <p>As mentioned above, the Digital Matters working group quickly discovered that
               disparate digital humanities/scholarship efforts had been underway at the University
               of Utah for nearly a decade. In 2007, a technology instruction librarian at the
               Marriott Library returned from the Digital Scholarship/Digital Libraries Symposium at
               Emory University inspired to pursue a DH build. Fortuitously, her exposure to Digital
               Humanities coincided with a renovation at the Marriott Library that included a
               planned Advanced Technology Studio. Under her leadership, the multimedia center
               expanded to include Digital Humanities services, including qualitative data and
               textual analysis, GIS services, an AV Studio, and data management services, resulting
               in the Digital Scholarship Lab (DSL) in September 2009. By 2010, the Digital
               Scholarship Lab had hired a GIS specialist, reassigned three existing staff members
               to DSL, led a variety of software workshops, and hosted a Digital Scholarship Fair to
               highlight their burgeoning DH services.</p>
            <p>The Digital Scholarship Lab failed. Despite early administrative buy-in, staff
               enthusiasm, and limited technological support, it was never able to summon a critical
               mass of engagement with campus partners. Post-recession funding required library
               administration to shift its focus to sustaining core library services, and campus
               assessments revealed a lack of interest and understanding of digital scholarship
               services. After seven years of struggle, it was subsumed by another department and
               the Digital Scholarship Lab was officially disbanded in 2014, while individual
               services such as GIS, data management, and the A/V Studio were spun off — and now
               thrive — in other areas, such as the Marriott Library’s Creativity and Innovation
               Services department.</p>
            <p>In many ways, the librarians at the Marriott Library were simply ahead of the curve;
               a robust digital scholarship community did not yet exist at the University of Utah.
               The Digital Scholarship Lab functioned in isolation of the rest of the campus, and
               efforts to offer services or engage in collaborative research fell short without
               resources for faculty incentives and/or established buy-in from administrators.
               Awareness of digital humanities had not yet reached the necessary inflection point
               for other departments to seek opportunities in the field. That is not to say that the
               DSL would have succeeded if it had simply appeared several years later, but the
               addiitonal burden of defining DH for stakeholders while the Digital Scholarship Lab
               was in its infancy compounded its difficulties. Finally, founding and housing the
               Digital Scholarship Lab in the library, for better or worse, brought to bear
               service-oriented associations that did not necessarily speak to more
               research-oriented faculty. </p>
            <p>Ironically, just as library administration shuttered the doors on the Digital
               Scholarship Lab, elsewhere on campus, digital humanities was starting to gain
               traction. Leveraging a block of funding for strategic hires in digital humanities,
               the English Department brought on two scholars in 2015 and 2016, Dr. David Roh and
               Dr. Lisa Swanstrom, with a mandate to build a DH community and space. Moreover, three
               colleges at the University of Utah — College of Humanities, College of Fine Arts, and
               College of Architecture+Planning — independently reached out to the Marriott Library
               in 2015 to gauge interest in developing a shared digital scholarship space. Still
               mindful of the Digital Scholarship Lab’s isolation and failed attempts at engagement,
               early discussions overcorrected slightly — initial talks comprised of more than
               thirty representatives from all four partner colleges! After nearly a decade,
               administrative will, faculty research interests, and library support regarding
               digital humanities had finally converged. </p>
            <p>The Digital Matters working group met from fall 2015 to spring 2017 and later
               transitioned to a more nimble steering committee, consisting of six representatives
               from all partner colleges, that assumed leadership and kept the deans apprised of its
               efforts. By 2015, <q>digital humanities</q> had become a common buzzword in academic
               libraries, and we strove to learn from the experiences of other libraries who had
               successfully built digital humanities programs. The first phase of information
               gathering included a series of interviews with Digital Humanities researchers Dan
               Cohen (Center for New Media and History, DPLA), Miriam Posner (UCLA Center for
               Digital Humanities), Bethany Nowviskie (University of Virginia Scholars’ Lab), and
               John Unsworth (Brandeis University). A few notable themes emerged from these
               interviews: <list type="ordered">
                  <item>A lab is a community. A strong community will be reflected in an active,
                     vibrant space. To do so, the lab should be a democratic environment empowering
                     students and staff. Moreover, staffing and expertise should take precedence
                     over technology and decor.</item>
                  <item>Strong relationships with a supportive administration are necessary. Not
                     only does administrative financial backing alleviate the need to rely on grant
                     funding, but the importance of political capital should not be
                     overlooked.</item>
                  <item>The mission should be driven by local needs. Some centers build tools, some
                     support faculty, others digitize content, and still others emphasize teaching.
                     Rather than trying to do everything in an unfocused manner, strategize, and be
                     selective. A narrow and focused mission should guide priorities.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>We worked in stages. The first stage would be establishing a physical presence on
               campus so that we could begin to build a community. In fall 2016, the Digital Matters
               Lab <q>Pop-Up</q> Space moved into the Marriott Library with a launch party. The
               space was light on technology but was equipped with collaborative spaces,
               whiteboards, and a few desktop workstations. More than offering computing power and
               expensive equipment, the temporary space became a hub where we could start building
               relationships by hosting talks, workshops, reading groups, and a monthly research
               interest group.</p>
            <p>The second stage was to secure funding. Thanks to a mix of serendipity and
               infrastructure, in May 2016 the Marriott Library Development team secured $1 Million
               from an anonymous donor for staffing, equipment, and buildout of the Digital Matters
               Lab. Heeding the advice we had received in our exploratory phase, we elected to use
               the money to secure five years of staffing and modest equipment while we continue to
               raise money for the permanent space. The steering committee had to then discuss
               several questions regarding personnel: what constitutes core staff for a digital
               humanities space? Should they conduct a national search or hire from within? Is there
               an immediate need for a developer? The committee considered the merits hiring various
               configurations of Director, Librarian, Programmer/Developer, Operations Manager,
               graduate students, visiting fellows, grant writer, and post-docs. The finalized
               structure was determined by a consideration of the objectives and goals for the next
               five years — sustainability, a regional identity, and campus integration. Ultimately,
               the steering committee decided that the first hire would be the Digital Matters
               Director who would set a vision for the Lab including its long-term sustainability.
               The Marriott Library created a faculty line to hire a dedicated Digital Matters
               Librarian who would be responsible for supporting projects, organizing speakers,
               workshops, and various training opportunities, and liaising with relevant and
               existing library services such metadata, copyright, and IT services. Our five-year
               budget also included significant resources set aside to fund semester-long faculty
               and graduate student fellowships and to eventually hire a program assistant to staff
               the front desk, maintain the website, and assist the Director and Librarian in the
               operations and events of the Lab. </p>
            <p>As of this writing, we are in the third and current stage — implementation. Over
               several months in 2017, the steering committee undertook the unglamorous work of
               hiring a director and librarian, procuring equipment, furniture, and a semi-permanent
               facility. Later, as the Digital Matters Lab became more of a known quantity, chance
               opportunities led to the hiring of an additional post-doctoral scholar from
               Environmental Humanities and faculty fellow from Multi-Disciplinary Design. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Local Color: Strategizing Around Projects (2018-present)</head>
            <p>The Digital Matters Lab mission is to be the locus for digital humanities research on
               campus and to build a national reputation for our center, through integrating digital
               scholarship with cultural criticism and theory while remaining grounded in our local
               surroundings in Utah. We sought to penetrate the campus’s consciousness by adding
               value, with the eventual goal of reaching financial and reputational stability so
               that the Digital Matters Lab can withstand budgetary vagaries.</p>
            <p>We began the process by embarking on a fact-finding mission to learn the respective
               priorities and character of our partner departments and schools. We met regularly to
               develop relationships and, at times, define <q>digital scholarship</q> and <q>digital
                  humanities</q> in relation to their fields. It was also imperative to carefully
               consider university legacies and strengths; for example, the University of Utah is
               renowned for its Entertainment Arts and Engineering (EAE)<note><ref
                     target="https://games.utah.edu/">https://games.utah.edu/</ref></note> program
               where students learn the fundamentals of video game development and animation.
               Accordingly, it would make sense for the Digital Matters Lab to incorporate game
               studies into its programming and projects. Similarly, the Marriott Library has an
               unparalleled Book Arts Program,<note><ref
                     target="https://lib.utah.edu/collections/book-arts/"
                     >https://lib.utah.edu/collections/book-arts/</ref></note> which focuses on the
               materiality and affordances of a print media; a strategic alignment of goals,
               including hosting credit-bearing classes and collaborative exhibitions, would be
               mutually beneficial.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, it behooved us to learn of the individual researchers and centers on
               campus that have created digital scholarship and public-facing research projects. For
               example, since the 1960s, the American West Center<note><ref
                     target="https://awc.utah.edu/">https://awc.utah.edu/</ref></note> has collected
               and digitized oral histories of western peoples and lands. Faculty members in English
               and Computer Science had developed software for poetic visualization,
                     Poemage.<note><ref target="http://www.sci.utah.edu/~nmccurdy/Poemage/"
                     >http://www.sci.utah.edu/~nmccurdy/Poemage/</ref></note> Professors of dance
               worked in virtual reality environments, capturing choreography with drones. Over in
               the School of Music, a faculty member collaborated with metadata specialists in the
               library to create an opera database, SongHelix,<note><ref
                     target="http://www.songhelix.com/">http://www.songhelix.com/</ref></note> to
               promote discoverability of songs by a litany of criteria for recitals. When planning
               for the first year, it benefited us to meet with faculty to think through how to best
               serve, connect, and promote the existing research going on at the University of
               Utah.</p>
            <p>To underscore the critical component and local environmental concerns of our mission,
               we selected a theme, <term>sustainability</term> as an organizing principle for the
               first four years. The theme helped us develop a narrative that would lend
               cohesiveness to our fledgling center and would also be legible to administration,
               donors, and other stakeholders. Forming connections and figuring out our place in the
               university and the broader digital community went hand-in-hand with building an
               identity as a lab that pushed the frontiers of critically-engaged digital research.
               We strategically chose projects, workshops, and speakers that integrated cultural
               criticism into their visions of digital arts and humanities. Sustainability not only
               prompts us to think of the durability of digital projects, but also asks us to think
               differently about the timescales on which we usually consider technology; instead of
               thinking in processing times and milliseconds, sustainability might prompt us to
               consider the millennia that our e-waste takes to degrade. Sustainability also
               challenges us to turn a critical eye toward our own methods, practices, and
               assumptions as digital humanities practitioners. We have to ask: what does digital
               humanities itself sustain? And how can we build a lab that is conscientious about
               what it seeks to sustain and what it chooses not to? Ultimately, the idea of
                  <term>sustainability</term> challenged us not only to think thematically around
               environmental issues, but structurally as we considered the long-term viability of
               our projects in terms of preservation, documentation, and formats.</p>
            <p>Finally, the theme of sustainability foregrounds our situatedness in Utah. At the
               same time that Utah has been the location of important events in the history of
               trans-continental communication technology systems (the golden spike, the golden
               splice, and fourth node of Arpanet), it has also become a testing ground for our
               environmental futures. Often these technological advances go hand-in-hand with rising
               environmental concerns. Utah has been the location of many commercial data centers
               such as those for Twitter, eBay, and Oracle <ptr target="#hu2015" loc="78"/>. But
               while commercial data centers benefit from cheap water, that does not reflect its
               scarcity in a drought-prone state. At the same time that Utah is the site for
               vanguard technology development, it sits at the forefront of debates about public
               lands, climate change, and air quality. Our situatedness puts us into a political,
               environmental, technological history rife with the intersection of technological and
               environmental concerns. The Digital Matters logo, a simplified topographic
               representation of the Great Salt Lake, whose water levels are steadily declining, not
               only reflects local geography but recognizes an arid future (see Figure 1).</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Digital Matters branding with the Great Salt Lake topography</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The lab continues to build a repertoire of critical digital research while building
               bridges to other entities across campus and engaging with technological issues and
               the environment. The work of the lab falls into the standard categories of research,
               instruction, and support. Rather than give a detailed description of each project, we
               present a broader, birds-eye view of the work that may be organizationally useful for
               understanding how to build a DH centers or program. </p>
            <div>
               <head>Research</head>
               <p>As all members of the staff joined Digital Matters with their own ongoing research
                  projects, we were committed to maintaining time for them. For example, Rebekah
                  Cummings arrived with an active portfolio in data management and metadata studies;
                  David Roh and Elizabeth Callaway, trained in English, had their respective ongoing
                  monographs, in addition to their own experimental DH projects. Fortunately, around
                  the same time the Marriott Library started emphasizing research among the
                  tenure-track librarians, so our pursuing individual research agendas aligned with
                  the library’s strategic shift. There was no requirement for research to tie
                  directly with Digital Matters, but the hope was that as our interests evolved in
                  the lab environment, a natural convergence would occur. Moreover, rather than have
                  a set percentage of time devoted to self-directed research projects, a focus on
                  research naturally unfolded as part of the culture. For instance, at the beginning
                  of each semester, we met to outline our goals, which not only included our
                  commitments to Digital Matters, but our own research objectives. We could then
                  discuss time commitments, scheduling, and workloads as book projects and articles
                  went underwent various phases of production. Encouraging transparency not only
                  allowed us to make room for each member, but also provided a welcome source
                  accountability.</p>
               <p>In addition to continuing to pursue our research agendas, we sought to engage with
                  two types of research projects — a collaborative, multi-institutional research
                  project of local significance, and funding faculty and graduate student projects
                  across the four partner colleges of the College of Humanities, College of Fine
                  Arts, College of Architecture+Planning, and the Marriott Library, guided by the
                  broader contours of our theme, sustainability. After a few false starts, we
                  collaborated with a local nonprofit, Better Days 2020,<note><ref
                        target="https://www.betterdays2020.com/"
                        >https://www.betterdays2020.com/</ref></note> and colleagues at Brigham
                  Young University’s Office of Digital Humanities to build an Omeka exhibit to
                  highlight the 150th anniversary of women’s suffrage in Utah, centered on the
                  digitizing, tagging, and analysis of the <title rend="italic">Woman’s
                     Exponent</title>, a nineteenth century Mormon feminist publication printed in
                  Salt Lake City. While Utah is quick to claim its place in history as the first
                  state in which women cast a ballot, there is more complex, nuanced story involving
                  intersections of suffrage, polygamy, and statehood. Still in the early stages,
                  this project aims to produce new knowledge and speak to the wider community in
                  Salt Lake City and Utah.</p>
               <p>In terms of funding research projects, we offer two graduate residency fellowships
                  and four faculty fellowships each year. This not only supports projects that
                  otherwise might not get off the ground but also legitimizes digital scholarship
                  across campus. In the first year offering these fellowships, our independent
                  advisory board selected projects that engage in some way with our four-year theme
                  of sustainability and with concerns important to Utah. Both of the Spring 2019
                  graduate fellows worked on digital/material art projects focusing on the
                  environment in the west. One graduate fellow, Tiana Birrell, used her time in the
                  Lab to map the extensive network of data centers, including the National Security
                  Administration (NSA), in Utah and the complicated network of rivers, dams, and
                  pipes that contribute to the cooling of those servers. A product of her research
                  is an art installation in the Lab comprised of video projection and sculptural
                  elements that convey the materiality and physicality of Utah’s network of rivers,
                  water, and data. A goal of her project — and the public art that accompanies it —
                  is to prompt discussion of local environmental concerns by highlighting the
                  significant allocation of public resources to these data centers, whose companies
                  select Utah expressly for its <q>cheap</q> water and electricity, low seismic
                  activity, few natural disasters, and access to an international airport. Our
                  second inaugural graduate student fellow, Jace Brittain, explored the tension
                  between human and animal agency through a literary aesthetic, focusing on the
                  epidemic of bark beetles and forest decimation in Utah. By using a combination of
                  3D scans, prints, poetry and prose, this work speculatively makes legible the
                  inscrutable patterns bark beetles create in boring through tree surfaces. Using
                  digital art as a commentary on nature, global warming, and agency granted
                  immediacy to this phenomenon, which has a tremendous effect on Utah’s ecosystems
                  yet often feels abstracted from daily life. </p>
               <p>Our faculty fellows’ projects similarly engage with local interests, in this case,
                  discourses of ownership of public and private bodies, and the relationship between
                  technology and indigeneity. Faculty fellow, Dr. Wendy Wisher, developed a piece
                  exploring the resonances between attitudes and policies toward public lands and
                  women's reproductive rights in Utah to propose a relationship between the two.
                  Another faculty fellow, Dr. Lourdes Alberto, created a digital archive of
                  documents generated by social activism in diasporic indigenous communities. While
                  not solely selected for their environmental/sustainability focus, these projects
                  reflect the range of interests expressed in our applicant pool of faculty and
                  students and speak to the interests of the broader Utah population.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Instruction</head>
               <p>Instruction ranges from workshops on tools, skills, and best-practices for faculty
                  to semester-length courses for undergraduates. Our workshop series not only trains
                  scholars in digital humanities tools and methods, but serves as an opportunity to
                  strengthen our mission of being the locus for digital research on campus. Topics
                  are decided by the community by way of surveys and polls during the planning
                  process, and connecting with experts to lead workshops helps develop
                  relationships. Workshops focus not only on tools, but methods and competencies;
                  sessions on Tableau, Gephi, and Omeka might be interspersed with Data Management
                  for the Arts and Humanities or Storytelling with Data. Tool-based workshops are
                  possibly the most challenging activity during which to explicitly incorporate our
                  stated commitment to digital cultural studies and sustainability, but the choice
                  of sample datasets instructors choose to teach with often lead to critical
                  discussions about cultural assumptions and the implications of its affordances. We
                  have found that there are ways to build self-reflexivity into even the most
                  tool-centered aspects of our programming. </p>
               <p>These skill-based workshops are complemented by the digital humanities-related
                  undergraduate courses. The DML Director, Dr. David Roh, teaches digital humanities
                  in the Department of English, and there are plans for experimental, project-based
                  courses in the Honors College. Additionally, we are working with invested
                  departments and the upper administration to implement a digital humanities
                  certificate for undergraduates, which incorporates classes in media studies,
                  computer science, cultural studies, as well as modules offered by the Digital
                  Matters Lab. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Support</head>
               <p>In addition to supporting projects with funding, the DML also provides the space
                  and opportunities for serendipitous encounters among researchers from different
                  departments and disciplines beyond the partner colleges. A Research Interest Group
                  (RIG) is open to all and meets regularly for events ranging from a speakers series
                  to reading groups to works-in-progress presentations; topics covered may range
                  from as environmental art or long-term data curation. The RIG provides occasions
                  for regular encounters among scholars from a variety of backgrounds, which then
                  lead to the building of a community that may result in collaborations on a given
                  project. Informal interactions expand the circle of proficiencies that
                  participants can draw upon when exploring research questions. Ideally, support and
                  space results in the profile of the lab as an interdisciplinary nexus to span the
                  entire length of the institution.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Lessons Learned</head>
            <p>The Digital Matters Lab’s launch at the University of Utah is not intended as a
               blueprint for other organizations to follow. If anything, we have learned that our
               identity, mission, and services are the direct result of our unique environment,
               partners, and individuals associated with the center. That said, many of the lessons
               we have learned mirror those of other successful digital humanities centers. In this
               section we have attempted to parse what lessons are broadly applicable as opposed to
               the more localized solutions and experiences we have chronicled above. </p>
            <list type="unordered">
               <item>Academic Partnerships/Collaboration is key. Beyond spreading risk and pooling
                  resources, partnering with several academic partners within campus led to a sense
                  of shared ownership and institutional investment in the DML — in our case, the
                  College of Humanities, Fine Arts, Architecture+Planning, and the Marriott Library.
                  Moreover, by appointing a contact person for each college — as members of the
                  advisory board — we could ask them to represent the interests of their
                  constituents, as well as convey our programs, projects, and mission to them — a
                  bilateral relationship. This has the additional benefit of structurally
                  integrating the unique strengths and foci of the university, rather than the DML
                  venturing into areas that may not align with the strategic missions of its
                  partners. That is not to say that having several partnerships is not without risk;
                  the danger was that attempting to integrate conflicting interests could leave the
                  DML rudderless or desultory. To counter committee paralysis, leadership had to
                  take responsibility for a vision and direction while listening and integrating
                  comments, with the understanding that s/he will not be able to please
                  everyone.</item>
               <item>Lab identity should emerge organically in response to the environment. While we
                  polled and consulted with a number of more established DH institutions, we were
                  mindful of the fact that we would need to adapt our priorities and character to
                  our particular placement and character. For us, this meant leveraging the existing
                  strengths of our institution, such as game studies and history of the American
                  West. A focus on locality also led us to select projects that speak to concerns
                  such as water rights, public lands, air quality, and moments of local historical
                  significance such the 150th anniversary of women’s suffrage in Utah.</item>
               <item>Sustainability is important but we must also allow for an experimental culture
                  where people feel allowed to fail or let projects die. With a new venture, there
                  is an incentive to take a conservative approach; after all, we have the dual
                  pressures of demonstrating our value to administration and figuring out a means of
                  stretching finite resources. At the same time, much of the research may not bear
                  fruit, or be immediately legible — and we want to allow for a culture that
                  provides room for research that is innovative, experimental, and even risky.
                  Taking a page from other institutions, we grant latitude for individual
                  researchers and staff to work on their own projects, with no expectation for
                  success or outcome other than their own intellectual fulfillment.</item>
               <item>There is an inherent tension between what the administration and development
                  office want (e.g. glittery technology, such as a visualization wall) and what
                  researchers need (e.g. human capital, flexibility, funding).<note>David S. Roh
                     discusses this inherent tension in <title rend="quotes">The DH Bubble: Startup
                        Logic, Sustainability, Performativity</title>. <title rend="italic">Debates
                        in the Digital Humanities</title>, vol. 3. Eds. Gold, Matthew and Lauren
                     Klein. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press (2019): 86-91.</note> It has
                  also become clear that while administrative support may be enthusiastic, there is
                  a gap in priorities regarding their needs and the needs of the DML. For research
                  purposes, it may be that most of the high costs come in the form of human capital
                  — salaries for staff, researchers, and students to dedicate time for their
                  respective projects. At the same time, funding begets funding in the sense that
                  tangible and sleek technological apparatus may enchant and attract attention. We
                  have to think strategically in purchasing equipment that maximizes attention and
                  utility.</item>
               <item>A multi-pronged approach. Mindful as we are of the kind of argument we are
                  attempting to make with our campus presence over the next few years, we must
                  balance the logistics of building a tight enough portfolio to distribute our
                  limited bandwidth efficiently with the need to integrate ourselves into the
                  greater campus in a way that results in a net positive. To that end, the DML
                  facilitates workshops for undergraduate, graduate students, and faculty, consults
                  on external projects, in addition to its own internal research.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion: Sustainable Futures?</head>
            <p>Like many Digital Humanities centers, the future of the Digital Matters Lab is
               promising but uncertain, and we suspect that its fate will depend on whether we are
               able to make a convincing argument for its contributions on several fronts —
               institutionally, regionally, and nationally. With enough initial funding to last four
               years, the DML must make a compelling case with university administration and campus
               constituents for its continued existence. Our first year (2018-2019) focused on
               infrastructure — hiring staff, establishing identity, formalizing workflows, setting
               a research agenda, and creating visibility. With a small staff comprised of two
               faculty members and a post-doc, we juggled the responsibilities of research,
               teaching, and service with administrative tasks such as maintaining our website,
               planning events, and ordering promotional material.</p>
            <p>Our primary concern heading into the second year is sustainability and permanence. As
               we move out of the foundation-building phase, we begin to consider what projects,
               staff, relationships, and services will mark us as an indispensable campus resource.
               Chief in our minds are the lessons learned from previous iterations of digital
               scholarship centers and services on campus and nationwide. One of those lessons is
               that DML needs to avoid insularity and remain connected to digital scholarship
               efforts across campus and across Utah. DML faculty and staff will continue to provide
               learning and research opportunities to undergraduate students, graduate students, and
               faculty to build a portfolio of innovative projects that speak to local concerns and
               our theme of sustainability. Grant opportunities will be considered and pursued when
               they align with the goals of the Digital Matters Lab but will not be used to maintain
               core staff and services. </p>
            <p>The Digital Matters Lab benefits from administrative support, five years of secure
               funding, and established cross-campus partnerships, but the long-term future is far
               from secure. We strive to cultivate the right mix of digital scholarships services,
               research and funding opportunities, instructional programming, and an active DH
               community that will be compelling to donors and administrators. Ultimately, the
               creation of a stable Digital Matters Lab and a permanent funding line for its staff
               relies on our ability to establish the DML as an invaluable hub for computationally
               enhanced humanities research and pedagogy, and a necessary resource at the University
               of Utah. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="anne2017" label="Anne et al. 2017">Anne, K.M., Carlisle, T., Dombrowski,
               Q., Glass, E., Gniady, T., Jones, J., Lippencott, J., MacDermott, J., 2017. <title
                  rend="italic">Building Capacity for Digital Humanities: A Framework for
                  Institutional Planning</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="battle2016" label="Battle and Mobley 2016">Battle, M., Mobley, T., 2016.
                  <title rend="quotes">Digital Public History in the Library: Developing the
                  Lowcountry Digital History Initiative at the College of Charleston</title>, in:
               White, J.W., Gilbert, H. (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Laying the Foundation: Digital
                  Humanities in Academic Libraries</title>. Purdue University Press, pp. 35–58. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctt163t7kq"
                  >https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctt163t7kq</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bayer2014" label="Bayer 2014">Bayer, L., 2014. <title rend="quotes">You
                  Complete Me: On Building a Vertically Integrated Digital Humanities Program at the
                  University of Georgia</title>. <title rend="italic">Grain</title> 26. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.7771/2380-176X.6947"
                  >https://doi.org/10.7771/2380-176X.6947</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gerber2017" label="Gerber 2017">Gerber, K., 2017. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Conversation as a model to build the relationship among libraries, digital
                  humanities, and campus leadership</title>. <title rend="italic">College
                  Undergraduate Libraries</title>. 24, 418–433. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1080/10691316.2017.1328296"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/10691316.2017.1328296</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hu2015" label="Hu 2015">Hu, T.H., 2015. <title rend="italic">A Prehistory
                  of the Cloud</title>. The MIT Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kamada2010" label="Kamada 2010">Kamada, H., 2010. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Digital humanities: Roles for libraries? College and Research Libraries</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">News</title> 71, 484–485. h<ref
                  target="ttps://doi.org/10.5860/crln.71.9.8441"
                  >ttps://doi.org/10.5860/crln.71.9.8441</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2010" label="Kirschenbaum 2010">Kirschenbaum, M.G., 2010.
                  <title rend="quotes">What Is Digital humanities and What’s It Doing in English
                  Departments?</title>
               <title rend="italic">ADE Bull</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lindquist2016" label="Lindquist et al. 2016">Lindquist, T., Long, H.,
               Watkins, A., 2016. <title rend="quotes">Advancing Digital Humanities at CU-Boulder
                  through Evidence-Based Service Design</title>, in: White, J.W., Gilbert, H.
               (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Laying the Foundation: Digital Humanities in Academic
                  Libraries</title>. Purdue University Press, pp. 127–148. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctt163t7kq"
                  >https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctt163t7kq</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="miller2016" label="Miller 2016">Miller, A., 2016. <title rend="quotes"
                  >DS/DH Start-Ups: A Library Model for Advancing Scholarship through
                  Collaboration</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Web Librarianship</title>.
               10, 83–100. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/19322909.2016.1149544"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/19322909.2016.1149544</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="millson-martula2017" label="Millson-Martula and Gunn 2017"
               >Millson-Martula, C., Gunn, K., 2017. <title rend="quotes">The digital humanities:
                  Implications for librarians, libraries, and librarianship</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">College Undergraduate Libraries</title>. 24, 135–139. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1080/10691316.2017.1387011"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/10691316.2017.1387011</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="neatrour2018" label="Neatrour et al. 2018">Neatrour, A.L., Callaway, E.,
               Cummings, R., 2018. <title rend="quotes">Kindles, card catalogs, and the future of
                  libraries: a collaborative digital humanities project</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Digital Library Perspectives</title>. 34, 162–187. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1108/DLP-02-2018-0004"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1108/DLP-02-2018-0004</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nowviskie2013" label="Nowviskie 2013">Nowviskie, B., 2013. <title
                  rend="quotes">Skunks in the Library: A Path to Production for Scholarly R
                  &amp;D.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Library Administration</title>. 53, 53–66. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01930826.2013.756698"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/01930826.2013.756698</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="resitry2018" label="DH Registry 2018">Registry of DH sites with library
               participation, 2018. <ref
                  target="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/13hZlUCp3Zc5l7vAJyxfpcyIL8lnb4sZhtvW7MzQlHNo/edit?usp=embed_facebook&amp;usp=embed_facebook"
                  >https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/13hZlUCp3Zc5l7vAJyxfpcyIL8lnb4sZhtvW7MzQlHNo/edit?usp=embed_facebook&amp;usp=embed_facebook</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rosenblum2016" label="Rosenblum and Dwyer 2016">Rosenblum, B., Dwyer, A.,
               2016. <title rend="quotes">Copiloting a Digital Humanities Center: A Critical
                  Reflection on a Libraries and Academic Partnership</title>, in: White, J.W.,
               Gilbert, H. (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Laying the Foundation: Digital Humanities in
                  Academic Libraries</title>. Purdue University Press, pp. 111–126. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctt163t7kq"
                  >https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctt163t7kq</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schaffner2014" label="Schaffner and Erway 2014">Schaffner, J., Erway, R.,
               2014. <title rend="quotes">Does Every Research Library Need a Digital Humanities
                  Center?</title> OCLC Online Computer Library Center, Inc.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sweeney2017" label="Sweeney et al. 2017">Sweeney, S.J., Flanders, J.,
               Levesque, A., 2017. <title rend="quotes">Community-Enhanced Repository for Engaged
                  Scholarship: A case study on supporting digital humanities research</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">College Undergraduate Libraries</title>. 24, 322–336. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1080/10691316.2017.1336144"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/10691316.2017.1336144</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vandegrift2013" label="Vandegrift and Varner 2013">Vandegrift, M., Varner,
               S., 2013. <title rend="quotes">Evolving in Common: Creating Mutually Supportive
                  Relationships Between Libraries and the Digital Humanities</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Journal of Library Administration</title>. 53, 67–78. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01930826.2013.756699"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/01930826.2013.756699</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zhang2015" label="Zhang et al. 2015">Zhang, Y., Liu, S., Mathews, E.,
               2015. <title rend="quotes">Convergence of digital humanities and digital
                  libraries</title>. <title rend="italic">Library Management</title>. 36, 362–377.
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1108/LM-09-2014-0116"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1108/LM-09-2014-0116</ref></bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
