<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Interlude: Gaining Access, Gaming Access: Balancing
                    Internal and External Support For Interactive Digital Projects </title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Matthew <dhq:family>Kelly</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Texas, Tyler</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>mkelly@uttyler.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Matthew Kelly is an Assistant Professor of English in the Department of
                            Literature and Languages at the University of Texas at Tyler. His
                            research focuses on the role of digital literacies and collective
                            pedagogical practices in video game communities as well as the impact of
                            integrating digital media technologies into the writing classroom. His
                            published work appears in <title rend="italic">CTheory</title>, <title
                                rend="italic">Games and Culture</title>, and <title rend="italic"
                                >First Person Scholar</title>.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000417</idno>
                <idno type="volume">013</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2019-08-01">01 August 2019</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>digital pedagogy</item>
                        <item>access</item>
                        <item>game studies</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2019-05-25" who="Madelyn">Finished initial encoding</change>
            <change when="2019-05-25" who="Julia">Reviewed encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>This short essay describes the difficulties and impromptu workarounds that
                    emerged when using the video game <title rend="quotes">Minecraft</title> as the
                    central teaching tool in several professional writing seminars. More
                    specifically, the author discusses a key moment in the semester where students
                    needed to move between university and non-university technology infrastructures
                    in order to create multiplayer gamespaces that were accessible to their peers.
                    In narrating this experience, the author will demonstrate how a discourse of
                        <soCalled>access</soCalled> can be used to examine the oft-invisible
                    policies, procedures, and restrictions that shape the way we compose, circulate
                    and make visible digitally-native work. Furthermore, the author will discuss how
                    a critical emphasis on <soCalled>access</soCalled> can help teachers and
                    students better mediate the relationship between internal or university-supplied
                    technological infrastructures and external platforms when creating interactive
                    digital projects.</p>
                <p>The underlying motivation of this essay is not to lambaste universities for lack
                    of institutional support nor is it to champion commercial organizations as
                    saviors for helping teachers successfully use digital platforms in the
                    classroom. Instead, the goal of this brief essay is to spur discussions
                    surrounding the following questions: how might we use issues regarding access to
                    better examine and navigate the hard-to-define boundaries that separate
                    university-sanction technology use from non-university sanctioned technology
                    use? How might calling students' attention to access refine the larger learning
                    objectives for Digital Humanities or DH-related courses?</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>This short essay describes the difficulties and impromptu workarounds that
                    emerged when using the video game <title rend="italic">Minecraft</title> as the
                    central teaching tool in several professional writing seminars.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p> In an institutional climate often guided by nebulous policies, procedures, and
                restrictions shaping how students use digital technologies in university spaces, it
                can be difficult for instructors to implement a streamlined process for creating
                interactive digital projects. In many cases, teachers and students must rely on a
                bricolage assemblage of third-party platforms, each with varying degrees of
                compatibility and long-term support, when designing digital texts <ptr
                    target="#eyman2015"/>. This, in turn, can create scenarios where digital
                compositions are left abandoned or rendered unusable on modern machines due to the
                fact that they are not housed within stable, sustainable university infrastructures.
                However, this is not to say that university-supplied resources for digital work are
                universally lackluster or that third-party software is the only solution to
                technology-based teaching issues. Rather, this situation demands that we rethink how
                to navigate the complex interrelationship between university and non-university
                platforms, especially when asking students to create digital projects using a
                variety of proprietary or commercialized software in institutional environments.
                This examination proposes that a revised understanding of access can be a useful
                framework for revealing, critiquing, and even modifying the oft-invisible boundaries
                separating university and non-university technology policies or infrastructures,
                boundaries that might unintentionally stymie the inventive potential of
                collaborative, interactive digital projects. </p>
            <p>The importance of access-based concerns became especially clear to me after a
                near-derailing of a collaborative game session in one of my upper-division writing
                classes. While teaching at the University of Pittsburgh during the 2015-2016
                academic year, I designed several Written Professional Communication seminars around
                the open-world video game <title rend="italic">Minecraft</title>. Students were
                tasked with composing a variety of documents that mimicked real-world genres — such
                as technical descriptions of gameplay mechanics and resource guides for new players
                — based on their first-hand experiences with the game. My rationale for
                incorporating a video game into a professional writing course was to highlight the
                idea that professional or technical writers must often negotiate open-ended
                interactions between other individuals (such as clients or customers) and non-human
                agents (such as computer programs or physical equipment). In a parallel fashion, the
                process of designing and documenting an interactive gamespace can mirror many of the
                same situations or obstacles which professional and technical writers face on a
                regular basis, seeing as game designers must rationalize the structural features of
                a video game while also envisioning how other players might interact with said
                features <ptr target="#greene2014"/>. The hope was that having students compose
                documents that detailed specific gameplay mechanics and intended player experiences
                would illustrate the rhetorical dimensions underlying real-world workplace writing
                scenarios</p>
            <p>A few weeks into the semester, I organized a <soCalled>lab day</soCalled> where
                students would come to class with a copy of <title rend="italic">Minecraft</title>
                installed on their computers so I could walk them through some basic mechanics of
                the charming block-based world. One student had previous experiences hosting <title
                    rend="italic">Minecraft</title> games with her friends and asked if she could
                create a multiplayer server for our class, which would allow all of us to inhabit
                the same virtual gamespace simultaneously as opposed to having students explore
                their own single-player worlds alongside each other. I quickly gave the project a
                vote of confidence and the student began setting up a server on her laptop.
                Unfortunately, these plans stalled the morning of our class when campus wifi refused
                to let the server-host configure <soCalled>port forwarding</soCalled> for our
                multiplayer game. Port forwarding is a process wherein communication requests can be
                re-directed through a router or firewall in order to remotely access files hosted on
                another computer, thereby allowing users to create a private
                network-within-a-network. Unbeknownst to us, university IT prohibited communication
                requests to be re-directed in such a way that permitted remote Internet access to
                another device on campus (which, in this case, was a student's laptop hosting a
                video game server). Restrictions on port forwarding make sense from a security
                standpoint because they can limit the threat of non-authorized remote connections
                (i.e., instances where devices could be remotely controlled by malicious software).
                However, the same policies that regulated port forwarding within university
                infrastructure also prevented students from using their own computers to create
                collaborative digital spaces for their classmates. To bypass these restrictions, the
                student who organized our class server offered to relocate to a cafe down the street
                so she could use their wifi to host our <title rend="italic">Minecraft</title>
                session. For the remainder of the period, I played virtual tour guide for our class
                while keeping in touch with the server-host via an instant-messaging feature within
                our university's email client.</p>
            <p>What I find most interesting about these policies and impromptu workarounds is that
                they demonstrate how issues of access can reveal the invisible boundaries which
                separate university-sanctioned tech practices from non-university-sanctioned
                activities; the struggles of one student trying to make a multiplayer video game
                accessible for her peers revealed the invisible policies that demarcate what is (or
                is not) a permitted usage of digital platforms within university infrastructure and
                the invisible line where a university's jurisdiction, so to speak, over technology
                usage begins or ends. It was not until a student ventured beyond the confines of
                university infrastructure that she was able to take up and apply a new configuration
                of digital platforms in order to circulate an interactive digital project that could
                be used by others. Put differently, the ability for a student to facilitate a
                collaborative peer-to-peer classroom experience was entirely contingent upon whether
                she resided within or beyond university spaces on both a virtual and literal level.
                To clarify, I am not implying that our institution had devious machinations to
                censor student actions. Rather, these teaching misfires highlight the difficulty and
                necessity of coaxing internal and external (i.e. university and non-university)
                systems to play nice when composing or distributing interactive digital
                projects.</p>
            <p>I used these difficulties as an opportunity to discuss institutional policies with my
                class and prepare them for our end-of-semester project, which tasked student groups
                with documenting and designing a multiplayer <title rend="italic">Minecraft</title>
                gamespace that taught users about the values or practices of a given professional
                community. The rest of our semester was an experiment in playing the game of access
                insofar as student groups needed to devise their own methods for creating, saving,
                and circulating their projects among their peers. Several groups purchased accounts
                for <title rend="italic">Minecraft</title> Realms, which is a subscription service
                that hosts multiplayer <title rend="italic">Minecraft</title> servers for a monthly
                fee. Because <title rend="italic">Minecraft</title> Realms handles all technical
                aspects of server-hosting duties, students did not encounter the same technical
                issues that plagued our lab day. One student group wanted to implement custom mods
                in their project so they set up an independent server server with the understanding
                that the server-host needed to be off-campus in order for group members to work on
                their gamespace. In each of these scenarios, students needed to manipulate the line
                separating university and non-university technological infrastructures by creating
                their own impromptu solutions for cataloging their composing practices and making
                accessible all the work they had invested in these projects throughout the semester.
                As our class progressed, these workarounds became central features of student
                learning experiences and several groups detailed the ways in which they negotiated
                technical limitations during their end-of-semester presentations. In documenting how
                they gamed access in order to gain access, students were able to explore larger
                institutional procedures (one student talked about repeatedly installing <title
                    rend="italic">Minecraft</title> on temporary laptops loaned out from the campus
                library while her primary computer was being fixed) in addition to pragmatic
                concerns regarding digital composing practices (a student who lost nearly all of his
                progress because of software issues bluntly stated the he learned to <title
                    rend="quotes">never update to the newest version</title> in the middle of a
                project). Hence, issues of access operated as the proverbial canary in the coalmine
                for identifying the invisible boundaries and policies that structure students'
                everyday interactions with digital technologies.</p>
            <p>Over the course of this brief case study, initial questions of access eventually
                dovetailed into larger questions of digital archiving and preservation; workarounds
                for making students' <title rend="italic">Minecraft</title> projects accessible for
                prospective players emerged alongside strategies for preserving these gamespaces in
                such a way that group members could continue designing their virtual worlds in a
                consistent, sustainable manner. Despite the unique circumstances surrounding my
                video game-centric teaching experiment, the intersection between access, archiving,
                and preservation has been an emerging concern across digital humanities scholarship.
                Universities have begun responding to these issues by creating initiatives to
                support the long-term curation of digital work. For example, the Digital Scholarship
                Lab at the University of Richmond goes beyond simply backing up files for
                interactive texts in a static database. Instead, full-time DSL faculty coordinate
                the development of interactive projects with their respective authors while using a
                variety of open-source platforms — such as MySQL, Omeka, and JavaScript — to ensure
                long-term sustainability and broad accessibility of digitally-native texts. Projects
                curated and hosted by the DSL include <soCalled>Visualizing Emancipation</soCalled>
                (an interactive map that documents the uneven spread of emancipation during and
                after the Civil War) as well as <title rend="quotes">Renewing Inequality</title>
                (which visualizes how urban renewal projects during the 1950s and 60s led to the
                mass displacement of low-income and minority communities throughout American
                cities), both of which encourage users to see these interactive texts as outlets for
                further research or teaching.</p>
            <p>While the DSL is an excellent example of contemporary efforts to protect interactive
                texts from the threat of digital obsolescence, we should not gauge the success of
                this initiative based solely on the amount of resources and labor dedicated to
                producing digital projects. Instead, we should measure the impact of institutional
                undertakings such as the DSL based on the support offered to authors and audiences
                of digitally-native work. That is to say, successful institutional support for
                digital work can be evaluated based on the capacity for audiences across a variety
                of spaces and settings to engage with digital projects regardless of institutional
                affiliation or circumstances. Failing to circulate digital work beyond a small
                handful of faculty members at a specific university would severely undermine the
                on-going critical contributions of digital projects and their authors, seeing as the
                scholarly or pedagogical value of many interactive texts resides in their capacity
                to be actively used by other individuals. Consequently, the DSL's emphasis on
                ensuring access to interactive texts for audiences beyond those in traditional
                university environments offers one model that can help scholars and teachers
                envision what constitutes sustainable university support when discussing resources
                for digital work.</p>
            <p>Initiatives such as the DSL resonate with the same themes underlying my
                students' <title rend="italic">Minecraft</title> projects in the sense that
                questions surrounding access can operate as a framework for identifying,
                negotiating, and even modifying the invisible boundaries that regulate the
                production or circulation of digital work within and beyond university
                infrastructures. The success of my students' <title rend="italic">Minecraft</title>
                projects hinged on their ability to navigate the invisible line separating
                university- from non-university technology policies and platforms in order to make
                their collaborative projects accessible to their peers. Similarly, the success of
                the DSL stems from its ability to streamline the curation, preservation, and
                distribution of digital texts across university and non-university spaces, thereby
                making interactive projects accessible to a wide range of audiences. Hence, the
                small-scale workarounds created by students and contemporary large-scale
                institutional undertakings both demonstrate how a renewed focus on access can help
                us re-approach the obstacles that scholars, teachers, and students face when
                composing digitally-native work.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eyman2015" label="Eyman 2015"> Eyman, D. and Ball, C. <title
                        rend="quotes">Digital Humanities Scholarship and Electronic
                        Publication.</title> In B. Hart-Davidson, and J. Ridolfo (eds), <title
                        rend="italic">Rhetoric and the Digital Humanities</title> , Chicago (2015),
                    pp. 65-79.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="greene2014" label="Greene 2014"> Greene, J. and Palmer, L. <title
                        rend="quotes">It's All Fun and Games Until Someone Pulls Out a Manual:
                        Finding a Role for Technical Communicators in the Game Industry.</title> In
                    J. DeWinter, and R. Moeller (eds), <title rend="italic">Computer Games and
                        Technical Communication: Critical Methods and Applications at the
                        Intersection</title> , Burlington (2014), pp. 17-33.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
