<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Open, Equitable, and
               Minimal: Teaching Digital Scholarly Editing North and South</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Raffaele <dhq:family>Viglianti</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-->https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3094-139X</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities, University of
                  Maryland, USA</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>rviglian@umd.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Dr. Raffaele (Raff) Viglianti is a Senior Research Software Developer at the
                     Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities, University of Maryland.
                     His research is grounded in digital humanities and textual scholarship, where
                     “text” includes musical notation. He researches new and efficient practices to
                     model and publish textual sources as innovative and sustainable digital
                     scholarly resources. Dr. Viglianti is currently an elected member of the Text
                     Encoding Initiative technical council and the Technical Editor of the Scholarly
                     Editing journal.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Gimena <dhq:family>del Rio Riande</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-->https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8997-5415</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>National Council on Scientific and Technical Research,
                  Argentina</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>gdelrio@conicet.gov.ar</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Gimena del Rio Riande is Associate Researcher at CONICET (National Council on
                     Scientific and Technical Research, Argentina) where she does research at the
                     Institute of Bibliographic Studies (IIBICRIT) and coordinates the Digital
                     Humanities Lab (CAICYT). She is the director of the first university
                     postgraduate training course and the Digital Humanities Association (AAHD) in
                     Argentina.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Nidia <dhq:family>Hernández</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-->https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7557-6846</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>National Council on Scientific and Technical Research,
                  Argentina</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>nidiahernandez@conicet.gov.ar</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Nidia Hernández is a linguist and a specialist in data processing at
                     CAICYT-CONICET (Buenos Aires, Argentina). She develops resources for Digital
                     Editions of Early Modern Latin American texts for the Digital Humanities lab
                     (HDCAICYTLAB) and she also collaborates in projects of documentation,
                     processing and analysis of endangered languages of South America.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Romina <dhq:family>De Léon</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>CONICET (National Council on Scientific and Technical Research,
                  Argentina) </dhq:affiliation>
               <email>rdeleon@conicet.gov.ar</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Romina De León is a research assistant at CONICET (Argentina). She embodies a
                     Liberal Arts approach as she combines former Chemical Engineering studies and a
                     current academic interest in History. She participates in the publication and
                     curation of digital editions of Early Modern Latin American texts and the
                     edition of scholar publications in Digital Humanities (CAICYT-CONICET). She is
                     secretary and editor of Revista de Humanidades Digitales (UNED-Spain), editor
                     assigned to the historical number of INCIPIT (IIBICRIT-CONICET).</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000591</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->2</idno>
         	<date when="2022-06-25">25 June 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2022-08-02" who="BRG">fixed bibliography sortKey</change>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000591/000591.xml"
               >GitHub </ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>In this paper, we present our preliminary reflections on whether minimal computing as
               a practice can extend beyond <quote rend="inline">computing done under some
                  technological constraints</quote> to served as a common ground between different
               digital humanities research dynamics in the Global North and South. We explore this
               question by commenting on our experience in developing and teaching an undergraduate
               course to students enrolled from both the University of Maryland, College Park in the
               United States and Universidad del Salvador in Buenos Aires, Argentina. The class was
               delivered for its first iteration in September–November 2020 and introduced students
               to digital publishing and textual scholarship of bilingual Spanish and English texts,
               presenting minimal computing as a shared set of values including: use of open
               technologies, ownership of data and code, and reduction in computing
               infrastructure.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>In this paper, we present our preliminary reflections on whether minimal computing as
               a practice can extend beyond <quote rend="inline">computing done under some
                  technological constraints</quote> to serving as a common ground between different
               digital humanities research dynamics in the Global North and South.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>

            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>What if minimal computing principles extended <quote rend="inline">beyond computing
                  done under some technological constraints</quote>
               <ptr target="#workinggroup2021"/>, but also were at the core of a global digital
               humanities commons? Could this commons model a set of shared principles and
               technologies to empower students and scholars to work autonomously on their own
               projects? With these questions in mind, researchers from the University of Maryland,
               College Park in the United States and the National Scientific and Technical Research
               Council (Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y Técnicas, CONICET) in
               Argentina designed a joint course, delivered for the first time from
               September–November 2020, to teach minimal computing approaches to North and South
               American students. The class introduced students to digital publishing and textual
               scholarship with minimal computing presented as a shared set of values: use of open
               technologies, ownership of data and code, reduction in computing infrastructure and,
               consequently, environmental impact.</p>
            <p>Minimal computing can be a solution for the development of projects in the Global
               South, where access to infrastructure such as web hosting or even reliable and
               affordable Internet access is limited for humanities students and faculty. Our
               course, which will continue through 2022 at minimum, positions minimal computing as
               an approach that can bring together students from the North and the South in the same
               class — through video conference and other means — to discuss and address the
               barriers and opportunities for a more open and equitable global digital
               humanities.</p>
            <p>In this essay we will discuss: 1) the open and minimal technologies we use for
               teaching students to create digital scholarly editions and why we have chosen them;
               2) the bilingual teaching materials adopted and why we chose them; and 3) how
               students collaborate online in Spanish and English in small cross-institutional
               groups using Spanish and English texts from early colonial times in the Americas.</p>
            <p>Through our work on this course, we are not only offering training on specific
               minimal computing skills but are also contributing to much-needed analysis of the
               different technological and academic contexts around the world: issues related to
               infrastructure, language, digital literacy, and Open Science practices. We seek to
               raise awareness about the different kinds of digital humanities around the world,
               which will both benefit our students and make a case to the global digital humanities
               community that technology cannot be owned by anyone, but must be used and contributed
               to by all.</p>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>From Global to Open Digital Humanities</head>
            <p>While Anglophone digital humanities has established itself as part of many graduate
               and postgraduate programs, summer schools, centers, labs, books, and journals, the
               Latin American and Spanish humanidades digitales is still defining itself and
               pondering how to devise a curriculum of its own <ptr target="#delrioriande2015"/>.
               However, both share a defining feature: their continuous growth as part of our
               contemporary digital and digitized world. This shared feature has led many scholars
               to redefine their work under the impact of the digital and to consider the
               consequences of a <q>global turn</q> that has put into question many aspects of their
               academic, linguistic, and technical practices <ptr target="#earhart2018"/>. </p>
            <p>The debate over a <q>global digital humanities</q> resulted in a considerable shift
               in 2013 when the Global Outlook Digital Humanities (GO::DH) Special Interest Group of
               the Alliance for the Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO) was founded. GO::DH
               pointed out the importance of problematizing digital humanities as a field built and
               understood from multiple perspectives <ptr target="#gil2016b"/>, something that the
               Alliance for Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO) addressed both in DH2015 in
               Australia — named <title rend="italic">Global Digital Humanities</title> — and in the
               panel on diversity in the field of digital humanities at DH2016 in Kraków <ptr
                  target="#odonnell2016"/>. This trend is also confirmed by the annual Global
               Digital Humanities Symposium that has been taking place at Michigan State University
               since 2016 and in initiatives such as the IFLA Special Interest Group<note> More
                  information about the Digital Humanities/Digital Scholarship Special Interest
                  Group of the International Federation of Library Associations and Institutions
                  (IFLA) can be found at <ref target="https://www.ifla.org/ES/node/25695"
                     >https://www.ifla.org/ES/node/25695</ref>. </note> and the Asociación Argentina
               de Humanidades Digitales (AAHD) 2016 conference, <title rend="italic">Local
                  Constructions in Global Contexts</title>
               <ptr target="#delrioriande2018"/>.<note> Programme and Proceedings of the AAHD
                  Conference <title rend="italic">Local Constructions in Global Contexts </title> is
                  available at <ref target="https://www.aacademica.org/aahd.congreso"
                     >https://www.aacademica.org/aahd.congreso</ref>. </note> Another relevant event
               that proves how the global dimension of digital humanities has had an impact on its
               organizational core is the process initiated in 2016 with the goal of changing the
               governance and the financial model of ADHO, expanding its boundaries to regions of
               the Global South <ptr target="#fiormonte2017b"/>. </p>
            <p>Nonetheless, despite the benefits that we could expect from a global digital
               humanities, it is crucial to remember that the concept of the <q>global</q> is
               complex and even contradictory, especially when related to technology in all its
               facets. In the context of global digital humanities, <q>technology</q> includes:
                  <term>software architecture</term>, or the availability and cost of software
               solutions and the expertise to develop and adopt them; <term>infrastructure as
                  hardware</term>, or the availability and cost of computers, peripherals, and other
               instruments capable of supporting the research software and approaches a digital
               humanities project may need; and <term>infrastructure as long-term
                  preservation</term>, or the strategies, data management plans, and institutional
               support needed for guaranteeing the availability of digital humanities research
               outputs in the future. This technology, as Anne Cong-Huyen argues, is never
                  <q>neutral</q> or truly <q>global</q>:</p>
            <cit><quote rend="block">[D]igital and electronic technologies are of particular
                  importance because they are often perceived as being neutral, without any
                  intrinsic ethics of their own, when they are the result of material inequalities
                  that play out along racial, gendered, national, and hemispheric lines. Not only
                  are these technologies the result of such inequity, but they also reproduce and
                  reinscribe that inequity through their very proliferation and use, which is
                  dependent upon the perpetuation of global networks of economic and social
                  disparity and exploitation.</quote>
               <ptr target="#conghuyen2013"/></cit>
            <p>The term <soCalled>global</soCalled> moreover, is itself a paradox: global impacts
               are perceived differently at local and regional levels, and there is no single and
               unique process of globalization, but rather a set of different processes with global
               dimensions. For example, while Global North digital humanities scholars have focused
               on understanding diversity and awareness of linguistic privilege, interrogating the
               degree to which global technological practices can exclude participation in the field
                  <ptr target="#fiormonte2017a"/>
               <ptr target="#fiormonte2016"/>
               <ptr target="#risam2018"/>
               <ptr target="#gil2015"/>
               <ptr target="#earhart2018"/>, the Spanish-speaking humanidades digitales situation is
               multifaceted. Undoubtedly, even though Spain and many countries in Latin America and
               the Caribbean share a language, their social, cultural, epistemic, and economic
               contexts are completely different. Spain is a country in the European Union, while
               Latin America is the most unequal region in the world that groups more than twenty
               countries that have been experiencing the impact of labor-saving technologies since
               the beginning of the century <ptr target="#krull2016"/>. Also, it is important to
               note that in Latin America the free, public dissemination of research has long been
               understood primarily as a public good managed by the academic community. Scielo, the
               largest open access harvesting platform in the region, was founded in 1997, five
               years before the 2002 meetings in Budapest, Bethesda, and Berlin that produced the
               first open access declarations <ptr target="#budapest2002"/>
               <ptr target="#bethesda2003"/>
               <ptr target="#berlin2003"/>. Non-commercial, open access publication — without
               article processing charges (APC)<note> An APC is a fee paid to the publisher to make
                  an article free at point of access. Whilst Open Access principles promote free
                  availability of research and scholarly output, research papers are not cost-free
                  to produce. The cost of publication is moved from the reader (via subscriptions
                  and pay-walls) to the author (via the APC) <ptr target="#tennant2015"/>.</note> —
               is the standard method of dissemination in Latin America and is widely understood as
               a key engine of knowledge democratization.</p>
            <p>Reflections on how digital humanities could benefit from open approaches such as
               these have been part of manifestos and debates in the last ten years but have rarely
               been systemized. Todd Presner made the first emphatic assertion: <quote rend="inline"
                  >The digital is the realm of the open: open source, open resources [...]. Anything
                  that attempts to close this space should be recognized for what it is: the
                  enemy</quote>
               <ptr target="#presner2009"/>. One year later, the Paris Manifesto focused on the
               technical aspects of what <q>open</q> means in digital humanities: <quote
                  rend="inline">[W]e call for open access to data and metadata, which must be
                  documented and interoperable, both technically and conceptually</quote>
               <ptr target="#dacos2010"/>. However, many other scholars use the term <q>open</q> to
               represent values of collaboration <ptr target="#spiro2012"/>
               <ptr target="#delrioriande2019"/> or authority <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2010"
                  />.<note> According to Kathleen Fitzpatrick, <quote rend="inline">The key problems
                     that we face again and again are social rather than technological in nature:
                     problems of encouraging participation in collaborative and collective projects,
                     of developing sound preservation and sustainability practices, of inciting
                     institutional change, of promoting new ways of thinking about how academic work
                     might be done in the coming years</quote>
                  <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2010"/>.</note> In the past few years, in part due to the
               influence of scholars from the Global South, the concept of open digital humanities
               scholarship has been given greater consideration. In a workshop at the 2018 ADHO
               conference, the debate was framed in this way: </p>
            <p><quote rend="block">What would it take to bring DH [digital humanities] into a more
                  global openness, not only in terms of access but also in terms of methods, best
                  practices and opportunities for collaboration? And what could this openness look
                  like set against the backdrop of the long-standing and highly developed open
                  access movement in Latin America and the Caribbean? <ptr target="#schallier2018"
                  /></quote></p>
            <p>Any reflection on a global digital humanities should think and teach our students
               about the many important questions related to power and inequality, like the extreme
               asymmetry in research outputs between scholars from well-resourced and
               not-so-well-resourced countries, sometimes understood in terms of Global North and
               South <ptr target="#chan2019"/>. And by outputs we do not only mean articles or
               books, but also the core of digital humanities scholarship: online web-based projects
               and the ways in which we teach them.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Open and Global Digital Scholarly Editing through Minimal Computing</head>
            <p>In recent years, Open Science has emerged as: </p>
            <cit><quote rend="block">[...] the practice of science in such a way that others can
                  collaborate and contribute, where research data, lab notes and other research
                  processes are freely available, under terms that enable reuse, redistribution and
                  reproduction of the research and its underlying data and methods.</quote>
               <ptr target="#foster2021"/>
            </cit>
            <p>Digital technologies and infrastructures play a significant role in the open
               dissemination of knowledge. Surprisingly, even though <quote rend="inline">Digital
                  Humanities is a technologically embedded field</quote> and <quote rend="inline"
                  >epistemic technologies are bound to play a significant role</quote>
               <ptr target="#svensson2016"/>, digital humanities critical literature hasn’t focused
               on the benefits of Open Science for enabling collaborative, scalable, and long
               lasting global research.<note> Marcel Knöchelmann argues that there is not an open
                  discourse in the humanities comparable to those in the sciences <ptr
                     target="#knochelmann2019"/>.</note> For example, digital scholarly editing and
               digital scholarly editions (DSEs) are not always perceived as <q>open.</q></p>
            <p> If editing is <quote rend="inline">without doubt one of the oldest scholarly
                  activities within the Humanities</quote>
               <ptr target="#pierazzo2016"/>, DSEs are at the core of digital humanities <ptr
                  target="#earhart2012"/>. While not all textual scholars might rely on the same
               definition of DSEs, they recognize their features and uses <ptr target="#sahle2016"
               />. Free, open standards such as the ones developed by the Text Encoding Initiative
               (TEI), along with eXtensible Markup Language (XML) technologies, such as eXtensible
               Stylesheet Language Transformations (XSLT) and XQuery, and dedicated software<note>
                  Some examples are TEI Boilerplate, Juxta, Versioning Machine, TextGrid, Ediarium,
                  eLaborate, Edition Visualization Technology, and CETEIcean.</note> have
               characterized the digital editing field. The scholarly editions themselves, however,
               haven’t always been successful as open products of research. Bodard and Garcés posed
               this issue when they claimed that, analogous to the Open Source Software movement,
               DSEs — which they call <q>Open Source Critical Editions</q> or <q>OSCE</q> — should
               be licensed for reuse, including all sources, data, methods, and software <ptr
                  target="#bodard2009"/>. While it is common practice to make TEI data publicly
               available, the debate over how DSEs need to be structured to be truly <q>open</q> is
               still ongoing and best practices have yet to be established. Vanessa Hannesschläger,
               for example, has recently surveyed licenses appropriate for DSEs powered by TEI and
               singled out Creative Commons ones as appropriate for an international context and for
               enabling an open culture of reuse with a global impact; however, there has yet to be
               widespread agreement with this proposal <ptr target="#hannesschlager2020"/>. </p>
            <p>From a Global South perspective, the DSE field is perceived as being dominated by
               standards and technologies that are still unfamiliar to scholars; not surprisingly,
               these methods are typically described in the context of Anglophone projects <ptr
                  target="#allestorrent2020"/>. Indeed, beyond some very specific projects and
               initiatives, multilingual resources related to DSEs, such as tutorials, software,
               books, and articles, are generally difficult to find in languages other than English.
               Moreover, the use of proprietary software for most editorial work has become a
               barrier for extending the DSE practice beyond Northern academies.<note> Most DSEs
                  rely on TEI documents encoded and processed with the help of the popular software
                  Oxygen XML Editor, which requires the purchase of a license. Most training and
                  teaching is also done using Oxygen, which has established a <term>de facto</term>
                  monopoly on DSEs production in the Global North.</note> Indeed, <quote
                  rend="inline">[d]igital scholarly editions are expensive to make and to
                  maintain</quote>
               <ptr target="#pierazzo2019"/>. As such, long-term web hosting, preservation, and
               access to servers pose a significant obstacle for not-so-well-funded scholars who
               lack access to grant funding or other institutional resources. Overall, DSEs require
               substantial infrastructure and advanced technical skills, while diverse needs,
               capacities, priorities, languages, and academic traditions may require different
               features from DSEs at a global scale.</p>
            <p>With that in mind, how can DSEs, one of the crown jewels of digital humanities <ptr
                  target="#pierazzo2016"/>, become global? From our perspective, this can be
               achieved by establishing a <q>digital commons.</q><note> The commons can be defined
                  as <quote rend="inline">resource[s] shared by a group of people that is subject to
                     social dilemmas</quote>
                  <ptr target="#hess2007"/>.</note> When the GO::DH Minimal Computing Working Group
               started a debate on power and inequality in digital humanities from a technological
               perspective, its intention was not to simply criticize or mourn a lack of diversity,
               but to establish an alternative discourse and create a new set of commons, namely
               technology of disobedience, architecture of necessity, and the moral modulor <ptr
                  target="#gil2016a"/>. The principles of minimal computing turned into new ways of
               undertaking digital humanities work and collaborating to building an alternative
               digital epistemology that has found a practical outlet in minimal DSEs with
                  Ed.,<note> Ed is a Jekyll theme for digital editions, developed by Alex Gil and
                  available at <ref target="https://github.com/minicomp/ed"
                     >https://github.com/minicomp/ed</ref>.</note> a tool for building minimal DSEs
               without elaborate text encoding. </p>
            <p>For these reasons, minimal computing informed the design of our joint course that
               teaches digital publishing and textual scholarship with minimal computing and text
               encoding. Specifically, we highlighted minimal computing as a shared set of values
               such as the use of open technologies, ownership of data and code, and reduction in
               computing infrastructure. The following question drove our course development: <quote
                  rend="inline">Could minimal computing provide a set of shared principles and
                  technologies to empower students and scholars to work autonomously on and have
                  more control over the future of their own projects?</quote><note>Canagarajah
                  writes in <title rend="italic">A Geopolitics of Academic Writing,</title>
                  <quote rend="inline">Periphery students are taught to be consumers of center
                     knowledge rather than producers of knowledge</quote>
                  <ptr target="#canagarajah2002" loc="283"/>.</note> We further considered: <quote
                  rend="inline">What if minimal computing extended beyond ‘computing done under some
                  technological constraints’ by standing at the core of a global Digital Humanities
                  commons, overcoming notions such as center and periphery, North and South?</quote>
               and <quote rend="inline">Could minimal computing serve as a common ground for
                  Northern and Southern digital humanists?</quote></p>
            <p>In Latin America, conversations on open and free technologies have been part of the
               Open Science agenda since the early 2000s, when the term <quote rend="inline"
                  >technological sovereignty</quote>
               <ptr target="#padilla2017"/> began to be used by Latin American activists who wanted
               to have more control over the software that they and their governments used. The
               Latin American Free and Open Source Software (FOSS) movement is aligned with the
               Latin American Open Science movement. Both share a strong sense of common ownership
               for the common good. Based on this, many networks like reGOSH have highlighted how
               the region could benefit from the development of open scientific tools, as a way of
               overcoming dependence on equipment suppliers in the Global North and increasing its
               digital autonomy.<note> reGOSH is the network for free-libre technologies for science
                  and education in Latin America: <ref target="https://regosh.libres.cc/en/home-en/"
                     >https://regosh.libres.cc/en/home-en/</ref>. </note> However, as we discussed
               above, Latin American countries have the most unequal income distribution in the
               world which results in research inequalities across the region <ptr
                  target="#amarante2016"/>. As a result, the allocation of resources for research in
               Latin America is in great disproportion to those in developed countries. This is the
               case of HD CAICYT Lab, the digital humanities laboratory at Argentinian CONICET,
               which has been doing digital humanities research with very limited funding and
               technological support from the institution since 2016.<note> The lab is part of
                  CAICYT’s institutional project, where challenges for its growth include the
                  scarcity of human resources and specific funding. Digital humanities project
                  funding is not common in the region, so sustainability depends mostly on external
                  funding and collaboration.</note> The lab, nonetheless, carries on work in an open
               research context aligned with the Argentinian national law on open access and the
               Open Science environment in Latin America. HD CAICYT Lab has been creating minimal
               editions via a workflow built around Recogito, an open source semantic annotation
               software developed by Pelagios Network <ptr target="#recogito2021"/>, incorporating
               TEI markup and rendering the edited texts in static sites built with Jekyll and
               GitHub pages. In 2016, Susanna Allés-Torrent led a minimal computing workshop at the
               Second International Conference of the Asociación Argentina de Humanidades Digitales
               (AAHD) in Buenos Aires, Argentina <ptr target="#allestorrent2016"/>. Scholars who
               attended the event felt empowered by the possibility of working autonomously on their
               own editions, and minimal computing was understood as a solution for the development
               of projects where access to infrastructure such as web hosting or even reliable and
               affordable Internet access is limited for humanities students and faculty. For our
               lab, HD CAICYT, minimal computing turned into the solution for computing done under
               technological limitations, as well as for <quote rend="inline">producing our own
                  scholarship ourselves</quote>
               <ptr target="#gil2015"/>.</p>
            <p>Minimal computing has become part of HD CAICYT Lab’s digital humanities standards and
               commons, integrating with our principles of openness: open corpora, documentation,
               collaboration, software, and publishing <ptr target="#delrioriande2018"/>.<note> See
                  Jekyll’s perspective on openness, collaboration, and code of conduct: <ref
                     target="https://jekyllrb.com/news/2017/10/19/diversity-open-source/"
                     >https://jekyllrb.com/news/2017/10/19/diversity-open-source/</ref>. </note>
               Since the Lab is unable to buy software or pay for servers and hosting, adopting
               minimal computing strategies created the conditions necessary for our work to be part
               of the global digital humanities landscape. As such, we practice minimal computing
               beyond its definition of simply <quote rend="inline">computing done under some
                  technological constraints</quote> as it becomes our primary instrument for any
               form of digital humanities.<note> See for example the digital scholarly edition of an
                  Argentinian chronicle called <title rend="italic">Historia de la Conquista del Río
                     de la Plata</title>, better known as <q>La Argentina Manuscrita,</q> written by
                  Ruy Diaz de Guzman in the early seventeenth century, available at <ref
                     target="https://arounddh.org/en/la-argentina-manuscrita"
                     >https://arounddh.org/en/la-argentina-manuscrita</ref>. </note>
            </p>
            <p>The Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH) at the University of
               Maryland has adopted minimal computing strategies primarily for digital preservation.
               MITH migrated a number of websites and web applications to static sites in order to
               reduce infrastructure demands and increase their longevity <ptr target="#summers2016"
               /> and posed the minimal computing archetypal question: <quote rend="inline">What do
                  we need?</quote>
               <ptr target="#gil2015"/> as one of the guiding principles for future and current
               projects. In working with communities in and around the University of Maryland
               campus, MITH staff works with and trains collaborators around minimal technologies
               that allow them to curate, maintain, and, most importantly, own community archives
               independently of MITH’s and the university’s infrastructure.<note> One example is the
                  Lakeland Community Archive Project, which documents a historic African American
                  community before and after segregation and contributes to an understanding of
                  urban renewal's impact on communities of color in College Park, Maryland, USA,
                  available at <ref target="https://mith.umd.edu/research/lakeland/"
                     >https://mith.umd.edu/research/lakeland/</ref>. </note> More specifically to
               DSEs, the prominent Shelley-Godwin Archive (S-GA) <ptr
                  target="#shelleygodwinarchive2021"/> has adopted technologies atypical for a
               TEI-based project from the start, with an eye towards Linked Open Data
                  integration<note> Particularly in relation with the then nascent International
                  Image Interoperability Framework: <ref target="https://iiif.io"
                     >https://iiif.io</ref>.</note> and towards the reduction of the infrastructural
               footprint of the project. This led to a case-study experiment aimed at enabling
               offline use of the archive inspired by minimal computing principles to <quote
                  rend="inline">increase its availability to a larger number of communities with
                  variable access to the Internet</quote>
               <ptr target="#viglianti2018"/>. TEI publishing in S-GA is handled directly in the
               browser, avoiding server-side transformations typical of many TEI projects that
               require substantial server infrastructure to be maintained and kept online long term.
               Partly informed by this experience, Raffaele Viglianti worked with Hugh Cayless on
                  CETEIcean,<note> CETEIcean is available at <ref
                     target="https://github.com/teic/ceteicean"
                     >https://github.com/teic/ceteicean</ref>. </note> a JavaScript library for
               publishing TEI (and other XML) documents within an HTML page <ptr
                  target="#cayless2018"/>.</p>
            <p>The different approaches to minimal computing and DSEs, context-dependent for HD
               CAICYT Lab and strategic for MITH, formed the basis of our collaboration on the
               course that we teach to undergraduate students in Buenos Aires and Maryland: Digital
               Publishing with Minimal Computing. Our combined experiences present our students with
               a perspective on minimal computing that is not entirely dependent on digital
               humanities practices in the Global North, but rather one that is based on a shared
               digital commons. Focusing on minimal computing allows us to teach the fundamentals of
               scholarly editing and digital publishing through free and open tools while engaging
               with issues of content ownership on the web that extend beyond textual scholarship.
               Our course challenges students to publish without relying on institutional
               infrastructure while keeping a critical eye towards commercial infrastructure,
               particularly in relation to data ownership and preservation. While this comes with an
               initially steep learning curve for discovering and adopting new digital tools, it
               also teaches students how to manage the fate of the resources they create.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Digital Publishing with Minimal Computing: Humanities at a Global Scale</head>
            <p>In December 2019, we proposed a course titled Digital Publishing with Minimal
               Computing: Humanities at a Global Scale<note> The bilingual public website for the
                  course is available at <ref target="https://mith.umd.edu/minimaldigipub/"
                     >https://mith.umd.edu/minimaldigipub/</ref>. </note> to the Global Classroom
               Initiative (GCI) program at the University of Maryland. This program offers support
               for the development of courses to be taught in collaboration with a higher education
               institution outside of the United States, with the goal of establishing courses that
               expose students to work that is cross-cultural, project-based, and virtual; the GCI
               argues that these courses mirror the work students will encounter throughout their
               lives. While this outcome is somewhat dependent on the students’ career choices and
               opportunities, it is evident that <quote rend="inline">globalization shrinks the
                  world, bringing a wider range of cultures into closer contact than ever before </quote>
               <ptr target="#unesco2013"/>. Thus, preparing students to participate in a globalized
               world is a worthwhile goal, particularly if this can be done in a way that fosters
               intercultural competences.<note> According to UNESCO, <quote rend="inline"
                     >Intercultural competences refer to having adequate relevant knowledge about
                     particular cultures, as well as general knowledge about the sorts of issues
                     arising when members of different cultures interact, holding receptive
                     attitudes that encourage establishing and maintaining contact with diverse
                     others, as well as having the skills required to draw upon both knowledge and
                     attitudes when interacting with others from different cultures</quote>
                  <ptr target="#unesco2013"/>.</note> The COVID-19 pandemic also exacerbated the
               virtual nature of this contact, as we adapted to rely even more heavily on
               technological links to collaborate both locally and globally.</p>
            <p>The course, which involves students from the Universidad del Salvador (USAL) in
               Argentina and from the University of Maryland (UMD) in the United States,<note> The
                  instructors in Argentina teach at Universidad del Salvador but are affiliated with
                  the Argentinian Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y Técnicas
                  (CONICET).</note> has received funding for at least three iterations between 2020
               and 2022, with a blend of online and in-person learning.<note> Our plan was to have
                  in-person lectures with a shared audio/video link joining the two classrooms
                  together. Given the global pandemic, however, the first iteration of the course
                  was fully online for all students in 2020 and online for Universidad del Salvador
                  and hybrid for University of Maryland students in 2021.</note> It is centered
               around a group project in which students collaborate virtually to create a bilingual
               (Spanish and English) digital edition of a multilingual colonial era text,<note> This
                  text is a travelogue written by a Basque trader called Acarette Du Biscay and its
                  publishing history is truly multilingual. Acarete's travels were published in his
                  native language, French, in the <title rend="italic">Relation des voyages du Sr…
                     dans la rivière de la Plata, et de-là par terre au Pérou</title> in 1672, as
                  part of volume IV of the famous Thevenot<title rend="italic"> Collection of
                     Relations De Divers Voyages Curieux</title>, and in 1696, independently, in the
                     <title rend="italic">Relation des voyages dans la rivière de la Plate</title>.
                  Two years later the 1698 London edition came to light in a collection entitled
                     <title rend="italic">Voyages and Discoveries in South America</title>, and
                  later as an individual book by Samuel Buckley's printing press as <title
                     rend="italic">An Account of a Voyage up the River de la Plata, and Thence over
                     Land to Peru: With Observations on the Inhabitants, as Well as Indians and
                     Spaniards, the Cities, Commerce, Fertility, and Riches of That Part of
                     America</title>. It was later translated from English to Spanish by Daniel
                  Maxwell, and published in <title rend="italic">La Revista de Buenos Aires</title>,
                  in May and June 1867, as <title rend="italic">Relación de los viajes de Monsieur
                     Ascarate du Biscay al Rio de la Plata, y desde aquí por tierra hasta el Perú,
                     con observaciones sobre estos paises</title>. </note> while learning about
               digital humanities approaches to literary studies, digital publishing, and history.
               The group project involving students from both institutions facilitates the
               cross-cultural collaboration that is central to GCI courses. Project-based learning
               is also an effective learning paradigm in which <quote rend="inline">students
                  actively construct their knowledge by participating in real-world activities
                  similar to those that experts engage in, to solve problems and develop
                  artifacts</quote>
               <ptr target="#krajcik2005"/>. </p>
            <p>This approach is not unfamiliar to digital humanities pedagogy <ptr
                  target="#clement2012"/>, given that digital humanities research itself tends to be
               scaffolded through project work that results in the development of artifacts such as
               tools or digital publications <ptr target="#burdick2012" loc="124"/>. It is also
               connected to a multiliteracies approach, which brings together linguistic diversity
               and multimodal forms of expression and representation in response to changes in
               globalized technological environments such as the Internet, and the growing
               linguistic and cultural diversity due to increased transnational migration <ptr
                  target="#newlondongroup1996"/>
               <ptr target="#cope2009"/>
               <ptr target="#clement2012"/>. Teaching through a minimal computing lens, moreover,
               greatly benefits from projects that exhort students to think both globally and
               locally by recognizing the technological affordances they have access to (as well as
               why and how) and by confronting the limitations and constraints that work against
               them, whether in hardware, software, education, network capacity, power, or indeed
               self-imposed limitations for pedagogical purposes. In other words, we train our
               students to recognize the privileges of having access to state-of-the-art
               computational resources as well as to devise strategies to circumvent limitations
               they may encounter by adopting minimal computing techniques. Students (and experts)
               from both cultural contexts are likely to encounter such limitations to varying
               degrees. Even those who have access to infrastructure through their institutions or
               future employers will encounter issues with preservation and portability of the
               digital publication projects that they have created. Learning to deploy minimal
               approaches can contribute to the viability of a digital humanities project and give
               students greater control over the future of their own work. This mimics and models to
               our students the role, as we have discussed above, that minimal computing can play in
               establishing open and global approaches for digital humanities research and pedagogy
               that willfully reduce the gap between Global South and Global North
               contributions.</p>
            <p>The nature of the cross-border collaboration between students is online and virtual,
               given their geographical separation. They attend virtual lectures and collaborate
               online via messaging and code sharing platforms, with the support of the instructors.
               This kind of engagement is often referred to as <quote rend="inline">Virtual
                  Exchange</quote>
               <ptr target="#bassani2019"/>
               <ptr target="#odown2018"/> or <quote rend="inline">Collaborative Online International
                  Learning</quote> (COIL) <ptr target="#guth2013"/>. The COIL Institute for Globally
               Networked Learning in the Humanities at the State University of New York was among
               the first to explore the applicability of this approach to humanities disciplines
               through an National Endowment for the Humanities grant. The final white paper reports
               on the twenty-four courses taught as part of the project and summarizes the surveys
               completed by instructors and students <ptr target="#guth2013"/>. The results
               highlighted how COIL courses offer a form of internationalization at home and a
                  <q>low-cost</q> alternative to study abroad exchange programs, which are typically
               accessible to a very limited number of students, at least in the United States <ptr
                  target="#li2013"/>. More importantly, the study identified clear merits of a
               project-based, cross-cultural approach to education in the humanities:</p>
            <cit><quote rend="block">To no surprise, most [survey respondents] cited the access to
                  different cultural points of view as adding that <q>something extra</q> to the
                  course. They found that this element increased student motivation, led to more
                  in‐depth learning and helped students be more willing to see ideas, texts, works
                  of art, etc. from different perspectives. In some ways it was as if the students
                  felt they had to perform better because they saw their partner class as a new
                  audience particularly during synchronous audio/video sessions and in asynchronous
                  discussion forums.</quote>
               <ptr target="#guth2013"/></cit>
            <p>Our course applies the COIL approach to teaching digital scholarly editing through
               the lens of minimal computing, which, in itself, is an instrument for fostering
               international competencies in both student and expert work towards a more open and
               global digital humanities practice. Creating a course of this kind is necessarily a
               collaborative process that takes time and requires exchange of ideas among
               instructors. Over the seven months between first developing our GCI project and the
               first iteration of the course in September 2020, we discussed our pedagogical
               priorities, developed the syllabus, and created multilingual student resources such
               as slides, tutorials, and guidelines.<note> This includes resources and materials we
                  have previously developed, like the TTHub, <ref target="https://tthub.io/"
                     >https://tthub.io/</ref>, a hub of tutorials, presentations and materials in
                  Spanish related to TEI training, or the bilingual Taxonomy of Digital Research
                  Activities in the Humanities/Taxonomía sobre Actividades de investigación digital
                  en humanidades (TaDiRAH): <ref
                     target="https://vocabularyserver.com/tadirah/es/index.php"
                     >https://vocabularyserver.com/tadirah/es/index.php</ref>. </note> English is
               typically assumed to be the language of global communication, playing an important
               role in both disseminating and seeking out information. As Ana Balula and Delfim Leão
               argue, <quote rend="inline">In terms of information availability, which underpins the
                  co-construction of knowledge, the use of English as lingua franca promotes the
                  dissemination of research outputs and breakthroughs</quote>
               <ptr target="#balula2019" loc="4"/>. Nonetheless, Ángela Giglia highlights the more
               localized nature of humanities discourse: <quote rend="inline">SSH [Social Sciences
                  and Humanities] research is often grounded in specific cultural or geographical
                  areas, hence the persistence of native languages opposed to English as lingua
                  franca in STEM [science, technology, engineering, and mathematics]</quote>
               <ptr target="#giglia2019" loc="143"/>. Multilingualism and bibliodiversity, or the
               diversity of academic content, are essential both at the national and international
               levels to preserve research in a wide range of global and local topics, studied from
               different epistemic and methodological approaches and inspired by various schools of
               thought and expressed in a variety of languages <ptr target="#balula2019"/>. </p>
            <p>We conduct shared lectures and communication between students in each group in
               English but facilitate learning and project work by providing bilingual course
               material. Because language is a primary medium in the transmission of culture and
               ideas, we also assign readings in both languages, trying to find papers that deal
               with similar topics and allowing students to choose between them <ptr
                  target="#allestorrent2020"/>.<note> In fact, Argentinian students learn
                  differently from the U.S.-based students in the course, as they go through a
                  two-fold process: they learn new digital humanities concepts and practices related
                  to minimal computing and DSEs while they improve or practice their English
                  language skills. </note> This is meant to both facilitate content acquisition and
               expose students to contributions that are not exclusively Anglo-centric when learning
               about digital humanities and DSEs in particular.<note> We use recommendations from
                  the GO::DH Translation Toolkit: the <soCalled>whispering</soCalled> approach <ptr
                     target="#gil2016b"/>, translating and writing down (on a whiteboard or in a
                  chat) the keywords, titles, and words we may identify as obscure. The Translation
                  Toolkit is available at <ref
                     target="https://go-dh.github.io/translation-toolkit/about/"
                     >https://go-dh.github.io/translation-toolkit/about/</ref>. </note> Moreover, we
               have seen that exposure to both languages enhances the virtual exchange
                  experience;<note> Multilingualism and cross-institutional experience was
                  informally identified by University of Maryland students as a major reason for
                  enrolling in the course. Moreover, a survey conducted by Universidad del Salvador
                  students about their own experience also mentioned positive assessments of the
                  multilingual approach to the course <ptr target="#calarco2021a"/>. </note> in
               addition to learning from bilingual resources, the groups create bilingual websites
               and work with source material in both languages. In adopting this strategy, we are
               following UNESCO’s report on intercultural competences: </p>
            <p><quote rend="block">Multilingualism (communicative competence in multiple languages)
                  and translation (conveying the same idea through different languages) are [...]
                  requirements for intercultural dialogue, and indications of intercultural
                  competences, enriching each group’s understanding of the other(s) as well of
                  themselves. <ptr target="#unesco2013"/></quote></p>
            <p>In preparing bilingual materials for the course, we kept these principles in mind and
               invested time in creating resources that would be useful outside of the immediate
               course context. To date, our primary contribution has been translating Amanda
               Visconti’s Jekyll tutorial on the <title rend="italic">Programming Historian</title>
               into Spanish.<note> The original Programming Historian tutorial in English is
                  available at <ref
                     target="https://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages"
                     >https://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages</ref>.
                  The Spanish translation is available at <ref
                     target="https://programminghistorian.org/es/lecciones/sitios-estaticos-con-jekyll-y-github-pages"
                     >https://programminghistorian.org/es/lecciones/sitios-estaticos-con-jekyll-y-github-pages</ref>.
               </note> This translation not only involved lexical and grammatical choices but also
               extralinguistic adaptations such as changing the screenshots. This decision was
               motivated not only by the presence of text in English in the images but also by the
               layout differences between the macOS and Microsoft Windows. The original tutorial is
               based on macOS and is infrequently used by Latin American students because of the
               elevated price of Apple computers. In order to make the tutorial accessible to our
               public, we provided priority to installation instructions for Windows and reproduced
               all the visual aids for a Windows environment.<note> The translation labor related to
                  digital humanities tutorials or educational resources always involves a situated
                  approach. As Allés-Torrent and de Rio Rande note of TEI materials, <quote
                     rend="inline">It is not enough for the Spanish-speaking community to translate
                     [these texts], since it is necessary to re-create the problems and adapt
                     existing materials to their own needs and examples</quote>
                  <ptr target="#allestorrent2020" loc="13"/>. </note> We also created an extension
               to the free code editor Visual Studio Code, called Scholarly XML,<note> Scholarly XML
                  is available at <ref
                     target="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=raffazizzi.sxml"
                     >https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=raffazizzi.sxml</ref>.</note>
               that provides functionalities essential to learning and encoding TEI, such as XML
               validation and code completion suggestions. Despite their function in TEI pedagogy,
               these features typically require complex installation or are otherwise only available
               through commercial software.<note> Other extensions for Visual Studio Code or for
                  other free code editors typically require Java tools to be installed to access XML
                  validation and code completion. We found this to be an obstacle when teaching TEI
                  with a minimal computing approach and thus developed an alternative that works
                  within Visual Studio Code without needing additional tools.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Since the majority of minimal computing aspects of the course are centered around
               project-based learning (PBL), we conclude this section by describing how we
               scaffolded the course activities through Joseph Krajcik and Phyllis Blumenfeld’s five
               key features of project-based learning <ptr target="#krajcik2005"/>. The first
               feature is identifying a driving question that relates to authentic activities
               undertaken by researchers in digital humanities (more specifically in digital textual
               scholarship), such as, <quote rend="inline">How do websites help us give new life to
                  historical texts?</quote> Second, we explore the driving question via <quote
                  rend="inline">situated learning</quote>
               <ptr target="#lave1991"/> — that is, by working in a real-world context. Minimal
               technologies for building websites allow our students to learn by doing with tools
               that make it feasible to engage with the driving question, but that are also used by
               professionals to develop open digital humanities artifacts. The third feature is
               engaging in collaborative activities to solve problems; students tackle the question
               and learn skills in groups made of individuals from both institutions, which, as
               explained above, is essential to the development of intercultural competences. The
               fourth feature recommends that PBL be <quote rend="inline">scaffolded with learning
                  technologies that help [students] participate in activities normally beyond their
                  ability</quote>
               <ptr target="#krajcik2005" loc="318"/>. In our case these technologies include
               bilingual learning materials and online collaboration channels that we establish
               together with the students’ input. While minimal computing technologies should, by
               definition, be within the students’ ability, our goal is to have the students
               leverage these technologies to answer the driving question and engage with textual
               scholarship work that will likely be unfamiliar to them. Finally, the fifth feature
               is that students create artifacts that address the driving question and that are
                  <quote rend="inline">publicly accessible representations of the class’s
                  learning</quote>
               <ptr target="#krajcik2005" loc="318"/>. Through structured assignments, each group
               creates a bilingual public website containing the encoded and edited text, together
               with paratextual content documenting their collaborative process and their engagement
               with the driving question.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusions</head>
            <p>In designing this course, we have had the unique opportunity to bring together
               digital humanities and humanidades digitales practices from the Global North and
               South. This joint effort has prompted us to reflect on what is common and shareable
               in our approach to digital scholarly editing: how, and in what ways, is knowledge
               exchanged in different cultural, linguistic, and technological literacies? </p>
            <p>Minimal computing, understood not just as a response to technological constraints,
               but rather as an intentional methodological stance, strikes us as fundamental for
               building a shared commons that is both open and global. Moreover, we are building a
               bilingual syllabus (readings, tools, and project-based learning activities) centered
               on minimal computing as a way of countering epistemic and knowledge inequity <ptr
                  target="#chan2019"/>. Our work purposely moves beyond a North-to-South approach to
               curriculum and knowledge exchange to a synergetic North-and-South one, aimed at
               empowering knowledge creation in the language(s) in which an individual is most
               comfortable.</p>
            <p>We are aware that minimal computing, and to some extent project-based learning, are
               approaches developed in the North, and adopting them under the guise of an
               internationalization agenda brings risks, such as overlooking local practices when
               building and sharing knowledge in the classroom. We are also conscious that while
               technology can increase access to knowledge, it may entrench cultural imperialism.
               Nonetheless, we envision a middle ground by adapting tutorials and educational
               materials, as well as balancing Spanish and Anglophone authors in the bibliographies
               students should be reading. In this sense, our course emphasizes a pedagogy of
               multiliteracies and a polycentric digital humanities perspective.</p>
            <p>The first iteration of the course in 2020 concluded successfully, with an enrollment
               of 23 students (11 at UMD and 12 at USAL). After the course, USAL students continued
               to collaborate through presentations on their experiences with minimal computing at
               different events, including a presentation <ptr target="#calarco2021a"/> at <title
                  rend="italic">#NoviembreHD</title>, a one-month congress organized by the
               Argentine Association of Digital Humanities (AAHD) <ptr target="#noviembrehd2020"/>,
               and a poster at the Global Digital Humanities Symposium, organized by the University
               of Michigan <ptr target="#calarco2021b"/>. Several students also started their own
               digital publishing projects with the technologies they learned.<note> Cristian Suárez
                  Giraldo started a digital edition of a 19th century Colombian text, available at
                     <ref target="https://suarezg106.gitlab.io/conversacion-eafit/"
                     >https://suarezg106.gitlab.io/conversacion-eafit/</ref>. Gabriel Calarco
                  developed a digital edition of a Hispanic medieval text, available at <ref
                     target="https://github.com/gabrielcalarco/-Ecfrasis-en-el-Libro-de-Alexandre"
                     >https://github.com/gabrielcalarco/-Ecfrasis-en-el-Libro-de-Alexandre</ref>.
               </note> This is evidence that the course is not only creating a favorable environment
               for collaboration and exchange, but also is providing participants with the tools for
               independent work in the field of digital scholarly editing.</p>
            <p>By preparing for this course, we not only developed training on specific minimal
               computing and text encoding skills, but we also engaged with different technological
               and academic contexts around the world by addressing issues and perspectives related
               to infrastructure, language, digital literacy, and Open Science. Our continued
               challenge is uncovering how our work teaching minimal computing can effectively
               advance a more open and global digital humanities. We aim at moving beyond the limits
               of the course itself, by upholding approaches to pedagogy and digital humanities
               research that work towards what we claim should be a core tenet for the global
               digital humanities community: that technology should be owned by no one and used and
               contributed to by all.</p>
         </div>


      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="allestorrent2016" label="Allés-Torrent 2016"> Allés-Torrent, Susanna.
                  <title rend="quotes">Crear una edición mínima con Jekyll y GitHub Pages.</title> I
               Congreso Internacional. Humanidades Digitales. Construcciones locales en contextos
               globales. November 8, 2016. <ref
                  target="https://susannalles.github.io/workshops/edicion-con-Jekyll.html"
                  >https://susannalles.github.io/workshops/edicion-con-Jekyll.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="allestorrent2020" label="Allés-Torrent and del Rio Riande 2020">
               Allés-Torrent, Susanna and del Rio Riande, Gimena. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Switchover: Teaching and Learning the Text Encoding Initiative in Spanish.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title> 12 (2020). <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.4000/jtei.2994"
               >https://doi.org/10.4000/jtei.2994</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="amarante2016" label="Amarante et al. 2016"> Amarante, Verónica, Marco
               Galván and Xavier Mancero. <title rend="quotes">Inequality in Latin America: A Global
                  Measurement.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Cepal Reviews</title> 118 (2016). <ref
                  target="https://www.cepal.org/en/publications/40423-inequality-latin-america-global-measurement"
                  >https://cepal.org/en/publications/40423-inequality-latin-america-global-measurement</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="balula2019" label="Balula and Leão 2019"> Balula, Ana and Delfim Leão.
                  <title rend="quotes">Is Multilingualism Seen as Added-value in
                  Bibliodiversity?</title> In <title rend="italic">ELPUB 2019 23rd edition of the
                  International Conference on Electronic Publishing</title>. Marseille, France,
               2019. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.4000/proceedings.elpub.2019.17"
                  >https://doi.org/10.4000/proceedings.elpub.2019.17</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bassani2019" label="Bassani and Buchem 2019"> Bassani, Patrícia Scherer
               and Ilona Buchem. <title rend="quotes">Virtual Exchanges in Higher Education:
                  Developing Intercultural Skills of Students Across Borders Through Online
                  Collaboration.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Revista Interuniversitaria de Investigación en Tecnología
                  Educativa</title> 6 (2019). <ref target="https://doi.org/10.6018/riite.377771"
                  >https://doi.org/10.6018/riite.377771</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bodard2009" label="Bodard and Garcés 2009"> Bodard, Gabriel and Juan
               Garcés. <title rend="quotes">Open Source Critical Editions: A Rationale.</title> In
                  <title rend="italic">Text Editing, Print, and the Digital World</title>, edited by
               Marilyn Deegan and Kathryn Sutherland, 83–98. London, NY: Ashgate Press, 2009. <ref
                  target="https://blog.stoa.org/files/2010/09/Bodard-Garces_2009_Open-source-digital-editions.pdf"
                  >https://blog.stoa.org/files/2010/09/Bodard-Garces_2009_Open-source-digital-editions.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="berlin2003" label="Berlin 2003"> Berlin Declaration. Accessed May 12,
               2022. <ref target="https://openaccess.mpg.de/Berlin-Declaration"
                  >https://openaccess.mpg.de/Berlin-Declaration</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bethesda2003" label="Bethesda 2003"> Bethesda Statement on Open Access
               Publishing. Accessed May 12, 2022. <ref
                  target="http://legacy.earlham.edu/~peters/fos/bethesda.htm"
                  >http://legacy.earlham.edu/~peters/fos/bethesda.htm</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="budapest2002" label="Budapest 2002"> Budapest Open Access Initiative.
               Accessed May 12, 2022. <ref
                  target="https://www.budapestopenaccessinitiative.org/read"
                  >https://www.budapestopenaccessinitiative.org/read</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="burdick2012" label="Burdick et al. 2012"> Burdick, Anne, Johanna Drucker,
               Peter Lunenfeld, Todd Presner and Jeffrey Schnapp. <title rend="italic"
                  >Digital_Humanities</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="calarco2021a" label="Calarco et al. 2021a"> Calarco, Gabriel Alejandro,
               Pamela Gionco, Rocío Luciana Méndez, David Merino Recalde, Gabriela Elizabeth Striker
               and Christian Suárez Giraldo. <title rend="quotes">Digital Publishing with Minimal
                  Computing (UMD-USAL, 2020): Nuestra Experiencia Como Estudiantes.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Zenodo</title>, 2021. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5519564"
                  >https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5519564.</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="calarco2021b" label="Calarco et al. 2021b"> Calarco, Gabriel Alejandro,
               Iñaki Cano García, Pamela Gionco, Rocío Méndez, David Merino Recalde, Federico Sardi,
               Maria Alejandra Sotelo, Gabriela Striker and Cristian Suárez-Giraldo. <title
                  rend="quotes">El mismo texto, diferentes ediciones digitales. Resultados y
                  experiencias de estudiantes de ‘Digital Publishing with Minimal
                  Computing/Ediciones digitales con minimal computing-Global Classrooms
                  (UMD/USAL)’.</title>
               <ref target="http://2021.msuglobaldh.org/abstracts/#mismo-texto"
                  >http://2021.msuglobaldh.org/abstracts/#mismo-texto</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="canagarajah2002" label="Canagarajah 2002"> Canagarajah, A. Suresh. <title
                  rend="italic">A Geopolitics of Academic Writing</title>. Pittsburgh: University of
               Pittsburgh Press, 2002. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cayless2018" label="Cayless and Viglianti 2018"> Cayless, Hugh and
               Raffaele Viglianti. <title rend="quotes">CETEIcean: TEI in the Browser.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Balisage: The Markup Conference</title>, Washington, DC, 2018.
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.4242/BalisageVol21.Cayless01"
                  >https://doi.org/10.4242/BalisageVol21.Cayless01</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chan2019" label="Chan et al 2019"> Chan, Leslie, Angela Okune, Rebecca
               Hillyer, Denisse Albornoz and Alejandro Posada. <title rend="italic">Contextualizing
                  Openness : Situating Open Science</title>. Ottawa: University of Ottawa Press,
               2019.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="clement2012" label="Clement 2012"> Clement, Tanya. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Multiliteracies in the Undergraduate Digital Humanities Curriculum: Skills,
                  Principles, and Habits of Mind.</title> In <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                  Pedagogy: Practices, Principles and Politics</title>, edited by Brett D. Hirsch,
               365–388. Cambridge, UK: Open Book Publishers, 2012. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0024"
               >https://doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0024</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="conghuyen2013" label="Cong-Huyen 2013"> Cong Huyen, Anne. <title
                  rend="quotes">#CESA2013: Race in DH – Transformative Asian/American Digital
                  Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Anne Cong-Huyen</title>, September 24, 2013. <ref
                  target="https://anitaconchita.org/uncategorized/cesa2013-race-in-dh-transformative-asianamerican-digital-humanities/"
                  >https://anitaconchita.org/uncategorized/cesa2013-race-in-dh-transformative-asianamerican-digital-humanities/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cope2009" label="Cope and Kalantzis 2009"> Cope, Bill and Kalantzis, Mary.
                  <title rend="quotes">‘Multiliteracies’: New Literacies, New Learning.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Pedagogies: An International Journal</title> vol. 4.3 (2009):
               164–195. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dacos2010" label="Dacos 2010"> Dacos, Marin. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Manifesto for the Digital Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Hypotheses</title>, March 11, 2011. <ref
                  target="https://tcp.hypotheses.org/411"
               >https://tcp.hypotheses.org/411</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="delrioriande2015" sortKey="DelRioRiande2015" label="del Rio Riande 2015">
               Riande, Gimena del Rio. <title rend="quotes">¿De qué hablamos cuando hablamos de
                  Humanidades Digitales?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Actas I Jornadas de Humanidades Digitales de la AAHD.
                  Humanidades Digitales: Tecnologías, Culturas, Saberes </title>(2014): 50-62.
               Editorial de la Facultad de Filosofía y Letras: Buenos Aires. <ref
                  target="https://www.aacademica.org/jornadasaahd/3.pdf"
                  >https://aacademica.org/jornadasaahd/3.pdf.</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="delrioriande2018" sortKey="DelRioRiande2018"
               label="del Rio Riande et al. 2018"> del Rio Riande, Gimena, Gabriel Calarco, Gabriela
               Striker and Romina De León. Humanidades Digitales: Construcciones locales en
               contextos globales. Editorial de la Facultad de Filosofía y Letras: Buenos Aires,
               2018. <ref target="https://www.aacademica.org/aahd.congreso/tabs/proceedings"
                  >https://.aacademica.org/aahd.congreso/tabs/proceedings</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="delrioriande2019" sortKey="DelRioRiande2019"
               label="del Rio Riande and Tóth-Czifra 2019"> del Rio Riande, Gimena and Erzsébet
               Tóth-Czifra. "El metablog OpenMethods o cómo abrir la investigación en Humanidades
               Digitales." Hipertext.net 19 (2019): 55-65. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="earhart2012" label="Earhart 2012"> Earhart, Amy E. <title rend="quotes"
                  >The Digital Edition and the Digital Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Textual Cultures.</title> vol. 7.1 (2012): 18–28. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.2979/textcult.7.1.18"
                  >https://doi.org/10.2979/textcult.7.1.18</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="earhart2018" label="Earhart 2018"> Earhart, Amy E. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Digital Humanities Within a Global Context: Creating Borderlands of Localized
                  Expression.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Fudan Journal of the Humanities and Social Sciences</title> vol.
               11.3 (2018): 357–369.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fiormonte2017a" label="Fiormonte 2017"> Fiormonte, Domenico. <title
                  rend="quotes">Digital Humanities and the Geopolitics of Knowledge.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Studies/Le Champ Numérique</title> Vol. 7.1 (2017). <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.274"
               >https://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.274</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fiormonte2017b" label="Fiormonte and del Rio Riande 2017"> Fiormonte,
               Domenico and Gimena del Rio Riande . <title rend="quotes">Por unas Humanidades
                  Digitales globales.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Infolet</title> 10, October 9, 2017. <ref
                  target="https://infolet.it/2017/10/09/humanidades-digitales-globales"
                  >https://infolet.it/2017/10/09/humanidades-digitales-globales</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fiormonte2016" label="Fiormonte and Priego 2016"> Fiormonte, Domenico and
               Priego, Ernesto. <title rend="quotes">Knowledge Monopolies and Global Academic
                  Publishing.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Winnower,</title> August 26, 2016. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.15200/winn.147220.00404"
                  >https://doi.org/10.15200/winn.147220.00404</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fitzpatrick2010" label="Fitzpatrick 2010"> Fitzpatrick, Kathleen. <title
                  rend="quotes">Reporting from the Digital Humanities 2010 Conference.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education,</title> July 13, 2010. <ref
                  target="https://www.chronicle.com/blogs/profhacker/reporting-from-the-digital-humanities-2010-conference?bc_nonce=tf4f67u5418qnfo3df0aqm&amp;cid=reg_wall_signup"
                  >https://www.chronicle.com/blogs/profhacker/reporting-from-the-digital-humanities-2010-conference?bc_nonce=tf4f67u5418qnfo3df0aqm&amp;cid=reg_wall_signup</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="foster2021" label="FOSTER 2021">
               <title rend="quotes">Open Science, Definition.</title>
               <title rend="italic">FOSTER</title>. Accessed April 2, 2022. <ref
                  target="https://www.fosteropenscience.eu/foster-taxonomy/open-science-definition"
                  >https://www.fosteropenscience.eu/foster-taxonomy/open-science-definition</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="giglia2019" label="Giglia 2019"> Giglia, Elena. <title rend="quotes"
                  >OPERAS: bringing the long tail of Social Sciences and Humanities into Open
                  Science.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Italian Journal of Library and Information Science</title> vol.
               10.1 (2019): 140−156. <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.4403/jlis.it-12523"
                  >http://dx.doi.org/10.4403/jlis.it-12523. </ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gil2015" label="Gil 2015"> Gil, Alex. <title rend="quotes">The User, the
                  Learner and the Machines We Make.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Minimal Computing Working Group,</title> May 21, 2015. <ref
                  target="https://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2015/05/21/user-vs-learner/"
                  >https://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2015/05/21/user-vs-learner/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gil2016a" label="Gil 2016"> Gil, Alex. <title rend="quotes">Interview with
                  Ernesto Oroza.</title> In <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities
                  2016</title>, edited by Matthew K. Gold and Lauren F. Klein, 184-193. Minneapolis:
               University of Minnesota Press, 2016. <ref
                  target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/65be1a40-6473-4d9e-ba75-6380e5a72138/section/f2df3413-259e-46fe-9982-f1dba0c386fb#ch16"
                  >https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/65be1a40-6473-4d9e-ba75-6380e5a72138/section/f2df3413-259e-46fe-9982-f1dba0c386fb#ch16</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gil2016b" label="Gil and Ortega 2016"> Gil, Alex and Ortega, Élika. <title
                  rend="quotes">Global Outlooks in Digital Humanities: Multilingual Practices and
                  Minimal Computing.</title> In <title rend="italic">Doing Digital Humanities
                  Practice, Training, Research</title>, edited by Constance Crompton, Richard J.
               Lane, and Ray Siemens, 22−34. London: Routledge, 2016.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="guth2013" label="Guth 2013"> Guth, Sarah. <title rend="quotes">The COIL
                  Institute for Globally Networked Learning in the Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">SUNY - COIL Center-SUNY Research Foundation</title>, 2013. <ref
                  target="http://coil.suny.edu/sites/default/files/case_study_report.pdf"
                  >http://coil.suny.edu/sites/default/files/case_study_report.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hannesschlager2020" label="Hannesschläger 2020"> Hannesschläger, Vanessa.
                  <title rend="quotes">Common Creativity International: CC-licensing and Other
                  Options for TEI-based Digital Editions in an International Context.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title> 11 (2020). <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.4000/jtei.2610"
               >https://doi.org/10.4000/jtei.2610</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hess2007" label="Hess and Ostrom 2006"> Hess, Charlotte and Elinor Ostrom,
               eds. <title rend="italic">Understanding Knowledge as a Commons: From Theory to
                  Practice.</title> Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="krajcik2005" label="Krajcik and Blumenfeld 2005"> Krajcik, Joseph and
               Blumenfeld, Phyllis. <title rend="quotes">Project-Based Learning.</title> In <title
                  rend="italic">The Cambridge Handbook of the Learning Sciences,</title> edited by
               R. Keith Sawyer, 317–334. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press, 2005. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511816833.020"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511816833.020</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="knochelmann2019" label="Knöchelmann 2019"> Knöchelmann, Marcel. <title
                  rend="quotes">Open Science in the Humanities, or: Open Humanities?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Publications</title> 7 (2019): 65-81.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="krull2016" label="Krull 2016"> Sebastian, Krull. <title rend="italic">El
                  cambio tecnológico y el nuevo contexto del empleo Tendencias generales y en
                  América Latina</title>. Santiago de Chile, Comisión Económica para América Latina
               y el Caribe (CEPAL), 2016.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lave1991" label="Lave and Wenger 1991"> Lave, Jane and Wenger, Etienne.
                  <title rend="italic">Situated Learning: Legitimate Peripheral Participation.
               </title>Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press, 1991.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="li2013" label="Li 2013"> Li, Yulong. <title rend="quotes">Cultivating
                  Student Global Competence: A Pilot Experimental Study.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Decision Sciences Journal of Innovative Education</title> vol.
               11.1 (2013): 125–143. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="workinggroup2021" label="Minimal Computing Working Group"> Minimal
               Computing Working Group. <title rend="quotes">About.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Minimal Computing: A Working Group of GO::DH</title>. Accessed
               April 2, 2022. <ref target="https://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/about/"
                  >https://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/about/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="newlondongroup1996" label="New London Group 1996"> The New London Group.
                  <title rend="quotes">A Pedagogy of Multiliteracies: De- signing Social
                  Futures.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Harvard Educational Review</title> vol. 66.1 (1996):
               60–93.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="noviembrehd2020" label="Noviembre HD 2020"> Noviembre HD. Asociación
               Argentina de Humanidades Digitales, November 5-30, 2020. Buenos Aires, Argentina.
                  <ref target="https://www.aacademica.org/noviembrehd"
                  >https://www.aacademica.org/noviembrehd</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="odonnell2016" label="O’Donnell et al. 2016"> O’Donnell, Daniel Paul,
               Barbara Bordalejo, Padmini Ray Murray, Gimena del Rio Riande and Elena
               González-Blanco Garcia. <title rend="quotes">Boundary Land as a Defining Feature of
                  the Digital Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2016 Book of Abstracts</title>, 76–82.
               Krakow: Jagiellonian University and Pedagogical University, 2016. <ref
                  target="http://dh2016.adho.org/abstracts/406"
                  >http://dh2016.adho.org/abstracts/406</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="odown2018" label="O’Down 2018"> O’Dowd, Robert. <title rend="quotes">From
                  Telecollaboration to Virtual Exchange: State-of-the-art and the Role of
                  UNICollaboration in Moving Forward.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Virtual eExchange</title> 1 (2018): 1–23. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="okune2016" label="Okune 2016"> Okune, Angela, Becky Hillyer, Denisse
               Albornoz, Nanjira Sambuli and Leslie Chan. <title rend="quotes">Tackling Inequities
                  in Global Scientific Power Structures.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The African Technopolitan</title> vol. 4.1 (2016). <ref
                  target="https://tspace.library.utoronto.ca/handle/1807/71107"
                  >https://tspace.library.utoronto.ca/handle/1807/71107</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="padilla2017" label="Padilla 2017"> Padilla, Margarita. <title
                  rend="quotes">Soberanía tecnológica ¿De qué estamos hablando?</title> In <title
                  rend="italic">Soberanía tecnológica</title>, Vol. 2, edited by Alex Haché, 3-15.
               Barcelona: Descontrol, 2017. <ref
                  target="https://ritimo.org/IMG/pdf/sobtech2-es-with-covers-web-150dpi-2018-01-13-v2.pdf"
                  >https://ritimo.org/IMG/pdf/sobtech2-es-with-covers-web-150dpi-2018-01-13-v2.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pierazzo2016" label="Pierazzo 2016"> Pierazzo, Elena. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Modelling Digital Scholarly Editing: From Plato to Heraclitus.</title> In <title
                  rend="italic">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories and Practices</title>, edited by
               Elena Perazzo and Matthew Driscoll, 41–58. Cambridge, UK: Open Book Publishers, 2016.
                  https://<ref target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1fzhh6v.7"
                  >jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1fzhh6v.7</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pierazzo2019" label="Pierazzo 2019"> Pierazzo, Elena. <title rend="quotes"
                  >What Futures for Digital Scholarly Editions? From Haute Couture to
                  Prêt-à-Porter.</title>
               <title rend="italic">International Journal of Digital Humanities</title> vol. 1.2
               (2019): 209–220. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s42803-019-00019-3"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1007/s42803-019-00019-3</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="presner2009" label="Presner 2009"> Presner, Todd. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Digital Humanities Manifesto 2.0 Launched.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Todd Presner</title>, June 22, 2009. <ref
                  target="http://www.toddpresner.com/?p=7">http://toddpresner.com/?p=7</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="recogito2021" label="Recogito 2021">
               <title rend="italic">Recogito</title>. Accessed April 2, 2022. <ref
                  target="https://github.com/pelagios/recogito2"
                  >https://github.com/pelagios/recogito2</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="risam2018" label="Risam 2018"> Risam, Roopika. <title rend="italic">New
                  Digital Worlds</title>.<title rend="italic"> Postcolonial Digital Humanities in
                  Theory, Praxis, and Pedagogy</title>. Evanston, IL: Northwestern University Press,
               2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sahle2016" label="Sahle 2016"> Sahle, Patrick. <title rend="quotes">What
                  is a Scholarly Digital Edition?</title> In <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarly
                  Editing: Theories and Practices</title>, edited by Elena Perazzo and Matthew
               Driscoll, 19–40. Cambridge, UK: Open Book Publishers, 2016. <ref
                  target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1fzhh6v.6"
                  >https://jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1fzhh6v.6</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shelleygodwinarchive2021" label="Shelley-Godwin Archive 2021">
               <title rend="italic">The Shelley-Godwin Archive</title>. Accessed April 2, 2022. <ref
                  target="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/">http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schallier2018" label="Schallier et al. 2018"> Schallier, Wouter, Gimena
               del Rio Riande, Daniel O’Donnell and April Hathcock. <title rend="quotes">Where is
                  the Open in DH.</title>
               <title rend="italic">DH2018</title>. Accessed October 16, 2021. <ref
                  target="https://dh2018.adho.org/en/where-is-the-open-in-dh/"
                  >https://dh2018.adho.org/en/where-is-the-open-in-dh/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="spiro2012" label="Spiro 2012"> Spiro, Lisa. <title rend="quotes">‘This Is
                  Why We Fight’: Defining the Value of the Digital Humanities.</title> In <title
                  rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, edited by Matthew K.
               Gold, 16–35. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2012. <ref
                  target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled-88c11800-9446-469b-a3be-3fdb36bfbd1e/section/9e014167-c688-43ab-8b12-0f6746095335"
                  >https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled-88c11800-9446-469b-a3be-3fdb36bfbd1e/section/9e014167-c688-43ab-8b12-0f6746095335</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="summers2016" label="Summers 2016"> Summers, Ed. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Web’s Past is Not Evenly Distributed.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities</title>, May
               27, 2016. <ref target="https://mith.umd.edu/webs-past-not-evenly-distributed"
                  >https://mith.umd.edu/webs-past-not-evenly-distributed</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="svensson2016" label="Svensson 2016"> Svensson, Patrik. <title
                  rend="quotes">Sorting out the Digital Humanities.</title> In <title rend="italic"
                  >A New Companion to Digital Humanities</title>, edited by Susan Schreibman, Ray
               Siemens, and John Unsworth, 476–492. Chichester, UK: John Wiley and Sons,
               2016.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tennant2015" label="Tennant and Mounce 2015"> Tennant, John and Ross
               Mounce. <title rend="quotes">Open Research Glossary (Version 1).</title>
               <title rend="italic">figshare</title>, July 14, 2015. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.1482094.v1"
                  >https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.1482094.v1</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="unesco2013" label="UNESCO et al. 2013"> UNESCO, Wendy Leeds-Hurwitz and
               Katerina Stenou. <title rend="italic">Intercultural Competences: Conceptual and
                  Operational Framework</title>, 2013. <ref
                  target="https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000219768"
                  >https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000219768</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="viglianti2018" label="Viglianti 2018"> Viglianti, Raffaele. <title
                  rend="quotes">Using Static Sites Technology for Increased Access: The Case of the
                  Shelley-Godwin Archive.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Design for Diversity Learning Toolkit</title>, 2018. <ref
                  target="https://des4div.library.northeastern.edu/shelley-godwin-archive/"
                  >https://des4div.library.northeastern.edu/shelley-godwin-archive/</ref>.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
