<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">The Stylometry of Film Dialogue: Pros and
               Pitfalls</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Agata <dhq:family>Hołobut</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Jagiellonian University in Kraków</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>agata.holobut@uj.edu.p</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Agata Hołobut is an associate professor at the Institute of English Studies, Jagiellonian University in Kraków. Her main areas of interest include literary and audiovisual translation, as well as visual arts and cognitive semiotics. She has written several papers on film dialogue, literary, audiovisual, and intersemiotic translation, and published, together with Monika Woźniak and Jan Rybicki, a monograph <title rend="italic">Historia na ekranie: Gatunek filmowy a przekład audiowizualny</title> (<title rend="quotes">History on Screen: Film Genre in Audiovisual Translation,</title> 2017).</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Jan <dhq:family>Rybicki</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Jagiellonian University in Kraków</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>jan.rybicki@uj.edu.pl</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Jan Rybicki is an associate professor at the Institute of English Studies, Jagiellonian University in Kraków. With a background in English literary studies, comparative literature and translation studies, he has published on stylometry in translation (<title rend="quotes">The Great Mystery of the (Almost) Invisible Translator: Stylometry in Translation</title>), authorship attribution (<title rend="quotes">Partners in Life, Partners in Crime?</title>) and gender (<title rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">Vive la différence</hi>: Tracing the (Authorial) Gender Signal by Multivariate Analysis of Word Frequencies</title>). His latest papers include attributive work on Harper Lee and Elena Ferrante. He helped write the <hi rend="italic">stylo</hi> package for R. A literary translator in his previous lifetime, he translated into Polish such authors as Golding, Gordimer, Fitzgerald, Ishiguro or le Carré</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000498</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               >014</idno>
            <idno type="issue">4</idno>
            <date when="2020-12-20">20 December 2020</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change who="BRG" when="2022-07-29">updated and added bibl elements</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>We examine film dialogue with quantitative textual analysis (stylometry, sentiment
               analysis, distant reading). Working with transcribed dialogue in almost 300
               productions, we explore the complex way in which most-frequent-words-based stylometry
               and lexicon-based sentiment analysis produce patterns of similarity and difference
               between screenwriters and/or a priori IMDB-defined genres. In fact, some of our
               results show that counting and comparing very frequent word lists reveals further
               similarities: of theme, implied audience, stylistic patternings. The results are
               encouraging enough to suggest that such quantitative approach to film dialogue may
               become a welcome addition to the arsenal of film studies methodology. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>Examines quantitative methods for anlayzing film dialogue</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Film dialogue</head>
            <p>Although dialogue has been integral to film structure since the introduction of sound
               in the 1920s and used in silent film intertitles at least since 1904 <ptr
                  target="#kozloff2000" loc="20"/>
               <ptr target="#pitera1979"/>, it has garnered relatively little attention from film
               scholars. Stylistic immaturity and technical imperfections of the first talkies made
               early theorists, such as Rudolf Arnheim, Sergei Eisenstein or Siegfried Krakauer
               bemoan the loss of artistry inherent to silent films <ptr target="#kozloff2000"
                  loc="7"/> and encouraged others to describe the compositional complexity of the
               new invention in contrast to its silent, though hardly wordless, predecessor <ptr
                  target="#hendrykowski1999"/>. Still, as Sarah Kozloff argues in her
               ground-breaking monograph <title rend="italic">Overhearing Film Dialogue</title>
               (2000), Western film scholarship has long been marked by <q> verbo-immunity</q> or
               even <q>verbophobia</q> in its approach to cinematic art, privileging the visual over
               the auditory and the non-verbal over the verbal: <cit><quote rend="block">Although
                     what the characters say, how they actually say it, and how the dialogue is
                     integrated with the rest of the cinematic techniques are crucial to our
                     experience and understanding of every film since the coming of sound, for the
                     most part analysts incorporate the information provided by a film’s dialogue
                     and overlook the dialogue as signifier. Canonical textbooks on film aesthetics
                     devote pages and pages to editing and cinematography but rarely mention
                     dialogue. Visual analysis requires mastery of a recondite vocabulary and
                     trained attentiveness; dialogue has been perceived as too transparent, too
                     simple to need study</quote>
                  <ptr target="#kozloff2000" loc="6"/></cit></p>
            <p>This apparent disregard may have stemmed from a number of reasons, one of them being
               a deeply-grounded belief in the autonomy of various art forms. Scholars intent on
               presenting film as primarily a visual medium deemed dialogue negligible, because they
               considered it too closely related to other forms of expression, such as stage drama
               or prose-writing and hence unspecific to cinema <ptr target="#piazza2011" loc="8"/>.
               Film talk, however, differs considerably from verbal exchanges intended for the page
               or for the stage, as it is always affected by performers’ interpretive choices and
               the <quote rend="inline">simultaneous signification of
                  camerawork/mise-en-scene/editing</quote>
               <ptr target="#kozloff2000" loc="16"/>. It is an integral element of fiction film and,
               as Sarah Kozloff argues, it performs unique narrative functions: (1) it anchors the
               diegesis and the characters, (2) it explains causal links between events presented
               onscreen, (3) it enacts narrative events, such as professing feelings, setting up
               deadlines or passing sentences, (4) it reveals the characters’ personalities, (5) it
               controls the viewers’ emotional and axiological reactions and (6) it helps create the
               impression of realism. It also plays an important aesthetic role, exploiting the
               artistic potential of language, conveying ideological messages and giving stars an
               opportunity to show off their skills <ptr target="#kozloff2000" loc="33–4"/>. Since
               the publication of Kozloff’s book a number of film scholars have pursued her line of
               study, tracing the evolution of screenwriting styles in America, emphasizing the
               requirements of particular genres (e.g. screwball comedy, science fiction, gangster
               film, western), investigating the idiom of selected auteurs (Cassavetes, Hawks,
               Welles, Sturges) and typical verbal representations of different social groups. The
               most important contribution to the field has been arguably the collected volume
                  <title rend="italic">Film Dialogue</title> edited by Jeff Jaeckle (2013). </p>
            <p>Telecinematic dialogue has also received in-depth attention from linguists working
               within the fields of stylistics, pragmatics, sociolinguistics and discourse analysis
               (e.g. <ref target="#bobrowski2015">Bobrowski 2015</ref>; <ref target="#piazza2011"
                  >Piazza 2011</ref>; <ref target="#piazza2011a">Piazza 2011a</ref>; <ref
                  target="#richardson2010">Richardson 2010</ref>), as well as audiovisual
               translation experts interested in different techniques, strategies and modes of
               language transfer. Most research has been driven by qualitative approaches, yet
               quantitative measures have also been adopted by scholars using monolingual, as well
               as multilingual and multimedia corpora to investigate the relationship of scripted
               speech to real-life conversation, to examine the stylistics of television dialogue
               and the consistency of character identity revealed through language (e.g. <ref
                  target="#bednarek2010">Bednarek 2010</ref>; <ref target="#bednarek2011"
               >2011</ref>; <ref target="#bednarek2018">2018</ref>; <ref target="#quaglio2009"
                  >Quaglio 2009</ref>; <ref target="#zago2016">Zago 2016</ref>; <ref
                  target="#zago2018">Zago 2018</ref>), to explore verbal discourse in different film
               genres <ptr target="#verianopinto2014"/>, to analyze the sociolinguistic and
               pragmatic idiosyncrasies of interlingual dubbing (e.g. <ref target="#freddi2009"
                  >Freddi 2009</ref>; <ref target="#freddi2013">Freddi 2013</ref>) and its
               relationship to spontaneous speech (e.g. <ref target="#heiss2005">Heiss 2005</ref>;
                  <ref target="#romerofresco2009">Romero Fresco 2009</ref>) or to study interlingual
               translation in the visual context (e.g. <ref target="#valentini2006">Valentini
                  2006</ref>; <ref target="#valentini2008">2008</ref>; <ref target="#valentini2009"
                  >2009</ref>).<note>For an overview of corpus research into audiovisual
                  translation, see <ref target="#banos-pinero2013">Baños-Piñero 2013</ref>. For an
                  overview of research into scripted speech, see <ref target="#bednarek2017"
                     >Bednarek 2017</ref>. </note>
            </p>
            <p>What many of these approaches demonstrate is that film and television genres are
               characterized by distinctive language patterns; dialogues in screwball comedy,
               melodrama, western, sitcom or police procedural are endowed with genre-specific
               functions and genre-specific stylistic, pragmatic and rhetorical features (such as
               the literary stylization of classic novel adaptations, the use of slang and jargon in
               gangster films or the omnipresence of techno-bubble in science fiction). As Kozloff
               explains: <cit><quote rend="block">Partially, they [these verbal genre conventions]
                     are motivated by the subject matter. Screenwriters are always concerned that
                     dialogue be appropriate to characters’ social backgrounds, and thus
                        <q>realistic</q> (...). Partially, films are clearly copying preexisting
                     expectations created by other forms of representation (...). And partially, I
                     believe, dialogue patterns are related to the underlying gender dynamics of
                     each genre: whether the genre is primarily addressed to male or female viewers
                     and how each genre treats its male and female characters are crucial factors in
                     its use of language.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#kozloff2000" loc="137"/></cit> What some of the qualitative analyses
               (e.g. <ref target="#jaeckle2013">Jaeckle 2013</ref>; <ref
                  target="#milawskaratajczak2019">Miławska-Ratajczak 2019</ref>) also show is famous
               writer-directors' signature verbal style. All these insights have led us to believe
               that these gene- and <term>auteur</term> - specific verbal patterns, described by
               scholars and noticed by average viewers, may be further explored by stylometric
               measures. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Research objectives</head>
            <p>In our research, we decided to adopt a variety of procedures, using quantitative
               textual analysis tools derived from stylometry (a.k.a. computational stylistics) and
               from automated sentiment analysis, a significant subdiscipline of text mining. As
               these approaches rely on computational work, they allow to analyze large sets of
               texts in ways similar to distant reading <ptr target="#moretti2007"/>Moretti 2007).
               Used on diverse corpora of literary and non-literary texts, they have already proven
               helpful in plagiarism detection, authorship attribution, as well as genre- and
               diachrony research, as will be explained below. Their application to film dialogue,
               however, has so far been limited <ptr target="#mckie2014"/>
               <ptr target="#holobut2016"/>
               <ptr target="#holobut2017a"/>
               <ptr target="#vanzyl2016"/>
               <ptr target="#byszuk2017"/>
               <ptr target="#holobut2017b"/>
               <ptr target="#holobut2018"/> and it certainly merits further attention for a nuber of
               reasons. Firstly, stylometric analysis can complement other advancements in the realm
               of cinemetrics <ptr target="#baxter2014a"/>
               <ptr target="#baxter2014b"/> by bringing neglected cinematic speech to film scholars’
               attention. Secondly, it provides yet another level of potential comparison between
               film dialogue and other dialogic genres, stage drama in particular. Both theatre and
               screen plays combine literary and performative dimensions. Stage drama has already
               been analyzed in its literary dimension by qualitative and quantitative means, with
               obvious precedence to, often, heated arguments on Shakespearean authorship
               attribution (to name but a few of the latest: <ref target="#vickers2002">Vickers
                  2002</ref>; <ref target="#craig2009">Craig and Kinney 2009</ref>; <ref
                  target="#vickers2011">Vickers 2011</ref>, <ref target="#rudman2016">Rudman
                  2016</ref>). Equally obviously, this leaves the space open for the stylometry of
               filmic speech. Thirdly, stylometry and automated sentiment analysis can open new
               avenues for qualitative research, revealing <quote rend="inline">patterns overlooked
                  in close reading</quote>
               <ptr target="#hayles2010" loc="75"/>. That is why in our research we intended to test
               the usefulness of the mentioned tools in identifying the potential stylometric
               similarities or differences between film fictional dialogues, revealing regularities
               typical of a given genre, theme, historical context, writer, director- and/ or film
               cycle. In our previous studies, we focused exclusively on historical films and
               literary adaptations, combining quantitative stylometric with qualitative stylistic
               and pragmalinguistic analysis of filmic speech (cf. <ref target="#holobut2017b"
                  >Hołobut 2017b</ref>). This time, we collected a multigeneric corpus of
               transcribed dialogue lists to 278 Anglophone productions, spanning over eighty-four
               years of cinematic art (for a complete list of productions included, see <ref
                  target="#appendix01">Appendix 1</ref>), running a pilot quantitative analysis, to
               be potentially elaborated by qualitative means.<note>These were edited intralingual
                  subtitles, randomly checked with the screen version for accuracy. It goes without
                  saying that intralingual subtitles may occasionally involve the simplification of
                  screen exchanges to match an average reading speed. As all forms of transcription
                  of scripted speech back into writing, it also requires the sanitation of
                  overlapping fragments and intrusive repetitions. However, the dialogue lists we
                  randomly compared with complete audiovisual material revealed only minimal traces
                  of condensation, quite insignificant for the procedures we applied and the methods
                  used are insensitive to the edition techniques usually used to condense dialogues
                  in captions (such as grammatical tense revision). </note> We labelled each
               dialogue list with the name of the screenwriter and the date of release and divided
               them into six rough generic/thematic categories following IMDb listings: chick flick,
               vampire, superhero (as distinguished by the dominant theme); romance, thriller,
               action (as distinguished by the dominant genre). This division is admittedly
               provisory and tentative for several reasons:</p>
            <list type="unordered">
               <item>film genres are in themselves fuzzy categories, as suggested by film scholars
                  and experts in media semiotics (cf. <ref target="#chandler1997">Chandler
                     1997</ref>; <ref target="#altman1999">Altman 1999</ref>; <ref
                     target="#grant2003">Grant 2003</ref>; <ref target="#bondebjerg2015">Bondebjerg
                     2015</ref>);</item>
               <item>most productions included in the corpus evade easy categorization, being best
                  ascribed to a number of major film genres simultaneously and fitting better more
                  precise sub-generic distinctions (for example, IMDb classifies many superhero
                  films as action/adventure/fantasy or action/adventure/science-fiction hybrids, yet
                  some productions, such as <title rend="italic">Deadpool</title> or <title
                     rend="italic"> Thor: Ragnarok</title> have an additional comedic twist, while
                  others, like Christopher Nolan’s visions of <title rend="italic">Batman</title>,
                  qualify as thriller/crime);</item>
               <item>thematic groupings obviously intersect with major generic ones; for example,
                  some vampire films reveal horror and some – dominant romance features, as do a
                  number of releases stereotypically categorized by IMDb viewers as “chick flicks”,
                  although many of the latter belong to the sub-genre of romantic comedy; that is
                  why we have decided to keep this dubious appellation;</item>
               <item>some productions included in the corpus conform better to <term>auteur</term>
                  than genre classifications imposed on them, hence their status may be considered
                  dubious.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Still, we did not consider these complexities and inconsistencies in categorization
               as detrimental to our stylometric analysis. On the contrary, we hoped that by
               inspecting in detail the correlations between particular film scripts, we may detect
               certain genre-, theme-, diachrony- or author-related regularities which would allow
               us to revise or reshuffle the adopted categories. We therefore subjected the corpus
               to a number of quantitative procedures, the origin and methodology of which will be
               explained below.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Introducing stylometry and sentiment analysis.</head>
            <p>Quantitative research on literary language has been developing at least since John
               Burrows studied character idiolects in Jane Austen, showing that her major characters
               with similar functions in different novels tend to use the most common words of their
               lexicon in similar ways (Burrows 1989). This was an early application of multivariate
               analysis of word frequencies that had already been around since Mosteller and Wallace
               showed that authors differ in this respect strongly enough to allow attribution
               (1964). We now know that minute differences in individual usage of very frequent and
               seemingly very insignificant words such as <q>the,</q>
               <q>a,</q>
               <q>in,</q>
               <q>and,</q>
               <q>such </q> and <q>as</q> – when treated with appropriate statistical tools – are
               enough to tell authors apart; or, more precisely, to point out which of several
               candidate writers is the real author of an anonymous text. These authorship
               attribution methods, sometimes still called non-standard authorship attribution
               methods, have in fact become a standard approach whenever the hand that held the pen
               (or that tapped on the keyboard) is obscured for any reason: plagiarism, publishers’
               promotional policy or mere authorial whims. They have been recently used to check
               that Harper Lee did in fact write both <title rend="italic">To Kill a Mockingbird
               </title>and <title rend="italic">Go Set a Watchman</title>
               <ptr target="#choinski2019"/>; that Robert Galbraith and J.K. Rowling are one and the
               same person <ptr target="#juola2015"/>; and that Elena Ferrante, the bestselling yet
               non-existent Italian woman, writes suspiciously like the real Italian man, Domenico
               Starnone <ptr target="#tuzzi2018"/>.</p>
            <p>But many other stylometric experiments in method have also shown that what
               stylometrists call the authorial signal (meaning nothing more, in fact, than the
               authors’ individual idiosyncrasies in word usage that can be made evident through
               statistics) is just one of the classifications that can be made on any sets of texts.
               Not only texts by the same authors are similar in this respect. On another level,
               texts written by authors writing over several literary periods tend to exhibit a
               chronological <quote rend="inline">evolution</quote>
               <ptr target="#burrows1994"/>
               <ptr target="#rybicki2017a"/>, and while this can be easily explained by simple
               evolution of language over centuries, it is also a fact that many writers (including
               Shakespeare, Dickens, James and Conrad) exhibit a chronological progression within
               their own <term>oeuvre</term>
               <ptr target="#hoover2007"/>
               <ptr target="#rybicki2017b"/>. Works of the same writer in two different genres
               exhibit different stylometric traits; this has already been shown for Shakespeare and
               Molière <ptr target="#rybicki2011"/>
               <ptr target="#rybicki2017b"/>; what is more, genre can be a factor in large-scale
               comparisons of authorial word usage <ptr target="#mealand1999"/>. Interestingly,
               there is much less of this <q>stylometric universal</q> in translation: some
               translators seem to exhibit their own and stable <q>stylometry</q> while others have
               a different word usage for each author they translate <ptr target="#burrows2002"/>,
               and translations in a large set tend to group more often by their original authors
               than by translators <ptr target="#rybicki2012"/>; nevertheless, traces of translators
               can be traced within a collaborative work <ptr target="#rybicki2013"/>. </p>
            <p>That such results are stable, reproducible and robust in terms of statistics is
               obviously due to the fact that the features of text used for counting are very simple
               and, at the same time, very numerous. The first hundred most frequent word-types in
               any collection of texts (which usually account for as much as a half of every text)
               contains little more than various function words; <q>meaningful</q> words – the usual
               stuff of literary study – are still a minority in the first thousand. This could
               suggest that stylometry based on most frequent word counts misses the crucial element
               of literary texts, meaning, or <emph>what</emph>, and focuses on style, or
                  <emph>how</emph>; but, on the one hand, word counts alone are hardly style, and,
               on the other, Hough insisted that style is just <quote rend="inline">an aspect of
                  meaning</quote>
               <ptr target="#hough1969" loc="8"/>. Attempts to bridge the gap between stylistics and
               stylometry continue (c.f. <ref target="#hermann2015">Hermann 2015</ref>), but there
               is still much work to do; one explanation of the power of the most frequent words is
               that they <quote rend="inline">do not function as discrete entities. Since they gain
                  their full meaning only through the different sorts of relationship they form with
                  each other, they can be seen as markers of those relationships and, accordingly,
                  of everything that those relationships entail</quote>
               <ptr target="#mckenna1999"/>. </p>
            <p>The reason why most-frequent-word stylometry, and not some other types of textual
               analysis, has been such a powerful newcomer into (digital) literary studies is
               perhaps just one of the many examples that computer-based methods – especially
               unsupervised ones – are notoriously fallible when dealing with the semantics of the
               literary text. This is very visible in the tribulations of sentiment analysis, which
               has been a focus of much quantitative textual research at least since Stone et al.
               made it one of the objects of their study <ptr target="#stone1966"/>. It must be said
               that while sentiment analysis can be of use, and is often used, in large-scale
               browsing of non-literary texts and/or to gauge the overall mood of large sections of
               the Internet, news etc., its application to artistic writing is somewhat more
               problematic due to the features of the literary text that define it as literary.
               Ambiguity, irony, metaphor or even simple negation all cause problems in
               disambiguating the sentiment/emotional <q>value</q> of words and phrases. </p>
            <p>Despite this problem, the presence of some interest in sentiment in literature can be
               attested to by the numerous software packages that try to make it possible. One of
               the most recent, Jockers’s <term>syuzhet</term> package <ptr target="#jockers2016"/>
               for R <ptr target="#rcore2014"/>, employs a number of lexicons of sentiment-related
               terms to trace curves of negative and positive emotions in single novels, associating
               lexical items found in individual texts to emotive categories. Among these, the NRC
               Word-Emotion Association Lexicon <ptr target="#mohammad2010"/> has already been used
               to trace the evolution of sentiment across larger literary corpora and follows
               Plutchik’s concept of eight <quote rend="inline">basic emotions</quote> (anger,
               disgust, fear, sadness and anticipation, joy, surprise, trust; <ptr
                  target="#plutchik1991"/>; alternatively, it also identifies two <quote
                  rend="inline">sentiments,</quote> respectively: negative and positive <ptr
                  target="#mohammad2011"/>. A similar approach has been adopted by Acerbi et al. for
               English novels of the 20th century, who observed a general decrease, with time, of
               terms of emotion by tracing the evolution of terms related to some general categories
               such as fear or joy <ptr target="#acerbi2013"/>. An even more extensive chronological
               study performed on three hundred years of English and Polish fiction showed a steady
               growth of negative sentiments and <quote rend="inline">negative</quote> emotions with
               time <ptr target="#rybicki2018"/>. </p>
            <p>The main drawback sentiment analysis has is that most of the readily-available
               methods use a lexicon approach, where individual words are assigned a
               sentiment/emotion value. The NRC Word-Emotion Association Lexicon, which we used
               here, was a major crowdsourcing venture using Amazon’s Mechanical Turk, where
               numerous users contributed to produce a statistics-based system of evaluating and
               quantifying emotion; yet even this tool may cause a variety of problems. Consider the
               following examples from the NRC Lexicon (Table 1):</p>
            <table>
               <head>Example of emotional valence/sentiment values in the NRC Lexicon. Grey
                  background applied for items discussed in the text.</head>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>emotion/sentiment</cell>
                  <cell><term>baboon</term></cell>
                  <cell><term>dentistry</term></cell>
                  <cell><term>polish</term></cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>anger</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>anticipation</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>disgust</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>fear</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>joy</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>sadness</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>surprise</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>trust</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>negative</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>positive</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>0</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>The <q>baboon</q> example shows how a lexical item is assigned a value of
                  <q>disgust</q> and <q>negative</q> despite the fact that, in a text about
               theriology or even Africa, these associations should be made perfectly neutral; the
               Lexicon also seems to ignore the fact that presence of baboons may just as plausibly
               trigger <q>fear,</q> or that one may thus address a human being in <q>anger</q> as
               well as in <q>disgust.</q> The example of <q>dentistry</q> seems to take into
               consideration the most stereotypical reaction to that noble profession; more
               importantly, the choice of this very rare word and the absence, in the Lexicon, of
               the much more frequent word <q>dentist</q> is an illustration of the numerous issues
               of representativeness in this approach. The final example, that of <q>polish,</q>
               shows an even more <q>mechanical</q> problem and the extent to which mere linguistic
               ambiguity may be a distorting factor: this word, when capitalized, may well require a
               very different sentiment/emotion value. More generally, distribution of emotions and
               sentiments within the literary text is uneven; smoothing any results may be risky, as
               evidenced by the difficulties with this problem in the <term>syuzhet</term> package
               (cf. <ref target="#swafford2015">Swafford 2015</ref>, <ref target="#jockers2017"
                  >Jockers 2017</ref>).</p>
            <p>Despite these pitfalls, our attempt to measure sentiment and emotion in film dialogue
               seems worthwhile. After all, while the lexicon-based method may be wrong at times, it
               is important that it is wrong in a consistent way. Much as the tool is imprecise,
               there is no reason to suppose different texts will be treated in any different way.
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Methods</head>
            <p>For most-frequent-word-based stylometric analysis, the texts were treated with the
               well-established Delta procedure <ptr target="#burrows2002"/> implemented in the
                  <term>stylo</term> package for R <ptr target="#eder2016"/>, the statistical
               programming environment <ptr target="#rcore2014"/>. The entire ensemble of texts in
               electronic form serves as input for <term>stylo</term>, which then tokenizes the text
               (separates it into words). The word tokens are then counted in the whole set to
               produce a descending frequency list of word-types, so that the 100 or more of these
               may be identified. A given number of those very frequent words (usually, from 100 to
               1000) is used as the features of the analysis: their frequency is now counted in each
               individual text to create a frequency table; its columns are treated as sequences of
               numbers that can be compared using an appropriate distance (dissimilarity) measure.
               Our study uses the so-called Cosine Delta distance, which has been shown to work best
               in authorship attribution <ptr target="#evert2017"/>. It is based on cosine
               similarity of the angle between two vectors, x = z(T) and y = z(T1), and is
               calculated according to the formula: <formula rend="block" notation="mathml"><math
                     xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                     xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                     <mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mi mathvariant="normal">cos</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mo>∝</mo>
                        </mrow>
                     </mrow>
                     <mo>=</mo>
                     <mfrac>
                        <mrow>
                           <msubsup>
                              <mo>∑</mo>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>i</mi>
                                 <mo>=</mo>
                                 <mn>1</mn>
                              </mrow>
                              <mrow>
                                 <msub>
                                    <mrow>
                                       <mi>n</mi>
                                    </mrow>
                                    <mrow>
                                       <mi>s</mi>
                                    </mrow>
                                 </msub>
                              </mrow>
                           </msubsup>
                           <mrow>
                              <msub>
                                 <mrow>
                                    <mi>x</mi>
                                 </mrow>
                                 <mrow>
                                    <mi>i</mi>
                                 </mrow>
                              </msub>
                           </mrow>
                           <msub>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>y</mi>
                              </mrow>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>i</mi>
                              </mrow>
                           </msub>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mroot>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mo>(</mo>
                                 <msubsup>
                                    <mo>∑</mo>
                                    <mrow>
                                       <mi>i</mi>
                                       <mo>=</mo>
                                       <mn>1</mn>
                                    </mrow>
                                    <mrow>
                                       <msub>
                                          <mrow>
                                             <mi>n</mi>
                                          </mrow>
                                          <mrow>
                                             <mi>s</mi>
                                          </mrow>
                                       </msub>
                                    </mrow>
                                 </msubsup>
                                 <mrow>
                                    <msubsup>
                                       <mrow>
                                          <mi>x</mi>
                                       </mrow>
                                       <mrow>
                                          <mi>i</mi>
                                       </mrow>
                                       <mrow>
                                          <mn>2</mn>
                                       </mrow>
                                    </msubsup>
                                    <mo>)</mo>
                                 </mrow>
                              </mrow>
                              <mrow/>
                           </mroot>
                           <mroot>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mo>(</mo>
                                 <msubsup>
                                    <mo>∑</mo>
                                    <mrow>
                                       <mi>i</mi>
                                       <mo>=</mo>
                                       <mn>1</mn>
                                    </mrow>
                                    <mrow>
                                       <msub>
                                          <mrow>
                                             <mi>n</mi>
                                          </mrow>
                                          <mrow>
                                             <mi>s</mi>
                                          </mrow>
                                       </msub>
                                    </mrow>
                                 </msubsup>
                                 <mrow>
                                    <msubsup>
                                       <mrow>
                                          <mi>y</mi>
                                       </mrow>
                                       <mrow>
                                          <mi>i</mi>
                                       </mrow>
                                       <mrow>
                                          <mn>2</mn>
                                       </mrow>
                                    </msubsup>
                                    <mo>)</mo>
                                 </mrow>
                              </mrow>
                              <mrow/>
                           </mroot>
                        </mrow>
                     </mfrac>
                  </math></formula> where ns is the number of most-frequent word-types used in the
               analysis, while z(T) and z(T1) are z-score values for the frequency of a word in,
               respectively, texts T and T1. Z-scores are calculated with the usual formula:
                  <formula rend="block" notation="mathml"><math
                     xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                     xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                     <mi>z</mi>
                     <mfenced separators="|">
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>T</mi>
                        </mrow>
                     </mfenced>
                     <mo>=</mo>
                     <mfrac>
                        <mrow>
                           <msub>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>f</mi>
                              </mrow>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>s</mi>
                              </mrow>
                           </msub>
                           <mfenced separators="|">
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>T</mi>
                              </mrow>
                           </mfenced>
                           <mo>-</mo>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <msub>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>μ</mi>
                              </mrow>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>s</mi>
                              </mrow>
                           </msub>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <msub>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>σ</mi>
                              </mrow>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>s</mi>
                              </mrow>
                           </msub>
                        </mrow>
                     </mfrac>
                  </math></formula> where fs(T) denotes relative frequency of word s in text T, µs
               is mean frequency of word s in the entire set of texts, and σs is standard deviation
               of frequency of word s in the same set <ptr target="#smith2011"/>.</p>
            <p>This produces a distance matrix: a square table of <q>distances,</q> or degrees of
               dissimilarity, between each pair of texts – the smaller the value, the more similar
               the two texts are. Usually, at least in literary texts of some length, the smallest
               values are those between texts written by the same author; our studies have shown
               that this is a much less marked phenomenon in film dialogue, and even less so in TV
               series <ptr target="#holobut2016"/>
               <ptr target="#holobut2017a"/>. While this is already the kind of output that may be
               examined, analyses of larger numbers of texts require visualization of the patterns
               of similarity and difference between the texts, which can be achieved with further
               statistical procedures. We use Ward’s hierarchical cluster analysis to draw tree
               diagrams that bring together the nearest neighbors (texts most similar to each
               other); usually, for greater reliability of the results, this is repeated for
               different numbers of most-frequent word types (in our study, for 100, 200, 300, …
               1000) most frequent words, and the results are further processed in consensus network
               analysis <ptr target="#eder2017"/> in <title rend="italic">Gephi</title>
               <ptr target="#bastian2009"/>.</p>
            <p>While the stylometric part of the analysis was performed on all grammatical word
               forms, sentiment analysis requires that the texts be lemmatized, or converted to
               their basic grammatical forms. This was done with the standard automatic tool,
               Treetagger <ptr target="#schmid1994"/>. Sentiments and emotions (as defined by <ref
                  target="#mohammad2011">Mohammad 2011</ref>) were counted using the <quote
                  rend="inline">NRC Lexicon</quote> within the <term>syuzhet</term> package <ptr
                  target="#jockers2016"/>. Counts of emotions were summed for each text and
               proportions between positive and negative sentiments established for each text.
               Graphs were produced to visualize the results; the Lexicon’s eight emotions were
               treated similarly but relative to individual text lengths.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Results</head>
            <p>Figure 1 presents a network analysis performed with the above-mentioned method on the
               full set of film dialogues. </p>
            <figure>
               <head>Network analysis of the entire set of film dialogues, color-coded by
                  (principal) genre: action/adventure, red; chick flick, yellow; romance, grey;
                  superhero, orange; thriller, blue and vampire, green).</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>As can be seen, clustering by generic-thematic grouping is especially successful for
               thrillers (blue), with particularly strong connections visible among films sharing
               sub-generic properties. For instance, Brian Singer’s crime/drama/thriller <title
                  rend="italic">The Usual Suspects</title> (1995) written by Christopher McQuarrie
               shows on the one hand strong connections to David Fincher’s crime/mystery drama
                  <title rend="italic">Seven</title> (1995) and on the other – to Quentin
               Tarantino’s <title rend="italic">Reservoir Dogs</title> (1993), the Coen brothers’
                  <title rend="italic">Fargo</title> (2006), and Martin Scorsese’s <title
                  rend="italic">The Departed </title> (2006), thus demonstrating close stylometric
               affinities between different productions combining elements of crime, drama and
               thriller and raising interesting questions about the sensitivity of stylometric tools
               to the exponents of low register (possibly reflected in the grammatical simplicity of
               utterances affecting the frequency of function words) and the pragmatics of deduction
               and threat (cf. <ref target="#kozloff2000" loc="220">Kozloff 2000: 220</ref>) typical
               of crime films.</p>
            <p>John McTiernan’s <title rend="italic">Die Hard</title> (1988), classified by IMDb as
               action/thriller, shows strong ties to both genres, being much closer to other action
               productions (such as Steven Spielberg’s <title rend="italic">Jaws</title>, 1975), but
               at the same time showing surprisingly tight stylometric bonds to Tarantino’s <title
                  rend="italic">Pulp Fiction</title> (1994), Michael Mann’s <title rend="italic"
                  >Heat</title> (1995) and Luc Besson’s <title rend="italic">Leon</title> (1994),
               classified as crime/drama/thrillers.</p>
            <p>A separate sub-area on our map is occupied by Alfred Hitchcock’s masterpieces
               intertwined with classic noir productions. <title rend="italic">Dial M for
                  Murder</title> (crime, thriller 1954), written by a British playwright Frederick
               Knott, links strongly to Hitchcock’s <title rend="italic">Psycho</title> (an
               adaptation of Robert Bloch’s novel; horror, mystery, 1960) and <title rend="italic"
                  >Rebecca</title> (an adaptation of Daphne du Maurier’s novel; drama, mystery,
               romance,1940), as well as to Carol Reed’s <title rend="italic">The Third Man</title>,
               written by Graham Greene (film-noir, mystery, thriller, 1949). <title rend="italic"
                  >Rebecca</title> is closely related to his <title rend="italic">Psycho</title> and
                  <title rend="italic">Vertigo</title> (an adaptation of Boileau-Narcejac’s novel;
               mystery, romance, thriller, 1958), as well as to Billy Wilder’s film noir <title
                  rend="italic">Double Indemnity</title> co-authored by the director and Raymond
               Chandler (crime, drama, film noir, 1944). At the same time, it connects strongly to
               David Lean’s romance <title rend="italic">Brief Encounter </title> and other
               representatives of the romance genre, such as Sydney Pollack’s <title rend="italic"
                  >Out of Africa</title> (1985) or Edward Zwick’s <title rend="italic">Legends of
                  the Fall</title> (1994). Hitchcock’s <title rend="italic">Rear Window</title>
               (mystery, thriller 1954) is bonded with <title rend="italic">Psycho</title>, as well
               as <title rend="italic">The Third Man</title> and <title rend="italic">Double
                  Indemnity</title>. They constitute quite a tight-knit area in the diagram,
               allowing the diachronic, generic and <term>auteur</term> director signals to collude
               and encouraging further qualitative research into how Hitchcock’s belief in the
               subservience of dialogue to <q>pure cinema</q> may have affected his collaborator’s
               screenwriting style and reflected earlier film-making conventions. The only Hitchcock
               production that does not blend in with the other scripts analyzed is <title
                  rend="italic">North by Northwest</title> (adventure, mystery, thriller, 1959),
               written by Ernest Lehman and apparently intended by the writer as <quote
                  rend="inline">the Hitchcock picture to end all Hitchcock pictures</quote> (qtd. in
                  <ref target="#freedman2015" loc="36">Freedman 2015: 36</ref>). The dialogue lines
               demonstrate closer links to Roman Polański’s neo-noir <title rend="italic">Chinatown
               </title> (1974), and Jacques Tourneur’s noir <title rend="italic">Out of the
                  Past</title> (1947) than to Hitchcock’s other films. These neighbor with two
               representatives of the gangster genre in our corpus, Francis Ford Coppola’s <title
                  rend="italic">Godfather </title> (1972, 1974). An in-depth inspection of this
               grouping suggests that further sub-division into mystery, gangster and film noir
               might reveal additional patterning in dialogue techniques. This supports Sarah
               Kozloff’s <quote rend="inline">close-reading</quote> observations on the functional
               and pragma-stylistic distinction to be made between noirs and gangster films, the
               former featuring characters who are <quote rend="inline">middle-class,</quote>
               solitary, <quote rend="inline">cynical and deliberately <q>hardboiled</q></quote> and
               the latter featuring self-educated <quote rend="inline">groups of
                  confederates</quote>
               <ptr target="#kozloff2000" loc="203"/>. It is interesting, however, that films
               directed by Alfred Hitchcock (and written by different acclaimed authors) display
               stronger stylometric bonds than those both written and directed by other acclaimed
                  <term>auteurs</term>, such as Quentin Tarantino or the Coen brothers. </p>
            <p>Another grouping that forms a successful cluster is the thematic category “chick
               flick”. As listed by IMDb users, it is dominated by romcoms, but it also contains
               romance drama and family drama, films that demonstrably tap into the realm of human
               emotions and range from humor to pathos. They consistently occupy the right-hand side
               of the map and intermingle with productions categorized as <q>romances,</q> a
               grouping that clearly overlaps with the one discussed. Thus, the grey
                  <q>intrusions</q> into the yellow-dominated area on the diagram are all
                  <term>auteur</term> romances: John Carney’s romantic musical dramas <title
                  rend="italic">Once</title> (2007) and <title rend="italic">Sing Street</title>
               (2016), Damien Chazelle’s <title rend="italic">La La Land</title> (2016) and Bradley
               Cooper’s most recent remake of <title rend="italic">A Star is Born</title> (2018), as
               well as critically acclaimed verbal masterpieces: Richard Linklater’s romantic drama
               trilogy <title rend="italic">Before Sunrise </title> (1995), <title rend="italic"
                  >Before Sunset </title>(2004) and <title rend="italic">Before Midnight
               </title>(2013) co-created with performers Julie Delpy and Ethan Hawke, Woody Allen’s
                  <title rend="italic">Manhattan</title> (1979) and <title rend="italic">Annie Hall
               </title> (1977) and Spike Jonze’s <title rend="italic">Her</title> (2013), the last
               two presented with the Academy Award for Best Original Screenplay and clearly devoid
               of melodramatic traces typical of many representatives of the “romance” category. </p>
            <p>Another interesting regularity to be observed in this area of the diagram is the
               clustering of films written or co-authored by Richard Curtis: <title rend="italic"
                  >Four Weddings and a Funeral</title> (1994), the two Bridget Jones films (2001,
               2004), <title rend="italic">Notting Hill</title> (1999), <title rend="italic">Love,
                  Actually</title> (2003) and <title rend="italic">About Time</title> (2013). The
               only aberration on the romcom/romance map is James Cameron’s <hi rend="italic"
                  >Titanic</hi> (1997), hidden in the depths of action/adventure/thriller, in the
               neighborhood of Spielberg’s <title rend="italic">Jaws</title> (1975) and Inarritu’s
                  <title rend="italic">Revenant</title> (2015). It seems that James Cameron’s
               unsentimental provenance and interest in non-romantic genres may have left
               stylometric traces in his dialogue technique. </p>
            <p>Vampire films (green), by contrast, reveal their individual and complex generic
               affinities. The <title rend="italic">Twilight</title> saga, spread around the central
               part of the diagram, shows marked stylometric affinities across the episodes, yet it
               clearly demonstrates the gradual loss of romantic undertone, with the first two
               episodes: <title rend="italic">Twilight</title> (2008) and <title rend="italic">New
                  Moon</title> (2009) classified as fantasy/drama/romance showing bonds with
               romantic comedies and romances and the more recent parts of the series uniting with
               classic thriller productions. Another area is occupied by horror rather than fantasy
               representations of the vampire theme: Coppola’s <title rend="italic">Dracula</title>
               (1992), Burton’s <title rend="italic">Dark Shadows</title> (2012), Jordan’s <title
                  rend="italic">Interview with the Vampire</title> (1994) and dated horrors:
               Sangster’s <title rend="italic">Lust for a Vampire</title> (1971) and Francis’s
                  <title rend="italic">Dr Terror’s House of Horrors </title> (1965). These
               regularities may, indeed, suggest that stylometric measures based on most frequent
               word frequencies are sensitive to the changing functionalities of filmic speech,
               romance depending more on the explicit expression of emotion <ptr
                  target="#kozloff2000" loc="249"/> and horror – on the implicit build-up of
               suspense. </p>
            <p>As for other groupings, action/adventure films, including superhero productions, all
               cluster to the left-hand side of the diagram. What merits attention is the
               stylometric consistency of big franchises, with particular episodes clustering
               regardless of their authorial parentage. Some blockbuster series can be attributed to
               the same screenwriter throughout, allowing the authorial and thematic signals to
               coincide: for instance, the <title rend="italic">Pirates of the Caribbean</title>
               swashbucklers (written by Ted Elliott and Terry Rossio), the <title rend="italic"
                  >Matrix </title> trilogy (by Lana and Lilly Wachowski), the <title rend="italic"
                  >Lord of the Rings </title> and the <title rend="italic">Hobbit</title> series,
               which intertwine in our analysis (written by Fran Walsh, Philippa Boyens, Peter
               Jackson). </p>
            <p>The Batman series is clearly divided into two main areas: a cluster of Christopher
               Nolan’s most recent productions: <title rend="italic">Batman Begins</title> (2005),
                  <title rend="italic">The Dark Knight</title> (2008) and <title rend="italic">The
                  Dark Knight Rises</title> (2012) and another cluster of three older episodes:
                  <title rend="italic">Batman Returns</title> (1992) directed by Tim Burton as well
               as <title rend="italic">Batman Forever</title> (1995) and <title rend="italic">Batman
                  and Robin</title> (1997) directed by Joel Schumacher. Tim Burton’s original <title
                  rend="italic">Batman</title> (1989), however, occupies a distant location on the
               map, tied closely to thriller films, and showing little stylometric relation to the
               following pictures, possibly inspired more by the gangster/crime genre to which it
               visually alludes. </p>
            <p>The <title rend="italic">Star Wars</title> franchise is, unsurprisingly, separated
               into three areas. The two oldest episodes: <title rend="italic">Star Wars</title>
               (1977) and <title rend="italic">The Empire Strikes Back</title> (1980) are united
               with a strong stylometric bond. Lawrence Kasdan and George Lucas’s <title
                  rend="italic">Return of the Jedi</title> (1983) connects them to the more recent
               trilogy: <title rend="italic">The Phantom Menace</title> (1999), <title rend="italic"
                  >Attack of the Clones</title> (2002) and <title rend="italic">Revenge of the
                  Sith</title> (2005), written by George Lucas. They neighbour closely with Lucas’s
               other productions, namely Steven Spielberg’s <title rend="italic">Indiana Jones and
                  the Raiders of the Lost Ark</title> (written by Kasdan, 1982) and <title
                  rend="italic">Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade</title> (written by Boam, 1989).
               The most recent <title rend="italic">Star Wars</title> incarnations produced by
               Disney: <title rend="italic">The Force Awakens</title> (2015), <title rend="italic"
                  >The Last Jedi</title> (2017) and <title rend="italic">Rogue One</title> (2016)
               form a separate cluster, showing a different dialogue technique. Interestingly,
               Lawrence Kasdan’s most recent addition to the series, <title rend="italic">Solo: A
                  Star Wars Story</title> (2018) does not reveal any stylometric affinities to the
               remaining pictures; indeed <title rend="italic">Solo</title> does seem to fly solo. </p>
            <p>As for other series, <title rend="italic">Jurassic Park</title> and <title
                  rend="italic">Jurassic World</title> episodes show stylometric links. Richard
               Donner’s <title rend="italic">Superman</title> (1978) bonds with its recent remake,
                  <title rend="italic">Superman Returns</title> (2006) are Richard Lester’s <title
                  rend="italic">Superman II </title>(1980). Significantly, the comedic third
               episode, <title rend="italic">Superman III</title> (1983) is separated from the
               remaining ones. Other remakes, such as <title rend="italic">The Last of the
                  Mohicans</title> (1937, 1992) and two out of the four versions of <title
                  rend="italic">A Star is Born</title> (1937; 1954) also demonstrate marked
               stylometric similarity. </p>
            <p>When isolated from other categories, the sub-generic nuances of action/adventure
               productions become somewhat more marked (<ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref>).
               This configuration also exhibits a strong authorial signal and, very
               characteristically for film dialogues, a tendency to cluster by thematic universe
                  <ptr target="#holobut2016"/>
               <ptr target="#holobut2017a"/>H. As a result, the mob-ridden environment of Gotham and
               Spiderman’s New York becomes very similar to that of the more direct depictions of
               the mafia by Coppola. </p>
            <figure>
               <head>Network analysis of the action/adventure (red) and superhero (orange)
                  genre.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Sentiment analysis can be mostly presented with much less statistical manipulation,
               simply by plotting the various sentiment/emotion scores against time of film release.
               Figure 3 shows the proportion of positive to negative sentiments in our entire set of
               film dialogues (data points) and the linear trend (lines) of this ratio. In the
               figure, balanced positive-to-negative contents would place a given film at 0.5 on the
               vertical scale; anything above that value contains more positive than negative terms;
               anything below 0.5 descends into negativity. As can be seen, values for
               all groupings are highly scattered; nevertheless, some trends in the appearance of
               positive and negative sentiments may be observed. The oldest genres in this set,
               romances and thrillers, exhibit a fairly stable proportion, with, unsurprisingly, a
               much higher participation of the positive despite a slight downwards trend. By
               contrast, the initially much more negative thrillers rise slightly from darker to
               lighter moods. A much more marked fall in positive sentiments can be observed in
               the dialogues of action/adventure films and even more so in the superhero
               subgenre; in the second decade of the 21st century, they are more negative in
               sentiment than even the thrillers. Still, negativity flourishes the most in an
               entirely different class: in the vampire movies; their verbally expressed positive
               sentiments dwindle almost to 0.5 at the end of the timeline, perhaps not unrelatedly
               to a very marked and mirror-image ascent of positive values in chick flicks. </p>
            <figure>
               <head>Positive-to-negative sentiment ratio in the entire set of film dialogues,
                  color-coded by (principal) genre, with linear trendlines.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Numeric results for the eight basic Plutchik emotions are consistent with both those
               for positivity/negativity and with each other. Based on the results of the
               Kruskal-Wallis tests obtained for each pair of emotions (well below any values that
               could suggest statistical insignificance), their representation in the boxplots in
               Figure 4 shows a very strong correlation for high levels of anticipation and joy
               between chick flicks and romances. These two categories are also very much alike in
               their equally low values of anger, disgust, and fear. At the same time, in terms of
               these five emotions, both romances and chick flicks differ with very high statistical
               significance from the other genres. Sadness and fear are also statistically higher in
               films about vampires; this grouping is also significantly deficient in trust. It may
               be said more generally that, in terms of sentiment and emotion analysis, three rather
               than six categories are discernible here: 1) chick flicks and romances, 2) vampire
               films, 3) action, superhero and thriller movies.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Relative frequencies of words associated with the eight basic emotions in the
                  entire set of film dialogues. Boxes denote the range of the 25th-75th percentiles;
                  the short horizontal line inside each box is the median; whiskers and circles
                  denote outlying (extreme) values.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Discussion</head>
            <p>Several interesting observations can be made on the basis of this study. Not the
               least of these is that the tentative theme/genre classifications that we have started
               with have been verified by our quantitative approach in both stylometry and sentiment
               analysis. Our most-frequent-word analysis shows that while some of our initial
               groupings do seem to create discernible communities, individual films do not seem to
               care. These stylometric <q>misclassifications</q> (such as the affinity of Woody
               Allen’s sophisticated comedies to other comedic productions rather than for instance
               period romance dramas) are understandable and attest to the inadequacy of our <hi
                  rend="italic">a priori</hi> film classification rather than that of the
               stylometric approach; indeed, these misclassifications often correct the rough
               pigeon-holing that we used, revealing the influence of authorial and sub-generic
               nuance on the measurable features of film dialogue style and mutual relationships
               between dialogue techniques in different groups of films considered.</p>
            <p>Film dialogue seems to successfully reflect the fact that individual films rarely
               conform to the requirements of a single, unadulterated, major-level genre such as
               action films or thrillers. This becomes quite evident when one views in detail the
               network analysis graph in full complexity of its signals. At times, films cluster by
               screenwriter as if in accordance with the <term>Schreiber</term> theory of film
               authorship; at times, the director’s choices seem to bring together different
               screenwriters’ efforts, as if to vindicate the claims of <term>auteur</term>
               theorists who believe in the director’s influence over the collective work of
               different specialists, screenwriters included. Then there are mainstream films that
               do cluster by genre. Elsewhere, the collaborative nature of making movies takes over
               to create a strong franchise signal, which in turn may be overridden by that of the
               studio: after all, in our graphs, Disney <title rend="italic">Star Wars</title> have
               left the orbit of their predecessors. Diachrony is another significant element which
               deserves more in-depth qualitative analysis, possibly looking at the evolution of
               non-verbal cinematic techniques; the language of film dialogue in the 1940s and the
               1950s stands apart from later productions. What is more, the diachronic element is
               not limited to the date of the films’ release; our stylometric results can also
               reflect their temporal setting, quite plausibly due to archaic stylization of the
               spoken parts. This has already been noted in an earlier study on historical films and
               series <ptr target="#holobut2017a"/>.</p>
            <p>It is quite remarkable that, despite all the above caveats against lexicon-based
               sentiment analysis, much of our results of this type of distant reading agrees with
               what we know about the genres from <q>close viewing.</q> The fact that computational
               sentiment analysis agrees so well, indeed so boringly, with human presuppositions
               might be a result of the somewhat crude approach – through decontextualized lexical
               items. At the same time, however, the crude nature of the lexicon approach may be
               reflected in the fact that, contrarily to most-frequent-word stylometry, sentiment
               analysis shows fewer, rather than more, valid divisions: chick flicks merge with
               romances, action/superhero films with thrillers. Meanwhile, vampire movies, an
               internally conflicted category according to Delta, acquires a separate status due to
               higher levels of <q>fear</q> and lower levels of <q>trust.</q> This quantitative
               procedure can act as a starting point for more in-depth qualitative evaluation of
               emotions (both those expressed by characters and those evoked in viewers) and the
               dominance of particular speech acts in the verbal exchanges on screen (such as
               teasing in comedy, threatening in gangster films, commanding in drama or explaining
               in science-fiction, cf. <ref target="#kozloff2000">Kozloff 2000</ref>). </p>
            <p>It may seem paradoxical that of the two approaches used in this study, the one that
               seems to have less to do with semantics – the comparison of frequencies of very
               frequent words, grammatical words, function words, <q>synsemantic</q> words – also
               seems to reflect, albeit indirectly, the semantics of the film dialogues – their
               differing functionalities, their stylistic patternings, their themes, their thematic
               subgenres, their implied audience. At the same time, an approach more directly aimed
               at meaning: the search for terms of sentiment, <term>syuzhet</term>, emotion, suffers
               from the computers’ still-underdeveloped ability to <q>understand</q> the meaning of
               literary texts and can only confirm – at best – what we already know about film
               genres. In fact, the little information we obtain from this latter part of the study
               makes our flawed (oversimplified) classification seem almost adequate – which it
               certainly is <emph>not</emph>. Still, it is enough to teach us never to trust a
               vampire...</p>
            <p>Dialogue is only a small part of film. At first glance – and for quite a long time in
               the history of film studies – it seemed much less important to the overall form and
               meaning of the art than image or non-verbal sound. Film scholars, cognitive
               scientists and digital experts have already undertaken extensive research into film
               narrative structure (e.g. <ref target="#murtagh2009">Murtagh 2009</ref>; <ref
                  target="#mckie2014">McKie 2014</ref>), film digital archiving (e.g. <ref
                  target="#bateman2016">Bateman 2016</ref>) and other <q>measurable</q> parameters
               of cinematic art, such as shot lengths, types of shots, motion types and/or visual
               characteristics of the image onscreen such as light intensity (e.g. <ref
                  target="#salt2007">Salt 2007</ref>; <ref target="#cutting2011">Cutting 2011</ref>;
                  <ref target="#suchan2016">Suchan 2016</ref>; <ref target="#heftberger2018"
                  >Heftberger 2018</ref>). Our study shows that results of these more standard
               digital film studies could be interestingly confronted with quantitative analysis of
               films’ textual layer for better insight into the specificities and the mutual
               influences of film genres, authorial <term>oeuvre</term> or chronology; if only to
               see to what extent the sentiments and the emotions and the style in film dialogue go
               hand in hand – or not – with the visual and the non-verbal auditory components in
               various film genres and periods of film history. </p>
            <p>Such a multifaceted analysis of film would be a dream interdisciplinary project, and,
               in Shakespearean phrase, devoutly to be wished. The fact that it has not been yet
               done, at least to our knowledge, is a result of obvious difficulties. It is possible
               to produce a large corpus of film dialogue texts, for instance editing the
               screenplays available online (cf. <ref target="#murtagh2009" loc="302">Murtagh 2009:
                  302</ref>); distant reading was made for big data (in this case, textual data too
               extensive to be processed by the naked eye); once the texts are acquired, the
               machines do the rest. However, the same can hardly be said of the more
                  <q>technical</q> sides of filmmaking listed in the preceding paragraph: there,
               each item would require much annotation and coding, resulting in a much higher
               complexity of the project. The good news is that now that (we believe) interesting
               textual features of film dialogue have been found, the incentive to combine it with
               other features of film may result in a much larger project than the one that could be
               described within the limited space of this paper.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>Appendix 1. </head>
            <list type="unordered">
               <head>List of films included in the corpus divided into subcategories (following
                  IMDBs classifications) and ordered chronologically: </head>
               <item><list type="unordered">
                     <head>Action</head>
                     <item>The Godfather, dir. F. F. Coppola, USA (1971) [crime, drama]</item>
                     <item>The Godfather, dir. FF. Copola, USA (1974) F. F. Coppola [crime,
                        drama]</item>
                     <item>Jaws, dir. S. Spielberg, USA (1975) [adventure, drama, thriller]</item>
                     <item>Star Wars, dir. G. Lucas, USA (1977) [action, adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Star Wars Episode V: The Empire Strikes Back, dir. I. Kershner, USA
                        (1980) [action, adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Raiders of the Lost Ark, dir. S. Spielberg, USA (1981) [action,
                        adventure]</item>
                     <item>Star Wars Episode VI: Return of the Jedi, dir. R. Marquand, USA (1984)
                        [action, adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Indiana Jones and the Temple of Doom, dir. S. Spielberg, USA (1984)
                        [action, adventure]</item>
                     <item>Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade, dir. S. Spielberg, USA (1989)
                        [action, adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Jurassic Park, dir. S. Spielberg, USA (1993) [adventure, sci-fi,
                        thriller]</item>
                     <item>The Lost World: Jurassic Park, dir. S. Spielberg (1997) [action,
                        adventure, sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>The Matrix, dir. L. and L. Wachowski, USA (1999) [action, sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Lord of the Rings: The Fellowship of the Ring, dir. P. Jackson, News,
                        Zealand, USA (2001) [adventure, drama, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Star Wars Episode I: The Phantom Menace, dir. G. Lucas, USA (2001)
                        [action, adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Jurassic Park III, dir. J. Johnston, USA (2001) [action, adventure,
                        sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Lord of the Rings: The Two Towers, dir. P. Jackson, New Zealand, USA
                        (2002) [adventure, drama, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Star Wars Episode II: Attack of the Clones, dir. G. Lucas, USA (2002)
                        [action, adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>The Lord of the Rings: The Return of the King, dir. P. Jackson, New
                        Zealand, USA (2003) [action, adventure, drama]</item>
                     <item>The Matrix Reloaded, dir. L. and L. Wachowski, USA (2003) [action,
                        sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>The Matrix Revolutions, dir. L. and L. Wachowski, USA (2003) [action,
                        sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>The Pirates of the Caribbean: he Curse of the Black Pearl, dir. G.
                        Verbinski, USA (2003) [action, adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Star Wars Episode III: Revenge of the Sith, dir. G. Lucas, USA (2005)
                        [action, adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>The Pirates of the Caribbean: The Dead Man’s Chest, dir. G. Verbinsku,
                        USA (2006) [action, adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Pirates of the Caribbean: At World’s End, dir. G. Verbinski, USA (2007)
                        [action, adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull, dir. S. Spielberg,
                        USA (2008) [action, adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Pirates of the Caribbean: On Stranger Tides, dir. R. Marshall, USA (2012)
                        [action, narrative, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>The Hobbit: An Unexpected Journey, dir. P. Jackson, USA, New Zealand
                        (2012) [adventure, family, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>The Hobbit: The Desolation of Smaug, dir. P. Jackson, USA, New Zealand
                        (2013) [adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Rush, dir. R. Howard, UK, Germany, USA (2013) [action, biography,
                        drama]</item>
                     <item>Hobbit: The Battle of the Five Armies, dir. P. Jackson, USA, New Zealand
                        (2014) [adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Jurassic World, dir. C. Trevorrow, USA (2015) [action, adventure,
                        sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Star Wars Episode VII: The Force Awakens, dir. J. J. Abrams, USA (2015)
                        [action, adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>The Revenant, dir. A. G. Iñárritu, USA, Hong Kong, Taiwan (2015) [action,
                        adventure, biography]</item>
                     <item>Rogue One, dir. G. Edwards, USA (2016) [action, adventure, sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Star Wars: The Last Jedi, dir. R. Johnson, USA (2017) [action, adventure,
                        fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Jurassic World: The Fallen Kingdom, dir. J. A. Bayona, USA (2018)
                        [action, adventure, sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Solo: A Star Wars Story, dir. R. Howard, USA (2018) [action, adventure,
                        fantasy]</item>
                  </list></item>
               <item><list type="unordered">
                     <head>Chick flick</head>
                     <item>Ice Castles, dir. D. Wrye, USA (1978) [drama, romance, sport]</item>
                     <item>Terms of Endearment, dir. J.L. Brooks, USA (1983) [comedy, drama]</item>
                     <item>Splash (1984), dir. R. Howard, USA [comedy, fantasy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Pretty in Pink, dir. H. Deutch, USA (1986) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Dirty Dancing, dir. E. Ardolino, USA (1987) [drama, music,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Moonstruck, dir N. Jewison, USA (1987) [comedy drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Beaches, dir. G. Marshall, USA (1988) [comedy, drama, music]</item>
                     <item>Steal Magnolias, dir. H. Ross, USA (1989) [comedy, drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>When Harry Met Sally, dir. R. Reiner, USA (1989) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Ghost, dir. Jerry Zucker, USA (1990) [drama, fantasy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Pretty Woman, dir. G. Marshall, USA (1990) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Father of the Bride, dir. Ch. Shyer, USA (1991) [comedy, family,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Fried Green Tomatoes, dir. J. Avnet, USA (1991) [drama]</item>
                     <item>Thelma and Louise, dir. R. Scott, USA (1991) [adventure, crime,
                        drama]</item>
                     <item>Indecent Proposal, dir. A. Lyne, USA (1993) [drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Sleepless in Seattle, dir. N. Ephron, USA (1993) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Untamed Heart, dir. T. Bill (1993), USA [comedy, drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Four Weddings and a Funeral, dir. M. Newell, UK [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Boys on the Side, dir. H. Ross, USA, France (1995) [comedy, drama]</item>
                     <item>Clueless, dir. A. Heckerling, USA (1995) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>A Month by the Lake, dir. J. Irvin, UK, USA (1995) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>While You Were Sleeping, dir. J. Turteltaub, USA (1995) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>The Truth About Cats and Dogs, dir. M. Lehmann, USA (1996) [comedy,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Romy and Michele’s High School Reunion, dir. D. Mirkin, USA (1997)
                        [comedy]</item>
                     <item>My Best Friend’s Wedding, dir. P.J. Hogan, USA (1997) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Titanic, dir. J. Cameron, USA (1997) [drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Home Fires, dir. D. Parisot, USA (1998) [comedy, romance, drama]</item>
                     <item>Hope Floats, dir. F. Whitaker, USA (1998) [drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Ever After, dir. A. Tennant, USA (1998) [comedy, drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Stepmom, dir. Ch. Columbus, USA (1998) [comedy, drama]</item>
                     <item>How Stella Got Her Groove Back, dir. K. R. Sullivan, USA (1998) [comedy,
                        drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Practical Magic, dir. G. Dunne, USA (1998) [comedy, drama,
                        fantasy]</item>
                     <item>The Wedding Singer, dir. F. Coraci, USA (1998) [comedy, music,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>You’ve Got Mail, dir. N. Ephron, USA (1998) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Notting Hill, dir. R. Curtis, UK, USA (1999) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Forces of Nature, dir. B. Hughes, USA (1999) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>10 Things I Hate About You, dir. G. Junger, USA (1999) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Never Been Kissed, dir. R. Gosnell, USA (1999) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>She’s All That, dir. R. Iscove, USA (1999) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Runaway Bride, dir. G. Marshall, USA (1999) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Miss Congeniality, dir. D. Petrie, USA (2000) [action, comedy,
                        crime]</item>
                     <item>Save the Last Dance, dir. T. Carter, USA (2000) [drama, music,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>The Wedding Planner, dir. A. Shankman, Germany, USA (2001) [comedy,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Serendipity, dir. P. Chelsom, USA (2001) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Bridget Jones’ s Diary, dir. S. Maguire, UK, France, USA (2001) [comedy,
                        drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>The Princess Diaries, dir. G. Marshall, USA (2001) [comedy, family,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Legally Blonde, dir. R. Luketic, USA (2001) [ comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Maid in Manhattan, dir. W. Wang, USA (2002) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Sweet Home Alabama, dir. A. Tennant, USA (2002) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>My Big Fat Greek Wedding, dir. J. Zwick, Canada, USA (2002) [comedy,
                        drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Crossroads, dir. T. Davies, USA (2002) [comedy, drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Divine Secrets of the Ya-Ya Sisterhood, dir. C. Khouri, USA (2002) [
                        drama]</item>
                     <item>A Walk t Remember, dir A. Shankman, USA (2002) [ drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>How to Lose a Guy in 10 Days, dir. D. Petrie, USA (2003) [comedy,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Uptown Girls, dir. B. Yakin, USA (2003) [ comedy, drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Le Divorce, dir. J. Ivory, USA (2003) [ drama, romance, comedy]</item>
                     <item>Love, Actually, dir. R. Curtis, UK, USA, France (2003) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Alex and Emma, dir. R. Reiner, USA (2003) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Under the Tuscan Sun, dir. A. Wells, USA, Italy (2003) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Legally Blonde 2, dir. Ch. Herman-Wormfeld, USA (2003) [comedy]</item>
                     <item>Love Don’t Cost a Thing, dir. T. Byer, USA (2003) [comedy, romance,
                        drama]</item>
                     <item>Bridget Jones: The Edge of Reason, dir. B. Kidron, UK, USA (2004)
                        [comedy, drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>The Notebook, dir. N. Cassavetes, USA (2004) [drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>13 Going on 30, dir. G. Winick, USA (2004) [comedy, fantasy,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>50 First Dates, dir. P. Segal, USA (2004) [comedy, drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Raisin Helen, dir. G. Marshall, USA (2004) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>The Little Black Book, dir. N. Hurran, USA (2004) [comedy, romance,
                        drama]</item>
                     <item>Mean Girls, dir. M. Waters, USA (2004) [comedy]</item>
                     <item>Fever Pitch, dir. B and P. Farelly, USA (2005) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Monster-in-Law, dir. R. Luketic, USA, Germany (2005) [comedy,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>The Wedding Date, dir. C. Kilner, SUA (2005) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>The Perfect Man, dir. M. Rosman, USA (2005) [comedy, family,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Hitch, dir. A. Tennant, USA (2005) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Prime, dir. B. Younger, USA (2005) [comedy, drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>The Sisterhood of the Travelling Pants, dir. K. Kwapis (2005) [comedy,
                        drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Must Love Dogs, dir. G. D. Goldberg, USA (2005) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Last Holiday, dir. W. Wang, USA (2006) [comedy]</item>
                     <item>Failure to Launch, dir. T. Dey, USA (2006) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>The Break-Up, dir. P. Reed, USA (2006) [comedy, drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>The Devil Wears Prada, dir. D. Frankel, USA, France (2006) [comedy,
                        drama]</item>
                     <item>P.S. I Love You, dir. R. LaGravenese, USA (2007) [drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Enchanted, dir. K. Lima, USA (2007) [animation, comedy, family]</item>
                     <item>Music and Lyrics, dir. M. Lawrence, USA (2007) [comedy, music,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Mamma Mia!, dir. Ph. Lloyd, USA, UK, Germany (2007) [comedy, musical,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Definitely, Maybe, dir. A. Brooks, USA (2008) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Made of Honor, dir. P. Weiland, USA, UK (2008) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>27 Dresses, dir. A. Fletcher, USA (2008) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Sex and the City, dir. M. P. King, USA (2008) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>The Sisterhood of the Traveling ants 2, dir. S. Hamri, USA (2008)
                        [comedy, drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>The Time Traveler’s Wife, dir. R. Schwentke, USA (2008) [drama, fantasy,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Bride Wars, dir. G. Winick, USA (2009) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>He’s Just Not That Into You, dir. K. Kwapis, Germany, USA (2009) [comedy,
                        drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>The Proposal, dir. A. Fletcher, USA (2009) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Couples Retreat, dir. P. Billingsley, USA (2009) [comedy]</item>
                     <item>Julie and Julia, dir. N. Ephron, USA (2009) [biography, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>The Ugly Truth, dir. R. Luketic, USA (2009) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Labor Pains, dir. L. Shapiro, USA (2009) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Valentine’s Day, dir. G. Marshall, USA (2009) [comedy romance]</item>
                     <item>The Switch, dir. J. Gordon, W. Speck, USA (2010) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Letters to Juliet, dir. G. Winnick, USA (2010) [adventure, comedy,
                        drama]</item>
                     <item>Dear John, dir. L. Hallström, USA (2010) [drama, romance, war]</item>
                     <item>The Back-Up Plan, dir. A. Poul, USA (2010) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Sex in the City, dir. M. P. King, USA (2010) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Easy A, dir. W. Gluck, USA (2010) [comedy, drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Something Borrowed, dir. L. Greenfield, USA [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Love, Wedding, Marriage, dir. D. Mulroney, USA (2011) [comedy]</item>
                     <item>Bridesmaids, dir. P. Feig, USA (2011) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Crazy, Stupid Love, dir. G. Ficarra, J. Requa, USA (2011) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>What to Expect When You’re Expecting, dir. K. Jones, USA (2012) [comedy,
                        drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Pitch Perfect, dir. J. Moore, USA (2012) [comedy, music, romance]</item>
                     <item>Safe Have, dir. L. Hallström, USA (2012) [drama, romance,
                        thriller]</item>
                     <item>About Time, dir. R. Curtis, UK (2013) [comedy, drama, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>The Other Woman, dir. N. Cassavetes, USA (2014) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>The Single Moms Club, dir. T. Perry, USA (2014) [comedy, drama]</item>
                     <item>Lila and Eve, dir. Ch. Stone III, USA (2015) [crime, drama,
                        mystery]</item>
                     <item>How to Be Single, dir. Ch. Ditter, USA (2016) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Home Again, dir. H. Meyers-Shyer, USa (2017) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Crazy Rich Indians, dir. J. M. Chu, USA (2018) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Book Club, dir. B. Holderman, USA (2018) [comedy, drama, romance]</item>
                  </list></item>
               <item><list type="unordered">
                     <head>Romance</head>
                     <item>It happened One Night, dir. F. Capra, USA (1934) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>The Last of the Mohicans, dir. G. B. Seitz, USA (1936) [adventure, drama,
                        history]</item>
                     <item>A Star is Born, dir. W. W. Wellman, J. Conway, USA (1937) [drama]</item>
                     <item>Gone with the Wind, dir. V. Flemming, G. Cukor, USA (1939) [drama,
                        history, romance]</item>
                     <item>Rebecca, dir. A. Hitchcock, USA (1940) [drama, mystery, romance]</item>
                     <item>Casablanca, dir. M. Curtiz, USA (1942) [drama, romance, war]</item>
                     <item>Brief Encounter, dir. D. Lean, USA (1945) [drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>The Best Years of Our Lives, dir. W. Wyler, USA (1946) [drama, romance,
                        war]</item>
                     <item>Out of the Past, dir. J. Tourneur, USA (1947) [crime, drama,
                        film-noir]</item>
                     <item>Singin’ in the Rain, dir. S. Donen, G. Kelly, USA (1952) [comedy,
                        musical, romance]</item>
                     <item>Roman Holiday, dir. W. Wyler, USA (1953) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>A Star is Born, dir. G. Cukor, USA (1954) [drama, musical,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Vertigo, dir. A. Hitchcock, USA (1958) [mystery, romance,
                        thriller]</item>
                     <item>Some Like It Hot, dir. B. Wilder, USA (1959) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>The Apartment, dir. B. Wilder, USA (1960) [comedy, drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Charade, dir. S. Donen, USA (1963) [comedy, mystery, romance]</item>
                     <item>Doctor Zhivago, dir. D. Lean, USA, Italy, UK (1965) [drama, romance,
                        war]</item>
                     <item>Sounds of Music, dir. R. Wise, USA (1965) [biography, drama,
                        family]</item>
                     <item>The Gradate, dir. M. Nichols, USA (1967) [comedy, drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Fiddler on the Roof, dir. N. Jewison, USA (1971) [drama, family,
                        musical]</item>
                     <item>Harold and Maude, dir. H. Ashby, USA (1971) [comedy, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>A Star is Born, dir. F. Pierson (1976) [drama, music, romance]</item>
                     <item>Annie Hall, dir. W. Allen, USA (1977) [comedy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Manhattan, dir. W. Allen, USA (1979) [comedy, drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Out of Africa, dir. S. Pollack, USA, UK (1985) [biography, drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>The Princess Bride, dir. R. Reiner, USA (1987) [adventure, family,
                        fantasy]</item>
                     <item>The Last of the Mohicans, dir. M. Mann, USA (1992) [action, adventure,
                        drama]</item>
                     <item>Groundhog Day, dir. H. Ramis, USA (1993) [comedy, fantasy,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Forrest Gump, dir. R. Zemeckis, USA (1994) [drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Legends of the Fall, dir. E. Zwick, USA (1994) [drama, romance,
                        war]</item>
                     <item>Before Sunrise, dir. R. Linklater, USA (1995) [drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Good Will Hunting, dir. G. Van Sant, USA (1997) [drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>The English Patient, dir. A. Minghella, USA, UK (1997) [drama, romance,
                        war]</item>
                     <item>The Horse Whisperer, dir. R. Redford, USA (1998) [drama, romance,
                        western]</item>
                     <item>Big Fish, dir. T. Burton, USA (2003) [adventure, drama, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Before Sunset, dir. R. Linklater (2004), USA [drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Eternal Sunshine of the Spotless Mind, dir. M. Gondry, USA (2004) [drama,
                        romance, sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Once, dir. J. Carney, Ireland (2007) [drama, music, romance]</item>
                     <item>Slumdog Millionaire, dir. D. Boyle, L. Tandan, UK, USA, France, Germany,
                        India (2008) [drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Mr Nobody, dir. J. Van Dormael, USA (2009) [drama, fantasy,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>The Perks of Being a Wallflower, dir. S. Chbosky, USA (2012) [drama,
                        romance]</item>
                     <item>Before Midnight, dir. R. Linklater, USA (2013) [drama, romance]</item>
                     <item>Her, dir. S. Jonze, USA (2013) [drama, romance, sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Sing Street, dir. J. Carney, Ireland, UK, USA (2016) [comedy, drama,
                        music]</item>
                     <item>La La Land, dir. D. Chazelle, USA, Hing Kong (2016) [comedy, drama,
                        music]</item>
                     <item>A Star is Born, dir. B. Cooper, USA (2018) [drama, music, romance]</item>
                  </list></item>
               <item><list type="unordered">
                     <head>Superhero</head>
                     <item>Superman, dir. R. Donner, USA, UK, Switzerland, Canada, Panama (1978)
                        [action, adventure, drama]</item>
                     <item>Superman II, dir. R. Lester, R. Donner, USA, UK, Canada (1980) [action,
                        adventure, sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Superman III, dir. R. Lester, UK, USA (1983) [action, comedy,
                        sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Batman, dir. T. Burton, USA (1989) [action, adventure]</item>
                     <item>Batman Returns, dir. T. Burton, USA (1992) [action, crime,
                        fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Batman Forever, dir. J. Schumacher, USA (1995) [action, adventure,
                        fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Batman and Robin, dir. J. Schumacher, USA, UK (1997) [action,
                        sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Spider-Man, dir. S. Raimi, USA (2002) [action, adventure, sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Spider-Man 2, dir. S. Raimi, USA (2004) [action, adventure,
                        sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Batman Begins, dir. Ch. Nolan, USA (2005) [action, adventure,
                        thriller]</item>
                     <item>V for Vendetta, dir. J. McTeigue, USA (2005) [action, drama,
                        sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Superman Returns, dir. B. Singer, USA (2006) [action, adventure]</item>
                     <item>Spider-Man 3, dir. S. Raimi, USA (2007) [action, adventure,
                        sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>The Dark Knight, dir. Ch. Nolan, USA (2008) action, crime, drama] </item>
                     <item>Iron Man, dir. J. Favreau, USA (2008) [action, adventure, sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Thor, dir. K. Branagh, USA (2011) [action, adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>The Amazing Spider-Man, dir. M. Webb, USA (2012) [action, adventure,
                        fantasy]</item>
                     <item>The Avengers, dir. J. Whedon, USA (2012) [action, adventure,
                        sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>The Dark Knight Rises, dir. Ch. Nolan, USA (2012) [action,
                        thriller]</item>
                     <item>Thor: The Dark World, dir. A. Taylor, USA (2013) [action, adventure,
                        fantasy]</item>
                     <item>The Amazing Spider-Man 2, dir. M. Webb, USA (2014) [action, adventure,
                        sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>The Avengers: Age of Ultron, dir. J. Whedon, USA (2015) [action,
                        adventure, sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Deadpool, dir. T. Miller, USA (2016) [action, adventure, comedy]</item>
                     <item>Doctor Strange, dir. S. Derrickson, USA (2016) [action, adventure,
                        fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Logan: Wolverine, dir. J. Manglod, USA (2017) [action, drama,
                        sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Thor: Ragnarok, dir. T. Waititi, USA (2017) [action, adventure,
                        comedy]</item>
                     <item>The Avengers: Infinity War, dir. A. Russo, J. Russo, USA (2018) [action,
                        adventure, fantasy]</item>
                  </list></item>
               <item><list type="unordered">
                     <head>Thriller</head>
                     <item>The Third Man, dir. C. Reed, UK (1949) [film-noir, mystery,
                        thriller]</item>
                     <item>Dial M for Murder, dir. A. Hitchcock, USA (1954) [crime, thriller]</item>
                     <item>Double Indemnity, dir. B. Wilder, USA (1954) [crime, drama,
                        film-noir]</item>
                     <item>On the Waterfront, dir. E. Kazan, USA (1954) [crime, drama,
                        thriller]</item>
                     <item>Rear Window, dir. A. Hitchcock, USA (1954) [mystery, thriller]</item>
                     <item>North by Nothwest, dir. A. Hitchcock, USA (1959) [adventure, mystery,
                        thriller]</item>
                     <item>Psycho, dir. A. Hitchcock, USA (1960) [horror, mystery, thriller]</item>
                     <item>What Ever Happened to Baby Jane?, dir. R. Aldrich, USA (1962) [drama,
                        horror, thriller]</item>
                     <item>Chinatown, dir. R. Polanski, USA (1974) [drama, mystery, thriller]</item>
                     <item>Blade Runner, dir. R. Scott, USA, Hong Kong (1982) [sci-fi,
                        thriller]</item>
                     <item>Die Hard, dir. J. McTiernan, USA (1988) [action, thriller]</item>
                     <item>Silence of the Lambs, dir. J. Demme, USA (1991) [crime, drama,
                        thriller]</item>
                     <item>Reservoir Dogs, dir. Q. Tarantino, USA (1992) [crime, drama, thriller] </item>
                     <item>Léon, dir. L. Besson, France, USA (1994) [crime, drama, thriller]</item>
                     <item>The Heat, dir. M. Mann, USA (1995) [crime, drama, thriller]</item>
                     <item>Pulp Fiction, dir. Q. Tarantino, USA (1994) [crime, drama]</item>
                     <item>The Usual Suspects, dir. B. Singer USA, Germany (1995) [crime, mystery,
                        thriller]</item>
                     <item>Fargo, dir. J. and E. Coen, USA (1996) [crime, drama, thriller]</item>
                     <item>L.A. Confidential, dir. C. Hanson, USA (1997) [crime, drama,
                        mystery]</item>
                     <item>Seven, dir. D. Fincher, USA (1997) [crime, drama, mystery]</item>
                     <item>The Sixth Sense, dir. M. Night Shyamalan, USA (1999) [drama, mystery,
                        thriller]</item>
                     <item>Memento, dir. Ch. Nolan, USA (2000) [mystery, thriller]</item>
                     <item>Donnie Darko, dir. R. Kelly, USA (2001) [drama, sci-fi, thriller]</item>
                     <item>Mulholland Drive, dir. D. Lynch, USA (2001) [drama, mystery,
                        thriller]</item>
                     <item>Kill Bill dir. Q. Tarantino, USA (2003) [action, crime, thriller]</item>
                     <item>The Departed, dir. M. Scorsese, USA (2006) [crime, drama,
                        thriller]</item>
                     <item>The Prestige, dir. Ch. Nolan, USA, Hong Kong (2006) [drama, mystery,
                        sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>No Country for Old Men, dir. A. and J. Coen, USA (2007) [crime, drama,
                        thriller]</item>
                     <item>Shutter Island, dir. M. Scorsese, USA (2010) [mystery, thriller]</item>
                     <item>Prisoners, dir. D. Villeneuve, USA (2013) [crime, drama, mystery]</item>
                     <item>Gone Girl, dir. D. Fincher, USA (2014) [crime, drama, mystery]</item>
                     <item>Room, dir. L. Abrahamson, USA (2015) [drama, thriller]</item>
                     <item>Vampire</item>
                     <item>Dr Terror’s House of Horrors, dir. F. Francis, UK (1965) [horror]</item>
                     <item>Lust for a Vampire, dir. J. Sangster, UK (1971) [horror]</item>
                     <item>Dracula, dir. F. Ford Coppola, USA (1992) [horror]</item>
                     <item>Interview with the Vampire: The Vampire Chronicles, dir. N. Jordan, USA
                        (1994) [drama, horror]</item>
                     <item>From Dusk till Dawn, dir. R. Rodriguez, USA (1996) [action, crime,
                        horror]</item>
                     <item>Blade, dir. S. Norrington, USA (1998) [action, horror, sci-fi]</item>
                     <item>Underworld, dir. L. Wiseman, USA, UK, Germany, Hungary (2003) [action,
                        fantasy, thriller]</item>
                     <item>Van Helsing, dir. S. Sommers, USA, Czech Republic (2004) [action,
                        adventure, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Twilight, dir. C. Hardwicke, USA (2008) [drama, fantasy, romance]</item>
                     <item>Jennifer’s Body, dir. K. Kusama, USA (2009) [comedy, horror]</item>
                     <item>The Twilight Saga: New Moon, sir. Ch. Weitz, USA (2009) [adventure,
                        drama, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>The Twilight Saga: Eclipse, dir. D. Slade, USA (2010) [adventure, drama,
                        fantasy]</item>
                     <item>The Twilight Saga: Breaking Dawn Part 1, dir. B. Condon, USA (2011)
                        [adventure, drama, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>The Twilight Saga: Breaking Dawn Part 2, dir. B. Condon, USA (2012)
                        [adventure, drama, fantasy]</item>
                     <item>Dark Shadows, dir. T. Burton, USA, Australia (2012) [comedy, fantasy,
                        horror]</item>
                     <item>The Mortal Instruments: City of Bones, dir. H. Zwart, USA, Germany,
                        Canada, UK (2013) [action, fantasy, horror]</item>
                     <item>Vampire Academy, dir. M. Waters, USA, UK (2014) [action, comedy,
                        drama]</item>
                     <item>Goosebumps, R. Letterman, USA, Australia (2016) [adventure, comedy,
                        family]</item>
                  </list></item>
            </list>
         </div>

      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="acerbi2013" label="Acerbi et al. 2013">Acerbi A, Lampos V., Garnett P.,
               and Bentley A. R. <title rend="quotes">The Expression of Emotions in 20th Century
                  Books</title>, <title rend="italic">PLoS ONE</title> 8(3) (2013): e59030, doi:
               10.1371/journal.pone.0059030.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="altman1999" label="Altman 1999">Altman, R. <title rend="italic"
                  >Film/Genre</title>. British Film Institute, London (1999). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="banos-pinero2013" label="Baños-Piñero et al. 2013">Baños-Piñero, R.,
               Bruti, S. and Zanotti, S (eds) <title rend="italic">Perspectives: Studies in
                  Translatology. Special Issue: Corpus Linguistics and Audiovisual Translation: In
                  Search of an Integrated Approach</title>, 21(4) (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bastian2009" label="Bastian et al. 2009">Bastian, M., Heymann, S. and
               Jacomy, M. <title rend="quotes">Gephi: An Open Source Software for Exploring and
                  Manipulating Networks</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                  International AAAI Conference on Weblogs and Social Media</title>, San Jose, Ca
               (2009).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bateman2016" label="Bateman et al. 2016">Bateman, J. A., Tseng, Chiao-I.,
               Seizov, O., Jacobs, A., Lüdtke, A., Müller, M. G. and Herzog, O. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Towards Next-generation Visual Archives: Image, Film and Discourse</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Visual Studies</title> 31 (2016); pp. 131-154.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baxter2014a" label="Baxter 2014a">Baxter, M. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Cinemetric Data Analysis</title> (2014), <ref
                  target="http://www.cinemetrics.lv/dev/Cinemetrics_Book_Baxter.pdf"
                  >http://www.cinemetrics.lv/dev/Cinemetrics_Book_Baxter.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baxter2014b" label="Baxter 2014b">Baxter, M. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Quantitative Film Studies [a bibliography]</title> (2014), <ref
                  target="http://www.cinemetrics.lv/dev/bibliography_with_essay_Baxter.pdf"
                  >http://www.cinemetrics.lv/dev/bibliography_with_essay_Baxter.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bednarek2010" label="Bednarek 2010">Bednarek, M. <title rend="italic">The
                  Language of Fictional Television. Drama and Identity</title>, Continuum, London –
               New York (2010). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bednarek2011" label="Bednarek 2011">Bednarek, M. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Stability of the Televisual Character: A Corpus Stylistic Case Study</title>. In
               R. Piazza, M. Bednarek and F. Rossi F. (eds), <title rend="italic">Telecinematic
                  Discourse</title>. Approaches to the Language of Films and Television Series, John
               Benjamins, Amsterdam – Philadelphia (2011), pp.185–204. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bednarej2017" label="Bednarek and Zago 2017">Bednarek and M., Zago, R.
                  <title rend="quotes">Bibliography of Linguistic Research on Fictional (Narrative,
                  Scripted) Television Series and Films/Movie, Version 1</title> (2017), <ref
                  target="http://unipv.academia.edu/RaffaeleZago"
                  >http://unipv.academia.edu/RaffaeleZago</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bednarek2018" label="Bednarek 2018">Bednarek, M. <title rend="italic"
                  >Language and Television Series: A Linguistic Approach to Television
                  Dialogue</title>. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bondebjerg2015" label="Bondebjerg 2015">Bondebjerg, I. <title
                  rend="quotes">Film: Genres and Genre Theory</title>. In J. D. Wright (ed.), <title
                  rend="italic">International Encyclopedia of the Social and Behavioral
                  Sciences</title>, 2nd edition, Vol 9, Oxford (2015), pp. 160–164.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bobrowski2015" label="Bobrowski 2015">Bobrowski, J. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Płaszczyzny stylizacji językowej w dialogu filmowym</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Polonica</title>, 35 (2015): 179–189. <ref
                  target="http://dx.doi.org./10.17651/POLON.35.14"
                  >http://dx.doi.org./10.17651/POLON.35.14</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="burrows2002" label="Burrows 2002">Burrows, J. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Englishing of Juvenal: Computational Stylistics and Translated Texts</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Style</title> 36 (4) (2002): 677-698.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="burrows1987" label="Burrows 1987">Burrows, J. <title rend="italic"
                  >Computation into Criticism: A Study of Jane Austen's Novels and an Experiment in
                  Method</title>, Clarendon, Oxford (1987).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="burrows1994" label="Burrows 1994">Burrows, J. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Tiptoeing into the Infinite: Testing for Evidence of National Differences in the
                  Language of English Narrative</title>, <title rend="italic">Research in Humanities
                  Computing</title> 2 (1994): pp 1-33.</bibl>
         	<bibl xml:id="byszuk2017" label="Byszuk 2017">Byszuk, J. <title rend="italic">The Voices of 
         		Doctor Who</title> 2017. <ref target="https://ruj.uj.edu.pl/xmlui/handle/item/222426">https://ruj.uj.edu.pl/xmlui/handle/item/222426</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chandler1997" label="Chandler 1997">Chandler, D. <title rend="italic">An
                  Introduction to Genre Theory</title> (1997), <ref
                  target="http://www.aber.ac.uk/media/Documents/intgenre/chandler_genre_theory.pdf"
                  >http://www.aber.ac.uk/media/Documents/intgenre/chandler_genre_theory.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="craig2009" label="Craig and Kinney 2009">Craig, H. and Kinney, A. <title
                  rend="quotes">Shakespeare, Computers, and the Mystery of Authorship</title>,
               Cambridge University Press, Cambridge (2009).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cutting2011" label="Cutting et al. 2011">Cutting, J. E., Brunick, K. L.,
               DeLong, J. E. and Iricinschi, C. <title rend="quotes">Quicker, Faster, Darker:
                  Changes in Hollywood Film over 75 Years</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >i-Perception</title> 2 (2011): pp 569-576.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="choinski2019" label="Choiński et al. 2019">Choiński, M., Eder, M. and
               Rybicki, J. <title rend="quotes">Harper Lee and Other People: A Stylometric
                  Diagnosis</title>, <title rend="italic">Mississippi Quarterly</title>, 70(3):
               355-374.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eder2016" label="Eder et al. 2016">Eder, M., Rybicki and J., Kestemont, M.
                  <title rend="quotes">Stylometry with R: A Package for Computational Text
                  Analysis</title>, <title rend="italic">R Journal</title> 8 (1) (2016):
               107-121.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eder2017" label="Eder 2017">Eder, M. <title rend="quotes">Visualization in
                  Stylometry: Cluster Analysis Using Networks</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital
                  Scholarship in the Humanities</title> 32 (1) (2017): 50-64</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="evert2017" label="Evert et al. 2017">Evert, S., Proisl, T., Jannidis, F.,
               Reger, I., Pielström, S., Schöch, C. and Vitt, T. <title rend="quotes">Understanding
                  and Explaining Delta Measures for Authorship Attribution</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> 32 (sup. 2) (2017):
               4-16.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="freddi2013" label="Freddi 2013">Freddi M. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Constructing a Corpus of Translated Films: A Corpus View of Dubbing</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Perspectives: Studies in Translatology</title>, 21 (4)
               (2013): 491–503. DOI: 10.1080/0907676X.2013.831925.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="freddi2009" label="Freddi and Pavesi 2009">Freddi M. and Pavesi M. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Pavia Corpus of Film Dialogue: Methodology and Research
                  Rationale</title>. In M. Freddi, M. Pavesi (eds), <title rend="italic">Analysing
                  Audiovisual Dialogue: Linguistic and Translational Insights</title>, Clueb,
               Bologna (2009), pp. 95–100.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="freedman2015" label="Freedman 2015">Freedman, J. <title rend="italic">The
                  Cambridge Companion to Alfred Hitchcock</title>, Cambridge University Press,
               Cambridge, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="grant2003" label="Grant 2003">Grant, B.K. (ed.). <title rend="italic">Film
                  Genre Reader</title>. University of Texas Press, Austin ([1984] 2003).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="heiss2005" label="Heiss and Soffritti 2005">Heiss, Ch. and Soffritti, M.
                  <title rend="quotes">Parallelkorpora <q>gesprochener Sprache</q> aus Filmdialogen?
                  Ein multimedialer Ansatz für das Sprachenpaar Deutsch-Italienisch</title>. In J.
               Schwitalla, E. Wegstein (eds) <title rend="italic">Korpus Linguistik Deutsch –
                  synchron, diachron, kontrastiv</title>, Niemeyer, Tübingen (2005): 207-217.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="heftberger2018" label="Heftberger 2018">Heftberger, A. <title
                  rend="italic">Digital Humanities and Film Studies</title>, Springer, Berlin
               (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hendrykowski1999" label="Hendrykowski 1999">Hendrykowski, M. <title
                  rend="italic">Język ruchomych obrazów</title>, Ars Nova, Poznań (1999).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hermann2015" label="Hermann et al. 2015">Herrmann, J. B., van Dalen-Oskam,
               K. and Schoech C. <title rend="quotes">Revisiting Style, a Key Concept in Literary
                  Studies</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Literary Theory</title> 9 (1)
               (2015): 25-52.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hayles2010" label="Hayles 2010">Hayles, K. N. <title rend="quotes">How We
                  Read: Close, Hyper, Machine</title>, <title rend="italic">ADE Bulletin</title>,
               150, (2010): 62-79. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="holobut2016" label="Hołobut et al. 2016">Hołobut, A., Rybicki, J. and
               Woźniak, M. <title rend="quotes">Stylometry on the Silver Screen: Authorial and
                  Translatorial Signals in Film Dialogue</title>, Digital Humanities 2016:
               Conference Abstracts, Jagiellonian University and Pedagogical University, Krakow
               (2016): pp. 561–565.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="holobut2017a" label="Hołobut et al. 2017">Hołobut, A., Rybicki, J. and
               Woźniak, M. <title rend="quotes">Old Questions, New Answers: Computational Stylistics
                  in Audiovisual Translation Research</title>. In M. Deckert (ed), <title
                  rend="italic">Audiovisual Translation: Research and Use</title>, Peter Lang,
               Frankfurt (2017): pp. 203-216.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="holobut2017b" label="Hołobut and Woźniak 2017">Hołobut, A. and Woźniak, M.
                  <title rend="italic">Historia na ekranie: Gatunek filmowy a przekład
                  audiowizualny</title>, Wydawnictwo UJ, Kraków.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="holobut2018" label="Hołobut and Rybicki 2018">Hołobut, A. and Rybicki, J.
                  <title rend="quotes">Pride and Prejudice and Programming: A Stylometric
                  Analysis</title>. In L. Raw (ed), <title rend="italic">Adapted from the Original:
                  Essays on the Value and Values of Works Remade for a New Medium</title>,
               McFarland, Jefferson (2018): pp. 134-147.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hoover2007" label="Hoover 2007">Hoover, D. <title rend="quotes">Corpus
                  Stylistics, Stylometry, and the Styles of Henry James</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Style</title> 41(2) (2007): 174-203.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hough1969" label="Hough 1969">Hough, G. <title rend="italic">Style and
                  Stylistics</title>, Routledge &amp; Kegan Press, London (1969).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jaeckle2013" label="Jaeckle 2013">L. Jaeckle (ed), <title rend="italic"
                  >Film Dialogue</title>, Wallflower Press, London – New York (2013). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jockers2016" label="Jockers 2016">Jockers, M. L. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Syuzhet: Extracts Sentiment and Sentiment-Derived Plot Arcs from Text</title>
                  (2016)<hi rend="italic">,</hi>
               <ref target="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/syuzhet/index.htm"
                  >https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/syuzhet/index.htm</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jockers2017" label="Jockers 2017">Jockers, M. L. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Resurrecting a Low Pass Filter (well, kind of)</title>, Matthew L. Jockers Blog
               (2017), <ref target="http://www.matthewjockers.net/2017/01/12/resurrecting/"
                  >http://www.matthewjockers.net/2017/01/12/resurrecting/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="juola2015" label="Juola 2015">Juola, P. <title rend="quotes">The Rowling
                  Case: A Proposed Standard Analytic Protocol for Authorship Questions</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship the Humanities</title> 30 (supp. 1):
               100-113. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kozloff2000" label="Kozloff 2000">Kozloff, S. <title rend="italic"
                  >Overhearing Film Dialogue</title>, University of California Press, Berkeley
               (2000).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mckenna1999" label="McKenna et al. 1999">McKenna, W., Burrows, J. and
               Antonia, A. <title rend="quotes">Beckett’s Trilogy: Computational Stylistics and the
                  Nature of Translation</title>, <title rend="italic">Revue Informatique et
                  Statistique dans les Sciences humaine</title>s 35 (1999): 151-171.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mckie2014" label="McKie 2014">McKie, S. <title rend="italic">Screenwriting
                  2.0: What Are the Possibilities of Screenplay <q>Datafication</q>? How the
                  Screenplay as Sata Can Impact Creating and Managing, Presenting and Sharing,
                  Analyzing and Visualizing Textual Screenplay Content</title>, PhD thesis, Royal
               Holloway College, London (2014).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mealand1999" label="Mealand 1999">Mealand, D. <title rend="quotes">Style,
                  Genre, and Authorship in Acts, the Septuagint, and Hellenistic Historians</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 14 (4) (1999):
               479-506.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="milawska-ratajczak2019" label="Miławska-Ratajczak 2019"
               >Miławska-Ratajczak, M. <title rend="italic">Dialog w roli głównej. Polszczyzna we
                  współczesnym kinie na przykładzie wybranych utworów</title>, Universitas, Kraków
               (2019). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mohammad2011" label="Mohammad 2011">Mohammad, S. <title rend="quotes">From
                  Once Upon a Time to Happily Ever After: Tracking Emotions in Novels and Fairy
                  Tales</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the ACL 2011 Workshop on
                  Language Technology for Cultural Heritage, Social Sciences, and Humanities</title>
               (LaTeCH), Portland, OR, June 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mohammad2010" label="Mohammad and Turney 2010">Mohammad, S., and Turney P.
                  <title rend="quotes">Emotions Evoked by Common Words and Phrases: Using Mechanical
                  Turk to Create an Emotion Lexicon</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                  NAACL-HLT 2010 Workshop on Computational Approaches to Analysis and Generation of
                  Emotion in Text</title>, Los Angeles, June 2010.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="moretti2007" label="Moretti 2007">Moretti, F. <title rend="italic">Graphs,
                  Maps, Trees: Abstract Models for Literary History</title>, Verso, London, New York
               (2007). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mosteller1964" label="Mosteller and Wallace 1964">Mosteller, F. and
               Wallace, D. <title rend="quotes">Inference and Disputed Authorship: The
                  Federalist</title>, Addison-Wesley, Reading (1964).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="murtagh2009" label="Murtagh et al. 2009">Murtagh, F, Ganz, A. and McKie,
               S. <title rend="quotes">The Structure of Narrative: The Case of Film Scripts</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Pattern Recognition</title>, 42 (2009): 302 –312.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="piazza2011" label="Piazza 2011">Piazza, R. <title rend="italic">The
                  Discourse of Italian Cinema and Beyond: Let Cinema Speak</title>, Continuum,
               London–New York (2011).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="piazza2011a" label="Piazza et al. 2011">Piazza, R., Bednarek, M. and
               Rossi, F. (eds). <title rend="italic">Telecinematic Discourse: Approaches to the
                  Language of Films and Television Series</title>, John Benjamins,
               Amsterdam–Philadelphia (2011).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pitera1979" label="Pitera 1979">Pitera, Z. <title rend="italic">Miłe kina
                  początki</title>. Wydawnictwa Artystyczne i Filmowe, Warszawa (1979).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="plutchik1980" label="Plutchik 1980">Plutchik, R. <title rend="quotes">A
                  General Psychoevolutionary Theory of Emotion</title>. In R. Plutchik and H.
               Kellerman (eds), <title rend="italic">Emotion: Theory, Research, and Experience: Vol.
                  1. Theories of Emotion</title>, Academic, New York (1980), pp. 3-33.</bibl>
         	<bibl xml:id="plutchik1991" label="Plutchik 1991">Plutchik, R. <title rend="quotes">The 
         	Emotions</title>. University Press of America (1991).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="quaglio2009" label="Quaglio 2009">Quaglio, P. <title rend="italic"
                  >Television Dialogue: The Sitcom Friends vs Natural Conversation</title>, John
               Benjamins, Amsterdam–Philadelphia (2009).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rcore2014" label="R Core Team 2014">R Core Team. <title rend="italic">R: A
                  Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</title>, R Foundation for
               Statistical Computing, Wien (2014), <ref target="http://www.R-project.org/"
                  >http://www.R-project.org/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="richardson2010" label="Richardson 2010">Richardson, K. <title
                  rend="italic">Television Dramatic Discourse: A Sociolinguistic Study</title>,
               Oxford University Press, Oxford (2010).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="romerofresco2009" label="Romero Fresco 2009">Romero Fresco, P. <title
                  rend="quotes">Naturalness in the Spanish Dubbing Language: A Case of Not-so-close
                  Friends</title>, <title rend="italic">Meta</title> 54(1) (2009): 49–72.
               doi:10.7202/029793ar</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rudman2016" label="Rudman 2016">Rudman, J. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Non-Traditional Authorship Attribution Studies of William Shakespeare’s Canon:
                  Some Caveats</title>, <title rend="italic">Biblioteca di Studi di Filologia
                  Moderna: Collana</title>, Riviste e Laboratorio (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rybicki2012" label="Rybicki 2012">Rybicki, J. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Great Mystery of the (Almost) Invisible Translator: Stylometry in
                  Translation</title>. In M. Oakes, M. Ji, <title rend="italic">Quantitative Methods
                  in Corpus-Based Translation Studies</title>, John Benjamins, Amsterdam (2012),
               231-248.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rybicki2017a" label="Rybicki 2017a">Rybicki, J. <title rend="quotes">A
                  Second Glance at a Stylometric Map of Polish Literature</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Forum of Poetics</title> 10 (2017): pp. 6-21.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rybicki2017b" label="Rybicki 2017b">Rybicki, J. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Reading Novels with Statistics: What Numbers of Words Tell Us about Authorship,
                  Genre, or Chronology</title>. In J.A. Dobelman (ed), <title rend="italic">Models
                  and Reality: Festschrift For James Robert Thompson</title>, T&amp;NO Company,
               Chicago (2017), pp. 207-224.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rybicki2018" label="Rybicki 2018">Rybicki, J. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Sentiment Analysis Across Three Centuries of the English Novel: Towards Negative
                  or Positive Emotions?</title> EADH Conference Abstracts, Galway (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rybicki2011" label="Rybicki and Eder 2011">Rybicki, J.and Eder, M. <title
                  rend="quotes">Deeper Delta Across Genres and Languages: Do We Really Need the Most
                  Frequent Words?</title>, <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic
                  Computing</title> 26 (3) (2011): 315-332.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rybicki2013" label="Rybicki and Heydel 2013">Rybicki, J. and Heydel, M.
                  <title rend="quotes">The Stylistics and Stylometry of Collaborative Translation:
                  Woolf's <q>Night and Day</q> in Polish</title>, <title rend="italic">Literary and
                  Linguistic Computing</title> 28 (4) (2013): 708-717.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schmid1994" label="Schmid 1994">Schmid, H. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Probabilistic Part-of-Speech Tagging Using Decision Trees</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Proceedings of International Conference on New Methods in Language
                  Processing</title>, Manchester, UK, 1994.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="salt2007" label="Salt 2007">Salt, B. <title rend="italic">Moving into
                  Pictures: More on Film History, Style, and Analysis</title>, Starword, London
               (2007).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schmidt2012" label="Schmidt 2012">Schmidt, B. <title rend="quotes">Making
                  Downton More Traditional</title> (2012), <ref
                  target="http://www.prochronism.com/2012/04/making-downton-more-traditional.html"
                  >http://www.prochronism.
               com/2012/04/making-downton-more-traditional.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="smith2011" label="Smith and Aldridge 2011">Smith, P. and Aldridge, W.
                  <title rend="quotes">Improving Authorship Attribution: Optimizing Burrows’ Delta
                  Method</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Quantitative Linguistics</title>,
               18(1) (2011): 63–88.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stone1966" label="Stone et al. 1966">Stone, P. J., Dunphy, D.C., and
               Smith, M. S. <title rend="italic">The General Inquirer: A Computer Approach to
                  Content Analysis</title>, MIT Press, Cambridge, MA (1966).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="suchan2016" label="Suchan and Bhatt 2016">Suchan, J. and Bhatt, M. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Geometry of a Scene: On Deep Semantics for Visual Perception
                  Driven Cognitive Film Studies</title>, <title rend="italic">2016 IEEE Winter
                  Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV)</title>, Lake Placid, NY
               (2016), pp. 1-9. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="swafford2015" label="Swafford 2015">Swafford, A. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Problems with the Syuzhet Package</title>, Anglophile in Academia: Annie
               Swafford’s Blog (2015), <ref
                  target="https://annieswafford.wordpress.com/2015/03/02/syuzhet/"
                  >https://annieswafford.wordpress.com/2015/03/02/syuzhet/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tuzzi2018" label="Tuzzi and Cortelazzo 2018">Tuzzi, A. and Cortelazzo, M.
               (eds), <title rend="italic">Drawing Elena Ferrante’s Profile</title>, Padova
               University Press, Padova (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="valentini2008" label="Valentini 2008">Valentini, C. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Forlixt1: The Forli Corpus of Screen Translation: Exploring
                  Macrostructures</title>. In D. Chiaro, D. Heiss, Ch. Bucaria (eds), <title
                  rend="italic">Between Text and Image: Updating Research in Screen
                  Translation</title>, John Benjamins, Amsterdam–Philadelphia (2008), pp. 37–51. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="valentini2009" label="Valentini and Linardi 2009">Valetini, C. and Linardi
               S. <title rend="quotes">Forlixt 1: A Multimedia Database for AVT Research</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">inTRAlinea</title>, Special Issue: The Translation of
               Dialects in Multimedia (2009), <ref
                  target="http://www.intralinea.org/specials/article/Forlixt_1_A_multimedia_database_for_AVT_research"
                  >http://www.intralinea.org/specials/article/Forlixt_1_A_multimedia_database_for_AVT_research</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vanzyl2016" label="Van Zyl and Botha 2016">Van Zyl, M. And Botha Y. <title
                  rend="quotes">Stylometry and Characterisation in <title rend="italic">The Big Bang
                     Theory</title></title>, <title rend="italic">Literator</title>, 37 (2), a1282
               (2016), <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.4102/lit.v37i2.1282"
                  >http://dx.doi.org/10.4102/lit.v37i2.1282</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="verianopinto2014" label="Veirano Pinto 2014">Veirano Pinto M. <title
                  rend="quotes">Dimensions of Variation in North American Movies</title>. In T.
               Berber Sardinha, M. Veirano Pinto (eds), <title rend="italic">Multi-Dimensional
                  Analysis, 25 Years On: A Tribute to Douglas Biber</title>, John Benjamins,
               Amsterdam–Philadelphia (2014), pp. 109–147. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vickers2002" label="Vickers 2002">Vickers, B. <title rend="italic"
                     ><q>Counterfeiting</q> Shakespeare: Evidence, Authorship, and John Ford's
                  Funerall Elegye</title>, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge (2002).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vickers2011" label="Vickers 2011">Vickers, B. <title rend="italic"
                  >Authorship Attribution Studies and Shakespeare's Canon (A Review of Shakespeare,
                  Computers, and the Mystery of Authorship</title>, <title rend="italic">Shakespeare
                  Quarterly</title> 62 (1) (2011): 106-142.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zago2016" label="Zago 2016">Zago, R. <title rend="italic">From Originals
                  to Remakes. Colloquiality in English Film Dialogue Over Time</title>, Bonanno
               Editore, Acireale/Roma (2016). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zago2018" label="Zago 2018">Zago, R. <title rend="italic">Cross-Linguistic
                  Affinities in Film Dialogue</title>, Sike, Roma (2018). </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
