<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article">Old Ways for Linking Texts in the Digital Reading Environment: The
               Case of the Thompson Chain Reference Bible</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
               <dhq:author_name>Brent <dhq:family>Nelson</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Saskatchewan</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>brent.nelson@usask.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Brent Nelson is Associate Professor of English at the University of
                     Saskatchewan. Most of his current research employs digital approaches of one
                     kind or another. He is director of the John Donne Society’s Digital Prose
                     Project, and with Richard Cunningham is leading the Textual Studies research
                     team on INKE (Implementing New Knowledge Environments). He is also general
                     editor of a digital archive of primary materials related to early modern
                     collections of curiosities. </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
               <dhq:author_name>Jon <dhq:family>Bath</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Saskatchewan</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>jon.bath@usask.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Jon Bath is the Director of the Humanities and Fine Arts Digital Research
                     Centre at the University of Saskatchewan. His research focuses on the
                     relationship between the linguistic content and the form of textual objects,
                     with a special interest in typography and relational databases. He is the
                     co-lead, along with Jon Saklofske, of the INKE Modelling and Prototyping team
                     and is a member of the JackPine Press collective.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000137</idno>
            <idno type="volume">006</idno>
            <idno type="issue">2</idno>
            <date when="2012-10-12">12 October 2012</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
         <change when="2012-08-15" who="MCC">encoded file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
            <p>This paper will briefly survey the historical development of linking systems in the
               Christian Bible, from their theological foundations to their formation in the
               architecture of the printed book. It will then examine the apogee of intra-Biblical
               linking systems in the Thompson Chain Reference Bible, particularly its
               chain-referencing system for thematic linking between texts. Finally, it will use
               this mature print technology to consider the state of the hyperlink in current
               Web-interfaces. It will show that while in many ways modern attempts at a dynamic
               hyperlink surpass this elaborate linking system in functionality, in a few key
               functions this old print technology out-performs what is commonly and readily
               available in current Web-browsers. In pursing this comparative analysis we aim to
               demonstrate the importance of understanding the organization and navigational
               structure of the codex in designing digital reading environments that will meet and
               surpass the affordances of print.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
            <p>What can the book teach the app?</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>Old Ways for Linking Texts in the Digital Reading Environment: The Case of the
            Thompson Chain Reference Bible</head>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>INKE (Implementing New Knowledge Environments) is a humanities-led project whose
               mandate is to inform and influence the development of reading technologies to ensure
               that the needs of the most exacting of readers (principally, scholars) are met [<ref target="http://www.inke.ca">www.inke.ca</ref>]. The textual studies team in INKE
               adopts a perspective that is at once historical and critical. Our close attention to
               book history gives us a historical frame in which to assess the present state of
               digital textuality and to inform future developments in reading technology in the
               digital environment. It is from this point of view that the present paper addresses
               what we call the problem of chronologism in this incunable period of digital
               publication. This problem is evinced, on the one hand, in the dismissal of a mature
               technology — print — as an outmoded medium that has already been surpassed, and on
               the other hand, in the popular valorization of the digital medium (still in its
               infancy) and the revolution in publication that it has launched. As a counter-point
               to this bias, and a point of context for the work of the Textual Studies team in the
               larger context of INKE, this paper introduces a powerful system for linking texts, a
               system that in some ways exceeds the capacity of current Web-based hyperlinking, and
               one that was born in print. Indeed, this technology is about 100 years old, and its
               intellectual origins can be traced back almost two millennia. The technology in
               question is the chain-linking referencing system invented by Frank Charles Thompson
               and implemented in his Thompson Chain Reference Bible, first published in 1908. The
               modern iterations of this bible offer powerful reading environments that in many ways
               offer a critique of the digital reading interface. This paper will briefly survey the
               historical development of linking systems in the Christian Bible, from their
               theological foundations to their formation in the architecture of the printed book.
               It will then examine the apogee of intra-Biblical linking systems in the Thompson
               Chain Reference Bible, particularly its chain-referencing system for thematic linking
               between texts. Finally, it will use this mature print technology to consider the
               state of the hyperlink in current Web-interfaces. It will show that, while in many
               ways modern attempts at a dynamic hyperlink surpass this elaborate linking system in
               functionality, in a few key functions, this old print technology out-performs what is
               commonly and readily available in current Web-browsers. In pursuing this comparative
               analysis we aim to demonstrate the importance of understanding the organization and
               navigational structure of the codex in designing digital reading environments that
               will meet and surpass the affordances of print.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>On the Demands of the Reader upon Reading Technology</head>
            <p>The development of reading environments goes as far back as the invention of writing
               supports, but the introduction of print technologies brought new possibilities for
               rich reading environments that could meet the needs of demanding readers. Among the
               most exacting of readers were students of the Christian Bible. Scholars and theorists
               of new media have given scant attention to the achievements of enriched reading
               environments in the modern study Bible, yet in many ways the modern pioneer of the
               genre, the Thompson Chain Reference Bible, anticipated both the hyperlink and the
               graphical interface, foundational and familiar elements of the World Wide Web. Book
               historians have long recognized the Bible as a central site for the development of
               reading technology in western history. For centuries, the Bible has been the focus of
               serious study and scholarship as a sacred text, and the very nature of Christianity
               as a religion of the book has ensured that this text has been subjected to the most
               rigorous demands of readership. This is not to suggest that other readers of sacred
               scriptures weren't demanding, but Christian theology was of a particular nature that
               demanded a certain kind of access for its followers to their sacred text.  From the
               beginning, Christian exegesis was based on placing passages in dialogue with each
               other, an intense and intricate hermeneutic of intra-textuality.  As the poet George
               Herbert expressed it in the seventeenth century:<quote rend="block" source="#canonical">
                  <lg>
                     <l>This verse marks that, and both do make a motion </l>
                     <l>Unto a third, that ten leaves off doth lie:</l>
                     <l>Then as dispersed herbs do watch a potion,</l>
                     <l>These three make up some Christians destinie</l>
                  </lg>
                  <ref type="offline">
                     <title rend="quotes">The H. Scriptures II,</title> lines 5–8</ref>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Christian theology of various stripes was built on theme-based linkages between
               texts. What George Herbert describes here particularly is the hermeneutics of
               typology. The typological method looks to the Old Testament for characters and
               incidents (the <emph>type</emph>) that anticipate or foreshadow by some resemblance
               an element or aspect of the New Testament, particularly in the life of Christ (the
                  <emph>antetype</emph>). This typological habit derives from Jesus’ own method of
               correlating events related to him with historical incidents in the Hebrew Scriptures.
               For example, <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">And just as Moses lifted up the serpent in the
                  wilderness, so must the Son of Man be lifted up, that whoever believes in him may
                  have eternal life</quote>
               <ref type="offline">[John 3:14–15]</ref> alludes to Numbers 21:4–9. In a typological
               reading, Moses’ act of deliverance on the cusp of the Promised Land is taken to be a
               type foreshadowing the crucifixion. This method of correlating Christian teaching
               with Old Testament events is core to St. Paul’s theology and central to the Church
               Fathers.</p>
            <p>This view of the text and what it means to read it made navigation and referencing
               essential to the needs of a Christian reader of the Bible. It is not surprising,
               therefore, to find that a great many of the important developments in reading
               technology were implemented in the course of Bible production, some of which have
               informed book production more widely, and many more that have never extended beyond
               Bible-reading environments. In this paper, we focus on one area of functionality, the
               function of referencing.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Historical Background: The Development of the Reference Bible</head>
            <p>Referencing helps the user to identify and locate a target text and to share that
               location with others. In paper-based reading technologies, referencing is enabled by
               structural divisions and markers in the text. Until these divisions became
               universalized, readers of the Bible relied on scanning large portions of text or on
               mnemonic methods for remembering or referencing particular locations. Thus, textual
               navigation took a big step forward with the introduction of chapter divisions,
               introduced by Stephen Langton, Archbishop of Canterbury, in the early 13th century to
               enable referencing and, in turn, cross-referencing, an important function in his
               system of exegesis <ptr target="#gibson1993" loc="10"/>. The adoption of these
               chapter divisions by the commercialized scriptoria of Paris led to their universal
               implementation. Another divisional marker for navigating the Bible came with the
               numbering of the folio and then the page, but the limitation of this device, unlike
               the universally adopted chapter divisions, was that its use was specific to a
               particular edition and thus could only serve as a device for information exchange if
               two users were using books from the same printing. Introduced to bibles by Erasmus in
               his 1516 edition of the New Testament, pagination (according to Paul Saenger) placed
               a <quote rend="inline" source="#saenger1999">renew[ed] emphasis on the leaf as a locus point</quote> that
                  <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#saenger1999">reflected a concern with precision in text location as an
                  indispensible aid in the painstaking task of textual comparison</quote>
               <ptr target="#saenger1999" loc="35"/></cit>. This move toward greater structural
               granularity was driven by both the humanist passion for textual accuracy and the
               imperative of Christian exegesis. With the Reformation and the printing of the Bible
               in the vernacular, a greater emphasis was placed on public preaching and exegesis,
               adding new motivation for a common and universal referencing system.</p>
            <p>Neither foliation nor pagination made much of an impact on the architecture and
               navigation of early bibles. More important was the introduction of mechanisms for
               locating precise passages within the established chapter divisions. The first major
               development in dividing chapters was the use of marginal alphabets. This feature of
               book architecture began as a purely mental system, known as the Dominican index
               system, developed by Hugh of Saint-Cher in the mid-13th century as a way of thinking
               about and referring to chapters by dividing them into units, imagined either as four
               or seven sections nominated A through D or A through G respectively. By this method,
               a concordance, for example, could reference a particular use of a word by naming an
               imagined point in a numbered chapter with an added measure of specificity — if the
               reader was adept at making such mental calculations, and provided the calculations of
               the creator of the concordance were correspondingly adept. Alphabets were first
               written upon the margins of manuscript Bibles by the Lollards at the end of the 14th
               century in their copies of Wycliffe’s vernacular New Testament, which were intended
               for use by the laity. These were used not as a generalized structuring system for
               navigation, but rather as dedicated pointers to correlate text and paratext. The
               letters were placed in the margins adjacent to the point where each new Gospel or
               Epistle reading for the day began, according to the Use of Salisbury.</p>
            <p>By the mid-16th century, the alphabet system was no longer needed for Bibles, which
               now had standardized verse divisions in place. The first complete numeration of
               verses through the entire Bible was accomplished by another Dominican friar, Santes
               Pagini, in a 1528 Lyonese Bible. Robert Estienne (aka Stephanus) introduced the
               modern verse divisions that are in use today, printing the numbers intra-textually in
               his 1555 Bible to mark these divisions. The Geneva Bible introduced these same verse
               divisions into the English Bible. This development of a largely arbitrary common
               referencing system is unparalleled in print culture.<note>There are other instances
                  of seemingly arbitrary reference systems. For instance, the alphabetic
                  organization of reference material or the use of line numbers to identify specific
                  passages both appear arbitrary but are based upon fixed constraints in the text —
                  either the spelling of the words or the presence of line breaks. What makes the
                  division of the Bible into verses unique is that these divisions had little
                  relation to the actual structural divisions in the text, such as paragraph breaks,
                  and that they have remained constant even though the micro-structural form of the
                  Bible has subsequently changed through the processes of translation, linguistic
                  revision and re-punctuation.</note> The Christian Bible is the unique instance in
               the western tradition of a common text that has acquired a universally adopted,
               canonical referencing system of such granularity. From this canonical referencing
               system grew a series of navigational aids that have made it the most navigable, and
               probably most navigated, book in the western tradition. In particular, it made all
               the more powerful two long-established navigational architectures: the concordance
               and the marginal cross-reference, both of which are common in modern Bibles. The
               concordance works much like an index, pointing from outside the Biblical text to
               passages that contain a particular common word.<note>This first concordance was
                  completed in the 13th century shortly after Stephen Langton’s division of the
                  Books of the Bible into chapters <ptr target="#gibson1993" loc="10–11"/>. With the
                  introduction of verse divisions, they soon became common.</note> Marginal
               cross-references are internal citations that point to a related passage elsewhere in
               the Bible. These are sometimes, but not always, bi-directional. And sometimes one can
               jump from one verse to another, and from there to yet another (and so on), following
               a related theme or idea across the Bible, but usually these linkages are haphazard
               and not so extensive. </p>
            <figure>
               <head>The first modern concordance of the Bible in English. Samuel Newman, <title rend="italic">A Large and Compleat Concordance to the Bible in English</title>
                  2nd ed. (1658). Published by permission of the Thomas Fisher Rare Book Library,
                  University of Toronto.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>An example of the modern marginal cross-reference.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The point of this brief survey is that a particular kind of reading and an increase
               in lay readership motivated this important navigational innovation to enable ease of
               use, and that in this mature medium of print, we have an example of a highly refined,
               sophisticated, and powerful navigational system that developed over time into such an
               essential element of Bible reading that it seems perfectly natural to the text. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>
               <title rend="italic">The Thompson Chain Reference Bible</title> as Reading
               Technology</head>
            <p>A major development in Bible navigation systems came with the publication of the
               Thompson Chain Reference Bible in 1908 by Dr. Frank Charles Thompson. Thompson was
               born in 1858 in Elmira, New York and was ordained in 1879. As a young preacher in the
               late 1800s, Dr. Thompson became dissatisfied with the reference Bibles that were then
               available. He recognized a need for a study Bible that was easy to use and yet
               scholarly, and above all, one that would enable informed navigation of this
               much-travelled text. He started developing a navigational system for his own use,
               which would become his chain-link system. Some members of his congregation saw
               Thompson’s annotated Bible and his linking system and encouraged him to publish it so
               others could benefit from it. In 1908, the first edition of the Thompson Chain
               Reference Bible was printed by Methodists Book Concern of Dobbs Ferry, New York. In
               1913, Thompson partnered with B. B. Kirkbride in Indianapolis, Indiana, to form the
               Kirkbride Bible Company, which publishes the Thompson Chain Reference Bible to this
                  day.<note>The biographical information on Thompson available on the Web derives
                  mostly from Kirkbride’s own website <ref target="http://www.kirkbride.com/thompson-story.asp">http://www.kirkbride.com/thompson-story.asp</ref>.</note> Published
               three-quarters of a century before the World Wide Web, Thompson’s chain-reference
               system in many respects anticipated the modern hyperlink.</p>
            <p>Thompson’s system identifies an extensive list of topics and between five and twenty
               references from throughout the Bible that speak to or exemplify each topic.
               Thompson’s topics are extensive, though selective, and, as one would expect,
               theologically determined.<note>These topics owe a great deal to the long history of
                  such topical indexes culminating in 1Orville James Nave’s topical Bible
                  (essentially a biblical commonplace book) in the 19th century.</note> The topics
               are identified in the margins adjacent to the relevant verse, and each verse is
               linked to the next in a series of references pertaining to the topic, creating a
               chain of links that run through the Bible on each topic. For example, in the margin
               at Matthew 9:9, we see:<quote rend="block" source="#x">
                  <lg>
                     <l> ch. 4.20, Obedience to Christ,</l>
                     <l> [ch. 21.6</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>Detail of Matthew 9:6-10 from The Thompson Chain Reference Bible (1908).</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>This is a link in a chain of topical references, and it points in two directions. It
               points forward to the next point in the chain — Matthew 21.6 (which in turn points to
               Matthew 26.19, and so on). And it also points backward to the first link in the chain
               — Matthew 4.20: that is, one can’t jump to the immediately prior point in the chain,
               but it is possible to jump back to the first and work through the chain to the
               present link, and from there onward to the last. The chains are not intended to be
               exhaustive. For example, at Matthew 9:7 we find a marginal note that says:<quote rend="block" source="#canonical">
                  <lg>
                     <l> See Obedience to Christ</l>
                     <l> [ch.4.20. </l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>The verse is not itself part of the chain, but the marginal note again points us in
               two directions. It points first to the topic, <title rend="quotes">Obedience in
                  Christ,</title> which is listed in an alpha-ordered <title rend="quotes">Subject-Index</title> at the back of the Bible, under <q>O.</q>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>Detail of topic of <title rend="quotes">Obedience</title> from The Thompson
                  Chain Reference Bible (1908).</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Here one can see at once all the links in the chain. The second direction is, again,
               back to the first reference in the chain on this topic, Matthew 4.20. In this way,
               there are really three ways of entering the chain: by a link in the chain, by a
               topically-relevant verse that is not part of the chain but directs the reader to that
               chain, and by means of the topical index in the back. Once in the chain, the user can
               jump forward to the next link, backward to the first link, or to any point in the
               chain through the topical index at the back, effectively enabling the reader to move
               back to a point in the text that has not been visited previously.</p>
            <p>Thompson’s links are not only multi-directional, but also declarative about the
               nature of their linkage. Each link indicates the nature of its target. In the
               instance cited above, the topical title — <title rend="quotes">Obedience to
                  Christ</title> — identifies the content of the linkage: all of the verses in the
               chain have this theme in common. It is also worth noting that in the immediate
               context of these declarative links, one might see themes of related interest pointing
               to other chains, such as <title rend="quotes">Discipleship</title> or <title rend="quotes">Christ’s Power</title> in the context of Matthew 9, or other topics
               related to <title rend="quotes">Obedience</title> in the context of the subject
               index. In this way the reader has access to a web of thematically related links
               intersecting along any given thematic chain.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>
               <title rend="italic">The Thompson Chain Reference Bible</title> in the Digital
               Environment</head>
            <p>Olive Tree Bible Software has developed an electronic version of the Thompson Chain
               Referencing system for use with hand-held devices. Based on the description of the
               product on the company’s website, which features prominently the history of Thomson’s
               bible, together with a summary of its study helps, it appears this new version of the
               Bible is aiming at the same audience that has come to value its print counterpart.
               Given the similarity between the Thompson Chain Reference Bible’s linking system and
               the hyperlink, and more generally the need for making textual connection, one might
               understandably expect an electronic version to exploit the linking functionality so
               brilliantly anticipated in print. Interestingly, the electronic version provides
                  <emph>less</emph> hyperlinking capability than the printed Bible does.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Screen shot of a demonstration of the Thompson Chain Referencing System for
                  iPhone. <ptr target="#olivetree"/>.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The Olive Tree website declares that this system <q>works with any
                  Bible translation in your electronic library,</q> which is not as promising as
               it sounds. The availability of a canonical referencing system would make it a
               relatively simple matter to make this navigational superstructure compatible with any
               of the many versions of the Bible that are available for hand-held devices, but in
               fact it is tied to the versions published in the Olive Tree electronic library. The
               possibilities for this sort of stand-off relationship between canonical structure and
               textual content are illustrated by Paul Dyck’s electronic edition of a
               seventeenth-century <q>concordance</q> or <q>harmony</q> (a cut-and-paste patchwork
               of printed Bibles recomposed to correlate parallel passages in the synoptic Gospels)
               that was produced by Nicholas Ferrar’s community at Little Gidding in Cambridgeshire.
               Dyck and collaborator Stuart Williams developed an application called <title rend="quotes">Gospelgrab</title> to reconstruct these Bible-based documents. Dyck
               uses XML to describe the skeletal structure of the concordance based on the canonical
               referencing system of the Bible. Williams wrote a script in Python that uses these
               references to <q>grab</q> the referenced texts from a public-domain King James Bible
               to populate the structure. One might imagine a similar function for the electronic
               Thompson Chain system, but instead, the long history of refinement in biblical
               navigation stops short at the very point where just such a system seems to lead.</p>
            <p> More disappointing is the lack of link-forward functionality within the text itself.
               In the print version the links are located in the <q>marginal notes</q> directly
               adjacent to the relevant text. In the hand-held version the links are segregated to a
               separate screen so that they function very much like an index that points into the
               text, rather than enabling the user to link through the text. In the Android version,
               the topic number is a hot link that will bring up, in a new window, the full biblical
               text, cued to the nominated verse. To navigate to another verse in the chain,
               however, one must leave the Biblical text and return to the skeletal index. The
               iPhone version is slightly better in that clicking on a link brings up the individual
               text in a pop-up window, leaving the index visible behind it. Crucially, neither
               version allows a true hyperlinking, click-forward function. Looking at the page of a
               printed Thompson Chain Reference Bible, with the topic-number placed in the margin
               beside the text, one could easily imagine clicking on the topic <q>link</q> and
               moving from text to text through the chain of related passages. The Olive Tree
               software does not offer this functionality. Further, given that all of the links are
               already determined, one might also imagine having at each link in the chain the
               option of linking forward <emph>or backward</emph> through the chain. Rather than
               building upon the remarkable functionality of the print architecture of Thompson’s
               system, the electronic version reverts back to a much more traditional index-based
               navigational architecture.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Old Ways of Linking vs. New</head>
            <p>So then, what can be learned from this episode in the history of print? Above all, it
               behooves digital humanists to study and critique such achievements in print as a
               means of evaluating the current state of Web-based knowledge environments in order to
               better articulate desiderata in this new medium. For example, the Thompson Chain
               Reference Bible’s system of chained references immediately calls to mind the
               Web-browser environment where points in different texts link to other points in other
               texts, but there is a crucial difference between the two. In current Web browsers one
               can move forward to another document via a hyperlink or use the <q>Back</q> or
                  <q>History</q> functions to re-visit documents which have already been viewed. In
               the Thompson Chain Reference Bible, one can also use the chain system or the index to
               move backwards through the text to discover previous points in the chain which have
               never been previously visited. The closest Web-based approximation of this behaviour
               is to take advantage of a search engine’s index of links to identify pages that link
               to the page in question; for instance, one can use a standard Google search box to
               determine which pages link to a certain page using the search syntax:
                  <q>link:[URL].</q> For example, <q>link:www.inke.ca</q> locates all the pages that
               link to <ref target="http://www.inke.ca">www.inke.ca</ref> and then presents to the
               user a list of those pages. However, knowledge of this capability is far from
               widespread, and it is not well integrated into the standard functionality of the
               Web-browsing environment.<note>Google states that this is one of the most commonly
                  requested features <ref target="http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2007/02/who-links-to-your-site.html">http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2007/02/who-links-to-your-site.html</ref>. The
                  aforementioned page also features a <q>Links to this post</q> section, which
                  demonstrates Google Blogger’s implementation of a <q>backwards</q> navigation
                  system similar to that of the Thompson Chain Reference Bible.</note> The
               bi-directional capability of the chain system is one capacity of a print-technology
               that electronic environments are just beginning to implement, and imperfectly at
               that.</p>
            <p>The tremendous amount of intellectual labour involved in the creation of the Thompson
               Chain Reference Bible speaks to another issue, one of critical importance as
               ever-increasing amounts of print material are digitized and made available online:
               link-creation. It is not feasible to hand-code the huge number of links that need to
               be added to this material, thus systems have been developed to add links
               automatically. In addition to the obvious time and cost savings over manual creation
               of all these links, automated link creation is considered to be a more exact and
               predictable means to link documents because it is assumed that the link-creation
               algorithms, unlike fallible humans, will be entirely consistent in their linking
               methodologies <ptr target="#truran2007" loc="1–2"/>. A further potential advantage of
               automated-link creation is that the links need not be created ahead of time and can
               instead be generated during browsing. As opposed to the traditional static hypertext,
               which presents the same links to all users, regardless of their interest, dynamic or
               adaptive systems <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#brusilovsky2001">build a model of the goals, preferences and
                  knowledge of each individual user and use this model throughout the interaction
                  with the user</quote>
               <ptr target="#brusilovsky2001" loc="87"/></cit>. A familiar example of this is an online
               bookstore that suggests other books the user might be interested in based on that
               user’s past purchases and browsing history and the purchases of other users with
               similar behaviours. Rather than treating all customers as if they have the same
               interests, this adaptive system can play the role of the helpful sales clerk and
               point the user in the (probably) right direction.</p>
            <p>While adaptive hypertext systems undoubtedly hold great promise for user-centred Web
               experiences, one published study of a system of this sort illustrates very well why
               developing a new interface for information retrieval requires not only technical
               knowledge of search algorithms, but also a humanities-based understanding of how
               complex reading processes work. In his PhD thesis and related article, Jim C. Tam
               discusses a system for creating dynamic links and compares the effectiveness of this
               system to a system with static hypertext links. Interestingly, this study is based on
               the Thompson Chain Reference Bible. Tam and his collaborators found that users,
               especially non-expert users, were more effective at finding information in a
               hypertext Bible with dynamically created links than they were when using one with
               static links based on the Thompson chain referencing system. It is worth examining
               the basis of this comparison. The very prejudice implicit in the terms <q>static</q>
               and <q>dynamic</q> aside (calling them <q>human</q> and <q>machine-made</q> would be
               equally accurate, and perhaps less loaded), the authors arrive at their result by
               stripping the <q>static</q> system of many of its key features and by asking
               questions better suited to the dynamic interface. Users of the dynamic system started
               their queries by being able to do a full-text search of the Bible that generated a
               list of passages containing those words. These search terms were also used for the
               initial dynamic link creation: the system parsed the documents for the search terms
               and made instances of these words and phrases link to each other <ptr target="#tam1997b" loc="350"/>. As the users followed these links their actions
               were used to dynamically create further links. Static users, in contrast, were
               presented with a table of contents that provided little contextual evidence of what
               was contained in each chapter, so the users had to either know, or guess, where to
               begin to look. But, of course, most users of the Thompson Chain Bible would not start
               at the table of contents: they would take advantage of the extensive index to
               immediately narrow their focus. However, test subjects in this study did not have
               access to this index, and thus non-expert users were left guessing as to which
               chapter might contain the information they were looking for. The questions asked of
               the test subjects were also biased towards fact-finding — <quote rend="inline" source="#tam1997a">Name a
                  miracle performed by Jesus</quote>; <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#tam1997a">Name two characters in
                  the Bible who were stoned by the people</quote>
               <ptr target="#tam1997a" loc="141"/></cit> — rather than theme-based enquiry. This
               distinction between fact- and concept-based queries is crucial in understanding the
               performance of these two systems. Search algorithms are very good at pattern
               matching, but not nearly as developed for inferring concepts that are not coded in
               the semantics of a passage. Take for example the topic of <title rend="quotes">obedience to Christ</title> in Matthew 9:9. The editor identifies this passage as
               relevant based on the action of two characters in a scene: Jesus said <q>Follow
                  me,</q> and Matthew responds in a way that indicates, dramatically, his obedience:
               he <q>followed him.</q> Nothing in the semantics of this passage indicates
               obedience.</p>
            <p>Given the prejudices inherent in the test, it is not at all surprising that dynamic
               hypertext was found to be a more effective means for navigating a large text,
               especially when factual information is what is desired. In our desire to create
               systems that adapt to user needs (and to avoid the labor required of manual
               link-creation), we need to continue to look at past systems for information
               navigation, such as the Thompson Chain Bible, to ensure that developers fully
               understand the needs and desiderata of the most exacting users and the corresponding
               affordances of print technologies in these reading domains, so that what is offered
               in new reading environments represents true and authentic advancement in
               functionality. The primary advantage of the Thompson Chain linking system over
               current implementations of dynamic linking is in its facilitation of high-concept
               searching and navigation; it provides thematic linking that cannot be generated by
               keywords alone. Semantic linking systems are currently a long way from replicating
               the associations of a mind trained in the hermeneutics of such a well-developed
               knowledge domain as theology. The obvious disadvantage of the Thompson Chain linking
               system is that it requires editorial direction and is thus inherently biased and
               selective rather than (potentially) exhaustive: it is fixed and non-generative. For
               this reason, it is also necessarily labour-intensive. This sort of editorial work is
               practical in this case only because it is applied to a clearly defined and
               comparatively small domain.</p>
            <p>More important to contemporary information interface designers are the points of
               critique that the Thompson Chain Referencing system brings to bear on the current
               state of link-driven navigation on the Web. There are several ways in which it
               outperforms the commonly used Web-based technology, the standard hyperlink:</p>
            <list type="ordered">
               <item>It provides <q>smart linking,</q> that is, it declares the nature of the
                  targeting link by means of the theme word attached to the numerical references.
                  One of the great annoyances of the vast majority of Web-based linking is that
                  hyperlinks are often blind, giving little or no indication to the reader of the
                  nature or content of the target. </item>
               <item>It provides multi-directional linking, giving the reader the ability to move
                  backward in a thematic chain.</item>
               <item>It enables contextual association of links. For example, in the context of
                  Matthew 9:7 and 9:9, <title rend="quotes">Obedience to Christ</title> gives the
                  reader access to potentially related thematic chains, <title rend="quotes">Apostles Called</title> and <title rend="quotes">Glorifying God.</title>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>None of these functions is necessarily tied to the canonical referencing system of
               the Bible, and each could conceivably be achieved in a Web-based reading environment.
               The further possibilities of a stand-off navigational architecture that locates and
               links through texts that have a common, canonical referencing system at first seems
               uniquely suited to the Christian Bible, but it might well be adapted for other,
               similarly standardized texts such as poetry or drama.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion: a Latter-Day Attempt at Hyperlinking in Print</head>
            <p>This essay began with a critique of chronologism and the assumption that
               technological progress always amounts to gains in functionality. A recent peculiarity
               in print illustrates the sometimes stilted nature of progress in this incunable
               period of digital publication and the very real possibility that what appears to be
               an innovation in reading technology might very well be a step backward. In his book,
                  <title rend="italic">Virtually Anglo Saxon: Old Media, New Media, and Early
                  Medieval Studies in the Late Age of Print</title>, Martin Foys draws attention to
               the awkward situation of his book at the intersection of old and new media: <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#foys2007">Given its subject, there is, of course, a certain irony that this
                  book is a book [i.e. printed book], and also, therefore, <q>nothing like a
                     CD-ROM.</q> Though we might be living in the late age of print, the authority
                  of print remains strong</quote>
               <ptr target="#foys2007" loc="3"/></cit>. As if to illustrate the complexities and sometime
               incongruities of remediation <foreign>à la</foreign> Bolter and Grusin, and perhaps
               as a concession to his new-media conscience, Foys adapts to print the defining
               feature of Web architecture, the hyperlink — at least an approximation of it, and not
               an altogether successful one. Foys describes this referencing system in his
               introduction: <quote rend="block" source="#foys2007">As Vannevar Bush noted long ago, our minds remain
                  associative in function, not linear, and despite the neat sequence of media and
                  theory laid out just above [in his introduction], as a New Media inquiry, the
                  argument of <title rend="italic">Virtually Anglo-Saxon</title> does not, cannot,
                  really, develop in an orderly and linear fashion. While specific New Media
                  theories tend to anchor one discussion or another, other ideas, elsewhere in the
                  book more fully pronounced, continually crop up. Because of this, and because
                  readers may not choose to read this text in a linear order, a number of
                     <q>links</q> (similar to World Wide Web hyperlinks) to germane or explanatory
                  discussions will appear, signified by the → symbol. [→40] These links are only
                  suggestions, and certainly not the only possible ones to be made; they also serve
                  as a reminder of the state of <term>hypermediacy </term>that the printed form has
                  reached, and, further, as an easy example of how New Media has already begun to
                  remediate print. [→16] <ptr target="#foys2007" loc="4"/>.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>It is a clever compromise in a publishing culture that is still caught between old
               and new media. This reverse engineering of a hyperlink system, however, falls far
               short of both the Web browser and what had already been accomplished in print
               elsewhere, for example, in the Thompson chain system. Following the link to page 16,
               the reader is left to guess which point on the page was judged relevant in the mind
               of the author, and then the linkages stop there. One can either continue reading, or
               return to the point of origin (if the thumb has held the place), but one cannot
               navigate beyond these two points. It may be that the nature of this material doesn’t
               require this sort of sequential linking; or perhaps the anticipated benefits didn’t
               outweigh the considerable editorial effort that would have been required to complete
               such thematic chains. In other words, the demands of reading and the nature of the
               material did not supply sufficient motivation for carrying this experiment any
               further than it was taken, which brings us to the other major conclusion of this
               essay: that in designing new reading environments, there is much to be learned from
               past achievements in the domains of highly motivated reading communities. Long before
               the advent of the Internet and its defining characteristic — the hyperlink — the
               Thompson Chain Reference system developed only because the particular need to make
               such linkages in this particular domain of knowledge was so well appreciated and
               understood by its creator and his community of readers. Scholars in the humanities
               similarly need to assert their demands upon the development of new knowledge
               environments in the digital realm.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label="Brusilovsky 2001" xml:id="brusilovsky2001" key="brusilovsky2001">Brusilovsky, Peter. <title rend="quotes">Adaptive Hypermedia.</title>
               <title rend="italic">User Modeling and User-Adapted Interaction</title> 11 (2001),
               87–110.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Dyck 2008" xml:id="dyck2008" key="dyck2008">Dyck, Paul and Stuart Williams.
                  <title rend="quotes">Toward an Electronic Edition of an Early Modern Assembled
                  Book.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Studies / Le Champ Numérique</title> no 0.12 (2008).
                  <ref target="http://www.digitalstudies.org/ojs/index.php/digital_studies/article/view/132/181">http://www.digitalstudies.org/ojs/index.php/digital_studies/article/view/132/181</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Foys 2007" xml:id="foys2007" key="foys2007">Foys, Martin K. <title rend="italic">Virtually Anglo-Saxon: Old Media, New Media, and Early Medieval
                  Studies in the Late Age of Print</title>. Gainesville, FL: University of Florida
               Press, 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Gibson 1993" xml:id="gibson1993" key="gibson1993">Gibson, Margaret T.
                  <title rend="italic">The Bible in the Latin West</title>. Notre Dame: University
               of Notre Dame, 1993.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Herbert 1941" xml:id="herbert1941" key="herbert1941">Herbert, George.
                  <title rend="italic">The Works of George Herbert</title> ed. F. E. Hutchinson.
               Oxford: The Clarendon Press, 1941.</bibl>
            <bibl label="INKE 2012" xml:id="inke2012" key="inke2012">INKE: Implementing New
               Knowledge Environments. <ref target="http://www.inke.ca/">www.inke.ca</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Kirkbride Bible Co." xml:id="kirkbride" key="kirkbride">Kirkbride Bible Co.
               http://www.kirkbride.com/thompson-story.asp</bibl>
            <bibl label="Nave 1896" xml:id="nave1896" key="nave1896">Nave, Orville James. <title rend="italic">Nave's Topical Bible</title>. New York: International Bible Agency,
               1896–.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Newman 1658" xml:id="newman1658" key="newman1658">Newman, Samuel. <title rend="italic">A Large and Compleat Concordance to the Bible in English: According
                  to the Last Translation.</title> 2nd corrected ed. London, 1658.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Olive Tree Software" xml:id="olivetree" key="olivetree">The Thompson-Chain
               Referencing System. Olive Tree Software. <ref target="http://www.olivetree.com/store/product.php?productid=17248">http://www.olivetree.com/store/product.php?productid=17248</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl label="Saenger 1999" xml:id="saenger1999" key="saenger1999">Saenger, Paul. <title rend="italic">The Impact of the Early Printed Page on the Reading of the
                  Bible</title> ed. Paul Henry Saenger and Kimberly Van Kampen. London: British
               Library, 1999.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Tam 1997a" xml:id="tam1997a" key="tam1997a">Tam, Jim C. <title rend="italic">Design and Evaluation of Web-Based Dynamic Hypertexts</title>. PhD
               Thesis. University of Toronto, 1997.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Tam 1997b" xml:id="tam1997b" key="tam1997b">Tam, Jim C. et al. <title rend="quotes">Dynamic Hypertext Benefits Novices in Question Answering.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Human Factors and Ergonomics Society 41st
                  Annual Meeting</title> 1,2, 1997, 350–354.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Thompson 1908" xml:id="thompson1908" key="thompson1908">Thompson, Frank
               Charles (ed.) <title rend="italic">The Thompson Chain Reference Bible</title>. New
               York: Eaton &amp; Mains, 1908.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Truran 2007" xml:id="truran2007" key="truran2007">Truran, Mark, James
               Golding and Helen Ashman. <title rend="quotes">Autonomous Authoring Tools for
                  Hypertext.</title>
               <title rend="italic">ACM Computing Surveys</title> 39.3, article 8 August
               2007.</bibl>
         </listBibl>

      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>