<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
        xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
        xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
        xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">The Laboratory Turn: Exploring
                                        Discourses, Landscapes, and Models of Humanities Labs </title>
                                <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
                                <dhq:authorInfo>
                                        <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
                                        <dhq:author_name>Urszula
                                                  <dhq:family>Pawlicka-Deger</dhq:family>
                                        </dhq:author_name>
                                        <dhq:affiliation>Aalto University</dhq:affiliation>
                                        <email>pawlickadeger@gmail.com</email>
                                        <dhq:bio>
                                                <p>Urszula Pawlicka-Deger held a postdoctoral
                                                  researcher position in the Department of Media at
                                                  Aalto University, Finland before joining King’s
                                                  Digital Lab at King’s College London, UK as a
                                                  Marie Curie Fellow. Her research interests include
                                                  the epistemology of a humanities laboratory, the
                                                  process of knowledge production intertwined with
                                                  technologies, and the infrastructural influences
                                                  on humanistic work. Pawlicka-Deger was a Fulbright
                                                  scholar in the Creative Media and Digital Culture
                                                  at Washington State University Vancouver, US
                                                  (2014-2015), and a visiting researcher in the
                                                  Department of English at Stony Brook University,
                                                  US (2015-2016). She was awarded the Willard
                                                  McCarty Fellowship at the Department of Digital
                                                  Humanities at King’s College London, UK (2019),
                                                  where she was also a keynote speaker for the event
                                                  <title rend="quotes">Humanities Laboratories:
                                                  Critical Infrastructures and Knowledge
                                                  Experiments</title> organized in conjunction with
                                                  the Critical Infrastructure Studies Initiative. In
                                                  addition, she was awarded the Vanguard Fellowship
                                                  at the Institute of Advanced Studies at the
                                                  University of Birmingham, UK (2019), where she
                                                  organized the <title rend="quotes">Rebuilding
                                                  Laboratories</title> workshop to initiate an
                                                  interdisciplinary discussion on laboratories from
                                                  the perspective of digital humanities, science and
                                                  technology studies, and natural science. Over the
                                                  years, she has published peer-reviewed scholarly
                                                  articles and monographs and presented the research
                                                  outcomes at international meetings. Her last
                                                  publications related to the concept of a
                                                  laboratory include <title rend="quotes">Data,
                                                  Collaboration, Laboratory: Bringing Concepts from
                                                  Science into Humanities Practice</title> released
                                                  in <title rend="italic">English Studies</title>
                                                  (2017) and the forthcoming article <title
                                                  rend="quotes">Laboratory: A New Space in Digital
                                                  Humanities</title> in Institutions, <title
                                                  rend="italic">Infrastructures at the Interstices.
                                                  Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>
                                                  (University of Minnesota Press, 2021).</p>
                                        </dhq:bio>
                                </dhq:authorInfo>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                                <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
                                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000466</idno>
                                <idno type="volume">014</idno>
                                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                                <date when="2020-09-25">25 September 2020</date>

                                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                                        <cc:License
                                                rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"
                                        />
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <p>This is the source</p>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                                        <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                                                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                                                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
                                        </bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                                        <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled
                                                vocabulary</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <langUsage>
                                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                                <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
                        </langUsage>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                                        <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
                                        <list type="simple">
                                                <item/>
                                        </list>
                                </keywords>
                                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                                        <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
                                        <list type="simple">
                                                <item>infrastructure</item>
                                                <item>laboratory</item>
                                                <item>lab history</item>
                                                <item>humanities lab</item>
                                                <item>digital humanities center</item>
                                                <item>techno-science lab</item>
                                                <item>virtual lab</item>
                                                <item>situatedness</item>
                                        </list>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
                        <change when="2020-05-01" who="jmurel">Created file</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
                <front>
                        <dhq:abstract>
                                <p>The goal of this paper is to track the path of the formation of
                                        the laboratory turn in the humanities and understand the
                                        conditions, meanings, and functions of humanities labs. The
                                        first section investigates three discourses that gave rise
                                        to the emergence of a laboratory in the humanities: the
                                        transformation of the humanities infrastructure within the
                                        university, paradigm shifts in the social sciences, and the
                                        expansion of cultural categories of innovation, the maker
                                        movement (the proliferation of makerspaces), and the idea of
                                        community. Next, the author presents a history of the
                                        laboratory in the humanities and determines the shift from a
                                                <hi rend="italic">laboratory as a physical place to
                                                conceptual laboratory</hi>. The last section
                                        analyses five models for humanities labs based on
                                        laboratories’ statements and operations: the center-type
                                        lab, the techno-science lab, the work station-type lab, the
                                        social challenges-centric lab, and virtual lab. The research
                                        shows that the laboratory turn has emerged in the humanities
                                        as a part of a wider process of the <hi rend="italic"
                                                >laboratorization</hi> of social life, which has
                                        been occurring since the 1980s. Next, the study indicates
                                        the role of digital humanities as the driving force behind
                                        building a laboratory space, which supports situated
                                        practices, the collaborative, and technology-based projects.
                                        The paper shows that the humanities lab does not simply
                                        imitate the science lab but adapts this new infrastructure
                                        for its own purposes and needs.</p>
                        </dhq:abstract>
                        <dhq:teaser>
                                <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
                                <p>This article explores the labratory turn in the humantiies.</p>
                        </dhq:teaser>
                </front>
                <body>
                        <div>
                                <head>Introduction</head>
                                <p>Owen Hannaway defined a science laboratory as a place that <quote
                                                rend="inline">involves observation and manipulation
                                                of nature by means of specialized instruments,
                                                techniques, and apparatuses that require manual
                                                skills as well as conceptual knowledge for their
                                                construction and deployment</quote>
                                        <ptr target="#hannaway1986" loc="585"/>. A scientific
                                        laboratory implies a physical location, material
                                        instruments, equipment, and hands-on skills for knowledge
                                        production. With the proliferation and diversification of
                                        laboratories in city space, in cultural institutions
                                        (libraries and museums), in the virtual environment, and on
                                        the university campus, this definition seems difficult to
                                        maintain. One realization of labs that resists this
                                        elucidation is a humanities lab. A laboratory has emerged in
                                        the humanities as part of their rich infrastructure that
                                        includes a library and archive, the seminar and workshop,
                                        the classroom, the graduate program, the conference, the
                                        university press, the journal, the academic newsletter, etc.
                                        These all have been and remained institutional forms for the
                                        production of knowledge in the humanities. However, in
                                        recent years, we have observed how the present forms of
                                        infrastructure have been renamed <q>laboratories</q>: a
                                        library’s reading room at Yale University Library has been
                                        redesigned as the Franke Family Digital Humanities
                                        Laboratory, the University of Arizona College of Humanities
                                        has launched a new set of courses as the Humanities Lab, and
                                        research groups and seminars have been called a
                                                <q>laboratory</q>, for instance, Representing
                                        Migration Humanities Lab in the English Department at Duke
                                        University. The humanities labs have been built upon
                                        different types of existing infrastructure giving rise to
                                        new forms of their realization and interpretation. They
                                        include situated and virtual digital humanities labs as well
                                        as non-digital, seminar- and project-based humanities labs. </p>
                                <p>In this essay, I argue thus that the idea of a laboratory has
                                        been expanded and altered by social initiatives, such as
                                        library creative spaces, makerspaces, and hackathons. A
                                        laboratory goes beyond the notion of a physical place
                                        dedicated to scientific exploration, becoming, instead, a
                                        widely understood <emph>project</emph> (lab as concept,
                                        initiative, and program) focused on <q>labbing problems</q>
                                        (the approach to solve problems by applying the practices of
                                        labs; see more <ptr target="#kieboom2014"/>). Seen as a
                                                <term>project</term>, it insinuates that society is,
                                        in a certain sense, in a <term>projection state</term>,
                                        seeking new ways to tackle local and global challenges. The
                                        shift from a <emph> laboratory as a physical location</emph>
                                        to <term>conceptual laboratory </term>is thus crucial for
                                        the discussion of a new cultural paradigm. Referring to
                                        Thomas S. Kuhn’s paradigm concept <ptr target="#kuhn1996"/>,
                                        the laboratory turn entails fundamental changes in the
                                        practices and function of the humanities at large. </p>
                                <p>The purpose of this article is to track the path of the formation
                                        of the laboratory turn in the humanities and understand the
                                        conditions, meanings, and functions of humanities labs
                                        situated in North America, North-Western Europe, and
                                        Australia. In the first part of the article, I analyse
                                        briefly three discourses that gave rise to the emergence of
                                        a laboratory in the humanities: the transformation of the
                                        humanities infrastructure within the university, paradigm
                                        shifts in the social sciences, and the expansion of cultural
                                        categories of innovation, the maker movement, and the notion
                                        of community. Next, I present a history of the laboratory in
                                        the humanities and examine a wide range of application of
                                        the term <q>laboratory</q> to the humanities that cover
                                        institutional and technology-based labs (physical and
                                        virtual spaces engaging digital tools and technologies) and
                                        conceptual, non-digital labs (entities and projects that
                                        call themselves <q>labs</q> and don’t have an explicitly
                                        digital component). Drawing on this analysis, I indicate
                                        five models for humanities labs based on laboratories’
                                        statements and operations: the center-type lab, the
                                        techno-science lab, the work station-type lab, the social
                                        challenges-centric lab, and virtual lab. These five types of
                                        laboratories grew out of various origins and discourses. The
                                        goal is thus to grasp the complex landscape of the
                                        humanities labs, comprehend their functions, and reflect on
                                        their development and features. The result section presents
                                        the main findings of the research related to the emergence
                                        of the laboratory turn, the uniqueness of the humanities
                                        labs, and the implications of labs for the positioning of
                                        the humanities both within and outside of academia. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                                <head>Three Discourses of the Laboratory Turn</head>
                                <div>
                                        <head>Infrastructure Changes in the Humanities </head>
                                        <p>By looking at the history of the humanities, we can
                                                discern moments of significant shifts occurring at
                                                the time of cultural, social, and economic changes.
                                                Each significant moment in the history of higher
                                                education — the beginning of the twentieth century,
                                                the 1960s/1970s, the 1980s/1990s, and 2007/2008 — is
                                                hailed as a transformation period for the humanities
                                                (see more about the history of university and
                                                humanities: e.g., <ptr target="#bérubé1995"/>
                                                <ptr target="#readings1996"/>
                                                <ptr target="#kerr2001"/>
                                                <ptr target="#klein2005"/>
                                                <ptr target="#donoghue2008"/>
                                                <ptr target="#gottschall2008"/>
                                                <ptr target="#kagan2009"/>
                                                <ptr target="#wissema2009"/>
                                                <ptr target="#collini2012"/>
                                                <ptr target="#bod2013"/>
                                                <ptr target="#jay2014"/>). The discipline is seen as
                                                a reactive field seeking to adapt to new conditions
                                                and needs. One method which can be used to reimagine
                                                and strengthen the humanities is institutional
                                                change that entails new organizational structures
                                                and, alongside these structures, new research
                                                practices. Here, I outline briefly the
                                                infrastructural transformations which have been
                                                taking place in the U.S. since the 1980s/1990s.
                                                However, prior to doing so, it is worth recalling
                                                the most significant institutional change which
                                                occurred in the nineteenth century.</p>
                                        <p>At that time, the humanities were under the influence of
                                                the growing scientification of knowledge. The
                                                humanities were strongly engaged in precise and
                                                analytical research typical for scientific
                                                discourses. As Julie Thompson Klein describes it,
                                                  <quote rend="inline">The tendency toward
                                                  painstaking research and minute methodology became
                                                  as evident in historiography as in science. The
                                                  humanist’s equivalent of the laboratory was
                                                  analytic abstraction, reinforced by description,
                                                  classification, comparison, and compilation. Like
                                                  laboratory specimens, humanistic objects could be
                                                  manipulated, dissected, and embalmed; measured,
                                                  counted, and calibrated; and subjected to precise
                                                  methodologies</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#klein2005" loc="28"/>. In a certain
                                                metaphorical sense, the scientific laboratory was
                                                the first place in which humanistic research
                                                determined its methodology and infrastructure. At
                                                the beginning of the twentieth century, the
                                                university developed the modern system of
                                                disciplinarity, which consequently contributed to
                                                the independence of the humanities discipline. The
                                                moment of separation of the humanities from science
                                                meant that the humanities could shape the
                                                discipline’s own methodology. This new independence
                                                of the humanities and the building of the
                                                discipline’s own physical place became a key moment
                                                in the history of the humanities. Departing from a
                                                  <term>laboratory methodology</term> was
                                                accompanied by moving from a metaphorical
                                                  <term>laboratory</term> towards an office and a
                                                library: spaces that for a long time served as the
                                                main places for humanities research.</p>
                                        <p>Significant changes occurred in the 1980s as a result of
                                                the transformations in the academy. The phenomenon
                                                of mass universities, the weakening of disciplinary
                                                boundaries, and expanding globalization and
                                                corporatization led to a crisis in universities in
                                                the 1990s [e.g., <ref target="#bérubé1995">Bérubé et
                                                  al. 1995</ref>, <ref target="#readings1996"
                                                  >Readings 1996</ref>]. This crisis rhetoric has
                                                started to penetrate any discussion about the
                                                university, which is attacked for its
                                                corporatization and ignoring social problems, as
                                                well as the state of the humanities, which is
                                                accused of being unprofitable and impractical. Under
                                                these conditions, the humanities were transforming
                                                gradually into an interdisciplinary field, engaged
                                                in sociological, political, cultural, and feminist
                                                discourses. The shift towards inter- and
                                                transdisciplinary practices and social engagement
                                                was accompanied by the symbolic gesture of moving
                                                the humanities <quote rend="inline">beyond the walls
                                                  of the office</quote> into the public domain. The
                                                humanities moved out of their usual spaces — the
                                                office and the library — into a new territory — the
                                                center — to intensify interdisciplinarity and public
                                                engagement. The implementation of new practices was
                                                thus reinforced by institutional changes.
                                                Consequently, since the 1980s, the humanities have
                                                established many centres, aiming to foster
                                                interdisciplinarity, build bridges with the medical,
                                                technical, and natural sciences, and create a common
                                                space for the university and the local community
                                                  <ptr target="#klein2005" loc="76"/>. </p>
                                        <p>Next to the interdisciplinary research center, a new unit
                                                emerged with a focus on computing in the humanities.
                                                This center underpinned the development of
                                                humanities computing, renamed the digital humanities
                                                in the twentieth-first century. It played the role
                                                of a work station equipped with computers and other
                                                devices, gathering in the same place humanists,
                                                computer scientists, and programmers. However, the
                                                computing center was more than a physical work
                                                space; it was a significant ground for building new
                                                practices engaged in manipulating complex digital
                                                analysis tools and applying computing techniques. To
                                                advance computing within humanities practices, the
                                                discipline <quote rend="inline">required
                                                  institutional investment in an entirely different
                                                  infrastructure of courseware specialists, on a
                                                  large scale and at an urgent pace</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#flanders2002" loc="379"/>. These
                                                infrastructural changes were necessary in order to
                                                express these new practices within the humanities
                                                and, along with that, the new function and place of
                                                the humanities in the larger institutional arena.
                                                Therefore, the center played an important role in
                                                restructuring the humanities within the university
                                                as well as reconceptualizing the field as a meeting
                                                place for interdisciplinary researchers and the
                                                local community.</p>
                                        <p>The university entered the twenty-first century along
                                                with the accelerating power of technology, the
                                                emerging cyberinfrastructure, and intensifying
                                                globalization and internationalization. The
                                                university of the twenty-first century is an
                                                economically-driven institution centred on applied,
                                                profitable, and competitive research and training
                                                students in order to provide them with practical and
                                                useful skills. Based on J. G. Wissema’s
                                                considerations of the third generation university,
                                                the academy of the twenty-first century is
                                                distinguished by seeking alternative funding for
                                                cutting-edge scientific research, intertwining the
                                                two worlds of academic and industrial research,
                                                operating in an internationally competitive market,
                                                and the commercialisation of knowledge <ptr
                                                  target="#wissema2009" loc="31–2"/>. These
                                                technological, economic, and academic conditions
                                                have affected the humanities, which, particularly
                                                after 2007, entered a state of crisis. The
                                                humanities were seen as unproductive and out of
                                                touch with contemporary science and the technology
                                                culture, leading consequently to a decline in
                                                funding, reduction in the number of majors, and
                                                shrinking job market. Under these conditions, the
                                                humanities sought to find a strategy with which to
                                                reinforce their position. One of the implementations
                                                of the <quote rend="inline">tactical
                                                  humanities</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#pawlicka2017"/> is a <quote
                                                  rend="inline">scientification of the
                                                  humanities</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#stratilatis2014"/>, i.e., moving the
                                                humanities closer to the sciences <ptr
                                                  target="#gottschall2008"/>. The process of the
                                                scientification of the humanities has taken
                                                different forms, including the use of new research
                                                data and applied methodologies (qualitative methods,
                                                data mining), new research practices (collaboration,
                                                experimentation), new methods of evaluating research
                                                (parameterization, falsifiability, the ranking
                                                system of universities), as well as reconceiving
                                                institutions (forming laboratories). </p>
                                        <p>Consequently, the humanities took a step towards
                                                revamping their infrastructure, aimed at fostering
                                                and enhancing growing computational, collaborative,
                                                and interdisciplinary practices. In this light,
                                                drawing on Amy E. Earhart’s reflections, a
                                                laboratory emerged in the humanities discipline as
                                                  <quote rend="inline">more than a space, but a
                                                  symbol of our hope</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#earhart2015" loc="399"/>. It became a
                                                new institutional structure that was supposed to
                                                fuel the development of the humanities with new
                                                working models and research practices. The
                                                laboratory was intended to work as a driving force
                                                to develop a new model of the humanities based on
                                                collaboration, partnership, interdisciplinarity,
                                                situated practices, technology-focused work, and
                                                alternative, empirical education. </p>
                                        <p>The laboratory idea was thus applied to the humanities
                                                field in response to its structural crisis; the
                                                existing infrastructure (offices, library, seminars)
                                                was insufficient to meet contemporary scholars
                                                needs, such as advancing collaborative and
                                                interdisciplinary research and fostering frequent
                                                meetings and interaction [e.g., <ref
                                                  target="#hiatt2005">Hiatt 2005</ref>, <ref
                                                  target="#joselow2016">Joselow 2016</ref>, <ref
                                                  target="#breithaupt2017">Breithaupt 2017</ref>].
                                                Therefore, a lab was not only seen as a new
                                                institutional unit for the humanities but also as a
                                                conceptual model for conducting research embedded
                                                and entailed in a laboratory’s set of practices. In
                                                  <title rend="quotes">Designing a Lab in the
                                                  Humanities</title>
                                                <ptr target="#breithaupt2017"/>, Fritz Breithaupt
                                                described his experience in creating the
                                                Experimental Humanities Lab at Indiana University,
                                                Bloomington in 2015, which arose from simple weekly
                                                meetings that the students called <q>lab
                                                  meetings</q>. <quote rend="inline">Sure, we had
                                                  done several joint presentations and written some
                                                  small articles, with more pending. But was this a
                                                  lab?</quote>; Breithaupt’s striking question shows
                                                that firstly, the concept of the humanities lab is
                                                still far from a clear definition, and, secondly,
                                                that the lab idea grows out of the simple necessity
                                                of frequent meetings and conversations as well as
                                                the need to work together instead of remaining
                                                isolated in offices. The term “lab” is thus used to
                                                imply specific values embedded in a particular place
                                                or initiative. However, this tactical naming
                                                strategy doesn’t necessarily transparently disclose
                                                the actual workings of knowledge production.</p>
                                        <p>The impulse to establish laboratories in the humanities
                                                is also related strongly to the utilization of
                                                technology in research projects. Following the
                                                report of the American Council of Learned Societies
                                                Commission on Cyberinfrastructure for the Humanities
                                                and Social Sciences, <title rend="quotes">Our
                                                  Cultural Commonwealth</title>, we can see that
                                                physical laboratories have been established as a
                                                place for facilitating new research practices
                                                (collaboration, experimentation, and
                                                interdisciplinarity), advocating technological
                                                innovation, and developing a robust
                                                cyberinfrastructure <ptr target="#commonwealth2006"
                                                  loc="29"/>. A laboratory entails physical
                                                situatedness, i.e., work is performed in a
                                                particular place and context. Traditional models of
                                                humanistic research involve work in an office, a
                                                library, or at home since it is not attached to
                                                place and does not demand any particular equipment
                                                and devices. In contrast to this model, digital
                                                humanities require equipment, tools, and software
                                                that are accumulated and provided, physically and
                                                through licenses, in one space. This place gathers
                                                people from different disciplines and institutions:
                                                programmers, engineers, librarians, curators, and
                                                archivists. It becomes a work space for
                                                collaborative, interdisciplinary, and
                                                technology-based research. Thus, humanities research
                                                has been transformed from placeless and isolated
                                                work into the collaborative and situated practices
                                                of the digital humanities. As a result, the digital
                                                humanities have become the driving force behind
                                                building a laboratory space. This new vision of the
                                                humanities propelled the creation of laboratories
                                                with missions related strongly to the idea of
                                                reconstructing the humanities in the vein of
                                                technological innovations. Good examples are the
                                                following statements made by digital humanities
                                                labs: <quote rend="inline">LINHD mission is to
                                                  redefine the way of working in digital humanities
                                                  by promoting innovation and technology in the
                                                  environment of the new information society</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#linhd"/> by the Digital Humanities
                                                Innovation Lab (LINHD) established at the National
                                                University of Distance Education in 2014, and <quote
                                                  rend="inline">We at the Price Lab believe that if
                                                  the humanities are to survive and thrive, digital
                                                  research tools for the imagined future of our
                                                  various fields must be developed by scholars who
                                                  possess expertise in both humanistic inquiry and
                                                  digital technology</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#pricelab"/> by Price Lab for Digital
                                                Humanities launched at the University of
                                                Pennsylvania in 2015.</p>
                                        <p>Therefore, along with the development of the digital
                                                humanities, we can track the infrastructural changes
                                                in the humanities of the twenty-first century as
                                                moving from a center <ptr target="#zorich2008"/>
                                                <ptr target="#sample2010"/>
                                                <ptr target="#fraistat2012"/> to a laboratory <ptr
                                                  target="#emerson"/>
                                                <ptr target="#svensson2015"/>
                                                <ptr target="#svensson2016"/>
                                                <ptr target="#svensson2018"/>
                                                <ptr target="#earhart2015"/>
                                                <ptr target="#lane2017"/>
                                                <ptr target="#pawlicka2017"/>
                                                <ptr target="#pawlicka-deger"/>
                                                <ptr target="#smithies2017"/>
                                                <ptr target="#smithies2020"/>
                                                <ptr target="#foka2018"/>
                                                <ptr target="#pask2018"/>
                                                <ptr target="#ricaurte2018"/>. The years after 2010
                                                are particularly significant period in the history
                                                of the laboratory. First, we have experienced
                                                tremendous growth in numbers of labs launched in the
                                                academic and societal areas. Second, 2010 was
                                                proclaimed to be the year of <quote rend="inline"
                                                  >the death of the centre</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#sample2010"/>, which was now seen as
                                                an unsustainable place in which to house collective
                                                activities within the humanities. Third, in 2010,
                                                the Franklin Humanities Institute (FHI) at Duke
                                                University founded the Humanities Laboratories,
                                                heralded as a <quote rend="inline">new architecture
                                                  of multiple humanities laboratories</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#fhi"/>. This structure marked the
                                                beginning of a new model for a laboratory in the
                                                humanities as one that was created for a fixed
                                                period and a specific purpose, but which was not
                                                particularly related to physical situatedness and
                                                not necessarily involved a digital component. This
                                                model gave rise to <term>conceptual
                                                  laboratories</term>, which were seen more as
                                                projects and programs entailing different types of
                                                learning and research practices in the humanities
                                                rather than physical work spaces. The good examples
                                                of conceptual labs are Humanities Labs at Colby
                                                College, which were launched as innovative courses
                                                in 2014 <ptr target="#cchl"/>. The notion of the
                                                laboratory is used in terms of new modes of research
                                                and community outreach which do not necessarily
                                                require a fixed physical location and equipment.
                                                This significant change reflects the meaning of the
                                                laboratory turn: the lab does not refer to a
                                                physical place anymore; instead, it is related to a
                                                way of thinking, communicating, and working. </p>
                                        <p>The last reason for the <term>laboratory boom </term>
                                                after 2010 is related to the growing interest in the
                                                concept of community, public engagement, and
                                                  <term>do-it-yourself</term> culture. It entails
                                                popping out labs as makerspaces and hackathons in
                                                the academic space (e.g., the Curtin Library
                                                Makerspace at Curtin University) as well as
                                                establishing labs in city space; for instance,
                                                OpenLab was launched as a <quote rend="inline"
                                                  >challenge-driven innovation community</quote> by
                                                Karolinska Institute, KTH Royal Institute of
                                                Technology, Stockholm University and Södertörn
                                                University in 2013 and located in the City of
                                                Stockholm <ptr target="#openlab"/>. </p>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                        <head>Laboratory Studies and Conceptual Changes in the
                                                Social Sciences </head>
                                        <p>The second discourse on the laboratory turn brings us
                                                back to the 1980s and 1990s when the conceptual
                                                shifts in the social sciences occurred. The new
                                                concepts had a significant impact on emerging new
                                                theories and the research approach of the
                                                twenty-first century. Based on Don Ihde’s
                                                reflections, the following theoretical changes are
                                                indicated: the emergence of the new sociology of
                                                scientific knowledge, namely, social constructionism
                                                and the actor-network theory of the 1970s; the new
                                                philosophy of technology in the 1980s; and the
                                                concept of science as a cultural practice in the
                                                late 1980s and 1990s <ptr target="#ihde2009" loc="7"
                                                />. This concise timeline reveals the most
                                                significant shifts in the notion of science, namely,
                                                moving away from science as a knowledge towards
                                                science as a practice <ptr target="#pickering1992"
                                                />. As Hannaway claims: <quote rend="inline">Science
                                                  no longer was simply a kind of knowledge (one
                                                  possessed scientia); it increasingly became a form
                                                  of activity (one did science). That there should
                                                  have arisen in this period a place specially set
                                                  aside for such activity and bearing a new name
                                                  serves to measure the force of that shift</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#hannaway1986" loc="586"/>. A new
                                                approach to thinking about science was based on a
                                                conviction that knowledge is produced as a part of
                                                social and cultural practices; therefore, scientific
                                                knowledge itself should be understood as a social
                                                product. </p>
                                        <p>The perspective of science as a social practice opened up
                                                new questions regarding a place in which to
                                                construct science <ptr target="#latour1979"/>
                                                <ptr target="#galison1999"/>, a community of
                                                practice <ptr target="#wenger1998"/>, and material
                                                instruments and artefacts <ptr target="#latour1979"/>
                                                <ptr target="#lynch1985"/>
                                                <ptr target="#latour1987"/>. It was a move towards
                                                unveiling scientific practices and investigating the
                                                network of actors that take part in constructing
                                                scientific knowledge, i.e., space, material
                                                instruments, technology, and community. By the late
                                                1980s, there was no doubt that major changes were
                                                coming, driven by research in science and technology
                                                studies: <title rend="italic">Laboratory
                                                  Life</title> by Bruno Latour and Steve Woolgar
                                                (1979), <title rend="italic">The Manufacture of
                                                  Knowledge</title> by Karin Knorr Cetina (1981),
                                                  <title rend="italic">Art and Artifact in
                                                  Laboratory Science</title> by Michael Lynch
                                                (1985), and <title rend="italic">Science in
                                                  Action</title> by Latour (1987).</p>
                                        <p>Such a perspective on science entailed establishing new
                                                fields to explore the various aspects of the social
                                                construction of science. One area refers to a
                                                contextual theory of knowledge, assuming that the
                                                knowledge is situated in practice, in contrast to
                                                conceptual knowledge, which is abstracted from
                                                situations <ptr target="#brown1989" loc="32"/>. This
                                                means, to put it slightly differently, that situated
                                                knowledge is a part of the activity, context, and
                                                culture in which it is constructed and used. Viewed
                                                in this way, space for knowledge production began to
                                                be one of the key research issues. Place defines the
                                                condition of scientific knowledge construction and
                                                determines the research mode and perspectives. Under
                                                these circumstances, laboratory studies arrived
                                                eventually as a new field focused on the
                                                investigation of the space used for scientific
                                                inquiry <ptr target="#knorrcetina1995"/>.</p>
                                        <p>In this light, the emergence of the laboratory in the
                                                humanities entails a significant shift from the
                                                  <emph>text</emph> towards the <emph>place</emph>
                                                where it is constructed. The laboratory draws
                                                attention to the space in which humanities
                                                experiments are conducted, the knowledge is
                                                produced, and scholarly communication occurs.
                                                Consequently, the humanities are seen as a
                                                  <emph>practice</emph> and <emph>process</emph>
                                                that engages space, interactions, and equipment.
                                                Like the natural sciences and techno-science, the
                                                humanities involve <quote rend="inline"
                                                  >infrastructural thinking</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#svensson2015" loc="337"/>, according
                                                to which the architecture of the humanistic inquiry
                                                determines the process of knowledge construction. </p>
                                        <p>The 1980s and 1990s, as Robert E. Kohler observed
                                                astutely, were thus recognized as a productive time
                                                for laboratory studies, and the laboratory itself
                                                was seen as a social institution. After that time,
                                                the notion of the laboratory was neglected until
                                                interest was revived again in the twenty-first
                                                century <ptr target="#kohler2008" loc="761"/>.
                                                Kohler’s article <title rend="quotes">Lab
                                                  History</title> from 2008 is a significant
                                                gesture, implying that there was a surge in lab
                                                activity again after 2007 and a need for tracking
                                                its history. In this context, it is worth recalling
                                                another important publication, namely, <title
                                                  rend="italic">Representation in Scientific
                                                  Practice. Revisited</title>
                                                <ptr target="#coopmans2014"/>, a revised book
                                                originally published in 1990. The manuscript
                                                suggests that research topics come back again after
                                                twenty-four years. One key issue it addresses is a
                                                return to the idea of laboratory, which, as the
                                                editors note, <quote rend="inline">extends to other
                                                  spaces and places via collaborative ventures,
                                                  shared data centers, and information and
                                                  communication technologies</quote>, challenging
                                                  <quote rend="inline">the very distinction between
                                                  laboratory and field</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#coopmans2014" loc="1"/>. Both
                                                publications draw a connection between the study of
                                                scientific laboratories in the 1980s and
                                                laboratories of the twenty-first century, which have
                                                popped out in the humanities, social sciences, and
                                                outside of the university. </p>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                        <head>Cultural Categories: Innovation, the Maker Movement,
                                                and Community</head>
                                        <p>The last line of development of the laboratory turn runs
                                                through the prevailing cultural categories of the
                                                twenty-first century. Let us now take a look at the
                                                following three cultural discourses and their
                                                impacts on changes within the university and
                                                humanities. The first category of innovation has
                                                dominated cultural and social rhetoric and given
                                                rise to new concepts, such as the innovation society
                                                and innovation paradigm. According to this rhetoric,
                                                to tackle the complex social, cultural, and economic
                                                problems of the twenty-first century, society must
                                                turn into an innovation society, which drives
                                                breakthrough solutions and cutting-edge
                                                technologies. Such discourse has led to the design
                                                of the manifold varieties of innovations labs that
                                                have popped up like mushrooms within the university
                                                and city space as social institutions; for instance,
                                                the Scholarly Innovation Lab (SIL) at the UCLA
                                                library and the Digital Innovation Lab at the
                                                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. The
                                                innovation concept has begun to be a crucial
                                                category defining the humanities labs and signifying
                                                the new features found within these labs, including
                                                a strong link between the humanities and the
                                                creative industries, providing cutting-edge
                                                equipment for excellent research, and solving hard
                                                problems. As a result of this discourse, the concept
                                                of an innovative university emerged with the desire
                                                to turn the university into a successful and
                                                competitive business or entrepreneurial university
                                                  <ptr target="#thorp2010"/>. </p>
                                        <p>The innovation approach requires effective creative ideas
                                                and thinking outside the box. Creativity is seen as
                                                a key method with which to improve social and
                                                economic conditions and <quote rend="inline">devise
                                                  potentially better options for the future</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#moran2010" loc="76"/>. A societal
                                                awareness of the value of creativity is constructed
                                                by establishing <hi rend="italic">creative
                                                  spaces</hi> that integrate the local community
                                                around the processes of creative endeavours. One
                                                such place is a library creative space that <quote
                                                  rend="inline">focuses wholly or in part on content
                                                  creation as opposed to content consumption
                                                  alone</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#johnson2016" loc="4"/>. The process of
                                                creation can include drawings and photographs, audio
                                                materials, videos, three-dimensional objects,
                                                computer coding, web-based multimedia, and more.
                                                Hence, library creative spaces play a key role in
                                                expanding the function of the library from providing
                                                information resources and services to integrating
                                                and developing the community through creative
                                                activities. One realization of these creative spaces
                                                is the advent of a laboratory in the common space
                                                that is the library. A laboratory in the library
                                                offers space, equipment, and resources and guides
                                                learning how to use digital tools and create digital
                                                projects <ptr target="#goodman2014"/>
                                                <ptr target="#hamilton2015"/>
                                                <ptr target="#johnson2016"/>
                                                <ptr target="#kavanaghwebb2018"/>.</p>
                                        <p>Another type of creative space is the makerspace defined
                                                as a <quote rend="inline">center or workspace where
                                                  like-minded people get together to make
                                                  things</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#hatch2013" loc="13"/>. The concept of
                                                makerspace is particularly related to a creative and
                                                participatory culture. It was conceived of as an
                                                outgrowth of the cultural <term>maker
                                                  movement</term>, created as a <quote rend="inline"
                                                  >return to craft</quote>, in which people can
                                                build things together again <ptr
                                                  target="#proske2013"/>. Therefore, coming back to
                                                the idea of <emph>making things</emph> came about as
                                                a response to consumption and corporate culture,
                                                driving interest in hacker and
                                                  <term>do-it-yourself</term> cultures. Labcraft,
                                                using Hendrik Tiesinga and Remko Berkhout’s term
                                                  <ptr target="#tiesinga2014"/>, is thus seen as an
                                                innovative and, above all, community lab, seeking to
                                                connect people, create a space for dialogue, and
                                                transfer ideas to the world. Such labs aim to create
                                                new solutions and develop new ways of seeing the
                                                world. The maker movement has been embodied by the
                                                rise of media labs, established as institutionalized
                                                units (the academic media labs), cultural events
                                                (media lab workshops), and alternative models of
                                                education based on tinkering and hacking.
                                                Eventually, the <term>do-it-yourself</term> approach
                                                made inroads into academic culture through the
                                                launch of makerspaces (e.g., Maker Lab in the
                                                Humanities at the University of Victoria) and
                                                hackerspaces (e.g., Blow Things Up at the University
                                                of Colorado, Boulder) and organizing hackathons
                                                (e.g., in the Computational Humanities Lab at the
                                                University of Wisconsin–Madison). </p>
                                        <p>The last cultural category, which has accompanied the
                                                maker movement, is community. The labcraft,
                                                makerspace, and hackathon movements are all based on
                                                the idea of the community being the main resource
                                                and driving force behind them. The idea of the
                                                community, introduced in the 1990s <ptr
                                                  target="#wenger1998"/>, gained importance again in
                                                the twenty-first century, along with the concepts of
                                                civic engagement, activism, and the public
                                                humanities. Community and public engagement began to
                                                be common categories used to describe media and
                                                humanities labs. For instance, the Scholars’ Lab at
                                                the University of Virginia Library is described as a
                                                community lab with the following motto: <quote
                                                  rend="inline">We build up people and practices
                                                  more than products.</quote> The lab prioritizes
                                                the process of learning and working together: <quote
                                                  rend="inline"><q>People over projects</q> means
                                                  that we care more about such outcomes, than about
                                                  whether a formal <q>project</q> happens</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#scholarslab"/>. The Change Making
                                                Media Lab at the University of Southern California,
                                                in turn, is a good example of public engagement in
                                                that it collaborates with people outside of the
                                                academy and creates products, such as entertaining
                                                dramas, that have real impacts on the local
                                                community. </p>
                                        <p>Cultural trends and a circulation of particular concepts
                                                are reflected in the emergence of different types of
                                                academic institutions, ranging from the
                                                entrepreneurial to the engaged university. To meet
                                                contemporary challenges, the humanities have made an
                                                  <quote rend="inline">infrastructural turn</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#rockwell2010"/> to build a physical
                                                place that, through the architecture itself, brings
                                                new features to the field: innovation,
                                                experimentation, hands-on practices, and
                                                collaboration. Under such circumstances, humanities
                                                labs have been constructed. </p>
                                </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                                <head>A Brief History of the Laboratory in the Humanities</head>
                                <p>The first laboratories serving other than natural sciences were
                                        computer science labs established in media studies in the
                                        1980s and 1990s; for instance, the Laboratory Paragraphe at
                                        the University of Paris 8 in 1983, Media Lab at MIT in 1985,
                                        and Aalto Media Lab at Aalto University in 1993. Media labs
                                        were launched as production, dynamic, and experimental
                                        research spaces, studios, and ateliers. The goals of the
                                        first laboratories were to foster the creation of new media
                                        projects which explored the impact of technology on society
                                        and the human condition, developed hardware and software
                                        within the context of artistic projects, and tested the
                                        potential of electronic technologies. Concurrently, in the
                                        late 1990s, the word <q>lab</q> was applied to humanities
                                        and technology, for example, HUMlab at Umeå University was
                                        founded in 1997 and Stanford Humanities Lab at Stanford
                                        University in 1999. Although the institutional models for
                                        these units were not new, their conceptualization as
                                                <q>lab</q> was an original move. Nevertheless, the
                                        end of the twentieth century and beginning of the
                                        twenty-first century remained under the domination of media
                                        labs. </p>
                                <p>Since 2007, the situation changed significantly through the
                                        dissemination of the concept of a laboratory in the
                                        humanities domain. The laboratory concept has expanded
                                        rapidly across the humanities department (e.g., the Global
                                        History Lab in the Department of History at Princeton
                                        University, 2007; the Media Archaeology Lab in the
                                        Department of English at the University of Colorado,
                                        Boulder, 2009) and libraries (e.g., the Scholars’ Lab
                                        launched in the Alderman Library of the University of
                                        Virginia, 2008). The trend towards building laboratories
                                        continued unabated, reaching the point of the
                                                <term>laboratory boom</term> after 2010 that
                                        converged with the computational turn in the humanities <ptr
                                                target="#berry2011"/>, the development of the
                                        digital humanities <ptr target="#gold2012"/>, and the
                                        emergence of virtual laboratory (Alfalab, a project of the
                                        Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences, run in
                                        2009-2011). Since 2010, the concept of laboratory has spread
                                        over the university campus, made inroads into city space and
                                        public cultural institutions <ptr target="#mahey2019"/> and
                                        been launched in places that had never been designated for
                                        this purpose.</p>
                                <p>Along with the humanities labs, with names referring mainly to
                                        disciplines and cultural categories (e.g., the Culture Lab
                                        at Brown University and Participatory Cultures Lab at McGill
                                        University), digital humanities labs have begun to
                                        proliferate right next to existing models of centers (e.g.,
                                        the Digital Humanities Laboratory at Ecole Polytechnique
                                        Fédérale de Lausanne, Digital Humanities Lab at Utrecht
                                        University, and the Franke Family Digital Humanities
                                        Laboratory at Yale University). The proliferation of various
                                        labs in the humanities has led to the broadening of the
                                        concept of laboratory beyond the notion of a physical place.
                                        The term <q>laboratory</q> is used to describe the following
                                        places, initiatives, and ideas: an interdisciplinary
                                        department (the Humanities Lab at Lund University), a center
                                        (the HUMlab at Umeå University), a makerspace (the Maker Lab
                                        in the Humanities at the University of Victoria), an
                                        incubator for new ideas (the Humanities Lab at American
                                        University), a research workshop (the Northwestern
                                        University Digital Humanities Laboratory at Northwestern
                                        University), a collaboration of individuals (the Nebraska
                                        Literary Lab at the University of Nebraska), a coalition
                                        (the Humanities Action Lab led from Rutgers
                                        University-Newark), a student-led initiative (the Public
                                        Humanities Lab at the University of Virginia), a
                                        state-of-the-art facility (the Digital Humanities Lab at the
                                        University of Exeter), an innovative course (the Humanities
                                        Labs at Colby College), a study programme (the Humanities
                                        Lab at Leiden University), consortium (the DigHumLab at
                                        Aarhus University), a virtual research environment (the
                                        Digital Humanities Innovation Lab at the National University
                                        of Distance Education), and even a podcast (the Literature
                                        Lab Podcasts at Brandeis University). Consequently, the
                                        notion of laboratory has gone far beyond its traditional
                                        meaning, turning into a <term>project</term> that can be
                                        done or an <term>action</term> that can be taken, then
                                        dispersed all over the world. A good example of this
                                        approach is the Humanities Action Lab led from Rutgers
                                        University-Newark. It is a coalition of universities,
                                        organizations, and public spaces in twenty cities that
                                        collaborate to build community-curated public humanities
                                        projects. The lab can be created everywhere needed to engage
                                        a community around a particular challenge. </p>
                                <p>Thus, over the last years, we have observed the proliferation of
                                        humanities labs and the growing interest in a laboratory
                                        that implies a new mode of working. It suffices to mention
                                        conferences, panel discussions, and seminars devoted to the
                                        concept and organization of laboratory: <title rend="quotes"
                                                >Building the Humanities Lab: Scholarly Practices in
                                                Virtual Research Environments</title>, the panel
                                        session in the Digital Humanities conference at King’s
                                        College London in 2010; <title rend="quotes">Theories and
                                                Practices of the Literary Lab</title> roundtable at
                                        Modern Language Association National Meeting in Boston in
                                        2013; <title rend="quotes">The Hum Lab: A Consortial
                                                Workshop</title> at Haverford College in 2014;
                                                <title rend="quotes">The Humanities Laboratory:
                                                Discussions of New Campus Models</title>, organized
                                        by Arizona State University’s Institute for Humanities
                                        Research for the National Endowment for the Humanities in
                                        2016; <title rend="quotes">Reimagining the Humanities
                                                Lab</title>, a panel discussion at ADHO Digital
                                        Humanities Conference in Mexico City in 2018; <title
                                                rend="quotes">What Is a Feminist Lab?</title>
                                        symposium at the University of Colorado, Boulder in 2019;
                                                <title rend="quotes">Humanities Laboratories:
                                                Critical Infrastructures and Knowledge
                                                Experiments</title> workshop at King’s College
                                        London in 2019; <title rend="quotes">Rebuilding
                                                Laboratories</title> workshop at the University of
                                        Birmingham in 2019; and <title rend="quotes">The
                                                Architecture of Science and the Humanities</title>
                                        workshop at Netherlands Institute for Advanced Study in
                                        2019. This list shows that there is an urgent need to
                                        discuss this institutional model for the humanities and
                                        understand its implications for scholarly research and
                                        teaching practices. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                                <head>Typology of Humanities Labs</head>
                                <p>To comprehend a laboratory in the humanities and identify its
                                        different realization, I firstly collected the descriptions
                                        of labs ranging from media labs to digital and non-digital
                                        humanities labs <ptr target="#pawlicka-deger2019"/>,
                                        scrutinize the context and meaning of the term
                                                <q>laboratory</q>, analyse their mission statements,
                                        and further determine their functions. Before discussing the
                                        typology in detail, however, we can pose a significant
                                        question of what is a humanities lab in itself? To answer
                                        this question, let us look at below statements from three
                                        laboratories: <cit><quote rend="block">At Humanities +
                                                  Design our mission is to produce, through the lens
                                                  of humanistic inquiry, new modes of thinking in
                                                  design and computer science to serve data-driven
                                                  research in the humanities. We believe that
                                                  humanistic inquiry, grounded in interpretation,
                                                  has much to contribute to the development of
                                                  technologies if they are to help us reveal
                                                  ambiguity and paradox, allowing human-scale
                                                  exploration of complex systems. In the laboratory
                                                  environment, theoretical and methodological
                                                  discussions happen side-by-side with hands-on work
                                                  with digital materials. Humanities scholars and
                                                  students, designers, engineers, and computer
                                                  scientists engage together in ongoing tool design
                                                  as defined by the specific needs of participating
                                                  humanities projects.</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#hd"/></cit>
                                        <cit><quote rend="block">The Digital Humanities Laboratory
                                                  (DHLab), a unit of Yale University Library, offers
                                                  space, community, and resources for Yale scholars
                                                  who are using computational methods to pursue
                                                  research questions in the arts, humanities, and
                                                  humanistic social sciences. Located inside
                                                  Sterling Memorial Library, the Franke Family
                                                  Digital Humanities Laboratory is a hub for
                                                  consultations, training, and opportunities that
                                                  support Yale students, faculty, and cultural
                                                  heritage professionals in their engagement with
                                                  digital tools and techniques.</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#dhlab"/></cit>
                                        <cit><quote rend="block">The Humanities Lab at ASU is
                                                  designed as an experimental space in which
                                                  interdisciplinary faculty teams work with students
                                                  from a variety of academic and cultural
                                                  backgrounds to investigate grand social
                                                  challenges, to construct researchable questions
                                                  that delve deeply into those challenges, and to
                                                  generate possible approaches to complex, “wicked”
                                                  issues like immigration, health, and climate
                                                  change, for which there are no easy
                                                  answers.</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#azhl"/></cit></p>
                                <p>The first lab, the Humanities + Design is a research lab at the
                                        Center for Spatial and Textual Analysis at Stanford
                                        University focused on designing and producing tools through
                                        the lens of humanistic inquiry. Critical thinking practiced
                                        by humanities scholars is thus applied to a hands-on work
                                        conducted by designers, engineers, and computer scientists.
                                        The lab team works on building open source tools for digital
                                        research, such as Data Pen, an instrument for creating data
                                        sets that draws from linked data sources, and a
                                        visualization tool Palladio. The second example represents a
                                        lab established as a shared space at the university’s
                                        library. It is a facility that provides equipment and
                                        digital technologies and support in digital humanities
                                        skills acquisition for both research and teaching purposes
                                        through consultations, training, and guest lectures. This
                                        multifunctional lab has been built to offer space,
                                        community, and resources for scholars in the arts,
                                        humanities, and social sciences. The last statement, in
                                        turn, describes the Humanities Lab at Arizona State
                                        University which is a set of lab-based courses. The lab
                                        offers an experimental space where students and faculty work
                                        on a particular problem in intergenerational collaborative
                                        teams for one or two semesters. Each lab is devoted to a
                                        specific socio-cultural challenge that is investigated
                                        through critical thinking, critical engagement, hands-on
                                        practices, and interdisciplinary discussions. Although these
                                        three labs represent different functions and practices, each
                                        is guided by a <q>laboratory</q> ethos, defined by the
                                        Stanford Humanities Lab: collaborative, co-creative, and
                                        team-based <ptr target="#hartwig2011"/>. These features are
                                        the core of laboratory where the humanistic inquiry,
                                        knowledge, and practices are applied, produced, tested, and
                                        investigated. </p>
                                <p>This wide range of uses of the term <q>laboratory</q> implies
                                        that labs are varied due to the function and activities.
                                        Based on the collected data, I indicate the following six
                                        functions of laboratories in the humanities:</p>
                                <list type="ordered">
                                        <item>Research-focused lab - a place for conducting,
                                                coordinating, and promoting cross-disciplinary
                                                research, ranging from theoretical, critical, and
                                                methodological analysis and interpretations to
                                                practices based on learning-by-doing approach, such
                                                the application of digital tools, experimentation,
                                                and prototyping.</item>
                                        <item>Design-focused lab - a place for designing and
                                                producing technical tools, applications, website,
                                                platforms, and creative works which provide new
                                                methods, tools, and a subject of critical
                                                research.</item>
                                        <item>Work station-type lab - a place for providing
                                                equipment, hardware, software, and resource for
                                                facilitating research, teaching, and learning. </item>
                                        <item>Service-focused lab - a place for meeting the
                                                individual needs of users through consulting,
                                                technological services (web hosting, maintenance,
                                                dissemination and preservation for digital
                                                projects), and computer services (support for
                                                conducting digital projects).</item>
                                        <item>Public engagement-focused lab - a place that conducts
                                                research and organizes events related to social
                                                challenges and community affairs, creates
                                                community-curated and participatory projects,
                                                develops new ways of collaborations with public
                                                audiences, and promotes civic engagement. </item>
                                        <item>Pedagogical-focused lab - a place for teaching,
                                                training, and learning through courses, seminars,
                                                lectures, workshops, etc. A laboratory that implies
                                                collaborative and experimental practices, entails
                                                the dissemination of new forms of teaching and
                                                learning in the humanities, including hands-on
                                                practices based on the learning-by-doing approach
                                                (popularized by creative spaces, makerspaces, and
                                                hackerspaces that practice prototyping, tinkering,
                                                and hacking; e.g. the Maker Lab in the Humanities at
                                                the University of Victoria and the Computational
                                                Humanities Lab at the University of
                                                Wisconsin–Madison); experiential learning and
                                                offsite research, that is to say, learning through
                                                direct experience outside a traditional academic
                                                setting, for instance, through traveling (The Global
                                                Humanities Lab course in the Alice Kaplan Institute
                                                for the Humanities at Northwestern University offers
                                                students the investigation of an international
                                                humanities through traveling to cities being the
                                                subject of the study) or field trips (e.g. the
                                                Encountering Food course of the Humanities and Arts
                                                Labs at Albion College where students explore local
                                                and global food through a series of projects and
                                                field trips and organize a community dinner);
                                                problem-based learning meaning that students
                                                investigate an open-ended problem through
                                                collaborative and interdisciplinary practices (e.g.
                                                the Humanities Lab at Arizona State University); and
                                                community-curated public humanities projects (e.g.
                                                practiced by the Humanities Action Lab, a coalition
                                                of universities, organizations, and public spaces in
                                                forty cities, led from Rutgers University-Newark).
                                        </item>
                                </list>
                                <p>Since any laboratory is a self-defined entity focused on a
                                        specific function, activity, and practice, it can be
                                        difficult to build a common definition of the laboratory in
                                        the humanities. However, based on the above reflections, I
                                        attempt to create the following working definition of the
                                        humanities lab: </p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="italic">A laboratory in the humanities is a
                                                technical, research, and intellectual infrastructure
                                                for humanistic issues and inquiries which offers
                                                space (physical, virtual or conceptual), community,
                                                and resources to conduct a set of activities
                                                resulting from its specific function (e.g. research,
                                                design, work station, service, pedagogical, and
                                                public engagement). Laboratory initiatives are
                                                guided by the following principles:
                                                interdisciplinarity, collaboration, co-creation,
                                                team-based, and experimentation.</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>The widespread application of the term <q>laboratory</q> has led
                                        to the fact that there is no single model for the humanities
                                        laboratory. Based on more than two hundred laboratories,
                                        established in North America, North-Western Europe, and
                                        Australia, I determine five models for the humanities labs
                                        due to their situatedness (physical or virtual), traditions,
                                        functions, scholarly questions, practices, and activities.
                                        Let us now explore these five models (the center-type lab,
                                        the techno-science lab, the work station-type lab, the
                                        social challenges-centric lab, and virtual lab), investigate
                                        their organization and indicate a discourse from which they
                                        originate. </p>
                                <div>
                                        <head>The center-type labs </head>
                                        <p>To characterize the center model-based laboratories, it
                                                is essential to summarize the infrastructure changes
                                                that occurred in the humanities over the past years.
                                                In the 1990s, as previously stated, the first
                                                laboratories emerged in the humanities (e.g. the
                                                English Media Lab at the Department of English of
                                                the University of Manitoba in 1995 and the HUMlab at
                                                Umeå University in 1997) modelled upon media labs
                                                for providing digital and analog media, facilitating
                                                the use of digital and online resources, and
                                                assisting with the application of digital tools for
                                                the study of literature, language, culture, and
                                                history. Since the 1990s, the digital humanities
                                                have been rapidly developing through establishing
                                                the first humanities computing centers, later
                                                becoming the digital humanities centers, defined by
                                                Zorich as <quote rend="inline">an entity where new
                                                  media and technologies are used for
                                                  humanities-based research, teaching, and
                                                  intellectual engagement and
                                                  experimentation</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#zorich2008" loc="4"/>. The center
                                                played a crucial role in facilitating and
                                                reinforcing digital humanities research at the
                                                university by providing digital resources, services,
                                                and tools, supporting the teaching of new digital
                                                practices, and hosting symposia and lectures (e.g.,
                                                the Centre for Computing in the Humanities at King’s
                                                College London established in 1991 and Maryland
                                                Institute for Technology in the Humanities in 1999).
                                                Along with the proliferation of the digital
                                                humanities centers, a new institutional unit emerged
                                                in the humanities — a laboratory — modelled on a
                                                center for advancing and fostering the humanities
                                                research on and with digital technologies (e.g., the
                                                Electronic Textual Cultures Lab at the University of
                                                Victoria founded in 2005 and Scholars’ Lab at the
                                                University of Virginia in 2006). </p>
                                        <p>The next changes involve the reorganization of digital
                                                humanities centers into departments (e.g., the
                                                Centre for Computing in the Humanities was renamed
                                                the King’s College Department of Digital Humanities)
                                                and thereby, the institutionalization of the
                                                discipline and the establishment of digital
                                                humanities programmes and degrees. Later, the
                                                infrastructure of the center would be a strategic
                                                choice for the university to further set up the
                                                department of digital humanities (e.g. the
                                                Department of Digital Humanities at the University
                                                of Helsinki grew out of the Helsinki Centre for
                                                Digital Humanities, research network, and
                                                infrastructure established in 2016). Meantime,
                                                laboratories have been launched in the humanities
                                                departments and libraries, emulating the center
                                                model or establishing an entirely new infrastructure
                                                for the humanities research, teaching, and
                                                activities. </p>
                                        <p>Laboratories built upon the center model are a central
                                                institution at the university for conducting,
                                                coordinating, and promoting research, teaching, and
                                                infrastructure for digitization in the humanities
                                                and social science. They play a key role in building
                                                collaboration across departments and providing
                                                support and training to the entire university, as
                                                exemplified by the Price Lab for Digital Humanities
                                                at the University of Pennsylvania: <quote
                                                  rend="inline">The Price Lab serves as a central
                                                  node of communication and exchange across Penn’s
                                                  many departments, centers, and schools with
                                                  expertise and interest in the digital
                                                  humanities</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#pricelab"/>. Instances of laboratories
                                                that were influenced by the center model in other
                                                institutions include: the HUMlab at Umeå University
                                                (1997); the Humanities Lab at Lund University
                                                (2005); Electronic Textual Cultures Lab at the
                                                University of Victoria (2005); the Scholars’ Lab at
                                                the University of Virginia (2006); the Digital
                                                Humanities Lab at the University of Basel (2010);
                                                the Carolina Digital Humanities: Digital Innovation
                                                Lab at the University of North Carolina at Chapel
                                                Hill (2011); the UC Arts Digital Lab at the
                                                University of Canterbury (2011); the D-Lab at the
                                                University of California, Berkeley (2013); the NULab
                                                for Texts, Maps, and Networks at Northeastern
                                                University (2013); the Digital Humanities Lab at
                                                Utrecht University (2014); the Digital Humanities
                                                Innovation Lab (LINHD) at the National University of
                                                Distance Education (2014); the Franke Family Digital
                                                Humanities Laboratory at Yale University (2015); and
                                                the Price Lab for Digital Humanities at the
                                                University of Pennsylvania (2015), </p>
                                        <p>The center-type lab model is identified by the following
                                                features:</p>
                                        <list type="unordered">
                                                <item>Physical situatedness – the lab is mainly
                                                  located in humanities departments or in
                                                  libraries;</item>
                                                <item>Manifold functions – the lab carries out
                                                  various functions from conducting and coordinating
                                                  cross-disciplinary research to providing space,
                                                  equipment, and resources to facilitating research,
                                                  teaching, and learning;</item>
                                                <item>Facilities and equipment – the lab offers
                                                  space, resources, and equipment for conducting and
                                                  facilitating research projects; </item>
                                                <item>A wide range of research projects – the lab
                                                  involves research groups and projects devoted to
                                                  the broad scope of humanities study;</item>
                                                <item>Academic appointments and staffing – the lab
                                                  affiliates faculty and researchers as well as its
                                                  own staff;</item>
                                                <item>The community – the goal of the lab is to
                                                  bring together faculty, staff, and students as
                                                  well as independent scholars and participants from
                                                  cultural institutions and industry interested in a
                                                  particular discipline, practices, and methods
                                                  through series of open lectures, workshops, and
                                                  seminars; </item>
                                                <item>Education – the lab offers teaching and
                                                  training in the form of workshops, courses,
                                                  academic degree programs, postgraduate and faculty
                                                  training, fellowships, internships, and summer
                                                  schools;</item>
                                                <item>Service – the lab offers a number of services
                                                  to support faculties, staff, and students:
                                                  consulting, providing technology solutions,
                                                  maintaining and preserving digital projects,
                                                  etc.</item>
                                        </list>
                                        <p>While any one of these features might be present in other
                                                models, the center is clearly distinguished by a
                                                large-scale central role in advancing humanities
                                                scholarship as well as supporting the study and the
                                                uses of digital methods and technologies for
                                                research and teaching in the humanities. </p>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                        <head>The techno-science labs </head>
                                        <p>In the natural sciences a laboratory is an ordinary place
                                                which provides facilities, instruments, and
                                                equipment with which to conduct experiments, test
                                                hypotheses, and investigate samples. Science
                                                laboratories have a long history dating back to the
                                                alchemical laboratory in the sixteenth century;
                                                however, for the purposes of this paper, we will
                                                focus on the techno-science model developed in the
                                                second half of the twentieth century, along with the
                                                acceleration of technological innovation. A crucial
                                                moment in a lab history occurred when the laboratory
                                                was exposed as a space for constructing knowledge
                                                through the use of technology and instruments rather
                                                than a place for revealing reality. Sociology of
                                                scientific knowledge, mentioned in the previous
                                                section, played a key role in this movement.
                                                Techno-science implies that science cannot be
                                                detached from the technological tools that shape our
                                                perceptions and help to produce the knowledge; thus,
                                                our observations are always embodied via the
                                                practical use of instruments. </p>
                                        <p>Techno-science labs associated with the categories of
                                                production, technology, innovation, and
                                                experimentation became an inspirational architecture
                                                for the humanities in need of a new place to explore
                                                the emerging innovative uses of technology in the
                                                study of history, art, and culture. Therefore, the
                                                impulse to establish a laboratory in the humanities
                                                came about in order to replicate the knowledge
                                                production environment associated with science. A
                                                science-based lab is thus seen as a driving force
                                                for cutting-edge projects and a natural space for
                                                developing and applying technologies to humanities
                                                research. The following labs are good
                                                representations of the techno-science lab model in
                                                the humanities: the Stanford Humanities Lab at
                                                Stanford University (1999-2009); the Critical Media
                                                Lab at the University of Waterloo (2008); the
                                                CulturePlex Lab at the University of Western Ontario
                                                (2010); the Digital Humanities and Literary
                                                Cognition Lab at Michigan State University (2012);
                                                the Humanities + Design a Research Lab at Stanford
                                                University (2012); the Maker Lab in the Humanities
                                                at the University of Victoria (2012); the Poetic
                                                Media Lab at Stanford University (2013); and the
                                                King’s Digital Lab at King’s College London (2015). </p>
                                        <p>Based on these examples, laboratories built using the
                                                techno-science model are driven by the following
                                                functions: providing state-of-the-art facilities and
                                                equipment for experimental and innovative research;
                                                promoting new ways of conducting research, teaching,
                                                and learning through the application of digital
                                                technologies; introducing new digital methods and
                                                new modes of knowledge (e.g., data mining, mapping,
                                                data visualization, simulation, 3D digitisation,
                                                tinkering, coding, prototyping, and fabricating);
                                                producing data-driven research in the humanities;
                                                designing applications, tools, and platforms used in
                                                digital humanities research and teaching; and
                                                designing technical infrastructure for the
                                                humanities. </p>
                                        <p>The principles that guide the techno-science-based
                                                laboratory are identified as:</p>
                                        <list type="unordered">
                                                <item>Physical situatedness – the lab is located in
                                                  a particular place, in different departments (e.g.
                                                  the Critical Media Lab is housed in the Institute
                                                  of Experimental Design and Media Cultures, while
                                                  the Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition Lab
                                                  at the Department of English), and shared by
                                                  people coming from various disciplines who work
                                                  together on research projects;</item>
                                                <item>Equipment and technology – the lab is equipped
                                                  with technological devices and tools that are
                                                  necessary for conducting experiments and
                                                  innovative projects; for example, hardware,
                                                  software, applications, platforms, 3D digital
                                                  technologies, eye-tracking systems, and so
                                                  forth;</item>
                                                <item>Interdisciplinarity – strong post-disciplinary
                                                  modes of research carrying out by humanities
                                                  scholars, designers, computer scientists, software
                                                  analysts, and engineers;</item>
                                                <item>Experimental research – conducting a
                                                  technology-based project that attempts to explore
                                                  new methods of creativity, fill research gaps, and
                                                  open new scholarly perspectives; </item>
                                                <item>Manual work – doing hands-on work with the use
                                                  of material devices, instruments, and
                                                  technologies; </item>
                                                <item>Collaboration – projects are done via
                                                  collaborative actions between faculty, staff, and
                                                  students, between different disciplines and
                                                  departments, and between the university, industry
                                                  and the public sphere; </item>
                                                <item>Applied research – designing applications,
                                                  tools, digital methods, and resources to meet the
                                                  specific needs of humanities projects (e.g., Breve
                                                  and Palladio, which are open-source tools for
                                                  research designed by Humanities + Design a
                                                  Research Lab);</item>
                                                <item>Products – the lab work is focused on
                                                  designing measurable, applicable, and practical
                                                  products, for instance, the Lacuna tool, produced
                                                  by the Poetic Media Lab at Stanford University, is
                                                  used in the Rhizomatic Reading project developed
                                                  at the Center for Digital Humanities in the
                                                  Princeton University Library to analyse
                                                  connections across literary texts.</item>
                                        </list>
                                        <p>The humanities labs originated from techno-science labs
                                                are focused on production, tools, and research
                                                products. Although they stress the notions of
                                                community and collectivity, these concepts are not
                                                their goals in and of themselves but rather a way to
                                                achieve their objectives. Each lab represents
                                                distinct aspects and missions, but their common and
                                                the most significant feature is technology <quote
                                                  rend="inline">being the glue</quote>, to use
                                                Pierre Proske’ description of the Media Lab
                                                Melbourne <ptr target="#proske2013"/>. Digital
                                                technology, tools, and platforms are at once the
                                                methods, the research, and the objects of study
                                                themselves. Drawing on the description of Stanford
                                                Humanities Lab, we can summarize that these labs
                                                involves a <quote rend="inline">triangulation of
                                                  arts practice, commentary/critique, and outreach,
                                                  merging research, pedagogy, publication and
                                                  practice. They didn’t just comment and discuss,
                                                  they built: new media, interactive archives,
                                                  predictive models of social change, new courses,
                                                  collaborative research workshops, art
                                                  exhibitions</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#hartwig2011"/>.</p>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                        <head>The work station-type lab </head>
                                        <p>The next model is called both the work station and
                                                service model <ptr target="#maron2014"/>, referring
                                                to the idea of desktop classrooms, a computer lab,
                                                and instructional technology spaces. This type of
                                                laboratory operates as a physical room that
                                                accumulates equipment and devices used to support
                                                faculty and students in their work. It functions as
                                                the work space that supplies facilities, such as
                                                editing software, digital cameras, and audio
                                                recording devices; provides services, such as
                                                printing and studio spaces; and supports the use of
                                                software and devices. Labs based on the work station
                                                model are located mainly in libraries, which play a
                                                key role in facilitating humanities research by
                                                providing resources and equipment. The library is
                                                also seen as a major place for digital humanities
                                                since it typically carries out the following tasks:
                                                digitizing materials, building digital collections
                                                and resources, and supporting research data
                                                management. Examples of the works station-type
                                                laboratories include: the Digital Scholarship Lab at
                                                Brown University (2012); the Digital Humanities Lab
                                                at the University of Massachusetts Amherst (2012);
                                                the Digital Humanities Lab at the University of
                                                Wisconsin-Milwaukee (2013); the Digital Scholarship
                                                Lab at the University of Oklahoma (2014); Willson
                                                Center Digital Humanities Lab at the University of
                                                Georgia (2015); the Digital Humanities Lab at
                                                Bowling Green State University (2015); the Digital
                                                Humanities Lab at Rutgers University (2015); the
                                                Humanities Research Lab at California State
                                                University, Northridge (2016); the Digital
                                                Humanities Lab at the University of Exeter (2017);
                                                the Digital Humanities Lab in the Centre for Digital
                                                Humanities Research at Australian National
                                                University (2017); and the Digital Scholarship Lab
                                                at Michigan State University (2018).</p>
                                        <p>These labs are guided by the following functions:
                                                supplying facilities, equipment, and devices;
                                                supporting faculty and students in their studies;
                                                providing help in research data management; and
                                                training faculty and students in regard to the
                                                utilization of equipment, digital tools, and
                                                software.</p>
                                        <p>The work station model is distinguished by features
                                                listed below: </p>
                                        <list type="unordered">
                                                <item>Physical situatedness – the lab is located
                                                  mainly in libraries but also in the humanities
                                                  departments;</item>
                                                <item>Reconfigurable space – the place is made to be
                                                  adjusted according to needs and conditions; for
                                                  example, the Digital Scholarship Lab at the Brown
                                                  University Library can be converted from a lecture
                                                  hall to a team project room;</item>
                                                <item>Facilities, equipment, and technological tools
                                                  – the lab provides different types of facilities
                                                  (sound recording studio, interview room),
                                                  equipment (computers, cameras, eye trackers, 3D
                                                  printers), and software; </item>
                                                <item>Specific function – the lab defines its
                                                  purposes clearly, which may range from providing
                                                  equipment and tools for students, supporting
                                                  research data management, offering technical
                                                  assistance, such as metadata encoding and
                                                  archiving digital projects, and training faculty
                                                  and students on the use of various media and
                                                  tools;</item>
                                                <item>Specific users – the lab targets specific
                                                  users who have access to the lab and permission to
                                                  use its facilities; for instance, the Digital
                                                  Humanities Lab at Rutgers University is available
                                                  only to members of the Rutgers digital humanities
                                                  community;</item>
                                                <item>Terms and conditions – since the lab welcomes
                                                  everyone from any discipline and level of
                                                  experience, it provides rules related to the use
                                                  of the lab’s facilities and equipment. </item>
                                        </list>
                                        <p>The humanities lab as a work station aims to provide an
                                                environment, services, and facilities which support
                                                scholarly work rather than innovative research
                                                projects, as in the case of techno-science labs. A
                                                laboratory is thus understood literally as a place —
                                                referring again to Hannaway’s definition — equipped
                                                with specialized instruments and apparatuses that
                                                require hands-on skills and knowledge for their
                                                utilization. </p>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                        <head>The social challenges-centric lab </head>
                                        <p>The next model of a humanities laboratory grows out of
                                                social labs, community labs, and citizen labs <ptr
                                                  target="#hassan2014"/>
                                                <ptr target="#kieboom2014"/>
                                                <ptr target="#tiesinga2014"/>
                                                <ptr target="#ricaurte2018"/> as well as public
                                                humanities initiatives. It comes from seeking <quote
                                                  rend="inline">new research methods, new lines of
                                                  inquiry, and new ways of engaging with public
                                                  audiences</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#fhi"/> for tackling real-world
                                                problems and stimulating social changes. Marlieke
                                                Kieboom claims that one way to address global and
                                                local problems is to establish a new space entailing
                                                new practices, methods, and solutions; a promising
                                                place for undertaking the challenges is a laboratory
                                                seen as a <quote rend="inline">container for social
                                                  experimentation</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#kieboom2014" loc="9"/>. A lab implies
                                                new practices, such as collaboration, integration,
                                                public action, and dialogue across departments,
                                                institutions, and communities. A laboratory is an
                                                experimental space where the humanities can merge
                                                with other disciplines and take part in the process
                                                of addressing local and global concerns. The great
                                                example of this model is the Humanities Lab at
                                                Arizona State University founded by Sally Kitch in
                                                2017 to enhance problem-based study and
                                                interdisciplinary and intergenerational
                                                collaboration. As Kitch said, <cit><quote
                                                  rend="inline">I started the Humanities Lab because
                                                  I realized that our students were not benefitting
                                                  from the kind of interdisciplinary, exploratory
                                                  experiences faculty were getting through the IHR.
                                                  (…) So I wanted to see if we could establish a way
                                                  for students to get that experience; to recognize
                                                  the humanities as important for approaching and
                                                  addressing today’s challenges, because the kinds
                                                  of questions that really plague us are humanistic
                                                  at their core. They’re about values and culture
                                                  and understanding the way people form beliefs and
                                                  the kinds of attitudes we carry around with us and
                                                  the way we all live in our own narratives. And
                                                  encountering that is essential for solving these
                                                  problems.</quote>
                                                  <ptr target="#greguska2019"/></cit> The Humanities
                                                Lab was created as an experimental space for
                                                investigating <q>wicked</q> problems, such as
                                                immigration, health, and climate change through the
                                                humanities inquiry approach and intervention: <quote
                                                  rend="inline">Most of the really big challenges we
                                                  face are not fundamentally about technology,
                                                  science, economics, etc. They are human challenges
                                                  that have been with us for a very long time and
                                                  therefore require human-centred inquiry as part of
                                                  the search for a solution. Yet, often the
                                                  humanities disciplines are not included in such
                                                  discussions. Therefore, the Humanities Lab brings
                                                  the humanities to the table by emphasizing the
                                                  study of values and the way we understand the
                                                  world around us. Merging the humanities with
                                                  diverse disciplines helps us to see the grand
                                                  social challenges more holistically and therefore
                                                  puts us in a better position to conceptualize
                                                  solutions.</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#azhl"/></p>
                                        <p>Unlike the techno-science model, which is centred on
                                                designing and applying technological tools to
                                                research projects, the social challenges-centric
                                                model aims to build a common and interventive space
                                                that in itself is a way to address the most profound
                                                social issues. I indicate three varieties of the
                                                social challenges-centric model for a humanities
                                                lab: coalition-based lab, problem-based lab, and
                                                community engagement lab. This model is thus not a
                                                unified structure, but a dynamic form driven by the
                                                ideas of community, dialogue, and intervention. </p>
                                        <p>The first type of lab arises as an initiative of a
                                                coalition of various institutions that activate a
                                                laboratory as an urgent need to react to pressing
                                                problems in a particular place. The Humanities
                                                Action Lab (HAL) is a coalition of universities,
                                                issue organizations, and public spaces in forty
                                                cities led from Rutgers University-Newark. Students
                                                and stakeholders in each city investigate a
                                                particular problem in a local context, produce
                                                community-curated public humanities projects, and
                                                stimulate public dialogue on the urgent questions.
                                                Laboratories can also work on the same problem
                                                explored then by different communities and from
                                                various perspectives. They develop local
                                                contributions to national project that further
                                                  <quote rend="inline">travel nationally and
                                                  internationally to museums, public libraries,
                                                  cultural centers, and other spaces in each of the
                                                  communities that helped create them</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#hal"/>. The examples of national
                                                projects are <title rend="quotes">Guantánamo Public
                                                  Memory Project</title> hosted by Columbia
                                                University. This initiative involved over 300
                                                students from 13 universities to research, document,
                                                and interpret the history of the US naval base at
                                                Guantánamo Bay, Cuba. <quote rend="inline">Students
                                                  from around the country collaborated with more
                                                  than 600 community stakeholders including Haitian
                                                  refugees, former service people, and attorneys
                                                  representing current detainees, to explore GTMO’s
                                                  history from many perspectives, as well as the
                                                  questions it raises today. Together they created a
                                                  traveling exhibit, web platform, digital and
                                                  physical archive, interview collection, and series
                                                  of public dialogues. The exhibit has traveled for
                                                  more than 3 years to 18 cities and counting, with
                                                  public dialogues in each place. More than 500,000
                                                  people will have had a face-to-face encounter with
                                                  the exhibit, and many more online and through
                                                  social media</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#hal"/>. This type of laboratory is a
                                                great example of how the humanities can bring
                                                together people from various institutions around a
                                                particular challenge, participate in public dialogue
                                                and call for action at the local and national
                                                level.</p>
                                        <p>The problem-based lab is in turn set up around a central
                                                theme for a specific purpose. It thus creates an
                                                environment — problem space — around particular
                                                urgent social and cultural issues that need to be
                                                addressed by integrative and interdisciplinary
                                                approach. Good examples are the labs within the
                                                Humanities Laboratories at the Franklin Humanities
                                                Institute of Duke University, where each individual
                                                lab is devoted to a particular problem and launched
                                                for mainly three years. The first lab at the FHI,
                                                Haiti Lab, was established after Haiti’s natural
                                                disaster in 2010 to broaden knowledge about Haitian
                                                culture, history, and language and expand Haitian
                                                studies in the U.S. Other labs at the FHI devoted to
                                                significant social phenomena and challenges are
                                                BorderWork(s) Lab (2011-2014) investigating the acts
                                                of division and demarcation in the world; Health
                                                Humanities Lab (2016- present) undertaking issues of
                                                clinical medicine and public health from the
                                                perspective of the humanities and social science;
                                                and From Slavery to Freedom Lab (2018- present)
                                                examining the life and afterlives of slavery and
                                                emancipation. The similar type of problem-based lab
                                                is also set up within the Humanities Lab at Arizona
                                                State University where each lab works as a one- or
                                                two-semester course bringing together students and
                                                faculty around <q>wicked</q> issues. The lab is thus
                                                established for a fixed period of time to
                                                investigate grand social challenges, construct
                                                researchable questions, and generate possible
                                                approaches to complex problems. So far, the
                                                Humanities Lab program has launched the following
                                                courses: Health &amp; Wellbeing Lab, Sexual Violence
                                                Lab, Sustaining Humans Lab, Rebuilding Puerto Rico
                                                Lab, and Facing Immigration Lab. The next great
                                                example, differing from the previous ones, is the
                                                Human Security Collaboratory (HS Collab) launched by
                                                the Global Security Initiative (GSI) at Arizona
                                                State University focused on addressing complex
                                                problems related to digital security and civil
                                                rights through the application of digital humanities
                                                tools and inquiries. The lab’s current projects
                                                include <title rend="quotes">Border Quants</title>,
                                                a collective of artists and scholars conducting
                                                research related to digital human rights, personal
                                                data protection, and decolonial approaches to data
                                                use, and <title rend="quotes">Vibrant Lives</title>,
                                                an immersive performance installation as a critical
                                                comment on the use and monetization of personal data
                                                production. The important part of the lab’s
                                                activities is a public engagement through events,
                                                such as a series of lunchtime conversations about
                                                digital human security issues. </p>
                                        <p>The third type of lab — the community engagement lab —
                                                aims to promote civic engagement through
                                                participatory approaches to research and social
                                                action. Good examples are the mentioned HS Collab at
                                                Arizona State University and the Engage Media Lab at
                                                The New School. The latter lab is a student group
                                                and research lab that develops workshops,
                                                screenings, and research projects in collaboration
                                                with The New School students and the New York City
                                                community. Other instances include the Public
                                                Humanities Lab at the University of Virginia and the
                                                Participatory Cultures Lab at McGill University. The
                                                last one is particularly focused on participatory
                                                research devoted to issues of social justice,
                                                gender-based violence, food security, and poverty
                                                alleviation. Research projects use various tools
                                                that engage a community: digital storytelling,
                                                photovoice, participatory archiving, and more.
                                                Community engagement projects are conducted through
                                                the collaboration with variety countries including
                                                South Africa, Ethiopia, Mozambique, Vietnam, and
                                                Indonesia. </p>
                                        <p>To summarize, instances of laboratories built upon the
                                                social challenges-centric model include: the
                                                Humanities Laboratories at Duke University (2010);
                                                the Participatory Cultures Lab at McGill University
                                                (2010); the Engage Media Lab at The New School
                                                (2011); the Humanities Action Lab led from Rutgers
                                                University-Newark (2014); the Human Security
                                                Collaboratory (HS Collab) at Arizona State
                                                University (2015); the Humanities Lab at Arizona
                                                State University (2017); and the Public Humanities
                                                Lab at the University of Virginia (2017). </p>
                                        <p>Based on these cases, the social challenges-centric model
                                                of labs can encompass the following functions:
                                                building a community around the lab and challenges;
                                                fostering collaboration and communication across
                                                departments, institutions, and communities; engaging
                                                with the local community beyond the university;
                                                connecting the diverse local perspectives of
                                                communities around the world; producing
                                                community-curated public humanities projects;
                                                propelling positive social, cultural, and
                                                environmental changes; promoting civic engagement;
                                                and initiating new public dialogues.</p>
                                        <p>The model is guided by the following principles:</p>
                                        <list type="unordered">
                                                <item>Flexible structure – the lab can be situated
                                                  physically or virtually and formed as a meeting
                                                  place, research group or course; in this sense, a
                                                  lab can be created anywhere at the university or
                                                  beyond;</item>
                                                <item>Flexible duration – the lab can be set up for
                                                  a specific period of time and then can be closed
                                                  down once a project is concluded and goals are
                                                  achieved;</item>
                                                <item>The community – people gathered around the lab
                                                  are the main resources and their dialogue are the
                                                  driving forces of the lab;</item>
                                                <item>Collaboration and integration – the lab is an
                                                  integrative environment for faculty, staff,
                                                  students, and the local community;</item>
                                                <item>Specific purpose of the lab – the goals are
                                                  particularly related to social challenges, global
                                                  “wicked” problems, and the local community;</item>
                                                <item>The infrastructure of engagement – the lab
                                                  works as the infrastructure that provides space
                                                  and tools for intervening in social issues,
                                                  translating ideas into action, and enhancing the
                                                  engaged humanities;</item>
                                                <item>A wide range of methods – the lab uses various
                                                  methods for tackling problems, such as public
                                                  dialogues, interventions, digital methods,
                                                  interviews, testimonies, prototyping, and
                                                  participatory-based methods;</item>
                                                <item>Public actions – public initiatives are a
                                                  product of the lab, including exhibits, web
                                                  platforms, digital and physical archives,
                                                  interview collections, and series of public
                                                  dialogues.</item>
                                        </list>
                                        <p>The social challenges-centric model for the humanities
                                                lab originates from the concepts of social labs,
                                                citizen labs, and public creative spaces. While the
                                                techno-science model is centred on applied research,
                                                technological issues, and innovative approaches, the
                                                social challenges-centric model is created around
                                                people, social issues, and public engagement.
                                                Further, while the techno-science model produces
                                                quantifiable and applied projects, the products of
                                                this model of labs are dynamic, powerful, and
                                                influential. As Zaid Hassan claims, <quote
                                                  rend="inline">Complex challenges are therefore
                                                  dynamic and can change in unexpected ways over
                                                  time, whereas technical challenges are relatively
                                                  stable and static in comparison</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#hassan2014"/>. To conclude, the social
                                                challenges-centric model can be created in any
                                                environment where there is a need to initiate
                                                dialogue and collaboration across communities to
                                                solve particular local problems.</p>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                        <head>The virtual lab </head>
                                        <p>Thus far, the term <q>laboratory</q> has been used in the
                                                context of Hannaway’s definition of a place which
                                                accumulates instruments, techniques, and
                                                apparatuses. The techno-science, work station, and
                                                community labs have one major thing in common, which
                                                is physical situatedness <ptr target="#svensson2015"
                                                />. A concrete location with an infrastructure and
                                                facilities determines the knowledge creation
                                                practices, the collaboration methods, and social
                                                interactions. However, in recent years, along with
                                                the development of cyberinfrastructure, we have
                                                witnessed the expansion of a new lab model: the
                                                virtual laboratory. </p>
                                        <p>The advancement of cyberinfrastructure underpinned the
                                                development of the digital humanities field that
                                                applies computational tools and methods to the
                                                humanities. The discipline of digital humanities is
                                                based on the utilization of digital source
                                                materials, digital methods, and new ways of
                                                collaborating in the digital environment. The core
                                                feature of the digital humanities is thus virtual
                                                situatedness, defined as the digital, internet-based
                                                workspace with an infrastructure, connection, and
                                                operation that affect the work and research
                                                communication. Scholars work in the virtual space,
                                                including online platforms and the virtual research
                                                environment, which directs digital humanities
                                                research, supports the use of digital tools, and
                                                enables scholarly collaboration. Digital humanities
                                                scholars are thus examples of researchers who work
                                                in both physical and virtual spaces. Therefore,
                                                their research rooms comprise physical places, such
                                                as a laboratory or center, as well as a virtual
                                                laboratory. Hence, the concept of laboratory goes
                                                beyond the category of physical location towards a
                                                placeless and virtual idea not determined by walls
                                                and physical situatedness. The virtual model of the
                                                humanities lab plays a key role in the
                                                cyberinfrastructure that enhances the web-based
                                                research environment, supports national and
                                                international collaborations, facilitates networks
                                                of scholars, and provides data services, resources,
                                                and tools.</p>
                                        <p>Given the scope of the function and the operation of the
                                                virtual laboratory, the model comprises two types of
                                                labs. The first is formed as a collaborative
                                                platform for enhancing communication and cooperation
                                                and promoting new modes of learning and research
                                                with the use of digital tools and technologies.
                                                HASTAC (Humanities, Arts, Science and Technology
                                                Alliance and Collaboratory) constitutes a good
                                                example of this initiative. It is a community-based
                                                publishing and an academic social networking
                                                platform that enables global communication, sharing,
                                                and collaborations among students and researchers
                                                across the humanities, social sciences, media
                                                studies, the arts, and technology sectors. Alfalab
                                                (2009-2011), in turn, was a collaborative network
                                                and a virtual project of five institutes of the
                                                Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences that
                                                aimed to promote, provide, and apply the use of
                                                digital tools and methods in the humanities research
                                                practices and foster a cooperation of humanities
                                                researchers at national and international levels. </p>
                                        <p>The second type, called the virtual research environment,
                                                is a virtual space for facilitating digital research
                                                processes, providing databases, tools, and services,
                                                and promoting collaboration across the university,
                                                academic institutions, and cultural organizations.
                                                It is an innovative, web-based, and
                                                community-oriented digital environment with an
                                                international dimension, defined by Annamaria Carusi
                                                and Torsten Reimer as a <quote rend="inline">set of
                                                  web applications, online tools, systems and
                                                  processes interoperating to facilitate or enhance
                                                  the research process within and without
                                                  institutional boundaries; it enables collaborative
                                                  research activities beyond geographical
                                                  barriers</quote>
                                                <ptr target="#carusi2010" loc="12"/>. Examples of
                                                virtual research environments for the humanities are
                                                the TextGrid Laboratory provided by DARIAH-DE;
                                                DHVLab, the Digital Humanities Virtual Laboratory
                                                carried out at the Ludwig Maximilian University of
                                                Munich (it consists of a teaching and research
                                                infrastructure in the applications and methods used
                                                in the digital humanities); HuNI (Humanities
                                                Networked Infrastructure), a virtual laboratory
                                                developed as part of the Australian government’s
                                                NeCTAR (National e-Research Collaboration Tools and
                                                Resources) program (it is a platform that combines
                                                data from many Australian cultural websites into the
                                                humanities and creative arts database); the Digital
                                                Humanities Innovation Lab (LINHD) at the National
                                                University of Distance Education in Spain (a
                                                laboratory that serves as a hub for infrastructures
                                                and tools for digital humanities projects in Spain
                                                and Spanish speaking countries); and the Nordic
                                                Digital Humanities Laboratory (NDHL), the ongoing
                                                initiative that aims to create convergence in Nordic
                                                humanities and arts e-infrastructures through a
                                                participant-driven virtual laboratory for
                                                data-intensive research. </p>
                                        <p>Hence, the structure of the virtual model of the
                                                humanities laboratory can be grasped through:</p>
                                        <list type="unordered">
                                                <item>Virtual situatedness – research and
                                                  collaboration processes take place in the digital
                                                  and shared workspace;</item>
                                                <item>Technology and software – they are key
                                                  composers of virtual spaces and the main
                                                  conditions for sustaining, accessing, and using
                                                  the virtual laboratory;</item>
                                                <item>Users-driven – the virtual lab is created for
                                                  and by the research community; thus, the
                                                  development of the virtual lab depends on users’
                                                  activities, support, and feedback;</item>
                                                <item>Network approach – the main purpose of the lab
                                                  is building the interaction and collaboration
                                                  network between researchers, universities, and
                                                  organizations;</item>
                                                <item>Service and resource-based project – the
                                                  virtual lab provides data services, digital
                                                  materials, tools, and an environment for research
                                                  practices and collaboration;</item>
                                                <item>Terms and conditions – the lab space is
                                                  determined by the terms and conditions related to
                                                  access, using, and sharing the data and other
                                                  resources within the virtual platform.</item>
                                        </list>
                                        <p>The advancement of cyberinfrastructure ushered in the era
                                                of virtual laboratories, created in the digital
                                                environment beyond physical, geographical, and
                                                cultural borders. Similar to the center-type lab,
                                                the techno-science and work station-type lab, the
                                                virtual laboratory facilitates scholarly practices
                                                and enables collaborative, innovative, and
                                                technology-based projects. Hence, the virtual lab
                                                represents a laboratory with the aspects
                                                characterized by the rest of the models. The main
                                                difference lies in situatedness; while the previous
                                                labs are all determined by a physical location and
                                                physical infrastructure, digital labs are signified
                                                by virtual milieu and software. </p>
                                </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                                <head>Conclusions</head>
                                <p>The paper has shown that the laboratory turn has emerged in the
                                        humanities as a part of a wider process of the
                                                <term>laboratorization</term> of social life, which
                                        has been occurring since the 1980s and with a significant
                                        intensification in the last ten years. The emergence of the
                                        laboratory in the humanities is thus the effect of
                                        superimposing three discourses that appeared in different
                                        domains: in the humanities, social sciences, and culture.
                                        Laboratories made inroads into the humanities, introduced
                                        new methods and practices and put the humanities on a par
                                        with applied science. A laboratory, however, is more than a
                                        new infrastructure within the humanities, it is a <quote
                                                rend="inline">meeting place</quote>
                                        <ptr target="#humlab"/>, an <quote rend="inline">incubator
                                                for new ideas</quote>
                                        <ptr target="#auhl"/>, and a <quote rend="inline">conceptual
                                                vehicle</quote>
                                        <ptr target="#criticalmedia"/>. The lab becomes
                                        conceptualized as a way of thinking entailing new social
                                        practices and new research modes (collaboration,
                                        experimentation, and hands-on practices). Hence, the
                                        laboratory turn has been driven by the movement away from
                                        building physical labs towards creating concept-based
                                        laboratories (lab courses, lab projects). The study has
                                        shown that the year of 2010 became a significant period in
                                        the history of the laboratory in the humanities. The
                                        Franklin Humanities Institute at Duke University established
                                        a new model for the humanities labs, which gave rise to
                                        conceptual laboratories seen more as problem-based projects
                                        rather than physical work spaces. This essay has focused on
                                        the application of the term <q>laboratory</q> to the
                                        humanities field in the academy. Therefore, the issues of
                                        the implementation of labs beyond this field and the
                                        university’s campus remain still unexplored, including the
                                        emergence of labs in GLAM sector, the formation of cultural
                                        and citizens labs along with makerspaces and hackerspaces in
                                        public domain, and the use of the word <q>lab</q> in
                                        different areas of social life. Humanities labs constitute
                                        part of the ongoing move towards turning various social
                                        spaces and initiatives into a <term>laboratory</term> that
                                        is a good lever to intervene in local and global complex
                                        problems, testing and scaling ideas, and designing
                                        prototypes through a collaboration of experts and citizens. </p>
                                <p>The second major finding was that the implementation of
                                        laboratory emerged as the essential process in the
                                        development of the humanities, one, which required the
                                        reconstruction of infrastructure to support new research
                                        practices and methods related to the utilization of
                                        technology and digital tools. Therefore, the digital
                                        humanities have become the driving force behind building a
                                        laboratory space, which supports situated practices, the
                                        collaborative, and technology-based projects. Furthermore,
                                        the digital humanities have propelled the development of the
                                        virtual laboratory, which involves virtual situatedness, a
                                        collaborative and academic network, and the digital research
                                        environment. </p>
                                <p>The next significant finding to emerge from this study is that
                                        borrowing the laboratory concept from science does not mean
                                        imitating its form and features. The humanities have
                                        developed unique models of labs differing in the scale of
                                        operation, infrastructure, and functions: the center-type
                                        lab, the techno-science lab, the work station-type lab, the
                                        social challenges-centric lab, and virtual lab. The previous
                                        section has shown that each type produces knowledge
                                        resulting from a lab structure and mission. Humanities labs
                                        do not represent a unified structure; instead, they consist
                                        of a group of various types of labs, which have their own
                                        architectures, goals, and practices. As a result, the
                                        humanities lab does not simply imitate the science lab but
                                        adapts this new infrastructure for its own purposes and
                                        needs. What fascinates me here is also the way how the
                                        humanities reposition themselves in the academy and public
                                        domain by bringing the field into dialogue with the sciences
                                        in interdisciplinary labs, building their own
                                        infrastructure, and designing a lab as a site of
                                        intervention in social challenges. </p>
                                <p>This study has important implications for understanding the
                                        concept of laboratory in the humanities as well as
                                        developing new models and sites. However, one challenge of
                                        the humanities lab remains to be discussed: its
                                        sustainability. The problem of sustainability concerns any
                                        model of laboratory <ptr target="#maron2014"/>. It is a
                                        question of maintaining the long-term viability of a lab and
                                        sustaining the commitments of time and effort made by the
                                        people who are the core of the laboratory. Through examining
                                        lab projects that completed their activities (e.g., Alfalab,
                                        2009-2011; the Computational Humanities Lab at the
                                        University of Wisconsin–Madison, 2012-2014; the Digital
                                        Cultures Lab at Douglas College, 2014-2018), it becomes
                                        clear that it is a major concern requiring further
                                        investigation. The Digital Matters Lab at the University of
                                        Utah has taken action in that direction and chosen the topic
                                        of <q>sustainability</q> for its activities and projects
                                        through 2022. It aims to address the questions of the
                                        accessibility of digital materials and the sustainability of
                                        in-progress artefacts <ptr target="#dmlab"/>. Thus, the
                                        humanities lab is a fascinating phenomenon in the history of
                                        the humanities and many issues regarding its infrastructure,
                                        action, and impact require further analysis and reflection.
                                </p>
                        </div>
                	<div type="appendix" xml:id="acknowledgements">
                                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                                <p>The research included in this article was presented during my
                                        lecture, entitled <title rend="quotes">A Laboratory as
                                                Critical Infrastructure in the Humanities</title> at
                                        the workshop <title rend="quotes">Humanities Laboratories:
                                                Critical Infrastructures and Knowledge
                                                Experiments</title>, hosted by the Department of
                                        Digital Humanities with King’s Digital Lab in conjunction
                                        with the Critical Infrastructure Studies Initiative at
                                        King’s College London on 23 May 2019. I thank the Department
                                        of Digital Humanities at King’s College London for awarding
                                        me the Willard McCarty Fellowship 2018/2019 and giving an
                                        opportunity to share my research. I would like to thank the
                                        participants at the workshop for the feedback I received. I
                                        also thank two anonymous reviewers for their careful reading
                                        and many insightful comments and suggestions. </p>
                        </div>
                </body>
                <back>
                        <listBibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="berry2011" label="Berry 2011">Berry, D. M. <title
                                                rend="quotes">The Computational Turn: Thinking About
                                                the Digital Humanities</title>, Culture Machine, 12
                                        (2011). </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="bod2013" label="Bod 2013">Bod, R. <title rend="italic"
                                                >A New History of the Humanities: The Search for
                                                Principles and Patterns from Antiquity to the
                                                Present</title>. Oxford University Press, New York
                                        (2013).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="bérubé1995" label="Bérubé et al. 1995">Bérubé, M. and
                                        Nelson, C. (eds). <title rend="italic">Higher Education
                                                under Fire. Politics, Economics and the Crisis of
                                                the Humanities</title>. Routledge, London and New
                                        York (1995).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="breithaupt2017" label="Breithaupt 2017">Breithaupt, F.
                                                <title rend="quotes">Designing a Lab in the
                                                Humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">The
                                                Chronicle of Higher Education</title>, February 06,
                                        2017. <ref
                                                target="http://www.chronicle.com/article/Designing-a-Lab-in-the/239132"
                                                >http://www.chronicle.com/article/Designing-a-Lab-in-the/239132</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="brown1989" label="Brown et al. 1989">Brown, J. S.,
                                        Collins, A. and Duguid P. <title rend="quotes">Situated
                                                Cognition and the Culture of Learning</title>,
                                                <title rend="italic">Educational Researcher</title>,
                                        18(1) (1989): 32-42.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="carusi2010" label="Carusi et al. 2010">. Carusi, A.
                                        and Reimer, T. <title rend="quotes">Virtual Research
                                                Environment Collaborative Landscape Study</title>.
                                        JISC (2010). <ref
                                                target="http://www.jisc.ac.uk/media/documents/publications/vrelandscapereport.pdf"
                                                >http://www.jisc.ac.uk/media/documents/publications/vrelandscapereport.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="collini2012" label="Collini 2012">Collini, S. <title
                                                rend="italic">What Are Universities For?</title>
                                        Penguin Books, London (2012). </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="coopmans2014" label="Coopmans et al. 2014">Coopmans,
                                        C., Vertesi, J., Lynch, M. E., and Woolgar, S. (eds) <title
                                                rend="italic">Representation in Scientific
                                                Practice</title>. Revisited. MIT Press, Cambridge
                                        and London (2014). </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="criticalmedia" label="Critical Media Lab n.d."
                                        >Critical Media Lab. <title rend="quotes">The Academy of Art
                                                and Design FHNW in Basel</title>. <ref
                                                target="https://www.ixdm.ch/critical-media-lab/"
                                                >https://www.ixdm.ch/critical-media-lab/</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="dhlab" label="Yale DH Lab n.d.">Digital Humanities
                                        Laboratory at Yale University Library. <title rend="quotes"
                                                >Our Mission</title>. <ref
                                                target="https://dhlab.yale.edu/about.html"
                                                >https://dhlab.yale.edu/about.html</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="dmlab" label="Digital Matters Lab n.d.">Digital
                                        Matters Lab. <title rend="quotes">Theme:
                                                Sustainability</title>, <ref
                                                target="https://digitalmatters.utah.edu/digital-matters-lab/"
                                                >https://digitalmatters.utah.edu/digital-matters-lab/</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="donoghue2008" label="Donoghue 2008">Donoghue, F.
                                                <title rend="italic">The Last Professors: The
                                                Corporate University and the Fate of the
                                                Humanities</title>. Fordham University Press, New
                                        York (2008).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="earhart2015" label="Earhart 2015">Earhart, A. E.
                                                <title rend="quotes">The Digital Humanities as a
                                                Laboratory</title>. In P. Svensson and D. T.
                                        Goldberg (eds). <title rend="italic">Between Humanities and
                                                the Digital</title>. MIT Press, Cambridge and London
                                        (2015), pp. 391-400.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="emerson" label="Emerson et al. n.d.">Emerson, L.,
                                        Parikka, J., Wershler, D. <title rend="italic">The Lab Book.
                                                Situated Practices in Media Studies</title>.
                                        University of Minnesota Press (forthcoming). <ref
                                                target="https://manifold.umn.edu/projects/the-lab-book"
                                                >https://manifold.umn.edu/projects/the-lab-book</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="flanders2002" label="Flanders et al. 2002">Flanders,
                                        J. and Unsworth, J. <title rend="quotes">The Evolution of
                                                Humanities Computing Centers</title>, <title
                                                rend="italic">Computers and the Humanities</title>,
                                        36 (2002): 379–380. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="foka2018" label="Foka et al. 2018">Foka, A. et al.
                                                <title rend="quotes">Beyond Humanities qua Digital:
                                                Spatial and Material Development for Digital
                                                Research Infrastructures in HumlabX</title>, <title
                                                rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the
                                                Humanities</title> 33(2) (2018): 264-278. DOI: <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqx008"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqx008</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="fraistat2012" label="Fraistat 2012">Fraistat, N.
                                                <title rend="quotes">The Function of Digital
                                                Humanities Centers at the Present Time</title>. In
                                        M. K. Gold (ed). <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                                                Humanities</title>, University of Minnesota Press,
                                        Minneapolis (2012). <ref
                                                target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/23"
                                                >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/23</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="galison1999" label="Galison et al. 1999">Galison, P.
                                        and Thompson E. (eds). <title rend="italic">The Architecture
                                                of Science</title>. MIT Press, Cambridge and London
                                        (1999).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="gold2012" label="Gold 2012">Gold, M. K. (ed). <title
                                                rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                                                Humanities</title>. University of Minnesota Press,
                                        Minneapolis (2012). <ref
                                                target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/"
                                                >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="goodman2014" label="Goodman 2014">Goodman, A. L.
                                                <title rend="quotes">Digital Media Labs in
                                                Libraries</title>, <title rend="italic">Library
                                                Technology Reports</title>, August/September 50(6)
                                        (2014). </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="gottschall2008" label="Gottschall 2008">Gottschall, J.
                                                <title rend="quotes">Literature, Science, and a New
                                                Humanities</title>. Palgrave Macmillan, New York
                                        (2008).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="greguska2019" label="Greguska 2019">Greguska, E.
                                                <title rend="quotes">Confronting grand social
                                                challenges with humanities</title>, <title
                                                rend="italic">ASU Now: Access, Excellence,
                                                Impact</title>, February 21, 2019. <ref
                                                target="https://asunow.asu.edu/20190221-solutions-confronting-grand-social-challenges-humanities"
                                                >https://asunow.asu.edu/20190221-solutions-confronting-grand-social-challenges-humanities</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="hal" label="HAL n.d.">Humanities Action Lab. <ref
                                                target="https://www.humanitiesactionlab.org/about"
                                                >https://www.humanitiesactionlab.org/about</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="hamilton2015" label="Hamilton et al. 2015">Hamilton,
                                        M. and Hanke Schmidt, D. <title rend="italic">Make It Here:
                                                Inciting Creativity and Innovation in Your
                                                Library</title>. Libraries Unlimited, Santa Barbara,
                                        CA (2015).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="hannaway1986" label="Hannaway 1986">Hannaway, O.
                                                <title rend="quotes">Laboratory Design and the Aim
                                                of Science: Andreas Libavius versus Tycho
                                                Brahe</title>, <title rend="italic">Isis</title> 77
                                        (1986): 585-610.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="hartwig2011" label="Hartwig 2011">Hartwig, D. <title
                                                rend="quotes">Guide to the Stanford Humanities Lab
                                                Records</title>. <title rend="italic">Online Archive
                                                of California</title> (2011). <ref
                                                target="https://oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/kt3b69r9xx/entire_text/"
                                                >https://oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/kt3b69r9xx/entire_text/</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="hassan2014" label="Hassan 2014">Hassan, Z. <title
                                                rend="italic">The Social Labs Revolution: A New
                                                Approach to Solving our Most Complex
                                                Challenges</title>. Berrett-Koehler, San Francisco
                                        (2014).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="hatch2013" label="Hatch 2013">Hatch, M. <title
                                                rend="italic">The Maker Movement Manifesto: Rules
                                                for Innovation in the New World of Crafters,
                                                Hackers, and Tinkerers</title>. McGraw-Hill
                                        Education, New York (2013). </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="hiatt2005" label="Hiatt 2005">Hiatt, G. <title
                                                rend="quotes">We Need Humanities Labs</title>,
                                                <title rend="italic">Inside Higher Ed</title>,
                                        October 26, 2005. <ref
                                                target="https://www.insidehighered.com/views/2005/10/26/we-need-humanities-labs"
                                                >https://www.insidehighered.com/views/2005/10/26/we-need-humanities-labs</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="hd" label="Humanities + Design n.d.">Humanities +
                                        Design a Research Lab at the Center for Spatial and Textual
                                        Analysis at Stanford University. <ref
                                                target="https://hdlab.stanford.edu/"
                                                >https://hdlab.stanford.edu/</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="azhl" label="ASU Humanities Lab n.d.">Humanities Lab
                                        at Arizona State University. <ref
                                                target="https://humanities.lab.asu.edu/"
                                                >https://humanities.lab.asu.edu/</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="auhl" label="AU Humanities Lab n.d.">Humanities Lab. A
                                        Research Center for the Humanities at American University.
                                                <ref target="http://auhumanitieslab.com/"
                                                >http://auhumanitieslab.com/</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="cchl" label="Colby College Humanities Lab n.d."
                                        >Humanities Labs at Colby College. <ref
                                                target="http://www.colby.edu/centerartshumanities/arts-and-humanities-labs/"
                                                >http://www.colby.edu/centerartshumanities/arts-and-humanities-labs/</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="fhi" label="FHI-DU Humanities Labs n.d.">Humanities
                                        Laboratories at the Franklin Humanities Institute at Duke
                                        University. <ref target="https://fhi.duke.edu/labs"
                                                >https://fhi.duke.edu/labs</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="humlab" label="HUMlab n.d.">HUMlab at Umeå University.
                                                <ref target="http://www.humlab.umu.se/en"
                                                >http://www.humlab.umu.se/en</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="ihde2009" label="Ihde 2009">Ihde, D. <title
                                                rend="italic">Postphenomenology and Technoscience:
                                                The Peking University Lectures</title>. State
                                        University of New York Press, Albany (2009). </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="jay2014" label="Jay 2014">Jay, P. <title rend="italic"
                                                >The Humanities <q>Crisis</q> and the Future of
                                                Literary Studies</title>. Palgrave Macmillan, New
                                        York (2014).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="johnson2016" label="Johnson 2016">Johnson, E. D. M.
                                                <title rend="quotes">The Right Place at the Right
                                                Time: Creative Spaces in Libraries</title>. In S. S.
                                        Hines and K. Moore (eds). <title rend="italic">The Future of
                                                Library Space.</title> Advances in Library
                                        Administration and Organization 36 (2016): 1-36. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="joselow2016" label="Joselow 2016">Joselow, M. <title
                                                rend="quotes">Labs Are for the Humanities,
                                                Too</title>, <title rend="italic">Inside Higher
                                                Ed</title>, July 12, 2016. <ref
                                                target="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2016/07/12/conference-explores-humanities-labs"
                                                >https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2016/07/12/conference-explores-humanities-labs</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="kagan2009" label="Kagan 2009">Kagan, J. <title
                                                rend="italic">Three Cultures. Natural Sciences,
                                                Social Sciences and the Humanities in the 21st
                                                Century</title>. Cambridge University Press,
                                        Cambridge and New York (2009).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="kavanaghwebb2018" label="Kavanagh Webb 2018">Kavanagh
                                        Webb, K. <title rend="italic">Development of Creative Spaces
                                                in Academic Libraries: A Decision Maker’s
                                                Guide.</title> Chandos Publishing, Cambridge, MA
                                        (2018).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="kerr2001" label="Kerr 2001">Kerr, C. <title
                                                rend="italic">The Uses of the University</title>.
                                        Harvard University Press, Cambridge, MA (2001).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="kieboom2014" label="Kieboom 2014">Kieboom, M. <title
                                                rend="italic">Lab Matters: Challenging the Practice
                                                of Social Innovation Laboratories</title>.
                                        Kennisland, Amsterdam (2014). </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="klein2005" label="Klein 2005">Klein, J. T. <title
                                                rend="italic">Humanities, Culture, and
                                                Interdisciplinarity. The Changing American
                                                Academy</title>. State University of New York Press,
                                        Albany (2005). </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="knorrcetina1995" label="Knorr Cetina 1995">Knorr
                                        Cetina, K. <title rend="quotes">Laboratory Studies: The
                                                Cultural Approach to the Study of Science</title>.
                                        In S. Jasanoff, G. E. Markle, J. C. Peterson, T. Pinch
                                        (eds). <title rend="italic">Handbook of Science and
                                                Technology Studies</title>. Sage, Thousand Oaks, CA
                                        (1995), pp. 140-166. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="kohler2008" label="Kohler 2008">Kohler, R. E. <title
                                                rend="quotes">Lab History</title>, <title
                                                rend="italic">Isis</title> 99 (2008):
                                        761–768.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="kuhn1996" label="Kuhn 1996">Kuhn, T. S. <title
                                                rend="italic">The Structure of Scientific
                                                Revolutions</title>. University of Chicago Press,
                                        Chicago and London (1996). </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="lane2017" label="Lane 2017">Lane, R. <title
                                                rend="italic">The Big Humanities: Digital
                                                Humanities/Digital Laboratories</title>. Routledge,
                                        London and New York (2017).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="latour1979" label="Latour et al. 1979">Latour, B. and
                                        Woolgar, S. <title rend="italic">Laboratory Life: The
                                                Construction of Scientific Facts</title>. Princeton
                                        University Press, Princeton (1979).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="latour1987" label="Latour 1987">Latour, B. <title
                                                rend="italic">Science in Action. How to Follow
                                                Scientists and Engineers Through Society</title>.
                                        Harvard University Press, Cambridge (1987).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="linhd" label="LINHD n.d.">Digital Humanities
                                        Innovation Lab at the National University of Distance
                                        Education. <ref target="http://linhd.uned.es"
                                                >http://linhd.uned.es</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="lynch1985" label="Lynch 1985">Lynch, M. <title
                                                rend="italic">Art and Artifact in Laboratory
                                                Science</title>. Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, London
                                        (1985).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="mahey2019" label="Mahey et al. 2019">Mahey, M. et al.
                                                <title rend="quotes">Open a GLAM Lab</title>.
                                        Digital Cultural Heritage Innovation Labs, Book Sprint,
                                        Doha, Qatar, 23-27 September, 2019. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="maron2014" label="Maron et al. 2014">Maron, N. L. and
                                        Pickle, S. <title rend="italic">Sustaining the Digital
                                                Humanities. Host Institution Support beyond the
                                                Start-Up Phase</title>. Ithaka S+R (2014). <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.18665/sr.22548"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.18665/sr.22548</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="moran2010" label="Moran 2010">Moran, S. <title
                                                rend="quotes">The Roles of Creativity in
                                                Society</title>. In J. C. Kaufman and R. J.
                                        Sternberg (eds). <title rend="italic">The Cambridge Handbook
                                                of Creativity</title>. Cambridge University Press,
                                        Cambridge (2010), pp. 74-90. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="openlab" label="OpenLab n.d.">OpenLab. Karolinska
                                        Institute, KTH Royal Institute of Technology, Stockholm
                                        University and Södertörn University. City of Stockholm. <ref
                                                target="http://openlabsthlm.se/"
                                                >http://openlabsthlm.se/</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="commonwealth2006"
                                        label="Our Cultural Commonwealth 2006">Our Cultural
                                        Commonwealth. <title rend="quotes">The report of the
                                                American Council of Learned Societies Commission on
                                                Cyberinfrastructure for the Humanities and Social
                                                Sciences</title>. American Council of Learned
                                        Societies, New York (2006).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="pask2018" label="Pask 2018">Pask, K. <title
                                                rend="quotes">In the Literature Lab</title>, <title
                                                rend="italic">Modern Language Quarterly</title>,
                                        79(1) (2018): 1-24. DOI: <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.1215/00267929-4264249"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.1215/00267929-4264249</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="pawlicka2017" label="Pawlicka 2017">Pawlicka, U.
                                                <title rend="quotes">Data, Collaboration,
                                                Laboratory: Bringing Concepts from Science into
                                                Humanities Practice</title>, <title rend="italic"
                                                >English Studies</title>, 98(5) (2017): 526-541.
                                                <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.1080/0013838X.2017.1332022"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.1080/0013838X.2017.1332022</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="pawlicka-deger2019" label="Pawlicka-Deger 2019"
                                        >Pawlicka-Deger, U. <title rend="quotes">(Digital)
                                                Humanities and Media Labs Around the World</title>
                                        [Data set]. Zenodo (2019). <ref
                                                target="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.2631219"
                                                >http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.2631219</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="pawlicka-deger" label="Pawlicka-Deger n.d."
                                        >Pawlicka-Deger, U. <title rend="quotes">Laboratory: A New
                                                Space in Digital Humanities</title>. A. McGrail, A.
                                        D. Nieves, S. Senier (eds). <title rend="italic"
                                                >Institutions, Infrastructures at the
                                                Interstices</title>. Debates in the Digital
                                        Humanities. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis
                                        (Forthcoming).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="pickering1992" label="Pickering 1992">Pickering, A.
                                                <title rend="quotes">From Science as Knowledge to
                                                Science as Practice</title>. In A. Pickering (ed).
                                                <title rend="italic">Science as Practice and
                                                Culture</title>, University of Chicago Press,
                                        Chicago and London (1992), pp. 1-26. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="pricelab"
                                        label="Price Lab for Digital
                                        Humanities n.d."
                                        >Price Lab for Digital Humanities. <title rend="quotes">What
                                                We Do</title>, University of Pennsylvania. <ref
                                                target="https://pricelab.sas.upenn.edu/about/what-we-do"
                                                >https://pricelab.sas.upenn.edu/about/what-we-do</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="proske2013" label="Proske 2013">Proske, P. <title
                                                rend="quotes">Media Lab Melbourne. Interview with:
                                                Pierre Proske</title>, <title rend="italic"
                                                >desktop</title>, February 12, 2013. <ref
                                                target="https://desktopmag.com.au/features/media-lab-melbourne/"
                                                >https://desktopmag.com.au/features/media-lab-melbourne/</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="readings1996" label="Readings 1996">Readings, B.
                                                <title rend="italic">The University in
                                        Ruins</title>. Harvard University Press, Cambridge,
                                        Massachusetts and London (1996).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="ricaurte2018" label="Ricaurte Quijano 2018">Ricaurte
                                        Quijano, P. <title rend="quotes">Citizen Laboratories and
                                                Digital Humanities</title>, <title rend="italic"
                                                >Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 12(1) (2018).
                                                <ref
                                                target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/12/1/000352/000352.html"
                                                >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/12/1/000352/000352.html</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="rockwell2010" label="Rockwell 2010">Rockwell, G.
                                                <title rend="quotes">As Transparent as
                                                Infrastructure. On the research of
                                                cyberinfrastructure in the humanities</title>. In J.
                                        McGann (ed). <title rend="italic">Online Humanities
                                                Scholarship: The Shape of Things to Come,
                                                Proceedings of the Mellon Foundation Online
                                                Humanities Conference at the University of
                                                Virginia</title>, Rice University Press, Houston
                                        (2010), pp. 461-487.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="sample2010" label="Sample 2010">Sample, M. <title
                                                rend="quotes">On the Death of the Digital Humanities
                                                Center</title>. <title rend="italic">Sample
                                                Reality</title>, March 26, 2010. <ref
                                                target="http://www.samplereality.com/2010/03/26/on-the-death-of-the-digital-humanities-center/"
                                                >http://www.samplereality.com/2010/03/26/on-the-death-of-the-digital-humanities-center/</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="scholarslab" label="Scholars' Lab n.d.">Scholars’ Lab
                                        at the University of Virginia Library. <title rend="quotes"
                                                >About</title>, University of Virginia. <ref
                                                target="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/about/"
                                                >https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/about/</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="smithies2017" label="Smithies et al. 2017">Smithies,
                                        J. et al. <title rend="quotes">Mechanizing the Humanities?
                                                King’s Digital Lab as Critical Experiment</title>,
                                        Digital Humanities 2017, DH2017, ADHO Conference in
                                        Montreal, 10 August (2017). <ref
                                                target="https://jamessmithies.org/blog/2017/08/17/mechanizing-humanities-kings-digital-lab-critical-experiment/"
                                                >https://jamessmithies.org/blog/2017/08/17/mechanizing-humanities-kings-digital-lab-critical-experiment/</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="smithies2020" label="Smithies et al. 2020">Smithies,
                                        J. and Ciula, A. <title rend="quotes">Humans in the Loop:
                                                Epistemology &amp; Method in King’s Digital
                                                Lab</title>. In. S. Dunn and K. Schuster (eds).
                                                <title rend="italic">Routledge International
                                                Handbook of Research Methods in Digital
                                                Humanities</title>. Routledge, London (2020).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="stratilatis2014" label="Stratilatis 2014">Stratilatis,
                                        C. <title rend="quotes">University rankings and the
                                                scientification of social sciences and
                                                humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Ethics in
                                                Science and Environmental Politics</title>, 13
                                        (2014): 177-192.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="svensson2015" label="Svensson 2015">Svensson, P.
                                                <title rend="quotes">The Humanistiscopes: Exploring
                                                the Situatedness of Humanities
                                                Infrastructure</title>. In P. Svensson and D. T.
                                        Goldberg (eds). <title rend="italic">Between Humanities and
                                                the Digital</title>. MA. MIT Press, Cambridge and
                                        London (2015), pp. 337-354.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="svensson2016" label="Svensson 2016">Svensson, P.
                                                <title rend="italic">Big Digital Humanities:
                                                Imagining a Meeting Place for the Humanities and the
                                                Digital</title>. University of Michigan Press, Ann
                                        Arbor (2016). DOI: <ref
                                                target="http://dx.doi.org/10.3998/dh.13607060.0001.001"
                                                >http://dx.doi.org/10.3998/dh.13607060.0001.001</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="svensson2018" label="Svensson 2018">Svensson, P.
                                                <title rend="quotes">Contemporary and Future Spaces
                                                for Media Studies and Digital Humanities</title>. In
                                        J. Sayers (ed). <title rend="italic">Routledge Companion to
                                                Media Studies and Digital Humanities</title>.
                                        Routledge, New York (2018), pp. 152-161.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="thorp2010" label="Thorp et al. 2010">Thorp, H. and
                                        Goldstein, B. <title rend="italic">Engines of Innovation:
                                                The Entrepreneurial University in the Twenty-First
                                                Century</title>. University of North Carolina Press,
                                        Chapel Hill (2010).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="tiesinga2014" label="Tiesinga et al. 2014">Tiesinga,
                                        H. and Berkhout, R. (eds) <title rend="italic">Labcraft: How
                                                Social Labs Cultivate Change Through Innovation and
                                                Collaboration</title>. Labcraft Publishing, London
                                        and San Francisco (2014). </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="wenger1998" label="Wenger 1998">Wenger, É. <title
                                                rend="italic">Communities of Practice: Learning,
                                                Meaning, and Identity</title>. Cambridge University
                                        Press, Cambridge (1998). </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="wissema2009" label="Wissema 2009">Wissema J. G. <title
                                                rend="italic">Towards the Third Generation
                                                University: Managing the University in
                                                Transition</title>. Edward Elgar Publishing,
                                        Cheltenham (2009). </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="zorich2008" label="Zorich 2008">Zorich, D. <title
                                                rend="italic">A Survey of Digital Humanities Centers
                                                in the United States</title>. Council on Library and
                                        Information Resources, Washington (2008).</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                </back>
        </text>
</TEI>
