<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">AI and Medical Images: Addressing Ethical Challenges to Provide 
               Responsible Access to Historical Medical Illustrations</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Lise <dhq:family>Jaillant</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2680-4571</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Loughborough University, UK</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>l.jaillant@lboro.ac.uk</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                 <p>Dr. <name>Lise Jaillant</name> is a Reader (Associate Professor) in Digital Cultural Heritage at 
                    <name>Loughborough University</name>, <name>UK</name>. She has a background in publishing history and 
                    digital humanities. Dr. <name>Jaillant</name> is an expert on born-digital archives and the issues of 
                    preservation and access to these archives. Since 2020, she has been the UK PI for four projects on 
                    archives and artificial intelligence funded by the <name>AHRC</name> (<name>Arts and Humanities 
                    Research Council</name>). These international projects aim to make digitised and born-digital archives 
                    more accessible to researchers and to use innovative research methods such as AI to analyse archival 
                    data. More information can be found at 
                    <ref target="http://www.lisejaillant.com/">http://www.lisejaillant.com</ref>.
                 </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Katherine <dhq:family>Aske</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1724-201X</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Edinburgh Napier University, UK</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>k.aske@napier.ac.uk</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                 <p>Dr. <name>Katherine Aske</name> is Lecturer (Assistant Professor) in English at <name>Edinburgh Napier 
                    University</name>, UK, researching female beauty, skincare, and proto-dermatology in the long eighteenth 
                    century. Her first monograph, <title rend="italic">Being Pretty in the Eighteenth Century: A Cultural 
                    History of Female Beauty</title>, is forthcoming with Bloomsbury. She is also the Editorial Assistant 
                    for the <title rend="italic">Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</title>.
                 </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000755</idno>
            <idno type="volume">018</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
            <date when="2024-07-19">19 July 2024</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <term corresp="#archives"/>
               <term corresp="#digitization"/>
               <term corresp="#machine_learning"/>
               <term corresp="#cultural_heritage"/>
               <term corresp="#access"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>medical images</item>
                  <item>digital archives</item>
                  <item>artificial intelligence</item>
                  <item>responsible access</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000755/000755.xml">GitHub</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>This article examines the ethical considerations and broader issues around access to digitised historical medical 
               images. These illustrations and, later, photographs are often extremely sensitive, representing disability, disease, 
               gender, and race in potentially harmful and problematic ways. In particular, the original metadata for such images can 
               include demeaning and sometimes racist terms. Some of these images show sexually explicit and violent content, as well 
               as content that was obtained without informed consent. Hiding these sensitive images can be tempting, and yet, archives 
               are meant to be used, not locked away. Through a series of interviews with 10 archivists, librarians, and researchers 
               based in the <name>UK</name> and <name>US</name>, the authors show that improved access to medical illustrations is 
               essential to produce new knowledge in the humanities and medical research, as well as to bridge the gap between 
               historical and modern understandings of the human body. Improving access to medical illustration can also help to 
               address the <q>gender data gap</q>, which has acquired mainstream visibility thanks to the work of activists such as 
               <name>Caroline Criado-Perez</name>, the author of <title rend="italic">Invisible Women: Data Bias in a World Designed 
               for Men</title>. Users of historical medical archives are therefore a diverse group, which includes researchers in 
               medicine, history, and medical and digital humanities, as well as artists, journalists, and activists.
            </p>
            <p>In order to improve discoverability and facilitate access to these archives in an ethical way, this article highlights 
               the importance of appropriate metadata, which can be enhanced through the use of artificial intelligence (AI) tools. 
               Indeed, AI can be used to create new metadata when original information is incomplete or is missing altogether, or 
               when it includes problematic language. AI can also help with the disaggregation of data by gender and/or 
               racial ethnicity. Moreover, it can recommend similar images to allow users to explore other parts of the collections. 
               However, AI can also pose issues, for example when it suggests inappropriate metadata or similarity search results. 
               Keeping humans in the loop is therefore essential when applying AI to sensitive medical images. Ultimately, this article 
               argues that access to sensitive images cannot be separated from responsibility. Recommendations are made to help 
               cultural heritage institutions find the right balance, to provide access for research and education, and to also protect 
               children and other vulnerable audiences from encountering images that can be described as shocking and even 
               traumatising. 
            </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Through a series of interviews with 10 archivists, librarians, and researchers based in the <name>UK</name> and 
               <name>US</name>, the authors show that improved access to medical illustrations is essential to produce new knowledge 
               in the humanities and medical research, as well as to bridge the gap between historical and modern understandings of the 
               human body.
            </p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head/>
            <p>Digitisation has profoundly changed the way we conduct humanities research. The ability to search through library 
               catalogues, archival databases, and online collections has opened new horizons of research by improving the 
               discoverability of records (including visual records), thereby allowing them to be used as data. However, in this sea 
               of accessible data, there is a growing issue of representation. As cultural heritage organisations continue to deal with 
               challenges regarding gender and race, the sector is still looking for best practices to enhance diversity and make their 
               digital collections more representative. When images are potentially harmful, or pose ethical challenges (for example, 
               when they show images of colonialised populations described in racist terms), it is often easier to keep them hidden 
               away and inaccessible. The vast digitisation efforts of the past two decades have therefore led to divergent outcomes: 
               visual archival images have become more accessible, and yet, vast troves of images are difficult to discover and use –– 
               particularly when search engines largely rely on text-based metadata.
            </p>
            <p>In this article, we look at the specific case of archival medical images (taken in a broad sense, to include images 
               used by medical professionals from ancient times to the present day, but also images documenting people who were judged 
               as <q>abnormal</q> because of their skin colour, disability, and/or other physical characteristics). Lying somewhere 
               between knowledge and curiosity, medical images of human bodies throughout history have been sources of health 
               information, sociocultural beliefs, and sites of intrigue and taboo. From the highly detailed anatomical drawings in 
               <name>Andreas Vesalius</name>'s <title rend="italic">De humani corporis fabrica</title> (1543) and the pregnant bellies 
               depicted in midwifery manuals, to images of the <q>monstrous</q> physiognomies of criminals, illustrations of dissected, 
               diseased, pathologized, atypical, and disabled bodies have been in circulation for centuries. In their complex and 
               varied forms, historical medical images present a wide corpus for medical humanities researchers, as well as other 
               medical disciplines. However, these records can create serious ethical challenges in terms of their online accessibility, 
               particularly when illustrations move into photographs of patients or bodies that may be exploitative or of an 
               insensitive nature. Even when these images are over a century old, with increased ethical considerations and the 
               difficulty in categorising a diverse range of collections, historical medical images present one of the most difficult 
               types of records to manage within the heritage sector.
            </p>
            <p>Medical images can be sensitive in multiple ways. Health-related data and data concerning a person's sex life or sexual 
               orientation are classified as sensitive in legislations such as the European GDPR (General Data Protection 
               Regulation).<note>See Article 4(13), (14), and (15) and Article 9 and Recitals (51) to (56) of the GDPR.</note> These 
               data are subject to specific processing conditions. However, the GDPR only protects personal data of living persons. 
               It does not apply to the personal data of deceased persons. Archival medical images — especially those produced more 
               than 100 years ago — can be digitised and made available with a public domain licence. These medical photographs, 
               drawings, and illustrations are not sensitive in a narrow, legal sense, and yet they contain sensitivities, including 
               representations of disabilities and diseases (including sexually transmitted diseases and other stigmatised conditions). 
               Bodies that were once considered as abnormal (such as those with different skin colours or people with tattoos, 
               scarification, or other physical characteristics) are frequently featured in medical collections. In the case of more 
               recent collections, the data rights of living people represented in pictures are not the only considerations that 
               archives need to consider. Some of these images can be challenging for other reasons. For example, campaigns against 
               AIDS frequently represented explicit sex scenes to encourage people to use condoms and adopt safer sexual 
               practices.<note>For examples of explicit sexual images made available via the Wellcome Collection online catalogue, 
               see <title rend="italic">A naked man shaving...</title> 
               (<ref target="https://wellcomecollection.org/works/k2effvut">https://wellcomecollection.org/works/k2effvut</ref>), 
               <title rend="italic">Two Naked Men Holding Penis Models...</title> 
               (<ref target="https://wellcomecollection.org/works/actceyfe">https://wellcomecollection.org/works/actceyfe</ref>), 
               <title rend="italic">Two Men Performing Anal Sex...</title> 
               (<ref target="https://wellcomecollection.org/works/e4avd4xz">https://wellcomecollection.org/works/e4avd4xz</ref>), and 
               other advertisements by the <title rend="quotes">Core Program</title>.</note> Once digitised and put online, these images 
               can be accessed by anyone — including children and other vulnerable users.<note>In this article, 
               <quote rend="inline">vulnerable</quote> refers to <quote rend="inline">a person in need of special care, support, or 
               protection</quote>, for example because of age or disability. See <title rend="quotes">vulnerable (adj.), additional 
               sense</title>, <title rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</title>, March 2024, 
               <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/OED/1825525669">https://doi.org/10.1093/OED/1825525669</ref>.</note> Archival 
               repositories therefore face a dilemma of whether to show or not show sensitive medical images — and how to decide what 
               is or is not considered sensitive.
            </p>
            <p>While this article focuses mainly on the case of <emph>viewers</emph> of sensitive archival images, the digitisation of 
               such images can also be harmful for the people depicted in them. For example, images of naked children originally taken 
               in a medical context can, once digitised, be accessed and shared without context by anyone, including sexual criminals. 
               In the case of archival documents created in the past 100 years, individuals could still be alive, and (in theory) their 
               consent must be obtained prior to digitisation and public release to comply with the GDPR and other data protection 
               legislation. In practice, many libraries and archives have <q>take down</q> policies, which rely on an <q>opt out</q> 
               basis (rather than the <q>opt in</q> requirement mandated by the law). In the past few years, this approach has been 
               criticised on ethical grounds, with a strong emphasis on privacy and consent.<note>In a 2017 article, 
               <name>Michelle Moravec</name> used the example of the feminist magazine <title rend="italic">Spare Rib</title> to 
               encourage other researchers to ask the following question before using digitised archives: <quote rend="inline">Have the 
               individuals whose work appears in these materials consented to this?</quote> <ptr target="#moravec_2017" loc="186"/>. 
               Making such documents available on the internet has raised the issue of consent as well as the ethics of widely releasing 
               sensitive or private materials intended for other uses.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Through a series of interviews with 10 heritage professionals and academic researchers working with historical medical 
               image records within archives, libraries, and museums, this study considers key challenges and ethical implications in 
               making historical medical records accessible in the digital age.<note>For a discussion on ethics in relation to medical 
               images, see <ptr target="#keet_kramer_2022"/>.</note> Artificial intelligence (AI) can and is being used to improve 
               access to historical medical illustrations, for example by automatically creating metadata, when original metadata 
               contains problematic language or is missing altogether. AI can also help with the disaggregation of data by gender and/or 
               race or ethnicity, where such information is known. Furthermore, AI can be used to suggest similar images through 
               computer vision and machine learning. The objective of such use is to encourage users to explore other parts of these 
               collections and to discover additional materials without typing new keywords. However, AI can also pose challenges, 
               for example by suggesting inappropriate metadata or search results, or by isolating an image from its original context. 
               Keeping humans in the loop is therefore essential when applying AI to sensitive medical images.
            </p>
            <p>Drawing on large, open-access medical image databases, including the Wellcome Collection database and the UK Medical 
               Heritage Library (UKMHL), as well as significant archival collections across the <name>UK</name>, <name>US</name>, and 
               <name>Canada</name>, this article considers some of the broader issues facing the cultural heritage sector and the 
               challenges medical images present. We conducted 10 interviews with professionals in libraries, archives, and museums, 
               as well as academics in the <name>UK</name> and <name>US</name> who had worked with digital collections of medical 
               images open to the public. The study had a limited scope, focusing on the <name>UK</name> context (with predominantly 
               <name>UK</name>-based interviewees). However, our in-depth interviews have revealed key information that will be useful 
               to anyone interested in digital medical images — from professionals in libraries, archives, and museums, to scholars in 
               the digital humanities and medical humanities, as well as medical researchers and healthcare professionals. The intention 
               of this article is to identify challenges with digitisation, metadata, and wider concerns regarding the gender data gap, 
               diversity, and decolonisation through the accessibility (or inaccessibility) of medical images.<note>While the authors 
               recognise that the global scope of these interviews is limited, interviewees were approached based on their work with 
               large-scale, digital medical image libraries available to search in English that are publicly accessible within the 
               <name>UK</name>. This meant focussing on major <name>UK</name> institutions with open-access digital medical image 
               collections. Further interviewees were sourced through their work with or curation of these medical image collections to 
               explore practical uses of medical images as research tools. In addition to the largely <name>UK</name> focus, we have 
               included interviews with professionals exploring the educational uses of historical medical images in modern medical 
               training at the <name>University of Minnesota</name></note> This article presents theoretical and practical approaches 
               to making these important resources more accessible and/or usable to users. The decisions made regarding representation 
               in historical medical records can be key to discussing broader issues of representation across the galleries, libraries, 
               archives, and museums (GLAM) sector.
            </p>
            <p>The main objectives of this article are to:
            <list type="unordered">
              <item>Outline the key issues and challenges associated with historical medical images, both illustrative and 
                 photographic</item>
              <item>Address the ethical considerations for making medical images more accessible</item>
              <item>Consider the current and potential uses of AI in medical visual collections and the challenges associated with 
                 AI</item>
              <item>Recommend potential solutions to the problems of access to sensitive archival images, with a focus on balancing 
                 access and responsibility</item>
            </list>
               The first section of this article looks at the discoverability and usability of archival medical images. We then examine 
               issues associated with the diversity and representativeness of collections. Section 3 explores initiatives to change or 
               enrich metadata to increase representativeness. The final section focuses on AI applied to medical images, including 
               the ethical issues contained therein. The conclusion features take-away points to encourage GLAM professionals to find 
               the right balance between access and responsibility, namely by paying constant attention to the needs of children and 
               other vulnerable users.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Section 1: Discovering and Using Archival Medical Images</head>
            <p>Current scholarly literature on the use of medical images occupies broad fields of study, from the glossy images 
               included in art history publications, such as <name>Domenico Bertoloni Meli</name>'s <title rend="italic">Visualising 
               Disease</title> (2018) or <name>Richard Barnett</name>'s <title rend="italic">The Sick Rose</title> (2014), to the use 
               of historical medical images in modern medicine and AI datasets <ptr target="#krasnoryadtseva_dalbeth_petrie_2020"/> 
               <ptr target="#delp_jones_1996"/> <ptr target="#hajar_2011"/> <ptr target="#rubalcava_gadepalli_2021"/> 
               <ptr target="#bamba_et_al_2021"/>. According to <ptr target="#rea_et_al_2017"/>, while medical museums have often been a 
               place of restricted access, the digitisation of medical artefacts is becoming more widespread and 
               <quote rend="inline">can enable wider access</quote> to the <quote rend="inline">rich history of medical science</quote>.
            </p>
            <p>For example, medical illustrations can provide evidence for medical professionals studying the history of particular 
               diseases. As one interviewee told us: <quote rend="block">Maybe it's for diseases which people no longer get, but 
               actually in terms of symptoms and in terms of diagnosis and just understanding how diseases have developed, that picture 
               can tell them an awful lot about [another] disease present 200 years ago that maybe doesn't exist now or doesn't exist 
               in that form now.<note>Anon., interview, 14 December 2022, via MS Teams.</note></quote> Issues such as copyright on 
               modern images in medical textbooks mean that education providers are experiencing an increase in litigation cases for 
               unauthorised use of copyrighted medical materials, particularly in the increasing uses of online resources in medical 
               training <ptr target="#gutman_2011"/> <ptr target="#dmytriw_sadler_neumann_2015"/>. But, as 
               <ptr target="#dmytriw_sadler_neumann_2015"/> suggest, older, out-of-copyright images and those licensed through Creative 
               Commons could be updated using digital tools, thus improving access to anatomical illustration for educational purposes. 
               Indeed, many medical illustrations from the earlier twentieth century are highly accurate and suitable for training 
               modern medical practitioners, with a little updating.
            </p>
            <p>Many of these older illustrations are openly accessible. There are large collections of global historical medical images 
               available through the Wellcome Collection database<note>See 
               <ref target="https://wellcomecollection.org/images">https://wellcomecollection.org/images</ref></note>, a go-to for 
               medical humanities researchers, with over 1 million items in their online catalogue. More specific digital collections 
               include the nineteenth-century European medical records available in the UK Medical Heritage Library, which are available 
               to search via a number of visualisations, including body parts and medical conditions.<note>See 
               <ref target="https://ukmhl.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/home">https://ukmhl.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/home</ref>.</note> 
               There are also extensive digitised collections in <name>UCLA</name>'s Index of Medieval Medical Images<note>See 
               <ref target="https://digital.library.ucla.edu/catalog/ark:/21198/zz0002fn7s">https://digital.library.ucla.edu/catalog/ark:/21198/zz0002fn7s</ref></note> 
               and the <name>University of Toronto</name>'s Anatomia Collection: Anatomical Plates 1522–1867<note>See 
               <ref target="https://anatomia.library.utoronto.ca/">https://anatomia.library.utoronto.ca/</ref>. This collection features 
               approximately 4,500 full page plates and other significant illustrations of human anatomy selected from the 
               <name>Jason A. Hannah</name> and <name>Academy of Medicine</name> collections on the history of medicine at the 
               <name>Thomas Fisher Rare Book Library</name> at the <name>University of Toronto</name>. Each illustration has been fully 
               indexed using medical subject headings (MeSH), and techniques of illustration, artists, and engravers have been 
               identified whenever possible. There are 95 individual titles represented, ranging in date from 1522 to 1867.</note>, as 
               well as further records on Europeana.<note>See 
               <ref target="https://www.europeana.eu/en">https://www.europeana.eu/en</ref>.</note> The National Library of Medicine 
               (NLM, <name>Maryland</name>, <name>US</name>) provides an Open-I search for medical images<note>See 
               <ref target="https://openi.nlm.nih.gov/">https://openi.nlm.nih.gov/</ref>.</note> and allows users to filter results to 
               show images from their History of Medicine Collection.
            </p>
            <p>These large, digitised collections are often supplemented by a series of funded projects, which allow smaller 
               institutions to make their collections accessible. As storage and digital interfaces can be important practical issues, 
               especially for smaller institutions, this is one way to help provide access and limit the disparity of archival 
               materials. <name>Katie Birkwood</name>, Rare Books and Special Collections Librarian at the <name>Royal College of 
               Physicians</name> (<name>RCP</name>) <name>London</name>, told us that <quote rend="inline">in 2015 and 2016, [they] were 
               part of the UK Medical Heritage Library project that Wellcome ran with the Internet Archive</quote> and that the <name>RCP</name> 
               <quote rend="inline">digitised about 4,100 of our nineteenth-century books, across the theme of medicine</quote> for the 
               site.<note><name>Katie Birkwood</name>, interview, 14 December 2022, via MS Teams.</note> Although the <name>RCP</name> 
               does not have the capacity to host its own digital database, the Internet Archive has allowed the college to host some 
               of their digitised materials online. While these types of digitisation initiatives are helping to make archival 
               collections more accessible, they still come with limitations and compromises due to funding, metadata, and the 
               practicalities of digitising potentially fragile materials. For all the visibility of the bodily forms in these 
               historical records, many medical image collections remain inaccessible online, or else siloed within individual 
               catalogues, often with thin metadata, out-dated terminologies, or missing contextual records. Many items are lacking 
               the machine-readable data necessary to create meaningful connections between records. In this way, visual materials 
               continue to pose considerable problems for institutions when it comes to cataloguing and discoverability, as well as 
               display and dissemination <ptr target="#tsafrir_ohry_2001"/>. Entire collections are locked away when they are 
               considered too sensitive (for example, images of skulls and bodies of the deceased, taken during the colonial period). 
               Paradoxically, in the age of mass digitisation initiatives, researchers often face challenges in discovering, sourcing, 
               and contextualising medical illustrations, which have played a significant role in our understanding of medical and 
               social history.
            </p>
            <p>The lack of metadata and the sensitivity of records are not the only obstacles to access. The format of the materials 
               can also make digitisation complicated. From cheaply printed health books to fully illustrated anatomical atlases, 
               these visual and often multimodal records vary in size and quality, featuring different types of images — from woodcuts 
               and black-and-white prints to coloured illustrations and photographs. Medical atlases, for example, are often very large 
               in size, are used as teaching resources, and are difficult to digitise without specialist equipment. These types of 
               records can also require manual appraisals to make them accessible for online databases, which is often beyond the 
               capacity of many institutions. Additionally, the formal diversity of these records poses challenges for existing 
               automation tools trained on photographic images, such as CAMPI (Computer-Aided Metadata Generation for Photo Archives 
               Initiative), which struggle with illustrated images.
            </p>
            <p>Due to their size and fragility, non-bound illustrations are often not a priority or at times even an option for 
               digitisation, meaning that many visual medical records are restricted to in-person reading room tables. Due to the ease 
               of scanning and the availability of host-sites, such as the Internet Archive, it is bound books, both published and 
               non-published, which are predominantly the items selected for digitisation. <name>Katie Birkwood</name> 
               (<name>RCP</name>) told us that in the case of the Medical Heritage Library project, small books could easily fit on a 
               regular scanner. Other formats were less likely to be selected for digitisation: <quote rend="inline">Anything that had 
               to go on an oversized scanner, we had to be very picky about and so fewer of those got sent. And if something's in bad 
               physical condition, you're less likely to send it.</quote><note><name>Katie Birkwood</name>, interview, 14 December 2022, 
               via MS Teams.</note> The <name>RCP</name> has a collection of 250 large-scale anatomical illustrations, which are not 
               bound and are not available online. <quote rend="inline">We can't use the Internet Archive and access portal because 
               it's not really what it's for</quote>, said one archivist. <note>Anon., interview, 14 December 2022, via MS 
               Teams.</note> Items that have been selected for digitisation in part due to their format become more accessible, but 
               also risk being seen as more valuable than others. And when items prioritised for digitisation, and even for 
               preservation, are imbibed with the impression of value, it perpetuates further issues in diversity and 
               representation.
            </p>
            <p>In addition to format, external funding has an impact on the decisions to digitise some images and not others. As 
               <name>Daryl Green</name>, Library and Information professional for the <name>University of Edinburgh</name> told us, 
               <quote rend="inline">what's getting prioritised for digitisation is what's getting funded externally, which is not how 
               an institution should do these things</quote>.<note><name>Daryl Green</name>, interview, 12 January 2023, via MS 
               Teams.</note> The impracticalities that surround the digitisation for many institutions across the GLAM sector — often 
               involving external project remits or limitations due to cost and specialist equipment — mean that there is a risk of 
               false representation happening across the sector, which can affect the types of research being undertaken.
            </p>
            <p>In short, online image collections, although vast, represent records prioritised for digitisation — items that are 
               often selected for their potential interest to database users, their suitability for digitisation, or for specific, 
               funded and themed projects. While images of a medical nature are only one relatively small aspect on a much broader 
               spectrum, they continue to underpin current research in the humanities and other fields. As 
               <ptr target="#nikolaidou_et_al_2022"/> note, the <quote rend="inline">growth of digital libraries has contributed to 
               the research on historical documents by providing high-quality digitised images to researchers to process and 
               analyse</quote>, meaning the availability of online records has a direct impact on what is being researched.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Section 2: Issues of Diversity and Representativeness of Ccollections</head>
            <p>Access to historical medical illustrations is essential to understand current issues such as ableism (i.e., 
               discrimination and social prejudice against people with disabilities). Medical illustrations have reinforced ableist 
               standards of the human form in medicine and popular culture throughout history. As literacy rates and printing 
               technologies improved across the globe, and as medical texts became more available to public users, the fascination with 
               physical and medical anomalies increased. Interest in racial and cultural differences, disabilities and physical 
               differences, diseases, and injuries expanded throughout the sixteenth, seventeenth, and eighteenth centuries, continuing 
               well into the nineteenth and twentieth centuries. These periods saw a huge increase in the production of medical 
               illustrations and images, including depictions of bodies labelled as <q>monstrous</q>. The depiction of 
               <q>monstrous</q> births in reproductive manuals, for example, is indicative of the increasing public fascination in 
               anomalies from an increasingly connected world, and, while unsympathetic and stigmatising, do demonstrate a move away 
               from a <q>standard</q> representation of the body in historical medical works. Several of these types of images are 
               available on the Wellcome Collection online image catalogue, for example. However, the image database also demonstrates 
               some of the issues this article wishes to address.
            </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure01">
              <head><title rend="italic">Two human figures with abnormalities</title>. Public domain. Source: 
                 Wellcome Collection, 
                 <ref target="https://wellcomecollection.org/works/hyy38v99">https://wellcomecollection.org/works/hyy38v99</ref>.</head>
              <figDesc/>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png" style="width: 500px"/>
            </figure>
            <p>When searching on the Wellcome's image collection for the keyword <q>monstrosity</q>, a common phrase used to describe a 
               discriminatory facet of historical medical literature, there are image results that have been entirely removed from their 
               original context, including photographs, and some that lack any further description. Similar results occur when searching 
               the word <q>abnormalities</q>. Examples include a black-and-white printed image of baby twins conjoined at the 
               stomach<note>See 
               <ref target="https://wellcomecollection.org/works/x9gb8vkw">https://wellcomecollection.org/works/x9gb8vkw.</ref>. This image 
               is also available through the same keyword search on the <name>University of Toronto</name>'s Anatomia library, but there 
               is more contextual information provided: 
               <ref target="https://collections.library.utoronto.ca/view/anatomia:RBAI072_0107">https://collections.library.utoronto.ca/view/anatomia:RBAI072_0107</ref>.</note>  
               and another similar image of adult conjoined twins titled <title rend="quotes">Two human figures with abnormalities</title> 
               and assigned the following subject keywords: <quote rend="inline">monsters; abnormalities; abnormality; Siamese; conjoined 
               twins.</quote><note>See 
               <ref target="https://wellcomecollection.org/works/hyy38v99">https://wellcomecollection.org/works/hyy38v99</ref>.</note> 
               Although these images have clearly been taken from illustrated medical texts, their tags and keywords have been generated 
               using AI tools based on very little data. While the Wellcome Collection continues to make improvements to their image 
               collection, their database is supplemented with an image similarity search that utilises machine learning, which, 
               unfortunately, can present further mis-association and misinterpretation of sensitive medical images. With such thin 
               metadata available and the evident inadequacies of similarity searches, particularly for sensitive materials, these 
               digitised illustrations are difficult to contextualise without further research and investigation. Moreover, the limitations 
               of historically relevant keywords present ethical considerations in the balancing of historically accurate terminology and 
               record discoverability.
            </p>
            <p>Improving the discoverability and accessibility of medical illustrations and their original contexts could also help 
               researchers to understand the ongoing gender data gap in healthcare. Historians such as <name>Ludmilla Jordanova</name> 
               have argued that medical texts and images reinforced the idea that the white, male, able body was the standard of the human 
               form, with the only real difference in female bodies being their reproductive systems <ptr target="#jordanova_1989"/>. This 
               androcentric view has been perpetuated by the availability of digital records and anatomical images. Indeed, most 
               figure-based images included in medical literature from the fifteenth to early-twentieth century largely show explicitly 
               female anatomy only to demonstrate pregnancy and birth, or to distinguish female genitalia. As <name>Elinor Cleghorn</name> 
               has argued, the perception of the female body throughout history was, medically, socially, and culturally speaking, dictated 
               by the possession of a uterus <ptr target="#cleghorn_2021"/>. The trend in depicting mostly male bodies in historical 
               medical materials is often put down to the lack of female test subjects. The subsequent medical studies that have developed 
               based on male bodies are underlined as one of the major reasons why women's diseases are still being misdiagnosed 
               <ptr target="#young_fisher_kirkman_2018"/> <ptr target="#maas_appelman_2010"/> <ptr target="#fairweather_rose_2004"/>. 
               This trend and the gender data gap in medical research it represents continues to persist to this day 
               <ptr target="#merone_et_al_2022"/> <ptr target="#criado-perez_2019"/> <ptr target="#cleghorn_2021"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Efforts to address this gender data gap have acquired mainstream visibility thanks to the work of activists such as 
               <name>Caroline Criado-Perez</name>, the author of <title rend="italic">Invisible Women: Data Bias in a World Designed for 
               Men</title>. According to <name>Criado-Perez</name>, the <quote rend="inline">male-default bias</quote> in medicine has 
               been evident since at least the ancient Greeks, who saw the female body as a <quote rend="inline">mutilated male</quote>, 
               where ovaries were simply underdeveloped testicles inside the body. The perception that the able, male body is 
               <quote rend="inline"><emph>the</emph> human body</quote> <ptr target="#criado-perez_2019" loc="196–197"/> persists even 
               though, as modern research has shown, hormonal differences have been found to affect every tissue and organ system in the 
               entire human body <ptr target="#keitt_et_al_2004"/> <ptr target="#phillips_gee_wells_2022"/>.
            </p>
            <p>The over-use of the male body in history continues to plague contemporary medical knowledge. From the work of 
               <name>Leonardo da Vinci</name> and <name>Vesalius</name> through to one of the best-known illustrated medical texts, 
               <name>Henry Gray</name>'s <title rend="italic">Anatomy of the Human Body</title> (1859), medical illustrations of the 
               human body have historically been idealised depictions of what was unlikely to be ideal specimens. These illustrations 
               have been copied, altered, and reprinted over centuries — and are now the main images that get prioritised for 
               digitisation. Indeed, many of the original drawings in Gray's <title rend="italic">Anatomy</title>, wood-engravings by 
               Professor <name>Henry Van Carter</name>, have appeared in subsequent editions, even to the modern day 
               <ptr target="#tsafrir_ohry_2001"/>. These illustrations are not inaccurate, and they are often the images that are now 
               most readily available in digital medical collections, including those held by the NLM and Wellcome Collection. The issue 
               is not only one of accuracy, but of representation.
            </p>
            <p>The gender data gap, reinforced by the lack of diversity in historical medical images, feeds into broader social issues. 
               Discussing the problematic maternal mortality rates in the <name>United States</name>, <quote rend="inline">particularly 
               with non-white populations</quote>, <name>Emily Beck</name> (Assistant Curator at the Wangensteen Historical Library of 
               Biology and Medicine) asked: <quote rend="block">[W]here can we see the fingers of that in earlier material? What happens 
               when all you see are very well-fed, white male bodies in the prime of their life, and ask them, <quote rend="inline">What 
               do your anatomy texts look like? Who is represented there? What does that do for the kinds of research that you 
               have?</quote><note><name>Emily Beck</name>, interview, 12 January 2023, via MS Teams.</note></quote>
            </p>
            <p>As we have seen, historical medical images have been dominated by the standard of white, male, able bodies — but they can 
               also feature some diversity. As highlighted by <name>Keren Rosa Hammerschlag</name>'s investigation into 
               <name>Friedrich Tiedemann</name>'s <title rend="italic">Tabulae arteriarum corporis humani</title> (1822), translated into 
               English in 1829 as <title rend="italic">Plates of the Arteries of the Human Body</title>, some medical atlases did feature 
               a diverse range of anatomy from males and females <ptr target="#hammerschlag_2021a"/>. Indeed, according to 
               <name>William Schupbach</name> (Research Developer, Wellcome Collection) a <quote rend="inline">smaller number of works, 
               mostly eighteenth or nineteenth century, which concentrate on viscera, show men and women</quote>, and the decision to 
               represent different bodies <quote rend="inline">really all depends what the purpose of the illustration 
               is</quote>.<note><name>William Schupback</name>, interview, 12 January 2023, via MS Teams.</note> While the purpose of an 
               image can draw many interpretations, taking an example from nineteenth-century surgeon <name>Joseph Maclise</name>'s more 
               inclusive work, <title rend="italic">Surgical Anatomy</title> (1851), <name>Hammerschlag</name> has drawn attention to the 
               representation of a black male subject in the London edition, as well as the deliberate removal of the same figure in the 
               American edition published the same year in a context of heightened racial tensions <ptr target="#hammerschlag_2021b"/>. 
               Archival medical images can therefore offer a broad spectrum of social and cultural attitudes towards gender, race, and 
               ability, representing key sources in tracing the dissemination of medical knowledge in any given period — but only if they 
               are accessible.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Section 3: Changing metadata to increase representativeness</head>
            <p>While we consider the potentials of these images for use in the modern day, we must pause to ask: is it possible to create 
               a more diverse archive? Precedents exist. In the 1960s and 1970s, feminist archivists and historians established new 
               archival collections needed to write women's history. In this study, we want to highlight the specific issues that occur 
               when women are largely invisible in archival collections.<note>Work in this area is ongoing. For example, see the 
               <name>UK</name>-based project for recovering women's contribution to the book trade within archival collections, led by 
               <name>Helen Williams</name> and <name>Ruth Frendo</name>, <title rend="quotes">Communicating Women's Work in the Historical 
               Archive</title>, available at: 
               <ref target="https://womenmakingbooks.wordpress.com/projects/">https://womenmakingbooks.wordpress.com/projects/</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Where records, illustrated and non-illustrated, have been digitised, the creators of these records and the people 
               represented are seldom defined by gender, meaning that online catalogue and database searches are often unable to 
               distinguish medical records produced by or featuring women, or other under-represented contributors. A staff member at the 
               Wellcome Collection informed us that where gendered data is already available, such as in biographical information held in 
               other online sources, <quote rend="inline">we will be taking on that extra metadata about gender, birth dates, death dates, 
               locations that they were connected to</quote>.<note>Anon., interview, 13 January 2023, via MS Teams.</note> The intention to 
               illuminate under-represented groups is a central reason for including gender in material records. But it is not without its 
               complexities. Indeed, disaggregating data based on gender is more challenging than applying a binary categorisation. 
               <name>Katie Birkwood</name> told us that items in their catalogue seldom have a marker for author’s gender. She added: 
               <quote rend="block">[T]hat's a hugely divisive issue in the library cataloguing world, because new rules were brought out a 
               few years ago saying that when you make a name heading file for a person, you should be including gender. And that brings up 
               all sorts of issues with anyone who has transitioned or doesn't have a binary gender, and why should we be documenting 
               gender?<note><name>Katie Birkwood</name>, interview, 14 December 2022, via MS Teams.</note></quote>
            </p>
            <p><name>Birkwood</name> notes that research is being done to help illuminate female contributors and collectors, but often 
               this work is limited by the availability and discoverability of materials. <name>Emily Beck</name> highlighted a similar 
               issue, saying: <quote rend="block">[W]e are trying to do our level best to make it easier for people to find these materials, 
               . . . working on making bibliographies of other kinds of populations, like black populations and indigenous [people and yet] 
               we fully acknowledge that our collection is western European. It very much elevates white male voices, and so we're just 
               trying to do our best to address that head-on.<note><name>Emily Beck</name>, interview, 12 January 2023, via MS 
               Teams.</note></quote> While the use of gendered labelling does present further considerations and complexity in terms of 
               representation — and risks alienating individuals who have transitioned or do not identify with a binary gender — at the 
               same time, the decision to not disaggregate data (and a lack of guidance on how to effectively disaggregate data, 
               particularly around gender), is disguising under-represented contributors, not least in the history of medicine. As 
               Professor <name>Fay Bound Alberti</name> (<name>Kings College London</name>) pointed out: <quote rend="inline">what are our 
               responsibilities to the historical subjects [as the] ways in which images are produced are always embedded in the sexism and 
               racism of the time?</quote><note><name>Fay Bound Alberti</name>, interview, 17 January 2023, via MS Teams.</note>
            </p>
            <p>One approach, as <name>Lois Hendrickson</name> (Curator, Wangensteen Historical Library of Biology and Medicine, 
               <name>University of Minnesota</name>) discussed, is to recover marginalised groups and individuals in catalogue data. In a 
               new initiative, the library is focussing on three topics — women, disability, and black history — to help improve 
               representation within their special collections and rare books. <name>Hendrickson</name> is working to address gender  
               with a colleague who took common women's names in French and English from the nineteenth and twentieth centuries and ran 
               that against the catalogue to create a Python script to improve the records, using Open 
               Refine.<note><name>Lois Hendrickson</name>, interview, 12 January, via MS Teams.</note> <name>Emily Beck</name>, continuing 
               the discussion of disaggregating data by gender, suggested that relevant materials are <quote rend="inline">difficult to 
               locate . . . , especially if you are relatively inexperienced in terms of searching in library catalogues, and we want to 
               make sure that people are able to study the history of voices that are not necessarily raised up very frequently in the 
               historiography</quote>.<note><name>Emily Beck</name>, interview, 12 January 2023, via MS Teams.</note> <name>Beck</name> and 
               <name>Hendrickson</name> advocated that the Wangensteen Library are doing what they can to ensure that the collection is 
               <quote rend="inline">a more robust representation of a global history of 
               medicine</quote>.<note><name>Lois Hendrickson</name>, interview, 12 January 2023, via MS Teams.</note> While there is a 
               willingness to approach these prominent issues in representation, many of the potential solutions are currently siloed 
               within individual institutions.
            </p>
            <p>Current debates on representation, diversity, and language used in archival collections have also led to broader changes of 
               metadata considered offensive or otherwise problematic. Discussing representation and search terms for images, interviewees 
               from the Wellcome Collection described the decision to remove the term <quote rend="inline">rodent disease</quote> from the 
               headings in a nineteenth-century collection, <title rend="quotes">Gentlefolk of <name>Leeds</name> afflicted with 
               disease</title>. For example, the collection includes an 1820 oil painting representing a young man, <name>J. Kay</name>, 
               <quote rend="inline">afflicted with a disease which has eaten away part of his face</quote> (Figure 2).
            </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure02">
              <head><title rend="italic">A young man, <name>J. Kay</name>, afflicted with a disease which has eaten away 
                 part of his face. Oil painting, ca. 1820</title>. Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0). Source: 
                 Wellcome Collection, Ref #603117i, 
                 <ref target="https://wellcomecollection.org/works/gzgzm2sf">https://wellcomecollection.org/works/gzgzm2sf</ref>.</head>
              <figDesc/>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png" style="width: 500px"/>
            </figure>
            <p>As <name>William Schupbach</name> (Wellcome Collection) noted: <quote rend="block"><quote rend="inline">Rodent 
               disease</quote> to mean cancer is a common nineteenth-century term. So, the original catalogue record reflects terminology 
               of the date of the portrait. The new description is not contemporary with the portrait, but it doesn't distort — it doesn't 
               say, <quote rend="inline">He's got cancer</quote>, or, <quote rend="inline">He's got syphilis</quote>. It just puts into 
               plain language of the twenty-first century, and indeed twentieth century, by saying, <quote rend="inline">It appears to eat 
               away part of his nose</quote>. Eating away is what <quote rend="inline">rodent</quote> means, so it's simply replacing the 
               Latin medical term with an English vernacular term.<note><name>Schupback</name>, interview, 12 January 2023, via MS 
               Teams.</note>
            </quote></p>
            <p>There are several layers of metadata here, with the addition and then deletion of the phrase <quote rend="inline">rodent 
               disease</quote>, yet the term is still searchable. The original title inscribed on the verso of the painting 
               (<title rend="quotes">Cancer of the nose</title>) was considered inexact by the cataloguer, who added the following 
               metadata: <quote rend="inline">[H]e seems to have <quote rend="inline"><name>Hutchinson</name>'s teeth</quote>, a symptom of 
               congenital syphilis, the inscription may be a euphemism</quote>.
            </p>
            <p>Changing metadata with the intention to remove problematic terms can in turn lead to more challenges. As another staff 
               member at the Wellcome Collection told us: <quote rend="block">I've gone back to look at all these <name>Leeds</name> 
               portraits and there's not been a uniform decision around the language. So that's one of the challenges I think we have, 
               that there are so many of these scenarios, when do we stop and what do we do?<note>Anon., interview, 12 January 2023, via 
               MS Teams.</note></quote> In making these decisions, while aligning with current equality, diversity, and inclusion 
               initiatives, there is a significant lack of guidance and best practices in dealing with visual records, particularly those 
               of a potentially sensitive nature. Often the decisions to change or alter records are being done in house, and those 
               decisions, without explicit best policy guidance, are a serious challenge. As <name>Emily Beck</name> told us, 
               <quote rend="inline">[T]hinking about what happens when we change the language to make it more appropriate — does that 
               actually make it harder to locate those materials?</quote><note><name>Emily Beck</name>, interview, 12 January 2023, via MS 
               Teams.</note> In updating metadata and terminology, there are <quote rend="inline">huge red flags and warning signs that 
               come up when you start trying to explicitly tag images</quote>, as one professional at the Wellcome Collection told us.
            </p>
            <p>Changing metadata is problematic, but leaving outdated terms can be an even bigger issue. <quote rend="inline">We know that 
               every computer vision system out there is full of biases that we don't necessarily want to perpetuate within the 
               collection</quote>, said the same Wellcome professional. They continued, <quote rend="inline">But equally the data set that 
               we have is historical, [and] does contain all sorts of biases itself that we don’t want to project forwards out into the 
               world and the future</quote>.<note>Anon., interview, 13 January 2023, via MS Teams.</note> With growing awareness that AI 
               systems are trained using all kinds of data (including metadata from digital archives), GLAM professionals are increasingly 
               reluctant to leave outdated metadata unchanged. In doing so, they are departing from traditional archival thinking, which 
               views the role of the archivist as neutral, committed only to preserving the fonds without changing anything in the records 
               or their original classification. This thinking, which finds its origins in the nineteenth century, is increasingly being 
               challenged by a new vision of the archivist as an activist who actively intervenes in the collection.
            </p>
            <p>This change is, arguably, a necessary one in the digital age. Once online, images are continuously copied, adapted, updated, 
               and reused — just as the earlier printed versions were, although on a far greater and more immediate scale. The Europeana 
               database, for example, provides search results from the Wellcome Collection image database. So even when records are updated 
               with more appropriate data, other versions can continue to carry outdated language. As one interviewee at the Wellcome 
               Collection told us: <quote rend="block">[T]he problem we have with those is a lot of them are already in circulation online 
               — on Twitter, on Wikimedia — lots of different places. . . . Well, should we take them down? Should we restrict access if 
               we know that they're already out there? Or do we try and sort of improve what we have and try and improve the accuracy by 
               updating our record?<note>Anon., interview, 12 January 2023, via MS Teams.</note></quote> This issue highlights the ongoing 
               complexities of accessibility and responsibility, particularly for images that can appear without their original contexts. 
               How can representation be controlled in a vast sea of digital access?
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Section 4: AI Applied to Medical Images</head>
            <p>With the current mass-digitisation initiatives for many archives, the use of AI tools to process such large amounts of 
               digitised and born-digital archival data is becoming a necessity.<note>For specific case studies and examples where AI has 
               been successfully applied to archival collections, see <ptr target="#jaillant_2022"/> and the special issue of the 
               <title rend="italic">Journal on Computing and Cultural Heritage</title> (Volume 16, Issue 4, 2023) on 
               <title rend="quotes">Applying Innovative Technologies to Digitised and Born-Digital Archives</title> (list of articles 
               available at <ref target="https://www.aeolian-network.net/outcomes/">https://www.aeolian-network.net/outcomes/</ref>).</note> 
               However, the application of AI within the cultural heritage and information management sectors is still associated with 
               challenges and criticisms, and many of our interviewees suggested that manual processing remains the preferred technique, 
               particularly when dealing with ethical issues and problems in representation. <name>Daryl Green</name> 
               (<name>University of Edinburgh</name>) told us: <quote rend="block">[I]f you were to ask me, <quote rend="inline">I'm going 
               to give you a hundred-thousand pounds for a year. You can put that towards just cataloguing your immense backlog of archival 
               material or you can put that towards fooling around with AI technology</quote>, and ten times out of ten I'm going to say 
               backlog, because that's what's needed.<note><name>Green</name>, interview, 12 January 2023, via MS Teams.</note></quote> 
               In this perspective, AI is not seen as a priority when there are more urgent tasks to complete — such as cataloguing 
               collections that are currently inaccessible.
            </p>
            <p>While there is some resistance to applying AI to collections, cataloguing and manually adding metadata to huge numbers of 
               digital images is often not possible and can inadvertently create a larger backlog. In order to automate the process, AI 
               can be used to create new metadata when original information is incomplete or missing altogether, or when it includes 
               potentially harmful or outdated language. Using computer vision, it is possible to identify people featured in images, in 
               order to enrich the metadata and humanise individuals who were frequently described with generic, discriminatory, and 
               sometimes racist language. AI can also serve to disaggregate data by gender and/or race or ethnicity, and it can provide 
               sensitivity reviews. Following recommendations on gendered metadata <ptr target="#havens_et_al_2022"/> 
               <ptr target="#lee_guo_nambudiri_2022"/>, it is possible to enrich historical medical images and medical texts with such 
               data. Improving access to historical medical record through digital technologies and data categorisation is crucial to 
               furthering medical humanities research in the digital age. Such improvements would allow the cultural heritage sector and 
               researchers to engage more readily with concerns in the representation of disability, gender, and race in historical records 
               <ptr target="#akers_et_al_2021"/> <ptr target="#massie_et_al_2021"/> <ptr target="#parker_larkin_cockburn_2017"/> 
               <ptr target="#brilmyer_2018"/> <ptr target="#white_2012"/> <ptr target="#whelan_2020"/>.
            </p>
            <p>While this may be possible for some archives, we also acknowledge that these technologies are not widely available and 
               that they require specific skills and funding to implement. An alternative to active intervention on the metadata is to 
               suggest similar images, thus providing more context on a collection. This is the option currently chosen by the Wellcome 
               Collection, which utilises a machine learning algorithm to provide a <quote rend="inline">visually similar images</quote> 
               search feature across their collection. While this visual search allows for certain images to be brought together without 
               relying on accompanying metadata, computer vision tools for historical images and illustrations are notoriously inaccurate 
               <ptr target="#foka_2021"/> <ptr target="#aske_giardinetti_2023"/>. As one staff member at the Wellcome told us: 
               <quote rend="block">When you type in the word <q>skeleton</q>, the search engine doesn’t look at the images at all. It 
               looks at the descriptions of those images — the captions, the titles, the whatever — and if a thing matches those titles, 
               then you get a result. But the results are not always great, particularly in a collection of data that is as messy as 
               ours. . . The example at the front of my mind is that there was a very kind of tight cluster of words that related to food, 
               and in the visual features that we extracted from images, it was hard for the computer vision algorithm to differentiate 
               between pictures of meat and pictures of gory surgery. An algorithm doesn't necessarily know how to differentiate that 
               context.<note>Anon., interview, 13 January 2023, via MS Teams.</note></quote>
            </p>
            <p>There are other examples of inappropriate images suggested by the <quote rend="inline">visually similar images</quote> tool. 
               For example, the Wellcome Collection catalogue features a poster of a breastfeeding mother used in a health campaign in 
               <name>Belgium</name> after the Second World War, alongside a photograph of a male prostitute.<note>The breastfeeding poster 
               can be found here: 
               <ref target="https://wellcomecollection.org/works/wsqmrqfj">https://wellcomecollection.org/works/wsqmrqfj</ref>. Then, 
               click <quote rend="inline">View 1 image</quote> to reach the Images section of the catalogue. Clicking on the image will 
               produce <quote rend="inline">visually similar images</quote>, including the picture of the male sex worker. Clicking on this 
               photo will then lead to sexually explicit pictures associated with health campaigns against AIDS.</note> The caption 
               of the latter image (<title rend="quotes">A rent boy offers himself subject to use of a condom; an advertisement for safe 
               sex by the Deutsche AIDS-Hilfe</title>) and the date provided for picture (the 1990s) bear little resemblance to the 
               metadata for the breastfeeding poster. The visual aspects of the two pictures are also dissimilar, with two women and a baby 
               on the one side, and a young man on the other side. And yet, these two images are presented as <quote rend="inline">visually 
               similar</quote>. A disclaimer states: <quote rend="inline">We use machine learning to find images in our collection with 
               similar shape and features</quote>. Users are invited to get in touch if <quote rend="inline">something doesn’t look 
               right</quote>. The onus to report problems is therefore transferred to users, instead of resting with the archival 
               institution.
            </p>
            <p>While the accuracy of such tools is still in development, image-based searches cannot fully replace text-based research 
               queries, even if both have their limitations. As suggested by the team behind <title rend="italic">Towards a National 
               Collection: Deep Discoveries</title> at the end of their recent project examining use of computer vision within the cultural 
               heritage sector, archival databases need to provide users with hybrid search options or <quote rend="inline">generous 
               interfaces</quote>, enabling both keyword and visual searches, to increase accessibility and representation.<note>See 
               <ref target="https://tanc-ahrc.github.io/DeepDiscoveries/index.html">https://tanc-ahrc.github.io/DeepDiscoveries/index.html</ref> 
               and 
               <ref target="https://blog.nationalarchives.gov.uk/deep-discoveries-exploring-a-new-way-of-discovering-and-connecting-digitised-collections/">https://blog.nationalarchives.gov.uk/deep-discoveries-exploring-a-new-way-of-discovering-and-connecting-digitised-collections/</ref>.</note> 
               But this is still a long way from being the standard practice.
            </p>
            <p>Further to the issue of enabling access is being able to responsibly manage that access. Ethical issues regarding digital 
               medical images are often associated with the changing audience for these images — from a restricted readership to anyone who 
               has access to the internet. When records are made openly available online, they can be accessed by viewers who might be 
               shocked by what they see. Explicit images of surgery or of sexual practices are clearly not suitable for children, and yet, 
               they are widely available. According to the sociologist <name>Deborah Lupton</name>, medical illustrations have 
               <quote rend="block">moved from being exclusively the preserve of medical students and surgeons to being open to the gaze of 
               all. Online technologies now allow anyone with access to a computer to view highly detailed visual images of the inside of 
               the body. Although these images may have been produced for medical students and medical practitioners and other healthcare 
               workers, they are readily available to the general public. <ptr target="#lupton_2014" loc="172"/></quote>
               Digitisation of medical images therefore comes with a number of serious ethical considerations considering what should and 
               should not, be made available to the public.
            </p>
            <p>As <name>Temi Odumosu</name> highlights, navigating potentially sensitive images is an enormous ethical challenge for 
               cultural heritage institutions <ptr target="#odumosu_2020"/>. Indeed, the identification of racially and culturally 
               insensitive records and the decolonisation of archives are at the forefront of current policy changes across institutions, 
               as decolonisation statements are being made available to users of online archival databases across the <name>UK</name>, 
               <name>US</name>, and <name>Europe</name>. These policies address the use of outdated language, insensitive terminology, and 
               the cultural prejudices prevalent at the time of record production, acting as a pre-warning for database users. Moreover, 
               informed consent doctrines have guided data collection endeavours for several decades, particularly in the medical and 
               science sectors concerning human subjects. However, according to <name>Vinay Uday Prabhu</name> and <name>Abeba 
               Birhane</name>, the age of big data has gradually eroded issues of consent, privacy, and agency. Large-scale image datasets, 
               like ImageNet, have troublesome labelling, as well as a lack of sources or context. Yet such datasets are being widely used 
               to train machine learning and computer vision models <ptr target="#odumosu_2020"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Indeed, as <ptr target="#yang_et_al_2020"/> suggest, computer vision technology is being used by many, but it is 
               representative of only a few. Computer vision has indeed faced challenges in its poor performance regarding underrepresented 
               groups. For example, it is notoriously bad at accurately identifying non-white faces. This is because most computer vision 
               and machine learning tools are trained using images from internet-based sources, containing high quality, colourised 
               images with a clear subject focus, but often lacking diversity.
            </p>
            <p>While facial recognition tools are still trained on images of similar-shaped faces, such automation leaves images of 
               faces and bodies that are not considered the norm undeterminable and, as a result, largely invisible on online archival 
               databases, even where visual image searches are enabled. Such medical images therefore provide serious ethical and practical 
               challenges for archival record managers. As <name>Tsyng-Yi Lin</name> et al. acknowledged in an influential essay published 
               in 2014, recognition systems perform fairly well on iconic views of objects (profile, centralised, and unobstructed), but 
               struggle to recognise objects otherwise <ptr target="#lin_et_al_2014"/>. Much progress has been made in the field of 
               computer vision since then, but the tools remain imperfect. Moreover, as <ptr target="#wang_et_al_2019"/> have discovered, 
               even when datasets are balanced, for example in terms of gender, trained models can significantly amplify the association 
               between labels and gender, even to the same extent as if the data had not been balanced. A biased dataset, according to 
               <ptr target="#deviyani_2022"/>, is one that generally has attributes with an uneven class distribution, meaning that tools 
               trained on these datasets perform badly for minority classes. In the case of computer vision and image recognition software 
               for images of persons, the distribution of racially and gender-diverse images, as well as the types of images, will have a 
               direct effect on the efficiency of the tool.
            </p>
            <p>One significant area that has faced backlash within the field of computer vision is the recent reanimation of the ancient, 
               pseudo-medical practice of physiognomy<note>Physiognomy refers to <quote rend="inline">the study of the features of the 
               face, or of the form of the body generally, as being supposedly indicative of character; the art of judging character from 
               such study</quote>. See <title rend="quotes">physiognomy (n.), sense I.1.a</title>, <title rend="italic">Oxford English 
               Dictionary</title>, September 2023, 
               <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/OED/6988649344">https://doi.org/10.1093/OED/6988649344</ref>.</note> within machine 
               learning algorithms applied to images of faces at scale <ptr target="#stark_hutson_2022"/> <ptr target="#goldenfein_2019"/> 
               <ptr target="#zhang_et_al_2017"/>. When facial-recognition algorithms are trained on large, existing datasets such as IMDB-WIKI, 
               the largest dataset of human faces with age and gender tags, the bias towards conventionally attractive, 
               <q>celebrity</q> faces directly informs the effectiveness of the tool. According to <name>Luke Stark</name> and <name>Jevan 
               Hutson</name>, the use of such facial recognition datasets is a matter of <quote rend="inline">urgent concern</quote>. The 
               automated reading of a human's bodily composition, gender, race, expression, and physical characteristics based largely on 
               <q>celebrity</q> images mirrors the ancient and unequivocally ableist practice of physiognomy — idealising conventionally 
               attractive faces — in a way that <name>Stark</name> and <name>Hutson</name> deem to be <quote rend="inline">oppressive and 
               unjust</quote> <ptr target="#stark_hutson_2022"/>. While there will always be drawbacks to the use of AI in the recognition 
               of images, especially those of human beings, we must proceed cautiously, especially as AI becomes a greater part of the world. 
               We must continue to build more diverse databases, and the diversity of human figures in medical image collections could offer 
               a way to help to address this current imbalance. If more images of the human body in all its varied forms were available as 
               machine-readable datasets, automated visual identification technologies could be better trained to identify a wider diversity 
               of bodies using explainable AI approaches.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>This article has argued that access to archival medical images is generally advisable, although the subject demands further 
               discussion and communication between researchers and professionals in data and record management. Keeping entire collections 
               hidden because they contain potentially harmful or outdated metadata, or because they represent scenes that we find 
               disturbing, is not sustainable. There is no point keeping archival materials that are never used. Moreover, the reliance of 
               AI systems on high-quality data means that it is risky to restrict the sources used to train these systems. Without diverse 
               sources, the risk is that AI relies too much on similar datasets (for example, images of male, able bodies). In turn, this 
               can lead to unsatisfactory outcomes when AI is used to add metadata, in the case of missing or incomplete data. Likewise, 
               when AI is used to improve search functionalities based on image similarity, it produces better results when it has been 
               trained on large and diverse datasets. Well-trained AI systems can lead users to discover images in parts of the collections 
               they would not have encountered without computational assistance.
            </p>
            <p>However, access cannot be separated from responsibility. The digital revolution has evolved in a landscape of permissiveness 
               and lack of regulation, leading to the loss of privacy and other socially disastrous consequences.<note>On the lack of 
               regulation, see <name>Zuboff</name>'s <title rend="quotes">Surveillance Capitalism Has Had 20 Years Unimpeded By Law</title> 
               (quoted in <ptr target="#kavenna_2019"/>) and <ptr target="#zuboff_2019"/>.</note> In the case of 
               <name>Molly Russell</name>, a 14-year-old British girl who died by suicide after viewing harmful social media content, the 
               inquest into her death found that tech companies such as Instagram and Pinterest were not doing enough to protect 
               vulnerable users. The images that <name>Molly</name> viewed should not be pushed to children's accounts by algorithms, 
               the senior coroner found. The family's legal representative compared the impact of the digital revolution on children with 
               that of the industrial revolution: <quote rend="inline"><quote rend="inline">It is a feature of all revolutions that they 
               tend to put progress first and safety of the vulnerable second</quote></quote> (quoted in <ptr target="#milmo_2022"/>). 
               This parallel between the lawlessness of the digital revolution and that of earlier revolutions has famously been 
               developed in <name>Shoshana Zuboff</name>'s <title rend="italic">The Age of Surveillance Capitalism</title> (2019). The 
               toxicity of online content is also at the heart of <name>Gaia Bernstein</name>'s <title rend="italic">Unwired: Gaining 
               Control over Addictive Technologies</title> (2023), which compares the disastrous consequences of the unregulated digital 
               revolution to the ravages of the once unfettered tobacco industry.
            </p>
            <p>There is not a lot of difference between encountering harmful content on Instagram or Pinterest and encountering it on the 
               digital platform of a GLAM institution.<note>We are not arguing that commercial platforms and not-for-profit digital 
               platforms in the GLAM sector are similar. Instead, we are arguing that the viewers' experience of encountering harmful 
               content is not dissimilar on these different platforms.</note> For example, a child preparing a school project could come 
               across explicit photographs on the Wellcome Collection platform, as we have seen in the introduction. More should be done 
               to protect these vulnerable users. For collections that contain sexually explicit or violent images, platforms should 
               implement age verification using an independent third party.<note>For more on age verification via independent third 
               parties, see the recommendations of the CNIL (<name>France</name>'s national data protection agency) as delinieated in 
               <title rend="quotes">Online Age Verification: Balancing Privacy and the Protection of Minors</title>, 2022, 
               <ref target="https://www.cnil.fr/en/online-age-verification-balancing-privacy-and-protection-minors">https://www.cnil.fr/en/online-age-verification-balancing-privacy-and-protection-minors</ref>.</note> 
               This is the model that the French government has recently pushed for, in its attempt to regulate the online pornography 
               industry. Keeping humans in the loop is essential when applying AI to sensitive medical images. It is not responsible to 
               use AI to suggest <quote rend="inline">visually similar images</quote> without human control. At the very least, sensitive 
               images should only be viewed after age verification and after clicking to indicate consent following a content 
               warning.<note>For a discussion on content warnings, see <name>Dentler</name> et al., <quote rend="inline">Sensitivity and 
               Access: Unlocking the Colonial Visual Archive with Machine Learning</quote> in this special issue.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Finding the right balance between access and responsibility is not easy. It requires regulations at the national level 
               to protect minors and other vulnerable users from encountering potentially distressing, violent, and sexually explicit 
               online content. But it also requires professional guidelines to determine <emph>how</emph> to show potentially harmful 
               images to an audience of non-vulnerable users. In the absence of guidelines, GLAM professionals are too often left on 
               their own to design alternative metadata in the case of outdated, racist, or otherwise problematic language. They are again 
               left on their own when it comes to displaying sensitive images. Releasing vast amounts of sensitive content without any 
               oversight could lead to unintended consequences, the severity of which for vulnerable users cannot be underestimated.
            </p>
            <p>Following <name>Gaia Bernstein</name>'s example, we would like to offer these <hi rend="bold">takeaway points</hi> to 
               encourage further discussion and research in the topic of access to sensitive images:
            <list type="unordered">
              <item>Hiding sensitive medical images is not a viable option for several reasons: archives are meant to be used, not locked 
                 away; having more images available would diversify datasets, potentially leading to social good — including addressing 
                 ableism and decreasing the gender data gap.
              </item>
              <item>AI can be used to make images — including sensitive images — more discoverable and accessible. For example, AI can 
                 be used to add a new layer of metadata, or to suggest similar images in other parts of the collection, and to offer users 
                 content warnings.
              </item>
              <item>However, access cannot be separated from responsibility. It is not responsible to release sensitive images without 
                 any oversight, or to push sensitive content to users who have viewed images considered similar.
              </item>
              <item>More national regulations and professional guidelines are needed to prevent children and vulnerable users from 
                 encountering sexually explicit, violent, or otherwise problematic images.</item>
            </list>
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Acknowledgments</head>
            <p>This research was made possible thanks to a grant funded by the AHRC (Arts and Humanities Research Council; project 
               reference #AH/W008408/1) in the <name>United Kingdom</name>.
            </p>
        </div>
      </body>
      <back>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="akers_et_al_2021" label="Akers et al. 2021">Akers, K.G. et al. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Racial, 
             gender, sexual, and disability identities of the <title rend="italic">Journal of the Medical Library 
             Association</title>'s editorial board, reviewers, and authors</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Journal of the Medical Library Association</title>, 109(2), pp. 167–173. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5195/jmla.2021.1216">https://doi.org/10.5195/jmla.2021.1216</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="aske_giardinetti_2023" label="Aske and Giardinetti 2023">Aske, K. and Giardinetti, M. (2023) 
             <title rend="quotes">(Mis)matching metadata: Improving accessibility in digital visual archives through the 
             EyCon project</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal on Computing and Cultural Heritage</title>, 16(4). 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1145/3594726">https://doi.org/10.1145/3594726</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bamba_et_al_2021" label=" Bamba et al. 2021">Bamba, Y. et al. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Object and 
             anatomical feature recognition in surgical video images based on a convolutional neural network</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">International Journal of Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery</title>, 16, pp. 
             2045-2054. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11548-021-02434-w">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11548-021-02434-w</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="barnett_2014" label="Barnett 2014">Barnett, R. (2014) <title rend="italic">The sick rose, or, 
             disease and the art of medical illustration</title>. London: Thames &amp; Hudson.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bernstein_2023" label="Bernstein 2023">Bernstein, G. (2023) <title rend="italic">Unwired: 
             Gaining control over addictive technologies</title>. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bertoloni_2018" label="Bertoloni 2018">Bertoloni Meli, D. (2018) <title rend="italic">Visualizing 
             disease: The art and history of pathological illustrations</title>. Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="brilmyer_2018" label="Brilmyer 2018">Brilmyer, G. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Archival assemblages: 
             Applying disability studies' political/relational model to archival description</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Archival Science</title>, 18, pp. 95-118. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10502-018-9287-6">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10502-018-9287-6</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cleghorn_2021" label="Cleghorn 2021">Cleghorn, E. (2021) <title rend="italic">Unwell women: A 
             journey through medicine and myth in a man-made world</title>. London: Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="criado-perez_2019" label="Criado-Perez 2019">Criado-Perez, C. (2019) <title rend="italic">Invisible 
             women: Data bias in a world designed for men</title>. New York: Abrams Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="delp_jones_1996" label="Delp and Jones 1996">Delp, C. and Jones, J. (1996) 
             <title rend="quotes">Communicating information to patients: The use of cartoon illustrations to improve 
             comprehension of instructions</title>, Academic Emergency Medicine, 3(3), pp. 264–270. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1553-2712.1996.tb03431.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1553-2712.1996.tb03431.x</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="deviyani_2022" label="Deviyani 2022">Deviyani, A. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Assessing dataset 
             bias in computer vision</title>, <title rend="italic">arXiv</title>. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2205.01811">https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2205.01811</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dmytriw_sadler_neumann_2015" label="Dmytriw, Sadler, and Neumann 2015">Dmytriw, A.A., 
             Sadler, M.S., and Neumann, P.E. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Reviving out-of-copyright medical illustrations 
             for use in medical curricula</title>, Clinical Anatomy, 28(7), pp. 822–824. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1002/ca.22575">https://doi.org/10.1002/ca.22575</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fairweather_rose_2004" label="Fairweather and Rose 2004">Fairweather, D. and Rose, N.R. (2004) 
             <title rend="italic">Women and autoimmune diseases</title>, <title rend="italic">Emerging Infectious Diseases</title>, 10(11). 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3201/eid1011.040367">https://doi.org/10.3201/eid1011.040367</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="foka_2021" label="Foka 2021">Foka, A.F. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Computer vision applications 
             for art history: Reflections and paradigms for future research</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings of 
             EVA London 2021, EVA, 2021</title>. London, UK, 5-9 July. London: BCS Learning &amp; Development Ltd., pp. 73–80. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.14236/ewic/EVA2021.12">https://doi.org/10.14236/ewic/EVA2021.12</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="goldenfein_2019" label="Goldenfein 2019">Goldenfein, J. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Algorithmic 
             transparency and decision-making accountability: Thoughts for buying machine learning algorithms</title>, in
             Office of the Victorian Information Commissioner (ed.) <title rend="italic">Closer to the machine: Technical, 
             social, and legal aspects of AI</title>. Melbourne, Victoria: Office of the Victorian Information 
             Commissioner, pp. 41–61. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://ovic.vic.gov.au/wp-content/uploads/2019/08/closer-to-the-machine-web.pdf">https://ovic.vic.gov.au/wp-content/uploads/2019/08/closer-to-the-machine-web.pdf</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gutman_2011" label="Gutman 2011">Gutman, S.A. (2011) <title rend="quotes">Copyright in the age of 
             digital scholarship</title>, <title rend="italic">The American Journal of Occupational Therapy</title>, 
             65(2), pp. 123–124. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5014/ajot.2011.000877">https://doi.org/10.5014/ajot.2011.000877</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hajar_2011" label="Hajar 2011">Hajar, R. (2011) <title rend="quotes">Medical illustration: Art in 
             medical education</title>, <title rend="italic">Heart Views</title>, 12(2), pp. 83-91. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.4103/1995-705X.86023">https://doi.org/10.4103/1995-705X.86023</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hammerschlag_2021a" label="Hammerschlag 2021a">Hammerschlag, K.R. (2021a) <title rend="quotes">Black 
             Apollo: Aesthetics, dissection, and race in <name>Joseph Maclise</name>'s <title rend="quotes">Surgical 
             Anatomy</title></title>, <title rend="italic">British Art Studies</title>, 20. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.17658/issn.2058-5462/issue-20/khammerschlag">https://doi.org/10.17658/issn.2058-5462/issue-20/khammerschlag</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hammerschlag_2021b" label="Hammerschlag 2021b">Hammerschlag, K.R. (2021b) 
             <title rend="quotes">Drawing racial comparisons in nineteenth-century British and American anatomical 
             atlases</title>, in Marshall, N.R. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Victorian science and imagery: Representation 
             and knowledge in nineteenth century visual culture</title>. Pittsburgh, PA: University of Pittsburgh Press, 
             pp. 167–188.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="havens_et_al_2022" label="Havens et al. 2022">Havens, L. et al. (2022) 
             <title rend="quotes">Uncertainty and inclusivity in gender bias annotation: An annotation taxonomy and 
             annotated datasets of British English text</title>, in Hardmeier, C. et al. (eds.) 
             <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 4th workshop on gender bias in natural language processing, GeBNLP, 2022</title>. 
             Seattle, WA, 10-15 July. Stroudsburg, PA: Association for Computational Linguistics, pp. 30–57. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2022.gebnlp-1.4">https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2022.gebnlp-1.4</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="jaillant_2022" label="Jaillant 2022">Jaillant, L. (ed.) (2022) <title rend="italic">Archives, 
             access and artificial intelligence: Working with born-digital and digitized archival collections</title>. 
             Bielefeld, Germany: Bielfeld University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="jordanova_1989" label="Jordanova 1989">Jordanova, L.J. (1989) <title rend="italic">Sexual visions: 
             Images of gender in science and medicine between the eighteenth and twentieth centuries</title>. 
             New York: Harvester Wheatsheaf.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kavenna_2019" label="Kavenna 2019">Kavenna, J. (2019) <title rend="quotes"><name>Shoshana 
             Zuboff</name>: <quote rend="inline">Surveillance capitalism is an assault on human autonomy</quote></title>, 
             <title rend="italic">The Guardian</title>, 4 October. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2019/oct/04/shoshana-zuboff-surveillance-capitalism-assault-human-automomy-digital-privacy">https://www.theguardian.com/books/2019/oct/04/shoshana-zuboff-surveillance-capitalism-assault-human-automomy-digital-privacy</ref> 
             (Accessed: 16 April 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="keet_kramer_2022" label="Keet and Kramer 2022">Keet, K. and Kramer, B. (2022) 
             <title rend="quotes">Advances in digital technology in teaching human anatomy: Ethical predicaments</title>, 
             in Shapiro, L. and Rea, P.M. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Biomedical visualisation: Volume 12: The importance 
             of context in image-making</title>. New York: Springer. 173–191.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="keitt_et_al_2004" label="Keitt et al. 2004">Keitt, S.K., Fagan, T.F., and Marts, S.A. (2004) 
             <title rend="quotes">Understanding sex differences in environmental health: A thought leaders' 
             roundtable</title>, <title rend="italic">Environmental Health Perspectives</title>, 112(5), pp. 604–609. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1289/ehp.6714">https://doi.org/10.1289/ehp.6714</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="krasnoryadtseva_dalbeth_petrie_2020" label="Krasnoryadtseva, Dalbeth, and Petrie 2020">Krasnoryadtseva, A., 
             Dalbeth, N., and Petrie, K.J. (2020) <title rend="quotes">The effect of different styles of medical 
             illustration on information comprehension, the perception of educational material and iIllness 
             beliefs</title>, <title rend="italic">Patient Education and Counseling</title>, 103(3), pp. 556–562. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pec.2019.09.026">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pec.2019.09.026</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lee_guo_nambudiri_2022" label="Lee, Guo, and Nambudiri 2022">Lee, M.S., Guo, L.N., and Nambudiri, 
             V.E. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Towards gender equity in artificial intelligence and machine learning 
             applications in dermatology</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of the American Medical Informatics 
             Association</title>, 29(2), pp. 400–403. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/jamia/ocab113">https://doi.org/10.1093/jamia/ocab113</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lin_et_al_2014" label="Lin et al. 2014">Lin, T.-Y. et al. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Microsoft COCO: Common 
             objects in context</title>, <title rend="italic">13th European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV 2014)</title>. 
             Zurich, Switzerland, 6-12 September. New York: Springer, pp. 740-755. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-10602-1_48">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-10602-1_48</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lupton_2014" label="Lupton 2014">Lupton, D. (2014) <title rend="italic">Digital sociology</title>. London: 
             Routledge.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="maas_appelman_2010" label="Maas and Appelman 2010">Maas, A. and Appelman, Y. (2010) <title rend="quotes">Gender 
             differences in coronary heart disease</title>, <title rend="italic">Netherlands Heart Journal</title>, 18(12), pp. 598-602. 
             <ref target="http://doi.org/10.1007/s12471-010-0841-y">http://doi.org/10.1007/s12471-010-0841-y</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="massie_et_al_2021" label="Massie et al. 2021">Massie, J.P. et al. (2021) <title rend="quotes">A picture of 
             modern medicine: Race and visual representation in medical literature</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of the 
             National Medical Association</title>, 113(1), pp. 88–94. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jnma.2020.07.013">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jnma.2020.07.013</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="merone_et_al_2022" label="Merone et al. 2022">Merone, L. et al. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Sex inequalities 
             in medical research: A systematic scoping review of the literature</title>, <title rend="italic">Women's Health 
             Reports</title>, 3(1), pp. 49–59. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1089/whr.2021.0083">https://doi.org/10.1089/whr.2021.0083</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="milmo_2022" label="Milmo 2022">Milmo, D. (2022) <title rend="quotes"><name>Molly Russell</name> inquest 
             must lead to action on internet dangers, says coroner</title>, <title rend="italic">The Guardian</title>, 29 September. 
             Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2022/sep/29/molly-russell-inquest-must-lead-to-action-on-internet-dangers-says-coroner">https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2022/sep/29/molly-russell-inquest-must-lead-to-action-on-internet-dangers-says-coroner</ref>. 
             (Accessed: 16 April 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="moravec_2017" label="Moravec 2017">Moravec, M. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Feminist research practices and 
             digital archives</title>, <title rend="italic">Australian Feminist Studies</title>, 32(91-92), pp. 186–201. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/08164649.2017.1357006">https://doi.org/10.1080/08164649.2017.1357006</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="nikolaidou_et_al_2022" label="Nikolaidou et al. 2022">Nikolaidou, K. et al. (2022) <title rend="quotes">A 
             survey of historical document image datasets</title>, <title rend="italic">International Journal on Document Analysis 
             and Recognition</title>, 25, pp. 305–338. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10032-022-00405-8">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10032-022-00405-8</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="odumosu_2020" label="Odumosu 2020">Odumosu, T. (2020) <title rend="quotes">The crying child: On colonial 
             archives, digitization, and ethics of care in the cultural commons</title>, <title rend="italic">Current 
             Anthropology</title>, 61(S22), pp. S289–S302. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1086/710062">https://doi.org/10.1086/710062</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="parker_larkin_cockburn_2017" label="Parker, Larkin, and Cockburn 2017">Parker, R., Larkin, T., and Cockburn, 
             J., (2017) <title rend="quotes">A visual analysis of gender bias in contemporary anatomy textbooks</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Social Science &amp; Medicine</title>, 180, pp. 106–113. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2017.03.032">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2017.03.032</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="phillips_gee_wells_2022" label="Phillips, Gee, and Wells 2022">Phillips, S.P., Gee, K., and Wells, L. (2022) 
             <title rend="quotes">Medical devices, invisible women, harmful consequences</title>, <title rend="italic">International 
             Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</title>, 19(21). 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph192114524">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph192114524</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rea_et_al_2017" label="Rea et al. 2017">Rea, P. et al. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Digitisation of anatomical 
             specimens and historical pathology specimens for educational benefit</title>, in Ma, M. and Oikonomou, A. (eds.) 
             <title rend="italic">Serious games and edutainment applications</title>, vol. 2. New York: Springer, pp. 101–119. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-51645-5_5">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-51645-5_5</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rubalcava_gadepalli_2021" label="Rubalcava and Gadepalli 2021">Rubalcava, N.S. and Gadepalli, S.K. (2021) 
             <title rend="quotes">From ancient texts to digital imagery: A brief history on the evolution of anatomic 
             illustrations</title>, <title rend="italic">The American Surgeon</title>, 87(8), pp. 1259–1266. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0003134820956307">https://doi.org/10.1177/0003134820956307</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="stark_hutson_2022" label="Stark and Hutson 2022">Stark, L. and Hutson, J. (2022) 
             <title rend="quotes">Physiognomic artificial intelligence</title>, <title rend="italic">Fordham Intellectual Property, 
             Media &amp; Entertainment Law Journal</title>, 32(4), pp. 922–977. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://ir.lawnet.fordham.edu/iplj/vol32/iss4/2/">https://ir.lawnet.fordham.edu/iplj/vol32/iss4/2/</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tsafrir_ohry_2001" label="Tsafrir and Ohry 2001">Tsafrir, J. and Ohry, A. (2001) 
             <title rend="quotes">Medical illustration: From caves to cyberspace</title>, <title rend="italic">Health Information &amp; 
             Libraries Journal</title>, 18(2), pp. 99–109. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1471-1842.2001.d01-16.x">https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1471-1842.2001.d01-16.x</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="wang_et_al_2019" label="Wang et al. 2019">Wang, T. et al. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Balanced datasets are not 
             enough: Estimating and mitigating gender bias in deep image representations</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings of 
             the IEEE/CVF international conference on computer vision, ICCV/CVF, 2019</title>. Seoul, South Korea, 27 October-2 
             November. Piscataway, NJ: The Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers, Inc., pp. 5310-5319. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://arxiv.org/abs/1811.08489">https://arxiv.org/abs/1811.08489</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="whelan_2020" label="Whelan 2020">Whelan, A.M. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Unequal representation: Race, sex, 
             and trust in medicine — COVID-19 and beyond</title>, <title rend="italic">Bill of Health</title>, 30 November. 
             Available at: 
             <ref target="https://blog.petrieflom.law.harvard.edu/2020/11/30/covid-race-gender-clinical-trials-disparities/">https://blog.petrieflom.law.harvard.edu/2020/11/30/covid-race-gender-clinical-trials-disparities/</ref> 
             (Accessed: 16 April 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="white_2012" label="White 2012">White, S. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Crippling the archives: Negotiating 
             notions of disability in appraisal and arrangement and description</title>, <title rend="italic">The American 
             Archivist</title>, 75(1), pp. 109–124. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.17723/aarc.75.1.c53h4712017n4728">https://doi.org/10.17723/aarc.75.1.c53h4712017n4728</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="yang_et_al_2020" label="Yang, K. et al. 2020">Yang, K. et al. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Towards fairer datasets: 
             Filtering and balancing the distribution of the people subtree in the ImageNet hierarchy</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings 
             of the 2020 conference on fairness, acountability, and transparency, FAT, 2020</title>. Barcelona, Spain, 27-30 January. 
             New York: The Association for Computing Machinery, pp. 547-558. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1145/3351095.3375709">https://doi.org/10.1145/3351095.3375709</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="young_fisher_kirkman_2018" label="Young, Fisher, and Kirkman 2018">Young, K., Fisher, J., and Kirkman, M. (2018) 
             <title rend="quotes"><quote rend="inline">Do mad people get endo or does endo make you mad?</quote>: Clinicians' discursive constructions 
             of medicine and women with endometriosis</title>, <title rend="italic">Feminism &amp; Psychology</title>, 29(3). 
             <ref target="http://doi.org/10.1177/0959353518815704">http://doi.org/10.1177/0959353518815704</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="zhang_et_al_2017" label="Zhang et al. 2017">Zhang, T. et al. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Physiognomy: 
             Personality traits prediction by learning</title>, <title rend="italic">International Journal of Automation and 
             Computing</title>, 14(4), pp. 386-395. 
             <ref target="http://doi.org/10.1007/s11633-017-1085-8">http://doi.org/10.1007/s11633-017-1085-8</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="zuboff_2019" label="Zuboff 2019">Zuboff, S. (2019) <title rend="italic">The age of surveillance capitalism: 
             The fight for a human future at the new frontier of power</title>. New York: PublicAffairs.
          </bibl>  
        </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>