<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">A Model for Representing Diachronic
                    Terminologies: the Saussure Case Study</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Silvia <dhq:family>Piccini</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Institute for Computational Linguistics</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>silvia.piccini@ilc.cnr.it</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Silvia Piccini graduated in Classical Literature at the University of
                            Pisa, where she subsequently obtained her Phd in linguistics. During her
                            studies, she perfected her knowledge of the Baltic languages, with
                            frequent stays at the University of Vilnius. Since 2011 she has been
                            researcher at the Institute of Computational Linguistics <title
                                rend="quotes">A. Zampolli</title> of the CNR of Pisa. Her main
                            research interest deals with computational terminology and formal
                            languages for knowledge representation. She has been a member of Cercle
                            Ferdinand de Saussure since 2018.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Andrea <dhq:family>Bellandi</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Institute for Computational Linguistics</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>andrea.bellandi@ilc.cnr.it</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Andrea Bellandi is a researcher at the Institute of Computational
                            Linguistics <title rend="quotes">A. Zampolli</title> of the Italian
                            National Research Council (ILC-CNR). He got a Ph.D. in Computer Science
                            in the Knowledge Representation and Reasoning area. He works on
                            computational lexicography and computer-assisted translation. He is the
                            main developer of LexO, a semantic web native tool for the management of
                            linguistic Linked Data resources.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Emiliano <dhq:family>Giovannetti</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Institute for Computational Linguistics</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>emiliano.giovannetti@ilc.cnr.it</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Emiliano Giovannetti is a researcher at the Institute of Computational
                            Linguistics <title rend="quotes">A. Zampolli</title> of the Italian
                            National Research Council (ILC-CNR). He is the author of over eighty
                            publications on knowledge extraction from texts, knowledge
                            representation, natural language processing, computational lexicography
                            and computer-assisted translation. He has coordinated numerous national
                            and international projects, among which the Project for the Translation
                            of the Babylonian Talmud into Italian and the PRIN 2017 on Religious
                            Diversity.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000549</idno>
                <idno type="volume">015</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2021-07-30">30 July 2021</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list>
                        <item>diachronic terminology</item>
                        <item>Semantic Web</item>
                        <item>Linked Data</item>
                        <item>N-ary model</item>
                        <item>Saussure’s terminology</item>
                        <item>lemon</item>
                        <item>OWL</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
        	<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target=
        		"https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000549/000549.xml">GitHub
        	</ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>The aim of this article is to present a model for representing in an explicit and
                    formal way the diachronic evolution of concepts and terms in a given domain, so
                    that this formalization can be machine-actionable. The approach we here propose
                    is based on Semantic Web technologies in order to guarantee interoperability and
                    reuse across scientific communities of diachronic terminological resources that
                    can be thus easily accessed, interconnected and mutually enriched. More
                    specifically, the representation of dynamic evolution of terms and concepts was
                    performed in OWL using the N-ary relations mechanisms. In addition, a set of
                    SWRL rules was set up, in order to automatically identify the evolution of the
                    concepts evoked within a text, as well as the terms representing these concepts.
                    Our model was adopted to formally represent diachronic aspects of Saussure’s
                    terminology as they emerge from his works. An example will be provided to
                    highlight the potential of such a knowledge structuration for gaining a wider
                    understanding of the profound terminological and conceptual changes brought
                    about by the paradigmatic and epistemological revolutions in sciences.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>This article explores how to represent diachronic evolution of concepts and terms
                    in a given domain.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head/>
            <div>
                <head>1. Introduction</head>
                <p>Πάντα ῥεῖ. Everything is subjected to the inexorable law of change: the reality,
                    the categories through which we organize it and the words we use to talk about
                    it.</p>
                <p>This is particularly the case for the history of science. Over the centuries,
                    scholars have built different theoretical models in response to the continuous
                    innovation that emerged from observation sometimes producing a real scientific
                    revolution in the worldview. Needless to say, a change in conceptual level often
                    corresponds to a change in terminology<note>The term terminology is here to be
                        understood as the set of <quote rend="inline">lexical items belonging to
                            specialized areas of usage of one or more languages</quote>
                        <ptr target="#sager1990" loc="2"/>.</note>: new terms can be introduced to
                    express the new system of concepts or old terms can be dismissed when the
                    concept becomes obsolete. The aim of this article is to present a model for
                    formally representing the diachronic evolution of concepts and terms in a given
                    domain, so that this formalization can be machine-actionable. Taking advantage
                    from past experiences conducted in the context of several projects<note><title
                            rend="quotes">Clavius on the Web</title>
                        <ptr target="#piccini2016"/>, <quote rend="inline">Per un'edizione digitale
                            dei manoscritti di Ferdinand de Saussure</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ruimy2013"/>, and <title rend="quotes">Totus Mundus</title>
                        <ptr target="#piccini2017"/>.</note>, we propose here an approach based on
                    Semantic Web technologies that guarantees interoperability and reuse of
                    diachronic terminological resources across scientific communities.</p>
                <p>The development of standards for representing and exchanging data has always been
                    a concern in the terminological field. Interoperability across terminological
                    formats is basically ensured by adopting the ISO standard 30042: 2008 TBX
                    (TermBase eXchange), an XML-based family of terminology exchange formats
                    compliant with the Terminological Markup Framework (TMF - ISO 16642: 2003).</p>
                <p>Over the last few years, interesting solutions for interoperability have been
                    offered by the Semantic Web technologies and the Linked Open Data initiative
                    which allow data to be shared, reused across applications and linked with the
                    resources available on the Web, thus benefiting from the whole datacloud of URIs
                    with which reference resources like DBpedia are already networked.</p>
                <p>In terminology, there has been a growing trend towards representing and
                    publishing terminological resources on the Semantic Web according to Linked Open
                    Data principles, as demonstrated for example by the NCBO (National Center for
                    Biomedical Ontology) BioPortal, a repository of more than 300 biomedical
                    ontologies and terminologies converted into RDF <ptr target="#salvadores2013"/>;
                    or by the Open Biomedical Ontologies (OBO) consortium <ptr target="#smith2007"/>
                    aiming to create a family of new or extant ontologies based on shared principles
                    compliant with the Semantic Web technologies. These and other similar
                    initiatives are all driven by the same need, namely to avoid that terminologies,
                    created by proprietary software, exist independently of each other, hidden in
                    isolated databases. The lack of semantic interoperability, indeed, precludes any
                    possibility of progress, as medical data can be exploited to their full
                    potential only if they are interconnected to each other. Sharing large
                    quantities of data structured in ontologies makes it possible to use IT
                    applications and artificial intelligence systems, enabling thus better
                    diagnostics, early disease prevention and, more generally, a deeper
                    understanding of the human biology and health.</p>
                <p>Another initiative deserving to be mentioned is the EuroVoc management based on
                    technologies in line with W3C recommendations and with the latest developments
                    in classification standards. A collaborative project started in 2019 and
                    undertaken by the Publications Office of the European Union and the
                    International Labour Office <ptr target="#dechandon2019"/> aims to align EuroVoc
                    with other controlled vocabularies and publish them as Linked Open Data. The
                    objective is to improve data accessibility and guarantee large-scale
                    interoperability, thus facilitating the authoring-translating-publishing chain
                    as well as the work in public administrations and international
                    organisations.</p>
                <p>Finally, Cimiano et al. (<ref target="#cimiano2015">2015</ref>) proposed an
                    approach to convert terminological datasets originally stored in TBX format to
                    RDF by means of an online service named TBX2RDF, allowing thereby terminological
                    resources to be used and enhanced across different scientific communities and,
                    in particular, to become part of the great Linguistic Linked (Open) Data cloud
                    (see <foreign>infra</foreign>).</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, as we shall see, using these technologies to represent the
                    diachronic evolution of terminological and conceptual data constitutes an
                    interesting challenge, since OWL (Web Ontology Language), the W3C standard
                    language developed to represent ontologies in the Semantic Web, is fundamentally
                    static and monotonic.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. Terminology and Diachrony</head>
                <p>In the terminological literature, the diachronic dimension has been neglected for
                    a long time. This was mainly due to the onomasiological, prescriptive and static
                    approach underlying the General Theory of Terminology (GTT) elaborated by Wüster
                    in 1968.</p>
                <p>Wüster’s approach to terminology was based on a neo-positivist referential and
                    taxonomic semiotics <ptr target="#slodzian2000"/>, according to which concepts
                    take precedence over words. In GTT terms are monosemic and concepts are
                    monoreferential; a perfect correspondence is established between them: each
                    concept corresponds to one and only one term. The term is thus equivalent to a
                    symbol, to a <quote rend="inline">désignateur rigide</quote>
                    <ptr target="#kripke1995"/>, since it works in much the same way as the system
                    of proper names works in general language. Conceptual structures, on the other
                    hand, are regarded as universal and static like their referents and any
                    diachronic dimension is neutralised.</p>
                <p>In outlining the theoretical and methodological differences between lexicology
                    and terminology, Cabré (<ref target="#cabre1999">1999: 8</ref>) emphasized that
                    terminology is only concerned with synchronic aspects: <quote rend="block">This
                        view, which today is considered the most systematic, coherent theoretical
                        approach to terms, differs from lexicological theory in three ways: in the
                        priority of the concept over the designation; in being exclusively concerned
                        with the level of the terminological unit and not with the other levels of
                        linguistic description; in excluding any diachronic approach of
                        information.</quote></p>
                <p>Terminology began to open up to diachrony timidly after the <quote rend="inline"
                        >odyssée terminotique</quote>
                    <ptr target="#slodzian2000"/> of the 80s, when an impressive number of term
                    banks, based on the synchronic traditional vision of the Viennese school, were
                    produced and spread (EURODICAUTOM, NORMATERM, UNITERM, TERMIUM, IATE etc.). In
                    1988 a symposium entitled <title rend="quotes">Terminologie diachronique</title>
                    was organized by the <title rend="italic">Centre de Terminologie</title> of Bruxelles, but ten years after
                    Møller (1998) still regretted a <quote rend="inline">quantitative and / or
                        qualitative deficit</quote> in that branch of terminology for which he
                    coined the neologism <soCalled>terminochronie</soCalled>. Over the last twenty
                    years several studies have been conducted focussing on the evolution of concepts
                    and terms in specialized languages (see inter al. <ref
                        target="#vancampenhoudt1997">van Campenhoudt 1997</ref>, <ref
                        target="#dury2008">Dury 2008</ref>, <ref target="#zanola2014">Zanola
                        2014</ref>, <ref target="#kristiansen2014">Kristiansen 2014</ref>), as well
                    as on methods for compiling diachronic corpora <ptr target="#dury2004"/> and
                    identifying the evolution of knowledge in corpora <ptr target="#picton2009"
                    />.</p>
                <p>As underlined by Dury and Picton (<ref target="#dury2009">2009</ref>), this lack
                    of interest for diachronic aspects in terminology was mainly due to technical,
                    pragmatic, psychological, and most of all theoretical and historical obstacles.
                    Diachronic terminology is, indeed, by definition a textual terminology <ptr
                        target="#bourigault1999"/>
                    <ptr target="#pearson1998"/>, a terminology of <soCalled>discourse</soCalled>.
                    Terms must be analysed in their real context of use and must not be seen as
                    abstract and static labels associated with concepts. They should be rather
                    regarded as linguistic signs, which enter into a dynamic relationship both with
                    the concepts and with the other linguistic signs that constitute the
                    terminological system. In a diachronic perspective, terminological work is
                    fundamentally semasiological and descriptive. In order to grasp terminological
                    variation over time, the starting point is the sense that a term acquires within
                    a real linguistic context and the focus is on language as it is actually used
                        (<foreign>Ist-Norm</foreign>) in real specialised (con-)texts and not on
                    language as it should be used (<foreign>Soll-Norm</foreign>). To use Bourigault
                    and Slodzian words (<ref target="#bourigault1999">1999: 31</ref>), <quote
                        rend="inline">le texte est le point de départ de la description lexicale à
                        construire. On va du texte vers le terme</quote>.</p>
                <p>Texts are usually the unique source that the scholars have at their disposal in
                    order to access disappeared states of languages and more completely understand
                    the history of terms and their evolution over time. Texts play a crucial role to
                    establish when and how words acquire (terminologization) and lose
                    (determinologization) their terminological status, or how a term passes from one
                    specialized field to another or from the intimate pages of a scholar to the
                    entire scientific community.</p>
                <p>Regarding this last aspect, in particular, texts constitute a precious means to
                    record the typical terminological fluctuation that precedes or follows the
                    formation of the so-called <soCalled>normal science</soCalled> state. As a
                    matter of fact, in a phase of <soCalled>normal science</soCalled>, when the
                    development of knowledge is adherent to what Kuhn (<ref target="#kuhn1970"
                        >1970</ref>) calls <soCalled>paradigm</soCalled>, the system of terms is
                    standard, explicitly defined and consensually used within a scientific
                    community. In revolutionary phases, on the contrary, when a revision of existing
                    scientific beliefs or practices is involved, terminology can be characterized by
                    great instability. Texts become thus a conceptual and terminological space of
                    creativity, where scholars think, reflect and give a linguistic form to their
                    ideas. In these cases, ephemeral lexical formations are often attested only in
                    the idiolect of the one who forged them without ever taking root within the
                    scientific community.</p>
                <p>An example of this phenomenon will be illustrated in Section 6 with Ferdinand de Saussure’s terminology.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3. Modelling an Interoperable Terminological Resource</head>
                <p>When modelling a digital scholarly resource, the key point is to choose a model
                    capable of maximizing its usefulness in the community of reference. According to
                    the <title rend="quotes">FAIR guidelines</title>, scholarly data should be
                    Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable <ptr target="#wilkinson2016"
                    />. First of all, for data to be findable, they must be referred to using a
                    globally unique and persistent identifier and must also be indexed in a
                    searchable resource. Furthermore, data must be accessible through a standardized
                    protocol and, at the same time, has to be interoperable in virtue of its
                    representation in a formal and shared knowledge representation language.
                    Finally, to be reusable, data must be <quote rend="inline">described with a
                        plurality of accurate and relevant attributes</quote> (<ref
                        target="#wilkinson2016">ibidem: 4</ref>).</p>
                <p>In order to pursue the FAIR policies and to build fair diachronic terminological
                    resources, our choice was to adopt the paradigms of Semantic Web technologies
                        <ptr target="#bernerslee2001"/> and Linked (Open) Data <ptr
                        target="#bizer2011"/>.</p>
                <p>The intuition behind the Semantic Web is to shift from a Web of documents, viewed
                    as separate data silos containing unstructured or semi-structured data, to a Web
                    of data where open repositories of semantically enriched data can be accessed
                    and interlinked. To make this vision concrete, the following technologies -
                    often referred to as the Semantic Web layer cake or Semantic Web technology -
                    are used: Resource Description Framework<note><ref
                            target="https://www.w3.org/RDF/">https://www.w3.org/RDF/</ref></note>
                    (RDF), RDF Schema (RDFS), Web Ontology Language (OWL), Semantic Web Rule
                    Language (SWRL) and SPARQL Protocol and RDF Query Language (SPARQL).</p>
                <p>Semantic Web and Linked (Open) Data best practices require datasets to be
                    published using RDF: data is described as triples in the form of Subject -
                    Predicate - Object, where the Subject is a resource, the Object can be either a
                    resource or a data value (such as a string of character or a number), and the
                    Predicate (also called <soCalled>property</soCalled>) relates the Subject and
                    the Object together. Basically, a dataset in the Linked Data world is a set of
                    triples.</p>
                <p>OWL is a family of languages, based on RDF/XML, and recommended by the World Wide
                    Web Consortium since 2004 for representing and sharing ontologies<note>According
                        to Gruber (<ref target="#gruber1993">1993: 199</ref>), <quote rend="inline"
                            >an ontology is a specification of a conceptualization</quote>.</note>
                    on the Web. There are three variants of OWL, with different levels of
                    expressiveness: OWL Lite, which supports a classification hierarchy and simple
                    constraints; OWL DL, which provides the maximum expressiveness while retaining
                    computational completeness and decidability, and OWL Full which allows for
                    maximum expressiveness, resulting nonetheless undecidable.</p>
                <p>In order to publish structured data on the Web in a way that they can be easily
                    linked to each other, a number of rules was set up by Berners-Lee, known as
                    Linked (Open) Data principles. According to them, each entity of a dataset must
                    be uniquely identified by a special <soCalled>address</soCalled> called URI
                    (Uniform Resource Identifier), each URI must be available on the Web via the
                    HTTP protocol<note><ref
                            target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypertext_Transfer_Protocol"
                            >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypertext_Transfer_Protocol</ref></note>,
                    each look up of a URI must be answered with useful information and using
                    standards, and finally, whenever possible, data should be linked to other
                    data.</p>
                <p>Over the last years, the Linked (Open) Data approach has attracted the attention
                    of a linguistic community becoming more and more sensitive to the question of
                    interoperability between resources. An increasing number of openly available and
                    interconnected linguistic datasets have been published as part of the Web of
                    data, resulting in the so-called Linked Open Data Cloud (LLOD). This trend,
                    nicely visualised in <ref target="https://lod-cloud.net"
                        >https://lod-cloud.net</ref>, is particularly boosted by the Ontology
                    Lexicon (Ontolex) community group, whose activity resulted in the creation of
                        <emph>lemon</emph><note><ref target="https://lemon-model.net/"
                            >https://lemon-model.net/</ref> and <ref
                            target="https://www.w3.org/2016/05/ontolex/"
                                >https://www.w3.org/2016/05/ontolex/</ref> for details, see McCrae et al. (<ref target="#mccrae2017">2017</ref>)</note>
                    (Lexicon Model for Ontologies), a meta-model allowing lexical resources to be
                    published in RDF, linked and shared according to Semantic Web principles. At
                    present <emph>lemon</emph> constitutes a standard <foreign>de facto</foreign>,
                    as it is grounded on W3C and ISO standards, such as LMF (Lexical Markup
                    Framework) <ptr target="#francopoulo2006"/>, Lexinfo <ptr target="#cimiano2011"
                    /> – this latter aligned with ISOCat - and LIR (Linguistic Information
                    Repository) <ptr target="#montiel2008"/>.</p>
                <p><emph>Lemon</emph> has been successfully adopted in many different contexts for
                    different purposes, such as, for example, to publish several existing lexical
                    resources as linked data, including DBnary <ptr target="#serasset2015"/>, the
                    Parole-Simple-Clips Italian lexicon <ptr target="#delgratta2015"/>, WordNet <ptr
                        target="#mccrae2014"/>, UBY <ptr target="#ecklekohler2015"/> and BabelNet
                        <ptr target="#ehrmann2014"/>, to represent linguistic resources for
                    sentiment analysis within the EuroSentiment project <ptr
                        target="#sanchezrada2014"/>, to model linguistic annotations in FrameBase, a
                    linked open knowledge base which integrates and interconnects heterogeneous
                    sources of structured knowledge <ptr target="#rouces2017"/>.</p>
                <p>The <emph>lemon</emph> core module, named <emph>ontoLex</emph><note>Please refer to <ref
                            target="https://www.w3.org/2016/05/ontolex/#core"
                            >https://www.w3.org/2016/05/ontolex/#core</ref></note>, is composed of
                    three fundamental elements: i) the <title rend="italic">Lexical Entry</title>
                    class, in turn specified in <title rend="italic">Word</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Multiword Expression</title>, and <title rend="italic"
                        >Affix</title>; ii) the <title rend="italic">Lexical Form</title> class
                    where the morphological variants of a lexical entry are described and associated
                    with a written representation (<title rend="italic">writtenRep</title>); iii)
                    the <title rend="italic">Lexical Sense</title> class, which constitutes the
                    reification of the relationship between a lexical entry and an ontology entity
                    defined in a given <soCalled>external</soCalled> ontology. In <title
                        rend="italic">lemon</title>, in fact, concepts, conceived as
                    extra-linguistic entities, receive a formal and explicit description in a
                    separate ontology, according to the principle known as <quote rend="inline"
                        >semantics by reference</quote>
                    <ptr target="#buitelaar2010"/>.</p>
                <p>The <emph>lemon</emph> model has been designed to be modular and extensible: in
                    other words, new modules can be created, if required, to represent a peculiar
                    aspect of a lexical or terminological resource. To manage semantic shifts, for
                    example, a diachronic extension, called <title rend="italic">lemonDIA</title>,
                    was developed <ptr target="#khan2014"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4. Models and Tools for the Representation of Diachrony</head>
                <p>Knowledge representation languages underlying Semantic Web technologies are based
                    on binary relations. They typically connect two instances without any temporal
                    information, thus making the representation of time a difficult matter to deal
                    with. In order to tackle this issue, different approaches have been proposed in
                    the literature (see inter al.
                    <ref target="#flouris2008">Flouris 2008</ref>, <ref target="#makri2011">Makri
                        2011</ref>): Temporal Description logics <ptr target="#artale2000"/>
                    <ptr target="#lutz2008"/>, Versioning <ptr target="#klein2001"/>, Reification
                        <ptr target="#kanmani2016"/> and 4D-fluents <ptr target="#welty2006"/>. In
                    the following, a brief description of each approach is provided.</p>
                <p><title rend="italic">Temporal Description Logics (TDL</title>). Description
                    logics (DLs) <ptr target="#baader2003"/>
                    <ptr target="#baader2001"/>
                    <ptr target="#calvanese2001"/> are a family of knowledge representation
                    formalisms underlying the Ontology Web Language (OWL-DL). They are a decidable
                    subset of first-order logic. TDLs extend DL with standard temporal logic
                    operators such as <quote rend="inline">always in the future</quote>, and <quote
                        rend="inline">until</quote>. Many TDLs have been proposed in the literature
                        <ptr target="#artale2000"/>
                    <ptr target="#lutz2008"/> with the most expressive of them being undecidable.
                    Extending DL entails to extend OWL, which is based on DL. Since OWL is a W3C
                    recommendation (2004) for publishing and sharing ontologies in a <title
                        rend="quotes">Semantic Web vision</title>, adopting TDL would entail to
                    abandon the Semantic Web framework. On the contrary, the other approaches
                    described in the following can be implemented using OWL directly.</p>
                <p><emph>Versioning</emph>. Another strategy commonly adopted to handle and keep
                    track of ontology modifications in time is versioning: whenever a change takes
                    place, a new version of the resource is created (see Figure 1). Several works
                    are grounded on this approach: Grandi (<ref target="#grandi2009">2009</ref>)
                    presents a multi-temporal RDF database model employing triple timestamping with
                    temporal elements; Zekri et al. (<ref target="#zekri2017">2017</ref>) present an
                    infrastructure and a suite of tools to support the creation and validation of
                    OWL ontologies with time-varying instances; in Tappolet and Bernstein (<ref
                        target="#tappolet2009">2009</ref>), the usage of Named Graphs is
                    proposed.</p>
                <p>The drawback of versioning approach is mainly twofold. Firstly, the fact that a
                    new version of the whole resource needs to be created every time a change occurs
                    leads to redundant information. Secondly, the more numerous the versions of the
                    resource are, the more complex and time-consuming the performance of exhaustive
                    searches becomes.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head><emph>Versioning</emph> - when a change takes place, a new version of the
                        resource is created.</head>
                    <figDesc>Shows steps of change from resource r0 to resource rn over
                        time.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p><emph>Reification</emph>. Reification is a technique for representing
                    relationships with arity greater than two.<note><ref
                            target="https://www.w3.org/TR/swbp-n-aryRelations/"
                            >https://www.w3.org/TR/swbp-n-aryRelations/</ref></note> Reifying a
                    relationship means representing it as a class of entities. The N-ary Relations
                    pattern, conceived to model a relationship as a resource, is based on
                    reification.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Example related to the fact that the sense of the term <emph>t<hi
                                rend="subscript">i</hi></emph> denotes the concept <emph>c<hi
                                rend="subscript">j</hi></emph>: (a) example of reification - (b)
                        example of N-ary relation pattern.</head>
                    <figDesc>Two charts showing reification on the left and relation pattern on the
                        right.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Figure 2(a) illustrates how the reification process works: the relation
                        <emph>denotes</emph> is transformed into a class, here named <title
                        rend="italic">Reified relation</title>. The subject and the object of
                        <emph>denotes</emph>, as well as the relation itself, become the attributes
                    of the new class. Let us suppose that the relation <emph>denotes</emph> links a
                    term t<hi rend="subscript">i</hi> (in particular its specific sense) to a
                    concept c<hi rend="subscript">j</hi> at a specific time T<hi rend="subscript"
                        >0</hi>. As shown in Figure 2(b), the relationship <emph>denotes</emph>(t<hi
                        rend="subscript">i</hi>, c<hi rend="subscript">j</hi>, T<hi rend="subscript"
                        >0</hi>) can be reified as the new class <title rend="italic"
                        >DenotationEvent</title> with three binary relations:
                        <emph>denotes</emph>(t<hi rend="subscript">i</hi>, d<hi rend="subscript"
                        >e</hi>), <emph>denotes</emph>(d<hi rend="subscript"/>e, 
                    c<hi rend="subscript">j</hi>), and <emph>time</emph>(d<hi rend="subscript"
                    >e</hi>, T<hi rend="subscript">0</hi>). The first two relations link t<hi
                        rend="subscript">i</hi> to c<hi rend="subscript">j</hi> by means of d<hi
                        rend="subscript">e</hi>, which is an instance of the class <title
                        rend="italic">DenotationEvent</title>. The third relation assigns a temporal
                    extent T<hi rend="subscript">0</hi> to d<hi rend="subscript">e</hi>,
                    representing the temporal validity of the original property
                        <emph>denotes</emph>(t<hi rend="subscript">i</hi>, c<hi rend="subscript"
                        >j</hi>).</p>
                <p>The main disadvantages of this technique are that: i) the complexity of the
                    ontology increases due to the proliferation of entities, both classes and
                    properties (as a matter of fact, whenever a temporal relation has to be
                    represented, a new object is created); ii) the OWL reasoning capabilities become
                    limited <ptr target="#welty2006"/> and can be maintained only by means of
                    time-consuming strategies, since the reified property is transformed into a
                    class and the characteristics which can be added to a property in OWL (such as
                    functionality, inverse functionality, transitivity or symmetry) are no longer
                    associated directly with the relation itself.</p>
                <p><emph>4D-fluents (four-dimensionalist).</emph> The basic idea underlying this
                    approach is that each entity has a temporal part, described by a set of time
                    slices. Each slice represents a temporal period, in which all the features of an
                    entity remain constant. Changes affect the properties of the temporal part
                    keeping the entity unchanged. In order to add the time dimension to a resource,
                    the <title rend="italic">TimeSlice</title> and <title rend="italic">TimeInterval</title> classes with the <title rend="italic">timeSliceOf</title>
                    and <title rend="italic">timeInterval</title> properties need to be introduced,
                    as Figure 3 depicts. Returning to the previous example, in the 4D-fluents
                    approach, the property <emph>denotes</emph> would connect instances of the
                        <title rend="italic">TimeSlice</title> class and would hold between slices
                    of entities. The time slices of an entity have a specific lifetime, that is the
                    time interval of the relation they participate in.</p>
                <p>As in the N-ary model so also in the 4-D fluents approach the domain and the
                    range of the property <emph>denotes</emph> change, both represented by the
                        <title rend="italic">TimeSlice</title> class. So, this model as well suffers
                    from some limitations in OWL reasoning capabilities. With respect to the N-ary
                    model, the 4-D fluents approach is affected by a wider proliferation of entities
                    (compare the blue objects in Figure 2).</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Example of 4D-fluents representation.</head>
                    <figDesc>Chart showing 4D-fluents representation.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>So far, the main mechanisms for representing time evolving information were
                    illustrated. In the next two subsections, we present a vocabulary to represent
                    time-related facts, i.e. OWL-Time, and a set of rules, i.e. SWRL, which operate
                    on temporal relations to infer new temporal knowledge and to detect inconsistent
                    assertions.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>4.1 OWL-Time and Allen’s Relations</head>
                    <p>OWL-Time<note><ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/owl-time/"
                                >http://www.w3.org/TR/owl-time/</ref></note> is an ontology of
                        temporal concepts, conceived to describe the temporal properties of
                        resources. It provides a vocabulary for expressing facts about topological
                        relations among instants and intervals, together with information about
                        durations and date-time. Figure 4(a) illustrates a diagram of OWL-Time
                        ontology. The properties <title rend="italic">hasTemporalDuration</title>,
                            <title rend="italic">hasBeginning</title>, <title rend="italic"
                            >hasEnd</title>, and <title rend="italic">hasTime</title> provide a
                        standard way to attach time information to ontological entities.</p>
                    <p>Let us consider, for example, that the term t<hi rend="subscript">i</hi>
                        denotes the concept c<hi rend="subscript">j</hi> from 1898 to 1903. In this
                        case all the needed temporal facts can be specified using OWL-Time
                        vocabulary.</p>
                    <p>However, if we wanted to answer questions like <quote rend="inline">What are
                            the intervals overlapping the interval 1898-1903?</quote>, or <quote
                            rend="inline">what are the relations holding in that interval?</quote>,
                        OWL-Time vocabulary would not be enough. James F. Allen (<ref
                            target="#allen1983">1983</ref>) provided then a calculus for temporal
                        reasoning, by introducing thirteen base relations capturing the possible
                        relations between two intervals (see Figure 4(b)). They allow the
                        computation of any relative position or sequence. In the context of the
                        Semantic Web, these rules can be represented by means of the Semantic Web
                        Rule Language (SWRL), described in the following section. The use of this
                        language makes it possible to assert new instances of relationships between
                        the ontology entities.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>(a) OWL-Time - the core model of temporal entities. (b) Allen’s rules
                            between time periods.</head>
                        <figDesc>Two charts showing temporla entities on the left and Allen's rile
                            between time periods on the right.</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4.2 Semantic Web Rule Language</head>
                    <p>Semantic Web Rule Language<note><ref
                                target="https://www.w3.org/Submission/SWRL/"
                                >https://www.w3.org/Submission/SWRL/</ref></note> (SWRL) is a
                        language based on a subset of Datalog with both unary and binary predicates,
                        representing the rule layer within the Semantic Web stack. The form of these
                        rules is an implication between an antecedent (body) and a consequent
                        (head), each consisting of zero or a conjunction of more atoms.<note>Rules
                            having conjunctive consequents could easily be transformed into multiple
                            rules each with an atomic consequent.</note> Whenever the conditions
                        specified in the antecedent hold, then the conditions specified in the
                        consequent must hold as well. Atoms can be of the form C(x), P(x,y),
                        sameAs(x,y), differentFrom(x,y), or builtIn(r,x,...) where <term>C</term> is
                        an OWL description or data range, <term>P</term> is an OWL property,
                            <term>r</term> is a built-in relation, <term>x</term> and <term>y</term>
                        are either variables or OWL individuals or OWL data values, as appropriate.
                        For example, the following SWRL rule infers if an instant <term>i<hi
                                rend="subscript">1</hi></term> is before an instant <term>i<hi
                                rend="subscript">2</hi></term>, by verifying a set of premises:</p>
                    <p>Instant(?i<hi rend="subscript">1</hi>) ∧ Instant(?i<hi rend="subscript"
                            >2</hi>) ∧ inXSDDateTime(?i<hi rend="subscript">1</hi>, ?y) ∧
                            inXSDDateTime(?i<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>, ?w) ∧
                        <lb/>swrl:lessThan(?y, ?w) <lb/>→ before(?i<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>,
                            ?i<hi rend="subscript">1</hi>)</p>
                    <p>where the built-in swrl:lessThan(?y, ?w) is satisfied when the date
                        represented by the variable ?y is earlier than that represented by
                            ?w.<note>For a complete built-ins list, please refer to Section 8 in
                                <ref target="https://www.w3.org/Submission/SWRL/"
                                >https://www.w3.org/Submission/SWRL/</ref>.</note> In this case,
                        when temporal information is provided as a date, the qualitative relations
                        are specified using SWRL rules that apply on the quantitative
                        representation. The rules can be applied to qualitative temporal information
                        as well. In the following, a rule about the relation <emph>during</emph> is
                        provided:</p>
                    <p>ProperInterval(?a) ∧ ProperInterval(?x) ∧ before(?b, ?y) ∧ before(?z, ?c) ∧
                        <lb/>hasBeginning(?a, ?b) ∧ hasBeginning(?x, ?y) ∧ hasEnd(?a, ?c) ∧
                        hasEnd(?x, ?z) <lb/>→ During(?x, ?a)</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5. Adding Time to Terminologies</head>
                <p>Given the different approaches to modelling time described in the previous
                    section, we chose to adopt the N-ary model.</p>
                <p>The reason for this choice is twofold. First of all, the N-ary relations approach
                    is supported by the Ontology Engineering and Patterns Task Force of the Semantic
                    Web Best Practices and Deployment Working Group.<note><ref
                            target="https://www.w3.org/TR/swbp-n-aryRelations/"
                            >https://www.w3.org/TR/swbp-n-aryRelations/</ref></note> Secondly, with
                    respect to the perdurantist approach, the N-ary model requires the introduction
                    of a smaller number of objects and thus <quote rend="inline">outperforms the
                        4D-fluents representation in terms of required assertions (axioms) and
                        consequently in reasoning time</quote>
                    <ptr target="#batsakis2017" loc="14"/>.</p>
                <p>In order to formalize terminology evolution following the N-ary approach, we took
                    inspiration from the model introduced by Preventis et al. (2014)<note>The
                        plug-in for Protégé CHRONOS, devoted to creating and editing temporal
                        ontologies in OWL, is based on this model.</note> to handle temporal
                    ontologies in OWL. In particular, we introduced the following entities: <list
                        type="unordered">
                        <item>the class <emph>Event</emph>, which represents the reification of a
                            property holding in a certain time. To model the class <title
                                rend="italic">Event</title> we used the relative type <title
                                rend="italic">dcmitype:Event</title> taken from the Dublin Core
                            Metadata Initiative (DCMI) and defined as a <quote rend="inline"
                                >non-persistent, time-based occurrence</quote><note><ref
                                    target="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Event"
                                    >http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Event</ref></note>;</item>
                        <item>the object property <emph>during</emph>, having the class <title
                                rend="italic">dcmitype:Event</title> as domain and the class <title
                                rend="italic">time:ProperInterval</title> of the OWL-Time ontology
                            as range. The latter is defined as <quote rend="inline">a temporal
                                entity with non-zero extent or duration, i.e. for which the value of
                                the beginning and end are different</quote>.<note><ref
                                    target="https://www.w3.org/TR/owl-time/#time:ProperInterval"
                                    >https://www.w3.org/TR/owl-time/#time:ProperInterval</ref></note>
                            <emph>during</emph> has been modelled as a sub-property of <title
                                rend="italic">dcterms:date</title> (described as a <quote
                                rend="inline">point or period of time associated with an event in
                                the lifecycle of the resource</quote>) of the DCMI
                                    vocabulary<note><ref target="http://purl.org/dc/terms/date"
                                    >http://purl.org/dc/terms/date</ref></note>;</item>
                        <item>the object property <title rend="italic">temporalProperty</title>,
                            which relates individuals of the class <title rend="italic"
                                >dcmitype:Event</title> respectively to the source and to the target
                            individuals of the original property which has been reified. As we will
                            see in detail shortly, the object properties that are converted into
                            temporal ones are formalised as sub-properties of <title rend="italic"
                                >temporalProperty</title>.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Following the N-ary approach outlined above, the terminological layer of our
                    model was formalised by extending the <emph>lemon</emph> model. The model does
                    not contain a complete collection of linguistic categories; consequently, it
                    builds on Lexinfo ontology<note>Please refer to <ref
                            target="https://www.lexinfo.net/">https://www.lexinfo.net/</ref></note>
                    in order to provide a vocabulary to describe the properties of linguistic
                    objects. More specifically, the four lexico-semantic relationships defined in
                    Lexinfo, namely synonymy, antonymy, hypernymy, hyponymy<note>In this paper, we
                        considered exclusively these properties. Other lexico-semantic properties
                        can be taken into account as well, for example translation defined in
                        Lexinfo vocabulary (see <ref
                            target="https://www.lexinfo.net/ontology/3.0/lexinfo"
                            >https://www.lexinfo.net/ontology/3.0/lexinfo</ref>).</note> were
                        <soCalled>temporalised</soCalled> (<title rend="italic"
                        >temporalSynonym</title>, <title rend="italic">temporalAntonym</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">temporalHypernym</title>, and <title rend="italic"
                        >temporalHyponym</title>) and thus converted into sub-properties of <title
                        rend="italic">temporalProperty</title> to indicate their involvement in a
                    temporal event. The same was done for the properties <title rend="italic"
                        >ontolex:reference</title>, which links every individual of the <title
                        rend="italic">ontolex:LexicalSense</title> class to a concept defined in an
                    ontology, and <title rend="italic">ontolex:sense</title>, linking an individual
                    of the class <title rend="italic">ontolex:LexicalEntry </title>to a specific
                    sense.</p>
                <p>In addition, each of these relations was reified and converted into subclasses of
                    the class <title rend="italic">dcmitype:Event</title>: <title rend="italic"
                        >senseEvent</title> representing the reification of sense relation, <title
                        rend="italic">referenceEvent</title> representing the reification of the
                    relation linking a sense and an ontology concept, <title rend="italic"
                        >equivalentEvent</title>, <title rend="italic">incompatibleEvent</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">broaderEvent</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >narrowerEvent</title> representing respectively the reification of
                    synonymy, antonymy, hypernymy, hyponymy relations holding between two
                    senses.</p>
                <p>The class <title rend="italic">dcmitype:Event</title> as well as its subclasses
                    mentioned above are related to the class <title rend="italic"
                        >time:ProperInterval</title> through the object property
                    <emph>during</emph>.</p>
                <p>So, for example, in order to represent the temporal synonymy (Figure 5), the
                    class <title rend="italic">equivalentEvent</title> is related to the class
                        <title rend="italic">time:ProperInterval</title> through the relation <title
                        rend="italic">temporalSynonym</title>, specifying the time period in which
                    the relation of synonymy holds between two senses.</p>
                <p>As we can see, the introduction of an intermediate object, namely the individual
                    of the class <title rend="italic">equivalentEvent</title>, splits the static
                    relation linking a subject and an object into two parts. Instead of a single
                    triple linking two senses (<emph>s<hi rend="subscript">1</hi></emph> sense
                            <emph>s<hi rend="subscript">2</hi></emph>), two triples are created, in
                    which the individual of the class <title rend="italic">equivalentEvent</title>
                    appears as subject in one case and as object in the other.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Synonymy is represented as a temporal event that occurs during an
                        interval: sense <emph>s<hi rend="subscript">a</hi></emph> of a certain
                        lexical entry is asserted to be synonym of sense <emph>s<hi rend="subscript"
                                >b</hi></emph> of another lexical entry in a specific time interval
                            <emph>i</emph>.</head>
                    <figDesc>A flowchart beginning with the EquivalentEvent.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>However, this is not enough. As we underlined above, to define in which period a
                    term is used with a certain sense and to denote a specific concept, scholars
                    need to resort to textual sources.</p>
                <p>As a result, our model is based on the key concept of attestation; more
                    specifically, the senses of a term are linked to the text where they are
                    attested, and for each text the writing time is defined by means of specific
                    relations. To represent texts and attestations, as the main entities
                    constituting the textual layer of our model, we introduced the following
                    entities: <list type="unordered">
                        <item>the class <title rend="italic">Text</title>, which represents every
                            work produced in a written form. As many methodological and theoretical
                            works have underlined over the years, the notion of text is highly
                            complex and culturally rich and, thus, difficult to define and
                            formalize. A detailed discussion is beyond the scope of this article.
                            The term <soCalled>text</soCalled> is to be understood here in a broad
                            sense, including entities that are very different from each other, such
                            as books, published articles, handwritten notes, drafts of unfinished
                            works etc. It can be considered equivalent to the type
                                    <soCalled><term>Text</term></soCalled> as defined in the Dublin
                            Core Metadata Initiative Type Vocabulary (<title rend="italic"
                                >dcmitype:Text</title>), namely a <quote rend="inline">resource
                                whose content is primarily words for reading</quote>.<note><ref
                                    target="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"
                                    >http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text</ref></note> If scholars need
                            to use vocabularies providing more subtle distinctions, many models for
                            representing documents in Linked Data have been already proposed,
                            offering an opportunity for high quality bibliographic data to be
                            exposed to the Semantic Web, such as FRBR (Functional Requirements for
                            Bibliographic Records) <ptr target="#carlyle2011"/> or Bibframe
                            (Bibliographic Framework) <ptr target="#kroeger2013"/>. Importantly
                            enough, if a different vocabulary is adopted, the validity of our model
                            is not compromised;</item>
                        <item>the object property <title rend="italic">hasAttestation</title>, which
                            relates a sense, instance of the class <title rend="italic"
                                >ontolex:LexicalSense</title>, to an instance of the class <title
                                rend="italic">dcmitype:Text</title>; a few works about the modeling
                            of the attestation of a term in a document have been already done <ptr
                                target="#khan2017"/>
                            <ptr target="#bellandi2017"/>; for the sake of reuse of existing
                            vocabularies we adopted the <title rend="italic">hasAttestation</title> property defined by the LAWD
                            (Linked Ancient World Data) ontology<note><ref
                                    target="http://lawd.info/ontology/hasAttestation"
                                    >http://lawd.info/ontology/hasAttestation</ref></note>;</item>
                        <item>the object property <title rend="italic">hasWritingTime</title>,
                            defined as a subproperty of <title rend="italic">dcterms:date</title>,
                            which relates an individual of the class <title rend="italic"
                                >dcmitype:Text</title> to an individual belonging to the class
                                <title rend="italic">time:ProperInterval</title> of the OWL-Time
                            ontology.</item>
                    </list> It is up to the scholar to define the boundaries of the writing
                    interval, which can be qualitative or quantitative. In fact, only in rare cases
                    he/she can define with certainty the extent of the period in which an author has
                    worked on drafting a text, with the aid of internal elements or external sources
                    (for example, the author explicitly declares that he/she has written that work
                    in a certain period, etc.).</p>
                <p>In most cases, on the contrary, temporal information on the writing process is
                    vague and ambiguous and partially bounded intervals (<soCalled>before
                        X</soCalled>, <soCalled>after Y</soCalled>, etc.) need to be defined.
                    Instead of specifying the exact duration or the starting and ending points in
                    time, scholars describe intervals with respect to their mutual relations, by
                    establishing the <term>terminus post quem</term> or the <foreign>terminus ante
                        quem</foreign>, namely the limits of the possible range of dates in which a
                    work has been written.<note>It is important to underline that every relation
                        defined by the scholar is - by default - considered valid for the entire
                        time interval of the reference corpus.</note></p>
                <p>As for published texts, instead of the <title rend="italic"
                        >hasWritingTime</title> property, the <title rend="italic">dcterms:issued</title><note><ref target="http://purl.org/dc/terms/issued"
                            >http://purl.org/dc/terms/issued</ref></note> can be used, with the year
                    of publication constituting the end of the drafting period.</p>
                <p>An overview of the model is illustrated in Figure 6.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Overview of the proposed model. (a) the textual layer is constituted by
                        texts and attestation. (b) the terminological layer relies on a N-ary
                        version of <emph>lemon</emph>, where each reified class is an event having a
                        temporal extent. (c) the ontological layer concerns the formal definitions
                        of the concepts denoted by the terms and it is described with OWL.</head>
                    <figDesc>A visualization of layers of the proposed model.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>To take maximum advantage of the adoption of OWL as the representation language
                    of the resource, we have also conceived a set of SWRL rules to automatize the
                    attribution of some temporal information.</p>
                <p>The following rule states that, if a sense is attested in a text written in a
                    certain time interval, then that sense <soCalled>exists</soCalled> during the
                    same interval.</p>
                <p>Text(?t) ^ time:ProperInterval(?i) ^ hasWritingTime(?t, ?i) ^
                    ontolex:LexicalEntry(?l) ^ ontolex:LexicalSense(?s)<lb/> ^ isAttestedIn(?s, ?t)
                    ^ ontolex:sense(?l, ?s) ^<lb/> swrlx:createOWLThing(?se, ?s)<lb/> ⇾
                    senseEvent(?se) ^ temporalSense(?l, ?se) ^ temporalSense(?se, ?s) ^ during(?se,
                    ?i)</p>
                <p>More specifically, given a text <emph>t</emph> written in a time interval
                        <emph>i</emph> (defined as an instance of <emph>time:ProperInterval</emph>),
                    and given a lexical entry <emph>l</emph> with a lexical sense <emph>s</emph>
                    (these two related to each other through the synchronic <emph>ontolex:sense</emph> relation)
                    attested in text <emph>t</emph>, then <emph>l</emph> has sense <emph>s</emph>
                    (in a diachronic perspective) during the interval <emph>i</emph>. The premise of
                    the rule is composed of the following steps: i) an anonymous individual
                        <emph>se</emph> is created <emph>ex novo</emph> in the antecedent part of
                    the rule using the <emph>createOWLThing</emph> built-in relation<note><ref
                            target="https://github.com/protegeproject/swrlapi/wiki/ExtensionsBuiltInLibrary"
                            >https://github.com/protegeproject/swrlapi/wiki/ExtensionsBuiltInLibrary</ref></note>;
                    ii) <emph>se</emph> is defined, in the consequent part, as an event representing
                    the reified relation (in particular by instantiating it as a member of the class
                        <emph>senseEvent</emph>); iii) the property <emph>temporalSense</emph> is
                    used to relate the lexical entry <emph>l</emph> to <emph>se</emph> and, in turn,
                    to relate <emph>se</emph> to sense <emph>s</emph>; iv) finally, the event
                        <emph>se</emph> is defined as happening in the same time interval
                        <emph>i</emph> during which the text has been written.</p>
                <p>If the sense of a lexical entry is attested in more than one text (each one
                    written in a specific temporal interval), the rule will be fired for each text,
                    thus relating the lexical entry to that sense in a more complex period
                    constituted of multiple time intervals.</p>
                <p>Similarly, the temporal validity of the <emph>ontolex:reference</emph> relation,
                    linking each <emph>ontolex:LexicalSense</emph> to one and only one concept of an
                    ontology, can be inferred from the writing time of the text as well, using the
                    following SWRL rule:</p>
                <p>Text(?t) ^ time:ProperInterval(?i) ^ hasWritingTime(?t, ?int) ^<lb/>
                    ontolex:LexicalSense(?s) ^ isAttestedIn(?s, ?t) ^ Concept(?c) ^
                    ontolex:reference(?s,<lb/> ?c) ^ swrlx:createOWLThing(?re, ?c)<lb/> ⇾
                    referenceEvent(?re) ^ temporalReference(?s, ?re) ^ temporalReference(?re, ?c)
                    ^<lb/> during(?re, ?i)</p>
                <p>If a sense <emph>s</emph> is linked to a concept <emph>c</emph> through the
                    (synchronic) <emph>ontolex:reference</emph> property, and if <emph>s</emph> is
                    attested in a specific text <emph>t</emph> written in the time interval
                        <emph>i</emph>, then, in a diachronic perspective, the relation reference
                    holds in the same time interval <emph>i</emph> as well. In other words, the fact
                    that a word is used with a particular sense in a specific text is equivalent to
                    saying that in that period that term was used to express that specific
                    concept.</p>
                <p>Figures 7 and 8 show respectively how the temporal versions of ontolex relations
                        <emph>ontolex:sense</emph> and <emph>ontolex:reference</emph> can be
                    automatically inferred by a reasoner and represented in our N-ary model starting
                    from the writing time of texts.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Classes and properties appearing in solid lines constitute the synchronic
                        part of the resource. Elements in dashed lines, representing the temporal
                        version of the <emph>ontolex:sense</emph> relation, can be automatically
                        implied by the firing of the SWRL rule.</head>
                    <figDesc>Flow chart beginning with the SenseEvent.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <head>Temporalization via reification of the <title rend="italic"
                            >ontolex:reference</title> relation.</head>
                    <figDesc>Flow chart beginning with the ReferenceEvent.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>We are also working at defining other rules taking into account the relations of
                    synonymy, antonymy, hypernymy, and hyponymy, with the aim of automatizing the
                    creation of their diachronic counterparts, with the addition of Allen’s
                    relations described in Section 4.1.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>6. The Construction of a Diachronic Resource: the Saussure Case Study</head>
                <p>Ferdinand de Saussure (Geneva, 1857-1913), the father of general linguistics,
                    never published his theories on general linguistics and semiotics in an organic
                    work. He strove to structure the flow of his thoughts and ideas in handwritten
                    notes, which are often characterized by a synthetic, fragmentary and hermetic
                    nature. These manuscripts display an obsessive and constant search for clear,
                    effective and unambiguous terms, against the <quote rend="inline">ineptie de la
                        terminologie courante</quote> (Letter to Meillet written in 1984, see <ref
                        target="#benveniste1964">Benveniste 1964</ref>). He changed the meaning to
                    some terms over time, assigned additional specific meanings to already existing
                    terms, used some expressions ephemerally, and even forged new words. This
                    terminological fluctuation reflects the difficulties underlying every process of
                    theoretical creation and sheds light on the evolutionary dynamics through which
                    concepts take shape and cut through language to finally find their linguistic
                    expression. This process of <foreign>rumination</foreign>
                    <ptr target="#fenoglio2012"/> is typical when dealing with theoretical
                    terminologies as in the case of Saussure, who tries to revolutionize the current
                    linguistic vision and to lay the foundations of linguistics as a science.</p>
                <p>Saussure’s terminology has been the subject of numerous studies <ptr
                        target="#godel1957"/>
                    <ptr target="#engler1968"/>
                    <ptr target="#cosenza2016"/>. In 2011 the first electronic thesaurus of
                    Saussure's terminology, named <title rend="italic">Simple_FdS</title>
                    <ptr target="#ruimy2013"/>, was built as part of the project <quote
                        rend="inline">Per una edizione digitale dei manoscritti di F. de
                        Saussure</quote>, coordinated by then President of the Cercle Ferdinand de
                    Saussure Daniele Gambarara.</p>
                <p>The architecture of <title rend="italic">Simple_FdS</title> was based on the
                    lexical model SIMPLE <ptr target="#lenci2000"/> and was therefore inspired by
                    the Generative Lexicon theory elaborated by Pustejovsky (<ref
                        target="#pustejovsky1995">1995</ref>). The Generative Lexicon theory, mainly
                    applied to general language, has proved to be very effective in the description
                    of specialized language and terminological lexicons as well (for example <ref
                        target="#arauz2012">Aráuz et al. 2012</ref>, <ref
                        target="#sanchezibanez2014">Sánchez Ibáñez and García Palacios 2014</ref>),
                    as it makes it possible to enrich the range of conceptual relations which is
                    traditionally based on generic-specific and part-whole relations.</p>
                <p>Initially, the electronic lexicon was conceived as static and no diachronic
                    aspects were taken into account. Recently, as we shall illustrate in Section
                    6.1, the model here proposed has been adopted to convert this terminological
                    resource from a static repository into a dynamic one.</p>
                <p>As underlined in Section 2, in diachronic terminology the textual dimension plays
                    a crucial role. Consequently, the first step was to build a good corpus, able to
                    represent the diachronic evolution we want to study. The texts included in
                    Saussure’s corpus can be considered as highly representative of diachronic
                    evolution of Saussure’s terminology, embracing all the thirty-seven years in
                    which the intellectual activity of the Genevan linguist unfolded. The period
                    covered by the corpus ranges from 1874 - when Saussure wrote his first <title
                        rend="italic">Essai pour réduire les mots du grec, du latin &amp; de
                        l'allemand à un petit nombre de racines</title> - until 1911, the year in
                    which he took the third course of general linguistics, the last academic
                    teaching held before his death, which occurred in 1913 after a long illness.</p>
                <p>Let us see in detail an example of the formalisation of the terminological
                    changes occurring in Saussure's writings.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>6.1 Temporalizing Saussure's Terminology: the Case of
                            <foreign>Signe</foreign></head>
                    <p>As is well known, Saussure's theories have been particularly influential in
                        semiotic studies. He emphasized first the dyadic and complex nature of
                        linguistic sign, which consists of two heterogeneous entities: a signifier
                            (<foreign>signifiant</foreign>), namely the hearer’s psychological
                        impression of a sound, and a signified (<foreign>signifié</foreign>), i.e. a
                        concept, an abstract idea. This terminology - still in use today - was
                        introduced by the Genevan linguist at the end of his life, after a long
                        theoretical reflection emerging in many of his handwritten pages.</p>
                    <p>Here, as an example, the concept of SIGNIFIER was chosen and the formal
                        representation of the different terms Saussure used over time to designate
                        this concept is illustrated, in accordance with the N-ary model we propose
                        here. In the following, the relationships and the classes taken from
                        existing standard vocabularies will be indicated with prefixes of the
                        respective vocabularies.</p>
                    <p>The concept of SIGNIFIER is denoted by many different terms in Saussurean
                        manuscripts, such as <foreign>signe</foreign>, <foreign>image
                            acoustique</foreign>, <foreign>image verbale</foreign>, <foreign>image
                            vocale</foreign>, <foreign>image auditive</foreign>,
                            <foreign>son</foreign>, <foreign>forme</foreign>. More specifically, the
                        term <foreign>signe</foreign> is attested intermittently from 1891 to 1911 in many works, such
                        as <title rend="italic">De la double essence du langage, Status et Motus,
                            Notes Item, Troisième Cours de linguistique générale</title> etc. To
                        formally represent this, the instance <emph>signe_sense</emph>, belonging to
                        the <emph>ontolex:LexicalSense</emph> class, was created and linked - by
                        means of the relation <emph>isAttestedIn</emph> - to the instances of the
                        class <emph>dcmitype:Text</emph> representing all the works where the term
                        occurs. The writing period of each text was formally defined. Here the case
                        of <title rend="italic">Double Essence du language</title> is shown. The
                        instance <emph>Double_Essence_Writing_Time</emph> of the class
                            <emph>time:ProperInterval</emph> (subclass of
                        <emph>time:Interval</emph>) was created and linked to the instance
                            <emph>Double_Essence</emph> through the relation
                            <emph>hasWritingTime</emph>. The writing interval of this work, which is
                        supposed to range from 1891 to 1892,<note>See Saussure’s letter to Gaston
                            Paris (30 December 1891). On the date of this manuscript, see Gambarara
                                (<ref target="#gambarara2009">2009</ref>).</note> was formally
                        defined by linking the instance <emph>Double_Essence_Writing_Time</emph>
                        through the relation <emph>time:hasBeginning</emph> to an instance of the
                        class <emph>time:Instant</emph>, defined by the Data Property
                            <emph>XSDDateTime</emph> with value <quote rend="inline"
                            >1891-01-01T00:00:00</quote> as well as through the relation
                            <emph>time:hasEnd</emph> to an instance of the class
                            <emph>time:Instant</emph>, defined by the Data Property
                            <emph>XSDDateTime</emph> with value <quote rend="inline"
                            >1892-12-31T00:00:00</quote>. The same formalisation was performed for
                        each work where this sense of <emph>signe</emph> was attested.</p>
                    <p>As described in Section 5, on the basis of the N-ary approach here adopted,
                        ontolex relations were reified and the following classes were introduced as
                        subclass of <emph>dcmitype:Event</emph>: <emph>broaderEvent</emph>
                        (reification of the hypernym relation); <emph>narrowerEvent</emph>
                        (reification of the hyponym relation); <emph>incompatibleEvent</emph>
                        (reification of the antonymy relation); <emph>equivalentEvent</emph>
                        (reification of the synonymy relation), <emph>referenceEvent</emph>
                        (reification of the inter-level relation <emph>reference</emph>) and finally
                            <emph>senseEvent</emph> (reification of the relation linking a lexical
                        entry to its senses).</p>
                    <p>By firing the two rules illustrated in Section 5, the classes
                            <emph>referenceEvent</emph> and <emph>senseEvent</emph> were
                        automatically populated. More specifically, in accordance with the first
                        rule, the instance <emph>signe_sense_ts</emph> was created and linked by
                        means of the relation <emph>temporalSense</emph> both to
                            <emph>signe_sense</emph> (individual of the
                            <emph>ontolex:LexicalSense</emph> class) and to <emph>signe_entry</emph>
                        (individual of the <emph>ontolex:LexicalEntry</emph> class). Similarly, by
                        firing the second rule, the individual
                            <emph>signe_sense_ref_signifiant_concept</emph> was created and linked
                        by the relation <emph>temporalReference</emph> both to
                            <emph>signe_sense</emph> and to an ontology concept, described in the
                            <emph>Simple_FdS</emph> ontology.</p>
                    <p>As underlined above, a terminological fluctuation can be observed in
                        Saussure's work as regard to the designation of the concept SIGNIFIER.</p>
                    <p>An attempt to completely renew semiotic terminology is attested in the
                        so-called <title rend="italic">Notes Items</title>. In these handwritten
                        pages, defined by Stetter (<ref target="#stetter1979">1979</ref>) as a
                            <quote rend="inline">fragment sémiologique central</quote>, Saussure’s
                        reflection upon linguistic sign achieved extraordinary theoretical heights.
                        Many heterodox neologisms were introduced, such as <foreign>sème</foreign>,
                            <foreign>sème linguistique</foreign>, <foreign>aposème</foreign>,
                            <foreign>kenôme</foreign>, <foreign>sôme</foreign>,
                            <foreign>contre-sôme</foreign> etc. Here the
                            <soCalled>material</soCalled> part of linguistic sign, namely the
                            <soCalled>signifier</soCalled>, is denoted in certain passages by the
                        term <foreign>aposème</foreign>. This terminology is abandoned later and the
                        term <foreign>signe</foreign> continues to be used to indicate at the same
                        time the <soCalled>material</soCalled> part of the linguistic sign and the
                        whole, namely the combination of SIGNIFIED (concept) and SIGNIFIER (acoustic
                        image). In order to avoid the confusion that the polysemy of the term
                            <foreign>signe</foreign> generated in his students, Saussure introduced
                            <foreign>in extremis</foreign> the term <foreign>signifiant</foreign>,
                        during his last course on general linguistics in 1911. He proposed thus to
                        retain the word <foreign>signe</foreign> to designate the linguistic entity
                        as a whole, and to replace the dyad <emph>signe</emph> and
                            <emph>concept</emph> respectively by <foreign>signifiant</foreign> and
                            <foreign>signifié</foreign>.</p>
                    <p>To formalise this terminological fluctuation, the instance
                            <emph>signe_sense_syn_aposème_sense</emph> of the
                            <emph>equivalentEvent</emph> class was created and the static triple
                            (<emph>signe_sense</emph>
                        <emph>lexinfo:synonymy aposème_sense</emph>) was split into the following
                        two triples in accordance with the N-ary model: (<emph>signe temporalSynonym
                            signe_sense_syn_aposème_sense</emph>) and
                            (<emph>signe_sense_syn_aposème_sense temporalSynonym aposème</emph>).
                        The instance <emph>signe_sense_syn_aposème_sense</emph> was then linked to
                        the interval <emph>Notes_Item_Writing_Interval</emph> by means of the
                        relation <emph>during</emph>.</p>
                    <p>In a similar way, the instance <emph>signe_sense_syn_signifiant_sense</emph>
                        of the <emph>equivalentEvent</emph> class was created and linked via
                            <emph>temporalSynonym</emph> to the individual <emph>signifiant</emph>.
                        The instance <emph>signe</emph> was in turn linked - by means of the same
                        relation - to the instance <emph>signe_sense_syn_signifiant_sense</emph>,
                        belonging to the reified class <emph>equivalentEvent</emph>. Finally, the
                        instance was linked to the interval <emph>troisième_Cours_Interval</emph>
                        (with beginning 1910 and end 1911) by means of the relation
                            <emph>during</emph>.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>6.2 Querying Saussure's Diachronic Terminology</head>
                    <p>Such a formalization, even if complex and redundant, makes it possible to
                        reconstruct on a timeline the evolution of the lexical-semantic
                        relationships between senses as well as the relations holding between senses
                        and concepts, and then to answer complex and sophisticated queries. Here are
                        just a few of the many queries which can be performed: <list
                            type="unordered">
                            <item>Which are the terms used over time to denote a concept
                                    <emph>c</emph>?</item>
                            <item>Which are the terms attested in a specific time interval
                                    <emph>i</emph> and used to denote a concept
                                <emph>c</emph>?</item>
                            <item>Which are the terms attested in a specific time interval
                                    <emph>i</emph> which are synonym (antonym or hypernym or
                                hyponym) of the term <emph>t</emph>?</item>
                            <item>Which are the terms synonyms of the term <emph>t</emph> in a
                                specific text <emph>T</emph>?</item>
                            <item>Which are the concepts denoted by the term <emph>t</emph> over
                                time?</item>
                            <item>Which are the concepts denoted by the term <emph>t</emph> in a
                                specific time interval <emph>i</emph>?</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Returning to our Saussure’s case study, let us suppose, for example, that
                        scholars would like to know which terms have been used by the Genevan
                        linguist over time as synonyms of the term <foreign>signe</foreign> (in the
                        sense of <foreign>signe linguistique</foreign>, namely <quote rend="inline"
                            >l’union de l’idée avec ce produit phonatoire</quote>).</p>
                    <p>The query results are represented here in the form of a graph (Figure 9), as
                        they appear in LexO, a collaborative web editor of lexical and
                        termino-ontological resources, developed by the Institute of Computational
                        Linguistics of the Italian National Research Council (ILC-CNR) and already
                        used within several research projects, such as DiTMAO <ptr
                            target="#bellandi2018"/> and Totus Mundus <ptr target="#piccini2018"
                            />.<note>For the time being, LexO supports the uploading of diachronic
                            resources, which are built according to the N-ary model, and offers a
                                <title rend="italic">Question Answering</title> system, implemented
                            as a user-friendly interface composed of several controlled natural
                            language templates. Each template makes it possible to formulate a query
                            in controlled natural language thanks to dropdown menus. For further
                            extensions of the tool LexO, see Section 7.</note></p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>The synonyms of the term <foreign>signe</foreign> used by Saussure
                            between 1890 and 1911</head>
                        <figDesc>Screenshot of interface showing synonyms of
                                <foreign>signe</foreign>.</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>As clearly appears in the graph, the formalization previously described makes
                        it emerge immediately Saussure’s unceasing and obsessive work in search for
                        the term that best represented the concept.</p>
                    <p>In an initial period, spanning approximately from 1891 and 1892, Saussure
                        introduces three interesting neologisms: <foreign>signe-idée</foreign>,
                            <foreign>son-idée</foreign> and <foreign>forme-sens</foreign>. These
                        three nominal compounds well reflect the fact that the linguistic sign is
                        composed of two parts that are closely connected as the two sides of a piece
                        of paper. In effect, the bipartite structure of the terms mirrors the dyadic
                        nature of the linguistic sign. Each element of the compound denotes one of
                        the two parts composing the linguistic sign. More specifically, the first
                        constituent of the compound refers to the signifier, i.e. the sound-image
                            (<foreign>signe</foreign>, <foreign>son</foreign>,
                            <foreign>forme</foreign>), while the second element denotes the
                        conceptual side, the idea conveyed by the sign (<foreign>idée</foreign>,
                            <foreign>sens</foreign>).</p>
                    <p>Later, in a time span ranging from 1899 to 1903, Saussure renames
                            <foreign>signe</foreign> as <foreign>sème</foreign> and distinguishes it
                        from its <soCalled>material</soCalled> constituent, named
                            <foreign>aposème</foreign> or <foreign>sôme</foreign> and from its
                        conceptual part, designated as <foreign>parasôme</foreign> or
                            <foreign>contre- sôme</foreign>, thus introducing a constellation of
                        neologisms derived from ancient Greek, as is usual in scientific
                        terminology. All these neologisms are abandoned and no longer adopted by the
                        Genevan linguist who prefers to continue using more traditional terms such
                        as <foreign>mot</foreign>, <foreign>terme</foreign>, <foreign>signe
                            linguistique</foreign>. These terms are all attested in the third course
                        of general linguistics held by Saussure in Geneva between 1910 and 1911.
                        Here Saussure definitely chooses the term <foreign>signe</foreign> to
                        indicate the whole resulting from the association of form, named
                            <foreign>signifiant</foreign>, and meaning, named
                            <foreign>signifié</foreign>, thus resolving the ambiguity that until
                        then had characterized the term <foreign>signe</foreign>: <quote
                            rend="inline">L'ambiguïté disparaîtrait si l'on désignait les trois
                            notions ici en présence par des noms qui s'appellent les uns les autres
                            tout en s'opposant. Nous proposons de conserver le mot signe pour
                            désigner le total, et de remplacer concept et image acoustique
                            respectivement par signifié et signifiant; ces derniers termes ont
                            l’avantage de marquer l’opposition qui les sépare soit entre eux, soit
                            du total dont ils font partie. [...]</quote>
                        <ptr target="#saussure1972" loc="99"/>.</p>
                    <p>Another query focussing on the period of attestation of the term
                            <foreign>signe</foreign> in all its meanings brings out this ambiguity
                        more clearly, as illustrated in Figure 10.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>The attestation period of the term <foreign>signe</foreign> in its
                            three meanings.</head>
                        <figDesc>Screenshot of the interface showing the meaning
                                <foreign>signe</foreign> during its attestation period.</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The green bar represents the period in which every sense is attested;
                        clicking on it in LexO interface the complete list of all the works where
                        the term occurs is provided.</p>
                    <p>As the graph shows, <emph>signe</emph> is used in the same period - and in
                        the same texts - with two different meanings, namely to indicate the most
                            <soCalled>concrete</soCalled> part of the linguistic sign
                            (<foreign>signe sense-2</foreign>) as well as to denote the union of a
                        concept and a form (<foreign>signe sense-3</foreign>).<note><foreign>Signe
                                sense-1</foreign> refers to any material entity to which we
                            associate a sense. This meaning is not taken into account here, as not
                            relevant for the purposes of this discussion.</note> This polysemy
                        generates ambiguity, and – as we know – ambiguity should be strongly avoided
                        in terminology where, according to GTT, the term must be monosemic and the
                        concept unambiguous. Saussure is aware of this and therefore during his last
                        course on general linguistics – and more precisely on May 19 1911 – proposes
                        to preserve the term <foreign>signe</foreign> in its third sense and to
                        replace it with the neologism <foreign>signifiant</foreign> as for the
                        second meaning.</p>
                    <p>As Saussure’s case study demonstrates, models and tools devoted to
                        representing and querying diachronic terminological resources play a crucial
                        role in order to better understand the terminological fluctuation and the
                        mobile and progressive conceptualisation which characterize some unstable
                        phases of science.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>7. Conclusion and Next Steps</head>
                <p>Representing the diachronic evolution of terminological and conceptual data in a
                    formal way constitutes a challenge, since standard formalisms adopted in the
                    Semantic Web for the representation of data have mainly been conceived for
                    static and monotonic information.</p>
                <p>In this work we have proposed a Semantic Web-based model for representing in an
                    explicit and formal way the diachronic evolution of concepts and terms in a
                    given domain, accompanied by a concrete use case focussing on the evolution of
                    linguistic terminology as attested in Ferdinand De Saussure’s writings. The
                    temporalization approach illustrated here is domain independent and can be
                    virtually applied to any RDF data model. The main drawback is that such an
                    approach requires a significant design effort in modelling and encoding specific
                    sets of temporal rules. In addition, the properties to be temporalized need to
                    be already known at the modelling time. However, in slightly
                        <soCalled>controlled</soCalled> domains like terminology and lexicography,
                    our approach turns out to be effective to describe the historical development of
                    a language, and its many temporal variations.</p>
                <p>The next research objectives are: i) the enrichment of the model, ii) the
                    exploitation of the resource, iii) the extension of the tool LexO to support the
                    construction of diachronic resources <ptr target="#bellandi2018"/>.<note>The
                        most recent stable version of LexO is available at <ref
                            target="https://github.com/andreabellandi/LexO-lite"
                            >https://github.com/andreabellandi/LexO-lite</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>As far as the enrichment of the model is concerned, we plan to design new SWRL
                    rules for the automatic temporalization of lexico-semantic properties holding
                    between senses, such as synonymy, antonymy etc.</p>
                <p>In addition, in order to manage the cases when the writing period of a text is
                    uncertain, we intend to develop an algorithm exploiting the resource for
                    automatic dating suggestion: the behaviour of terms in those texts, whose
                    writing time is known, will be used to advance hypotheses on the uncertain (or
                    even unknown) writing time periods of the other texts belonging to the corpus
                    under analysis. Needless to say, the accuracy of suggested time periods will be
                    proportionate to the amount of (certain) temporal information already encoded in
                    the diachronic resource.</p>
                <p>Finally, we are working to extend the tool LexO as to include the management of
                    texts and temporal information. The tool will be designed to relieve scholars
                    from the time consuming (and prone to errors) task of formalising the large
                    amount of entities required to represent the temporal information according to
                    the N-ary model. In addition, thanks to LexO scholars will not be required to
                    manage the formalisms and the languages underlying the Web Semantic technologies
                    such as RDF and OWL.</p>
                <p>The first extension of the tool LexO aimed at the inclusion of temporal
                    information will involve the integration of functions for the management of
                    text. As discussed in Section 2, diachronic terminology is a textual
                    terminology, and terms have to be analysed in their contexts of use. For this
                    reason, LexO will be equipped with a module through which users will be able to
                    import their documents and the relative time information (writing time, date of
                    publishing, etc.), organize them into folders, browse them and link each encoded
                    term to the relative attestations in the corpus.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="allen1983" label="Allen 1983">Allen, J. (1983). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Maintaing knowledge about temporal intervals</title>. <title rend="italic"
                            >Communications of the ACM</title>, 26(11), pp. 832-843.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="arauz2012" label="Aráuz et al. 2012">Aráuz L., Faber, P. and Montero
                    Martínez, S. (2012). <title rend="quotes">Specialized Language
                        Semantics</title>. In P. Faber, ed., <title rend="italic">A cognitive
                        linguistics view of terminology and specialized language</title>, Series:
                    Applications of Cognitive Linguistics [ACL] 20, 1st ed. Berlin, Boston: De
                    Gruyter Mouton, pp. 95-175.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="artale2000" label="Artale and Franconi 2000">Artale, A. and Franconi,
                    E. (2000). <title rend="quotes">A survey of temporal extensions of description
                        logics</title>. <title rend="italic">Annals of Mathematics and Artificial
                        Intelligence</title>, 30 (1-4), pp. 171-210.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="baader2003" label="Baader et al. 2003">Baader, F., Calvanese, D.,
                    McGuinness, D., Patel-Schneider, P., Nardi, D. (2003). <title rend="quotes">The
                        description logic handbook: Theory, implementation and applications</title>.
                    Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="baader2001" label="Baader and Sattler 2001">Baader, F. and Sattler U.
                    (2001). <title rend="quotes">An overview of tableau algorithms for description
                        logics</title>. <title rend="italic">Studia Logica</title>, 69 (1), pp.
                    5-40.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="batsakis2017" label="Batsakis et al. 2017">Batsakis, S., Petrakis E.,
                    Tachmazidis, I. and Antoniou, G. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Temporal
                        representation and reasoning in OWL 2</title>. <title rend="italic">Semantic
                        Web</title>, 8 (6), pp. 981-1000.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bellandi2017" label="Bellandi et al. 2017">Bellandi, A., Boschetti,
                    F., Khan, F., Del Grosso, A.M. and Monachini, M. (2017). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Provando e riprovando modelli di dizionario storico digitale: Collegare
                        voci, citazioni, interpretazioni</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings
                            of the AIUCD</title>, pp. 119-125.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bellandi2018" label="Bellandi et al. 2018">Bellandi, A., Giovannetti,
                    E., Weingart, A. (2018). <title rend="quotes">Multilingual and Multiword
                        Phenomena in a lemon Old Occitan Medico-Botanical Lexicon</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Information</title> 9 (3), 52.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bellandi2018b" label="Bellandi, Giovannetti, and Piccini 2018"
                    >Bellandi, A., Giovannetti, E., Piccini, S. (2018). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Collaborative Editing of Lexical and Termino-ontological resources: A Quick
                        Introduction to LexO</title>. <title rend="italic">The XVIII EURALEX
                        International Congress: Lexicography in Global Contexts Book of
                        Abstracts</title>, 17-21 July 2018, Ljubljana, Slovenia, pp. 23-27.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="benveniste1964" label="Benveniste 1964">Benveniste, E. (1964). <title
                        rend="quotes">Lettres de F. de Saussure à A. Meillet</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Cahiers Ferdinand de Saussure</title>, 21, pp. 89-130.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bernerslee2001" label="Berners-Lee et al. 2001">Berners-Lee, T.,
                    Hendler, J., Lassila, O. (2001). <title rend="quotes">The semantic web</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Scientific American</title>, 284(5), pp. 34-43.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bizer2011" label="Bizer et al. 2011">Bizer, Ch., Heath, T.,
                    Berners-Lee, T. (2011). <title rend="quotes">Linked data: The story so
                        far</title>. In Amit Sheth, ed., <title rend="italic">Semantic services,
                        interoperability and web applications: emerging concepts</title>, 1st ed.,
                    Hershey, Pennsylvania: IGI Global, pp. 205-227.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bourigault1999" label="Bourigault and Slodzian 1999">Bourigault D.,
                    Slodzian M. (1999). <title rend="quotes">Pour une terminologie
                    textuelle</title>. <title rend="italic">Terminologies nouvelles</title> 19, pp.
                    29-32.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="buitelaar2010" label="Buitelaar 2010">Buitelaar, P. (2010). <title
                        rend="quotes">Ontology-based Semantic Lexicons: Mapping between Terms and
                        Object Descriptions</title>, In C. Huang, N. Calzolari, A. Gangemi, A.
                    Lenci, A. Oltramari, &amp; L. Prevot, eds., <title rend="italic">Ontology and
                        the Lexicon: A Natural Language Processing Perspective. Studies in Natural
                        Language Processing</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, pp.
                    212-223.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cabre1999" label="Cabré 1999">Cabré, M. T. (1999). <title
                        rend="italic">Terminology: Theory, Methods and Applications</title>.
                    Amsterdam: John Benjamins Publishing.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="calvanese2001" label="Calvanese et al. 2001">Calvanese, D., De
                    Giacomo,G., Lenzerini, M. Nardi, D. (2001). <title rend="quotes">Reasoning in
                        Expressive Description Logics</title>. <title rend="italic">Handbook of
                        automated reasoning</title> 2, pp. 1581-1634.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="carlyle2011" label="Carlyle 2011">Carlyle, A. (2011). <title
                        rend="quotes">Understanding FRBR as a conceptual model</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Library Resources &amp; Technical Services</title>, 50 (4),
                    pp. 264-273.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cimiano2011" label="Cimiano et al. 2011">Cimiano, P., Buitelaar, P.,
                    McCrae, J., Sintek, M. (2011). <title rend="quotes">Lexinfo: A declarative model
                        for the lexicon-ontology interface</title>. <title rend="italic">Web
                        Semantics: Science, Services and Agents on the World Wide Web</title> 9 (1),
                    pp. 29-51.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cimiano2015" label="Cimiano et al. 2015">Cimiano, P., McCrae, J.P.,
                    Rodríguez-Doncel, V., Gornostay, T., Gómez-Pérez, A., Siemoneit, B., Lagzdins,
                    A. (2015). <title rend="quotes">Linked terminology: applying linked data
                        principles to terminological resources</title>. In Kosem, I., Jakubíček, M.,
                    Kallas, J., Krek, S., eds., <title rend="italic">Electronic lexicography in the
                        21st century: linking lexical data in the digital age. Proceedings of the
                        eLex 2015 conference</title>, 11-13 August 2015, Herstmonceux Castle, United
                    Kingdom. Ljubljana/Brighton: Trojina, Institute for Applied Slovene
                    Studies/Lexical Computing Ltd, Sussex, UK, pp. 504-517.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cosenza2016" label="Cosenza 2016">Cosenza, G. (2016). <title
                        rend="italic">Dalle parole ai termini. I percorsi di pensiero di F. de
                        Saussure</title>. Alessandria. Edizioni dell’Orso. Collezione <title
                        rend="quotes">Studi e Ricerche</title>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dechandon2019" label="Dechandon et al. 2019">Dechandon, D., Gerencsér,
                    A., Ruiz, M.R. (2019). <title rend="quotes">Terminology: Towards a Systematic
                        Integration of Semantics and Metadata</title>. In <title rend="italic"
                        >Translating and the Computer</title> 41, Proceedings of AsLing (The
                    International Association for Advancement in Language Technology), Geneva:
                    Editions Tradulex.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="delgratta2015" label="Del Gratta et al. 2015">Del Gratta, R.,
                    Frontini, F., Khan, F., Monachini, M. (2015). <title rend="quotes">Converting
                        the PAROLE SIMPLE CLIPS Lexicon into RDF with lemon</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Semantic Web</title>, 6 (4), pp. 387-392.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dury2004" label="Dury 2004">Dury, P. (2004). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Building a Bilingual Diachronic Corpus of Ecology: The Long Road to
                        Completion</title>. <title rend="italic">Icame Journal</title>, 28, pp.
                    5-16.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dury2008" label="Dury 2008">Dury, P. (2008). <title rend="quotes">The
                        rise of carbon neutral and compensation carbone: A diachronic investigation
                        into the migration of vocabulary from the language of ecology to newspaper
                        language and vice versa</title>. <title rend="italic">Terminology</title>,
                    14(2), pp. 230-248.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dury2009" label="Dury and Picton 2009">Dury, P., Picton, A. (2009).
                        <title rend="quotes">Terminologie et diachronie: vers une réconciliation
                        théorique et méthodologique?</title>. <title rend="italic">Revue française
                        de linguistique appliquée</title>, 14 (2), pp. 31-41.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ecklekohler2015" label="Eckle-Kohler 2015">Eckle-Kohler, J., McCrae,
                    J.P., Chiarcos, Ch. (2015). <title rend="quotes">LemonUby–A large, interlinked,
                        syntactically-rich lexical resource for ontologies</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Semantic Web</title>, 6 (4), pp. 371-378.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ehrmann2014" label="Ehrmann et al. 2014">Ehrmann, M., Cecconi, F.,
                    Vannella, D., McCrae, J.P., Cimiano, P., Navigli, R. (2014). <title
                        rend="quotes">Representing Multilingual Data as Linked Data: the Case of
                        BabelNet 2.0</title>. In N. Calzolari, K. Choukri, T. Declerck, H. Loftsson,
                    B. Maegaard, J. Mariani, A. Moreno, J. Odijk, S. Piperidis, eds., <title
                        rend="italic">Proceedings of LREC 2014</title>, pp. 401–408.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="engler1968" label="Engler 1968">Engler, R. (1968). <title
                        rend="italic">Lexique de la terminologie saussurienne</title>.
                    Utrecht-Anvers: Spectrum. Comité international permanent des linguistes.
                    Publication de la commission de terminologie.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fenoglio2012" label="Fenoglio 2012">Fenoglio, I. (2012). <title
                        rend="quotes">Genèse du geste linguistique : une complexité
                        heuristique</title>. <title rend="italic">Genesis</title> [En ligne], 35,
                    pp. 13-40. DOI : 10.4000/genesis.1033.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="flouris2008" label="Flouris et al. 2008">Flouris, G., Manakanatas D.,
                    Kondylakis H., Plexousakis D., Antoniou G. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Ontology
                        Change: Classification and Survey</title>. <title rend="italic">The
                            Knowledge Engineering Review</title>, 23, pp. 117-52.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="francopoulo2006" label="Francopoulo et al. 2006">Francopoulo, G.,
                    George, M., Calzolari, N., Monachini, M., Bel, N., Pet, M., Soria, C. (2006).
                        <title rend="quotes">Lexical markup framework (LMF)</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Proceedings of the Fifth International Conference on Language
                        Resources and Evaluation</title> LREC 2006, Genova, pp. 233-236.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gambarara2009" label="Gambarara 2009">Gambarara, D. (2009).
                    Présentation de section II <title rend="quotes">Système et cognition. Quaternion
                        et parallélie dans De l’Essence double du langage</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Cahiers Ferdinand de Saussure</title>, 61, pp. 75-86.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="godel1957" label="Godel 1957">Godel, R. (1957). <title rend="italic"
                        >Les sources manuscrites du Cours de linguistique générale de Ferdinand de
                        Saussure</title>. Genève: Droz.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="grandi2009" label="Grandi 2009">Grandi, F. (2009). <title
                        rend="quotes">Multi-temporal RDF ontology versioning</title>. In M. d'Aquin,
                    G. Antoniou, eds., <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 3rd International
                        Workshop on Ontology Dynamics</title> (IWOD-09), collocated with the 8th
                    International Semantic Web Conference (ISWC-2009), Washington DC, USA, October
                    26, 2009.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gruber1991" label="Gruber 1991">Gruber, T. R. (1991). <title
                        rend="quotes">A translation approach to portable ontologies</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Knowledge Acquisition</title>, vol. V (2), pp. 199-220.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kanmani2016" label="Kanmani 2016">Kanmani, A. Clara, Chockalingam, T.
                    and Guruprasad. N. (2016). <title rend="quotes">RDF data model and its multi
                        reification approaches: A comprehensive comparative analysis</title>. In
                        <title rend="italic">International Conference on Inventive Computation Technologies (ICICT)</title>, vol. 1, pp. 1-5.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="khan2016" label="Khan et al. 2016">Khan, F., Bellandi, A., Monachini,
                    M. (2016). <title rend="quotes">Tools and Instruments for Building and Querying
                        Diachronic Computational Lexica</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                        the Workshop on Language Technology Resources and Tools for Digital
                        Humanities</title> (LT4DH), Osaka, Japan: The COLING 2016 Organizing
                    Committee, pp. 164-171.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="khan2014" label="Khan et al. 2014">Khan, F., Boschetti, F., Frontini,
                    F. (2014). <title rend="quotes">Using lemon to model lexical semantic shift in
                        diachronic lexical resources</title>. In Ch. Chiarcos, J. Ph. McCrae, P.
                    Osenova, C. Vertan, eds., <title rend="italic">3rd. Workshop on Linked Data in
                        Linguistics: Multilingual Knowledge Resources and Natural Language
                        Processing</title>, p. 50.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="khan2017" label="Khan et al. 2017">Khan, F., Bowers, J., Frontini, F.
                    (2017). <title rend="quotes">Situating Word Senses in their Historical Context
                        with Linked Data</title>. In C. Gardent, Ch. Retoré, eds., <title
                        rend="italic">IWCS 2017 — 12th International Conference on Computational
                        Semantics — Short papers</title>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kuhn1970" label="Kuhn 1970">Kuhn, T.S. (1970). <title rend="italic"
                        >The structure of scientific revolutions</title>. 2nd ed., Chicago: The
                    University of Chicago Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="klein2001" label="Klein and Fensel 2001">Klein, M. CA., Fensel, D.
                    (2001). <title rend="quotes">Ontology versioning on the Semantic Web</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the First International Conference on
                        Semantic Web Working</title>. California: CEUR-WS.org, pp. 75-91.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kripke1995" label="Kripke 1995">Kripke, S. (1995). <title
                        rend="italic">La logique des noms propres</title>. Paris: Les Editions de
                    Minuit.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kristiansen2014" label="Kristiansen 2014">Kristiansen M. (2014).
                        <title rend="quotes">Concept change, term dynamics and culture-boundness in
                        economic-administrative domains</title>. In R. Temmermann and M. van
                    Campenhoudt, eds., <title rend="italic">Dynamics and terminology: an
                        interdisciplinary perspective on monolingual and multilingual culture-bound
                        communication</title>. Terminology and lexicography research and practice,
                    volume 16, Amsterdam; Philadelphia: John Benjamins Publishing Company, pp.
                    235-256.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kroeger2013" label="Kroeger 2013">Kroeger, A. (2013). <title
                        rend="quotes">The road to BIBFRAME: the evolution of the idea of
                        bibliographic transition into a post-MARC Future</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Cataloging &amp; classification quarterly</title>, 51 (8), pp.
                    873-890.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lacy2005" label="Lacy 2005">Lacy, L.W. (2005). <title rend="italic"
                        >Owl: Representing Information Using the Web Ontology Language</title>.
                    Victoria, BC, Canada: Trafford Publishing.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lenci2000" label="Lenci et al. 2000">Lenci, A., Bel, N., Busa, F.,
                    Calzolari, N., Gola, E., Monachini, M., Ogonowski, A., Peters, I., Peters, W.,
                    Ruimy, N., Villegas, M., Zampolli, A. (2000). <title rend="quotes">SIMPLE: A
                        General Framework for the development of Multilingual Lexicons</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">International Journal of Lexicography</title>, 13 (4).
                    Special issue <q>Dictionaries, Thesauri and Lexical-Semantic Relations</q>, pp.
                    249-263.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lutz2008" label="Lutz et al. 2008">Lutz, C., Wolter, F.,
                    Zakharyaschev, M. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Temporal Description Logics: A
                        Survey</title>. <title rend="italic">TIME</title>, pp. 3-14.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="makri2011" label="Makri 2011">Makri, P. (2011). 4D-Fluents Plug-In: A
                    Tool for Handling Temporal Ontologies in Protégé. <title rend="italic">Diss.
                        Diploma Thesis</title>. Department of Electronic and Computer Engineering,
                    Technical University of Crete.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mccrae2014" label="McCrae et al. 2014">McCrae, J.P., Fellbaum, C.,
                    Cimiano, P. (2014). <title rend="quotes">Publishing and linking WordNet using
                        lemon and RDF</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop
                        on Linked Data in Linguistics</title>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mccrae2017" label="McCrae et al. 2017">McCrae, J. P., Bosque-Gil, J.,
                    Gracia, J., Buitelaar, P., &amp; Cimiano, P. <title rend="quotes">The
                        OntoLex-Lemon Model: Development and Applications</title>. In I. Kosem, C.
                    Tiberius, M. Jakubíček, J. Kallas, S. Krek, V. Baisa, eds, <title rend="italic"
                        >Electronic lexicography in the 21st century. Proceedings of eLex 2017
                        conference</title>, September 19-21, Leiden, Netherlands. Lexical Computing
                    CZ s.R.O, Brno, Czech Republic, pp. 19-21.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="montiel2008" label="Montiel-Ponsoda 2008">Montiel-Ponsoda, E., Aguado
                    de Cea, G., Gómez-Pérez, A., Peters, W. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Modelling
                        multilinguality in ontologies</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                        the 21st International Conference on Computational Linguistics
                        (COLING)</title>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moller1998" label="Møller 1998">Møller, B. (1998). "À la recherche
                    d’une terminochronie". <title rend="italic">Meta</title>, XLIII-3, pp.
                    1-13</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pearson1998" label="Pearson 1998">Pearson, J. (1998). <title
                        rend="italic">Terms in Context, Studies in Corpus Linguistic</title>. Vol.
                    I, 1 ed., Amsterdam/Philadelphia: John Benjamins.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piccini2016" label="Piccini 2016">Piccini, S. (2016). <title
                        rend="quotes">CLAVIUS: verso la modellazione di una risorsa
                        termino-ontologica diacronica del dominio matematico-astronomico del XVII
                        secolo</title>. <title rend="italic">Atti del XXVI Convegno internazionale
                        Ass.I.Term.</title> Terminologia e organizzazione della conoscenza nella
                    conservazione della memoria digitale, 14 - 16 April 2016 - Rende, Italy, pp.
                    95-105.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piccini2017" label="Piccini 2017">Piccini, S., Corsi, E., Giovannetti,
                    E. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Une ressource termino-ontologique bilingue
                        chinois-italien: le cas de la traduction de la Mappemonde de Matteo Ricci
                        par Pasquale D’Elia</title>. In Ch. Roche, éd., <title rend="italic">TOTh 2017,
                        Terminologie &amp; Ontologie : Théories et Applications,</title> Série:
                    Terminologica, Éditions de l'Université Savoie Mont Blanc, pp. 33-49.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piccini2018" label="Piccini 2018">Piccini, S., Bellandi, A.,
                    Giovannetti, E. (2018). <title rend="quotes">A Semantic Web Approach to
                        Modelling and Building a Bilingual Chinese-Italian Termino-ontological
                        Resource</title>. In A. Čibej, V. Gorjanc, I. Kosem, S. Krek, eds., <title
                        rend="italic">The XVIII EURALEX International Congress: Lexicography in
                        Global Contexts Book of Abstracts</title>, 17-21 July 2018, Ljubljana,
                    Slovenia, pp. 87-90.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="picton2009" label="Picton 2009">Picton, A. (2009). <title
                        rend="italic">Diachronie en langue de spécialité. Définition d'une méthode
                        linguistique outillée pour repérer l'évolution des connaissances en corpus.
                        Un exemple appliqué au domaine spatial</title>. PhD. Dissertation. Toulouse
                    2.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="preventis2014" label="Preventis et al. 2014">Preventis, A., Petrakis,
                    E., Batsakis, S. (2014). <title rend="quotes">Chronos Ed: A tool for handling
                        temporal ontologies in Protégé</title>. <title rend="italic">International
                        Journal on Artificial Intelligence Tools</title>, 23 (4).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pustejovsky1995" label="Pustejovsky 1995">Pustejovsky, J. (1995).
                        <title rend="italic">The Generative Lexicon</title>, 1st ed. Cambridge MA:
                    The MIT Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rouces2017" label="Rouces et al. 2017">Rouces, J., de Melo, G., Hose,
                    K. (2017). <title rend="quotes">FrameBase: Enabling integration of heterogeneous
                        knowledge</title>. <title rend="italic">Semantic Web</title>, 8(6), pp.
                    817-850.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ruimy2013" label="Ruimy et al. 2013">Ruimy, N., Piccini, S.,
                    Giovannetti, E., Bellandi, A. (2013). <title rend="quotes">Lessicografia
                        Computazionale e Terminologia Saussuriana</title>. In D. Gambarara, M.P.
                    Marchese, eds., <title rend="italic">Guida per un'edizione digitale dei
                        manoscritti di Ferdinand de Saussure</title>, Alessandria: Edizioni
                    dell'Orso.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sager1990" label="Sager 1990">Sager J. (1990). <title rend="italic">A
                        Practical Course in Terminology Processing</title>. Amsterdam: John
                    Benjamins Publishing.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="salvadores2013" label="Salvadores et al. 2013">Salvadores, M.,
                    Alexander, P.R., Musen, M.A., Noy, N.F. (2013). <title rend="quotes">Bioportal
                        as a dataset of linked biomedical ontologies and terminologies in
                        RDF</title>. <title rend="italic">Semantic Web Journal</title>, 4(3), pp.
                    277-284.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sanchezrada2014" label="Sánchez-Rada et al. 2014">Sánchez-Rada, J. F.,
                    Vulcu,G., Iglesias C. A., and Buitelaar, P. (2014). <title rend="quotes"
                        >EUROSENTIMENT: Linked data sentiment analysis</title>. In M. Horridge, M.
                    Rospocher, J. van Ossenbruggen, eds., <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                        ISWC 2014 Posters &amp; Demonstrations Track, a track within the 13th
                        International Semantic Web Conference</title> (ISWC 2014), pp.
                    145-148.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sanchezo2014" label="Sánchez Ibáñez 2014">Sánchez Ibáñez, M., García
                    Palacios, J. (2014). <title rend="quotes">Semantic characterization of terms as
                        a trace of terminological dependency</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Terminology. International Journal of Theoretical and Applied Issues in
                            Specialized Communication</title>, 20 (2), pp. 171-197.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sansone2007" label="Sansone 2007">Sansone, S. A., Scheuermann, R. H.,
                    Shah, N., Whetzel, P. L., Lewis, S. (2007). <title rend="quotes">The OBO
                        Foundry: coordinated evolution of ontologies to support biomedical data
                        integration</title>. <title rend="italic">Nature biotechnology</title>,
                    25(11), 2007:1251.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="saussure1972" label="Saussure 1972">Saussure de, F. (1972). <title
                        rend="italic">Cours de linguistique générale</title>. Edition critique
                    préparée par Tullio De Mauro, Paris: Payot.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="serasset2015" label="Sérasset 2015">Sérasset, G. (2015). <title
                        rend="quotes">DBnary: Wiktionary as a Lemon-based multilingual lexical
                        resource in RDF</title>. <title rend="italic">Semantic Web</title>, 6 (4),
                    pp. 355-361.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="slodzian2000" label="Slodzian 2000">Slodzian M. (2000). <title
                        rend="quotes">L'émergence d'une terminologie textuelle et le retour du
                        sens</title>. In H. Béjoint and Ph. Thoiron, eds., <title rend="italic">Le
                        sens en terminologie</title>, Lyon: Presse universitaire de Lyon, pp.
                    61-85.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="smith2007" label="Smith et al. 2007">Smith, B., Ashburner, M., Rosse,
                    C., Bard, J., Bug, W., Ceusters, W., Goldberg, LJ., Eilbeck, K., Ireland, A.,
                    Mungall, CJ.; OBI Consortium, Leontis, N., Rocca-Serra, P., Ruttenberg, (2007)
                        <title rend="quotes">The OBO Foundry: coordinated evolution of ontologies to
                        support biomedical data integration</title>. <title rend="italic">Nature
                            Biotechnology</title>, 25, pp. 1251-1255.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stetter1979" label="Stetter 1979">Stetter, C. (1979). <title
                        rend="quotes">La fonction des réflexions sémiologiques dans la fondation de
                        la linguistique générale chez F. de Saussure</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Kodikas-Code</title>, Gunter Narr Verlag, Tübingen, vol. 1, n° l, p.
                    12.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tappolet2009" label="Tappolet and Bernstein 2009">Tappolet, J.,
                    Bernstein, A. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Applied temporal RDF: Efficient
                        temporal querying of RDF data with SPARQL</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >European Semantic Web Conference</title>, Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer, pp.
                    308-322.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vancampenhoudt1997" label="Van Campenhoudt 1997">Van Campenhoudt, M.
                    (1997). <title rend="quotes">Maille ou maillon : quand des terminographes
                        négligent l’évolution de l’usage</title>. In A. Clas, S. Mejri, T.
                    Baccouche, eds., <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 5th scientific days
                        Réseau: Lexicologie, Terminologie, Traduction</title> (Agence Universitaire
                    de la Francophonie), <title rend="italic">La mémoire des mots</title>, Tunis,
                    pp. 251-272.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="welty2006" label="Welty et al. 2006">Welty, Ch., Fikes, R., Makarios,
                    S. (2006). <title rend="quotes">A reusable ontology for fluents in OWL</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">FOIS</title>, vol. 150, pp. 226-236.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wilkinson2016" label="Wilkinson et al. 2016">Wilkinson, M.D.,
                    Dumontier, M., Aalbersberg, I.J., Appleton, G., Axton, M., Baak, A., Blomberg N.
                    et al. (2016). <title rend="quotes">The FAIR Guiding Principles for scientific
                        data management and stewardship</title>. <title rend="italic">Scientific
                        data</title> 3.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wuster1968" label="Wüster 1968">Wüster, E. (1968). <title
                        rend="italic">The Machine Tool. An Interlingual dictionary of basic
                        concepts</title>. 1 ed., London: Technical Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zanola2014" label="Zanola 2014">Zanola, M. T. (2014). <title
                        rend="italic">Arts et métiers au XVIIIe siècle. Essais de terminologie
                        diachronique</title>. Paris: L’Harmattan.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zekri2017" label="Zekri et al. 2017">Zekri A., Brahmia, Z., Grandi,
                    F., Bouaziz, R. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Temporal schema versioning in τOWL:
                        a systematic approach for the management of time-varying knowledge</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Journal of Decision Systems</title>, 26 (2), pp.
                    113-137.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
