<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">A Model for Representing Diachronic
                    Terminologies: the Saussure Case Study</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Silvia <dhq:family>Piccini</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Institute for Computational Linguistics</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email/>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Andrea <dhq:family>Bellandi</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Institute for Computational Linguistics</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email/>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Emiliano <dhq:family>Giovannetti</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Institute for Computational Linguistics</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email/>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000549</idno>
                <idno type="volume"
                    ><!-- volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date/>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl><list>
                            <item>diachronic terminology</item>
                            <item>Semantic Web</item>
                            <item>Linked Data</item>
                            <item>N-ary model</item>
                            <item>Saussure’s terminology</item>
                            <item>lemon</item>
                            <item>OWL</item>
                        </list></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>The aim of this article is to present a model for representing in an explicit and
                    formal way the diachronic evolution of concepts and terms in a given domain, so
                    that this formalization can be machine-actionable. The approach we here propose
                    is based on Semantic Web technologies in order to guarantee interoperability and
                    reuse across scientific communities of diachronic terminological resources that
                    can be thus easily accessed, interconnected and mutually enriched. More
                    specifically, the representation of dynamic evolution of terms and concepts was
                    performed in OWL using the N-ary relations mechanisms. In addition, a set of
                    SWRL rules was set up, in order to automatically identify the evolution of the
                    concepts evoked within a text, as well as the terms representing these concepts.
                    Our model was adopted to formally represent diachronic aspects of Saussure’s
                    terminology as they emerge from his works. An example will be provided to
                    highlight the potential of such a knowledge structuration for gaining a wider
                    understanding of the profound terminological and conceptual changes brought
                    about by the paradigmatic and epistemological revolutions in sciences.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p/>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head/>
            <div>
                <head>1. Introduction</head>
                <p>Πάντα ῥεῖ. Everything is subjected to the inexorable law of change: the reality,
                    the categories through which we organize it and the words we use to talk about
                    it.</p>
                <p>This is particularly the case for the history of science. Over the centuries,
                    scholars have built different theoretical models in response to the continuous
                    innovation that emerged from observation sometimes producing a real scientific
                    revolution in the worldview. Needless to say, a change in conceptual level often
                    corresponds to a change in terminology<note>The term terminology is here to be
                        understood as the set of <quote rend="inline">lexical items belonging to
                            specialized areas of usage of one or more languages</quote>
                        <ptr target="#sager1990" loc="2"/>.</note>: new terms can be introduced to
                    express the new system of concepts or old terms can be dismissed when the
                    concept becomes obsolete.</p>
                <p>The aim of this article is to present a model for formally representing the
                    diachronic evolution of concepts and terms in a given domain, so that this
                    formalization can be machine-actionable. Taking advantage from past experiences
                    conducted in the context of several projects<note><title rend="quotes">Clavius
                            on the Web</title>
                        <ptr target="#piccini2016"/>, <quote rend="inline">Per un'edizione digitale
                            dei manoscritti di Ferdinand de Saussure</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ruimy2013"/>, and <title rend="quotes">Totus Mundus</title>
                        <ptr target="#piccini2017"/>.</note>, we propose here an approach based on
                    Semantic Web technologies that guarantees interoperability and reuse of
                    diachronic terminological resources across scientific communities.</p>
                <p>The development of standards for representing and exchanging data has always been
                    a concern in the terminological field. Interoperability across terminological
                    formats is basically ensured by adopting the ISO standard 30042: 2008 TBX
                    (TermBase eXchange), an XML-based family of terminology exchange formats
                    compliant with the Terminological Markup Framework (TMF - ISO 16642: 2003).</p>
                <p>Over the last few years, interesting solutions for interoperability have been
                    offered by the Semantic Web technologies and Linked data initiative which allow
                    data to be shared, reused across applications and linked with the resources
                    available on the Web, thus benefiting from the whole datacloud of URIs with
                    which reference resources like DBPedia are already networked.</p>
                <p>In terminology, there has been a growing trend towards representing and
                    publishing terminological resources on the Semantic Web according to Linked Data
                    principles, as demonstrated for example by the NCBO (National Center for
                    Biomedical Ontology) BioPortal, a repository of more than 300 biomedical
                    ontologies and terminologies converted into RDF <ptr target="#salvadores2013"/>;
                    or by the Open Biomedical Ontologies (OBO) consortium <ptr target="#smith2007"/>
                    aiming to create a family of new or extant ontologies based on shared principles
                    compliant with the Semantic Web technologies.</p>
                <p>These and other similar initiatives are all driven by the same need, namely to
                    avoid that terminologies, created by proprietary software, exist independently
                    of each other, hidden in isolated databases. The lack of semantic
                    interoperability, indeed, precludes any possibility of progress, as medical data
                    can be exploited to their full potential only if they are interconnected to each
                    other. Sharing large quantities of data structured in ontologies makes it
                    possible to use IT applications and artificial intelligence systems, enabling
                    thus better diagnostics, early disease prevention and, more generally, a deeper
                    understanding of the human biology and health.</p>
                <p>Another initiative deserving to be mentioned is the Eurovoc management based on
                    technologies in line with W3C recommendations and with the latest developments
                    in classification standards. A collaborative project started in 2019 and
                    undertaken by the Publications Office of the European Union and the
                    International Labour Office <ptr target="#dechandon2019"/> aims to align EuroVoc
                    with other controlled vocabularies and publish them as Linked Open Data. The
                    objective is to improve data accessibility and guarantee large-scale
                    interoperability, thus facilitating the authoring-translating-publishing chain
                    as well as the work in public administrations and international
                    organisations.</p>
                <p>Finally, Cimiano et al. (<ref target="#cimiano2015">2015</ref>) proposed an
                    approach to convert terminological datasets originally stored in TBX format to
                    RDF by means of an online service named TBX2RDF, allowing thereby terminological
                    resources to be used and enhanced across different scientific communities and,
                    in particular, to become part of the great Linguistic Linked (Open) Data cloud
                    (see <foreign>infra</foreign>).</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, as we shall see, using these technologies to represent the
                    diachronic evolution of terminological and conceptual data constitutes an
                    interesting challenge, since OWL (Web Ontology Language), the W3C standard
                    language developed to represent ontologies in the Semantic Web, is fundamentally
                    static and monotonic.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. Terminology and diachrony</head>
                <p>In the terminological literature, the diachronic dimension has been neglected for
                    a long time. This was mainly due to the onomasiological, prescriptive and static
                    approach underlying the General Theory of Terminology (GTT) elaborated by Wüster
                    in 1968.</p>
                <p>Wüster’s approach to terminology was based on a neo-positivist referential and
                    taxonomic semiotics <ptr target="#slodzian2000"/>, according to which concepts
                    take precedence over words. In GTT terms are monosemic and concepts are
                    monoreferential; a perfect correspondence is established between them: each
                    concept corresponds to one and only one term. The term is thus equivalent to a
                    symbol, to a <quote rend="inline">désignateur rigide</quote>
                    <ptr target="#kripke1995"/>, since it works in much the same way as the system
                    of proper names works in general language. Conceptual structures, on the other
                    hand, are regarded as universal and static like their referents and any
                    diachronic dimension is neutralised.</p>
                <p>In outlining the theoretical and methodological differences between lexicology
                    and terminology, Cabré (<ref target="#cabre1999">1999: 8</ref>) emphasized that
                    terminology is only concerned with synchronic aspects: <quote rend="block">This
                        view, which today is considered the most systematic, coherent theoretical
                        approach to terms, differs from lexicological theory in three ways: in the
                        priority of the concept over the designation; in being exclusively concerned
                        with the level of the terminological unit and not with the other levels of
                        linguistic description; in excluding any diachronic approach of
                        information.</quote></p>
                <p>Terminology began to open up to diachrony timidly after the <quote rend="inline"
                        >odyssée terminotique</quote>
                    <ptr target="#slodzian2000"/> of the 80s, when an impressive number of term
                    banks, based on the synchronic traditional vision of the Viennese school, were
                    produced and spread (EURODICATOAM, NORMATERM, UNITERM, TERMIUM, IATE etc.).</p>
                <p>In 1988 a symposium entitled <title rend="quotes">Terminologie
                        diachronique</title> was organized by the Centre de Terminology of
                    Bruxelles, but ten years after Møller (1998) still regretted a <quote
                        rend="inline">quantitative and / or qualitative deficit</quote> in that
                    branch of terminology for which he coined the neologism
                        <soCalled>terminochronie</soCalled>.</p>
                <p>Over the last twenty years several studies have been conducted focussing on the
                    evolution of concepts and terms in specialized languages (see inter al. <ref
                        target="#vancampenhoudt1997">van Campenhoudt 1997</ref>, <ref
                        target="#dury2008">Dury 2008</ref>, <ref target="#zanola2014">Zanola
                        2014</ref>, <ref target="#kristiansen2014">Kristiansen 2014</ref>), as well
                    as on methods for compiling diachronic corpora <ptr target="#dury2004"/> and
                    identifying the evolution of knowledge in corpora <ptr target="#picton2009"
                    />.</p>
                <p>As underlined by Dury and Picton (<ref target="#dury2009">2009</ref>), this lack
                    of interest for diachronic aspects in terminology was mainly due to technical,
                    pragmatic, psychological, and most of all theoretical and historical
                    obstacles.</p>
                <p>Diachronic terminology is, indeed, by definition a textual terminology <ptr
                        target="#bourigault1999"/>
                    <ptr target="#pearson1998"/>, a terminology of <soCalled>discourse</soCalled>.
                    Terms must be analysed in their real context of use and must not be be seen as
                    abstract and static labels associated with concepts. They should be rather
                    regarded as linguistic signs, which enter into a dynamic relationship both with
                    the concepts and with the other linguistic signs that constitute the
                    terminological system.</p>
                <p>In a diachronic perspective, terminological work is fundamentally semasiological
                    and descriptive. In order to grasp terminological variation over time, the
                    starting point is the sense that a term acquires within a real linguistic
                    context and the focus is on language as it is actually used
                        (<foreign>Ist-Norm</foreign>), in real specialised (con-)texts and not on
                    language as it should be used (<foreign>Soll-Norm</foreign>). To use Bourigault
                    and Slodzian words (<ref target="#bourigault1999">1999: 31</ref>), <quote
                        rend="inline">le texte est le point de départ de la description lexicale à
                        construire. On va du texte vers le terme</quote>.</p>
                <p>Texts are usually the unique source that the scholars have at their disposal in
                    order to access disappeared states of languages and more completely understand
                    the history of terms and their evolution over time. Texts play a crucial role to
                    establish when and how words acquire (terminologization) and lose
                    (determinologization) their terminological status, or how a term passes from one
                    specialized field to another or from the intimate pages of a scholar to the
                    entire scientific community.</p>
                <p>Regarding this last aspect, in particular, texts constitute a precious means to
                    record the typical terminological fluctuation that precedes or follows the
                    formation of the so-called <soCalled>normal science</soCalled> state.</p>
                <p>As a matter of fact, in a phase of <soCalled>normal science</soCalled>, when the
                    development is adherent to what Kuhn (<ref target="#kuhn1970">1970</ref>) calls
                        <soCalled>paradigm</soCalled>, the system of terms is standard, explicitly
                    defined and consensually used within a scientific community.</p>
                <p>In revolutionary phases, on the contrary, when a revision of existing scientific
                    beliefs or practices is involved, terminology can be characterized by great
                    instability. Texts become thus a conceptual and terminological space of
                    creativity, where scholars think, reflect and give a linguistic form to their
                    ideas. In these cases, ephemeral lexical formations are often attested only in
                    the idiolect of the one who forged them without ever taking root within the
                    scientific community.</p>
                <p>An example of this phenomenon will be illustrated in Section 6 with Saussure’s
                    terminology.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> 3. Modelling an Interoperable Terminological Resource</head>
                <p>When modelling a digital scholarly resource, the key point is to choose a model
                    capable of maximizing its usefulness in the community of reference. According to
                    the <title rend="quotes">FAIR guidelines</title>, scholarly data should be
                    Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable <ptr target="#wilkinson2016"
                    />. First of all, for data to be findable, they must be referred to using a
                    globally unique and persistent identifier and must also be indexed in a
                    searchable resource. Furthermore, data must be accessible through a standardized
                    protocol and, at the same time, has to be interoperable in virtue of its
                    representation in a formal and shared knowledge representation language.
                    Finally, to be reusable, data must be <quote rend="inline">described with a
                        plurality of accurate and relevant attributes</quote> (<ref
                        target="#wilkinson2016">ibidem: 4</ref>).</p>
                <p>In order to pursue the FAIR policies and to build fair diachronic terminological
                    resources, our choice was to adopt the paradigms of Semantic Web technologies
                        <ptr target="#bernerslee2001"/> and Linked Data <ptr target="#bizer2011"
                    />.</p>
                <p>The intuition behind the Semantic Web is to shift from a Web of documents, viewed
                    as separate data silos containing unstructured or semi-structured data, to a Web
                    of data where open repositories of semantically enriched data can be accessed
                    and interlinked. To make this vision concrete, the following technologies -
                    often referred to as the Semantic Web layer cake or Semantic Web technology -
                    are used: Resource Description Framework<note><ref
                            target="https://www.w3.org/RDF/">https://www.w3.org/RDF/</ref></note>
                    (RDF), RDF Schema (RDFS), Web Ontology Language (OWL), Semantic Web Rule
                    Language (SWRL) and SPARQL Protocol and RDF Query Language (SPARQL).</p>
                <p>Semantic Web and Linked Data best practices require datasets to be published
                    using RDF: data is described as triples in the form of Subject - Predicate -
                    Object, where the Subject is a resource, the Object can be either a resource or
                    a data value (such as a string of character or a number), and the Predicate
                    (also called <soCalled>property</soCalled>) relates the Subject and the Object
                    together. Basically, a dataset in the Linked Data world is a set of triples.</p>
                <p>OWL is a family of languages, based on RDF/XML, and recommended by the World Wide
                    Web Consortium since 2004 for representing and sharing ontologies<note>According
                        to Gruber (<ref target="#gruber1993">1993: 199</ref>), <quote rend="inline"
                            >an ontology is a specification of a conceptualization</quote>.</note>
                    on the Web. There are three variants of OWL, with different levels of
                    expressiveness: OWL Lite, which supports a classification hierarchy and simple
                    constraints; OWL DL, which provides the maximum expressiveness while retaining
                    computational completeness and decidability, and OWL Full which allows for
                    maximum expressiveness, resulting nonetheless undecidable.</p>
                <p>In order to publish structured data on the Web in a way that they can be easily
                    linked to each other, a number of rules was set up by Berners-Lee, known as
                    Linked Data principles. According to them, each entity of a dataset must be
                    uniquely identified by a special <soCalled>address</soCalled> called URI
                    (Uniform Resource Identifier), each URI must be available on the Web via the
                    HTTP protocol<note><ref
                            target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypertext_Transfer_Protocol"
                            >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypertext_Transfer_Protocol</ref></note>,
                    each look up of a URI must be answered with useful information and using
                    standards, and finally, whenever possible, data should be linked to other
                    data.</p>
                <p>Over the last years, the Linked Data approach has attracted the attention of a
                    linguistic community becoming more and more sensitive to the question of
                    interoperability between resources. An increasing number of openly available and
                    interconnected linguistic datasets have been published as part of the Web of
                    data, resulting in the so-called Linked Open Data Cloud (LLOD). This trend,
                    nicely visualised in <ref target="https://lod-cloud.net"
                        >https://lod-cloud.net</ref>, is particularly boosted by the Ontology
                    Lexicon (Ontolex) community group, whose activity resulted in the creation of
                            lemon<note><ref target="https://lemon-model.net/"
                            >https://lemon-model.net/</ref>. The <title rend="italic">lemon</title> model has
                        been further developed into the <title rend="italic">OntoLex-lemon</title>
                        model by the W3C Ontolex Community group. For details, see McCrae et al.
                        (2017)</note> (Lexicon Model for Ontologies), a meta-model allowing lexical
                    resources to be published in RDF, linked and shared according to Semantic Web
                    principles. At present <title rend="italic">lemon</title> constitutes a standard de facto, as it is grounded
                    on W3C and ISO standards, such as LMF (Lexical Markup Framework) (Francopoulo et
                    al. 2006), Lexinfo (Cimiano et al. 2011) – this latter aligned with ISOCat - and
                    LIR (Linguistic Information Repository) (Montiel-Ponsoda et al. 2008).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="allen1983" label="Allen 1983">Allen, J. (1983). Maintaing knowledge
                    about temporal intervals. Communications of the ACM, 26(11), pp. 832–843.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="arauz2012" label="Aráuz et al. 2012">Aráuz L., Faber, P. and Montero
                    Martínez, S. (2012). Specialized Language Semantics. In: P. Faber, ed., A
                    cognitive linguistics view of terminology and specialized language,
                    Series:Applications of Cognitive Linguistics [ACL] 20, 1st ed. Berlin, Boston:
                    De Gruyter Mouton, pp. 95-175.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="artale2000" label="Artale and Franconi 2000">Artale, A. and Franconi,
                    E. (2000). A survey of temporal extensions of description logics. Annals of
                    Mathematics and Artificial Intelligence, 30 (1-4), pp. 171-210.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="baader2003" label="Baader et al. 2003">Baader, F., Calvanese, D.,
                    McGuinness, D., Patel-Schneider, P., Nardi, D. (2003). The description logic
                    handbook: Theory, implementation and applications. Cambridge: Cambridge
                    University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="baader2001" label="Baader and Sattler 2001">Baader, F. and Sattler U.
                    (2001). An overview of tableau algorithms for description logics. Studia Logica,
                    69 (1), pp. 5-40.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="batsakis2017" label="Batsakis et al. 2017">Batsakis, S., Petrakis E.,
                    Tachmazidis, I. and Antoniou, G. (2017). Temporal representation and reasoning
                    in OWL 2. Semantic Web, 8 (6), pp. 981-1000.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bellandi2017a" label="Bellandi et al. 2017a">Bellandi, A., Boschetti,
                    F., Khan, F., Del Grosso, A.M. and Monachini, M. (2017). Provando e riprovando
                    modelli di dizionario storico digitale: Collegare voci, citazioni,
                    interpretazioni. Proceedings of the AIUCD, pp. 119–125.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ballandi2017b" label="Bellandi et al. 2017b">Bellandi, A.,
                    Giovannetti, E., Piccini, S., Weingart, A. (2017). Developing LexO: A
                    Collaborative Editor of Multilingual Lexica and Termino-ontological Resources in
                    the Humanities. In F. Frontini, L. Grčić Simeunović, Š. Vintar, F. Khan, A.,
                    Parvisieds., eds., Proceedings of Language, Ontology, Terminology and Knowledge
                    Structures Workshop (LOTKS 2017), pp. 86-95.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bellandi2018" label="Bellandi et al. 2018">Bellandi, A., Giovannetti,
                    E., Weingart, A. (2018). Multilingual and Multiword Phenomena in a lemon Old
                    Occitan Medico-Botanical Lexicon. Information 9 (3), 52.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="benveniste1964" label="Benveniste 1964">Benveniste, E. (1964). Lettres
                    de F. de Saussure à A. Meillet. Cahiers Ferdinand de Saussure, 21, pp.
                    89-130.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bernerslee2001" label="Berners-Lee et al. 2001">Berners-Lee, T.,
                    Hendler, J., Lassila, O. (2001). The semantic web. Scientific American, 284(5),
                    pp. 34-43.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bizer2011" label="Bizer et al. 2011">Bizer, Ch., Heath, T.,
                    Berners-Lee, T. (2011). Linked data: The story so far. In Amit Sheth, ed.,
                    Semantic services, interoperability and web applications: emerging concepts, 1st
                    ed., Hershey, Pennsylvania: IGI Global, pp. 205-227.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bourigault1999" label="Bourigault and Slodzian 1999">Bourigault D.,
                    Slodzian M. (1999). Pour une terminologie textuelle. Terminologies nouvelles 19,
                    pp. 29-32.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="buitelaar2010" label="Buitelaar 2010">Buitelaar, P. (2010).
                    Ontology-based Semantic Lexicons: Mapping between Terms and Object Descriptions,
                    In C. Huang, N. Calzolari, A. Gangemi, A. Lenci, A. Oltramari, &amp; L. Prevot,
                    eds., Ontology and the Lexicon: A Natural Language Processing Perspective.
                    Studies in Natural Language Processing.Cambridge: Cambridge University Press,
                    pp. 212-223.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cabre1999" label="Cabré 1999">Cabré, M. T. (1999). Terminology:
                    Theory, Methods and Applications. Amsterdam: John Benjamins Publishing.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="calvanese2001" label="Calvanese et al. 2001">Calvanese, D., De
                    Giacomo,G., Lenzerini, M. Nardi, D. (2001). Reasoning in Expressive Description
                    Logics. Handbook of automated reasoning 2, pp. 1581-1634.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="carlyle2011" label="Carlyle 2011">Carlyle, A. (2011). Understanding
                    FRBR as a conceptual model.Library Resources &amp; Technical Services, 50 (4),
                    pp. 264-273.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cimiano2011" label="Cimiano et al. 2011">Cimiano, P., Buitelaar, P.,
                    McCrae, J., Sintek, M. (2011). Lexinfo: A declarative model for the
                    lexicon-ontology interface. Web Semantics: Science, Services and Agents on the
                    World Wide Web 9 (1), pp. 29-51.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cimiano2015" label="Cimiano et al. 2015">Cimiano, P., McCrae, J.P.,
                    Rodríguez-Doncel, V., Gornostay, T., Gómez-Pérez, A., Siemoneit, B., Lagzdins,
                    A. (2015). Linked terminology: applying linked data principles to terminological
                    resources. In Kosem, I., Jakubíček, M., Kallas, J., Krek, S., eds., Electronic
                    lexicography in the 21st century: linking lexical data in the digital age.
                    Proceedings of the eLex 2015 conference, 11-13 August 2015, Herstmonceux Castle,
                    United Kingdom. Ljubljana/Brighton: Trojina, Institute for Applied Slovene
                    Studies/Lexical Computing Ltd, , Sussex, UK, pp. 504-517.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cosenza2016" label="Cosenza 2016">Cosenza, G. (2016). Dalle parole ai
                    termini. I percorsi di pensiero di F. de Saussure. Alessandria. Edizioni
                    dell’Orso. Collezione “Studi e Ricerche”.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dechandon2019" label="Dechandon et al. 2019">Dechandon, D., Gerencsér,
                    A., Ruiz, M.R. (2019). Terminology: Towards a Systematic Integration of
                    Semantics and Metadata. In Translating and the Computer 41, Proceedings of
                    AsLing (The International Association for Advancement in Language Technology),
                    Geneva: Editions Tradulex.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="delgratta2015" label="Del Gratta et al. 2015">Del Gratta, R.,
                    Frontini, F., Khan, F., Monachini, M. (2015). Converting the PAROLE SIMPLE CLIPS
                    Lexicon into RDF with lemon. Semantic Web, 6 (4), pp. 387-392.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dury2004" label="Dury 2004">Dury, P. (2004). Building a Bilingual
                    Diachronic Corpus of Ecology: The Long Road to Completion. Icame Journal, 28,
                    pp. 5-16.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dury2008" label="Dury 2008">Dury, P. (2008). The rise of carbon
                    neutral and compensation carbone: A diachronic investigation into the migration
                    of vocabulary from the language of ecology to newspaper language and vice versa.
                    Terminology, 14(2), pp. 230-248.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dury2009" label="Dury and Picton 2009">Dury, P, Picton, A. (2009).
                    Terminologie et diachronie: vers une réconciliation théorique et
                    méthodologique?. Revue française de linguistique appliquée, 14 (2), pp.
                    31-41.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ecklekohler2015" label="Eckle-Kohler 2015">Eckle-Kohler, J., McCrae,
                    J.P., Chiarcos, Ch. (2015). LemonUby–A large, interlinked, syntactically-rich
                    lexical resource for ontologies. Semantic Web, 6 (4), pp. 371-378.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ehrmann2014" label="Ehrmann et al. 2014">Ehrmann, M., Cecconi, F.,
                    Vannella, D., Mccrae, J.P., Cimiano, P., Navigli, R. (2014). Representing
                    Multilingual Data as Linked Data: the Case of BabelNet 2.0. In N. Calzolari, K.
                    Choukri, T. Declerck, H. Loftsson, B. Maegaard, J. Mariani, A. Moreno, J. Odijk,
                    S. Piperidis, eds., Proceedings of LREC 2014, pp. 401–408.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="engler1968" label="Engler 1968">Engler, R. (1968). Lexique de la
                    terminologie saussurienne. Utrecht-Anvers: Spectrum. Comité international
                    permanent des linguistes. Publication de la commission de terminologie.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fenoglio2012" label="Fenoglio 2012">Fenoglio, I. (2012). Genèse du
                    geste linguistique : une complexité heuristique. Genesis [En ligne], 35, pp.
                    13-40. DOI : 10.4000/genesis.1033.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="flouris2008" label="Flouris et al. 2008">Flouris, G., Manakanatas D.,
                    Kondylakis H., Plexousakis D., Antoniou G. (2008). Ontology Change:
                    Classification and Survey. The Knowledge Engineering Review, 23, pp.
                    117–52.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="francopoulo2006" label="Francopoulo et al. 2006">Francopoulo, G.,
                    George, M., Calzolari, N., Monachini, M., Bel, N., Pet, M., Soria, C. (2006).
                    Lexical markup framework (LMF). Proceedings of the Fifth International
                    Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation LREC 2006, Genova, pp.
                    233-236.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gambarara2009" label="Gambarara 2009">Gambarara, D. (2009).
                    Présentation de section II “Système et cognition. Quaternion et parallélie dans
                    De l’Essence double du langage”. Cahiers Ferdinand de Saussure, 61, pp.
                    75-86.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="godel1957" label="Godel 1957">Godel, R. (1957). Les sources
                    manuscrites du Cours de linguistique générale de Ferdinand de Saussure. Genève:
                    Droz.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="grandi2009" label="Grandi 2009">Grandi, F. (2009). Multi-temporal RDF
                    ontology versioning. In M. d'Aquin, G. Antoniou, eds., Proceedings of the 3rd
                    International Workshop on Ontology Dynamics (IWOD-09), collocated with the 8th
                    International Semantic Web Conference (ISWC-2009), Washington DC, USA, October
                    26, 2009.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gruber1991" label="Gruber 1991">Gruber, T. R. (1991). A translation
                    approach to portable ontologies. Knowledge Acquisition, vol. V (2), pp.
                    199-220.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kanmani2016" label="Kanmani 2016">Kanmani, A. Clara, T. Chockalingam,
                    and N. Guruprasad. (2016). RDF data model and its multi reification approaches:
                    A comprehensive comparative analysis. In Inventive Computation Technologies
                    (ICICT), International Conference on, vol. 1, pp. 1-5. IEEE.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="khan2016" label="Khan et al. 2016">Khan, F., Bellandi, A., Monachini,
                    M. (2016). Tools and Instruments for Building and Querying Diachronic
                    Computational Lexica. In Proceedings of the Workshop on Language Technology
                    Resources and Tools for Digital Humanities (LT4DH), Osaka, Japan: The COLING
                    2016 Organizing Committee, pp. 164-171.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="khan2014" label="Khan et al. 2014">Khan, F., Boschetti, F., Frontini,
                    F. (2014). Using lemon to model lexical semantic shift in diachronic lexical
                    resources. In Ch. Chiarcos, J. Ph. McCrae, P. Osenova, C. Vertan, eds., 3rd.
                    Workshop on Linked Data in Linguistics: Multilingual Knowledge Resources and
                    Natural Language Processing, p. 50.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="khan2017" label="Khan et al. 2017">Khan, F., Bowers, J., Frontini, F.
                    (2017). Situating Word Senses in their Historical Context with Linked Data. In
                    C. Gardent, Ch. Retoré, eds., IWCS 2017—12th International Conference on
                    Computational Semantics—Short papers.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kuhn1970" label="Kuhn 1970">Kuhn, T.S. (1970). The structure of
                    scientific revolutions. 2nd ed., Chicago: The University of Chicago
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="klein2001" label="Klein and Fensel 2001">Klein, M. CA., Fensel, D.
                    (2001). Ontology versioning on the Semantic Web. Proceedings of the First
                    International Conference on Semantic Web Working. California: CEUR-WS.org, pp.
                    75-91.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kripke1995" label="Kripke 1995">Kripke, S. (1995). La logique des noms
                    propres. Paris: Les Editions de Minuit.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kristiansen2014" label="Kristiansen 2014">Kristiansen M. (2014).
                    Concept change, term dynamics and culture-boundness in economic-administrative
                    domains. In R. Temmermann and M. van Campenhoudt, eds., Dynamics and
                    terminology: an interdisciplinary perspective on monolingual and multilingual
                    culture-bound communication. Terminology and lexicography research and practice,
                    volume 16, Amsterdam; Philadelphia: John Benjamins Publishing Company, pp.
                    235-256.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kroeger2013" label="Kroeger 2013">Kroeger, A. (2013). The road to
                    BIBFRAME: the evolution of the idea of bibliographic transition into a post-MARC
                    Future. Cataloging &amp; classification quarterly, 51 (8), pp. 873-890.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lacy2005" label="Lacy 2005">Lacy, L.W. (2005). Owl: Representing
                    Information Using the Web Ontology Language. Victoria, BC, Canada: Trafford
                    Publishing.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lenci2000" label="Lenci et al. 2000">Lenci, A., Bel, N., Busa, F.,
                    Calzolari, N., Gola, E., Monachini, M., Ogonowski, A., Peters, I., Peters, W.,
                    Ruimy, N., Villegas, M., Zampolli, A. (2000). SIMPLE: A General Framework for
                    the development of Multilingual Lexicons. International Journal of Lexicography,
                    13 (4). Special issue ‘Dictionaries, Thesauri and Lexical-Semantic Relations’,
                    pp. 249-263.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lutz2008" label="Lutz et al. 2008">Lutz, C., Wolter, F.,
                    Zakharyaschev, M. (2008). Temporal Description Logics: A Survey. TIME, pp.
                    3-14.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="makri2011" label="Makri 2011">Makri, P. (2011). 4D-Fluents Plug-In: A
                    Tool for Handling Temporal Ontologies in Protégé. Diss. Diploma Thesis.
                    Department of Electronic and Computer Engineering, Technical University of
                    Crete.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mccrae2014" label="McCrae et al. 2014">McCrae, J.P., Fellbaum, C.,
                    Cimiano, P. (2014). Publishing and linking WordNet using lemon and RDF.
                    Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop on Linked Data in Linguistics.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mccrae2017" label="McCrae et al. 2017">McCrae, J. P., Bosque-Gil, J.,
                    Gracia, J., Buitelaar, P., &amp; Cimiano, P. The OntoLexLemon Model: Development
                    and Applications. In I. Kosem, C. Tiberius, M. Jakubíček, J. Kallas, S. Krek, V.
                    Baisa, eds, Electronic lexicography in the 21st century. Proceedings of eLex
                    2017 conference, September 19-21, Leiden, Netherlands. Lexical Computing CZ
                    s.R.O, Brno, Czech Republic, pp. 19-21.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="montiel2008" label="Montiel-Ponsoda 2008">Montiel-Ponsoda, E., Aguado
                    de Cea, G., Gómez-Pérez, A., Peters, W. (2008). Modelling multilinguality in
                    ontologies. Proceedings of the 21st International Conference on Computational
                    Linguistics (COLING).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moller1998" label="Møller 1998">Møller, B. (1998). A la recherche
                    d’une terminochronie. Meta, XLIII-3, pp. 1-13</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pearson1998" label="Pearson 1998">Pearson, J. (1998). Terms in
                    Context, Studies in Corpus Linguistic. Vol. I, 1 ed., Amsterdam/Philadelphia:
                    John Benjamins.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piccini2016" label="Piccini 2016">Piccini, S. (2016). CLAVIUS: verso
                    la modellazione di una risorsa termino-ontologica diacronica del dominio
                    matematico-astronomico del XVII secolo. Atti del XXVI Convegno internazionale
                    Ass.I.Term “Terminologia e organizzazione della conoscenza nella conservazione
                    della memoria digitale”. 14 – 16 April 2016. Rende (Italy).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piccini2017" label="Piccini 2017">Piccini, S., Corsi, E., Giovannetti,
                    E. (2017). Une ressource termino-ontologique bilingue chinois-italien: le cas de
                    la traduction de la Mappemonde de Matteo Ricci par Pasquale D’Elia. Proceedings
                    of the Conference TOTh 2017 Terminology &amp; Ontology: Theories and
                    applications, 8-9 June 2017, University of Savoie, Chambéry, France.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piccini2018" label="Piccini 2018">Piccini, S., Bellandi, A.,
                    Giovannetti, E. (2018). A Semantic Web Approach to Modelling and Building a
                    Bilingual Chinese-Italian Termino-ontological Resource. In A. Čibej, V. Gorjanc,
                    I. Kosem, S. Krek, eds., The XVIII EURALEX International Congress: Lexicography
                    in Global Contexts Book of Abstracts, 17-21 July 2018, Ljubljana, Slovenia, pp.
                    87-90.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="picton2009" label="Picton 2009">Picton, A. (2009). Diachronie en
                    langue de spécialité. Définition d'une méthode linguistique outillée pour
                    repérer l'évolution des connaissances en corpus. Un exemple appliqué au domaine
                    spatial. PhD. Dissertation. Toulouse 2.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="preventis2014" label="Preventis et al. 2014">Preventis, A., Petrakis,
                    E., Batsakis, S. (2014). Chronos Ed: A tool for handling temporal ontologies in
                    Protégé. International Journal on Artificial Intelligence Tools, 23 (4).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pustejovsky1995" label="Pustejovsky 1995">Pustejovsky, J. (1995). The
                    Generative Lexicon, 1st ed. Cambridge MA: The MIT Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rouces2017" label="Rouces et al. 2017">Rouces, J., de Melo, G., Hose,
                    K. (2017). FrameBase: Enabling integration of heterogeneous knowledge. Semantic
                    Web, 8(6), pp. 817-850.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ruimy2013" label="Ruimy et al. 2013">Ruimy, N., Piccini, S.,
                    Giovannetti, E., Bellandi, A. (2013). Lessicografia Computazionale e
                    Terminologia Saussuriana. In D. Gambarara, M.P. Marchese, eds., Guida per
                    un'edizione digitale dei manoscritti di Ferdinand de Saussure, Alessandria:
                    Edizioni dell'Orso.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sager1990" label="Sager 1990">Sager J. (1990). A Practical Course in
                    Terminology Processing, Amsterdam: John Benjamins Publishing.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="salvadores2013" label="Salvadores et al. 2013">Salvadores, M.,
                    Alexander, P.R., Musen, M.A., Noy, N.F. (2013). Bioportal as a dataset of linked
                    biomedical ontologies and terminologies in RDF. Semantic Web Journal, 4(3), pp.
                    277–284.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sanchezrada2014" label="Sánchez-Rada et al. 2014">Sánchez-Rada, J. F.,
                    Vulcu,G., Iglesias C. A., and Buitelaar, P. (2014). EUROSENTIMENT: Linked data
                    sentiment analysis. In Matthew Horridge; M. Rospocher, J. van Ossenbruggen,
                    eds., Proceedings of the ISWC 2014 Posters &amp; Demonstrations Track, a track
                    within the 13th International Semantic Web Conference (ISWC 2014), pp.
                    145-148.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sanchezo2014" label="Sánchez Ibáñez 2014">Sánchez Ibáñez, M., García
                    Palacios, J. (2014). Semantic characterization of terms as a trace of
                    terminological dependency, in Terminology. International Journal of Theoretical
                    and Applied Issues in Specialized Communication, 20 (2), pp. 171 - 197.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sansone2007" label="Sansone 2007">Sansone, SA., Scheuermann, RH.,
                    Shah, N., Whetzel, PL., Lewis, S. (2007). The OBO Foundry: coordinated evolution
                    of ontologies to support biomedical data integration. Nature biotechnology,
                    25(11), 2007:1251.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="saussure1972" label="Saussure 1972">Saussure de, F. (1972). Cours de
                    linguistique générale. Edition critique préparée par Tullio De Mauro, Paris:
                    Payot.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="serasset2015" label="Sérasset 2015">Sérasset, G. (2015). DBnary:
                    Wiktionary as a Lemon-based multilingual lexical resource in RDF. Semantic Web,
                    6 (4), pp. 355-361.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="slodzian2000" label="Slodzian 2000">Slodzian M. (2000). L'émergence
                    d'une terminologie textuelle et le retour du sens. In H. Béjoint and Ph.
                    Thoiron, eds., Le sens en terminologie, Lyon: Presse universitaire de Lyon, pp.
                    61-85.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="smith2007" label="Smith et al. 2007">Smith, B., Ashburner, M., Rosse,
                    C., Bard, J., Bug, W., Ceusters, W., Goldberg, LJ., Eilbeck, K., Ireland, A.,
                    Mungall, CJ.; OBI Consortium, Leontis, N., Rocca-Serra, P., Ruttenberg, (2007)
                    The OBO Foundry: coordinated evolution of ontologies to support biomedical data
                    integration. Nature Biotechnology, 25, pp. 1251–1255.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stetter1979" label="Stetter 1979">Stetter, C. (1979). La fonction des
                    réflexions sémiologiques dans la fondation de la linguistique générale chez F.
                    de Saussure. Kodikas-Code, Gunter Narr Verlag, Tübingen, vol. 1, n° l, p.
                    12.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tappolet2009" label="Tappolet and Bernstein 2009">Tappolet, J.,
                    Bernstein, A. (2009). Applied temporal RDF: Efficient temporal querying of RDF
                    data with SPARQL. European Semantic Web Conference, Berlin, Heidelberg:
                    Springer, pp. 308-322.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vancampenhoudt1997" label="Van Campenhoudt 1997">Van Campenhoudt, M.
                    (1997). Maille ou maillon : quand des terminographes négligent l’évolution de
                    l’usage. In A. Clas, S. Mejri, T. Baccouche, eds., Proceedings of the 5th
                    scientific days Réseau: Lexicologie, Terminologie, Traduction (Agence
                    Universitaire de la Francophonie), La mémoire des mots, Tunis,
                    Tunisia,251-272.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="welty2006" label="Welty et al. 2006">Welty, Ch., Fikes, R., Makarios,
                    S. (2006). A reusable ontology for fluents in OWL.FOIS, vol. 150, pp.
                    226-236.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wilkinson2016" label="Wilkinson et al. 2016">Wilkinson, M.D.,
                    Dumontier, M., Aalbersberg, I.J., Appleton, G., Axton, M., Baak, A., Blomberg N.
                    et al. (2016). The FAIR Guiding Principles for scientific data management and
                    stewardship. Scientific data 3.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wuster1968" label="Wüster 1968">Wüster, E. (1968). The Machine Tool.
                    An Interlingual dictionary of basic concepts. 1 ed., London: Technical
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zanola2014" label="Zanola 2014">Zanola, M. T. (2014). Arts et métiers
                    au XVIIIe siècle. Essais de terminologie diachronique. Paris:
                    L’Harmattan.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zekri2017" label="Zekri et al. 2017">Zekri A., Brahmia, Z., Grandi,
                    F., Bouaziz, R. (2017). Temporal schema versioning in τOWL: a systematic
                    approach for the management of time-varying knowledge. Journal of Decision
                    Systems, 26 (2), pp. 113-137.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
