<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!-- article title in English --></title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>first name(s) <dhq:family>family name</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID"><!-- if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000 --></idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation></dhq:affiliation>
                    <email></email>
                    <dhq:bio><p></p></dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            	
            	<!-- This information should be added when the file is created -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000774</idno>

            	
            	<!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="volume"><!-- volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date><!-- include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024 --></date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
<!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->                    
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            	<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
            		<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
            	</taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/wiki/DHQ-Topic-Keywords; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                	
                	<!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new <term> element for each -->
                    <term corresp=""/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item></item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            	<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
            		<list type="simple">
            			<item></item>
            		</list>
            	</keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
        	<!-- Replace "XXXXXX" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
        	<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target=
        		"https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000774/000774.xml">GitHub
        	</ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                
                <p>The present paper reports a pilot study to approach the sub- text in Chekhov’s short-story ”Ward No. 6” by means of informa- tion theory. 
                    The original text is enriched by glosses by which we intend to make explicit the implicit knowledge conveyed by the original text, i.e., the subtext. 
                    We generated several text variants with meaningful enrichments and one fake variant that served as a baseline. We could not observe that 
                    semantic surprisal as a feature of words and uniform information density have a sub- text effect throughout all text variants. 
                    However, it turned out that kurtosis and skewness are suitable classification criteria to distinguish meaningful enrichments from fake enrichments.
                </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p></p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
         <body>
                <div>
                    <head>1. Introduction</head>
                    <p>This paper is a first attempt to approach the subtext by means of infor- mation theory [1]. The object of study is a text by the Russian writer Anton P. Chekhov, 
                        namely the short-story ”Ward No. 6” (”Palata No. 6” in the original).
                    </p>
                    <p>The message conveyed by any text is composed of two kinds of meaning. The first is the explicit meaning, i.e. the meaning that is explicitly coded by the linguistic material appearing black on white. 
                        The second is the meaning that a cooperative interpreter will infer from the explicit text following Gricean or Neo-Gricean reasoning [2], 
                        making use of both linguistic knowledge and non-linguistic resources (world knowledge, conversational context). Even the most explicit text leaves open numerous informational gaps, 
                        which must be filled by the interpreter. These ”bridging inferences” [3] constitute the im- plicit meaning of the text, for which we utilise the term subtext here. 
                        Another metaphor which is sometimes employed is the visible text as opposed to dark text (e.g. [4]).
                    </p>
                    <p>The discourse about the subtext is rich (see [5, 6] for a survey), and the notion is controversial. According to the Oxford Dictionary of lit- erary terms [7], 
                        the subtext is “any meaning or set of meanings which is implied rather than explicitly stated in a literary work, especially in a play”. 
                        For the Russian Literary encyclopedia of terms and concepts [8], the subtext (“podtekst” in Russian) represents the “hidden sense of an utterance, 
                        stemming from the interaction of the literary mean- ings, the context, and the speech situation”. 
                        As can be seen, there are basically two ways of understanding what subtext is [9, p. 72]. 
                        Un- der the first reading, the one described above, advocated by [7], the term is basically synonymous to “pragmatic inferences”. 
                        Besides that, the term subtext is used in the literature also to refer to the ultimate sense of a literary text, i.e. 
                        to the interpretation that is intended by the author and that the reader has to decipher (e.g. [8, 10]). 
                        In that second respect, the meaning of subtext comes close to the ”moral of the story”. In what follows, we use subtext only in the first of these two readings.                        
                    </p>
                    <p>To approach the implicit meanings of a text, we will investigate the Russian short-story ”Palata No. 6”, 
                        written by Anton P. Chekhov, published in 1892. Chekhov is considered to have originated the role of the subtext, 
                        in his plays but also in his prose (e.g. [11, 12]). Us- ing a narrative text for our purposes has the advantage that the in- formational 
                        impact of the conversational context is reduced because the addressee (reader) 
                        does not have to calculate her own position as well as the position of the speaker (author).                    
                    </p>
                    <p>Related to the previous point, Chekhov is known for having devel- oped a specific literary technique of “concentration and shortness” [13, p. 48-49], 
                        manifesting itself in the language of the narrator, which usually shows simple syntax, parataxis, short sentences. 
                        This and the sparse use of adjectives, comparisons and metaphors is functional, 
                        for Chekhov’s intention is to challenge the reader intellectually and to encourage critical reading[13, p. 67][14]. 
                        The reader is asked to ac- tively interpret by filling the informational gaps of the texts. 
                        There- fore, we may expect a Chekhov story to entail a drastic discrepancy between what is said explicitly and what is meant by the text. 
                        If the subtext is “a level of speech between the lines” ([15]), we may thus safely expect a lot of speech between the lines in the work of Chekhov.
                    </p>
                    <p>The general language of the Chekhovian short-story is the Russian literary language [13, p. 49], 
                        which is important for our methodol- ogy to be introduced below. 
                        The particular text ”Ward No. 6” has been chosen, moreover, 
                        because of its considerable length compared to other short-stories of the author. 
                        For our methodology to work, we need a text of a certain cardinality of words.
                    </p>
                   </div>
             <div>
                 <head>2. Outline</head>
                 <p>
                     
                 </p>
                 
             </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl></bibl>
            </listBibl>
           
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
