<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Review of The Bloomsbury Handbook to the Digital
               Humanities (2023)<!--article title in English--></title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Soni <dhq:family>Wadhwa</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  >https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6707-7094<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>SRM University, India</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>soni.w@srmap.edu.in</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Soni Wadhwa is an Assistant Professor of English at SRM University (Andhra
                     Pradesh, India). Soni’s research interests include spatiality, Sindhi Studies,
                     digital archiving, and South Asian Studies.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000779<!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               >019<!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue">1<!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date when="2025-04-04">04 April 2025<!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
               <term corresp="#dh"/>
               <term corresp="#cultural_criticism"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>digital humanities</item>
                  <item>handbook</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000779/000779.xml"
               >GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>James O’Sullivan’s edited volume is, to use his words, likely to attract three kinds
               of readers: DH-experts, DH-curious, and naysayers. This review examines what the book
               offers to each category of readers, as a way of approaching the Herculean task of
               capturing a glimpse of 43 chapters that touch upon the domain in diverse ways. The
               self-critical spirit consistently demonstrated across chapters will stimulate
               dialogue regarding the gains made by DH when analysing culture textually.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>James O'Sullivan's edited volume is an important addition to contemporary discourse
               on DH. It has something for a variety of readers: experts, beginners, and
               critics.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>

         <p>A handbook is a tricky object: it must provide an overview of a domain: articulating its
            first principles, mapping its present debates and trajectories, and pointing to the
            directions where it is likely to head. Very often, it is also likely to be judged on the
            basis of what it excludes, engaged with on the basis of what it has missed rather than
            what it includes. It is against the background of that baggage of expectations that this
            review approaches its subject (the volume) through the editor’s own framing. James
            O’Sullivan, in his introduction to the handbook, clarifies that his volume was imagined
            as future-focused – offering reference materials and provocations to facilitate further
            progress in the field – and likely to be of interest to DH-experts, DH-curious, and
            naysayers. It is a rich collection divided into five parts: <quote rend="inline"
               >Perspectives &amp; Polemics</quote>, <quote rend="inline">Methods, Tools, &amp;
               Techniques</quote>, <quote rend="inline">Public Digital Humanities</quote>, <quote
               rend="inline">Institutional Contexts</quote>, and <quote rend="inline">DH
               Futures</quote>. With every part, individual chapters present overviews of subdomains
            while highlighting specific problems and approaches to address the same. For instance,
               <quote rend="inline">Methods, Tools, &amp; Techniques</quote> carries chapters around
            programming, encoding practices within textual editions, text mining, natural language
            processing, audio and visual data analysis, social media analysis, spatiality, data
            visualisation, and the importance of critical digital humanities as a praxis of digital
            humanities. As an independent part within the handbook, it brings together principles
            that guide DH praxis in the subdomains mentioned while also offering critiques of them
            where applicable. Thus, while the handbook cannot be rendered coherent in terms of
            argument, there are a few things to be said about its structure that can help readers
            approach it in specific ways. Let us examine what the volume does for these categories
            of readers rather than summarise over forty chapters spread over five parts.</p>

         <p>Firstly, the handbook is an interesting expression of how to approach dissent and
            critique. Usually, such compilations offer critiques at the end, <hi rend="italic"
               >after</hi> one has read about different definitions, theories and approaches
            prevalent within a subject. James O’Sullivan has thrown this sequencing logic out of the
            window for part one of the book, which has <quote rend="inline">polemics</quote> built
            into it. As the longest part (with 11 chapters), it engages with the question of what DH
            is and what it is not. Instead of clearing this opening space for providing an overview
            of the field, O’Sullivan piles upon it the task of critique and it is a genius move
            because, after all, what is an overview without critique? To understand what DH is,
            O’Sullivan’s readers must also take into account what it is not. For instance, one
            chapter (Johanna Drucker’s) argues that one must not take the tools for granted but
            develop a deeper understanding of how these tools work, failing which DH-ers would stop
            innovating or keep relying on tools and their output for arguments. Drucker rathers that
            they design new tools for diverse purposes or decide how to use them for different
            agendas. The chapters on the <quote rend="inline">peripheries and epistemic
               margins</quote>, non-Western DH, postcolonial DH, DH and race, queer DH, feminist DH,
            multilingual DH, and so on uncover silences and erasures within the field. Both
            DH-experts and DH-curious are likely to engage with this critique-next-to-definitions
            design of the book very well by identifying new questions to work on. Sullivan’s design
            also helps one realise that the field is richer for this kind of embedding of polemics
            within itself, and it demonstrates the constant introspection to which the researchers
            in the domain are committed. </p>

         <p>Second, the choice of contributors/chapters keeps critique an ongoing dialogue rather
            than something that is restricted to part one. For instance, the chapter on critical
            digital humanities (by David M. Berry) points out that a reliance on mathematization
            that tends to govern computational approaches, to, say, text mining, interferes with
            cultural critique and hides political questions such as those of labour or democracy.
            Another expression of self-critique and introspection comes from chapter 13 (by Quinn
            Dombrowski) on the importance of coding in DH: the insecurity brought in by a lack of
            proficiency in coding, or induced by those who claim DH to be a computational space,
            meant for the computationally fluent. Chapter 13 is an example of the fact that the DH
            community is not threatened by voices outside DH (such as Nan Z Da’s) but by those who
            undermine the work done outside computational skills, without realising that the skills
            required to translate humanities research into programming need not involve writing
            elegant codes, to count as relevant. One way to make the DH space inclusive is to
            prioritize thinking in terms of workflows over programming. Another position, by Joanna
            Byszuk (chapter 15), is that scholars must clearly articulate their methodologies and
            processes in their publications, rather than assume readers would not make sense of them
            and thereby keep critical aspects of research as well-guarded secrets. Similarly,
            Alexandra Schofield (chapter 16) argues that reading research output in NLP gives one
            the impression that the first attempt at a question is the successful one; more often
            than not, research in DH tends to be iterative, most of which is not shared in the
            conventional research article style of dissemination. For more people to make sense of
            DH methods, the illusion of question-to-solution model should change. DH-curious readers
            will find such insights helpful. </p>

         <p>Third, the idea that DH is a lot more than computation or programming finds ample
            expression in the pages of the handbook. DH is also about archiving, keeping scholarship
            open access, pursuing projects in cultural heritage, sustaining such projects within the
            university and the larger communities, investing in DH community building activities
            through documentation of pedagogies, working with print and book history and textuality
            in general, thinking about design, and reflecting on cultures of data and artificial
            intelligence. Indeed, the existence of these fields of inquiry throws text mining into
            stark relief: it turns out to be in a minority in the larger DH imagination. As Taylor
            Arnold and Lauren Tilton argue (chapter 17), consistent with the spirit of self-critique
            in the volume, an obsession with text mining betrays the logocentric orientation of DH,
            something that needs to change with rich imaginations of audio, visual, and even spatial
            texts within DH. Such a range of questions are likely to provide a lot of space to the
            naysayers about considering the impact of the discipline on questions of cultural texts,
            especially as can be seen in the final section on the <quote rend="inline"
               >futures</quote>: the suggestion that terms and ideas such as datawork and ETA
            (exploratory text analysis rather than computational literary or textual studies) in
            chapter 34 or the suggestion that computing can be an aid in hermeneutic scholarship
            (chapter 35) unpack the ways in which DH is likely to be practised and understood in the
            near (and maybe the distant) future. One development to look forward to is its
            intersection with public humanities, opening up all knowledge to specialists and the
            general publics (chapter 37), in not just making knowledge available as open access but
            also in making it more accessible or comprehensible. Between the time the book was
            finished and this time of reading about it, the AI aspect of this future has already
            happened (chapter 42). The book covers a lot of territory as it stops at this edge
            between the present and the future. </p>

         <p>James O’Sullivan’s <title rend="italic">Handbook</title> deserves to be read widely for
            its very approach to curation and conversation around a subject. Its relevance lies
            beyond DH. If every volume were to conceptualize its subject to include critical
            reflections, only articulating the backlash it has received, it would be a healthy sign
            of knowledge production in every domain. Perhaps, that is the greatest takeaway from the
            book: DH may have its naysayers but DH itself does not naysay, as it were, even to its
            naysayers.</p>


      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sullivan_2023" label="Sullivan 2023">Sullivan, James. (ed.) (2023) <title
                  rend="italic">The Bloomsbury Handbook to the Digital Humanities</title>.
               Bloomsbury Publishing.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
