<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Library Professionals: Instrumental in Black Digital Humanities</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Jina <dhq:family>DuVernay</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Clark Atlanta University; Gwinnett County Public Library</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>jinaduvernay@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                 <p><name>Jina DuVernay</name> is a librarian, an adjunct English instructor, and a Black arts and culture 
                    consultant who is active in the field of librarianship, serving on numerous committees and initiatives 
                    that advocate for the collection, stewardship, and discoverability of resources related to Black history 
                    and culture. <name>DuVernay</name> has served as a Councilor-at-Large for the <name>American Library 
                    Association</name> (<name>ALA</name>), as a Coretta Scott King Book Award Juror, and as an executive 
                    board member for the Black Caucus of <name>ALA</name>. <name>DuVernay</name> is currently pursuing a 
                    PhD in Humanities at <name>Clark Atlanta University</name>.
                 </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000767</idno>
            <idno type="volume">018</idno>
            <idno type="issue">4</idno>
            <date when="2024-12-06">6 December 2024</date>
            <dhq:articleType>opinion</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <term corresp="#archives"/>
               <term corresp="#race"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>librarians</item>
                  <item>libraries</item>
                  <item>archivists</item>
                  <item>Black digital humanities</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000767/000767.xml">GitHub</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
           <p>Librarians and archivists, particularly those whose work focuses on resources pertaining to the Black diaspora, play a vital role in the 
              field of Black digital humanities. Yet, all too often they are left out of conversations surrounding the Black digital humanities. This is a 
              missed opportunity. Reflecting on my own work as a library professional, I argue that bridging the gap between the Black digital humanities 
              and the social sciences, particularly library science, can prove to be incredibly fruitful in all phases of a digital humanity project.
           </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
           <p>Reflecting on my own work as a library professional, I argue that bridging the gap between the Black digital humanities and the social 
              sciences, particularly library science, can prove to be incredibly fruitful in all phases of a digital humanity project.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head/>
            <p>Librarians, archivists, and other library professionals, particularly those whose work focuses on resources pertaining to the Black diaspora, 
               play a vital role in the field of Black digital humanities. In addition to teaching, many library professionals provide subject area 
               expertise in the humanities to create, curate, and preserve resources that document the history and culture of Black people. As such, their 
               work extends to the digital humanities in that these library professionals digitize historical materials, create and share born-digital 
               resources, and think deeply about questions of access. Yet, all too often library professionals are left out of conversations surrounding the 
               Black digital humanities. This is a missed opportunity. Reflecting on my own work as a library professional, I argue that bridging the gap 
               between the Black digital humanities and the social sciences, particularly library science, can prove to be incredibly fruitful in all phases 
               of a digital humanities project.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Current State of Collaboration</head>
            <p>The work of some library professionals closely aligns with that of digital humanists. As scholars in other fields, academic library 
               professionals publish books and articles, lead digital projects, and teach classes on how to utilize different digital tools and resources. 
               In addition, they research, collect, preserve, and make accessible digitized and born-digital resources. Many learn basic coding skills in 
               library school, create finding aids, and catalog archival materials and other resources in the library. These are just a few examples of how 
               library professionals are making significant contributions to the field, and these skills should be considered an asset to any digital 
               humanities scholarship. However, while rightly criticizing gaps and silences in library archives, digital humanities scholarship has 
               sometimes elided the labor of library professionals who are passionately and diligently working behind the scenes, often dealing with very 
               difficult circumstances across a range of institutional challenges. As a result, some scholars do not utilize the expertise of library 
               professionals, are unaware of their skillset, or simply overlook their contributions to digital humanities altogether.
            </p>
            <p>The relative lack of collaboration between Black digital humanists and library professionals, I argue, can also be explained by the fact that 
               some institutions lack the infrastructure to implement digital scholarship on campus. While there are many colleges and universities that 
               have successfully incorporated digital humanities work into their academic spaces, there are many more institutions that have yet to do so. 
               Many factors may account for this, such as a lack of funding or expertise, or a perceived lack of interest amongst faculty, staff, and 
               students. However, collaborating with those on campus who have knowledge in the area of digital scholarship is advantageous for humanities 
               scholars, especially those at institutions that have little to no funding to create digital labs, centers, or other dedicated spaces for 
               digital humanities scholarship. Thus, seeking out assistance from colleagues across campus is imperative.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Why Collaboration Matters</head>
            <p>Humanities scholars at underfunded institutions or institutions that have yet to embrace digital humanities scholarship in earnest ought to 
               turn to their libraries for assistance. Indeed, the tremendous uptick in digital humanities positions within college and university libraries 
               in recent years, itself a response to the steady rise in digital humanities scholarship, indicates that library professionals would be an 
               asset to digital humanities and specifically to Black digital humanities. Humanities scholars may be suprised to learn that their institution 
               employs a Digital Humanities Librarian or Archivist, a Digital Initiatives and Resources Librarian, a Digital Scholarship Archivist, or even 
               a Digital Humanities Specialist, to name a few of the positions that have been implemented in recent years. These positions suggest that 
               institutions are increasingly positioning their libraries to respond to the growing demand for more collaboration and assistance with digital 
               tools and projects. It is increasingly possible for humanities scholars to visit their institution's library and find library professionals 
               ready to provide instruction on digital tools, assist with research needs, and share invaluable knowledge as collaborators on digital 
               humanities projects.
            </p>
            <p>In particular, library professionals whose work is dedicated to staying abreast of new scholarship and resources that pertain to 
               Black history and culture would likely have much to add to the planning, research, design, and development of any Black digital humanities 
               projects. These professionals hold titles such as African American Studies Librarian, Black Diaspora Archivist, and Curator for African 
               American Collections.
            </p>
            <p>Though some institutions have not yet established a concentrated position or dedicated space to focus solely on fostering digital 
               humanities, all is not lost. It is not a librarian's job to know all things, but it is their job to know how to find all things. Oftentimes, 
               this knowledge results from assisting a wide variety of researchers and from undertaking continual professional development. It is safe to 
               say that in the field of library sciences, an effective library professional is a nosy one! In fact, to be effective, library professionals 
               must seek to know the current trends in scholarship across various disciplines. Once library professionals have gained additional knowledge 
               and practice in digital humanities, they can share their newly acquired skills with scholars at their institutions. Even though some 
               institutions do not have funding for professional development in digital humanities, library professionals can and should seek out 
               opportunities independently.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Bridging the Gap through Professional Development</head>
            <p>As a librarian and archivist, I am constantly seeking ways to stay abreast of new and emerging scholarship to be effective in the field of 
               library and information science. I strive to know a little bit about a lot of things in order to assist a vast array of researchers and the 
               community at large, principally the Black community. I offer here some examples of opportunities that have made a difference to my 
               professional path, in hopes that some of these might serve as bridges for others as well. As a way to continue to develop professionally, I 
               have sought out learning opportunities which have been an important way for me to gain new knowledge about digital humanities. For example, 
               in 2022, I applied for and was selected to participate in the inaugural <ref target="https://calidhri.hcommons.org/">California Digital 
               Humanities Research Institute</ref>. This new endeavor was inspired by <name>The City University of New York</name>'s digital humanities 
               research institute and was hosted by <name>UCLA</name> Libraries and <name>UC Irvine</name> Libraries. That year, the theme for the free 
               Digital Ethnic Studies Institute was <title rend="quotes">The Black Press</title>. The virtual three-day institute featured three keynote 
               speakers and was geared towards those interested in learning about foundational geographic information systems as well as text mining tools 
               that use open datasets related to African American history. It was a wonderful opportunity to not only learn about different digital projects, 
               but to also meet others who were interested in the intersection of Black studies and digital humanities.
            </p>
            <p>Another opportunity that I took advantage of was a virtual pre-conference at the 
               <ref target="https://artepublicopress.com/recovery-program/">Recovering the U.S. Hispanic Literary Heritage Conference</ref>, which 
               highlighted digital tools and emphasized using archives for digital scholarship. I have also benefited from several virtual workshops 
               facilitated by the <name>Atlanta University</name> Center Data Science Initiative, where I learned more about how data sciences can be used 
               across all disciplines.
            </p>
            <p>Collaborative relationships and contributions to digital projects have also helped me forge connections within the scholarly community. For 
               instance, I have been a proud scholar of the <ref target="https://iopn.library.illinois.edu/omeka/s/BBIP/page"><name>University of 
               Kansas</name>' Black Book Interactive Project</ref>. As a scholar in the Introduction to the Digital Humanities Program, I was introduced to 
               many exciting digital projects that involved Black literature. Additionally, I am a member of the 
               <ref target="https://recoveryhub.siue.edu/steering-committee/">steering committee</ref> for the Recovery Hub for American Women Writers and 
               have enjoyed contributing as a reviewer to a digital project on the 
               <ref target="https://recoveryhub.siue.edu/2022/03/23/showcase-gloria-naylor-archive/">archive of <name>Gloria Naylor</name></ref>.
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, I have been an editor-at-large for <ref target=" https://dhandlib.org/">dh+lib</ref>, a research affiliate for the 
               <ref target="https://www.disconetwork.org/alumni">Digital Inquiry Speculation Collaboration Optimism Network</ref>, 
               and a copyeditor for <ref target="https://digblk.psu.edu/engage/resources/">The Center for Black Digital Research/#DigBlk</ref>. I have 
               also attended several virtual workshops offered by <name>Clark Atlanta University</name>'s Center for Africana Digital Humanities, for which 
               I created a bibliography on Black digital humanities to accompany their workshops. These are all activities through which library professionals, 
               particularly those new to the field, can contribute meaningfully and gain important professional experience. Programs like these are important 
               entry points and ways to build skills, discover potential collaborators, and learn the landscape so that we can help others navigate and learn.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>As institutions continue to embrace and implement digital humanities positions, labs, and centers in their libraries, archives, and 
               departments, collaboration on digital humanities projects will become much more beneficial. Scholars interested in Black digital humanities 
               can start where they are by banding together and assessing their available resources, the library being arguably the most important. The 
               opportunities for librarians and archivists to learn and grow in the digital humanities are ripe for the taking. Library professionals, 
               including those currently working in digital humanities positions as well as those with other specialties who nonetheless participate in 
               digital humanities professional development opportunities, are uniquely trained and prepared to collaborate on digital humanities projects. 
               Therefore, Black digital humanists and library professionals can bridge the gap by working together.
            </p>
        </div>
      </body>
      <back>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
