<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">A multi-dimensional ontology-based analysis of
                    the Censorship of Hebrew Manuscripts</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Gila <dhq:family>Prebor</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Department of Information Science Bar-Ilan University, Ramat
                        Gan, 52900, Israel</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>gila.prebor@biu.ac.il</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Dr. Gila Prebor is a senior lecturer in the Department of Information
                            Science, Bar-Ilan University, Ramat Gan, Israel. Her main research
                            fields include history of the Hebrew book, organization of information,
                            metadata, bibliographic technique and Digital Humanities. She is
                            co-editor of the journal: <title rend="italic">Alei Sefer: Studies in
                                Bibliography and in the History of the Printed and the Digital
                                Hebrew Book</title>.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Maayan
                        <dhq:family>Zhitomirsky-Geffet</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Department of Information Science Bar-Ilan University, Ramat
                        Gan, 52900, Israel</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>Maayan.Zhitomirsky-Geffet@biu.ac.il</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Dr. Zhitomirsky-Geffet is a Senior Lecturer in the Department of
                            Information Science in Bar-Ilan University. She is an expert in data
                            modelling and semantic web technologies. For the past decade Dr.
                            Zhitomirsky-Geffet's research focuses on various aspects of ontology
                            construction and crowdsourcing techniques and their application in the
                            field of digital humanities. She is the winner of the best paper award
                            of 2017 Emerald Literati Network Awards for Excellence. Her works have
                            been published in various prominent journals, such as: <title rend="italic">JASIS&amp;T</title>,
                           <title rend="italic"> Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> and <title rend="italic">PlosONE</title>, and presented at
                            major international conferences, e.g. ASIS&amp;T, Digital Humanities
                            (DH), ACL and WWW.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Isaac <dhq:family>Miller</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Department of Information Science
                        Bar-Ilan University, Ramat Gan, 52900, Israel</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>Isaac.Miller@biu.ac.il</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Dr. Yitzchak Miller is a lecturer in the Department of Information
                            Science at Bar-Ilan University where he teaches several computer science
                            courses on web and database technologies as well as a course in data
                            visualization. He provides support to faculty in incorporating data
                            visualization and other software tools into their Digital Humanities
                            research projects.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000442</idno>
                <idno type="volume">014</idno>
                <idno type="issue">1</idno>
                <date/>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2019-11-24" who="murelj">Created file, began encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>In this study, we present the first large-scale quantitative analysis of a corpus
                    of censored historical Hebrew manuscripts that have survived through the ages. A
                    new multi-dimensional ontology-based approach was applied to explore the
                    geographic, temporal, actor- and subject-based distribution of censorship
                    events. We adopted an ontology-based approach to apply statistical analysis on
                    the metadata of censored Hebrew manuscripts for estimating the scope and
                    quantifying the extent of the known facts on the censorship activity and its
                    various characteristics over the years. In addition, we revealed some previously
                    unknown phenomena and trends. Particularly, we analysed the relationship of
                    censorship on other types of events in manuscripts’ lifecycle and compared the
                    distribution of censored vs. non-censored manuscripts in different dimensions.
                    We also devised a set of rules to complete the missing locations of over 50% of
                    censorship events, which has substantially changed the big picture of spatial
                    distribution of censorship activity. From the temporal perspective our findings
                    demonstrate that censorship was conducted in <q>waves</q> and there was a
                    decrease in the creation of new manuscripts in periods of high censorship
                    activity. Certain subjects, such as Kabbalah and Philosophy were censored
                    significantly more than others, and the locations and script types’ distribution
                    in censored manuscripts differs from the non-censored manuscripts.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p/>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Our study aims to investigate the historical phenomenon of censorship of Hebrew
                    manuscripts performed by the Catholic Church in Italy<note>The geographical
                        terms in this paper represent geographical and cultural areas, but not
                        necessarily political entities. For example, by Italy we mean the territory
                        of modern Italy, and similarly when mentioning other geographical terms.
                            <ptr target="#beit-arié2018" loc="75"/>.</note> during the 16th-18th
                    centuries (1550-1775). Thus far, most of the studies on the censorship of Jewish
                    manuscripts and books during this period were done in a qualitative and focused
                    manner <ptr target="#baruchson-arbib2007"/>
                    <ptr target="#phillips2016"/>.</p>
                <p>Recently, quantitative methods have been embraced by scholars for the analysis of
                    Big Data in the Humanities <ptr target="#kaplan2017"/>
                    <ptr target="#leizeng2017"/>. Accordingly, in this paper we present the first
                    (to the best of our knowledge) large-scale quantitative analysis of historical
                    Hebrew manuscript data. For the purpose of this study, we identified 5,185
                    censored manuscripts in the catalogue of the Department of Manuscripts and the
                    Institute of Microfilmed Hebrew Manuscripts in the National Library of Israel
                        (<ref target="http://web.nli.org.il">(http://web.nli.org.il)</ref>), which
                    represent the largest collection of Hebrew manuscript metadata in the world.</p>
                <p>In Ethington (2007) the author argues that <cit><quote rend="inline">the past is
                            the set of all places made by human action. … Knowledge of the past,
                            therefore, is literally cartographic: a mapping of the places of history
                            indexed to the coordinates of spacetime</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ethington2007"/></cit>. Inspired by the multi-perspective
                    framework of Ethington's theory of visual representation of the past we propose
                    a new multi-dimensional methodology for the large-scale quantitative analysis of
                    historical manuscript data. Particularly, we examined the temporal, geographic,
                    actor- and subject-based dimensions of the censored manuscripts and also
                    compared the statistical distribution of censored manuscripts on these
                    dimensions to the non-censored manuscript corpus. The proposed methodology is
                    open-ended, as it is not limited to the dimensions specified above and can be
                    extended with more dimensions which might be relevant for a given data
                    collection.</p>
                <p>The availability of a relatively large censorship database on one hand, and the
                    ability to apply to it modern analysis and visualization techniques on the other
                    hand, has the potential to discover new insights into censorship activity over
                    the years. This includes both revealing unknown phenomena or trends as well as
                    bringing new (mainly quantitative) perspectives to known facts.</p>
                <p>Thus, the research questions posed in this research are: <list type="simple">
                        <item>How are censored manuscripts distributed in various dimensions
                            mentioned above? More specifically we explored: <list type="ordered">
                                <item>When were the peaks, inclines and declines in censorship
                                    activity and can they be explained by historical knowledge of
                                    the corresponding periods?</item>
                                <item>In what cities did censorship take place?</item>
                                <item>What major geographic transitions can be observed from the
                                    large-scale quantitative analysis of censorship data and what is
                                    known about them in historical literature?</item>
                                <item>Who were the most dominant censors?</item>
                                <item>Did censors work in collaboration and to what extent?</item>
                                <item>What was the rate of repetitive censorship, when a certain
                                    manuscript was censored more than once?</item>
                                <item>Finally, what were the main subjects of the censored
                                    manuscripts?</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>What are the differences between censored manuscripts in Italy in the
                            16th-18th centuries vs. non-censored manuscripts in the collection in
                            various dimensions? These differences can shed light on special
                            characteristics of the censored corpus which distinguish it from the
                            rest of the manuscripts. Particularly, as part of the spatial analysis
                            we investigated the following phenomena: <list type="ordered">
                                <item>Whether there is a difference in the distribution of censored
                                    vs. non-censored manuscript script types and whether this
                                    distribution changes over time?</item>
                                <item>Whether the distribution of censored manuscripts among their
                                    current storage locations differs from the overall distribution
                                    of storage locations of the dataset?</item>
                                <item>In addition, from the subject analysis perspective we
                                    examined: Whether the distributions of censored vs. non-censored
                                    manuscripts differ according to subjects?</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Historical Background</head>
                <p>In the context of the Counter-Reformation, during the 16th-18th centuries, the
                    Catholic Church closely supervised written and printed literature. Papal bulls
                    were issued against proscribed books, and indices were drawn up containing lists
                    of prohibited books (<title rend="italic">Index Librorum Prohibitorum</title>),
                    which also included Hebrew books. In addition to the indices that were written
                    for literature in general, some indices listed Hebrew books only (see <ref
                        target="#prebor2003">Prebor 2003</ref>; <ref target="#raz-krakotzkin2007"
                        >Raz-Krakotzkin 2007</ref>; <ref target="#francesconi2012">Francesconi
                        2012</ref>; <ref target="#francesconi2016">Francesconi 2016</ref>; <ref
                        target="#phillips2016">Phillips 2016</ref>; <ref target="#vanboxel2016">Van
                        Boxel 2016</ref>). <note>For studies on the impact of the index in Italy and
                        on the impact of censorship on the Italian Jewish communities see: <ref
                            target="#francesconi2012" loc="154">Francesconi 2012, p. 154,
                            n.2-3</ref>; <ref target="#francesconi2016" loc="102">Francesconi 2016,
                            p. 102, n.7-8</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The techniques of censorship directed towards Hebrew literature evolved
                    concurrently with, and as part of the development of church censorship as a
                    whole, and were formulated by the same bodies. Italian Jews who wished to save
                    their books operated in two ways: on the one hand, internal censorship of Hebrew
                    printed books and, on the other hand, by lobbying the Pope and Church leaders to
                    ease the instructions for confiscating books and forbidding the printing of the
                    Talmud.</p>
                <p>The Jewish lobbying of the Pope and Church leaders to ease directives regarding
                    confiscation of manuscripts and books led to the operation of external
                    censorship <ptr target="#baruchson-arbib2007"/>. One of the concessions won by
                    Italian Jews was the introduction of the censorship of manuscripts and printed
                    books possessed by the Jewish public, as an alternative to confiscation and
                    wholesale destruction of virtually all the books they possessed. The term
                        <term>purification</term> (<term>Ziquq</term>) is the commonly used term in
                    this context, parallel to the Latin term <term xml:lang="la">expurgatio</term>
                    <ptr target="#sonne1942"/>
                    <ptr target="#benayahu1971"/>. To carry out the expurgation, the Church put
                    censors at the disposal of the communities, most of them apostates and experts
                    in the Hebrew language, and the communities undertook to pay their fees. The
                    involvement of the Jews in the purification work arose from the fundamental
                    approach of the Church that the Jews were responsible for the <q>forbidden
                        literature</q> in their possession.</p>
                <p>The owners of Hebrew books were required in the name of the Inquisition to hand
                    them over to the censors, who kept them in the local office. Concealing books
                    was punished by their confiscation and a heavy fine, and in certain cases, also
                    by the confiscation of property and imprisonment. The books collected were
                    examined by the censors, who destroyed the forbidden books and punished those
                    who kept them. The books of a controversial nature were expurgated and returned
                    to their owners with the approval of the censor.</p>
                <p>The censorship procedure entailed erasing or replacing all the paragraphs which,
                    in the view of the censors, contravened the principles of Christianity, its
                    customs and rites, or those paragraphs which contained blasphemy, heresy or
                    errors. When the expurgation of the book was completed, the censor wrote a short
                    approval note. The approval note was written for the most part on the final page
                    of the book and sometimes on the title page. Proof of the activity of the
                    various censors can be found in a large number of manuscripts and printed works
                    which have survived until the present day, and in which ink erasures,
                    emendations, signs of removed pages and the signature of the censor can be
                    observed.</p>
                <p>In the next section we review literature on computational methods for
                    digitization and large-scale quantitative analysis of historical corpora and
                    present several case studies of this research paradigm.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Related work</head>
                <p>In the past decade computational methods were proposed and implemented for
                    historical data analysis, e.g. Geographic Information Systems and spatial
                    analysis for historical collections (see <ref target="#gregory2007">Gregory and
                        Healye 2007</ref>; <ref target="#ayers2010">Ayers 2010</ref>; <ref
                        target="#moretti2005">Moretti 2005</ref>; <ref target="#knowles2008">Knowles
                        and Hillier 2008</ref>), temporal and subject-based analysis and
                    visualisation of historical and cultural heritage collections (see <ref
                        target="#glinka2017">Glinka et al. 2017</ref>; <ref target="#chandna2016"
                        >Chandna et al. 2016</ref>).</p>
                <p>In this section we review several projects applying quantitative analysis of
                    historical data on literary resources, such as hand-written manuscripts and
                    printed books. The Schoenberg Institute of Manuscript Studies, maintained by the
                    University of Pennsylvania Libraries, presents the multi-faceted analysis of the
                    Schoenberg Database of Manuscripts (SDBM) (<ref
                        target="https://sdbm.library.upenn.edu/"
                        >https://sdbm.library.upenn.edu/</ref>). The database contains over 200,000
                    records representing 90,000 hand-written manuscripts from diverse collections
                    and institutions (Van Hooland and Verborgh, 2014). The SDBM's website displays
                    statistics on manuscript distribution over time and space as well as by subject,
                    authorship and provenance based on historical sales lists. The Stanford project
                    Republic of Letters presents quantitative analysis and visualisation of
                    Voltaire’s letters, distribution of letters and writers displayed on a map and
                    timeline, as well as their correspondence network <note><ref
                            target="http://republicofletters.stanford.edu/publications/voltaire/letters/"
                            >
                            http://republicofletters.stanford.edu/publications/voltaire/letters/</ref></note>.</p>
                <p>A closely related project which aimed to organize and quantitatively analyse the
                    data on Jewish historical manuscripts is <hi rend="italic">SfarData</hi> (<ref
                        target="http://sfardata.nli.org.il/">http://sfardata.nli.org.il/</ref>). <hi
                        rend="italic">SfarData</hi> is the codicological data-base of the Hebrew
                    Palaeography Project which locates all the medieval codices written in Hebrew
                    script, which contain explicit production dates (until 1540) or at least scribe
                    names (some 6000 codices). The project aims to study and document the codices’
                    visual and measurable material features and scribal practices in situ; to
                    classify these features and practices in order to build a historical typology of
                    the hand-produced Hebrew book. This, in turn, provides users of Hebrew
                    manuscripts with a tool for identifying the production region and assessing the
                    period of the studied manuscripts <ptr target="#beit-arié2018"/>.</p>
                <p>Several projects investigate printed book distribution over time and space. The
                    Footprints project maintains a database of printed Jewish books
                    (https://footprints.ccnmtl.columbia.edu/). The goal is to consolidate and
                    analyse scattered information on Jewish books (in Hebrew, in other Jewish
                    languages, and on books in Latin and non-Jewish vernaculars with Judaica
                    content) in order to build up a composite view of the movement of Jewish texts
                    and ideas from place to place and across time. The French Book Trade in
                    Enlightenment Europe (FBTEE) project <ptr target="#burrows2012"/> (<ref
                        target="http://fbtee.uws.edu.au/stn/">http://fbtee.uws.edu.au/stn/</ref>)
                    uses database technology to map the French book trade across late-Enlightenment
                    Europe, between 1769 and 1794. It investigates best-selling texts and authors;
                    reading tastes across Europe; changing patterns of demand over time; and
                    networks of exchange in the print-trade. The project tracks the movement of
                    around 400,000 copies of 4,000 books across Europe. It details, where possible,
                    the exact editions of these works, the routes by which they travelled and the
                    locations of the clients that bought or sold them.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Method</head>
                <div>
                    <head>The catalogue's data structure</head>
                    <p>The catalogue of the Department of Manuscripts and the Institute of
                        Microfilmed Hebrew Manuscripts in the National Library of Israel, lists most
                        of the Hebrew manuscripts in existence in the world, whether held in public
                        or in private collections. The catalogue provides rich data about these
                        manuscripts, including references to censorship (<ref
                            target="http://web.nli.org.il/sites/NLI/English/collections/manuscripts/Pages/default.aspx"
                            >http://web.nli.org.il/sites/NLI/English/collections/manuscripts/Pages/default.aspx</ref>).</p>
                    <p>The manuscript catalogue was exported as an XML file on January 31, 2016, and
                        contained a total of 163,248 records. First of all, we excluded 30,418
                        Genizah manuscript records (18.6% of all the records). The Genizah
                        manuscripts are fragments of codicological units that were separated from
                        their original manuscripts (due in part to damage or deterioration of
                        codices) and were preserved in designated storage units called Genizah (from
                        Hebrew <q>גניזה</q>, the verbal noun signifying the act of
                        storing/archiving). Most of them are from the famous Cairo Genizah and some
                        are from the European Genizah. These fragments are not relevant to our study
                        because they have different characteristics than codex manuscripts and since
                        Genizah research is a separate field of study <ptr target="#richler1990"
                        />.</p>
                    <p>Next, in order to create a dedicated censored manuscript collection, we
                        automatically searched the catalogue's XML file for records with the word
                        stem <q>censor</q> (both in English and in Hebrew). In almost all of the
                        cases, a proper <q>censor</q> stem was found in a dedicated MARC field,
                        leaving only the cases where some morphological variations of the stem
                            <q>censor</q> were found for manual inspection. The obtained dataset was
                        further narrowed by filtering out some tens of manuscripts that were not
                        censored in Italy and/or were censored later than 1775. The final dataset
                        contains 5,185 censored manuscripts.</p>
                    <p>The structure of the catalogue follows a fundamental observation about the
                        formation of medieval codices. The word <q>manuscript</q> has multiple
                        meanings including: scrolls and codices, entire volumes (these can include
                        several works copied by different scribes either at the same time or in
                        different periods), a fragment of a few folios or a single folio. In our
                        research we analyzed only codices. In every codex we found three fundamental
                        layers: (1) the entire manuscript – the Bibliographic Unit (BU) that refers
                        to the physical entity comprising the entire codex with its shelf-mark in
                        the collection (generally corresponding to microfilm numbers). (2)
                        Codicological Units (CU) – Some of the bibliographic units include a number
                        of codicological units, namely a number of different parts of the
                        manuscripts that were produced in different locations and/or at different
                        time periods, either with or without a common theme. (3) Paleographical
                        Units – The codicological units can also contain a number of paleographical
                        units, and fragments written by different hands <ptr target="#sirat2002"/>
                        <ptr target="#beit-arié2018"/>.</p>
                    <p>The catalogue database's basic unit, the record, describes a single CU. When
                        the entire manuscript comprises a single CU (i.e. the codex is a single
                        manuscript produced in one place and time), then the BU and the CU overlap
                        and we obtain a <term>unified codex</term>
                        <ptr target="#beit-arié2018"/>. The record's data, in this case, refers to
                        this manuscript as a whole (the majority, more than 90% of the manuscripts
                        in the catalogue are of such a unified nature). The catalogue does not have,
                        however, an independent notion (e.g. a special record type) of BU. Rather,
                        when a codex comprises several CUs (termed as an <term>assembled
                            codex</term> - multi-CU), the catalogue contains a special record, an
                            <term>index record</term> that describes and lists the CUs of this codex
                        BU. This set of CUs (excluding the index record) comprises a multi-CU BU
                        with the shelf-number as its unique ID. In contrast, when there is a series
                        of records that share a shelf number, but there is no index record with the
                        same shelf number, we did not construct a BU for them and treated each
                        record as an independent BU that contains a single CU. The index records
                        themselves were not counted while calculating the various statistics of this
                        study as in most cases they only summarize the data already contained in the
                        individual CU records. However, we did use the data contained in index
                        records when we built the study dataset, mainly as a means to verify the
                        completeness of the data gathered from the BUs individual records (e.g. in
                        some cases, the cataloguers specified the normalized full censor name only
                        in the index record, while in the individual records they only gave a
                        partial name).</p>
                    <p>In many cases it is difficult to decide when exactly in time a multi-CU BU (a
                        codex) was bound. For example, if two censor signatures appear in a single
                        BU, one dated to 1590 and the other dated to 1600, then one possibility is
                        that this codex was bound before censorship (i.e. before 1590 (and censored
                        together, while another possibility is that different CUs in this codex were
                        censored in different settings/occasions only to be later bound together.
                        Also, in some cases when the censor signed the manuscript, he also wrote the
                        name of the place where the censorship took place (e.g. Mantua, Lugo).
                        Following the previous example, by comparing the 1590's place of censorship
                        to the 1600's place of censorship one may learn about manuscript transitions
                        between people's hands and places. We manually checked all the BUs that
                        contain two CUs or more. For each such BU, we used several inference rules
                        to determine whether the signatures that the codex contains refer to all the
                        manuscripts (CUs) in this BU or not. For instance, when the signature(s)
                        appears at the end of the codex we assumed that the signature(s) refer(s) to
                        the entire BU. If different types of script were used in different CUs of
                        the BU, this can be an indication for distinct manuscripts that were
                        censored separately.</p>
                    <p>Based on the above observations, BUs can be logically divided into two types
                        of virtual entities: <term>Whole Censored Unit</term> and <term>Non-Censored
                            Unit</term>. A <term>Whole Censored Unit</term> (WCU) groups CUs (of the
                        given BU( that underwent censorship as a whole textual unit. The rest of the
                        CUs in a BU, which are non-censored CUs are grouped under a
                            <term>Non-Censored Unit</term> (NCU). We, thus, split partially or
                        wholly censored BUs to one or multiple WCUs and a single NCU (see <ref
                            target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>).</p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure01">
                        <head>The structure of the study’s dataset. WCUs and NCU have a hyphenated
                            borderline to highlight that they are virtual entities created for the
                            purposes of this study.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>We found that out of the 586 examined BUs, 428 were censored as a single WCU.
                        Out of the remaining 158 BUs, 144 BUs have undergone censorship as a single
                        WCU and were bound together with a non-censored unit at a later time. In 13
                        cases, we identified two separate WCU units, and in only one case did we
                        split a BU into three distinct WCUs as we could identify that each one of
                        them had been censored at different occasions and only later bound together
                        into a single physical codex.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The proposed data model</head>
                    <p>In this study we adopted the event-based modelling approach presented in <ref
                            target="#zhitomirsky-geffet2016">Zhitomirsky-Geffet and Prebor
                            2016</ref> and defined three types of events relevant to the goals of
                        this research:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Manuscript creation event (CRE) – representing an individual CU's
                            creation including the creation date and place, the script type and
                            subject/s of the manuscript;</item>
                        <item>Manuscript censorship event (CE) – representing a single censorship
                            action on a single WCU encapsulating the date and location of the
                            censorship action, and the involved censor/s name, life/activity period
                            and location/s (if known); there can be multiple CEs associated with the
                            same WCU at different periods and locations, each CE might be associated
                            with multiple censors involved in it, and, apparently, the same censor
                            can take part in different CEs;</item>
                        <item>Manuscript storage event (SE) – representing the information on
                            current storage (an institution and its geographic location) of an
                            individual BU.</item>
                    </list>
                    <figure>
                        <head>The study's event-based data model. The blue ellipses represent the
                            event types (Storage Event - SE, Creation Event - CRE and Censorship
                            Event - CE) and the rectangles are their main attributes. The hyphenated
                            lines represent <term>part-of</term> relationships between the data
                            entities, according to the dataset structure depicted in Figure 1 - CU
                            is part-of a WCU or an NCU, and WCU and NCU are parts of a BU.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>According to the attributes of these types of events (represented as
                        rectangles in Figure 2), the manuscript dataset was divided into subsets,
                        such as censored (WCUs) vs. non-censored (NCUs) manuscripts. These subsets’
                        data were analysed separately in different dimensions, then the findings
                        were compared and differences between the subsets were analysed.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Data analysis methodology</head>
                    <p>First, the corpus of manuscripts underwent a process of data cleaning and
                        normalization. This process included decomposition of catalogue fields with
                        mixed information into its defined atomic entities (e.g. people names,
                        events, dates and places), standardization of a variety of date formats in
                        the catalogue (e.g. specific Hebrew or Gregorian dates, ranges of years,
                        centuries), and names of places (which appear in different languages and
                        without the name of the country or geographic coordinates). Missing
                        information was completed as well, using existing authority files and
                        ontologies, such as VIAF (<ref target="https://viaf.org/"
                            >https://viaf.org/</ref>) and Geonames (<ref
                            target="http://www.geonames.org/">http://www.geonames.org/</ref>). As
                        part of this place normalization process we also obtained the coordinates of
                        all the mentioned places in the collection which were extracted from the
                        abovementioned authority files. The data normalization process was performed
                        semi-automatically. It was based on identifying lexical patterns for each
                        ontological entity, and further manual correction and completion by two
                        experts in manuscript studies. For instance, for extraction of the
                        censorship event’s location from the following string in the catalogue:
                        censor signature: <quote rend="inline">LUGO 1611 CAMILLO JAGHEL</quote>, the
                        matching pattern was &lt;CENSOR * [PLACE] [DATE] [NAME]&gt;, thus LUGO was
                        retrieved and then looked up in the Geonames’ <title rend="quotes"
                            >1000cities</title> list.</p>
                    <p>Next, we performed a systematic event-based analysis of the manuscript
                        corpus. In addition to the descriptive statistical analysis we propose a new
                        multi-dimensional methodology for a large-scale quantitative analysis of the
                        historical manuscript data. The following types of variables were
                        investigated for each of the dimensions:</p>
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>For the temporal dimension: we examined the date of CRE (a CU creation
                            event) and the date(s) of CE(s) (a WCU's censorship events).</item>
                        <item>For the spatial dimension: we used the place of CRE, the place(s) of
                            CE(s), the current place of the corresponding BU storage, and the CU's
                            type of script (the scribe's writing type is determined by its country
                            of origin (Beit-Arié, 2018,) which points out to the place of writing of
                            the manuscript – although it should be considered that sometimes writers
                            moved to other countries while still keeping their original script
                            type.</item>
                        <item>For the actor dimension: an individual censor activity was examined in
                            terms of the number of CEs in which the censor was involved.</item>
                        <item>For the subject dimension: we analysed subjects assigned to a
                            CU.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Based on the above dimensions and variables a three-phase analysis has been
                        performed:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Descriptive statistics and distribution of censored manuscript
                            collection (WCUs) in multiple dimensions;</item>
                        <item>Comparative analysis of the distribution of the two sub-collections of
                            manuscripts, WCUs (censored manuscripts) vs. NCUs (non-censored
                            manuscripts) in various dimensions.</item>
                        <!-- need third point -->
                    </list>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Results</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Descriptive statistics of the censored manuscript corpus</head>
                    <p>Only 5,185 CUs have censorship information recorded for them in the
                        catalogue. These 5,185 CUs are grouped in 2,466 WCUs, while the other
                        118,921 non-censored CUs are grouped in 85,562 NCUs (as shown in Table 1).
                        The total of 124,106 CUs are associated with 87,848 BUs. As explained
                        before, there are cases when a single BU was (manually) <q>split</q> into a
                        WCU and an NCU or cases when a BU was <q>split</q> into more than a single
                        WCU (a total of 158 of both cases). Note however, that the vast majority of
                        cases (87,690) are indeed cases where a BU consists of either a single WCU
                        or a single NCU. Moreover, note that 79,415 BUs (90% of all the BUs in the
                        study corpus) are unified codices, that is, BUs that comprise a single CU. </p>
                    <table>
                        <head>Table 1: Counts of the study’s main data entities</head>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell role="label">Entity</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Number of items</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">BUs</cell>
                            <cell role="data">87,848</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">WCUs</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2,466</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">CUs in WCUs</cell>
                            <cell role="data">5,185</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">NCUs</cell>
                            <cell role="data">85,562</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">CUs in NCUs</cell>
                            <cell role="data">118,921</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">CUs (total)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">124,106</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>The 2,466 WCUs are associated with 3,914 instances of Censorship Events (CEs)
                        (see <ref target="#table02">Table 2</ref>). The number of CEs is greater
                        than the number of WCUs since in many cases, a WCU has been censored more
                        than once, thus having more than one CE associated with it as discussed
                        below. From Table 2 it can be noticed that in addition to the 3,190 CE
                        instances where the censor responsible for the censorship was identified, in
                        724 cases, there is a clear notion of censorship, but no censor was
                        documented in the manuscript's record.</p>
                    <p>Out of the 3,914 CEs, we filtered out 64 CEs: 56 CEs did not occur in Italy
                        (and also didn't occur in the study period), and 8 Italian CEs were excluded
                        since they occurred after 1775. The resulted dataset of Italian censorship
                        events in the period of 1550-1775 consists, therefore, of 3,850 CEs (in
                        2,408 WCUs), 677 (17.6%) of which are un-named cases (see <ref
                            target="#table02">Tables 2</ref> and <ref target="#table03">3</ref>).
                        The earliest identified evidence of censorship in a manuscript in Italy is
                        from 1554 and only two censorship events of Italian identified censorship
                        have a recorded date after 1775 (in 1802 and in 1833), which fall outside
                        our study period of 1550-1775.</p>
                    <table xml:id="table02">
                        <head>Table 2: Censorship events' (CEs) descriptive statistics (Italy and
                            non-Italy cases) with named and un-named CE cases in the period of
                            1550-1775 and later.</head>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell role="data"/>
                            <cell role="label">Named censorship</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Un-named censorship</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Total number of CEs</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data"/>
                            <cell role="data">Italian</cell>
                            <cell role="data">non-Italian</cell>
                            <cell role="data">All</cell>
                            <cell role="data">In Italy</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Not in Italy</cell>
                            <cell role="data">All</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Italian</cell>
                            <cell role="data">non-Italian</cell>
                            <cell role="data">All</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="label">Dated (total) </cell>
                            <cell role="data">2,518</cell>
                            <cell role="data">8</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2,526</cell>
                            <cell role="data">391</cell>
                            <cell role="data">36</cell>
                            <cell role="data">427</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2,909</cell>
                            <cell role="data">44</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2,953</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="label">Between 1550-1775</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2,516</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2,516</cell>
                            <cell role="data">385</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0</cell>
                            <cell role="data">385</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2,901</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2,901</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="label">After 1775</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2</cell>
                            <cell role="data">8</cell>
                            <cell role="data">10</cell>
                            <cell role="data">6</cell>
                            <cell role="data">36</cell>
                            <cell role="data">42</cell>
                            <cell role="data">8</cell>
                            <cell role="data">44</cell>
                            <cell role="data">52</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="label">With no date (total)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">657</cell>
                            <cell role="data">7</cell>
                            <cell role="data">664</cell>
                            <cell role="data">292</cell>
                            <cell role="data">5</cell>
                            <cell role="data">297</cell>
                            <cell role="data">949</cell>
                            <cell role="data">12</cell>
                            <cell role="data">961</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="label">Dated between 1550-1775 </cell>
                            <cell role="data">657</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0</cell>
                            <cell role="data">657</cell>
                            <cell role="data">292</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0</cell>
                            <cell role="data">292</cell>
                            <cell role="data">949</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0</cell>
                            <cell role="data">949</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="label">After 1775</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0</cell>
                            <cell role="data">7</cell>
                            <cell role="data">7</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0</cell>
                            <cell role="data">5</cell>
                            <cell role="data">5</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0</cell>
                            <cell role="data">12</cell>
                            <cell role="data">12</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="label">All periods (total)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">3,175</cell>
                            <cell role="data">15</cell>
                            <cell role="data">3,190</cell>
                            <cell role="data">683</cell>
                            <cell role="data">41</cell>
                            <cell role="data">724</cell>
                            <cell role="data">3,858</cell>
                            <cell role="data">56</cell>
                            <cell role="data">3,914</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="label">Between 1550-1775 (total) </cell>
                            <cell role="data">3,173</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0</cell>
                            <cell role="data">3,173</cell>
                            <cell role="data">677</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0</cell>
                            <cell role="data">677</cell>
                            <cell role="data">3,850</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0</cell>
                            <cell role="data">3,850</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="label">After 1775</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2</cell>
                            <cell role="data">15</cell>
                            <cell role="data">17</cell>
                            <cell role="data">6</cell>
                            <cell role="data">41</cell>
                            <cell role="data">47</cell>
                            <cell role="data">8</cell>
                            <cell role="data">56</cell>
                            <cell role="data">64</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>From Table 3 we observe that out of the 677 CEs in Italy that have no censor
                        name associated with them, in 513 cases a censorship signature was blurry
                        and thus could not be identified. In 151 cases a clear sign of censorship
                        text erasures is present in the manuscript, but without a signature, and in
                        13 cases the cataloguers identified self-censorship actions.</p>
                    <table xml:id="table03">
                        <head>Table 3: The distribution of different cases of un-named
                            censorship.</head>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell role="label">Type of un-named CE</cell>
                            <cell role="label"># of cases in the entire dataset</cell>
                            <cell role="label"># of cases that are Italian CEs in the range
                                1550-1775</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="label">Un-identified signature</cell>
                            <cell role="data">560 (77.3%)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">513 (75.8%)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="label">Censorship without a signature</cell>
                            <cell role="data">151 (20.9%)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">151 (22.3%)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="label">Internal self-censorship</cell>
                            <cell role="data">13 (1.8%)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">13 (1.9%)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="label">Total</cell>
                            <cell role="data">724</cell>
                            <cell role="data">677</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>A rather interesting finding from analyzing the censorship events of the
                        2,408 WCUs in our corpus is the number of re-occurring censorship actions,
                        that is, censorship of manuscripts that have been already censored. In other
                        words, these are the cases where the same WCU (a single or a bounded set of
                        CUs) has been submitted for approval to the same or a different censor at
                        various times and locations. Of the 2,408 WCUs, 992 WCUs (41%) were censored
                        more than once (see the distribution in Table 4). For example, the WCU -
                        PARIS BN Velins 908 (identified by the shelf number F 73304) has been
                        censored on four different occasions by four different censors, according to
                        this manuscript’s record in the catalogue. It bears Luigi da Bologna’s
                        signature from 1599, Camillo Jagel’s signature from 1623, Renato de Modena’s
                        from 1626 and Girolamo da Durazzano’s from 1640. WCU - Moscow - Russian
                        State Library, Ms. Guenzburg 147 (F 6831), on the other hand, records
                        Girolamo da Durazzano’s signature, twice: once from 1640 and then from 1641,
                        which suggests that this manuscript was censored in two consecutive years by
                        the same censor (this manuscript has an earlier third signature by Renato de
                        Modena from 1626).</p>
                    <p>The fact that Hebrew printed books have undergone repeated censorship is well
                        known as is mentioned, for example, in <ref target="#baruchson-arbib2007">a
                            study by Baruchson-Arbib and Prebor (2007)</ref>. What we are showing in
                        our study is that a) the repeated censorship occurs in handwritten books as
                        well, and more importantly b) that its scope is quite substantial: in total,
                        for the 2,408 censored manuscripts (the WCUs) in our study, compared to an
                        expected 2,408 censorship events (CEs) (one for each), 3,850 distinct CEs
                        are registered for these manuscripts, i.e. 1,442 additional, repeated CEs
                        (see <ref target="#table04">Table 4</ref>). This finding may indicate that
                        the repeated censorship phenomenon cannot be explained only by sporadic
                        actions by local censors, and that much more weight should be attributed to
                        other, more general, explanations that were given to that phenomenon.</p>
                    <p>Several directions were suggested to explain this phenomenon. One explanation
                        for this phenomenon is possibly that Church authorities feared that the Jews
                            <q>corrected</q> their manuscripts after the censorship and hence
                        re-checking is required. However, the substantial amount of renewed
                        censorship must also be attributed to factors relating to the Church’s
                        conduct on one hand, and the conduct of local inquisition administrations,
                        on the other hand. Firstly, the act of censorship of Hebrew texts did not
                        receive an official and formal authorization. As a direct consequence,
                        manuscripts which were approved by an official censor did not gain the
                        official recognition of the Church. Also, the Church’s policy regarding the
                        censorship of Hebrew books was seldom changed as new Popes came into office
                        and the rules by which censors should examine the text did also change and a
                        stricter expurgation policy was adopted in the course of time <ptr
                            target="#raz-krakotzkin2007"/>. On a local inquisition basis, censors
                        apparently doubted their predecessors’ work for negligence or even
                        deliberate eye-closing facing the monetary benefits from the Jews who paid
                        for their job.</p>
                    <p>The findings in our study show that re-occurring censorship is a phenomenon
                        that spread across time and across places. There are cases where repetitive
                        censorship took place in the same place, while in other cases, the repeating
                        censorship occurred in different place(s), and usually by different
                        censor(s). Table 4 summarizes the repetitive censorship statistics. More
                        detailed investigation, however, which will be dedicated to this phenomenon,
                        could produce more insight. It may identify the censors who are responsible
                        for repeated censorship more than others, it may find whether the repeated
                        censorship happened on specific years or places, it might supply some
                        characteristic as to the time elapsed between CEs of the same manuscript
                        (e.g. is re-occurring censorship more common after a long time since
                        previous censorship or maybe shorter elapsed time is more common).</p>
                    <table xml:id="table04">
                        <head>Table 4: Number of CEs per WCU</head>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data"># of CEs on the same WCU</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Total # of WCUs of this case</cell>
                            <cell role="data"># of WCUs that have been censored more than
                                once</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Total # of CEs on the same WCU</cell>
                            <cell role="data"># of repeating CEs</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">1</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1,416</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1,416</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">2</cell>
                            <cell role="data">663</cell>
                            <cell role="data">663</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1,326</cell>
                            <cell role="data">663</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">3</cell>
                            <cell role="data">238</cell>
                            <cell role="data">238</cell>
                            <cell role="data">714</cell>
                            <cell role="data">476</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">4</cell>
                            <cell role="data">67</cell>
                            <cell role="data">67</cell>
                            <cell role="data">268</cell>
                            <cell role="data">201</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">5</cell>
                            <cell role="data">20</cell>
                            <cell role="data">20</cell>
                            <cell role="data">100</cell>
                            <cell role="data">80</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">6</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2</cell>
                            <cell role="data">12</cell>
                            <cell role="data">10</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">7</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2</cell>
                            <cell role="data">14</cell>
                            <cell role="data">12</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Total</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2,408</cell>
                            <cell role="data">992</cell>
                            <cell role="data">3,850</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1,442</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>By lexical processing the censorship recording in the catalogue, we were able
                        to automatically identify the cases where more than one censor was
                        responsible for a censorship mission. Part of these cases were identified by
                        having the censors’ signatures on the same page with a single mention of the
                        year of the censorship (e.g. Alessandro Scipione 1597 (275b); Dominico
                        Irosolomitano (275b)) like in the example of the campaign of expurgation by
                        a censorship committee that was in Mantua in 1595-1597 (see below). Other
                        cases were identified by their unique form of the censor’s approval text
                        which explicitly mentions the multiple censors as in the following example:
                            <quote rend="inline" xml:lang="la">Subsignavi ego Guidus menotius ...
                            Jac Geraldini ... 28 Marti 1556</quote>. <note>In English (from Latin):
                                <quote rend="inline">I signed Guidus menotius ... Jac Geraldini ...
                                28 Mars 1556</quote>.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Temporal analysis of the dataset</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Censorship Events Dates</head>
                        <p>We first looked at the years when the censorship actually took place and
                            have used for this analysis the subset of the 2,901 precisely dated CEs
                            out of the whole set of 3,850 CEs in the database. We have plotted a
                            5-year bin-based histogram of 2,901 dated CEs (see <ref
                                target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref>). The immediate observation from
                            inspecting the histogram in Figure 3 is that although the recorded range
                            of manuscript censorship in Italy is 222 years long (1554-1775), the
                            majority of the censorship events took place during a much shorter
                            period. The first substantial narrower period corresponds to the years
                            1589-1602 (with 36.0% of the total dated CEs) and the second substantial
                            period corresponds to the years 1607-1629 (with 49.1% of the total dated
                            CEs).</p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure03">
                            <head>Number of the dated CEs (1550-1775) (2,901 cases).</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>This wave-like distribution of CEs along the study time period supports
                            the historical knowledge we have about censorship activity in Italy.
                            Much of the censorship was performed in accordance with the instructions
                            of the church and local leaders and was the result of the activity of a
                            number of censors who were active in certain years. The first big wave
                            corresponds to the years 1589-1602 (with 36% of the total dated CEs).
                            This reflects the big campaign of expurgation by a censorship committee
                            that was in Mantua in 1595-1597. On August, 27th the bishop of Mantua
                            appointed a committee of censors of the Jewish books in Mantua. Domenico
                            Irosolimitano, determined by our analysis as the most dominant censor in
                            the corpus, was the head of the Censorship Committee in Mantuain
                            1595-1597, and the author of <title rend="italic">Sefer Ha-Ziquq</title>
                                (<title rend="italic">The Book of Purification</title>) <ptr
                                target="#baruchson-arbib2007"/>. Sefer Ha-Ziquq is an index of
                            forbidden Hebrew books specifying the corrections required for each of
                            them. This censorship committee was active in the years 1595-1597 and
                            censored hundreds of books and manuscripts <ptr
                                target="#baruchson-arbib1993"/>
                            <ptr target="#baruchson-arbib2007"/>. The second wave in 1607-1629 (with
                            49.2% of the total dated CEs) corresponds to the activity of two
                            prolific censors: Camillo Jagel da Correggio and Giovanni Domenico
                            Carretto. Camillo Jagel was active from 1611-1629 <ptr
                                target="#popper1899"/>. He began his activity as a censor in 1611 in
                            Lugo (Segra, 1977-1980), which we quantitatively verified by detecting
                            26 censorship signatures with his signature with the year 1611 and with
                            the place named Lugo. There are an additional 50 censorship cases with
                            Camillo Jagel’s signature dated to 1611, but lacking any place
                            reference. We inferred that these cases are based in Lugo as well. In
                            1613-1614 Jagel was in charge of expurgating Hebrew books in Modena and
                            according to Francesconi's (2012) findings he also wrote censorship
                            rules, lists of books to be censored and lists of passages to be erased
                                <ptr target="#francesconi2012"/>. After that, in 1619-1620, Jagel
                            was active in Ancona <ptr target="#popper1899"/>.</p>
                        <p>Giovanni Domenico Carretto served as a censor in 1607-1628, mainly in
                            1617-1619 when he was appointed to the position of censor of Mantua <ptr
                                target="#popper1899"/>. These two waves can be decomposed into a few
                            micro-waves as shown by our findings (Figure 11).</p>
                        <p>Regarding the research question of the periods of censorship activity,
                            the findings discussed above show that the censorship activity is not
                            uniformally spread over time. There are periods of increased activity
                            and periods of a <q>calmer</q> nature. Whereas there is a direct
                            correlation between the first wave of censorship (mainly 1595-1597 in
                            Mantua) to the censorship committee appointed to at that same time in
                            Mantua, there is no direct historical event that can be attributed to
                            the second censorship wave. It is, however, known that during different
                            Popes' ruling periods, an inclination to force a stricter censorship
                            policy or, on the contrary, to mitigate such activity was expressed <ptr
                                target="#raz-krakotzkin2007"/>. In a broader perspective, it will be
                            interesting to compare the trend of Hebrew literature censorship
                            activity to the Church censorship of prohibited books in general. It
                            might be discovered that <q>lower</q> activity periods are associated
                            both with Jewish and general non-Jewish texts alike and can be
                            attributed to different Papal periods.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Creation Events' Dates</head>
                        <p>Overall, Hebrew manuscript creation during the last millennium was
                            influenced by many factors. Examination of the distribution of the
                            entire dated CRE set in Italy in Figure 4 (the grey bars), shows major
                            changes in the rate of manuscripts creation over the years. This dataset
                            comprises 3,213 CUs with a known creation place – Italy, and with a
                            known precise or approximate creation time. In cases when only an
                            approximate date (range of dates rather than a specific year) of the CRE
                            was provided in the catalogue, the CRE was assigned a random year within
                            the given range. </p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure04">
                            <head>Counts of newly created manuscripts in Italy (grey bars) and
                                counts of manuscript censorship actions (red bars) (1200-1775) –
                                dated only CREs and CEs.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>There is a sharp rise in the rate of manuscript creation in Italy in the
                            14th century compared to earlier times. Then, during the 15th century
                            the manuscript creation rate is doubled. But in the 16th century we see
                            lower rates compared to the previous century with a growing rate during
                            the 1st half of the 16th century and a rather sharp decline in the 2nd
                            half of the century continuing in the 17th century with a lowest rate
                            point around 1700. From about that point, manuscript creation rates
                            start to rise again with a pick of manuscript creation rate around 1800.
                            From the middle of the 19th century we see an expected decline in
                            creating new manuscripts.</p>
                        <p>In order to investigate a possible relationship between the different
                            periods of high and low manuscript creation rates and the periods of
                            censorship activities, we plotted the censorship activity histogram on
                            top of the manuscript creation event histogram on the same time axis
                            (see the red bars in <ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>). It can be
                            noticed that the first declining period in CREs that starts around 1475
                            is not correlated with censorship activity as this have started only 75
                            years later, this decline is probably attributable to the invention of
                            the printing press.</p>
                        <p>However, the second manuscript creation declining period which starts in
                            1590, right after the beginning of substantial censorship activity,
                            might be influenced by substantial censorship activity in the closely
                            preceding and following time periods (<ref target="#figure04">Figure
                                4</ref>). During the period of high censorship activity (the 41-year
                            period between 1589 and 1629), Hebrew manuscript creation level in Italy
                            was relatively lower compared to all other times in the period of
                            1375-1775.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Spatial analysis of the dataset</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Censorship Events Locations</head>
                        <p>When signing the censorship action, the censors, in most cases, added the
                            date of the signature (mostly the year and in few cases the full date),
                            but they very rarely (only in 71 cases, less than 2%) specified the
                            place where this censorship had been performed and signed. </p>
                        <p>In order to complete the missing information on CEs locations we used
                            ontological relationships between events, censors, time periods and
                            locations and the information from the Pooper's list of Italian censors
                            (Popper, 1889). In this list, Pooper recorded all the censors known to
                            him in alphabetical order. For each censor he noted the years and places
                            of his activity. For example, the censor Alessandro Scipione was active
                            in Mantua in the years 1589-1590 and 1593-1598; Camillo Jagel was in
                            Lugo in 1611, in Modena-Reggio in 1613-1614 and in Ancona in 1619-1620.
                            We also used a newer study on the censor Domenico Irosolimitano that
                            gave us more information on his activity as a censor <ptr
                                target="#prebor2007"/>. Thus, given a CE’s censor name and date we
                            could infer its location from the corresponding location in the Pooper’s
                            list. As a result, we obtained places of censorship for 2,077 (53.9%)
                            out of all the CEs in the corpus. Eight of the inferred places did not
                            appear in the original list of 12 places that have been recorded in the
                            catalogue: Ferrara, Milano, Monreale, Turin, Venice, Modena-Reggio,
                            Ancona and the Papal States. In 1452–1796, 1814–1859 Modena and Reggio
                            were part of the Duchy of Modena and Reggio. The place name <q>Papal
                                States</q>, refers to a whole region which was at that time under
                            the Pope's rule. In different periods this region included different
                            parts of Northern Italy. Figure 5 displays the CEs geographic
                            distribution on a map.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure05">
                            <head>Places of censorship events (explicitly mentioned in the catalogue
                                and inferred) on Italy's map (2,077 CEs).</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>As can be seen in Figure 5 the distribution of places of censorship
                            events are spread out in various places in the Italian peninsula,
                            especially in the north. This uneven distribution, which as stated above
                            was dependant on the individual censor involved, also supports the
                            historical knowledge we have about censorship activity in Italy. Much of
                            the censorship was performed in accordance with the instructions of the
                            church and local leaders and was the result of the activity of a number
                            of censors who were active in certain places. The two places with the
                            highest censorship events are Mantua and Modena.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Script type analysis</head>
                    <p>Another aspect of spatial analysis can be learned from the script types of
                        the censored manuscripts. Hebrew manuscripts have been written in many
                        scripts that varied from region to region, each with its typical script
                        type. The Sephardic script, for example, is the typical script used by
                        Sephardic scribes who worked within the Jewish community in the Iberian
                        Peninsula. Since censored manuscripts were in the possession of the Jewish
                        community in Italy, analyzing the distribution of their script types may
                        provide new (quantitatively) perspectives of the extent of the transition of
                        manuscripts from outside regions into Italy as well as on the immigration of
                        non-Italian Jewish scribes who continued to write with the script type of
                        their homeland and education <ptr target="#beit-arié2018"/>.</p>
                    <p>Five main branches of script types were proposed in the literature: Eastern
                        script (which includes the Yemenite script and Persian script subtypes);
                        Sephardic script; Ashkenazic script; Italian script and Byzantine script
                            <ptr target="#beit-arié2018"/><ptr target="#richler1990"/>. The
                        catalogue named more than 70 distinct Hebrew script types. As a first step
                        of the analysis, we have compiled a list of 17 script type classes with an
                        additional <term>Miscellaneous</term> category for the rest of the scripts:
                        Ashkenazic Script, Italian Script, Eastern Script, Sephardic Script,
                        Yemenite Script, Western Script, Byzantine Script, Karaite Script, Persian
                        Script, Provencal Script, Samaritan Script, Ashkenazic-Italian Script,
                        Sephardic-Eastern Script, Sephardic-Provencal Script, Sephardic-Italian
                        Script, Sephardic-Western Script, Typewriter and Miscellaneous. Next, we
                        classified all the manuscripts into seven unified script classes
                            (<term>ustypes</term> for short). For instance, the Sephardic unified
                        script class was assigned to all manuscripts with variants of the Sephardic
                        Script (e.g. Sephardic-Eastern script, Sephardic-Western script and
                        Sephardic- Provencal script).</p>
                    <p>We then examined the distribution of the seven ustypes amongst 5,015 censored
                        manuscripts and compared it to their distribution among a set of 72,233
                        non-censored manuscripts (overall, 77,248 manuscripts were created before
                        1700 as almost no censorship took place afterwards). The result of this
                        comparison is depicted in Figure 6.<note>The two subsets of censored and
                            non-censored manuscripts contain slightly less manuscripts than all the
                            dated manuscripts before 1700 as few manuscripts lack script type
                            information (e.g. of the 5,046 dated manuscripts created before 1700 in
                            the 1st subset, 31 manuscripts are not included as they lack script
                            style indication).</note></p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Unified script types distribution for 77,248 manuscripts created
                            before 1700).</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>It can be immediately observed that the Italian script type is the dominant
                        one amongst the censored manuscripts (59.9%) compared to this script
                        occurrence percentage (only 19.9%) amongst the non-censored manuscript
                        created during the same time period. There was a significant difference in
                        script type distribution between the censored and non-censored corpora,
                        χ2(6)=118.21, p&lt;0.0001. This implies that a major part of the manuscripts
                        in the possession of Italian Jews at that time were probably written by this
                        community, namely, written in Hebrew with an Italian script type. This
                        finding also strengthens the results of Beit-Arié that the Italian script
                        was the most frequent one (55%) used in the manuscripts written in Italy
                        before 1540 <ptr target="#beit-arié2018"/>. These results can be explained
                        by Italy being the centre of the Catholic Church on the one hand, as well as
                        being a prominent centre of rich Jewish life and culture, on the other
                        hand.</p>
                    <p>The presence of manuscripts written in other script types can be explained by
                        manuscripts brought/bought by Italian Jews at different times as well by the
                        use of these writing scripts by newcomer Jews. We show that 17.4% of the
                        censored manuscripts were written in the Sephardic script which is an
                        indication of the (mainly forced) immigration of Sephardic Jews into this
                        region. This script type is found in only 14.0% of the non-censored scripts
                        which strengthen the indication of a major transition of Sephardic Jews into
                        Italy, compared to all other regions. Another well recognized fact confirmed
                        from this comparative analysis is regarding Yemenite manuscripts. From
                        Figure 6, one can infer that almost no manuscript written in Yemen arrived
                        in Italy before 1700, as there are no censored manuscripts found that were
                        written in the Yemenite script type. Thus, through analysis of script types
                        we can indirectly identify migrations (or the lack of migrations) of Jews
                        (with scribes among them) and partly answer research question number 1c
                        (other parts of this paper discuss other types of geographic migrations,
                        those of the manuscripts themselves, this time) see also in: <ref
                            target="#prebor2019">Prebor, Zhitomirsky-Geffet &amp; Miller
                            (2019)</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Analysis of the locations of manuscripts' storage events</head>
                    <p>Another indication of the migration of manuscripts (albeit, through a later
                        time span) is their current location. The original Hebrew manuscripts that
                        are documented in the catalogue of the Department of Manuscripts and the
                        Institute of Microfilmed Hebrew Manuscripts in the National Library of
                        Israel belong primarily to public collections held by many public
                        institutions (mainly academic or municipal/governmental libraries) or to
                        private collections all over the world. As part of our research we wanted to
                        shed light on the distribution of censored manuscripts in these
                        institutions. We found that the Hebrew manuscript corpus is spread across
                        1,133 different institutions around the globe (see <ref target="#figure07"
                            >Figure 7)</ref>. 37.6% of them are stored in Israel's libraries (the
                        majority are in the National Library of Israel in Jerusalem), 16.3% - in the
                        United States and 15.7% are located in Russia. </p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure07">
                        <head>Number of manuscripts (BUs) in countries' libraries.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>However, the picture for the censored manuscripts is quite different as can
                        be viewed in Figure 8.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Number of censored manuscripts (BUs) in countries' libraries for all
                            2,449 censored BUs (including those censored after 1775 in non-Italian
                            regions).</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The largest portion of the censored manuscripts is still stored in Italy and
                        the Vatican City: 35.6%. This portion is much higher than the portion of
                        Hebrew manuscripts in general found in Italy and Vatican City out of all
                        Hebrew manuscripts (5%). This is another indication of the censored
                        manuscripts being primarily written in Italy, as well as an indication of a
                        relatively high retention rate (i.e. archiving) of material of this nature
                        in a close proximity to where it was originally written/possessed.</p>
                    <p>Yet, the majority of censored manuscripts were transferred over the centuries
                        to institutions outside Italy as shown in Figure 8. Following Italy are the
                        United Kingdom (20.5%) and France (10.3%). Israel is only sixth with a 5.5%
                        share.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Subject-related analysis of the manuscripts</head>
                    <p>Catalogue records include subjects from the Library of Congress Subject
                        Headings (LCSH) (<ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects.html"
                            >http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects.html</ref>). Each manuscript
                        record was assigned multiple subjects which were sometimes too specific.</p>
                    <p>In order to determine what were the main subjects of the censored manuscripts
                        and whether there is a difference in the distribution of censored vs.
                        non-censored manuscripts among subjects, we created a list of 13 general
                        topics. The list of 13 subjects that generalize and group together some
                        hundreds of subjects from the catalogue are: Popular Beliefs and Magic,
                        Ancient Rabbinic Biblical Exegesis, Non-Legalistic Exegesis and Homilies,
                        Science, Philosophy and Ethics, History, Mishna and Talmud Commentaries,
                        Jewish Legal Texts, Liturgy, Bible and Commentaries, Kabbalah and Mysticism,
                        Letters and Belles Lettres, Grammar. The Miscellaneous category includes
                        Karaite literature, Jewish apocrypha, list of names, polemic, Gematria. For
                        each censored manuscript we asked an expert researcher to assign subjects
                        from the above list (thus, a single manuscript may have been assigned more
                        than one subject).</p>
                    <p>In order to compare the distribution of the subjects in the censored
                        manuscript corpus to that in the non-censored manuscript corpus, a random
                        sample of 857 non-censored manuscripts written before 1700 was
                        subject-annotated by our expert as well (with subjects from the above list
                        only). For this analysis, we used a subset of 5,046 censored CUs that were
                        created before 1700. The results are depicted in Figure 9.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Top subject distribution in the censored and non-censored manuscript
                            sample created before 1700, for 5,046 censored CUs and 857 non-censored
                            CUs.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>We found significant differences in subject distribution for censored vs.
                        non-censored manuscripts, χ2(7)=14.525, p&lt;0.05. The three major
                        differences are in the <term>Kabbalah and Mysticism</term>, <term>Philosophy
                            and Ethics</term>, and <term>Liturgy</term> that were censored
                        significantly more than other subjects. Subjects with percentages of 5% and
                        lower are included in Miscellaneous in Figure 9.</p>
                    <p>The subject analysis of the censored manuscripts might shed light on the
                        goals of the censorship activity. We found that the most censored subject
                        was <term>Kabbalah and Mysticism</term>, 20% of the censored manuscripts
                        belong to this subject (compared to only 14% of the non-censored
                        manuscripts). This is not surprising since in the 16th century Kabbalah
                        study became more widespread in Jewish culture and a debate arose over the
                        printing of Kabbalistic literature. In this period, Kabbalah also attracted
                        the attention of Christian scholars. Several Kabbalistic works were
                        translated into Latin, and the interest and preoccupation with Kabbalah
                        became wider. The main reason why Christian scholars expressed interest in
                        Kabbalah is the similarity they saw in some of the foundations of the
                        Kabbalah and the principles of the Christian faith. It is impossible to
                        ignore the historical context of the debate over Kabbalah literature in the
                        Jewish world in the period of the highest Catholic censorship activity when
                        each body acted out of its own motivations and goals <ptr
                            target="#raz-krakotzkin2007"/>
                        <ptr target="#weiss2016"/>. The second most censored subject is Philosophy
                        and Ethics (17% of the censored corpus compared to only 11.4% in the
                        non-censored corpus). The books of philosophy that deal with the core of
                        faith and content that can harm Christian faith, such as Rabbi Joseph Albo's
                            <title rend="italic">Sefer ha-Ikkarim</title> (<title rend="italic">The
                            Book of Principles</title>), which has the most comprehensive censorship
                        requirements in Sefer Ha-Ziquq <ptr target="#prebor2003"/>. The third
                        subject with a significant difference between the percentage of censored and
                        non-censored manuscripts is Liturgy. The ecclesiastical supervision of
                        liturgical books, especially in the Ashkenazi <term>mahzorim</term>
                        (festival prayer books), was massive because they contained anti-Christian
                        piyyutim (liturgical poems) and many expressions condemning the nations and
                        the Christian faith <ptr target="#benayahu1971"/>
                        <ptr target="#raz-krakotzkin2007"/>. The prayer books and the
                            <term>mahzorim</term> were the most popular category in the libraries of
                        the Jews of Mantua <ptr target="#baruchson-arbib1993"/>. The percentages of
                        the top-censored subjects partially correlate with the numbers of the
                        required corrections for various subjects specified in <title rend="italic"
                            >Sefer Ha-Ziquq</title>. The highest number of corrections (24 on
                        average) in <title rend="italic">Sefer Ha-Ziquq</title> is required for the
                        Liturgy subject and Kabballah is ranked third (with 16 corrections required
                        on average) following the ancient rabbinic biblical exegesis and
                        non-legalistic exegesis subject (Prebor, 2003). In contrast, we found more
                            <q>neutral</q> subjects that did not catch the censors' attention,
                        subjects with <q>non-problematic</q> content. This includes Karaite
                        literature, apocrypha, lists of names, polemics, gematria, letters and
                        belles-lettres, science, popular beliefs and magic, and history.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Analysis of the individual censor activity</head>
                    <p>The National Library cataloguers have identified 65 censors that worked in
                        Italy between 1554 and 1775. Some of the censors were very active with
                        hundreds of signed censorship actions, while others only appeared in 1, 2 or
                        3 CEs (censorship events). Figure 10 displays the counts of CEs for the
                        top-20 censors (out of the 65) that were involved in at least 15 CEs.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Number of CEs per censor (only for censors involved in at least 15
                            CEs). </head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Distribution of CEs for the top-4 censors (and all censors)
                            1590-1630.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure11.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>As shown in Figure 10 the most active censor was Domenico Irosolimitano.
                        Figure 11 displays his (and three additional most dominant censors’)
                        activity on a timeline. Domenico Irosolimitano acted mainly from 1595 to
                        1602 (the pick year is 1597) and then again in 1612. His signature is found
                        in 671 manuscripts (about 19% of all CEs) although only 378 (56.3%) of them
                        has a date of censorship. Domenico Irosolimitano was not the first censor to
                        act in Italy. He was preceded by several censors (Caesar Belliosus, Jacob
                        Geraldini, Guido Menotius, Hieronymus Caralus and Laurentius Franguellus)
                        that worked between 1554 and 1589, but each of these censors is responsible
                        to only few dozens of CEs. </p>
                    <p>The censors’ frames in Figure 11 are presented in chronological order of
                        their activity. Thus, the next censor (chronologically) is Luigi da Bologna
                        who acted mainly between 1597 and 1602. Unlike Domenico Irosolimitano who
                        has quite an exceptional pick year, the CEs of Luigi da Bologna are more
                        evenly spread along its active years and are virtually all dated (326 out of
                        351). The third censor, Camillo Jagel, acted mainly in three years: 1611,
                        1613 (the pick year) and 1619. Camillo Jagel was responsible for 371 CEs
                        (356 of them are dated). The fourth censor in Figure 11, Giovanni Domenico
                        Carretto, acted mainly in 1617-1619 (the pick year - 1618). He is the second
                        most active censor after Domenico Irosolimitano with 572 CEs (552 of them
                        are dated). </p>
                    <p>The last frame in Figure 11 shows the overall censorship activity
                        distribution over time. As can be observed, the CEs are not evenly
                        distributed along the timeline. There were four main micro-waves of
                        censorship activity in 1595-1602, 1608-1613, 1617-1619 and around 1626.
                        These micro-waves generally match the activity periods of the four most
                        dominant censors discussed above. </p>
                    <p>To complete the censor-related CEs analysis we performed a detailed breakdown
                        of the CEs over time for the top eight places (including “the Papal States”)
                        that have at least 30 CEs. The result is shown in Figure 12 (these places
                        refer to 96.7% of the CEs with known or inferred locations: 2,009 out of
                        2,077). The figure also demonstrates the relative part of CEs that are
                        associated with each of the most prominent censors (Domenico Irosolimitano,
                        Camillo Jagel, Luigi da Bologna and Giovanni Domenico Carretto, represented
                        with different colors).</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Distribution of CEs in top eight places (years: 1550-1690) (2,009
                            CEs), the colors correspond to the most dominant censors involved in
                            each place. </head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure12.png"/>

                    </figure>
                    <p>From Figure 12 it can be observed that in some places the censorship took
                        place during a very short period (sometimes of one or two years), e.g. in
                        Lugo, Ancona, Urbino and the Papal States. Censors’ movements in time and
                        geographic locations can be traced as well, e.g. Domenico Irosolimitano
                        (denoted by the red color in the chart circles) moved from Mantua to Ferrara
                        and then to Rome, and Camillo Jagel (marked by the green color) moved from
                        Modena-Reggio to Lugo and later to Ancona. Also, it can be noticed that
                        Rome's CEs are mainly attributed to Domenico Irosolimitano, who was also a
                        dominant censor in Ferrara and Mantua. Camillo Jagel is responsible for
                        virtually all censorship in Lugo and Ancona. Modena-Reggio CEs are mainly
                        executed by Luigi da Bologna with some noticeable contribution of Camillo
                        Jagel (the late CEs in the 1640's are Girolamo da Durazzano's). Finally,
                        Mantua's censorship was performed by Domenico Irosolimitano (in the early
                        period until 1603), while more than half of the CEs in 1617-1619 are
                        attributed to Giovanni Domenico Carretto. The CEs in the Papal States were
                        almost entirely signed by Caesar Belliosus and in Urbino all CEs were signed
                        by Antonio Francesco Enriques (not in the list of the top four censors).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>This study presents the first large-scale quantitative analysis of the corpus of
                    censored historical Hebrew manuscripts that survived through the centuries,
                    particularly focusing on Catholic Church censorship in Italy. The primarily
                    methodological contributions of this study include the following:</p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>Definition of the generic data model of the Manuscript catalogue
                        records.</item>
                    <item>A new multi-dimensional ontology-based approach for historical data
                        analysis from the geographic, temporal, actor- and subject-based
                        perspectives. </item>
                    <item>Utilizing previous studies results and ontological relationships for
                        automated rule-based inference of over 50% of missing locations of
                        censorship events.</item>
                    <item>Comparative analysis of censored vs. non-censored manuscript
                        corpora.</item>
                    <item>Qualitative examination of the quantitative results in light of the extant
                        literature and their historical and cultural context.</item>
                </list>
                <p>We found that the two centres of the most massive censorship in the history of
                    Hebrew manuscripts were Mantua with 832 CEs and Modena-Reggio with 741 CEs.
                    Also, rule-based inference helped discover eight censorship locations which did
                    not appear in the catalogue. The time periods of the most intensive censorship
                    activity in Italy were 1589-1602 and 1607-1629. The most active censors in Italy
                    were Domenico Irosolimitano (671 CEs) and Camillo Jagel (572 CEs). </p>
                <p>The distribution of the censored manuscript corpus differed from that of the
                    non-censored corpus in several dimensions, e.g. by subjects, script types and
                    storage locations. Furthermore, the following trends in censorship activity were
                    discovered by our analysis: </p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>A few big and micro-waves of censorship during the time period of the
                        study;</item>
                    <item>Geographic mobility of manuscripts, their creators and censors over time
                        (the script types' distribution reflects the dominance of the Italian script
                        along with a significant transition of scribes from Spain); </item>
                    <item>Current locations of the manuscripts (interestingly, as opposed to the
                        entire corpus, censored manuscripts were less geographically mobile and are
                        still mostly located in Italian libraries);</item>
                    <item>Censorship influence on the Jewish literature in terms of applying more
                        restrains on the “problematic subjects” (e.g. Kabbalah and Philosophy) and
                        indirectly reducing new manuscript creation (our findings show a substantial
                        retention in writing new manuscript during the pick periods of censorship
                        activity).</item>
                    <item>Repetitive censorship as a phenomenon (41% of the censored manuscript in
                        the corpus were censored more than once, while only 2% of the censored
                        manuscripts were collaboratively censored by two or more censors at the same
                        time and location).</item>
                </list>
                <p>The above results show the power of a large-scale statistical analysis of the
                    well-structured ontological data of the manuscripts. Firstly, the perspective of
                    known phenomena was reinforced by a concrete number, for example, the migrations
                    of Sephardic scribes to Italy. Also, the quantitative findings help determine
                    whether a phenomenon is negligible as in the case of the small number of mutual
                    co-censorship or substantial as in the case of repeating censorship. Secondly,
                    new, previously not identified, insights were discovered. For example the
                    relative restraint in creating manuscripts of “problematic subjects” manuscripts
                    during periods of intense censorship.</p>
                <p>This research has also some limitations, since Hebrew manuscripts are hosted in
                    many different libraries around the globe, the metadata recorded in the
                    catalogue is based mostly on microfilms or digitized images, and only in a few
                    cases the cataloguers inspected the codices themselves. In addition, the
                    catalogue of the Department of Manuscripts and Institute of Microfilmed Hebrew
                    Manuscripts was created during a 70-year period by many different people. A
                    large part of the catalogue was copied from catalogues of manuscripts in various
                    libraries in other countries and contains only partial information. The rules of
                    cataloging have changed over time. Therefore, there might be some mistakes in
                    the catalogue data, but according to our arbitrary inspection, their proportion
                    is relatively small and have no significant impact on the big picture of the
                    studied phenomena. </p>
                <p>In future work we plan to analyse more ontological event types, and extend the
                    methodology for automated discovery and correction of catalogue mistakes as well
                    as the completion of missing data.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgements">
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>This research has been funded by the Israel Science Foundation, grant no.
                    345/15.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ayers201" label="Ayers 2010">Ayers, E. L. <title rend="quotes">Turning
                        towards Place, Space, and Time</title>. In D. J. Bodenhamer, J. Corrigan and
                    T. M. Harris (eds), <title rend="italic">The Spatial Humanities: GIS and the
                        Future of Humanities Scholarship</title>, Bloomington (2010), pp.
                    1-13.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="beit-arié2018" label="Beit-Arié 2018">Beit-Arié, M. <title
                        rend="italic">Hebrew Codicology. Historical and Comparative Typology of
                        Medieval Hebrew Codices based on the Documentation of the Extant Dated
                        Manuscripts until 1540 from a Quantitative Approach</title>, Preprint
                    internet English version 0.2 (November 2018). Retrieved June 05, 2019 from: <ref
                        target="https://web.nli.org.il/sites/NLI/English/collections/manuscripts/hebrewcodicology/Pages/default.aspx"
                        >
                        https://web.nli.org.il/sites/NLI/English/collections/manuscripts/hebrewcodicology/Pages/default.aspx</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="baruchson-arbib1993" label="Baruchson-Arbib 1993">Baruchson-Arbib, S.
                        <title rend="italic">Books and Readers</title>, Bar-Ilan University Press,
                    Ramat-Gun. (1993).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="baruchson-arbib2007" label="Baruchson-Arbib 2007"> .Baruchson-Arbib,
                    S. and Prebor, G. <title rend="quotes">Sefer Ha-Ziquq: (An Index of forbidden
                        Hebrew books: The Book's use and its influence on Hebrew Printing</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">La Bibliofilia</title>, CIX (1) (2007): 3-31.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="benayahu1971" label="Benayahu 1971">Benayahu, M. <title rend="italic"
                        >Haskama VeReshut in Venetian Printed Books</title>, Ben-Zvi Institute
                    Mossad Harav Kook, Jerusalem. (1971).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burrows2012" label="Burrows and Curran 2012">Burrows, S. and Curran,
                    M. <title rend="quotes">The French Book Trade in Enlightenment Europe Project
                        and the STN Database</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital
                        Humanities</title>, 1 (3) (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chandna2016" label="Chandna et al. 2016">Chandna, S., Rindone, F.,
                    Dachsbacher, C., and Stotzka, R. <title rend="quotes">Quantitative exploration
                        of large medieval manuscripts data for the codicological research</title>.
                    In <title rend="italic">Large Data Analysis and Visualization (LDAV), 2016 IEEE
                        6th Symposium</title>, October 2016: 20-28.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ethington2007" label="Ethington 2007">Ethington, P. J. <title
                        rend="quotes">Placing the past: <q>Groundwork</q> for a spatial theory of
                        history</title>, <title rend="italic">Rethinking History</title>, 11 (4)
                    (2007): 465-493.‏</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="francesconi2012" label="Francesconi 2012">Francesconi, F. <title
                        rend="quotes">This passage can also be read differently…: How Jews and
                        Christians censored Hebrew texts in early modern Modena</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Jewish History</title>, 26 (1-2) (2012): 139-160.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="francesconi2016" label="Francesconi 2016">Francesconi, F. <title
                        rend="quotes">Illustrious Rabbis Facing the Italian Inquisition:
                        Accommodating Censorship in Seventeenth-Century Italy</title>. In <title
                        rend="italic">Jewish Books and their Readers</title>, Brill (2016), pp.
                    100-121.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="glinka2017" label="Glinka et al. 2017">Glinka, K., Pietsch, C. and
                    Dörk M., <title rend="quotes">Past Visions and Reconciling Views: Visualizing
                        Time, Texture and Themes in Cultural Collections</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quaterly</title>, 11 (2) (2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gregory2007" label="Gregory and Healey 2007">Gregory, I. N. and
                    Healey, R. G. <title rend="quotes">Historical GIS: structuring, mapping and
                        analysing geographies of the past</title>, <title rend="italic">Progress in
                        Human Geography</title>, 31(5) (2007): 638-653.‏</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kaplan2017" label="Kaplan and de Lenardo 2017">Kaplan, F., and di
                    Lenardo, I. <title rend="quotes">Big Data of the Past</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Frontiers in Digital Humanities</title>, 4, 12 (2017).‏</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="knowles2008" label="Knowles and Hillier 2008">Knowles, A. K and
                    Hillier, A. (Eds.). <title rend="italic">Placing history: how maps, spatial
                        data, and GIS are changing historical scholarship</title>. Redlands, ESRI
                    Press. (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="leizeng2017" label="Lei Zeng 2017">Lei Zeng, M. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Smart Data for digital humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of
                        Information and Documentation</title>, 2 (1), (2017): 1-2.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moretti2005" label="Moretti 2005">Moretti, F. <title rend="italic"
                        >Graphs, maps, trees: abstract models for a literary history</title>.
                    London, Verso. (2005).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="phillips2016" label="Phillips 2016">Phillips, A. E. <title
                        rend="quotes">Censorship of hebrew books on sixteenth century Italy: a
                        review of a decade of english and french language
                        scholarship</title>, <title rend="italic">Bibliofilia</title>, 118 (3)
                    (2016): 409-425.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="prebor2003" label="Prebor 2003">Prebor, G. <title rend="italic">Sepher
                        Ha-Ziquq by Domenico Yerushalmi (1555-1621) and its Influence on Hebrew
                        Printing</title>. Ph.D. thesis, Bar-Ilan University (2003). (In
                    Hebrew).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="prebor2007" label="Prebor 2007">Prebor, G. <title rend="quotes">From
                        Jerusalem to Venice: The Life of Domenico Yerushalmi, his writings and his
                        work as a Censor</title>. <title rend="italic">Pe'amim</title>, 111-112
                    (2007): 215-242. (In Hebrew).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="prebor2019" label="Prebor et al. 2019">Prebor, G., Zhitomirsky-Geffet,
                    M. and Miller, Y. (2019). <title rend="quotes">A new analytic framework for
                        prediction of migration patterns and locations of historical manuscripts
                        based on their script types</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital
                        Scholarship in the Humanities</title>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="popper1899" label="Popper 1899">Popper, W. <title rend="italic">The
                        Censorship of Hebrew Books</title>. The Knickerbocker press, New York.
                    (1899).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="raz-krakotzkin2007" label="Raz-Krakotzkin 2007">Raz-Krakotzkin, A.
                        <title rend="italic">The Censor, the Editor, and the Text: The Catholic
                        Church and the Shaping of the Jewish Canon in the Sixteenth Century</title>.
                    University of Pennsylvania Press, Philadelphia. (2007). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sonne1942" label="Sonne 1942">Sonne, I. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Expurgation of Hebrew Books</title>, <title rend="italic">Bulletin of the
                        New York Public Library</title>, XLVI,(1942): 975-1015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="richler1990" label="Richler 1990">Richler, B.  <title rend="italic"
                        >Hebrew manuscripts: a treasured legacy</title>, Ofeq Institute, Cleveland.
                    (1990).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sirat2002" label="Sirat 2002">Sirat, C. <title rend="italic">Hebrew
                        manuscripts of the Middle Ages</title>. New York: Cambridge University
                    Press, Cambridge. (2002).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vanboxel2016" label="van Boxel 2016">van Boxel, P. <title
                        rend="italic">Jewish books in Christian hands: theology, exegesis and
                        conversion under Gregory XIII (1572-1585)</title>. Biblioteca apostolica
                    vaticana, (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vanhooland2014" label="Van Hooland and Verborgh 2014">Van Hooland, S.
                    and Verborgh, R. <title rend="italic">Linked Data for Libraries, Archives and
                        Museums: How to clean, link and publish your metadata</title>. Neal-Schuman,
                    Chicago. (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weiss2016" label="Weiss 2016">Weiss, J. <title rend="italic">A
                        Kabbalistic Christian Messiah in the Renaissance</title>. Hakibbutz
                    Hameuhad, Bnei Brak. (2016). (In Hebrew).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zhitomirsky-geffet2016" label="Zhitomirsky-Geffet and Prebor 2016"
                    >Zhitomirsky-Geffet, M., and Prebor, G. <title rend="quotes">Toward an Ontopedia
                        for Historical Hebrew Manuscripts</title>. <title rend="italic">Frontiers in
                        Digital Humanities</title>, 3 (3) (2016).‏</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
