<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
	xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
	xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
	xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
				<title type="article" xml:lang="en">Networked Cross-Dressing: A Digital
					Refashioning of Shakespearean Gender Subversion</title>
				<!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Erik <dhq:family>Simpson</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<dhq:affiliation>Grinnell College</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>simpsone@grinnell.edu</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Erik Simpson is Professor of English and Samuel R. and Marie-Louise
							Rosenthal Professor of Humanities at Grinnell College. He is the
							author of two books: <title rend="italic">Literary Minstrelsy,
								1770-1830</title> and <title rend="italic">Mercenaries in
								British and American Literature, 1790-1830: Writing,
								Fighting, and Marrying for Money</title>.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Hannah L.P. <dhq:family>Brown</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<dhq:affiliation>Department of Psychology, University of
						Florida</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>hannahbrown@ufl.edu</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Hannah L. P. Brown is a Counseling Psychology Graduate Student at
							the University of Florida whose research combines feminist and
							queer theories with practical counseling questions.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Lana <dhq:family>Sabb</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<dhq:affiliation>Grinnell College</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>N/A</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Grinnell College</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Olly <dhq:family>Shortell</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<dhq:affiliation>Prescott College</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>olly.shortell@gmail.com</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Olly Shortell is a graduate student of Clinical Mental Health
							Counseling at Prescott College.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>James <dhq:family>Lee</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<dhq:affiliation>University of Cincinnati</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>james.jlee@uc.edu</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>James Jaehoon Lee, Ph.D is the Director of the Digital Scholarship
							Center and Associate Professor of Digital Humanities at the
							University of Cincinnati. His research and teaching focus on the
							areas of digital humanities, machine learning and data mining
							techniques on historical text and image archives, social network
							analysis, and data visualization. Much of his work has used
							machine learning methods applied to large text corpora and other
							unstructured datasets to rethink what it means to perform
							historical analysis. His research also investigates ways to
							visualize the results of machine learning algorithms in a
							human-interpretable way that enables non-technical audiences to
							glean useful information from the data. More recently, his
							research has branched out into fascinating collaborations
							applying digital humanities methods with partners in biomedical
							informatics, law, design, and archeology. He is the author of
								<title rend="italic">The Two-Soul’d Animal</title>
							(Northwestern University Press, 2018) and with Dr. Jeffrey
							Blevins, <title rend="italic">Social Media, Social Justice, and
								the Political Economy of Online Networks</title> (University
							of Cincinnati Press, 2022). His third book on <title
								rend="italic">Digital Shakespeares</title> is forthcoming
							from Routledge in 2024. His research has been published in the
								<title rend="italic">Harvard Data Science Review</title>,
							the <title rend="italic">Publications of the Modern Language
								Association (PMLA)</title>, <title rend="italic">New Media
								and Society</title>, <title rend="italic">Social Media and
								Society</title>, <title rend="italic">Cultural
								Analytics</title>, <title rend="italic">New Literary
								History</title>, <title rend="italic">Post-45</title>,
								<title rend="italic">Public Books</title>, and <title
								rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the
							Humanities</title>.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
				<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
				<!--This information will be completed at publication-->
				<idno type="DHQarticle-id">000562</idno>
				<idno type="volume">016</idno>
				<idno type="issue">3</idno>
				<date when="2022-07-07">7/7/22</date>
				<dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
				<availability status="CC-BY-ND">
					<cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>This is the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
					<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en" extent="original"/>
				<!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
					<!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
					<!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
			<change when="2022-08-02" who="BRG">added abstract from OJS documentation</change>
			<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
					target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000562/000562.xml"
					>GitHub </ref></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en" type="original">
		<front>
			<dhq:abstract>
				<!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
				<p>This paper uses network theory and network analysis to propose a new approach
					to analyzing cross-dressing in Shakespearean drama, specifically the key
					questions driving much of the scholarship on that topic in recent decades:
					What kind of disruption to the social order did cross-dressing represent in
					Early Modern England, and what did it mean to shift that disruption from
					the street to the stage? We know that the laws and customs of the age
					emphasized clothing that matched the outward appearances of people to their
					places in the social order. Network analysis allows us to analyze how
					characters become gendered through a non-linear, non-hierarchical lattice
					of social relationships. As the characters interact and social
					relationships change, the individual’s gendered subjectivity also
					transforms. We find that cross-dressing protagonists propel themselves from
					isolated social worlds into a complex web of relationships through
					cross-dressing, and that entry into sociability follows predictable
					patterns. By following those patterns, the characters combine roles--the
					broker and the heroine--that are normally separate in Shakespearean comic
					plots, creating a hybrid type that becomes visible through network
					analysis.</p>
			</dhq:abstract>
			<dhq:teaser>
				<!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
				<p>Using network theory to analyze cross-dressing in Shakesperean drama.</p>
			</dhq:teaser>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div>
				<head>Introduction</head>
				<p>This paper uses network theory and network analysis to propose a new approach
					to analyzing cross-dressing in Shakespearean drama, specifically the key
					questions driving much of the scholarship on that topic in recent decades:
					What kind of disruption to the social order did cross-dressing represent in
					Early Modern England, and what did it mean to shift that disruption from
					the street to the stage? We know that the laws and customs of the age
					emphasized clothing that matched the outward appearances of people to their
					places in the social order. A letter from John Chamberlain dated 1620
					exhibits the Jacobean stakes of conventionally gendered dress: <cit><quote
							rend="block">Yesterday the bishop of London called together all
							his clergie about this towne, and told them he had expresse
							commandment from the King to will them to inveigh vehemently
							against the insolencie of our women, and theyre wearing of brode
							brimed hats, pointed dublets, theyre haire cut short or
							shorne...the truth is the world is very much out of order.
						</quote></cit> As Mary Beth Rose points out, the King’s commandment
						<quote rend="inline">amounted to a declaration of war,</quote> and the
					results of that declaration revealed that <quote rend="inline">women in
						men’s clothing had assumed threatening enough proportions in the
						conservative mind to be singled out in a conscientious and thorough
						attempt to eliminate the style from social life</quote>
					<ptr target="#rose1988" loc="70"/>. </p>
				<p>The conservatives of the time attempted, in other words, to enact the kind of
					restoration of propriety that Stephen Greenblatt perceives at the end of
					Shakespeare’s <title rend="italic">Twelfth Night</title>, in which <quote
						rend="inline">[t]he sexes are sorted out, correctly paired, and
						dismissed to bliss — or will be as soon as Viola changes her
						clothes</quote>
					<ptr target="#greenblatt1988" loc="71"/>. Indeed, one way to view much of
					the cross-dressing in Early Modern drama is to see it as a fundamentally
					conservative set of practices. From this perspective, cross-dressing allows
					actors and their audiences the pleasure of seeing binary, hierarchical
					gender relationships troubled temporarily, and not too much. Jean E. Howard
					maintains that female cross-dressers retain their <quote rend="inline"
						>properly feminine subjectivity</quote> even while dressed as men <ptr
						target="#howard1988" loc="432"/>. The heroines are then comfortably
					restored to women’s status in a conception of gender that remains, in
					Greenblatt’s phrase, <quote rend="inline">teleologically male</quote>
					<ptr target="#greenblatt1988" loc="88"/>. </p>
				<p>Other scholars emphasize the extent to which cross-dressing fundamentally
					troubled conventional gender roles, especially in a theatrical world that
					involved all-male acting companies. As Phyllis Rackin puts it, the <quote
						rend="inline">boy actress's body was male, while the character he
						portrayed was female. Thus inverting the offstage associations, stage
						illusion radically subverted the gender divisions of the Elizabethan
						world</quote>
					<ptr target="#rackin1987" loc="38"/>. Marjorie Garber has reinforced this
					sense of radical subversion in arguing that cross-dressing historically
					signaled a <quote rend="inline">category crisis</quote> for the very
					concept of gender <ptr target="#garber1997" loc="17"/>. Rackin and Garber
					present a disruptive potential of cross-dressing analogous — in this narrow
					way — to what Judith Butler identifies in the later phenomenon of drag:
						<quote rend="inline">In the place of the law of heterosexual
						coherence, we see sex and gender denaturalized by means of a
						performance which avows their distinctness and dramatizes the cultural
						mechanism of their fabricated unity</quote>
					<ptr target="#butler1990" loc="137–8"/>.</p>
				<p>In the context of Renaissance drama, the perceptions of cross-dressing as
					fundamentally conservative or disruptive, as opposed as they seem, share a
					good deal of common ground. Both views see the potential disruption arising
					from all-male casting and the ways in which female characters cross
					boundaries while dressed as men, for example. Much of the disagreement
					arises from different assessments of the power of comic resolutions to
					contain that disruption. When the structure of comedy involves a movement
					from disruption to resolution, the difference between disruptive radicalism
					and reactionary essentialism can amount to a question of emphasis. Can the
					resolution contain the disruption? How much of the conventional hierarchy
					does a play restore when nominally female characters assume the clothing,
					legal status, and dispossessions of wives in patriarchal marriage?</p>
				<p>This paper seeks, if not to break that impasse, at least to shift the terms
					of the conversation away from the linear placement of Early Modern
					theatrical cross-dressing on a scale from radical disruption to the
					conservative reinforcement of norms. Network analysis allows us to analyze
					how characters become gendered through a non-linear, non-hierarchical
					lattice of social relationships. As the characters interact and social
					relationships change, the individual’s gendered subjectivity also
					transforms. We find that cross-dressing protagonists propel themselves from
					isolated social worlds into a complex web of relationships through
					cross-dressing, and that entry into sociability follows predictable
					patterns. By following those patterns, the characters combine roles — the
					broker and the heroine — that are normally separate in Shakespearean comic
					plots, creating a hybrid type that becomes visible through network
					analysis.</p>
				<p>This paper seeks, if not to break the impasse, at least to shift the terms of
					the conversation away from the linear placement of Early Modern theatrical
					cross-dressing on a scale from radical disruption to the conservative
					reinforcement of norms. Network analysis allows us to analyze how
					characters become gendered through a non-linear, non-hierarchical lattice
					of social relationships. As the characters interact and social
					relationships change, the individual’s gendered subjectivity also
					transforms. We find that cross-dressing protagonists propel themselves from
					isolated social worlds into a complex web of relationships through
					cross-dressing, and that entry into sociability follows predictable
					patterns. By following those patterns, the characters combine roles — the
					broker and the heroine — that are normally separate in Shakespearean comic
					plots, creating a hybrid type that becomes visible through network
					analysis.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Network Analysis Methods</head>
				<p>To perform our analysis, we generated network visualizations of each of
					Shakespeare’s plays including a crossdressing heroine using the Python
					library NetworkX. These visualizations, hosted at <ref
						target="https://rnlp.net/shakespeare/"
						>https://rnlp.net/shakespeare/</ref>, depict the relationships among
					characters scene-by-scene, shown as networks of nodes with edges connecting
					them. Across the play’s scenes, each node represents a single character and
					the edges linking nodes represent verbal interactions between the
					characters. Edge length represents the frequency of interactions between
					characters; i.e., characters that speak more lines to each other more
					frequently have shorter edges between them. Node size corresponds to the
					number of lines spoken by a given character in the play or scene in
					question. This means that the more lines a character utters, the larger the
					radius of their respective node is. For example, if we were interested in
					analyzing the visualization for Hamlet, Act 1, Scene 5 (fig. X), we see
					there are four nodes, one each for Hamlet, Ghost, Horatio, and Marcellus.
					Hamlet and the Ghost’s nodes are considerably larger than Horatio or
					Marcellus’s because Hamlet and the Ghost speak far more lines than either
					of the other two characters in the scene. Edges connect those characters
					that speak to one another; i.e. Hamlet is linked to Ghost, Horatio, and
					Marcellus, because he speaks to all of them while Ghost is linked only to
					Hamlet because he speaks to Hamlet and only Hamlet. </p>
				<figure>
					<head>Hamlet, Act 1, Scene 5.</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/hamlet_1_5(2).png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>We modeled our uses of NetworkX to measure and parse speaking relationships
					among Shakespeare characters after those expressed in <ref
						target="#lee2017">Lee (2017)</ref>. As such, rather than merely count
					exchanges between characters to create a simple character map, our
					visualizations include weighted relationships based on volume as well as
					frequency of speech — that is, we assign greater importance to longer
					utterances — ensuring a more comprehensive view of Shakespeare’s language
					than was typical before 2017. Building upon former methods, we also
					measured relationships using other social network analysis metrics to
					analyze our results <ptr target="#wasserman1994"/>. These included
					comparative degree counts (the number of edges connected to each node),
					density (the overall ratio of edges to nodes), and clustering (the
					probability of two nodes being connected if they are both connected to a
					third node). We display these metrics as graphs where applicable throughout
					the paper.</p>
				<p>Network visualizations have proven useful in many academic disciplines in
					recent years because they rearrange linear data in a two-dimensional space,
					foregrounding formerly latent connections as a visible structure. In
					literary studies and other areas of the humanities, where our data (usually
					language) is primarily observed one-dimensionally (through reading), it can
					be difficult to accurately observe trends and large scale relationships,
					let alone reenvision primary sources among so many other competing ideas in
					the academy. This is especially pertinent to scholars interested in
					analyzing source data in widely read and written about subdisciplines like
					Shakespeare Studies. It is our assertion that network visualizations are
					one way to engage with Shakespeare Studies and Queer Theory in an
					innovative way while also remaining true to the text.</p>
				<p>In another sense, reading Shakespeare as a series of networks also serves to
					circumvent presupposed organizing forms among characters. Because our
					networks are spatially arranged by machine, these visualizations represent
					the relationships among characters based only on the amount and
					directionality of their language. This means that relationships in the
					network are independent of qualitative taxonomies like social hierarchy,
					marriage, friendship, or employment <ptr target="#lee2017" loc="12"/>.
					Instead, our networks prioritize actual acts of speech to define
					relationships, away from any occlusion from paratextual descriptions
					provided in the list of characters or the implications of a name. For
					example, in <title rend="italic">As You Like It</title>, while Touchstone
					does appear as a relative <q>touchstone</q> between characters in the
					networks, he is mathematically displayed as such neither because of his
					position as the fool, nor because of his apt name, but simply because of
					how much and to how many people he speaks. From there, we might enrich our
					reading of Touchstone with the qualitative facts of his character, but they
					do not inform the network at the generative end. This revisioning of
					Shakespeare’s plays as two-dimensional relative spaces based on direction
					and amount of speech was pivotal to our analysis because it shifts focus
					away from conventional organizing structures that we may take for granted
					and onto how characters actually function in the text itself.</p>
				<p>While this project began with a general interest in the ways in which
					cross-dressed heroines are relationally positioned in Shakespeare’s
					gender-bending plays, our research did not initially start with a
					hypothesis or set of assumptions that we hoped to evidence with these
					network diagrams. Rather, we used the network visualizations as a way to
					perform exploratory data analysis of Shakespeare’s comedies in a different
					light. Ultimately, our findings confirmed to a certain extent existing
					understandings of the texts, as well as some conclusions drawn by other
					scholars interested in this area. We viewed such confirmation as valuable
					because it reinforced existing qualitative interpretations with a different
					mode of evidence gleaned from an independent method - network analysis
					rather than reading. Often however, as we will demonstrate in the following
					sections, our findings complicate, and at times challenge previous
					scholarly interpretations of Shakespeare’s comedies.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Embedding within the Social</head>
				<p>Shakespeare’s comedies have been defined by <quote rend="inline">inversions
						of the norms of behavior,</quote> which can temporarily provide <quote
						rend="inline">the exhilarating sense of freedom which transgression
						affords</quote>
					<ptr target="#gay2002" loc="2"/>. This line of reading relies on a
					definition of Bakhtin's carnivalesque from C.L. Barber, who famously
					posited that Shakespeare’s comedies hinged on a movement from release to
					clarification - from releasing vital energy normally <quote rend="inline"
						>locked up in awe and respect,</quote> to a <quote rend="inline"
						>heightened awareness of the relation between man and nature</quote>
					<ptr target="#barber2011" loc="6"/>. In Barber’s line of reading, the
					playful transgressions of the comedy unlock social energy by functioning as
					a sort of pressure valve. </p>
				<p>Criticism on the comedies has more recently moved away from the binary poles
					of order and its inversion within the play’s plot, toward a more
					historically nuanced understanding of cross-dressing on the stage as a
					disruptive failure of gender representation. Specifically, Tracey Sedinger
					has suggested that cross-dressing on stage in the early modern context
					rejects a definition of sexuality in relation to embodiment or any object
						<ptr target="#sedinger1997"/>. Rather, the logic of cross-dressing in
					the comedies is a sequence with a specific narrative temporality. Our
					analysis supports this interpretation of cross-dressing by Shakespeare’s
					characters as a generative sequence or process resituating the gendered
					subject within the play’s social network, as opposed to a transgression in
					relation to a normative social equilibrium. In our network analysis, the
					act of cross-dressing by female characters does not cut against the grain
					of the normative social structure so much as it reconfigures the contours
					of the structure itself. </p>
				<p>Our network visualizations show that when female characters don men’s
					clothing, the social network constructed between characters changes. The
					individual characters are thrust into dynamic webs of interactions, but
					more generally we see the proliferation of dense and tightly clustered
					communities. Those communities allow the protagonists to meet a variety of
					characters and ultimately participate in a social world that is at once
					larger and more complex. Density, which measures how many interactions each
					character has with the other characters in the scene, increases
					significantly after the female protagonist cross-dresses. The simple bar
					graph in Figure 1 shows the typical jump in density of interactions once
					the protagonist cross-dresses.</p>
				<figure>
					<head>Interactions of cross-dressing heroines before and after they
						cross-dress.</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>Figure 2 visualizes the interactions in each play that create the tendencies
					summarized in Figure 1. In Figure 2, for each play, we visualize four
					scenes from each play, in chronological sequence. In each case, the first
					scene (shown at the top of the four-scene sequence) takes place before the
					moment of cross-dressing, and the other three afterwards. These are only
					selected scenes, but they illustrate the kinds of increasing density of
					social networks that create the overall effects captured in our analysis. </p>
				<figure>
					<head>Set of network visualizations of scenes involving cross-dressing
						heroines.</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/DHQFigure.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>Looking at these patterns across the five plays, we see visual patterns
					emerging. The networks before cross-dressing are frequently structured like
					a barbell or a hub and spoke; the secondary characters are companions to
					the protagonists and do not interact with anyone but their masters and
					mistresses. That is, the networks cluster tightly around the major
					characters, who are isolated from one another. By contrast, when dressed as
					men, the female characters are able to join tightly bound networks in which
					many characters interact with each other. The high interconnectedness of
					these groups can also be measured by the clustering coefficient of these
					network, which increases in the plays after the female characters dress as
					men.</p>
				<figure>
					<head>Clustering of character interactions of cross-dressing
						heroines</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>Clustering can be explained with the following example: if Viola knows Olivia
					and Olivia knows Sir Toby, then the likelihood that Viola and Sir Toby also
					interact is high. These complex social circles expand to include characters
					of different classes and professions: Julia is captured by outlaws,
					Rosalind barters with a shepherd, Portia dresses as a doctor of law and
					orchestrates a court scene, and Imogen befriends both shepherds and Roman
					soldiers. Thus dressing as men allows these women to escape the confines of
					these dialogues and participate with a larger community. Through escaping
					their isolation the female characters are therefore embedded in the larger
					network and able to become participants in the social drama of the
					plays.</p>
				<p>The exception to this trend is Rosalind from <title rend="italic">As You Like
						It</title>, whose density and clustering measurements decrease after
					cross-dressing and assuming the guise of Ganymede. The playtext, however,
					gives us some indication of why this discrepancy occurs. Rosalind
					aggressively stretches the limits of her gender play as Ganymede, by
					staging a metatheatrical courtship scenario with the lovesick Orlando, in
					which Ganymede plays the role of Rosalind: <cit><quote rend="block"><lg>
								<l>I would cure you if you</l>
								<l>would but call me Rosalind and come every day to</l>
								<l>my cote and woo me.</l>
							</lg></quote> (3.3.433-435)</cit> In effect, Rosalind performs a
					double move, by initially adopting the male role of Ganymede, and then by
					performing the role of his object of desire, Rosalind. This complex
					layering of Rosalind’s gender play based on her adoption of a female role
					when in male disguise, allows her to play with the gendered courtship
					behaviors shaping the encounters in the forest of Arden by switching
					between object, subject, and ultimately the end of the play, the mediator
					of desire. Rosalind’s oscillation between male and female identities may
					account for this specific play’s density and clustering measurements.</p>
				<p>These networks suggest that that all five of the cross-dressing protagonists
					experience a change in sociality: when they put on men’s clothing they are
					no longer limited to one-on-one dialogues, but instead enter into a dense
					and interwoven community that allows for the drama to unfold. King James I
					recognized these effects that cross-dressing could have on the larger
					society when he expressed his fear that cross-dressing would create a
						<quote rend="inline">world very much out of order.</quote> However,
					Shakespeare paints a different picture of its influence: rather than
					creating chaos, cross-dressing transforms a sparse and isolated world into
					one that multiplies social interactions.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Brokerage: The Individual within the Network</head>
				<p>Drawing on theory of corporate organizations, Richard Jean So and Hoyt Long
					argue for the importance of brokerage functions in networks: when a network
					has two subgroups divided by a gap, the <q>broker</q> fills the hole in the
					network and thereby enables connections among the other people who had been
					separated <ptr target="#so2013" loc="162"/>. So and Long draw on the work
					of Ronald Burt, who writes, <quote rend="inline">A structural hole is a
						potentially valuable context for action, brokerage is the action of
						coordinating across the hole with bridges between people on opposite
						sides of the hole, and network entrepreneurs, or brokers, are the
						people who build the bridges</quote>
					<ptr target="#burt2005" loc="18"/>. We find this concept of brokerage
					useful for describing the implications of our analysis. As the female
					protagonists move into the denser networks they inhabit while dressed as
					men, they enable the comic resolutions of their plays by connecting
					communities that begin the plays as separate social worlds.</p>
				<p>On this point, the finding of the network analysis is intuitive and
					consistent with textual evidence from the plays. For example, in <title
						rend="italic">As You Like It</title>, Rosalind leads Touchstone and
					Celia into the forest, where the group meets the shepherd Corin. Although
					Touchstone tries to assume the typical male role and parlay with the
					shepherd, Rosalind hushes him and then bargains: <cit><quote rend="block"><lg>
								<l>Buy thou the cottage, pasture, and the flock,</l>
								<l>And thou shalt have to pay for it of us</l>
							</lg></quote> (II. V.95-96)</cit> In this exchange, Rosalind
					orchestrates a business deal between Corin and the party or <q>us</q> that
					Rosalind represents. Rosalind likewise manages Silvius and Phoebe’s
					relationship: <quote rend="inline">Cry the man mercy, love him...so take
						her to thee shepherd</quote> (V.V.491). Here, Rosalind addresses one
					party, then the other, ultimately joining the couple together. In <title
						rend="italic">Cymbeline</title>, Lucius entreats Imogen to speak for
					him: <quote rend="inline">I do bid thee beg my life, good lad</quote> (V.V.
					490). When she complies, Imogen acts as a bridge between Lucius and
					Cymbeline. Likewise, in <title rend="italic">The Two Gentlemen of
						Verona</title>, Julia acts as an ironic go-between to profess Proteus’
					love to Silvia: <quote rend="inline">And now am I, unhappy
						messenger</quote> (V.V. 116). And in <title rend="italic">Twelfth
						Night</title>, Viola acts as a bridge between Orsino and Olivia:
						<quote rend="inline">All the occurrence of my fortune since/ Hath been
						between this lady and this lord</quote> (V.I. 270-271). When the
					visual networks show that the cross-dressers are brokers, they therefore
					highlight a role that was already embedded in the text.</p>
				<p> The less intuitive aspect of this brokerage function lies in the brokers’
					centrality to their respective plays. The broker is more typically a
					marginal figure whose importance lies in creating connections whose
					importance outweighs the broker’s own. As So and Long put it, <quote
						rend="inline">One’s eyes naturally focus upon the massive <q>sun</q>
						or smaller <q>stars</q> that occupy our network visualizations, yet
						somewhat less visible broker figures significantly populate the
						literary field</quote>
					<ptr target="#so2013" loc="163"/>. This model accurately describes the
					function of Shakespeare’s more typical brokers, such as Horatio and
					Gertrude in <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title>, who do not cross-dress. As
					we can see Figure 4, the cross-dressers speak more and form more
					connections — measured by degrees, or the number of links to other nodes
					from each character — than do Gertrude and Horatio.</p>
				<figure>
					<head>Comparison of cross-dressing female protagonists with traditional
						broker figures Horatio and Gertrude. </head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>In this visualization, to compare the degrees and lines across plays, the
					numbers are represented as a percentage of the total degrees and lines of
					each play. Within a given play, we can use the unadjusted number of degrees
					to illustrate the connectedness of the characters relative to one another,
					as shown in Figure 5.</p>
				<figure>
					<head>Comparison of cross-dressing female protagonists to other characters
						in their respective plays. </head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>All of the cross-dressing protagonists are among the three most connected
					characters (in Imogen’s case, tied for third) in their respective plays. In
					Figure 6, network visualizations of scenes illustrate the connections that
					constitute each protagonist’s network.</p>
				<figure>
					<head>Network visualizations of scenes from five Shakespearean comedies. </head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>In the network of each play, the most connected characters have the smallest
					distances to other characters; put more technically, they minimize the sum
					of all distances to all other vertices. In the visualizations, therefore,
					the nodes of the most connected characters appear tightly clustered with
					the nodes of other characters. </p>
				<p> We can take this line of thinking an important step further: not only do the
					cross-dressing characters combines the roles of heroine and broker, but in
					doing so, they also assume a dramatic centrality beyond that of their
					counterparts in other Shakespearean comedies. Compare the networks formed
					by cross-dressing heroines, for example, to the position of the main female
					characters in two late scenes from comedies without cross-dressing
					characters, <title rend="italic">Taming of the Shrew</title> and <title
						rend="italic">A Midsummer Night’s Dream</title>. </p>
				<figure>
					<head>Scenes from <hi rend="italic">Taming of the Shrew </hi>and <hi
							rend="italic">A Midsummer Night’s Dream</hi>.</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>In both of these networks, non-cross-dressing female characters (Katharina,
					Bianca, Helena, Hermia, and Hippolyta) occupy positions at the margins of
					the networks. Cross-dressing female protagonists consistently gain a
					central position in the social networks involved in the final moves of the
					plays. Female characters who retain conventional dress and gender
					conventions, on the contrary, occupy a marginal social position during
					crucial scenes of narrative resolution.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Implications for Network Structure and Gender</head>
				<p>Considering a cross-dressed heroine in terms of networked sociability helps
					us see that character’s gender in terms of relation as well as identity:
					the cross-dressing not only allows a character initially gendered female to
					act like a man, so to speak, but it also allows her to connect like a man.
					The social worlds of all of these plays are male-dominated, in that
					characters of all genders speak primarily in response to men, but we find,
					in the data as well as intuitively, that male characters respond to men
					more than female characters do, reflecting the plays’ tendency to
					incorporate same-gender and well as mixed-gender conversations. The
					cross-dressed heroines, however, respond to male characters even more than
					other male characters do. As Figure 8 illustrates, when wearing men’s
					clothing, the heroines inhabit the social relations of men (or even
					statistical super-men), even to the point of leaving behind the
					conversational connections to other women that have previously defined
					their relationships. </p>
				<figure>
					<head>Percentage of utterances spoken in response to male characters’
						utterances by male, female, and female-to-male cross-dressed
						characters in the five comedies. </head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure11.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>These visualizations share a common assumption: that gender in the plays
					arises initially from the categorizations that the text offers us and,
					subsequently but crucially, from the nature of the characters’
					interactions. In this latter aspect, gender is fundamentally relational. In
					a more conventional linear model of gender, masculinity and femininity
					constitute two poles, and the focus of analysis is an individual character
					using cross-dressing to traverse the distance between those poles. Rather
					than investigating the gender identity of isolated characters — no matter
					how complex those identities may be — our approach instead describes the
					social relations within dynamic systems that produce the performed effects
					of gender in the plays. </p>
				<p>The grounding of our approach in textual rather than contextual data creates
					our focus on the carnivalesque effects of cross-dressing within the action
					of the plays. We do not mean, however, to minimize the importance of other
					approaches: for instance, Rackin’s helpful insistence on the gendering of
					the actors in all-male performances of the plays implies another kind of
					network visualization, showing every interaction as a male actor (in both
					senses) speaking exclusively to other male actors, with our conception of
					mixed-gender networks operating in ironic tension with that all-male
					theatrical world. And that is not to mention yet another layer of
					complication: that the <q>male</q> actors of those companies may also have
					experienced their gender as relational or non-binary, thus implying in
					their irrecoverable subjectivities <emph>another</emph> kind of multiply
					gendered network functioning in any given performance.</p>
				<p>In closing, we step back from the landscape of nodes and edges to consider
					the implications of our analysis for reading passages of these plays in
					light of a networked conception of gender. Jean Howard has made the case
					that the cross-dressing heroines fail to disrupt gender relations
					fundamentally because the cross-dressing women are reabsorbed into the
					conventional social world by the end of of the plays. Howard argues that in
					the conclusion of <title rend="italic">Twelfth Night</title>, for instance,
						<quote rend="inline">real threats are removed and both difference and
						gender hierarchy reinscribe</quote>
					<ptr target="#howard1988" loc="35"/>. While Howard concedes that <title
						rend="italic">As You Like It</title>
					<quote rend="inline">shows a woman manipulating [gender] representations in
						her own interest,</quote> Howard still maintains that the play
					ultimately has the <quote rend="inline">primary effect...of confirming the
						gender system</quote>
					<ptr target="#howard1988" loc="37, 36"/>. However, in the midst of her
					argument, Howard does note that this recuperation of the gendered subject
					in the social world <quote rend="inline">is never perfectly
						achieved</quote>
					<ptr target="#howard1988" loc="41"/>. </p>
				<p>Howard’s reading persuasively accounts for the conservative movement of these
					comic plots as well as the disruptive and incompletely contained
					undercurrents that cross-dressing creates. We perceive another reading that
					moves away from the conservative/radical opposition at the heart of that
					reading. In <title rend="italic">Twelfth Night</title>, Viola initially
					voices her desire to escape the bounds of society and create her own
					agency: <cit><quote rend="block"><lg>
								<l>O, that I served that lady,</l>
								<l>And might not be delivered to the world</l>
								<l>Till I had made mine own occasion.</l>
							</lg></quote> (I. II. 43-45)</cit> Here, Viola eschews typical
					feminine passivity and fantasizes that she will enter the social world once
					she has “made” her own place within it. Viola’s efforts, however, lead her
					not to independence but entanglement, as with the lives of Orsino and
					Olivia: <cit><quote rend="block"><lg>
								<l>O Time, thou must untangle this, not I.</l>
								<l>It is too hard a knot for me t’ untie.</l>
							</lg></quote> (II.III.40-41)</cit> In this moment, Viola states
					that she cannot individually control the <q>knot</q> of society, even
					though she may shape it through her decisions.</p>
				<p>Viola thereafter voices a new understanding of her agency that is contingent
					on her social circumstances: <cit><quote rend="block"><l>Do not embrace me
								till each circumstance</l>
							<l>Of place, time, fortune, do cohere and jump</l><l>That I am
								Viola;</l></quote> (V.I.263-265)</cit> Here, Viola
					recognizes that she cannot entirely <quote rend="inline">make her own
						occasion.</quote> Even her most fundamental statement of named
					identity, <quote rend="inline">I am Viola,</quote> becomes a dependent
					clause that is shaped by the space she inhabits, namely, the <q>place</q>
					as well as the <q>time</q> and <q>fortune</q> of her circumstances.
					Furthermore, all of those contingencies build on the fundamental irony of
					acting, that the pleasure of watching the play involves understanding that,
					in voice and body, Viola is not Viola at all. </p>
				<p>We propose that network analysis allows new and complementary understandings
					of the kinds of identity and contingency, being and relationship, that
					enable performed gender to make, and be made by, its own occasions. Our
					visualization of these Shakespearean networks illustrates cross-dressing
					not as an individual character’s movement a simple spectrum of more or less
					disruptive gender performance, but rather as an act of social
					reconfiguration made more visible by visualization methods such as social
					network analysis. By cross-dressing, the heroine moves to the center of a
					complex social world and brokers its transformations during the part of the
					play in which she dresses as a man. Even after she changes back into a
					woman’s clothing, in a seemingly dismaying regression back to the governing
					social norms that James I’s <q>commandant</q> sought to preserve, the
					play’s resolution comes about subtly in response to her more fundamental
					remaking of its networked communities.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<listBibl>
				<bibl xml:id="barber2011" label="Barber 2011">Barber, Cesar Lombardi. <title
						rend="italic">Shakespeare's festive comedy: A study of dramatic form
						and its relation to social custom</title>. Princeton University Press,
					Princeton (2011). </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="burt2005" label="Burt 2005">Burt, Ronald. <title rend="italic"
						>Brokerage and Closure: An Introduction to Social Capital</title>.
					Oxford University Press, Oxford (2005).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="butler1990" label="Butler 1990">Butler, Judith. <title
						rend="italic">Gender Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of
						Identity</title>. Routledge, New York (1990).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="folger2019" label="Folger 2019">Folger Shakespeare Library. <title
						rend="quotes">Shakespeare's Plays from Folger Digital Texts.</title>
					Ed. Barbara Mowat, Paul Werstine, Michael Poston, and Rebecca Niles. Folger
					Shakespeare Library, <ref target="http://www.folgerdigitaltexts.org/"
						>www.folgerdigitaltexts.org</ref>, (2019).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="garber1997" label="Garber 1997">Garber, Marjorie. <title
						rend="italic">Vested Interests: Cross-Dressing and Cultural
						Anxiety</title>. Routledge, London (1997). </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="gay2002" label="Gay 2002">Gay, Penny. <title rend="quotes">As she
						likes it: Shakespeare's unruly women.</title> Routledge, London
					(2002). </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="greenblatt1988" label="Greenblatt 1988">Greenblatt, Stephen.
						<title rend="italic">Shakespearean Negotiations</title>. University of
					California Press, Berkeley (1988). </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="howard1988" label="Howard 1998">Howard, Jean. <title rend="quotes"
						>Crossdressing, The Theatre, and Gender Struggle in Early Modern
						England,</title>
					<title rend="italic">Shakespeare Quarterly</title>, Vol. 39, No. 4
					(1988).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="lee2017" label="Lee and Lee 2017">Lee, James, and Lee, Jason.
						<title rend="quotes">Shakespeare’s Tragic Social Network; or Why All
						the World’s a Stage,</title>
					<title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 11, no. 2
					(2017).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="rackin1987" label="Rackin 1987">Rackin, Phyllis. <title
						rend="quotes">Androgyny, Mimesis, and the Marriage of the Boy Heroine
						on the English Renaissance Stage,</title>
					<title rend="italic">PMLA</title>, 102, no. 1 (1987).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="rose1988" label="Rose 1988">Rose, Mary Beth. <title rend="italic"
						>The Expense of Spirit: Love and Sexuality in English Renaissance
						Drama</title>. Cornell University Press, Ithaca (1988). </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="sedinger1997" label="Sedinger 1997">Sedinger, Tracey. <title
						rend="quotes"><q>If Sight and Shape be True</q>: The Epistemology of
						Crossdressing on the London Stage,</title>
					<title rend="italic">Shakespeare Quarterly</title>, 48, No. 1
					(1997).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="so2013" label="So and Long 2013">So, Richard Jean and Hoyt Long.
						<title rend="quotes">Network Analysis and the Sociology of
						Modernism,</title>
					<title rend="italic">boundary 2</title>, 40, no. 2 (2013).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="wasserman1994" label="Wasserman and Faust 1994">Wasserman, Stanley
					and Katherine Faust. <title rend="italic">Social Network Analysis: Methods
						and Applications</title>. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge
					(1994).</bibl>
			</listBibl>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
