<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article">The Landscape of Digital Humanities</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Patrik <dhq:family>Svensson</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>HUMlab, Umeå University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>patrik.svensson@humlab.umu.se</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Patrik Svensson the director of HUMlab at Umeå University and a docent in the
                     humanities and information technology. His research concerns digital humanities
                     as a field, learning and information technology, cyberinfrastructure for the
                     humanities and new media studies. His current work includes an article on
                     screens as humanistic infrastructure (with Erica Robles), implementing a new
                     HUMlab-X on the Umeå Arts Campus, and organizing an upcoming conference on
                        <q>Media Places.</q>
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>

         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000080</idno>
            <idno type="volume">004</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <date when="2010-07-20">20 July 2010</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>

      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2010-04-19" who="Alyssa">started encoding</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>


   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>The digital humanities is increasingly becoming a <q>buzzword</q>, and there is more
               and more talk about a broadly conceived, inclusive digital humanities. The field is
               expanding and at the same time being negotiated, and this article explores the idea
               of a broadly conceived landscape of digital humanities in some depth. It is argued
               that awareness across this landscape is important to the future of the field. The
               study starts out from typologies of digital humanities, a <q>flythrough</q> of the
               landscape, and a discussion of what being a digital humanist entails. The second part
               is an exploration of four concrete encounters: ACTLab at University of Texas at
               Austin, the Humanities Arts Science Technology Advanced Collaboratory (HASTAC), the
               Humanities Computing Program at the University of Alberta, and Internet Studies. In
               the third part of the article, it is suggested that a model based on paradigmatic
               modes of engagement between the humanities and information technology can help chart
               and understand the digital humanities. The modes of engagement analyzed are
               technology as a tool, study object, expressive medium, exploratory laboratory and
               activist venue.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Where do the digital humanities start and end? This article explores a dynamic and
               multi-faceted field.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>The Landscape of Digital Humanities</head>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Over the last five years, there has been a surge of activity in the multifarious
               emerging field often referred to as <q>digital humanities.</q> Of course,
               humanities-based engagement with information technology is not new, but we are now
               seeing a rich multi-level interaction with the <q>digital</q> that is partly a result
               of the persuasiveness of digital technology and the sheer number of disciplines,
               perspectives and approaches involved. Humanists are exploring differing modes of
               engagement, institutional models, technologies and discursive strategies. There is
               also a strategy-level push for the digital humanities which, among other things,
               affects university research strategies, external funding and recruitment.</p>
            <p>This is the second article in a four-part series exploring the intersection of the
               humanities and the digital. In the first article, I examined the discursive
               transition from humanities computing to digital humanities, looking at how this
               naming is related to shifts in institutional, disciplinary, and social organization.
               I also addressed the epistemic culture and commitments of humanities computing, and
               tensions between this tradition and a broad notion of digital humanities.</p>
            <p>In the current article, I start out from a broad notion of the digital humanities
               that is sometimes suggested but rarely analyzed in more detail. The landscape of
               digital humanities is explored more broadly through a <q>fly-through</q> critical
               overview of the landscape and an exploration of four concrete encounters. I argue
               that a better understanding of the landscape of the digital humanities is vital to
               the continued growth and consolidation of the field, and necessary to meet a range of
               exciting upcoming challenges. Importantly, acknowledging internal variation and
               tensions are critical to this enterprise, and it seems likely that the way forward is
               neither a singular vision of a unified, homogenous digital humanities nor extensive
               fragmentation and lack of shared awareness and common visions. It is suggested that
               one way of understanding and acknowledging the different traditions and epistemic
               commitments of the digital humanities is to consider different modes of engagement
               between the humanities and information technology. The third part of the article
               consequently offers an in-depth analysis of some paradigmatic modes of engagement
               between the humanities and information technology. I feel this approach will give a
               better sense of the breadth and depth of the field, different implementations, and
               points of connections and divergence. Further, I argue that a better understanding of
               the landscape of the digital humanities is vital to the continued growth and
               consolidation of the field, and necessary to meet a range of exciting upcoming
               challenges.</p>
            <p>The third article discusses cyberinfrastructure for the humanities and digital
               humanities more broadly, and presents a case study from HUMlab at Umeå University in
               Sweden. In the fourth and final article, I explore the multiple ways in which the
               digital humanities have been envisioned and how the digital humanities can often
               become a laboratory and means for thinking about the state and future of the
               humanities at large. I conclude by presenting a tentative visionary space for the
               future of the digital humanities.</p>
            <p>The article series as a whole traces the digital humanities as a project in terms of
               history, epistemic commitments, modes of engagement with the digital, conceptual
               foundations for associated cyberinfrastructure, visions and hope invested, as well as
               future directions for the field, and necessarily, for the humanities at large.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Outline</head>
            <p>This article is divided into three main parts that present different perspectives or
               lenses on the landscape of the digital humanities.</p>
            <p>The first part provides a territorial fly-through (critical overview) of the
               landscape of the digital humanities that discusses ways of <q>reading</q> the
               territory as well as specific parts of the terrain. The picture given is broad, but
               also fairly particular in relation to specific initiatives and associated discourses.
               Typologies of the digital humanities are discussed, as well as what it might entail
               to be a digital humanist. </p>
            <p>The second part of the paper presents four personal encounters with digital
               humanities initiatives that occurred between 2001 and 2009. These offer different
               perspectives on the digital humanities: ACTLab at University of Texas at Austin, the
               Humanities Arts Science Technology Advanced Collaboratory (HASTAC), the Humanities
               Computing Program at the University of Alberta and Internet Studies through an
               exchange with Charles Ess.</p>
            <p>The third part discusses paradigmatic modes of engagement between the humanities and
               information technology: information technology as a tool, an object of study, an
               exploratory laboratory, an expressive medium and an activist venue. The first three
               modes of engagement are given most attention. This analytical model provides one
               possible way of charting the territory of the digital humanities.</p>
            <p>Necessarily, any attempt at charting a large and indeterminate field such as digital
               humanities cannot be all-inclusive. The focus in the following exposition is large
               structures as well as particular examples, but the reader will find neither detailed
               accounts of specific fields such as computer mediated communication or history and
               computing, nor of associated fields such as technoscience (cf. <ptr target="#ihde2003"/>) with which there is some overlap.<note>Technoscience (and
                  science and technology studies more generally) largely focuses on the social
                  construction of knowledge production and the technological and social context of
                  science. There is a clear connection to the digital humanities through an interest
                  in the reconfiguration of human experience in the computational age, technology as
                  an object of critical reflection, and through an interest in sites and modes of
                  knowledge production.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Together, the fly-through, the encounters and the analytical framework will help
               garner a better understanding of the field of digital humanities. The mapping
               activity itself is as important as the resultant patchy map, however, and it is
               argued that the challenges and possibilities ahead call for a shared awareness and
               rich collaborations across the landscape of the digital humanities. <note>The current
                  author is based in the North of Europe with strong North American connections and
                  fairly substantial international network. The fieldwork has also included trips to
                  Australia, Japan and South Korea. Nevertheless, the landscape presented in this
                  article is not in any sense representative, global or all-inclusive, although it
                  is hoped that much of the analysis and categorization have bearing also on digital
                  humanities in other parts of the world. A useful resource and inclusive network is
                  centerNet (<ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/centernet/">http://digitalhumanities.org/centernet/</ref>), an international network for
                  digital humanities centers.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Part I: Exploring the Digital Humanities</head>
            <div>
               <head>Introduction</head>
               <p>In the following it will be assumed that the digital humanities comprise a field
                  in a loose sense. This is not to suggest a well-defined and delimited academic
                  field outside of the traditional humanities disciplines, but rather an inclusive
                  notion that will allow us to talk about different kinds of initiatives and
                  activities in the intersection between the humanities and information technology
                  or the digital. It is claimed that this conversation can be quite important to
                  further and consolidate digitally inflected work in the humanities. This does not
                  mean, however, that the ultimate goal necessarily is an all-inclusive digital
                  humanities.</p>
               <p>Any attempt at mapping a field such as the digital humanities will naturally be a
                  particular reading and interpretation of that field. We will start by surveying a
                  few suggested typologies for the digital humanities.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Typologies of the Digital Humanities</head>
               <p>In a 2008 talk <ptr target="#mcpherson2008"/> and subsequent article <ptr target="#mcpherson2009a"/>, Tara McPherson suggested a typology for the digital
                  humanities that makes distinctions between the computing humanities, blogging
                  humanities and multimodal humanities. According to McPherson, the computing
                  humanities focus on building tools, infrastructure, standards and collections
                  whereas the blogging humanities are concerned with the production of networked
                  media and peer-to-peer writing. The multimodal humanities bring together scholarly
                  tools, databases, networked writing and peer-to-peer commentary while also
                  leveraging the potential of the visual and aural media that are part of
                  contemporary life. This is a useful typology in that it is comprehensive, simple
                  and points to the importance of networked media and writing as well as describes
                  an ongoing development. It does not privilege nor explicitly single out the
                  digital as an object of analysis, which partly may be a result of a more general
                  focus on multimodal writing in the humanities at large, and arguably the most
                  prominent mode of engagement for the multimodal humanities is the digital as an
                  expressive medium. While the additive element of this typology is useful, we
                  should be aware of the complexities of some of these issues. For instance, the
                  tools used by computing humanists are probably very different from most of the
                  tools used by multimodal humanists. As we have seen in the earlier analysis of
                  humanities computing as digital humanities <ptr target="#svensson2009a"/>, the
                  epistemic commitments and conventions of a tradition cannot easily be subsumed in
                  another type of digital humanities (cf. also <ptr target="#ratto2006"/>).</p>
               <p>Along somewhat similar lines, <ptr target="#davidson2008"/> identifies two phases
                  of digital humanities — Humanities 1.0 and Humanities 2.0 — making use of the
                  distinction between Web 1.0 and Web 2.0. For instance, she says, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#davidson2008">Humanities 2.0 is distinguished from monumental,
                        first-generation, data-based projects not just by its interactivity but also
                        by openness about participation grounded in a different set of theoretical
                        premises, which decenter knowledge and authority</quote>
                     <ptr target="#davidson2008" loc="711–12"/>
                  </cit>. Davidson presents a well-articulated vision for the humanities where
                  technology is a key participant in the decentering of authorship, credentialing
                  practices, reward systems, interdisciplinarity, and collaboration. The argument
                  extends far beyond technology and basically concerns the situation and future for
                  the humanities more generally: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#davidson2008">In a time of paradigm shifts, moral and political
                        treachery, historical amnesia, and psychic and spiritual turmoil, humanistic
                        issues are central — if only funding agencies, media interests, and we
                        humanists ourselves will recognize the momentousness of this era for our
                        discipline and take seriously the need for our intellectual
                        centrality.</quote>
                     <ptr loc="715" target="#davidson2008"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Both McPherson and Davidson point to a transition from humanities computing or
                  computing humanities to multimodal humanities or humanities 2.0 (cf. also the
                  Digital Humanities Manifesto 2.0 and the distinction between a first and second
                  wave of digital humanities work). The endpoint can be interpreted as a current and
                  forward-looking variety of the digital humanities. There is a clear assumption of
                  change and trajectory here, and a risk that different epistemic traditions and
                  goals are conflated in this trajectory. In practice, it would seem that humanities
                  computing (even if called digital humanities) will not — at least not fully or
                  anytime soon — become the multimodal humanities or humanities 2.0 envisioned in
                  these articles. However, as both writers show, the intersection between these
                  traditions is a productive and important one. Importantly, while there is a great
                  deal of ongoing collaboration and identification of common goals, we need to be
                  aware of the fact that we are concerned with several epistemic traditions and
                  visions. It could be argued that there is a need for an expanded, multi-layered
                  discussion of visions, collaborative possibilities, and possibly but not
                  necessarily, an articulated convergent path forward.</p>
               <p>Another mode of analysis is provided by Hayles (<ptr target="#haylesa"/> and <ptr target="#haylesb"/>) who manifests her intellectual curiosity for the field
                  through identification of pivotal theoretical and methodological issues as well as
                  through interviews with 17 digital humanists. Among issues identified and
                  discussed are scalability, reading, algorithmic analysis, visualization and open
                  review. Two digital humanities environments, the Centre for Computing in the
                  Humanities at King’s College and the School of Literature, Communication, and
                  Culture at Georgia Tech, function as case studies, and add to the analysis partly
                  through their differentness. Hayles identifies two different strategies for
                  promoting a digital humanities agenda: assimilation and distinction. According to
                  Hayles, assimilation extends existing scholarship into digital domains whereas
                  distinction emphasizes new methodologies, novel research questions, and the
                  emergence of new fields. When she discusses the outcomes of different models, she
                  points to the risk of divergence: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#haylesa">The kinds of articulation that emerge have strong
                        implications for the future: will the Digital Humanities become a separate
                        field whose interests are increasingly remote from the Traditional
                        Humanities, or will it on the contrary become so deeply entwined with
                        questions of hermeneutic interpretation that no self-respecting Traditional
                        scholar could remain ignorant of its results? If the Digital Humanities were
                        to spin off into an entirely separate field, the future trajectory of the
                        Traditional Humanities would be affected as well. Obviously, this is a
                        political as well as an intellectual issue. In the case of radical
                        divergence (which I think would be a tragic mistake), one might expect turf
                        battles, competition for funding, changing disciplinary boundaries, and
                        shifting academic prestige.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#haylesa"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Interestingly, Hayles brings up questions of the disciplinary status of digital
                  humanities that have generated much discussion and debate over the years (cf. <ptr target="#svensson2009a"/>). This history is partly one of continuous tension
                  between the disciplines and various forms of digital humanities, and given this
                  fairly long track record (especially for humanities computing) and the current
                  multiplexity of the field, it seems quite unlikely that the digital humanities
                  would ever become a fully separate field.<note>Although there is definitely a wish
                     in some parts of the community to be semi-separate. This is a recent comment by
                     Willard McCarty in relation to the broader interest in and acceptance for
                     digital humanities: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mccarty2009">But let me offer a different criterion for success:
                           simply to be accepted as one of the community, to sit at the table among
                           equals and talk, then to go back home to a department of the digital
                           humanities, with its students, programmes, seminars and so on, and get on
                           with educating and being educated.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mccarty2009"/>
                     </cit>
                  </note> What is likely, in any case, is continued tension, and <quote rend="inline" source="#haylesa">occasional turf battles, competition for funding, changing
                     disciplinary boundaries and shifting academic prestige.</quote> Arguably,
                  disunification can bring stability to a disciplinary area such as digital
                  humanities (cf. <ptr target="#galison1997" loc="781–2"/>). Furthermore, fights
                  within disciplines can be seen as a way to maintain <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#sterne2005">intellectual vibrancy</quote>
                     <ptr target="#sterne2005" loc="251"/>
                  </cit>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>The Diverse Territory of Digital Humanities</head>
               <p>The complexity of digital humanities as a <q>field</q> comes partly from its
                  disciplinary and institutional diversity, and its multiple modes of engagement
                  with information technology. Looking at a restricted field, presumably part of the
                  digital humanities, Bell notes that the <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#bell2007">
                        <q>field</q> of cyberculture (or whatever) studies is diverse and heterodox,
                        too undisciplined to be called a discipline</quote>
                     <ptr target="#bell2007" loc="52"/>
                  </cit>.</p>
               <p>It is true that <q>digital humanities</q> probably defies any precise definition
                  and that it can hardly be called a discipline. The question is whether it even
                  constitutes a field. This is the position taken in the Digital Humanities
                  Manifesto 2.0 (2009): <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#manifesto2009">Digital Humanities is not a unified field but <emph>an
                           array of convergent practices</emph> that explore a universe in which: a)
                        print is no longer the exclusive or the normative medium in which knowledge
                        is produced and/or disseminated; instead, print finds itself absorbed into
                        new, multimedia configurations; and b) digital tools, techniques, and media
                        have altered the production and dissemination of knowledge in the arts,
                        human and social sciences. [original emphasis]</quote>
                     <ptr target="#manifesto2009"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>And even if the assumption of a field is made, the emerging nature of this field
                  will often be emphasized as in this definition from the website of the journal
                     <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#dhq2010a">Digital humanities is a diverse and still emerging field
                        that encompasses the practice of humanities research in and through
                        information technology, and the exploration of how the humanities may evolve
                        through their engagement with technology, media, and computational
                        methods.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#dhq2010a"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>The <soCalled>still</soCalled> in <soCalled>still
                     emerging</soCalled> seems to indicate that the field has been emerging for some
                     time,<note>Arguably for a fairly long time as the initial emergence (of
                     humanities computing) is often dated to the late 1940s.</note> and that it has
                  not yet reached a stable form.</p>
               <p>There may be several reasons for trying to promote digital humanities as a field.
                  In the case of humanities computing, there was already the sense of an established
                  field with journals, conferences and people primarily engaged in the field. This
                  is not to say that everyone engaged in humanities computing (or humanities
                  computing as digital humanities) would describe it as a field, but there is a
                  fairly general consensus and a strong tradition. The following quote, from the
                  introduction of the <title rend="italic">Blackwell Companion to the Digital
                     Humanities</title>, illustrates the somewhat ambivalent interrelation between
                  humanities computing and digital humanities, and also shows how the two
                     <q>fields</q> can coexist. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#schreibman2004">The digital humanities, then, and their interdisciplinary
                        core found in the field of humanities computing, have a long and dynamic
                        history best illustrated by examination of the locations at which specific
                        disciplinary practices intersect with computation.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#schreibman2004" loc="xxiv"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Under this reading, humanities computing provides the core whereas digital
                  humanities presumably also includes the disciplines. As I have shown earlier <ptr target="#svensson2009a"/>, the problem may be the conflation that results from
                  making the history of humanities computing into the history of digital humanities.
                  In any case, the strength of humanities computing as a field partly comes from the
                  epistemic investment in technology as tool and associated processes (ranging from
                  metadata schemes to project management), and as we have seen earlier, it can be
                  argued that this epistemic commitment often leads to a relatively weak link to the
                  disciplines (beyond the purely instrumental).</p>
               <p>An alternative focus on technology or the digital as study object, however, may
                  lead to a weaker sense of the field of digital humanities — exactly because of the
                  tight relation between the traditional discipline and the digitally inflected
                  study object. The study object would probably also tend to be aligned with the
                  epistemic commitments of an established discipline (or several disciplines) even
                  in the context of a multidisciplinary complex. As a result, the discipline may
                  change to incorporate such objects, but this is rarely a simple or
                  straight-forward process, and one interesting question is whether the digital
                  calls for other modes of investigation, collaboration and making that may be
                  partially incompatible with the epistemic commitments of the established
                  discipline or field: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#hall2008">It follows that the consequences and implications of
                        digital media for research into cultural studies themes, problematic, and
                        questions cannot be explored simply by using the recognized, legitimate,
                        preconstituted, disciplinary forms of knowledge: literary studies,
                        philosophy, sociology, history, psychoanalysis, and so on. Digital media
                        change the very nature of such disciplines, rending them “unrecognizable” as
                        Derrida says of psychoanalysis.</quote>
                     <ptr loc="81" target="#hall2008"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>On a more mundane scale, there is definitely a tension between the traditional
                  disciplines and some of the scholars and initiatives engaged with the digital as a
                  study object. This sentiment, which may lead to the establishment of
                  discipline-external centers or even new disciplines, is also significant. So while
                  technology as a study object will often foster a much tighter relationship to the
                  disciplines (closer to the heart of the disciplines) than technology as a tool,
                  there might also be distancing. However, this distancing is often not
                  institutionalized, which is an important factor in maintaining a fairly strong
                  link to the disciplines. Humanities computing, on the other hand, is almost always
                  institutionalized to some extent. For initiatives focused on the digital as a
                  study object, discipline-external sentiment can be seen as channeled through
                  organizations such as the Association of Internet Researchers, which gathers
                  researchers from a number of disciplines.</p>
               <p>In some cases, however, new fields or areas of research are institutionalized in
                  relation to specific themes or study objects. An example would be games studies
                  and internet studies, which have partly been institutionalized in some university
                  contexts (e.g. at the Center for Games Research at the IT University in
                  Copenhagen, the Singapore Internet Research Centre at Nanyang Technological
                  University and the Oxford Internet Institute). Typically these do not strongly
                  align themselves discursively with the digital humanities.</p>
               <p>Part of the problem with an inclusive and broad notion of digital humanities may
                  be that the relatively high level of abstraction makes it difficult to come to
                  grips with the field on a more basic and practical level. From a strategic level,
                  however, this may not be a problem, but rather an asset as it makes it possible to
                  frame a large scope, substantial impact and broad engagement. This engagement
                  often relates to the development of the humanities at large, a discussion of the
                  traditional humanities disciplines, and sometimes a call to action. The below
                  quote is from a HASTAC Forum discussion on the digital humanities where Brett
                  Bobley, head of the NEH (National Endowment of the Humanities) Office of Digital
                  Humanities, was one of the interlocutors. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#davidson2009">I don't know how Brett Bobley or others might answer this
                        but I don't actually find disciplines tragic . . . just in need of major
                        refurbishing and a good dose of introspection about what it is they do, how
                        willing they are to be irrelevant to a larger world, how they fight their
                        declining (in the humanities) numbers, and how urgently they reconsider
                        their shape and importance in the light of the new, global forms of
                        knowledge being produced everywhere around them, and changing the timelines
                        and the geography of knowledge production. It is such an exciting time and I
                        wish more in the humanities grasped the implications of what this new time
                        means for the shape of our many fields and inter-fields.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#davidson2009"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>There is a fair degree of sympathy and understanding for the traditional (but
                  seemingly declining) humanities in this statement, as well as a call for change.
                  The digital humanities, thus, becomes a site for change and action.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Two Types of Digital Humanities</head>
               <p>The diverse and multiple-mode territory of the digital humanities can be further
                  exemplified by two descriptions of digital humanities in an educational context.
                  The first text is a description of a planned, but not realized, interdisciplinary
                  major in the Digital Humanities at Stanford University: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#ish2008">The increasing importance assumed by digital technologies
                        in contemporary culture has given rise to new forms of scholarly inquiry,
                        new ways to assess and to organize humanistic knowledge, and new forms of
                        cultural communication. The very questions that the humanities disciplines
                        ask have changed. How have reading and writing changed in the digital era?
                        What new forms of cultural expression emerge with the advent of the digital
                        age and how do they build upon or break with the old? How should we assess
                        the ethical and political implications of digital technologies? What kinds
                        of tools do we have or do we need to develop in order to make sense of
                        and/or to take advantage of these new technologies?</quote>
                     <ptr target="#ish2008"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Here the emergent nature of digital humanities is emphasized, as well as a strong
                  link to the humanities disciplines and a partial reconfiguration of the
                  humanities. The major mode of engagement is technology as a study object, even if
                  there is also an interest in the instrumental use of digital technology, and to
                  some extent, information technology as a medium. In contrast, the following
                  description from the Centre for Computing in the Humanities (CCH) website at
                  King’s College provides a much more static description of digital humanities. The
                  main mode of engagement is clearly technology as a tool. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#cch2006">The digital humanities comprise the study of what happens
                        at the intersection of computing tools with cultural artefacts of all kinds.
                        This study begins where basic familiarity with standard software ends. It
                        probes how these common tools may be used to make new knowledge from our
                        cultural inheritance and from the contemporary world. It equips students to
                        analyze problems in terms of digital methods, choose those best for the job
                        at hand, apply them creatively and assess the results. It teaches students
                        to use computing as an instrument to investigate how we know what we know,
                        hence to strengthen and extend our knowledge of the world past and
                        present.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#cch2006"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>We need to be careful not to draw too far-reaching conclusions from such limited
                  and contextually situated material, but there can be no doubt that these two
                  descriptions suggest rather different types of digital humanities and epistemic
                  cultures. Unsurprisingly, there are several points of connection. One such
                  connection is offered by the mention of tools and creating tools at the end of the
                  first text, which relates to the predominant focus on tools and methods in the
                  second text. Interestingly, despite the general CCH focus on tools, the short text
                  does not say anything about creating new tools. <note>
                     <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mccarty2010">There's another reason I stick to the simplest of
                           tools. It's not just that these beginners would be stumped by Perl or
                           Python, say, it's that their attention would be diverted from the
                           intersection of the literary problem with computing to tool-making
                           itself.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mccarty2010"/>
                     </cit>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Perspectives from Library and Information Science</head>
               <p>Many digital humanities centers are housed in close proximity to university
                     libraries,<note>Examples include IATH at University of Virginia, MITH at
                     University of Maryland and the Humanities Laboratory at Lund University.</note>
                  which is not surprising given the centrality of libraries to the humanities, and
                  that many digital humanities initiatives have an interest in collections and
                  interdisciplinary practice. Furthermore, such initiatives can sometimes function
                  as resources in library based development and research work. Also, library
                  reconstruction, changing usage patterns and resizing may result in available space
                  and structural possibilities. A recent example of this type of symbiotic
                  relationship can be seen in the newly instituted Center for Digital Scholarship at
                  Brown (<ref type="offline">
                     <title rend="italic">Humanist</title> 23.636, February 12, 2010</ref>). There
                  is a close link to what can be called <q>digital cultural heritage,</q> which
                  deals with digital management of and access to cultural heritage more broadly. In
                  Europe, for instance, there is EU-funded research on cultural heritage, digital
                  libraries and digital preservation (DigiCult).</p>
               <p>Libraries are an important part of the infrastructure of the humanities, and in a
                  sense, a kind of humanities laboratory <note>This sense of the library is often
                     articulated in discussions of the future of libraries. For instance, in a
                     discussion about the Syracuse University Library, the humanities faculty made
                     it clear that they considered the library their central laboratory. <ptr target="#howard2009"/> See also <ptr target="#unsworth1999"/>.</note> placed
                  outside the departments and schools. Libraries are also, by default, important
                  players in relation to humanities-based information and information technology. It
                  is important to acknowledge, however, that traditional research libraries come
                  with a set of epistemic commitments pertaining to the role of collections, the
                  types of texts handled, tool building, collaboration with humanities scholars and
                  distribution (see <ptr target="#drucker2009b"/> for a critical discussion).</p>
               <p>The performed epistemic scope of library and information science in the context of
                  the digital humanities is prevalent and not always entirely transparent. One
                  recent example is a survey on digital humanities centers in the U.S. <ptr target="#zorich2008"/> prepared for the Council on Library and Information,
                  where we find an institution-level working definition of the digital humanities: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#zorich2008">A digital humanities center is an entity where new media
                        and technologies are used for humanities-based research, teaching, and
                        intellectual engagement and experimentation. The goals of the center are to
                        further humanities scholarship, create new forms of knowledge, and explore
                        technology’s impact on humanities-based disciplines.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#zorich2008"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>This is a fairly inclusive definition even though the outset could be said to be
                  representative of an instrumental mode of engagement (most clearly indicated by
                     <q>are used</q>). While the three goals presented here
                  are broad and open-ended, it could be argued that they construe technology as
                  being outside the disciplines rather than as an integrated part (which would be
                  congruent with mainly seeing information technology as a tool).</p>
               <p>Following the above definition, the report provides a list of activities, some or
                  all of which a digital humanities center undertakes in the analysis presented in
                  the survey (abbreviated): <list type="ordered">
                     <item>Builds digital collections as scholarly or teaching resources,</item>
                     <item>Creates tools for authoring, building digital collections, analyzing
                        collections, data or research processes, managing the research
                        process,</item>
                     <item>Uses digital collections and analytical tools to generate new
                        intellectual products,</item>
                     <item>Offers digital humanities training,</item>
                     <item>Offers lectures, programs, conferences or seminars on digital humanities
                        topics,</item>
                     <item>Has its own academic appointments and staffing,</item>
                     <item>Provides collegial support for and collaboration with members of other
                        academic departments at the home institution,</item>
                     <item>Provides collegial support for and collaboration with members of other
                        academic departments, organizations or projects outside the home
                        institution,</item>
                     <item>Conducts research in humanities and humanities computing (digital
                        scholarship),</item>
                     <item>Creates a zone of experimentation and innovation for humanists,</item>
                     <item>Serves as an information portal for a particular humanities
                        discipline,</item>
                     <item>Serves as a repository for humanities-based digital collections,
                        and</item>
                     <item>Provides technology solutions to humanities departments.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Although not necessarily evident in the more general definition quoted above, this
                  list of criteria makes it rather clear that there is a particular perspective or
                  orientation underlying the definition. This information and library science
                  perspective is perhaps not surprising given the origin of the survey (prepared for
                  CLIR), but it does create a discrepancy between the more general definition and
                  the particular activities listed. A similar narrowing down of epistemic scope (in
                  that case from a broad sense of digital humanities to traditional humanities
                  computing) was noticed in an analysis of the call for papers for the Digital
                  Humanities 2010 conference <ptr target="#svensson2009a"/>. The narrowing down in
                  the case of the CLIR report is particularly noticeable in the focus on building
                  digital collections and associated tools, using these collections, and serving as
                  a repository (1-3, 12). Many of the other list items are service oriented:
                  offering training, collegial support, serving as an information portal for
                  disciplines, and providing technology solutions (4, 5, 7, 8, 10, 13). The
                  remaining features are either structural (appointments and staffing) or more
                  oriented towards research and experimentation (12, 10, and to some extent 5). We
                  would not expect any list of this kind to be all-inclusive, but both the focus on
                  collections and the totality of the defining criteria can be said to have a rather
                  strong excluding function.</p>
               <p>The link between digital humanities and libraries is robust, but not static, and
                  the expansion of the digital humanities and changing roles for libraries may lead
                  to a new set of dynamics and a renewed sense of library as laboratory as well as a
                  physical and digital repository. The idea of the library as a space for
                  collaborative scholarship is strengthened through the introduction of more study
                  spaces for (primarily) students, project spaces for digital humanities and
                  technical infrastructure such as large, interactive screens. Perhaps libraries
                  have always been the analogue to laboratories, in that they are sites for
                  knowledge production, a repository or archive, and a place of exchange. In this
                  sense, the contemporary moment re-sensitizes the traditional function of the
                  library in order to extend its dynamic qualities, rather than those that may be
                  strictly archival.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Cyberculture Studies and Critical Digital Studies</head>
               <p>The type of library and library science definition of digital humanities centers
                  described above would probably not include research areas such as critical
                  cyberculture studies, which predominantly focus on digital culture and the
                  cultural construction of information technology as a study object: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#silver2006">Critical cyberculture studies is, in its most basic form, a
                        critical approach to new media and the contexts that shape and inform them.
                        Its focus is not merely the Internet and the Web, but rather, all forms of
                        networked media and culture that surround us today, not to mention those
                        that will surround us tomorrow. Like cultural studies, critical cyberculture
                        studies strives to locate its object of study within various overlapping
                        contexts, including capitalism, consumerism and commodification, cultural
                        difference, and the militarization of everyday life.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#silver2006" loc="6"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>The Resource Center for Cyberculture Studies is an online resource associated with
                  this area, and one of the services provided is an extensive set of book reviews.
                  These reviews are frequently carried out by several reviewers and are often
                  accompanied by author responses. This is a very valuable resource, and it also
                  gives an indication of the breadth and extent of more cultural study based
                  approaches to the digital and information technology. As of November 24, 2008,
                  there were 390 reviews available of the same number of books. Interestingly, this
                  resource does not seem to include any books that explicitly deal with humanities
                  computing or humanities computing as digital humanities. For instance, the 2004
                  volume <title rend="italic">Companion to the Digital Humanities</title> has not
                  been reviewed. The same is true of Willard McCarty’s <title rend="italic">Humanities Computing</title> (2005).<note>This was still true as of 30 January
                     2010.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Neither critical cyberculture studies, nor internet studies, nor initiatives such
                  as new media studies and critical digital studies, which all come from cultural
                  studies or art theory backgrounds, typically make frequent use of the term
                     <term>digital humanities</term>. There is obviously a link between these fields
                  and digital humanities as humanities computing, or digital humanities with a
                  library and information science focus, but the connection is not necessarily
                  simple or straightforward. In addition, the territories of all these <q>fields</q>
                  are currently being negotiated and explored. In any case, the contrast between the
                  King’s College description of the field of digital humanities cited above and the
                  description below of critical digital studies is quite significant. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#kroker2008">From the spectacular emergence of new media innovations
                        such as blogging, podcasting, flashmobs, mashups, and RSS feeds to
                        video-sharing websites (MySpace, YouTube), Wikipedia, and massively
                        multiplayer online role-playing games (MMORPGs), the how and what we know of
                        contemporary society, culture and politics is continuously being creatively
                        transformed by strikingly original developments in technologies of digital
                        communication. To the challenge of understanding the implications of
                        technological innovations, Critical Digital Studies responds by developing a
                        new method of critical digital studies: its scope — full-spectrum knowledge
                        of the digital future; its method — media archaeology; its practice —
                        crossing boundaries; and its goal — bending the digital future in the
                        direction of creative uncertainty.</quote>
                     <ptr loc="1" target="#kroker2008"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Here we are concerned with a rather future driven, positivistic and arguably
                  techno-romantic presentation (starting from <quote rend="inline" source="#kroker2008">the spectacular
                     emergence of new media innovations</quote>) that lists a number of contemporary
                  media representations, as well as suggesting an ongoing creative transformation of
                  society, culture and politics as a result of <quote rend="inline" source="#kroker2008">strikingly
                     original developments in technologies of digital communication</quote> — a
                  movement described by <ptr target="#raley2009" loc="25"/> as <quote rend="inline" source="#raley2009">the <ab>wired</ab> Left.</quote> The field itself is singularly defined in
                  terms of scope, method and goal. The goal is described as <quote rend="inline" source="#kroker2008">bending the digital future in the direction of creative uncertainty.</quote>
                  In another passage of the same chapter, this is elaborated as <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#kroker2008">privileging the intermediations, inflections, and
                        paradoxes that are so deeply characteristic of the digital flow</quote>
                     <ptr loc="9" target="#kroker2008"/>
                  </cit>. There is an activist sentiment here that is not very common in cultural
                  studies-based approaches to the digital (although discontent with the current
                  state of affairs may be emphasized), and very rare in traditional humanities
                  computing discourse. This mode of engagement could arguably be described as the
                  digital (or information technology) serving as a venue for <q>academic
                     activism.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Digital Humanities as Activism and Artistic Practice</head>
               <p>An example of digitally inflected academic activism is Sharon Daniel’s work on
                  women in prison, and on the prison system as a public secret, as exemplified her
                  piece <title rend="quotes">Public Secrets</title> published in the journal <title rend="italic">Vectors</title>. This is from the author's statement: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#daniel2007">Three years ago, on visiting day, I walked through a metal
                        detector and into the Central California Womens' Facility. It changed my
                        life. The stories I heard inside challenged my most basic perceptions — of
                        our system of justice, of freedom and of responsibility. Walk with me across
                        this boundary between inside and outside, bare-life and human-life, and
                        listen to Public Secrets.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#daniel2007"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Juhasz argues that she sees a turn towards art and activism in traditional
                  scholarship, and that the digital part <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#juhasz2009">is perhaps what was needed to push more scholars to engage
                        with the personal and political implications of their practices</quote>
                     <ptr target="#juhasz2009"/>
                  </cit>. She talks about collaboration, the role of affect and aesthetics and the
                  impact of audiences as important factors in this movement. While the extent of
                  this alleged <q>turn</q> could be disputed, it would seem that there is a
                  connection between the digital, associated expressive means, and academic
                  activism.</p>
               <p>An important, but difficult, issue is whether art, activist-based initiatives, or
                  academic activism at all should be considered to be part of the digital
                  humanities. The answer has to do with how we relate to divisions between the
                  humanities and art, the humanities and science, thinking and making, and the
                  university and the outside world. These categories are not binary, and it does
                  seem that the digital can sometimes help challenge these oppositions. Also, it
                  would seem that the contemporariness of much of interpretative digital humanities
                  work, coupled with an interdisciplinary sentiment and digital means of production
                  and intervention, support an interest in academic activism.</p>
               <p>We will return to a more in-depth discussion of the various modes of engagement
                  identified here, including technology as an activist venue, later in this article.
                  But let us first consider the inhabitants and landscape of the digital
                  humanities.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Digital Humanists and Digital Humanities</head>
               <p>As we have seen, digital humanities hardly make up an uncontested or well-defined
                  landscape. So far the picture has been painted using rather broad and structural
                  brush strokes. Another way of approaching this issue is to start from the
                  individual or particular — from the individual person engaged in what may be
                  called digital humanities.</p>
               <p>It would seem tenable to state that minimally, digital humanities is manifested by
                  a single scholar, teacher, artist, programmer, engineer or student doing some kind
                  of work — thinking, reflecting, writing, creating — at the intersection of the
                  humanities and information technology — or by <q>products</q> resulting from such
                  activities. Every combination of the humanities and technology does not qualify as
                  digital humanities, of course. For instance, while word processors may be
                  interesting as a study object from a humanities perspective — e.g. looking at
                  their conceptual history, the textually of revision functionality, or the
                  prescriptiveness of built-in dictionaries — a humanities scholar using a word
                  processor to write an article would not necessarily qualify as a digital
                  humanist.</p>
               <p>As a matter of fact, it is not entirely clear that even individuals deeply
                  engrossed in the digital humanities would necessarily identify with the
                  denominations <q>digital humanist</q> or <q>digital humanities.</q> Partly because
                  of the diversity and history of the field, disassociation may be rather vigorous: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#drucker2009a">How different is it [speculative computing] from digital
                        humanities? As different as night from day, text from work, and the force of
                        controlling reason from pleasures of delightenment.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#drucker2009a" loc="30"/>
                  </cit> Here the reading of digital humanities as traditional humanities computing
                  seems rather clear, and the positioning of speculative computing outside the
                  digital humanities would seem to contradict a very inclusive notion of the digital
                  humanities.</p>
               <p>The individual term <term>digital humanist</term> may be problematic because it
                  may seem both too general in not relating to a specific discipline or competence
                  (thus deemphasizing the discipline-specific or professional) and too specific in
                  emphasizing the <q>digital</q> part of the scholarly identity (if you are scholar)
                  or giving too much prominence to the humanities part of your professional identity
                  (if you are a digital humanities programmer or a system architect). The more
                  general and non-personal term <term>digital humanities</term> is more inclusive,
                  but somewhat limited because of its lack of specificity and relatively weak
                  disciplinary anchorage. For both variants, there is also a question of whether
                     <q>the digital</q> needs to be specified at all, and it is not uncommon<note>In
                     the present author's experience, this has happened on numerous occasions when
                     presenting on the digital humanities to audiences with a large portion of
                     non-humanities participants.</note> to encounter the argument that technology
                  and the digital are part or will be part of any academic area, and hence the
                  denotation <q>digital</q> is not required.</p>
               <p>But clearly these terms are gaining ground, and while the introduction of the term
                     <term>digital humanities</term> may originally have been a top-down or
                  strategy-driven process starting with journal names, funding initiatives and
                  conferences, it now seems as if also <term>digital humanist</term> is spreading
                  quickly as a means of self-identification. This is especially true of the plural
                  form in addressing digital humanists collectively as in <title rend="quotes">Calling all Digital Humanists in the Pacific Northwest: Organizing THATCamp
                     PNW</title>
                  <ptr target="#meloni2009"/>. A more recent development is that scholars to a
                  larger extent describe themselves as digital humanists on their personal websites
                  and in other contexts, although there may be a certain degree of hesitancy: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#french2009b">Recently I’ve claimed <q>digital humanist,</q> though that
                        term is arcane and hard to define. I define it as <q>someone with a
                           humanities degree who’s interested in computers.</q>
                     </quote>
                     <ptr target="#french2009b"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>It would seem that the individualized forms <term>digital humanist</term> and
                     <term>digital humanists</term> are more commonly used in relation to the
                  digital as tool (and the humanities computing tradition) than the digital as study
                  object, but the landscape is shifting. We also need to bear in mind that
                  institutional identity is often linked to particular disciplines and departments
                  rather than to the humanities more broadly (which is a much more abstract
                  construction). It could be speculated that comparatively speaking, people in the
                  digital humanities may seem to have a stronger sense of the humanities as a
                  construct and as a whole since they often operate across several disciplines and
                  since their position and identity are more strongly linked to the humanities at
                  large. As for <term>digital humanities</term>, several organizations and consortia
                  (with different agendas) are pushing for the term. A move of considerable symbolic
                  power is the 2008 establishment of the Office of Digital Humanities at the
                  National Endowment for the Humanities in the U.S.</p>
               <p>These changing patterns can be exemplified by means of some crude search data from
                  Google and the development between two data points approximately one and a half
                  years apart. Needless to say, these data should be treated with caution in terms
                  of methodology and accuracy, and the absolute figures have little significance.
                  What is interesting is the indication given by the relative change in frequency.
                  On March 10, 2008, the query <q>digital humanist</q> resulted in 420 hits on
                  Google. There were about the same number of hits for the plural form <q>digital
                     humanists</q> (456 hits), and there were (about) 99,800 instances of <q>digital
                     humanities.</q> The same queries executed on October 6, 2009, show that
                     <q>digital humanist</q> is about eight times more common (3460), <q>digital
                     humanists</q> 40 times more common (18,600), while the number of instances of
                     <q>digital humanities</q> has doubled (about 180,000). The general pattern
                  seems to be that direct references to digital humanists (singular and plural) have
                  become much more common relative to references to digital humanities. The more
                  frequent use of the plural form (five times as frequent as the singular form) is
                  not surprising given that it carries with it a lesser degree of individuation
                  (focusing on the group of digital humanists rather than individual people, cf.
                     <ptr target="#svensson1998"/>) and seems to point to digital humanists being
                  more commonly identified as a group of individuals. The more moderate relative
                  increase of <q>digital humanities</q> would seem to indicate a degree of
                  saturation or possibly moving away from the over-arching term to more specific
                  reference (<q>digital humanist</q> and <q>digital humanists</q>).</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Part II: Encounters</head>
            <div>
               <head>Introduction</head>
               <p>Another perspective on the landscape of digital humanities can be offered by
                  specific encounters with humanities and technology initiatives. In the following,
                  I draw on some personal encounters with such settings and people between 2001 and
                  2009. Most the encounters are given a material quality through the examination of
                  associated spaces, which is based on the assumption that space and spatial
                  grounding is closely related to knowledge production <ptr target="#livingstone2003"/>.</p>
               <p>The four encounters are by no means a representative sample, but rather a way of
                  continuing the discussion, exploring emerging issues and providing some
                  experiential and material grounding both in relation to the flythrough critical
                  overview of the landscape of the digital humanities presented in Part I and the
                  discussion of modes of engagement in Part III. They are also chosen because they
                  accentuate different modes of engagement and perspectives on the digital
                  humanities. The encounters are ACTlab at University of Texas, the Humanities Art
                  Technology Advanced Collaboratory (HASTAC), the Humanities Computing Program at
                  the University of Alberta, and Internet Studies (through an exchange with Charles
                  Ess).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Encounter 1</head>
               <p>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#private">
                     <emph>There is a large, solid wooden table in the middle of the
                        large, theater-like space. The very tall ceilings, the stage, stage lighting
                        and the industry-like facility all add to the sense of performance and
                        production space. Alongside the walls are workstations and in one end of the
                        space is a cozy corner with couches, a bookcase and Christmas lights. The
                        lights are dimmed and there are several simultaneous ongoing
                        activities.</emph>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>I visited the ACTLab at University of Texas at Austin in 2001 and encountered a
                  studio space with an articulated conceptual underpinning and a set of related
                  practices. I was struck both with the actual space and the clearly stated
                  relevance of its grounding: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#stone2005">It's hard to separate the ACTLab philosophy from the studio
                        space, and vice versa. They are co-emergent languages. The ACTLab studio is
                        the heart of our program and in its semiotics it embodies the ACTLab
                        philosophy.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#stone2005"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Most of the courses given were thematic, which often turns out to be a productive
                  or at least manageable interdisciplinary strategy. Broad themes allow faculty and
                  students from a range of departments to participate around a topic of interest. In
                  Sandy Stone’s words, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#stone2005">Our curricular philosophy is about constructing dynamic
                        topic frameworks which function by defining possible spaces of discourse
                        rather than by filling topic areas with facts</quote>
                     <ptr target="#stone2005"/>
                  </cit>. ACTLab courses at this time included <title rend="quotes">Postmodern
                     Gothic</title> (1996), <title rend="quotes">Gender and Sexuality at the
                     Millennium: The Future of Desire</title> (1998), <title rend="quotes">Reading
                     Reality: Virtual and Physical Narratives</title> (2000). There was a clear
                  emphasis on creating and the below description seem to indicate that making
                  precedes theory, or that making is primary or initial. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#actlab">ACTLab courses are concept-driven, rather than
                        skills-driven; but we believe that theory flows from the act of making,
                        rather than the other way around. The point of each ACTLab course is to help
                        you define, develop, and produce a project that reflects on the social,
                        cultural, aesthetic, political, and personal issues raised in that
                        particular class. […]  Our motto is <emph>make stuff</emph>. We offer you
                        the opportunity to engage cutting-edge technologies, but we also encourage
                        you to view these as tools rather than as ends in themselves. Make sure
                        you're taking advantage of technology, rather than waking up to find that
                        technology is taking advantage of you. That's why we encourage critical
                        thinking, and offer you the opportunity to engage cutting-edge theory along
                        with making. [original emphasis]</quote>
                     <ptr target="#actlab"/>
                  </cit>
                  <note>Accessed 18 August 2008.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Connecting making and critical practice is not simple, and the interrelation is
                  complex and often difficult to analyze. Obviously, these are not distinct
                  categories, and there is a fair deal of blurriness and a dynamic balance. In the
                  case of ACTLab it seems that making is privileged and that critical practice, to a
                  large extent, is achieved through the making. Consequently, there is considerably
                  less focus on more traditional forms of critical production and reflection. This
                  affects the balance and outset, and it seems that an enterprise such as ACTLab has
                  more in common with an art school or a media production studio than a humanities
                  department.</p>
               <p>ACTLab began 1992 in a <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#undocumented">closet</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">Sandy Stone’s description</ref>
                  </cit>. In the subsequent year, a classroom was appropriated, and soon after
                  another classroom. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#actlab">In the process we painted the entire space black and hung
                        Christmas lights from the ceiling, causing neighboring faculty to complain
                        that we were running a den of iniquity. The ACTLab's first floor plan had a
                        seminar table in the middle of the room, and the walls lined with
                        workstations.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#actlab"/>
                  </cit>
                  <note>Accessed 15 February 2010.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The space I visited in 2001 was the new TV/Film production studio acquired in
                  2000, and as noted above, the central table was still part of the setup. The space
                  was quite distinct in combining studio, performance and seminar elements as well
                  as incorporating various technologies (both analogue and digital), and
                  importantly, ACTLab could not be described as a sterile or instrumental space. The
                  spatial grounding of ACTLab is obviously important, and in the personal experience
                  of the author, there is a recurring interest in having lab and studio space when
                  talking to the digital humanities community.</p>
               <p>As evident from both the physical setup of the ACTLab studio and the above quote,
                  technology is an integral part of the setup — and although making does not
                  necessarily have to be digital or digitally supported, technology is undoubtedly
                  an important prerequisite in this space for <q>making stuff.</q> This closeness to
                  technology, <q>tinkering</q> and digitally supported expression is not necessarily
                  that common in the digital humanities. In terms of the modes of engagement
                  discussed in this article, the focus on technology as <q>tools
                     rather as ends in themselves</q> suggests an instrumental relation, which
                  here is intimately linked to the digital as a means of expression and as an
                  activist venue in various projects and installations. Also, through the themes
                  employed in the courses there is — to varying degrees — an interest in the digital
                  as a study object. Nevertheless, it is quite likely that the ACTLab community
                  would never use <q>digital humanities</q> to describe themselves (the online
                  correlation seems almost negative).<note>A Google search on 29 November 2009 for
                        <q>+<q>digital humanities</q> +<q>ACTlab</q>
                     </q> rendered 37 hits, most of which are chance correlations or ACTlab
                     email lists of job opportunities elsewhere.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Although the ACTLab relates to many different disciplines and institutions, there
                  seems to be a clear sense of being outside the traditional structures. Sandy Stone
                  talks about the codeswitching umbrella — a device used to hide what is beneath and
                  vice versa — and the contrast between the inside and outside is fundamental in the
                  model presented. Institutional dire necessities, discourses of closure, structure
                  and bean counting are contrasted with messy creativity, emergent work, risk,
                  passion and deliberate structurelessness. According to Stone, <quote rend="inline" source="#stone2005">When people below the umbrella experience passion, people above the umbrella
                     see structure.</quote> The sense of being outside and oppositional is recurring
                  in the narratives surrounding the ACTLab: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#stone2005">Like any oppositional practice, we don't just live under
                        the codeswitching umbrella; we also live under the institutional radar, and
                        to live under the radar you have to be small and lithe and quick. We cut our
                        teeth on nomadics, and although we've had some hair-raising encounters with
                        people who went to great lengths to stabilize the ACTLab identity, we're
                        still nomadic and still about oppositional practices.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#stone2005"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>This oppositional stance creates a strong discursive delineation between the
                  ACTLab and the rest of the university, and although Stone talks about operating
                  under the radar it also seems that ACTLab clearly and consistently signals its
                  status of being different and oppositional; this is part of the essence of the
                  ACTLab. There are several possible consequences of such a strategy; for instance a
                  strong sense of interior community and a focus on collaboration with particular
                  individuals rather than on structural and institutional collaboration. More
                  importantly, it would seem that an inside position — under the umbrella — is not
                  easily compatible with changing or subverting what is outside (e.g. the rest of
                  the university) — above the umbrella. This is a deliberate and justifiable
                  strategy, of course, but nevertheless an important question is whether there could
                  be mutual gains from a more permeable umbrella?</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Encounter 2</head>
               <p>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#private">
                     <hi rend="italic">It just so happens that on Sept. 29-30, SHL will be hosting
                        an important meeting on digital humanities work which will include two
                        sessions that might be of interest to you: one (in the late afternoon of
                        Sept. 29) a public conversation involving the directors of SHL, the Duke
                        Franklin center, UCHRI, and the like; the second, on the morning of Sept.
                        30, a closed door conversation between the leaders of several new SHL-type
                        research centers and top industry, foundation, and museum people about
                        potential partnerships. You would be most welcome to join either or
                        both.</hi>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>I was visiting Stanford University for a couple of meetings in the fall of 2004,
                  and was interested in establishing contact with the Stanford Humanities Laboratory
                  (SHL) and associated researchers. I was fortunate to stumble across a national
                  meeting on digital humanities organized by HASTAC — the Humanities Arts Science
                  Technology Advanced Collaboratory — mainly held on campus at Wallenberg Hall.
                  HASTAC had recently been co-founded by David Theo Goldberg, UC Humanities Research
                  Institute, and Cathy Davidson, Duke University (in 2002). The above email and
                  friendly invitation is from SHL director Jeffrey Schnapp.</p>
               <p>Wallenberg Hall is a renovated building in the central quad of the Stanford
                  campus, which integrates technology-supported teaching areas, communal spaces,
                  offices and open plan multiple-purpose zones. The large lecture theater which
                  hosted the HASTAC meeting I attended has flexible furniture and three projection
                  screens next to each other. Normally one screen serves as the primary screen and
                  the two others function as supplementary screens. I have seen all of the screens
                  used at the same time, but it is much more common that only the main screen is
                  used. While there was a distinct physical grounding for the meeting, the
                  multi-institutional sentiment and organization of HASTAC was rather based on the
                  idea of a virtual organization.</p>
               <p>At the HASTAC meeting I met a range of people interested in the digital humanities
                  from a number of mostly American universities and institutes. American-style
                  humanities centers were well represented. There was a multi-level discussion with
                  a slant towards the institutional, organizational and visionary. Cathy Davidson
                  and David Theo Goldberg spoke of HASTAC as a project. Both Davidson and Goldberg
                  combine excellent track records in more traditional humanities and social science
                  research with high-level institutional positions, which adds credibility and
                  probably also leads to the foregrounding of questions to do with institutional
                  practice, university-level strategies, national and international perspectives,
                  and funding. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#hastac">HASTAC propels collaboration to a new multi-institutional
                        level. Headed by the leaders in humanities-technology collaboration, HASTAC
                        commands academic attention, and harnesses the prestige and existing
                        infrastructure of top universities, industry, foundations, and government.
                        This leadership team is expert in managing and facilitating
                        interdisciplinary collaboration, and several illustrative projects are
                        already underway. By generating new funding opportunities and reward systems
                        for multi-author and multi-disciplinary projects, HASTAC will compel
                        universities and funders to take note of this new model of scholarship. As
                        an integral part of this process, the HASTAC collaborative will develop,
                        test, and disseminate HASTAC propels collaboration to a new
                        multi-institutional level.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#hastac"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>The language used in the quote above is clearly not indicative of a hesitant
                  humanities, but is rather an example of academic <q>power speak</q> and a clearly
                  proactive humanities. This is particularly clear in the choice of verbs such as
                     <q>commands</q> and <q>compel,</q> and in stressing high-level leadership and
                  expertise. This leadership and commanding perspective would seem to serve the
                  cause well, and helps in identifying the humanities as a strong partner.</p>
               <p>The fact that several humanities centers in the U.S. have served as important
                  platforms and as a driving force for HASTAC is not accidental. At their best,
                  humanities centers and cross-disciplinary institutes are catalysts for
                  humanities-wide perspectives and change (cf. <ptr target="#woodward2009" loc="113"/>). While they work closely with humanities departments, they also typically
                  maintain distance and a high degree of independence (see also <ptr target="#shanks2008"/> for a related vision of humanities hubs).</p>
               <p>At the Stanford-based event, a pronounced interest in collaborative practice,
                  laboratory environments and <q>new social relations</q> was expressed, as well as
                  a concern with the future of the humanities. Questions posed in this session
                  included <q>How will the Humanities survive?</q>, as well as
                  a general discussion of the importance of humanities leadership. The broad and
                  outward sentiment of HASTAC presents an interesting contrast to ACTLab in terms of
                  institutional strategy.</p>
               <p>This largely strategic level conversation was mixed with reporting and discussion
                  of a few ongoing projects and practical-level initiatives. One initiative
                  presented was the online journal <title rend="italic">Vectors</title>. Tara
                  McPherson described the vision behind <title rend="italic">Vectors</title>, which
                  is a truly innovative attempt at moving technology as medium far beyond
                  traditional scholarly manifestations while maintaining scholarly rigor and
                  engagement. Some of the topics of the journal relate to the digital as a study
                  object, but most do not. Some pieces might be described as installations while
                  others are more akin to traditional humanities computing tools, or standard, if
                  multi-modal, articles. Normally there is some element of interaction. The main
                  mode of engagement is arguably technology as an expressive medium, however, and it
                  could probably be argued that the journal rarely includes prototypical tools in
                  line with the humanities computing tradition. Rather, it offers a mix between
                  expressive medium and interpretative tool. We will look at <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> more closely in Part III of this article.</p>
               <p>More generally, initiatives like HASTAC, may risk — especially at an early phase —
                  focusing on strategic-level issues at the expense of the more mundane issues such
                  as actual research and real implementation. Put differently, there may be a gap
                  between strategy, politics and grand visions and the grounding found in individual
                  and institutional practice. This gap may be enlarged by the distributedness of
                  such virtual organizations, although importantly, this organizational form is also
                  scalable and potentially quite powerful. And because of the high-level, structural
                  interest, the scope of transformation advocated may extend far beyond the
                  intersection of the Humanities and information technology proper. While very
                  important and exciting, this large scope and far-reaching ambitions may create a
                  dissonance with ground-level research and education. It might be argued, however,
                  that initiatives such as HASTAC are in fact establishing academic <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#galison1997">trading zones</quote>
                     <ptr target="#galison1997"/>
                  </cit> for the digital humanities, and that dissonance is integral to that
                  process.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, there is an important and complex relationship among pushing for
                  changing funding, university and reward systems, and close contact with various
                  policy makers and industry. There may be a risk of relying too much on external
                  structures and hence directly or indirectly buying into belief systems that are
                  part of such structures. Also, while technology obviously plays an important role,
                  the kind of methodological and technological rigor and infrastructure associated
                  with e.g. humanities computing may not initially be part of the setup.</p>
               <p>Looking at the developments after 2004, HASTAC has grown with the support from a
                  number of institutes, universities, the MacArthur Foundation and several other
                  major funding agencies. Among other things, activities include workshops,
                  conferences and a number of diverse venues to <q>make things happen.</q> There is
                  also a more obvious researcher involvement (also from many young researchers), a
                  HASTAC scholar initiative (which combines local grounding and national level
                  networking), and a very productive attempt at creating an energetic and modern web
                  space for discussing and demonstrating issues with digital humanities, digital
                  media and learning (<ref target="http://hastac.org/">http://hastac.org/</ref>).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Encounter 3</head>
               <p>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#private">
                     <hi rend="italic">
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#private">I don’t want to lose the computing connection,</quote>
                        one of the students (with a computer science background) said. We are
                        discussing digital humanities as a term (relating it to humanities
                        computing) in one of the labs of the humanities computing program at the
                        University of Alberta in Canada. In a well-equipped lab mainly set up for
                        computer workstation work, there was also a large table affording laptop
                        work and meetings. I enjoyed the mixed environment as well as getting a
                        sense of what the students were working on. One student was engaged in a
                        facetted browsing project, another one was doing an analysis of web-based
                        games targeted at girls, and a third one was planning a short-term project
                        to do an international <q>slice</q> of digital humanities for a particular
                        day.</hi>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>I visited the University of Alberta in November 2008, which gave me the
                  opportunity to reconnect with humanities computing and digital humanities in
                  Canada. Based on my admittedly limited experience, it seems that Canadian
                  humanities computing is characterized both by a commitment to humanities computing
                  as practice and paradigm (hence maybe also less use of the term <term>digital
                     humanities</term>) and an openness and willingness to engage with humanities
                  and other disciplines broadly. This leads to a balancing act that often can
                  consume much time and energy, and requires administrative maneuverability. The
                  commitment to working with the disciplines in the case of the Humanities Computing
                  Programme at Alberta (which much humanities computing activities at Alberta is
                  centered around) is basic but not trivial: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#sinclair2002">The balance between pursuing in-depth studies in the
                        intellectual rigours of one discipline versus a broader integration of
                        theoretical approaches is a constant struggle. The programme committee, with
                        consultation from departmental representatives, decided that exposure to a
                        breadth of disciplines should be essential to the MA as a Faculty of Arts
                        programme, but that depth of knowledge in one discipline should be a
                        complementary priority. Students apply to do the MA in Humanities Computing
                        through a ‘home’ department: that is, one of the existing departments in the
                        Humanities, Social Sciences or Fine Arts.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#sinclair2002" loc="174"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>During my visit we had several discussions of institutional models and it was
                  entirely clear that this kind of integration was seen as crucial. Over time,
                  administrative and implementation pathways are established, although trying to
                  establish a multi-department model can be quite challenging. You need to involve a
                  number of departments and you are dependent upon them and their support, and while
                  affiliating students with humanities departments may not be difficult, a far
                  greater challenge may be with departments outside of the humanities proper (not
                  because of these departments, but because of administrative and disciplinary
                  boundaries). Likewise, finding sustainable ways of sharing resources (including
                  faculty) between departments and a humanities computing center or programme can be
                  difficult, especially if the departments are small or pressed financially.</p>
               <p>We also talked about space in relation to the lab I visited, as well as more
                  generally. It was obvious that the fairly large meeting table, prominently placed
                  in the lab as you enter the room, had not been easy to come by. In a <title rend="italic">Humanist</title> entry from 2002, Stéfan Sinclair reports
                  usefully about the first year’s experiences from running the M.A. program in
                  humanities computing at Alberta. One of the challenges he refers to is <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#sinclair2002a">offering social space to accompany the excellent lab space
                        that we have — Humanities Computing should certainly be aware of the
                        importance of human interaction in the work we do</quote>
                     <ptr target="#sinclair2002a"/>
                  </cit>. The social affordances of the space I visited had been come by through
                  taking tables assigned for computers and putting them together into a large
                  meeting table. The administration would not easily approve of a
                     <q>non-functional</q> table. This is a tendency I have come across in labs and
                  university environments around the world — the difficulty of controlling and
                  planning the spaces that often are at the heart of educational and research
                  programs.</p>
               <p>It was apparent from the students talking about their projects that humanities
                  computing at Alberta supports multiple modes of engagement with technology. While
                  technology as tool (as in traditional humanities computing) predominates, some
                  projects were much closer to technology as study object. In general, the
                  intellectual milieu seemed to draw on this multiplexity as well as on creating
                  (often through programming) as an important part of the research process. Part of
                  the discussion concerned Ph.D. possibilities and it was abundantly clear that few
                  schools offer the kinds of programs that meet student expectations.<note>See <ptr target="#klein1990" loc="166–169"/> for a discussion of interdisciplinary
                     degrees and graduate programs.</note> The question is whether such a program
                  should maintain the balance demonstrated in a program such as the M.A. in
                  Humanities Computing, or whether it would provide greater emphasis on either
                  technology or an individual discipline. The transfer between different academic
                  levels and schools can often prove to be a challenge as you build up new curricula
                  and interdisciplinary programs. The temptation can also be to abandon a strong
                  multiple affiliation model for more unified, and eventually disciplinary
                  program.</p>
               <p>I talked to Geoffrey Rockwell about process and methodology in relation to tool
                  building and textual analysis. He is a well-established researcher and organizer
                  in humanities computing who has long experience from large-scale projects such as
                  Tapor, and he has progressively advocated web-based, modular and relatively
                  open-ended tools for a long time (as opposed to the all-in-one software packages
                  that were common earlier in humanities computing), as well as engaged with social
                  software. When I was there, Rockwell and Stéfan Sinclair had just finished a bout
                  of what they call experiments in text analysis or extreme text analysis. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#rockwell2008">The idea is simple. Two people do text analysis together
                        with only one person on the computer and the other directing and commenting
                        (and typing a meta-narrative on another computer). This means that all
                        decisions have to be discussed and negotiated which means that one is forced
                        to reflect on what one is doing, which was the point for us. It takes
                        longer, but you get a better result and you are forced to reflect on what
                        you are doing […] Extreme Text Analysis, as we practiced it, was more a
                        reflective practice, that used experiments in small text analysis to reflect
                        on methodology and technology.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#rockwell2008"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>In their practice, they produce short web essays that do not focus on methodology
                  or text analysis, but on the research question posed. It could probably be argued,
                  however, that there is a basic tool-based sentiment here, which is maybe
                  emphasized by the brevity of the individual analyses. Through using modular tools
                  from the Tapor project, they are able to embed dynamic content in the web essays
                  and, for instance, allowing a reader to check a query or try another one. In the
                  example I was shown, the corpus query used in the article could be rerun, but
                  interestingly and innovatively, you could also run a different query. This type of
                  dynamic tool could be quite useful for not least text-centric academic
                  publication. The researchers document the process through a meta level document
                  and they provide reflections on text analysis. All this is done over a very
                  limited period of time. While Rockwell’s and Sinclair’s extreme text analysis
                  experiments are limited so far, there is no doubt that this is methodologically
                  and conceptually a very interesting approach to text analysis drawing on a new
                  generation of modular web tools, making and experimenting as an important part of
                  the process, and combining interpretative and methodological foci.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Encounter 4</head>
               <p>I had been intrigued by internet studies for quite some time and was interested in
                  Charles Ess’s work in the area, so his visit to HUMlab in the beginning of
                  November, 2009, was very timely. Ess is a professor of interdisciplinary studies
                  at Drury University and presently a guest professor at Aarhus in Denmark. We
                  initiated an energetic discussion about internet studies and other matters, and
                  among other things I learnt that there are presently three handbooks on internet
                  studies or internet research being planned or finished. After his visit, the
                  conversation continued, and the below is directly from our informal email
                  conversation concerning internet studies.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Patrik Svensson:</speaker>
                  <p>My sense of internet studies (IS) is that it largely focuses on internet as a
                     study object (no surprise of course).</p>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>Charles Ess:</speaker>
                  <p>I would say more on the sorts of human/social interactions that are facilitated
                     by the technologies and applications, FWIW — this focus is why...</p>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>PSV:</speaker>
                  <p>IS is not close to the technology in the sense of being involved in much tool
                     building. It does not typically take place in lab and studio environments.</p>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>CE:</speaker>
                  <p>Correct — though occasionally there are the equivalent of controlled
                     experiments that may use a <q>real</q> lab or something analogous.</p>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>PSV:</speaker>
                  <p>My guess is also that the community at large does not have a strong sense of
                     being part of <q>digital humanities</q> (neither in the humanities computing
                     sense, nor in the more expansive and newer reading even if the latter would be
                     closer I guess).</p>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>CE:</speaker>
                  <p>Unfortunately, I think this is correct — unfortunately, because as someone who
                     tries to keep abreast of both worlds, I'm convinced they have much useful and
                     fruitful to say to one another, but as I said, apart from me and perhaps one or
                     two other people, I don't see much in the way of bridges, much less strong
                     interactions between the two domains.</p>

                  <p>A good chunk of this may be the artifact of the origins of what has become
                     called Internet Studies predominantly in the social sciences. To be sure, there
                     is some work done from the standpoint of the humanities — critical versions of
                     cultural studies as applied both to online interactions and the
                     scholarship/research thereupon come to mind, as well as the applied ethics work
                     of Internet Research Ethics. But these are areas largely <emph>not</emph> at
                     work, so far as I can tell, in digital humanities and humanities computing.</p>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>PSV:</speaker>
                  <p>There is a strand in the second type of digital humanities that is very much
                     concerned with the future and development of the humanities (beyond the subject
                     area) — using the digital as a vehicle I think — and my sense is that this is
                     not part of IS to any large extent (seeing the field as potentially reforming
                     the humanities — publication practices, tenure evaluation, collaborative work
                     etc.). There would probably be a bit of this I guess — there seems to be a
                     strong interdisciplinary sentiment in internet studies.</p>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>CE:</speaker>
                  <p>Exactly — and again, it may reflect a resource limit, but not on <q>the other
                        side</q>: only so many humanists to go around, and while a few become
                     engaged with IS, more became engaged with DH.</p>

                  <p>(It occurs to me that this in turn may in part reflect the excitement in the
                     1980s re. hypertext and hypermedia, which dominated at least U.S. attention —
                     including the now venerable TLG [Thesaurus Linguae Graecae] that Willard
                     [McCarty] worked on. That is, those of us who cut our digital teeth on
                     hypertext and hypermedia could see very clearly how computing would radically
                     transform our work in the humanities, so I see this as providing considerable
                     direction and momentum in the trajectory you describe in terms of this strand
                     of the second type of DH.)</p>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>PSV:</speaker>
                  <p>Also, I do not get a sense that most internet studies researchers experiment a
                     great deal with alternative modes of expression, multimodal installations etc.
                     This is important to some kinds of new digital humanities — as represented in
                     the journal <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> among others.</p>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>CE:</speaker>
                  <p>I think it's more accurate to say that they primarily study it as an artifact
                     more than they actively experiment with it, e.g., as many people in
                     Scandinavia, for example, so so — here, in some measure, in conjunction with a
                     strong tradition of design. As you initially said, while more or less everyone
                     I know in IS is tech-happy and tech-savvy — very few take this to the point of
                     actively constructing alternative environments, etc. in the name of research.
                     There's just so much happening before us that it's all one can do to try to
                     research and explore the diverse social and communicative phenomena from
                     especially (but again, not exclusively) social science perspectives...</p>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>PSV:</speaker>
                  <p>Finally, there are some parts of new media like studies or initiatives (not
                     digital humanities normally) that engage in <q>academic activism</q> — using
                     technology to (potentially) change the world or make a political statement etc.
                     Again, my sense is that is not a major part of IS? You may find this sentiment
                     as part of certain kinds of cultural studies I imagine, but it does not seem to
                     be mainstream to me in IS.</p>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>CE:</speaker>
                  <p>Again, I think this is quite accurate — though a more complete picture, in my
                     view, goes like there. A significant number of researchers and scholars in IS
                     are motivated, to some degree or another, by what they see as the
                     transformative potentials of new communication technologies, though this is not
                     always apparent or overt in their work. On occasion, the commitment to
                     progressive politics creates tensions — both with the disciplinary requirements
                     for some version of objectivity (lots of discussion, of course, re.
                        <q>positivist</q> notions whose ghosts will walk the halls of many
                     departments...vis-à-vis, for example, participant-observer methodologies, etc.)
                     and, e.g., in the case of AoIR, institutional/organizational requirements to
                     avoid overt political stands. ICT4D [Information and communication technology
                     for development] is a place where this can comfortably and appropriate come to
                     expression, as well as in cultural studies of the Anglophone sort — though one
                     of our major points of contrast and tension (not to say, conflict) at the
                     recent AoIR conference was how more German-oriented and philosophical senses of
                     critical theory apparently failed to take on board the more radical critiques
                     from the standpoint of race, gender, and sexuality at home in a more Anglophone
                     critical studies tradition.</p>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>PSV:</speaker>
                  <p>I would be very thankful for any comments or clarifications! I realize that IS
                     is not one thing, and that the above is an overgeneralization. I am so glad I
                     met you, and with your experience, work on the edited volume etc. you are a
                     perfect person to ask.</p>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>CE:</speaker>
                  <p>I hope this helps somewhat — and again, many thanks in turn: this has been most
                     helpful indeed for me, and I couldn't be more pleased but to have had the
                     opportunity to start to discuss these matters with. To be sure, I like to think
                     that the work on the Blackwell volume, along with serving on the Executive
                     Committee of AoIR, etc., gives me something of a reasonable overview — but it
                     also gives me the very strong sense that for any generalization/observation I
                     may want to make, the object of my attention is in constant flux and
                     transformation and is being studied from thousands of diverse disciplinary and
                     cultural perspectives: what the hell do I know?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Part III: Modes of Engagement</head>
            <div>
               <head>Introduction</head>
               <p>In a conceptual and disciplinary map of the digital humanities, the encounters
                  described above and the examples cited earlier would be distributed over a rather
                  diverse territory. One important, distinguishing parameter is how different
                  perspectives and initiatives relate to information technology and the digital. For
                  example, as we have seen, traditional humanities computing tends to have a rather
                  instrumental relationship to information technology, which serves primarily as a
                  tool, whereas a cultural or media studies-based approach is more likely to focus
                  on digital culture and the cultural construction of information technology as a
                  study object.</p>
               <p>In the previous analysis, it has been suggested that the territory of the digital
                  humanities can be analyzed fruitfully through looking at principal modes of
                  engagement between the humanities and information technology or the digital.
                  Below, I will examine five major modes of engagement in some more detail:
                  information technology as a tool, as a study object, as an expressive medium, as
                  an experimental laboratory and as an activist venue. The first three modes will
                  receive the most attention. Importantly, these should not be seen as mutually
                  exclusive or overly distinct but rather as co-existing and co-dependent layers,
                  and indeed, the boundaries in-between increasingly seem blurry. This does not
                  mean, however, that it may not fruitful to analyze and discuss them individually
                  as part of charting the digital humanities.</p>
               <p>Different disciplines are likely to privilege different modes of engagement. For
                  instance, cultural anthropology would seem more concerned with technology and the
                  digital as an object of analysis than as a tool, and the converse relationship
                  would probably be true of large parts of history as a discipline. Similarly,
                  different approaches and interdisciplinary research fields express different
                  configurations of engagement with the digital. Some of these will be explored
                  below.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Tool</head>
               <p>The instrumental role of information technology seems rather self-evident.
                  Computers and, more generally, information technology are very capable of handling
                  an increasing set of tasks. Historically, computers have often been seen only as
                  tools, although that perception has changed over time<note>See also <ptr target="#wiberg2005"/> who discusses the development of information
                     technology use from crunching numbers to social interaction.</note>: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#bolter2003">In its fifty-year history, the computer so far has been a
                        calculating machine, an electronic brain, a filing cabinet, a clerk, and a
                        secretary. […] In the 1940s, when the brilliant and elegant John von
                        Neumann, the brilliant and eccentric Alan Turing, and many others were
                        designing the first programmable computers, they were not defining a new
                        medium. They were building super-fast calculating engines to solve problems
                        in science and engineering.</quote>
                     <ptr loc="15" target="#bolter2003"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Computers in humanities computing often take on the role of <q>calculating
                     engines,</q> and although the focus is not on science or engineering problem,
                  they often become <q>textual engines.</q> Also, underlying the use of computers as
                  a tool may be an ideology of cognition and functionalism (cf. <ptr target="#golumbia2009"/>). As has been noted, the instrumental relationship to
                  information technology is nearly a defining property for traditional humanities
                  computing. The website for the Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities
                  (IATH) states that <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#iath">[o]ur goal is to explore and develop information
                        technology as a tool for scholarly humanities research</quote>
                     <ptr target="#iath"/>
                  </cit>.<note>Read in a different way, a statement like this one might be seen as
                     an expression of the expected institutional function.</note> This focus on
                  tools naturally entails that the tools envisioned are different from standard
                  tools such as word processing and web browsers. The challenge, as identified by
                  Andrea Laue and others, also involves producing a new set of tools that are not as
                  machine-like: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#laue2004">In practice, the symbiotic machine became a problem-solving
                        rather than a problem-posing device. For the most part, that is how the
                        computer continues to function. Licklider’s dream remains largely
                        unfulfilled. Perhaps transforming the computer from machine to tool, from a
                        device that automates mundane mental tasks to one that augments critical and
                        creative thought, is the task now facing computing humanists.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#laue2004" loc="159"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Interestingly, Laue’s argument is clearly placed within the framework of computer
                  as machine or tool. In some other varieties of digital humanities, for instance
                  cybercultural, internet and media studies and internet studies, the instrumental
                  use of information technology does often not extend far beyond standard tools.
                  Here the tools used are mainly a means to an end and do not necessarily carry much
                  prominence. Neither is there typically a strong interest to create and develop
                  tools.</p>
               <p>Increasingly, however, different kinds of tools and data are made available over
                  the web, and it would seem much easier at the present for researchers to try out
                  available tools than previously — for instance, through employing web-based
                  software such as visualization tools or various APIs<note>Application Programming
                     Interface.</note> to online services such as map services, social platforms and
                  data base systems. Data can also be systematically collected from online
                  environments, games (e.g. game metrics), as well as through tools and
                  methodologies such as eye-tracking equipment (e.g. for analysis of game play or
                  online newspaper reading) and multi-spectral analysis (e.g. reconstruction of the
                  making of art pieces such as paintings). Environmental archaeology data can be
                  used for large scale aggregated modeling and visualizations of pre-historical
                  environments, and data and material about historical sites can be used to create
                  virtual reconstructions. Naturally, methodology and critical assessment of data
                  sources and interpretative processes are quite important here. The same is true of
                  grand projects such as <q>cultural analytics</q> at University of California at
                  San Diego, which strive to use quantitative, analysis, interactive visualization
                  and, to some degree qualitative analysis<note>The extent of qualitative analysis
                     in cultural analytics can be discussed. Lev Manovich tends to present a strong
                     quantitative model (see e.g. <ptr target="#manovich2009b"/> and the discussion
                     of Quantitative Cultural Analysis). See also <ptr target="#navas2009"/> for a
                     discussion of qualitative elements.</note> to <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#manovich2009a">begin analyzing patterns in massive cultural data
                        sets</quote>
                     <ptr target="#manovich2009a"/>
                  </cit>. Manovich describes the implications of such an approach: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#manovich2009b">We believe that a systematic use of large-scale
                        computational analysis and interactive visualization of cultural patterns
                        will become a major trend in cultural criticism and culture industries in
                        the coming decades. What will happen when humanists start using interactive
                        visualizations as a standard tool in their work, the way many scientists do
                        already?</quote>
                     <ptr target="#manovich2009b"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Here, very powerful tools are projected, and the cultural analytics research group
                  has some impressive examples<note>See <ptr target="#douglass2009"/>
                  </note>, but obviously any alignment with science methodology in this manner
                  should be critically analyzed, as well as the hopes invested in visualization and
                  access to large amounts of data. <ptr target="#lamarre2010"/> points to the
                  importance of the humanities being involved in setting agendas for this kind of
                  work to avoid <quote rend="inline" source="#lamarre2010">a massively scientifistic attitude</quote> as
                  well as his reservations in terms of methodology: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#lamarre2010">For experimenters know that the set-up is directed toward a
                        certain problematic, and if the results are not predictable in advance, they
                        will nonetheless fall in a certain range and register of experience. Without
                        foregrounding some of these issues, I think we risk capitulation to
                        neoliberalism and the university as hedge fund, to put it crudely.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#lamarre2010"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>There is obviously a range of available and possible digital tools for the
                  humanities, and it does not seem that the digital humanities has yet developed a
                  comprehensive framework, design sensibility and assessment methodology that will
                  allow us to design, critically discuss and evaluate different kinds of tools in
                  the best possible way (cf. <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2004"/>). Maybe this is not
                  possible given the diversity of tools and epistemic traditions, but at least we
                  need to foster careful design and the reflective analysis of tools. As for the
                  design process, there seems to be a fairly common realization that the digital
                  humanities have not traditionally focused on design or realized the importance of
                  it. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#drucker2009a">Blindness to the rhetorical effects of design as a form of
                        mediation (not of transmission or delivery) is an aspect of the cultural
                        authority of mathesis that plagues the digital humanities community.
                        [original emphasis] </quote>
                     <ptr target="#drucker2009a" loc="6"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>The work of Drucker and her colleagues at University of Virginia is inspirational
                  in the sense of innovation within a conceptual framework, a strong interest in
                  design and a critical discussion of both the framework and the actual tools.
                  Several of the tools or projects (e.g. <title rend="italic">Temporal
                     Modeling</title> and <title rend="italic">Ivanhoe</title>) are situated and
                  carefully described in <ptr target="#drucker2009a"/>. One interesting question is
                  why we do not see more interpretative tools of this kind following these early
                  experiments. It may be cost, a strong tradition of more established tools, low
                  adoption, or possibly limited generalizability over curricula and
                  institutions.</p>
               <p>Another fairly well-documented example is Pliny developed by the Center for
                  Computing in the Humanities at King’s College which is a note-taking and
                  annotation tool particularly aimed at humanities research and which allows users
                  to <quote rend="inline" source="#cch2006">integrate these initial notes into a representation of an
                     evolving personal interpretation</quote>
                  <ptr target="#cch2006"/>. There is a fairly strong conceptual grounding here: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#bradley2008">In <ref type="offline">Bradley 2005</ref> I suggested that
                        tool builders in the digital humanities would have better success persuading
                        their non-digital colleagues that computers could have a significant
                        positive benefit on their research if the tools they built fit better into
                        how humanities scholarship is generally done, rather than if they developed
                        new tools that were premised upon a radically different way to do
                        things.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#bradley2008"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Pliny is deliberately not web-based (and hence maybe set in a old-style
                  instrumental paradigm) and the power comes from the openness and not making too
                  many assumptions about what resources may be valid or how a detailed
                  interpretative process works — instead allowing space for that interpretation and
                  epistemic alignment to be carried out. In this space creating, Pliny and the UVA
                  tools have something in common, although the rationale, reasoning and epistemic
                  commitments behind them are quite different.</p>
               <p>A third example is the UC Los Angeles-based project HyperCities which may arguably
                  be classified as a tool or a set of tools, but project leader Todd Presner says
                  that he rather sees it as <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#presner2009">part of an intellectual-humanistic project for
                        conceptualizing/studying culture and cultural artifacts</quote>
                     <ptr target="#presner2009"/>
                  </cit>. HyperCities is an ambitious project with its research driven conceptual
                  grounding, use of online sources such as Google Maps, powerful visualization, rich
                  layering of information and materials, user (including student) annotation and
                  international perspective (cf. <ptr target="#presner2010"/>). It is quite easy to
                  see how it has real research and pedagogical potential, and how the interface and
                  richness of the materials can easily attract humanities scholars. It is also a
                  platform and concept that has both maintained a conceptual basis and developed
                  considerably from the early start as Hypermedia Berlin (the first pilot version
                  was launched in 2004). In essence, the platform has become much more participatory
                  and dependent on established Web 2.0 tools such as Google Maps.<note>As <ptr target="#haylesa"/> notes, although this can be construed as a problem
                     (mainly because of commercial interests), it can also be seen as a necessary
                     part of the solution.</note> The challenge for such large-scope projects may be
                  to keep abreast as new projects and platforms emerge, and also, some early system
                  level decisions can affect possible functionality. In the case of HyperCities, it
                  would seem that the system was not originally designed to allow for searching as a
                  main way to interact with the database and materials, which can be seen as
                  problematic when <q>search</q> is currently such a strong paradigm.</p>
               <p>This is obviously not the place to present a fully-fledged framework for
                  classifying and analyzing digital tools for the humanities, but hopefully the
                  above examples can work as a way of opening up a discussion of relevant
                  parameters. It is fairly obvious that we are concerned with a range of tools and
                  tool uses. Some are more specific to the digital humanities than others. For
                  instance, while word processors certainly play a very important role for digital
                  humanities, they are not specific to digital humanities. A concordance program,
                  however, is much more specific and used by a smaller group of people. Many of
                  these users would be <q>digital humanists</q> in disciplines such as linguistics
                  and literary studies. This tool has an analogue predecessor and a largely
                     <q>automatic</q> function. Consequently, it could be argued that a traditional
                  piece of concordance software exhibits a high level of automaticity and fairly low
                  degree of innovativeness. We may also want to refer to the interpretative,
                  representational and explorative powers of tools: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#mcgann2002">To date, the digital technology used by humanities scholars
                        has focused almost exclusively on methods of sorting, accessing, and
                        disseminating large bodies of materials. In this respect the work has not
                        engaged the central questions and concerns of the disciplines. It is largely
                        seen as technical and pre-critical, the occupation of librarians, and
                        archivists, and editors. The general field of humanities education and
                        scholarship will not take up the use of digital technology in any
                        significant way until one can clearly demonstrate that these tools have
                        important contributions to make to the exploration and explanation of
                        aesthetic works.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#mcgann2002"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>There is a difference between a tool that mainly allows you to search for
                  linguistic constructions in a text database (showing results in a table or
                  concordance list), and a tool that does that as well as provides an interface
                  where you can visualize results, create interpretative models, collaborate with
                  others and combine different medial representations (for instance sound-audio,
                  text, a timeline and relevant metadata).</p>
               <p>Further suggestions for what to look for in analyzing and designing tools are the
                  materiality of the interface, structural properties (e.g. layering of
                  information), collaborative affordances, interpretative scope and modes of
                  distribution. Through interaction design research, a number of digital artifact
                  qualities can be brought into the picture. For instance, <ptr target="#lovgren2004"/> bring up categories such as motivation (e.g.
                  playability and seductivity), immediate experience (e.g. pliability and fluency),
                  social level (e.g. social action space and identity), structural qualities or
                  engineering ideals (e.g. elegance and efficiency) and user creation of meaning
                  (e.g. ambiguity and surprise). Also, certain methodologies and work practices from
                  the design world may often add significantly to digital humanities practices — for
                  instance prototyping, participatory design and combining conceptual level work
                  with careful consideration of interface and interaction.</p>
               <p>Digital tools should not be seen as neutral artifacts. In their construction and
                  contextual use, they reproduce certain assumptions. While generic tools such as
                  word processing programs are arguably more easily construed as <q>neutral,</q> it
                  would seem that the subjective and epistemic nature of tools is more explicit with
                  interpretative and experimental tools. This does not mean that the epistemic
                  commitments associated with digital tools and tool use are well understood or
                  given enough attention. As <ptr target="#ratto2006"/> shows, these commitments are
                  particularly relevant when different disciplines and outsets deal with the
                     <q>same</q> digital objects, and hence important in relation to an expansive
                  notion of digital humanities. Epistemic commitments may influence and determine
                  identification of study objects, methodological procedures leading to results,
                  representative practices, and interpretative frameworks.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Study Object</head>
               <p>Information technology, or more broadly the digital, can be seen as affording
                  objects of analysis for the humanities. Linguists may use digital tools (such as
                  concordance software, acoustic analysis or dialectal mapping tools) to do their
                  research, but if they move to incorporate digitally mediated language or
                  communicative patterns in Second Life as objects of study into their research, we
                  are concerned with a different mode of engagement. Of course, these objects may be
                  studied using digital tools. These <q>new</q> objects of study (see <ptr target="#peters2009"/> for a sophisticated argument of the <q>new</q> in new
                  media) can be more or less controversial in relation to the discipline at
                  question. They can clearly be within the disciplines, arguably be part of new,
                  emerging disciplines or relate to different kinds of interdisciplinary centers and
                  associations.</p>
               <p>The institutionalization of the humanities in the late 19th century and former
                  part of the 20th century may be said to have linked certain objects of study, or
                  facets of those objects, to certain disciplines. In her analysis, <ptr target="#klein1990" loc="24–8"/> discusses this process of disciplining and how
                  it was related to scientification of knowledge, a new relationship between amateur
                  and professional, and often minute methodologies to handle humanistiqc objects.
                  The <q>same</q> analytical objects could be analyzed using the different
                  methodologies strongly associated with the disciplines, but with this growth of
                  disciplinary focus and specialization, there not would necessarily be a great deal
                  of synthesis.</p>
               <p>This model has been under pressure from an increased interest in interdisciplinary
                  studies and different types of thematically organized research agendas. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#davidson2004">It is easy to see, in hindsight, how disciplines
                        professionalized and specialized objects of analysis. To say that such
                        objects were (under the older regime) disciplinarily driven is to say that
                        disciplinary demands — historical and textual, institutional and official,
                        methodological and epistemological — determined which were legitimate for
                        analysis.</quote>
                     <ptr loc="49" target="#davidson2004"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Davidson and Goldberg point to how interdisciplinary practice calls for objects of
                  analysis that are more diffuse and multiplex than those disciplinarily conceived.
                  There is a tension between this type of object and the established sense of what
                  normally constitutes a valid object of analysis in the traditional humanities. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#drucker2009a">Traditional humanistic work assumes its object. A book,
                        poem, text, image, or artifact, no matter how embedded in social production
                        or psychoanalytic tangles, is usually assumed to have a discrete, bounded
                        identity.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#drucker2009a" loc="28"/>
                  </cit> Drucker emphasizes the codependent nature of that identity. One interesting
                  question is how and if these codependent identities and diffused objects of
                  analysis are manifested in the digital humanities work that primarily see the
                  digital as a study object.</p>
               <p>Let us again look at a particular community that can be assumed to have a
                  commitment to technology as study object in a broad sense. In this sense, study
                  objects include phenomena, cultural artifacts and processes that to some extent
                  are digitally inflected. There is a fairly large group of researchers whom engage
                  in <q>internet studies,</q> of which many are organized by the Association of
                  Internet Researchers (cf. the encounter described in Part II above). They had
                  their tenth conference in October 2009. The organization is presented on their
                  website as follows: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#aoir">The Association of Internet Researchers is an academic
                        association dedicated to the advancement of the cross-disciplinary field of
                        Internet studies. It is a member-based support network promoting critical
                        and scholarly Internet research independent from traditional disciplines and
                        existing across academic borders.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#aoir"/>
                  </cit> The description above must be taken to be a fairly authoritarian as it
                  appears on the main <q>about</q> page on the organization’s website. Moreover, it
                  is interesting to see that the research promoted is described as <q>independent from trauditional disciplines.</q> While we
                  should not read too much into this, it is somewhat telling that the perspective
                  presented is one of alleged independence rather than one pointing to the
                  interaction between the organization and associated research in the traditional
                  disciplines (where most of the participants are probably located
                  institutionally).</p>
               <p>Returning to the question of modes of engagement, it seems quite clear that the
                  principal mode for internet research of this type is the digital or the internet
                  as an object of analysis. This is not very surprising, of course, but it makes
                  internet studies an interesting area to look more carefully in this context — also
                  because it is a large and important organization. The investment in this
                  particular mode of engagement seems quite clear. As the above quote shows, the
                  internet is not necessarily seen as a study object that can be handled within the
                  realms of any existing or new discipline, or even from an interdisciplinary, but
                  not transdisciplinary, perspective. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#hunsinger2005">A trandisciplinary field is one defined by the globality of
                        its object of study, combined with the complex, emergent, and changing
                        nature of that object (Genosko, 2002, p. 26). The very nature of the
                        Internet as an object of study is its incomprehensibility as a whole from
                        disciplinary or interdisciplinary perspectives.</quote>
                     <ptr loc="277" target="#hunsinger2005"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>The study object is thus seen to be too complex or dynamic to be managed by any
                  one discipline, and it can be argued that an approach less based on traditional
                  institutional structure has clear advantages. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#shrum2005">In the indisciplined approach, there is no importance
                        attached to unity of perspective or method because there is no need to
                        engage in exclusionary boundary work. There is only a shared commitment to
                        the importance of systematically analyzing a new phenomenon, even if that
                        phenomenon changes.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#shrum2005" loc="274"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>We might question the ease of analyzing such objects without doing boundary work
                  (where much of the interesting tension tends to take place) and with only a common
                  commitment to analyzing a specific phenomenon (which in a sense makes the studied
                  phenomenon static). It would seem that there is a risk here to disregard the
                  epistemic commitments of the disciplines, as well as the emerging commitments of a
                  new research community.</p>
               <p>In any case, the connection to the digital humanities, which has a stronger
                  historical and epistemic link to technology as a tool, is seemingly weak. Part of
                  the reason is probably exactly the difference in main modes of engagement, and
                  there also seems to be a sense in the digital humanities community, not least the
                  parts more engaged with the digital as a study object, that internet research is
                  too large or too traditional (alluding to the institutional placement) to be
                  included under the heading digital humanities. Looking at the internet research
                  community on a more general level, there seems to be a sense that the perceived
                  independence is quite important. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#hunsinger2005">Internet research could become a subset telecom research,
                        digital studies, or something else, and when it takes on the identity of the
                        other, it will surely lose some of its current richness.</quote>
                     <ptr loc="278" target="#hunsinger2005"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>This emphasis on independent status was also quite clear from the AoIR website
                  definition discussed earlier. On a more particular level, it is also difficult to
                  identify a sense of internet research (in this organized sense) belonging to the
                  digital humanities. For instance, looking at instances of <q>digital
                     humanities</q> on the Air-L email list, the digital humanities is directly
                  mentioned in 27 out of 19619 posts<note>Result of search queries carried out on 08
                     October 8 2009 on the Air-L Archive at <ref target="http://listserv.aoir.org/pipermail/air-l-aoir.org/">http://listserv.aoir.org/pipermail/air-l-aoir.org/</ref>.</note>, and many
                  of these are announcements coming from departments or organizations more invested
                  in the digital humanities.</p>
               <p>In some ways, it is interesting to compare internet research and humanities
                  computing as they represent two parallel traditions with rather different
                  epistemic scopes and principal modes of engagement. In <ptr target="#svensson2009a"/>, a simple text based analysis of the proceedings of
                  the annual digital humanities conference (1996-2004) was carried out to get a
                  better sense of the scope of digital humanities as humanities computing. In order
                  to investigate a presumed commitment to technology as study object, we will now
                  briefly look at the annual Association of Internet Researcher conference in a
                  similar fashion. Again, this kind of data should not be taken too seriously, but
                  together with other material and analysis, it can add to our understanding of the
                  field.</p>
               <p>The analysis is based on ten iterations of the conference (1999-2008) through the
                  full programs of all the conferences. There is hence a partial chronological
                  mismatch with the above study of digital humanities conferences. All titles and
                  names of panels and sessions were included, and all other text removed. Functional
                  words (pronouns, prepositions, conjunctions, modal verbs etc.) were removed, and
                  all <q>content</q> words were retained. The 17 most frequent words all occurred in
                  all ten AoIR conference programs: <term>internet</term> (absolute frequency: 639),
                     <term>online</term> (421), <term>social</term> (213), <term>web</term> (179),
                     <term>digital</term> (148), <term>community</term> (145), <term>virtual</term>
                  (128), <term>research</term> (125), <term>media</term> (123),
                     <term>communities</term> (116), <term>new</term> (105),
                     <term>information</term> (102), <term>use</term> (87), <term>identity</term>
                  (80), <term>study</term> (80), <term>communication</term> (76) and
                     <term>case</term> (73). The contrast between this material and the data from
                  the digital humanities/humanities computing conferences analyzed earlier is
                  significant. While this may not be very surprising, it is interesting to note the
                  very clear pattern. Among the 20 most frequent words for each conference series,
                  there is not a single word that occurs in both corpora. This pattern is also clear
                  in less frequent terms, which tend to be less generic. Looking at the 20th-50th
                  most frequent words, humanities computing as evidenced in the material focuses on
                  databases, models, resources, systems, editions and words, whereas internet
                  studies focuses on space, divide, culture, self, politics and privacy.</p>
               <p>Humanities based engagement with the digital or technology as an object of
                  analysis is obviously multi faceted and complex, but looking at the digital
                  humanities in a broad sense, this mode of engagement seems quite prevalent.
                  Importantly, the digital may not have to be the main focus itself, but rather
                  phenomena, cultural artifacts and processes that are digitally inflected.
                  Initiatives with a significant investment in this mode often seem fairly discrete
                  in the landscape of the digital humanities while they are rarely in fact
                  recognized as digital humanities.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Expressive Medium</head>
               <p>One important and apparent consequence of increased digitalization and, in
                  particular, the web, is highly increased access to and availability of different
                  types of content and media. Some of this content is born-analogue and much of it
                  is born-digital. Increasingly, but not necessarily, these expressions are media
                  rich, polytextual and mixed. <ptr target="#schnapp2009" loc="147"/> discuss <quote rend="inline" source="#schnapp2009">fungibility</quote> — the gathering of many types of content
                  (moving image, text, music, 3D-design, database, graphical detail, virtual
                  walk-through etc.) into a single environment — as the core of digital mediation.
                  Content can accordingly be infinitely manipulated and remobilized without loss. As
                     <ptr target="#mcpherson2009a"/> points out, some disciplines in the humanities
                  have been affected significantly by this change including visual, media and
                  digital studies. This engagement has typically been on the level of object of
                  study rather than the production of expressive, creative media: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#mcpherson2009a">Nonetheless, we have been slow to explore the potential of
                        interactive, immersive, and multimedia expression for our own thinking and
                        scholarship, even as we dabble with such forms in our teaching. With a few
                        exceptions, we remain content to comment about technology and media, rather
                        than to participate more actively in constructing knowledge in and through
                        our objects of study. </quote>
                     <ptr target="#mcpherson2009a" loc="120"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Looking at where we do find complex, multimodal, interactive and networked
                  expressions in the humanities, it is clear that they are more common — but by no
                  means very common — in undergraduate education than in faculty research. This can
                  presumably be traced back to the idea that students are seen as more adept at
                  using new media and that they need this kind of literacy for future careers (in
                  particular outside the academy). On the whole, undergraduate education is probably
                  also more likely to change in relation to external expectations and availability
                  of new expressive modes than research carried out by senior scholars as part of a
                  highly structured reward system. This does not mean that the traditions of
                  undergraduate humanities education are not challenged by these modes: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#rabkin2006">That is, digital media, functioning as they do in the world
                        of networked computing, often break down the boundaries we once took for
                        granted in setting tasks for our students: the finality of composition, the
                        identity of the author, the role of the audience, and the unity of
                        purpose.</quote>
                     <ptr loc="136–7" target="#rabkin2006"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>For instance, looking at the role of the audience, it is quite clear that the
                  sense of an external, and potentially engaged audience, often has a strong
                  motivating function in educational contexts <ptr target="#svensson2009b"/>. More
                  generally, it seems that there is a movement, although fairly slow, in humanities
                  education towards alternative modes of production. <ptr target="#mactavish2006"/>
                  make an interesting comparison with the visual and performing arts and the process
                  leading to their integration into academic curricula: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#mactavish2006">In its growing interest in the research and instruction of
                        multimedia art, design, and culture, therefore, humanities computing finds
                        itself in league with the visual and performing arts in legitimizing
                        technological practice and the creation of non-textual-only scholarly
                        artefacts.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#mactavish2006" loc="241"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>It is not surprising to find that such expressions are more common in
                  undergraduate education than in faculty research and graduate education. An
                  important determining factor is the reward structures of academe. For tenure-track
                  scholars, there is often a sense that digital modes of representation may place
                  you at a relative disadvantage. Indeed, this may be outright advice from senior
                  faculty and administrators. These reward structures may be changing, but at a very
                  slow pace and there is no simple path forward although work such as <title rend="quotes">New Criteria for New Media</title>
                  <ptr target="#ippolito2009"/> is part of a lively and important discussion.</p>
               <p>The reward structures, however, do not always stop Ph.D. researchers from
                  expressing themselves alternatively, but it is often seen as an <q>extra</q>
                  undertaking which does not replace the traditional work needed to qualify
                  academically. Indeed, this pressure sometimes seems to result in securing very
                  strong academic merits as we well as engaging in alternative practices and modes
                  of production.<note>One example of several would be Alex Galloway at New York
                     University who, as a junior faculty, authored three books as well as producing
                     software and being a widely exhibited artist.</note> In some of the discourse
                  surrounding this issue, it may appear that every digital humanist would have an
                  interest in alternative, non-traditional production, but this is obviously not the
                  case. Monographs and, in some disciplines, peer-reviewed articles, are not just
                  tied to a traditional reward system, but may represent a dream of academic
                  expression and a distinct scholarly identity for many young researchers. This
                  sentiment may be difficult to disentangle from the fact that publishing presses
                  and venues are invested with respect and value. <ptr target="#mcpherson2009b"/>
                  points to the importance of working with academic presses to form new kinds of
                  partnerships and platforms for digitally-rich publication.</p>
               <p>There is a range of possible digitally inflected modes of expression, and these
                  are situated within different disciplinary, institutional and personal contexts,
                  and consequently come with different implications and degrees of risk taking. A
                  dissertation presented as a virtual world installation would naturally be much
                  more challenging to the established system than a personal research blog or a
                  research oriented Twitter feed. If that Twitter feed, however, was suggested as
                  carrying academic weight in a tenure portfolio, the stakes would be much higher.
                  Similarly, an online video clip would not be expected to adequately present a
                  research proposal to a funding agency, while it may be seen as potentially useful
                  (or at least not harmful) as a reference in a written application.</p>
               <p>It might be fruitful to also consider less extreme expressive situations where the
                  stakes are not quite as high. The MLA conference in December 2009 provides an
                  interesting example because of the use of networked (mainly text based)
                  communication channels, and how this communication and exposure contributed to a
                  conference that was not technology focused, as well as the external <q>reading</q>
                  of the conference. In particular, the digital humanities contingency at the
                  conference got received fairly large exposure despite their comparatively small
                  numbers. According to Amanda French's calculation, a mere three percent of the
                  conference participants were tweeters (in the sense of producing <q>Twitter
                     entries</q> or tweets), and only few of these came from outside of <q>digital
                     humanities.</q> The relatively large exposure was partly because there were
                  many digital humanities-like sessions, many of them reportedly well attended, but
                  also because the digital footprint of this contingency was comparatively large.
                  Twitter played an important role and the hash tag #MLA09 accumulated 1750 tweets
                  between Dec 4, 2009, and January 4, 2010 (the majority during the actual
                  conference, and the days before and after). Also, the story of one previous
                  attendee, Brian Croxall, and his not coming to the conference for financial
                  reasons made the connection between remote and present participation quite
                  prevalent. In particular as this non-attendee posted his panel contribution online
                  and tweeted about it at the same time as it was read at the conference <ptr target="#croxall2009"/>. Other participants at the conference posted their
                  contributions before they did their conference presentations, and in these cases
                  there may be a Twitter flow before, during and after the actual presentation.</p>
               <p>Some of these uses of media are no more revolutionary than adding a YouTube
                  reference to your application, and the buzz may not be proportionate to the actual
                  impact at the conference,<note>See <ptr target="#parry2010"/>. Matthew
                     Kirschenbaum points to the MLA having a history of being relatively quick at
                     adopting new technologies <ptr target="#golden2010"/>.</note> but overall, one
                  can see how the totality of the conversation and the flow, the media attention
                  (including two articles in the <title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher
                     Education</title>) and the power of aggregation of communication have the power
                  to influence established structures and possibly change the dynamics of an
                  academic conference with a considerable commitment to traditional humanities
                     values.<note>This makes MLA very different from clearly digitally inflected
                     conferences such as THATCamp.</note> Though perhaps not achieved at the MLA
                  conference, there were certainly some illustrative steps taken in this direction.
                  An even more recent example is provided by two partially simultaneous conferences
                  in March 2010 with strong links to the digital humanities: the <title rend="quotes">NITLE Summit 2010: Advancing towards Liberal Arts 3.0</title> and
                  the conference <title rend="quotes">Online Humanities Scholarship, The Shape of
                     Things to Come</title>. Here there was a fairly substantial Twitter-based
                  dialogue, uptake of tweeted questions on the floor, and cross tweeting between the
                  two conferences. I will look at these two conferences more closely in the fourth
                  article in this series.</p>
               <p>A quite different and unsuccessful example of recent use of networked media in a
                  conference situation is the Web 2.0 Expo conference in November 2009, at which a
                  so-called back channel was made front channel through a screen behind the
                  presenter. Tech celebrity Danah Boyd describes her experience of the setup as a
                  speaker: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#boyd2009">And then, within the first two minutes, I started hearing
                        rumblings. And then laughter. The sounds were completely irrelevant to what
                        I was saying and I was devastated. [...] I didn't know what was going on but
                        I kept hearing sounds that made it very clear that something was happening
                        behind me that was the focus of everyone's attention.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#boyd2009"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Her subsequent analysis importantly states that a public-facing Twitter stream
                  forces the audience to pay attention to the back channel. Part of the challenge
                  ahead is about exploring digitally inflected modes of academic expression, how
                  they interrelate, and their importance for humanities scholarship.</p>
               <p>As David Goldberg noted in a talk on May 14, 2009, at Umeå University, it is often
                  easier to accept a changing process than a changed end product. Most of the papers
                  and panels at the MLA conference discussed above were traditional in terms of
                  deliverance, and the use of networked media (mainly <q>process</q>) did not
                  influence these <q>products</q> in any major way (with the possible exception of
                  Croxall's paper). Looking at academic publishing rather than conferences, a rich
                  collaborative and networked process may be what leads to the publication of
                  monograph (a privileged form of publication), but the monograph itself is likely
                  to be seen as the product of one person or a few people. The process may partly be
                  multimodal and networked, but the product is likely to be textual and single
                  voice.</p>
               <p>It seems clear that new academic journals only published digitally are more likely
                  to be open to alternative modes of publication than traditional print
                     journals,<note>There are, however, a range of examples of traditional print
                     journals that have converted to a digital format successfully and innovatively
                     (e.g. <title rend="italic">Jump Cut</title>).</note> and I will now look at two
                  examples from the world of digital humanities: <title rend="italic">Digital
                     Humanities Quarterly</title> and <title rend="italic">Vectors: Journal of
                     Culture and Technology in a Dynamic Vernacular</title>. These journals reflect
                  two fairly different traditions in the digital humanities. The inaugural issue of
                     <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> is from the fall/winter of 2005 and the
                  first DHQ issue was published in the spring of 2007.</p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> is published by the
                  Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations as a peer review and open access
                  journal. It is exclusively an online publication and there is a commitment to <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#dhq2010a">experiments in new media.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#dhq2010a"/>
                  </cit> A distinction is made between text centric and media centric submissions,
                  and the former are submissions whose base format is text that may include ordinary
                  multimedia such as image, sound and video files (in standard formats). Media
                  centric submissions are defined as <quote rend="inline" source="#dhq2010b">submissions whose base
                     format is something other than text. They may include <q>extraordinary
                        multimedia</q> (multimedia in non-standard formats) and may involve more
                     complex interactive behavior.</quote> All submissions can be media centric (or
                  text centric), but there is also a specific submission type called <q>interactive
                     works.</q> According to the Guidelines for Submission, suitable works can
                  include original hypertext fiction, an online educational application or game, an
                  interactive visualization or an original interactive digital artwork <ptr target="#dhq2010b"/>. Despite this expressed interest in interactive works and
                  a commitment to experimentation, in many ways <title rend="italic">DHQ</title>
                  remains, at least on the level of its interface, a traditional, text-based
                  academic journal. However, we need to acknowledge the importance of the journal
                  having an open access format, underlying structured data and a rigorous
                  peer-review system as well as being freely and publicly available.</p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> never set out to be a traditional academic
                  publication, but rather an experimental journal. It would seem to be an expression
                  of the multimodal humanities that editor <ptr target="#mcpherson2009a"/> described
                  in her categorization of the digital humanities. The following description is from
                  a Call for Projects from the spring of 2004: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#vectors2004">
                        <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> is a new, international electronic
                        journal dedicated to expanding the potentials of academic publication via
                        emergent and transitional media. <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> brings
                        together visionary scholars with cutting-edge designers and technologists to
                        propose a thorough rethinking of the dynamic relationship of form to content
                        in academic research, focusing on the ways technology shapes, transforms and
                        reconfigures social and cultural relations.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#vectors2004"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>It is clear that <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> deliberately positions
                  itself in relation to traditional academic publishing as well as first-generation
                  multimedia work. There is a commitment to <q>moving far beyond
                     the <q>text with image</q> format of most online scholarly
                     publications.</q> At the beginning of 2010, five issues had been published
                  (Vol 1:1 to Vol 3:1), with a sixth expected to go live soon.</p>
               <p>On a simple numerical level, <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> and <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> have generated about the same number of issues,
                  although <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> started two years later. Each <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> issue has a specific theme, and for the first
                  five issues the themes have been <title rend="quotes">Evidence</title>, <title rend="quotes">Mobility</title>, <title rend="quotes">Ephemera</title>, <title rend="quotes">Perception</title> and <title rend="quotes">Difference</title>.
                  Of the <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> issues published so far, there is one
                  themed issue <title rend="quotes">Changing the Center of Gravity: Transforming
                     Classical Studies Through Cyberinfrastructure</title> and three thematic
                  clusters: <title rend="quotes">Done</title>, <title rend="quotes">Data
                     Mining</title> and <title rend="quotes">Digital Textual Studies: Past, Present,
                     and Future.</title> A simple comparison of the thematic foci hints at different
                  epistemic traditions being involved. The themes chosen for <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> relate to broad humanities-oriented research areas whereas the
                     <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> theme and clusters focus more on technology,
                  methodology and the development of textual studies. Again, the data are crude, but
                  the pattern is fairly clear.</p>
               <p>In the first five issues of <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> (Vol 1:1 to 3:2),
                  there are a total of 36 articles (including the <q>special cluster</q>
                  contributions). Of these, more than a third (14) have no non-textual elements
                  whatsoever, although three of the articles have textual tables. Another 4 articles
                  have a single non-textual element: a picture of deformed text, an inscription on a
                  stone, a mathematical formula, and a screenshot from a piece of software called
                  the manuscript browser. It is interesting to note that these images are indeed
                  very textual. Looking at the full <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> material, there
                  are many images of manuscripts, book pages and text-oriented software.</p>
               <p>It could be argued that the privileged mode of engagement of <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> is technology as a tool and that there is a strong interest in
                  digitalized text, editions, text analysis and methodology. Moreover, it would seem
                  that this epistemic tradition is also represented in the actual medial expression.
                  The journal is predominantly textual, many of the relatively few non-textual
                  elements allude to text, the text is XML encoded, and amenable to <q>use</q> and
                  reference. In sense of multimodal representation and digital expressiveness, the
                  journal is not experimental, although there is a solid textual basis that can
                  possibly be used in tools.</p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">Vectors</title>, on the other hand, is clearly invested in
                  the digital as an expressive medium in an experimental and creative way. The
                  technology itself does not seem to be a primary focus, whereas it is interwoven in
                  a critical study of the digital (on one level, as a study object) as well as in
                  the actual academic expression. This excerpt is from the introduction to the
                     <title rend="quotes">Difference</title> issue (Vol 1:3): <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#mcpherson2007">In trying to understand how difference matters in the
                        digital era, we should perhaps suspect that the very structures of our
                        information economy (and of the code that underwrites it) look a particular
                        way today precisely because the Civil Rights and other freedom movements
                        happened at mid-century. Both cybernetics and Civil Rights were born in
                        quite real ways of World War II and are caught in tight feedback loops.
                        Certain aspects of modularity, fragmentation, and dispersion that are
                        endemic to digital media also structure the more covert forms of racism and
                        racial representation that categorize post-Civil Rights discourse.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#mcpherson2007"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> presents a challenge in terms of analysis as
                  it is much more difficult to <q>get to</q> in terms of the full content compared
                  to <title rend="italic">DHQ</title>. In <title rend="italic">Vectors</title>,
                  media and content are embedded in the projects, and principally, the projects have
                  to be <q>experienced,</q> and the reader often gets content bit by bit. For a few
                  projects, there is a visualized index that provides access to different elements
                  that make up that particular project including text, images and connections
                  between elements. Interestingly, these indexes show some of the underlying
                  ontology of <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> in terms of the way content is
                  structured and packaged. The <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> team has
                  developed a Dynamic Backend Generator (DBG)<ptr target="#vectors2006a"/> described
                  as a scholarly middleware tool, an easy-to-use database authoring tool and an
                  intellectual sketchpad. Presumably, this tool is not used for all the projects. As
                  any tool, it would seem likely that it imposes a kind of structure and ontology
                  even if it is a very dynamic platform.</p>
               <p>While <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> allows traditional academic referencing
                  through text and numbered paragraphs, there is no easy way to reference bits of
                  content that are part of <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> projects.<note>It
                     could probably be done through using screen capture software and uploaded
                     captures, but this has to be achieved outside of the platform itself, and would
                     presumably be fairly far-fetched for most readers.</note> Indexes allow
                  reference to individual components outside of the project itself, but for most
                  projects, there is no readily available index of this kind. It may be argued that
                  limited referenceability of <title rend="italic">Vectors</title>' <q>packaging</q>
                  is a consequence of the multi-modal, installation-like format. Simple text is
                  obviously easier to reference than video or events in game-like worlds. However,
                  this an important issue in relation to a connected <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#ippolito2009">collective ether</quote>
                     <ptr target="#ippolito2009" loc="71"/>
                  </cit>, and there is a tension between self-contained installation-like academic
                  publications and the kind of referencing and collaborative knowledge building that
                  is an integral part of knowledge building in much of the humanities.</p>
               <p>This tension can also be evidenced in some of peer commentary and discussion
                  associated with the <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> projects. This comment is
                  by Leo Braudy in relation the Anne Friedberg’s <title rend="quotes">The Virtual
                     Window Interactive</title> (design by Erik Loyer): <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#braudy2006">I wonder generally if the basic interactive format in some
                        ways vitiates the force of an ongoing argument, not just in Friedberg’s
                        project but in any project presented this way. A book, say, can be randomly
                        accessed but also may have an argumentative spine. There is certainly a
                        strong spine here, but I find it gets lost in the array of examples and
                        commentary. The timeline functions as a spine of sorts, but primarily as it
                        focuses on the history of developing technology.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#braudy2006"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>This is not necessarily a criticism of the format of the journal or this
                  particular project, but rather an issue of what we expect, how cohesion and
                  complex argument are created, what our frame of reference is (book or artistic
                  installation), as well as modes of consumption.</p>
               <p>While there are obviously structural commonalities in design and expression in
                     <title rend="italic">Vectors</title>, there is considerably variation in terms
                  of expression. In the <title rend="quotes">Difference</title> issue discussed
                  above, the projects are quite different. <title rend="quotes">Blue Velvet:
                     Re-dressing New Orleans in Katrina's Wake</title> by David Theo Goldberg and
                  Stefka Hristova (design by Erik Loyer) is fairly sequential on one level, as you
                  get access to a new main text as soon as you have <q>read</q> the previous one.
                  Arguably text is the dominant carrier of meaning, although the piece is also
                  distinctly aural, visual and almost poetical. The textual expression itself is not
                  uniform. Not only does the text move, but it also is textured through the use of
                  different font sizes, colors and at times slanted text. The layout and
                  presentation of text is meaningful and an important part of the narrative. There
                  are also a number of images and a few films, all of which contribute to a coherent
                  and suggestive narrative. Another of the projects, <title rend="quotes">Killer
                     Entertainments</title> (by Jennifer Terry, design by Reagan Kelly), uses three
                  juxtaposed windows with video clips of combat from Iraq and Afghanistan as well as
                  contextual, networked nodes that provide information and critical reflection. The
                     <title rend="quotes">RED Project</title> (by Christian Sandvig, from the same
                  issue) traces predicted Wi-Fi use on an information layer on top of Yahoo! Maps
                  based on statistics, U.S. census data and a conceptual model.</p>
               <p>This expressive variation contrasts starkly with <title rend="italic">DHQ</title>,
                  where the format and mode of expression are quite predictable and
                  conventionalized. To use <title rend="italic">DHQ</title>’s terminology and
                  classification, <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> is text centric publication
                  whereas <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> is a media centric publication. These
                  expressive preferences are tightly linked to different epistemic traditions.
                     <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> comes from a humanities computing tradition
                  invested in text and tools, and <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> comes from a
                  cultural studies and media production setting (at University of Southern
                  California), where the digital is both a multiplex expressive mode and an object
                  of analysis.</p>
               <p>In most ways, <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> is a traditional, if digital,
                  publication. There is a structural layer of encoding, but at this point, it seems
                  more part of the back end than really useful for most readers, and there is
                  certainly great potential here. For instance, there would seem to be a niche in
                  relation to encouraging dynamic interfaces to textual databases (cf. the
                  discussion of extreme text analysis in Part II of this paper). There is also a
                  conveyed interest in alternative modes of expression, but there is not much yet in
                  terms of content. This clearly indicates the difficulty of actually facilitating
                  complex multi-modal modes of academic expression.</p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> has focused on being experimental and
                  multi-modal, and has implemented and funded a production process that includes
                  fellowships and additional resources. Needless to say, both are important
                  publication venues for the digital humanities, although in different ways. It is
                  not chance that the current article was intended for the <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> from the very beginning.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Exploratory Laboratory</head>
               <p>Some instrumental uses of digital technology in humanities contexts introduce an
                  exploratory methodology, where the researcher or student is encouraged to explore
                  materials, datasets or issues in an experimental fashion. A simple example would
                  be a series of multimedia productions produced in Sweden about 10 years ago which
                  covered the history of different parts of the capital (e.g. <title rend="quotes">Söderskivan</title> which covers the Southern part of Stockholm), by tracing
                  history, large-scale demographic data and an extensive set of materials through an
                  interactive and exploratory interface <ptr target="#stockholm1998"/>. This
                  interface allowed easy navigation through large data sets, used multiple modes of
                  visualization, gave quick responses and encouraged experimenting with the
                  material. Although not interpretative in a strong sense, there is definitely a
                  conceptual link to interpretative tools of the type discussed earlier, as
                  exemplified by the tools the University of Virginia has produced. In this case,
                  information technology does not only help manage, visualize and make accessible
                  very rich materials, but it also facilitates exploratory and experimental
                  interaction with the materials in a way that would not be possible without the
                  technology.</p>
               <p>At a more concrete level, humanities laboratories or digital humanities centers
                  can also be exploratory laboratories that support exploration and experimentation
                  whether in physical, digital or hybrid spaces. The exploratory affordances in an
                  environment such as HUMlab at Umeå University come from the availability of data
                  sets, a mix of analytical and creative practices, interdisciplinary challenges and
                  competencies, international visitors, easy access to different types of
                  technologies (that do necessarily have a precise, predefined function), and from
                  the sense of being in a collaborative, lab or studio like space. Digital platforms
                  such as TAPoR (Text Analysis Portal for Research) and Second Life can also
                  function as exploratory spaces. When museology and culture analysis students at
                  Umeå build exhibitions in Second Life and produce machinima films, the digital
                  space is used as a laboratory that enables enactments and experimentation that
                  would be quite difficult to facilitate in physical space. Similarly, when a
                  researcher explores a text corpus through a collection of <q>interactive</q> tools
                  provided in TAPoR, we may be concerned with a use of technology that extends
                  beyond instrumental tools.</p>
               <p>If we consider the digital more generally as a possible laboratory for the
                  humanities, the discussion can be extended beyond specific interpretative and
                  exploratory tools and spaces. The Humanities is often portrayed as not having a
                  predicative or intervening role, whereas the sciences are said to attempt to both
                  explain and predict natural phenomena. In looking at the primary interests of
                  natural scientists, social scientists and humanists, <ptr loc="4" target="#kagan2009"/> makes an overarching distinction between predication and
                  explanation of all natural phenomena (natural scientists), predication and
                  explanation of human behaviors and psychological states (social scientists), and
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#kagan2009">an understanding of human reactions to events and the
                     meanings humans impose on experience as a function of culture, historical era,
                     and life history</quote> (humanists).</p>
               <p>In a seminal article, <ptr target="#janlert2000"/> introduce the concept of
                     <term>cultural laboratory</term>. They discuss experimental practices of
                  disciplines such as physics, chemistry and biology, including controlled
                  experiments and interceptive methods in limited and controlled environments.
                  According to the authors, traditional humanities disciplines such as history,
                  linguistics, comparative literature and art history make use of such practices to
                  a very limited extent. Also, although the sciences study the <q>given</q> (nature)
                  and the humanities study the <q>created</q> (what humans give rise to), the
                  sciences are more prone to use active, interventionist methods and be involved in
                  creative processes (e.g. creating new technology or materials). The humanities,
                  which studies dynamic processes and cultural products associated with humankind,
                  tend to observe, document and analyze, and are rarely seen as an important factor
                  in creative processes.</p>
               <p>Janlert and Jonsson argue that there are several reasons as to why the humanities
                  tend to be analytical and passive in relation to their study objects: unmanageable
                  objects of analysis (difficult to control and restrict), lack of scalability
                  (often very substantial study objects that cannot be downscaled, and individual
                  cultural artifacts that scale up badly because of the large number required),
                  powerless models (limited quantitative models and lack of tools to manage
                  large-scale qualitative analysis) and, finally, intervening and creating are often
                  seen as controversial in the Humanities (ideologically difficult to implement
                  active and intervening work processes).</p>
               <p>It seems clear that modern information technology can have a significant role in
                  facilitating the type of exploratory space — cultural laboratory — that Janlert
                  and Jonsson discuss. The following is partly based on Janlert and Jonsson’s
                  article. Dynamic visualization can offer a window to large data sets and
                  possibilities to visualize or enact complex objects of analysis. Interactive tools
                  can help the researcher to get an intuitive sense of objects of analysis and the
                  model, and allow fast what-if analyses. On a more profound level, researcher
                  interaction can change the models themselves, or their parameters, data and
                  relations to allow the study of hypothetical correlations or comparison of
                  outcomes from different models applied on the same object or situations.
                     <q>Thick,</q> qualitative models — of detailed environments, objects, processes
                  and correlations, unstructured information — can be handled through use of
                  technology, and complex qualitative correlations can be modeled by massive
                  simulations. Digital, controlled spaces — such as virtual worlds — can be used to
                  facilitate cultural laboratory work. Participants in simulations could be humans
                  or computer run entities. Real time interactive data can feed into digitally
                  enhanced research spaces. Of course, all this is fairly visionary and
                  non-concrete, and maintaining a critical stance is quite important. There is no
                  doubt, however, that we see many of the elements discussed here in some of the
                  interpretative digital humanities tools, interfaces to large material, and some of
                  the <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> projects.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Activist Venue</head>
               <p>The issue of activism as related to the distinction between art, artistic practice
                  and the humanities is by no means clear or uncontested. We earlier used Sharon
                  Daniel’s <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> project <title rend="quotes">Public
                     Secrets</title> as an example of an activism in an academic setting, arguably
                  placed within the digital humanities. There is a strong sense of intervention here
                  that resonates with the <q>active</q> humanities discussed in the previous
                  section. It could be argued that work such as Daniel’s <title rend="quotes">Public
                     Secrets</title> brings together artistic installation and academic expression
                  in a single frame that serves both as cultural critique and activist call for
                  change. Making a connection between <quote rend="inline" source="#raley2009">their tinkering, playing,
                     and visualization</quote> and the academic criticism and cultural critique of
                  her own kind of work, <ptr target="#raley2009" loc="14"/> discusses the aesthetic
                  strategies of artists and activists as using hybrid forms of academic criticism
                     <ptr target="#raley2009" loc="5"/>. According to Drucker, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#drucker2009a">making things, as a thinking practice, is not only
                        formative but transformative</quote>
                     <ptr loc="31" target="#drucker2009a"/>
                  </cit>, and she includes aesthetic provocation as part of the practice of
                  speculative computing as opposed to traditional digital humanities <ptr loc="29" target="#drucker2009a"/>.</p>
               <p>As previously noted, it seems that the contemporary engagement, interventionist
                  interest, critical stance and creative forms of expression associated with some of
                  the digital humanities could be related to a mode of engagement according to which
                  the digital facilitates an activist venue.</p>
               <p>This activist engagement is, again, more prevalent in some areas than in others.
                  One example is when art and the digital come together, as in the Australian-based
                  email list <title rend="italic">-empyre-</title>. Here activist engagement is
                  often presented in an indirect form and sometimes in a highly theorized fashion. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#empyre">-empyre- facilitates critical perspectives on contemporary
                        cross-disciplinary issues, practices and events in networked media by
                        inviting guests -key new media artists, curators, theorists, producers and
                        others to participate in thematic discussions.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#empyre"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>-empyre- themes normally run for a month with guest editors, and previous themes
                  include Sedition (the anti-terrorism bill), Sites in Translation (the San
                  Diego/Tijuana border), Asian Perspective (with Young-Hae Chang Heavy Industries),
                  Play with a Purpose: Politics and Art in Computer Games, and DNA Poetics. In other
                  initiatives and forums, the direct engagement is typically much stronger and there
                  is a stronger focus on acting and intervening. An example of this would be a group
                  such as Preemptive Media (which is related to what is often referred to as
                  tactical media): <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#preemptivemedia">Preemptive Media is a group of artists, activists and
                        technologists who are making their own style of beta tests, trial runs and
                        impact assessments based on independent research. PM is most interested in
                        emerging policies and technologies because they are contingent and
                        malleable. The criteria and methods of PM programs are different from those
                        run by businesses and government, and, therefore, PM gets different results.
                        PM hopes that their inquiries create new opportunities for public discussion
                        and alternative outcomes in the usually remote and closed world of
                        technology-based research and development.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#preemptivemedia"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>In yet other types of experimental work, there may not be a strong or direct
                  agenda per se, but a sense of creating meaning through facilitating different
                  kinds of performative action through the support of digital technology. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#mcgonigal2008">In other words, the massively collaborative, search and
                        analysis gameplay of I Love Bees was a means to an end beyond innovative
                        entertainment. It sought to create a highly connected player-base dedicated
                        to, and impressively capable of, defining and solving large-scale problems
                        together.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#mcgonigal2008" loc="203–4"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Would we expect digital humanists to become involved in pervasive gaming, flash
                  mobs, online installations or Twitter performances? The above quote is from a
                  commercial project (I Love Bees), but similar kinds of methodologies have been
                  applied to e.g. academic discourse as in PlaceStorming v 3.0: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#vectors2006b">If your research were a superhero, what kind of superhero
                        would it be? This provocative question forms the foundation of Jane
                        McGonigal's PlaceStorming, which begins with the seemingly dubious union of
                        academic writing and pervasive, mobile gaming. Not only does the game put
                        the <q>site</q> back into <q>cite,</q> but it perforates the walls dividing
                        academia and the world at large, inviting academicians to relinquish the
                        sanctity of their written texts and gamers to play with those texts,
                        transforming their meaning through an unlikely process of disassembly,
                        recombination and discovery.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#vectors2006b"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>In the dialogue associated with the piece on the <title rend="italic">Vectors</title> website (with only two entries as of October 8, 2009), one
                  question raised (by Tracy Fullerton) concerns the extent to which this perforation
                  of the walls actually works in the sense of reaching outside an already initiated
                  group and particular context. While this perforation may not have been achieved
                  with this particular example, we need to acknowledge the importance of conceptual
                  experimentation. Additionally, assessing activist and participatory practice must,
                  necessarily, bring in a range of variables apart from actual or presumed
                  impact.</p>
               <p>In a suggestive article on <title rend="quotes">Artereality</title>, Schnapp and
                  Shanks point to the intensity and seriousness of the battle fought in <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#schnapp2009">the cultural spaces being opened up by digital
                        technologies</quote>
                     <ptr loc="147" target="#schnapp2009"/>
                  </cit>. Some of the underlying tensions are described here: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#schnapp2009">The most adventurous niches within higher education have
                        started to register these complexities. They have begun to expand their
                        models of training, research, and output in keeping with the distributive
                        nature of innovation, creation, and authorship within the knowledge economy.
                        Among the many accompanying shifts, there is an increasing erosion of the
                        boundary line once separating the roles of scholar, artist, and
                        technologist, as the old means of distributing knowledge give way to far
                        more fluid means that easily allow creative producers to function in many
                        roles and disseminate their productions to vast, geographically disparate
                        audiences. What has emerged are varieties of creative practice that bridge
                        the gap between thinking and doing, between the excavation of the past and
                        the creation of the present, based on what Aristotle referred to as
                           <term>phronesis</term>: knowledge integrated with practical reasoning. </quote>
                     <ptr loc="146" target="#schnapp2009"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>This kind of vision suggests that making a clear separation between activist and
                  art-based practice and more traditional humanities-based endeavors may not be
                  trivial, and according to Schnapp and Shanks, hardly desired.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>The territory of the digital humanities is currently under negotiation. While there
               is no doubt that the field is expanding, it is not entirely clear what is included
               and how the landscape can be understood or structured. These ongoing negotiations
               occur on multiple levels, from an individual graduate student and local institutions
               to national funding agencies and international institutional networking. They are
               consequently situated institutionally, physically, politically and epistemically.
               These negotiations, which tend to be located <q>in between,</q> are particularly
               important to any attempt at analyzing or advocating an inclusively conceived digital
               humanities.</p>
            <p>The current article started out from an inclusive notion of the digital humanities
               and three analytical and exploratory lenses: a critical overview of the landscape of
               the digital humanities, an investigation of specific encounters, and an analytical
               model based on paradigmatic modes of engagement. The critical overview of the
               landscape provided a structural and broad comprehension of the digital humanities as
               well as a critical discussion of typologies, varieties of digital humanities,
               epistemic traditions and digital humanists. In contrast, the four encounters focused
               on specific initiatives at particular points in time, and their material and
               ideational grounding. Based on the critical overview, the encounters and the analysis
               presented in the first article in this series, an analytical model was suggested
               based on paradigmatic modes of engagement between the humanities and information
               technology or the digital: tool, study object, expressive medium, exploratory
               laboratory and activist venue.</p>
            <p>In addition to shedding light on these negotiations, which tend to be located <q>in
                  between,</q> the current article has attempted to complement a comprehensive
               overview of the landscape with more detailed, personal accounts of specific
               encounters. These perspectives on the digital humanities were complemented by an
               extended discussion of the epistemically and categorically poignant distinction of
               different modes of engagement between the humanities and information technology.</p>
            <p>We are undoubtedly at an exciting and challenging point in time with regards to the
               area loosely described by the term <term>digital humanities</term>. As we have seen,
               the current landscape is multifaceted and characterized by a range of epistemic
               traditions and modes of engagement, and while there is a great deal of overlap and
               common interests, there is also a need of increased shared awareness. It could be
               argued that a better understanding of the landscape of the digital humanities,
               epistemic traditions and collaborative possibilities are vital to the further
               development of the field. A respectful dialogue of visions, agendas, competencies and
               research interests across much of this landscape can help us meet a range of exciting
               upcoming challenges.</p>
            <p>One such important challenge is the rethinking, shaping and implementing of
               cyberinfrastructure for the humanities. What type of research infrastructure do we
               need? How do we align ourselves with science and engineering driven agendas, and how
               can we make a strong and grounded argument for humanities cyberinfrastructure? These
               are some of the issues discussed in the third article of this series, in which I look
               at cyberinfrastructure for the humanities in relation to the ongoing debate about
               research infrastructure and the digital humanities. HUMlab at Umeå University serves
               as a case study, and design principles are discussed as well as the conceptual
               underpinnings of infrastructure such as digital humanities centers.</p>
            <p>In the final installment, I explore the hopes and visions invested in the digital
               humanities, and how the digital humanities often become a means for rethinking the
               humanities at large. How is the future of the humanities projected? Can the
                  <q>digital</q> fundamentally change the humanities? What issues are critical?
               Could the expanded dialogue called for above lead to a shared vision of the digital
               humanities? And do we even want one?</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgments</head>
            <p>This article has been substantially improved by comments and feedback given by
               Stephanie Hendrick, Erica Robles, Jenna Ng, Matthew Ratto, and the two anonymous DHQ
               reviewers. Emma Ewadotter helped competently with data collection and other matters.
               Useful feedback was also given at a seminar at UC Santa Barbara on November 12,
               2009.</p>

         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <listBibl>

            <bibl xml:id="actlab" label="ACTLab" key="actlab">ACTLab. <title rend="quotes">Welcome
                  to the ACTlab</title>. University of Texas. <ref target="http://www.actlab.utexas.edu/">http://www.actlab.utexas.edu/</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="aoir" label="AoIR" key="aoir">Association of Internet Researchers.<title rend="quotes">About</title>. Accessed 08 October 2009. <ref target="http://aoir.org/about/">http://aoir.org/about/</ref>. </bibl>

            <bibl label="Bell 2007" xml:id="bell2007" key="bell2007a">Bell, David. <title rend="italic">Cyberculture Theorists: Manuel Castells and Donna Hawaway</title>.
               New York: Routledge, 2007.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bolter2003" label="Bolter &amp; Gromala 2003" key="bolter2003a">Bolter,
               Jay David and Diane Gromala. <title rend="italic">Windows and Mirrors: Interaction
                  design, digital art, and the myth of transparency</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT
               Press, 2003.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="boyd2009" label="Boyd 2009" key="boyd2009">Boyd, Danah. <title rend="quotes">Spectacle at Web2.0 Expo… From My Perspective</title>. Blog entry,
               24 November 2009. Accessed 3 February 2010. <ref target="http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2009/11/24/spectacle_at_we.html">http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2009/11/24/spectacle_at_we.html</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Bradley 2008" xml:id="bradley2008" key="bradley2008c">Bradley, John.
                  <title rend="quotes">Pliny: A model for digital support of scholarship</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Information</title> 9:1 (2008).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="braudy2006" label="Braudy 2006" key="braudy2006">Braudy, Leo. <title rend="quotes">Peer Response to The Virtual Window Interactive</title>. <title rend="italic">Vectors Journal</title> Forums, 29 November 2006. Accessed 3
               February 2010. <ref target="http://vectors.usc.edu/forums/?viewId=333">http://vectors.usc.edu/forums/?viewId=333</ref>. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="brown2009a" label="Brown et al. 2009a" key="brown2009a">Brown, Susan,
               Patricia Clements, Isobel Grundy, Stan Ruecker, Jeffery Antoniuk, and Sharon Balazs.
                  <title rend="quotes">Published Yet Never Done: The Tension Between Projection and
                  Completion in Digital Humanities Research</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital
                  Humanities Quarterly</title> 3:2 (2009).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="cch2006" label="Centre for Computing in the Humanities" key="cch2006">Center for Computing in the Humanities. <title rend="quotes">Introduction to the
                  Digital Humanities</title>. King's College London. Accessed 19 February 2010. <ref target="http://www.kcl.ac.uk/schools/humanities/depts/cch/digihum/">http://www.kcl.ac.uk/schools/humanities/depts/cch/digihum/</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="croxall2009" label="Croxall 2009" key="croxall2009">Croxall, Brian. <title rend="quotes">The Absent Presence: Today's Faculty</title>. Paper presented to the
               2009 Modern Language Association Annual Convention, Philadelphia, 26-28 December
               2009. Accessed 21 February 2010. <ref target="http://www.briancroxall.net/2009/12/28/the-absent-presence-todays-faculty/">http://www.briancroxall.net/2009/12/28/the-absent-presence-todays-faculty/</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="daniel2007" label="Daniel 2007" key="daniel2007">Daniel, Sharon. <title rend="quotes">Public Secrets</title>. <title rend="italic">Vectors Journal</title>
               2:2 (2007). Accessed 21 February 2010. <ref target="http://vectors.usc.edu/projects/index.php?project=57">http://vectors.usc.edu/projects/index.php?project=57</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Davidson 2008" xml:id="davidson2008" key="davidson2008">Davidson, Cathy N.
                  <title rend="quotes">Humanities 2.0: Promise, Perils, Predictions</title>. <title rend="italic">Publications of the Modern Language Association of America
                  (PMLA)</title> 123:3 (2008), 707-717.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="davidson2009" label="Davidson 2009" key="davidson2009a">Davidson, Cathy N.
                  <title rend="quotes">Innovation AND Tradition</title>. HASTAC Discussion Forum on
               the Future of the Digital Humanities, 03 February 2009. Accessed 14 February 2010.
                  <ref target="http://www.hastac.org/forums/hastac-scholars-discussions/future-digital-humanities">http://www.hastac.org/forums/hastac-scholars-discussions/future-digital-humanities</ref>. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="davidson2004" label="Davidson &amp; Goldberg 2004a" key="davidson2004a">Davidson, Cathy N. and David Theo Goldberg. <title rend="quotes">Engaging the
                  Humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">Profession</title> (2004), 42-62.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="dhq2010a" label="DHQ About" key="adho"> Digital Humanities Quarterly.
                  <title rend="quotes">About DHQ</title>. <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/about/about.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/about/about.html</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="dhq2010b" label="DHQ IM Guidelines" key="dhq2010b"> Digital Humanities
               Quarterly. <title rend="quotes">Interactive Media Guidelines</title>. <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/submissions/mediaGuidelines.html">http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/submissions/mediaGuidelines.html</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="douglass2009" label="Douglass 2009" key="douglass2009">Douglass, Jeremy.
                  <title rend="quotes">Cultural Analytics: webcomics and video games</title>.
               Presented during Lev Manovich keynote address at Digital Humanities 2009, University
               of Maryland, 22 June 2009. <ref target="http://jeremydouglass.com/cv/Douglass,%20Jeremy.%20Digital%20Humanities%202009%20keynote%20guest%20spot.pdf">http://jeremydouglass.com/cv/Douglass,%20Jeremy.%20Digital%20Humanities%202009%20keynote%20guest%20spot.pdf</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Drucker 2009a" xml:id="drucker2009a" key="drucker2009c">Drucker, Johanna.
                  <title rend="italic">SpecLab: Digital Aesthetics and Projects in Speculative
                  Computing</title>. Chicago: Chicago University Press, 2009.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="drucker2009b" label="Drucker 2009b" key="drucker2009b">Drucker, Johanna.
                  <title rend="quotes">Blind Spots: Humanists Must Plan Their Digital
               Future</title>. <title rend="italic">The Chronicle Review</title>. 3 April
               2009.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="empyre" label="-empyre-" key="empyre">-empyre-. <title rend="quotes">About
                  -empyre</title>. Accessed 13 October 2009. <ref target="http://www.subtle.net/empyre/">http://www.subtle.net/empyre/</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="french2009a" label=" French 2009a" key="french2009a">French, Amanda.
                  <title rend="quotes">Make <q>10</q> louder, or, the amplification of scholarly
                  communication</title>. Blog Entry, 30 December 2009. Accessed 21 February 2010.
                  <ref target="http://amandafrench.net/2009/12/30/make-10-louder/?doing_wp_cron">http://amandafrench.net/2009/12/30/make-10-louder/?doing_wp_cron</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="french2009b" label="French 2009b" key="french2009b">French, Amanda. <title rend="quotes">Where Marketers Would Never Want to Tamper</title>. Blog Entry, 4
               May 2009. Accessed 14 February 2010. <ref target="http://amandafrench.net/2009/05/04/where-marketers-would-never-want-to-tamper/">http://amandafrench.net/2009/05/04/where-marketers-would-never-want-to-tamper/</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Galison 1997" xml:id="galison1997" key="galison1997">Galison, Peter. <title rend="italic">Image and Logic: A Material Culture of Microphysics</title>.
               Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1997.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="golden2010" label="Golden 2010" key="golden2010">Golden, Serena. <title rend="quotes">Tweetup at the MLA</title>. <title rend="italic">Inside Higher
                  Ed</title> 4 January 2010. <ref target="http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2010/01/04/tweeps">http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2010/01/04/tweeps</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="golumbia2009" label="Golumbia 2009" key="golumbia2009">Golumbia, David.
               2009. <title rend="italic">The Cultural Logic of Computation</title>. Cambridge, MA:
               Harvard University Press.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Hall 2008" xml:id="hall2008" key="hall2008">Hall, Gary. <title rend="italic">Digitize this Book! The politics of new media, or why we need open
                  access now</title>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2008.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="haylesa" label="Hayles Forthcoming PMLA" key="haylesa">Hayles, Katherine.
               Forthcoming. <title rend="quotes">How We Think: The Transforming Power of Digital
                  Technologies</title>. Submitted to <title rend="italic">PMLA</title>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Hayles Forthcoming Chapter" xml:id="haylesb" key="hayles2012a">Hayles,
               Katherine. Forthcoming. <title rend="quotes">How We Think: The Transforming Power of
                  Digital Technologies</title>. Book chapter.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="howard2009" label="Howard 2009" key="howard2009">Howard, Jennifer. <title rend="quotes">In Face of Professors' 'Fury,' Syracuse U. Library Will Keep Books
                  on Shelves</title>. <title rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education</title>
               12 November 2009. <ref target="http://chronicle.com/article/In-Face-of-Professors-Fury/49133/">http://chronicle.com/article/In-Face-of-Professors-Fury/49133/</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="hunsinger2005" label="Hunsinger 2005" key="hunsinger2005">Hunsinger,
               Jeremy. <title rend="quotes">Toward a Transdisciplinary Internet Research</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Information Society</title> 21:4 (2005), 277-279.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="iath" label="IATH" key="iath">Institute for Advanced Technologies in the
               Humanties. Univeristy of Virginia. Accessed 07 January 2009. <ref target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/">http://www.iath.virginia.edu/</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Ihde &amp; Selinger 2003" xml:id="ihde2003" key="ihde2003">Ihde, Don and
               Evan Selinger (eds). <title rend="italic">Chasing Technoscience: Matrix for
                  Materiality</title>. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2003.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="ish2008" label="Interdisciplinary Studies in Humanities" key="ish2008">Interdiscipliary Studies in Humanities Program. <title rend="quotes">Concentration
                  in Digital Humanities</title>. Stanford University. Accessed 18 August 2008. <ref target="http://www.stanford.edu/group/HSP/GPH/DigHUM_Req.htm">http://www.stanford.edu/group/HSP/GPH/DigHUM_Req.htm</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="ippolito2009" label="Ippolito et al. 2009" key="ippolito2009">Ippolito,
               Jon, Joline Blais, Owen F. Smith, Steve Evans and Nathan Stormer. <title rend="quotes">New Criteria for New Media</title>. <title rend="italic">Leonardo</title> 42:1 (2009), 71-75.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Janlert &amp; Jonsson 2000" xml:id="janlert2000" key="janlert2000">Janlert,
               Lars-Erik and Kjell Jonsson. <title rend="quotes">Kulturlaboratoriet</title>. <title rend="italic">Tvärsnitt</title> I (2009): 54-61.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Juhasz 2009" xml:id="juhasz2009" key="juhasz2009">Juhasz, Alex. <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities</title>. Blog entry, 17 July 2009. <ref target="http://aljean.wordpress.com/2009/07/17/digital-humanities/">http://aljean.wordpress.com/2009/07/17/digital-humanities/</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="kagan2009" label="Kagan 2009" key="kagan2009">Kagan, Jerome. <title rend="italic">The Three Cultures: Natural Sciences, Social Sciences, and the
                  Humanities in the 21st Century</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press,
               2009.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Kirschenbaum 2004" xml:id="kirschenbaum2004" key="kirschenbaum2004">Kirschenbaum, Matthew. <title rend="quotes">Interface, aesthetics, and
                  usability</title>. <title rend="italic">A Companion to Digital Humanities</title>
               ed. Susan Schreibman, Ray Siemens and John Unsworth, 523-542. Malden, MA: Blackwell,
               2004.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="klein1990" label="Klein 1990" key="klein1990">Klein, Julie. <title rend="italic">Interdisciplinarity: History, Theory, and Practice</title>. Detroit:
               Wayne State University Press, 1009.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Knorr Cetina 1999" xml:id="knorr1999" key="knorr1999">Knorr Cetina, Karin.
                  <title rend="italic">Epistemic Cultures: How the Sciences Make Knowledge</title>.
               Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1999.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="kroker2008" label="Kroker &amp; Kroker 2008" key="kroker2008">Kroker,
               Arthur and Marilouise Kroker. <title rend="italic">Critical Digital Studies: A
                  Reader</title>. Toronto: Toronto University Press, 2008.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="lamarre2010" label="LaMarre 2010" key="lamarre2010">LaMarre, Thomas.
                  <title rend="quotes">Visualization as the new language of theory</title>. <title rend="italic">-empyre- Email List</title> 7 Feb 2010. <ref target="https://lists.cofa.unsw.edu.au/pipermail/empyre/2010-February/002557.html">https://lists.cofa.unsw.edu.au/pipermail/empyre/2010-February/002557.html</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="laue2004" label="Laue 2004" key="laue2004">Laue, Andrea. <title rend="quotes">How the Computer Works</title>. <title rend="italic">A Companion to
                  Digital Humanities</title> ed. Susan Schreibman, Ray Siemens and John Unsworth,
               145-160. Malden, MA: Blackwell Publishing, 2004.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Livingstone 2003" xml:id="livingstone2003" key="livingstone2003">Livingstone, David. <title rend="italic">Putting Science in Its Place: Geographies
                  of Scientific Knowledge</title>. Chicago: Chicago University Press, 2003.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="lovgren2004" label="Lövgren &amp; Stolterman 2004" key="lovgren2004">Lövgren, Jonas and Erik Stolterman. <title rend="italic">Thoughtful Interaction
                  Design: A design perspective on information technology</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT
               Press, 2004.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Mactavish &amp; Rockwell 2006" xml:id="mactavish2006" key="mactavish2006">Mactavish, Andrew and Geoffrey Rockwell. <title rend="quotes">Multimedia Education
                  in the Arts and Humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">Mind Technologies:
                  Humanities Computing and the Canadian Academic Community</title> ed. Raymond
               Siemens and David Moorman, 225-243. Calgary: University of Calgary Press, 2006. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="manovich2009a" label="Manovich 2009a" key="manovich2009a">Manovich, Lev.
                  <title rend="quotes">Cultural Analytics</title>. Software Studies Initiative,
               University of California, Sand Diego. 20 June 2009. Accessed 21 February 2010 <ref target="http://lab.softwarestudies.com/2008/09/cultural-analytics.html">http://lab.softwarestudies.com/2008/09/cultural-analytics.html</ref>. .</bibl>

            <bibl label="Manovich 2009b" xml:id="manovich2009b" key="manovich2009b">Manovich, Lev.
                  <title rend="quotes">How to Follow Global Digital Cultures, or Cultural Analytics
                  for Beginners</title>. <title rend="italic">Deep Search</title>, ed. Felix Stalder
               and Konrad Becker. Transaction Publishers (English) and Studienverlag (German),
               2009.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mccarty2009" label="McCarty 2009" key="mccarty2009">McCarty, Willard.
                  <title rend="quotes">The Next Big Thing</title>. <title rend="italic">Humanist
                  Discussion Group</title> 23.526 (2009). <ref target="http://lists.digitalhumanities.org/pipermail/humanist/2009-December/000952.html">http://lists.digitalhumanities.org/pipermail/humanist/2009-December/000952.html</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mccarty2010" label="McCarty 2010" key="mccarty2010">McCarty, Willard.
                  <title rend="quotes">Tools and Lists</title>. <title rend="italic">Humanist
                  Discussion Group</title> 23.578 (2010). <ref target="http://lists.digitalhumanities.org/pipermail/humanist/2010-January/001004.html">http://lists.digitalhumanities.org/pipermail/humanist/2010-January/001004.html</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mcgann2002" label="McGann 2002" key="mcgann2002">McGann, Jerome. <title rend="quotes">Ivanhoe Game Summary</title>. 2002.<ref target="http://www.speculativecomputing.org/ivanhoe/framework/summary.html">http://www.speculativecomputing.org/ivanhoe/framework/summary.html</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="McGonigal 2008" xml:id="mcgonigal2008" key="mcgonigal2008">McGonigal, Jane.
                  <title rend="quotes">Why I Love Bees: A Case Study in Collective Intelligence
                  Gaming</title>. <title rend="italic">The Ecology of Games: Connecting Youth,
                  Games, and Learning</title> ed. Katie Salen, 199-228. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press,
               2008.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2007" label="McPherson 2007" key="mcpherson2007">McPherson, Tara.
                  <title rend="quotes">Introduction to Difference Issue</title>. <title rend="italic">Vectors Journal</title> 3:1 (2007). <ref target="http://vectors.usc.edu/issues/index.php?issue=5">http://vectors.usc.edu/issues/index.php?issue=5</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2008" label="McPherson 2008" key="mcpherson2008">McPherson, Tara.
                  <title rend="quotes">Dynamic Vernaculars: Emerent Digital Forms in Contemporary
                  Scholarship</title>. Lecture presented to HUMLab Seminar, Umeå University, 4 March
               2008. <ref target="http://stream.humlab.umu.se/index.php?streamName=dynamicVernaculars">http://stream.humlab.umu.se/index.php?streamName=dynamicVernaculars</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2009a" label="McPherson 2009a" key="mcpherson2009">McPherson,
               Tara. <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Media Studies and the Digital
                  Humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">Cinema Journal</title> 48:2 (Winter
               2009), 119-123.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2009b" label="McPherson 2009b" key="mcpherson2009b">McPherson,
               Tara. <title rend="quotes">We need some transitional models in b/w tradi...</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">HASTAC Discussion Forum on the Future of the Digital
                  Humanities</title> 05 February 2009. Accessed 21 February 2010. <ref target="http://www.hastac.org/forums/hastac-scholars-discussions/future-digital-humanities">http://www.hastac.org/forums/hastac-scholars-discussions/future-digital-humanities</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="meloni2009" label="Meloni 2009" key="meloni2009">Meloni, Julie. <title rend="quotes">Calling all Digital Humanists in the Pacific Northwest: Organizing
                  THATCamp PNW</title>. Blog entry, 03 August 2009. Accessed 27 November 2009. <ref target="http://www.hastac.org/blogs/jcmeloni/calling-all-digital-humanists-pacific-northwest-organizing-thatcamp-pnw">http://www.hastac.org/blogs/jcmeloni/calling-all-digital-humanists-pacific-northwest-organizing-thatcamp-pnw</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="navas2009" label="Navas 2009" key="navas2009">Navas, Eduardo. <title rend="quotes">Notes on Cultural Analytics Seminar, December 16-17, 2009, CALIT2,
                  San Diego</title>. Blog post, 29 December 2009. <ref target="http://remixtheory.net/?p=408">http://remixtheory.net/?p=408</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Parry 2010" xml:id="parry2010" key="parry2010">Parry, David. <title rend="quotes">The MLA, @briancroxall, and the non-rise of the Digital
                  Humanities</title>. Blog entry, 6 January 2010. <ref target="http://academhack.outsidethetext.com/home/2010/the-mla-briancroxall-and-the-non-rise-of-the-digital-humanities/">http://academhack.outsidethetext.com/home/2010/the-mla-briancroxall-and-the-non-rise-of-the-digital-humanities/</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Peters 2009" xml:id="peters2009" key="peters2009">Peters, Benjamin. <title rend="quotes">And lead us not into thinking the new is new: a bibliographic case
                  for new media history</title>. <title rend="italic">New Media &amp;
                  Society</title> 11:1&amp;2 (2009): 13–30.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bradley2006" label="Bradley 2006 " key="bradley2006">Bradley, John. <title rend="quotes">Pliny: A Note Manager</title>. Accessed 8 October 2009.<ref target="http://pliny.cch.kcl.ac.uk/index.html">http://pliny.cch.kcl.ac.uk/index.html</ref>. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="preemptivemedia" label="Preemptive Media" key="preemptivemedia">Preemptive
               Media. Accessed 8 October 2009. <ref target="http://www.preemptivemedia.net/">http://www.preemptivemedia.net/</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="presner2009" label="Presner 2009" key="[unlisted]">Presner, Todd Samuel.
                  <title rend="none">Personal communication</title>, Email correspondence, 07
               October 2009.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="presner2010" label="Presner 2010" key="presner2010">Presner, Todd Samuel.
                  <title rend="quotes">HyperCities: Building a Web 2.0 Learning Platform</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Teaching Literature at A Distance</title> ed. Anastasia
               Natsina and Takis Tagialis. London: Continuum Books, 2010.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Rabkin 2006" xml:id="rabkin2006" key="rabkin2006">Rabkin, Eric S. <title rend="quotes">Audience, purpose, and the medium: How digital media extend
                  humanities education</title>. <title rend="italic">Teaching Technology,
                  Textuality: Approaches to New Media</title>, ed. Hanrahan, Michael and Deborah L.
               Madsen, 135-147. Palgrave Macmillan, 2006.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="raley2009" label="Raley 2009" key="raley2009">Raley, Rita. <title rend="italic">Tactical Media</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota
               Press, 2009.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Ratto 2006" xml:id="ratto2006" key="ratto2006">Ratto, Matthew. <title rend="quotes">Epistemic commitments and archaeological representation</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Book of Abstracts of the XV World Congress</title>,
               International Union for Prehistoric and Protohistoric Sciences, Lisbon, 4-9 September
               2006, 60. <ref target="http://www.uispp.ipt.pt/UISPPprogfin/Livro2.pdf">http://www.uispp.ipt.pt/UISPPprogfin/Livro2.pdf</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="rockwell2008" label="Rockwell 2008" key="rockwell2008">Rockwell, Geoffrey.
                  <title rend="quotes"> What is extreme text analysis?</title>. <title rend="italic">Text Analysis Developers Alliance</title> 03 May 2008. <ref target="http://tada.mcmaster.ca/Main/WhatIsExtremeTextAnalysis">http://tada.mcmaster.ca/Main/WhatIsExtremeTextAnalysis</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="schnapp2009" label="Schnapp &amp; Shanks 2009" key="schnapp2009">Schnapp,
               Jeffrey T. and Michael Shanks. <title rend="quotes">Artereality (Rethinking Craft in
                  a Knowledge Ectonomy)</title>. <title rend="italic">Art School (Propositions for
                  the 21st Century)</title> ed. Steven Henry, 141-157. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press,
               2009.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Schreibman et al. 2004" xml:id="schreibman2004" key="schreibman2004a">Schreibman, Susan, Ray Siemens and John Unsworth.<title rend="quotes">The digital
                  humanities and humanities computing: An introduction</title>. <title rend="italic">A Companion to the Digital Humanities</title> ed. Susan Schreibman, Ray Siemens,
               and John Unsworth, XXIII-XXVII. Malden, MA: Blackwell Publishing, 2004.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="shrum2005" label="Shrum 2005" key="shrum2005">Shrum, Wesley. <title rend="quotes">Internet Indiscipline: Two Approaches to Making a Field</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Information Society</title> 21 (2005) 273–275.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Sinclair &amp; Gouglas 2002" xml:id="sinclair2002" key="sinclair2002">Sinclair, Stéfan and Sean W. Gouglas. <title rend="quotes">Theory into Practice: A
                  Case Study of the Humanities Computing Master of Arts Programme at the University
                  of Alberta</title>. In <title rend="italic">Arts and Humanities in Higher
                  Education</title> 1:2 (2002), 167-183.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="sinclair2002a" label="Sinclair 2002" key="sinclair2002a">Sinclair, Stefan.
                  <title rend="quotes">Report on MA in Humanities Computing at Alberta</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Humanist Discussion Group</title> 16.356 (2002). <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/humanist/Archives/Virginia/v16/0346.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/humanist/Archives/Virginia/v16/0346.html</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="silver2006" label="Silver 2006" key="silver2006">Silver, David. <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Where is Internet Studies?</title>. <title rend="italic">Critical Cyberculture Studies</title> ed. David Silver and Adrienne
               Massanari. New York: New York University Press, 2006.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Simanowski 2009a" xml:id="simanowski2009a" key="simanowski2009a">Simanowski, Roberto. <title rend="quotes">What is and toward what end do we read
                  digital literature?</title>. <title rend="italic">Literary Art in Digital
                  Performance: Case Studies in New Media Art and Criticism</title> ed. Francisco J.
               Ricardo, 10-16. New York: Continuum, 2009.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="sterne2005" label="Sterne 2005" key="sterne2005">Sterne, Jonathan. <title rend="quotes">Digital Media and Disciplinarity</title>. <title rend="italic">The
                  Information Society</title> 21 (2005), 249–256.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="stockholm1998" label="Stockholm City Archives 1998" key="stockholm1998">
               Stockholm City Archives. <title rend="italic">Söder i våra hjärtan - människor och
                  miljöer i Stockholm 1870-1930</title>. Stockholm: Stockholm Norstedts Rabén
               Multimedia, 1998.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Stone 2005" xml:id="stone2005" key="stone2005">Stone, Allucquére Rosanne.
                  <title rend="quotes">ACTLab Pedagogy- On being trans, and under the radar: Tales
                  from the ACTLab</title>. ACTLab, University of Texas, 2005. <ref target="http://www.actlab.utexas.edu/radar.shtml">http://www.actlab.utexas.edu/radar.shtml</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="svensson1998" label="Svensson 1998" key="svensson1998">Svensson, Patrik.
                  <title rend="italic">Number and Countability in English Nouns</title>. Uppsala:
               Swedish Science Press, 1998.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Svensson 2009a" xml:id="svensson2009a" key="svensson2009">Svensson, Patrik.
                  <title rend="quotes">Humanities computing as digital humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 3:3 (2009).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="svensson2009b" label="Svensson 2009b" key="svensson2009b">Svensson,
               Patrik. <title rend="quotes">Virtual worlds as arenas for language learning</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Computer Assisted Language Learning: Critical Concepts in
                  Linguistics</title> ed. P. Hubbard, Volume IV, 123-143. London &amp; New York:
               Routledge, 2009.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Shanks 2008" xml:id="shanks2008" key="shanks2008">Shanks, Michael. <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities — a vision</title>. 2008. <ref target="http://documents.stanford.edu/michaelshanks/386">http://documents.stanford.edu/michaelshanks/386</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="unsworth1999" label="Unsworth 1999" key="unsworth1999">Unsworth, John.
                  <title rend="quotes">The Library as Laboratory</title>. Presentation at the Annual
               Meeting of the American Library Association, 1999. <ref target="http://www3.isrl.illinois.edu/~unsworth/ala99.htm">http://www3.isrl.illinois.edu/~unsworth/ala99.htm</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="vectors2004" label="Vectors Journal 2004" key="vectors2004">Vectors
               Journal. <title rend="quotes">CFP: Vectors: Multimedia Projects: Evidence or
                  Mobility</title>, Calls for Papers website, Department of English, University of
               Pennsylvania, 19 February 2004. Accessed 3 February 2010. <ref target="http://call-for-papers.sas.upenn.edu/node/14096">http://call-for-papers.sas.upenn.edu/node/14096</ref>. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="vectors2006a" label="Vectors Journal DBG 2006" key="vectors2006a">Vectors
               Journal. <title rend="quotes">Dynamic Backend Generator (DBG): A Scholarly Middleware
                  Tool</title>. <title rend="italic">Vectors Journal</title> (2006). Accessed 3
               February 2009. <ref target="http://Vectorsjournal.org/journal/blog/dbg-overview/">http://Vectorsjournal.org/journal/blog/dbg-overview/</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="vectors2006b" label="Vectors Journal PlaceStorming 2006" key="vectors2006b">Vectors Journal. <title rend="quotes">Editor's Introduction to
                  PlaceStorming v. 3.0</title>. <title rend="italic">Vectors Journal</title> 1:2
               (2006). <ref target="http://vectors.usc.edu/projects/index.php?project=8">http://vectors.usc.edu/projects/index.php?project=8</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Wiberg 2005" xml:id="wiberg2005" key="wiberg2005">Wiberg, Mikael (ed.)
                  <title rend="italic">The Interaction Society: Practice, Theories, and Supportive
                  Technologies</title>. Information Science Publishing, IDEA-group, 2004.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="woodward2009" label="Woodward 2009" key="woodward2009">Woodward, Kathleen.
                  <title rend="quotes">The future of the humanities- in the present &amp; in
                  public</title>. <title rend="italic">Daedalus</title> 138 (2009), 110-123.</bibl>

            <bibl label="Zorich 2008" xml:id="zorich2008" key="zorich2008">Zorich, Diane M. <title rend="quotes">A Survey of Digital Humanities Centers in the United States</title>.
               Washington, DC: Council on Library and Information Resources, 2008. <ref target="http://www.clir.org/pubs/abstract/pub143abst.html">http://www.clir.org/pubs/abstract/pub143abst.html</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="manifesto2009" label="Presner, Todd, et al. 2009" key="manifesto2009">Presner, Todd, et al. <title rend="quotes">The Digital Humanities Manifesto
                  2.0</title>. UCLA Mellon Seminar in Digital Humanities. <ref target="http://www.humanitiesblast.com/manifesto/Manifesto_V2.pdf">http://www.humanitiesblast.com/manifesto/Manifesto_V2.pdf</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl label="HASTAC Vision" xml:id="hastac" key="hastac"> HASTAC Working Group. <title rend="quotes">The HASTAC Vision: Humanities, Arts, Science and Technology Advanced
                  Collaboratory</title>. <title rend="italic">Visual Resources Association
                  Bulletin</title> 30:3 (2004), 43-50.</bibl>

         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>