<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><q>Vivas to those who have failed:</q> Walt Whitman
               Electric and the (Digital) Humanities</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Nicole <dhq:family>Gray</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>ngray2@unl.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Nicole Gray is a project specialist in the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                     Libraries. She previously worked as a project manager and a contributing editor
                     for <title rend="italic">The Walt Whitman Archive</title>. Gray received a
                     Ph.D. in English from the University of Texas at Austin and has published
                     essays on nineteenth-century American literature, archives, and book history.
                     She is currently finishing a M.A. in Library and Information Science at the
                     University of Arizona.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000503</idno>
            <idno type="volume">014</idno>
            <idno type="issue">4</idno>
            <date when="2020-12-20">20 December 2020</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2020-10-27" who="jmurel">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>Digital methods in the humanities have helped to create the potential for
               resurrecting an experimental, recuperative critical mode that approaches literature
               in terms of its transformability. This essay draws on Walt Whitman’s poems and his
               material practices to model this mode by interweaving the transformative logics of
               poetry and code. This can help to illuminate the structural mechanics of each, as
               well as their mutual dependence on figurative language. These resonances speak to the
               diverse human voices, practices, and forms of creativity that define digital
               humanities work today no less than the poetry and print of past centuries.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>This articles examines a Walt Whitman manuscript through the lens of code.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <epigraph>
            <cit><quote rend="block">He sees eternity less like a play with a prologue and
                  denouement . . . . he sees eternity in men and women . . . he does not see men and
                  women as dreams or dots.</quote>
               <ref target="#whitman1855">Walt Whitman, preface to <title rend="italic">Leaves of
                     Grass</title> (1855)</ref></cit>
         </epigraph>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>The field that has emerged as the digital humanities started with dreams and dots:
               pixelated digits and, beyond them, the prospect of methods and archives that could
               encompass almost an infinite number of texts. As it has grown it has developed a
               reputation as one of the few comparatively well-funded, expanding fields in an
               increasingly de-funded, precariously or under-employed academic humanities.<note>On
                  this phenomenon as perception and as evolving actuality, see <ref
                     target="#kirschenbaum2010">Kirschenbaum (2010)</ref> and <ref
                     target="#kirschenbaum2012">(2012)</ref></note> It has also been criticized for
               a lack of ethnic and gender diversity and an unwillingness to think across cultures
               or to reckon with the theoretical insights of the humanities more
                  generally.<note>This criticism has prompted a series of conversations about
                  postcolonial, feminist, and queer digital humanities, as well as meditations on
                  the possible complicity of digital methods with neoliberal agendas. See <ref
                     target="#transformdh">#transformDH</ref> and <ref target="#dhpoco"
                     >#DHpoco</ref> for examples of the former; for the latter, see <ref
                     target="#allington2016">Allington et al. (2016)</ref> and <ref
                     target="#greenspan2019">Greenspan’s (2019)</ref> response.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As a result, in part, of these criticisms, the moment for work at the intersection of
               digital methods and the humanities has never been more exciting. Creators of forums
               like #TransformDH, #DHpoco, and #GlobalOutlookDH have worked to transform the digital
               humanities by opening up space for a more diverse set of practitioners and voices.
               Projects like the Colored Conventions Project and the Mukurtu CMS have built tools
               organized around artifacts and knowledge practices associated with African American
               and Indigenous communities. Scholars and programmers worldwide are engaging questions
               of access, training, and opportunity. </p>
            <p>With these developments have also come a set of theoretical provocations, challenges
               to return to the difficult work of thinking about digital media and its relationship
               to human beings.<note>Bailey writes that <quote rend="inline">The move <q>from margin
                        to center</q> offers the opportunity to engage new sets of theoretical
                     questions that expose implicit assumptions about what and who counts in digital
                     humanities as well as exposes structural limitations that are the inevitable
                     result of an unexamined identity politics of whiteness, masculinity, and
                     ablebodiness.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bailey2011"/></note>
               <quote rend="inline">[T]he black digital humanities promotes a system of
                  change,</quote> Kim Gallon has written: <quote rend="inline">it is a mechanism for
                  deregulating the tendency of technological tools, when employed in the digital
                  humanities, to deemphasize questions about humanity itself</quote>
               <ptr target="#gallon2016"/>. This transformative mode of thinking, the call to
               interrogate basic concepts and assumptions, shares some ground with an earlier moment
               in digital humanities. In the early 2000s, the SpecLab at the University of Virginia,
               led by Johanna Drucker and Jerome McGann, conducted a series of textual experiments
               with that era’s digital tools. These experiments in text and technology were informed
               by a methodological approach called <quote rend="inline">deformance</quote>, a
               creative and playful mode of reading.<note>Websites for SpecLab and the Applied
                  Research in Patacriticism group are now defunct, though legacy versions are
                  accessible through the Internet Archive’s Wayback Machine. See Samuels and
                  McGann’s development of the term <quote rend="inline">deformance</quote> in
                  relation to critical interpretation, editing, and translation, and elaborations by
                  McGann (<title rend="italic">Radiant Textuality</title>) and Drucker (<title
                     rend="italic">SpecLab</title>). Later work by scholars and artists like Nick
                  Montfort, Mez Breeze, and Alan Sondheim offers other examples of the creativity
                  that has emerged at the intersection of art and algorithms. For further discussion
                  of codework, the integration of programming syntax and creative expression, see
                     <ref target="#raley2002">Raley (2002)</ref>.</note> One goal of this
               speculative, theoretical work was an ongoing effort to reimagine key literary terms
               like <q>text</q> and <q>work.</q></p>
            <p>As digital methods that quantify and specify have come to play a prominent role in
               the digital humanities, perhaps it is worth exploring a complementary return to such
               ludic and experimental modes.<note>QueerOS is a notable recent example of this kind
                  of imaginative work (see <ref target="#barnett2016">Barnett et al. [2016]</ref>).
                  Play was proposed as a methodology for #DHpoco, as well; see Koh and Risam.</note>
               In the context of the transformation of the digital humanities by scholars of race
               and gender, however, we may need to reconceptualize the practice and the nomenclature
               of <q>deformance</q> to one of transformability.<note>The <quote rend="inline"
                     >emphasis was placed on de- rather than transformance,</quote> McGann writes,
                     <quote rend="inline">in order to show that the object of critical reflection is
                     not ultimately directed to the sign as such but to the rhetorical scene and its
                     functional (social) operators, not least of all the person(s) engaged in the
                     acts of deformance we commonly locate in a file headed
                     <q>Interpretation</q></quote>
                  <ptr target="#mcgann2001" loc="102"/>.</note> The malleability of form, for those
               who study connections between the body and identity, is a politically charged matter
               oriented toward the future as well as the present. Transformability shifts the focus
               from a product or process that has happened in the past, or is happening in the
               present, to the crucial role of imagination in turning to what is possible in the
               future. Transformability involves not only the many forms the text <emph>has</emph>
               taken — the realm of book history — or the many forms the text <emph>does</emph> take
               — the realm of textual editing — but also the many forms the text <emph>could</emph>
               take, the vast scope of its potential iterations within historical fields of embodied
               practice. </p>
            <p>Using Walt Whitman as a case study, this essay explores the ways that the dreams of
               an American poet have been and could be expressed in dots, presenting an opportunity
               and a provocation to apply the formal logic of machines to poems, and vice versa.
               Miriam Posner has written that a useful challenge for the digital humanities, now
               that many of its methods have become established, might involve rethinking some of
               the most basic structures and binaries enacted by data. The current political and
               cultural moment points to the importance of testing the logics that have made
               machines so functional and so central to human existence in the twenty-first century.
               Inseparable from such logics are complicated questions, long fundamental to poetry,
               about kinship, race or ethnicity, age, and gender — differences among human beings
               that affect the uses to which machines are put and the ways in which they have shaped
               and been shaped by historical narratives.</p>
            <p>Whitman is a useful case study in part because his knowledge about and investment in
               the technologies of print so thoroughly inform both his composition practices and his
               poetry. Transformation, and to some extent failure, also define his engagement of
               race over the course of his lifetime. Recent critical assessments have shown the ways
               Whitman grappled with trying to develop a national poetry at a moment when the
               nation’s internal contradictions were tearing it apart. The opposition to slavery and
               the forms of identification with enslaved people visible in his early poems largely
               gave way, after the U.S. Civil War, to a much more lukewarm position on the rights of
               freed slaves and other Americans of African descent.<note>See <ref
                     target="#klammer2006">Klammer (2006)</ref>; <ref target="#folsom2000">Folsom
                     (2000)</ref> and <ref target="#folsom2014">Folsom (2014)</ref>; and <ref
                     target="#mancuso1997">Mancuso (1997)</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the poem eventually titled <title rend="quotes">Song of Myself,</title> Whitman
               calls on his readers to <quote rend="inline">Unscrew the locks from the doors! /
                  Unscrew the doors themselves from their jambs!</quote>
               <ptr target="#whitman1855" loc="29"/>. If this were a hermeneutic challenge, one
               might propose questions tailored to our technological and philosophical moment: what
               would a model of criticism look like that combines a deconstruction of performative
               authorship, the thought-experiment of a (failed) mechanism, and a detailed attention
               to the material characteristics of an artifact? What lies between the sociology of
               the door-closer and the sociology of the text?<note>See <ref target="#latour1988"
                     >Latour (1988)</ref> and <ref target="#mckenzie1999">McKenzie (1999)</ref>,
                  respectively.</note> How do we map the crossroads of reparative reading and
               algorithmic criticism?<note>Ramsay’s algorithmic criticism is an effort to <quote
                     rend="inline">locate a hermeneutics at the boundary between mechanism and
                     theory</quote> that explores transformation as key to the generation of
                  humanities <quote rend="inline">data</quote>
                  <ptr target="#ramsay2011"/>. Sedgwick’s reparative reading continues to offer a
                  provocative possibility of thinking beyond (even computer) binaries, in part
                  because it suggests that the fact that boundaries may structure our world in
                  fundamental ways need not determine the kinds of actions or thoughts that must be
                  taken in relation to or as a function of that knowledge <ptr
                     target="#sedgwick2003"/></note> This essay draws on structures of computational
               processing to reimagine and ultimately transform a manuscript draft of lines that
               have been at the heart of critics’ discussions of Whitman’s poetic treatment of race.
               Combining the ludic with the Luciferic, it engages a struggle with embodiment in a
               text from the past in order to frame that text’s transformation and re-embodiment in
               a troubled present.</p>
            <p>In the first section of the essay, I discuss practices of text encoding and
               electronic transformation in widespread use by editors of humanities texts, arguing
               that such practices resonate linguistically and structurally with Whitman’s own
               poetic and material practices. The second section of the essay situates Whitman’s
               poem <title rend="quotes">The Sleepers</title> as a model for a critical approach
               that taps into a dialectic of dreams and failure that has been influential in the
               imagination and the politics of the United States. Casting the <q>dreamspace</q>
               Whitman creates in <title rend="quotes">The Sleepers</title> as an analogue of
               namespaces in computer and information science, I suggest that it functions as a
               transformative, experimental environment in which dreams, failure, contingency, and
               intentionality combine to produce radical insights and forms of identification. To
               exhibit that potential, I transform a manuscript draft fragment of <title
                  rend="quotes">The Sleepers</title> into a basic script written in the programming
               language Python. Such transformations have much to offer the critical imagination,
               drawing our attention to new textual dimensions and to the points at which poetic
               dreams fail to become functional dots or durable reparative interventions. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head><q>This electric self:</q> Machine Logics and the Transformability of Text</head>
            <p>One of the notable revisions Whitman made to his poem <title rend="quotes">Bardic
                  Symbols,</title> first published in the <title rend="italic">Atlantic
                  Monthly</title> in 1860, between that initial publication and its final version
                  (<title rend="quotes">As I Ebb’d With the Ocean of Life</title>) in later editions
               of <title rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</title>, was to substitute the word
                  <q>electric</q> for the word <q>eternal.</q> Setting the stage for poetic
               reflection, Whitman wrote in the 1860 version: <cit><quote rend="block"><lg>
                        <l>I, musing, late in the autumn day, gazing off southward,</l>
                        <l>Alone, held by the eternal self of me that threatens to get the
                           better<lb/>of me and stifle me</l>
                     </lg></quote><ptr target="#whitman1860" loc="445"/></cit> This self was still
               eternal in 1867, but by the 1881 edition of <title rend="italic">Leaves</title>,
               published just two years after Thomas Edison filed a U.S. patent for an electric lamp
               with a carbon filament, Whitman had revised both lines: <cit><quote rend="block"><lg>
                        <l>I musing late in the autumn day, gazing off southward,</l>
                        <l>Held by this electric self out of the pride of which I utter poems</l>
                     </lg></quote><ptr target="#whitman1881" loc="202"/></cit> Now electric rather
               than eternal, the poet’s self has also along the way become a prideful source of
               utterance rather than a stifling force. In becoming electric, the self is no longer
               alone, no longer occupied in wrestling with itself, but now turned outward and
               uttering poems.<note>The first substantive revision to the second line appeared in
                  the 1867 edition of <title rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</title>: <quote
                     rend="inline">Alone, held by this eternal self of me, out of the pride of which
                     I have utter’d my poems</quote>
                  <ptr target="#whitman1867" loc="331"/>. See <ref target="#gilmore2009">Gilmore
                     (2009)</ref> for a discussion of the electrical and technological developments
                  that underpinned the transformation of the poem titled <title rend="quotes">Poem
                     of the Body</title> in 1856 to <title rend="quotes">I Sing the Body
                     Electric</title> in 1867 and later editions.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The distance from the electric to the electronic self is a matter of a century, a
               couple of commonplace characters, and some successful inventions. Success, a word
               with roots in genealogical as well as temporal succession, can be considered to drive
               much of the work of description and transformation that is today fundamental to
               electronic editing and data manipulation in computational environments. The markup
               language XML, with the specific vocabulary created by the Text Encoding Initiative
               (TEI), has come to dominate the practice of digital editorial work on humanities
                  texts.<note>The use of XML has been questioned, and in several cases alternatives
                  proposed (see e.g. <ref target="#schloen2014">Schloen and Schloen [2014]</ref>),
                  but as inline or embedded markup it remains a common approach to encoding data and
                  a standard for digital scholarly editing.</note> As is the case with computer
               programming and markup languages more generally, the functionality of XML and its
               related languages depends on logic.</p>
            <p>The word <q>logic</q> is derived from the Greek <foreign>λόγος</foreign>, which has
               often been translated as <q>word.</q> Logic can refer to a formal system of reasoning
               depending on symbolic and mathematical procedures to establish claims, or, in a more
               loosely defined sense, to a set of rules or structures by which argumentation,
               reasoning, or understanding can be enacted within a given context (<q>logic, <hi
                     rend="italic">n</hi>.</q>). But <foreign>λόγος</foreign>
               is a complicated concept that extends further, encompassing speech or
                  utterance, teaching, collecting, discourse, mind, principle, law, act, reckoning,
                  cause, form, and pattern, as well as rational (or spiritual, or divine) order, or
                  even revelation — all with just a hint of temporality, drawing on the idea of
                     <q>original</q> or <q>originary.</q>
               <note> See <ref target="#liddell">Liddell-Scott-Jones</ref>. Biblical commentary has
                  explored the meaning of <foreign>λόγος</foreign>
                  in the context of John 1:1 (<quote rend="inline">In the beginning was the
                        Word...</quote>). See, e.g., <ref target="#jeffrey1992">Jeffrey and Morris
                        (1992)</ref> and <ref target="#vincent1889">Vincent (1889)</ref>. 
               </note> I will use logic throughout this essay to refer both to the structure of
               language, utterance, or argument and to this more complex sense, a spiritualized form
               of expression, the <emph>making material</emph> of structure or order in the world,
               divine or otherwise. </p>
            <p>The logic of XML depends on breaking data into machine-readable, processable parts,
               enforcing the description or the creation of boundaries. These boundaries ideally
               correspond to clearly defined units or categories, and they enable the construction
               of hierarchies and relationships. In the case of TEI these categories relate to
               inscribed materials like manuscripts or books. TEI also often encodes other
               categories that have been developed over years of academic production, like
               categories of genre, which underwrite the coherence of the discipline of literary
               criticism even as they are frequently challenged in individual studies. The logics
               that combine in the encoding practices and syntax of TEI are thus several, including
               logics of inscriptive technologies like the book and the manuscript, logics of
               categorical differences in style observed and enacted by literary criticism, and
               logics of information and meta-information that developed in library and
               computational contexts. </p>
            <p>The textual crux represented by the word <q>eternal</q> in Whitman’s <title
                  rend="quotes">Bardic Symbols,</title> for example, could be expressed in TEI. In a
               single file that described multiple versions of the poem, the tags
                  <code>&lt;app&gt;</code> (for critical apparatus entry) and
                  <code>&lt;rdg&gt;</code> (for reading), with the attribute <code>@wit</code> (to
               point to a textual witness), could be used to mark two versions of the line:<eg lang="xml"><![CDATA[<app>
   <rdg wit="#lg1860">
      <l>Alone, held by the eternal self of me that threatens
         <lb/>to get the better of me, and stifle me,</l>
   </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#lg1881">
      <l>Held by this electric self out of the pride of which I utter poems,</l>
   </rdg>
</app>]]></eg> Marking the text in this way reproduces several logics: the structural logic of the
               text (marking the line as a line with <code>&lt;l&gt;</code>); the logic of the
               critical apparatus that describes textual revision or versions of the text over time
                  (<code>&lt;app&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;rdg&gt;</code>); and the logic of the
               printed page, which consists of both inked characters and white space
                  (<code>&lt;lb/&gt;</code> or line break). </p>
            <p>A transformation of the text could proceed at the level of any of these logics, or
               all of them together. One could produce all the different versions of the line, one
               after the other, so they would display sequentially in a Web browser; or compare them
               as text strings and generate a visualization of the differences; or show the line in
               the context of other lines from the poem; or create a toggle allowing users to view
               or eliminate the line breaks, functionally reformatting the text. Data marked in XML
               can be transformed into Hypertext Markup Language (HTML), which in turn can be
               combined with display instructions to render readable, manipulable text in Web
               browsers. As display technologies and standards develop, XML remains useful, in
               theory, because the basic assumption is that it can be transformed into any number of
               other languages or data formats.</p>
            <p>For Whitman, as the change from <q>eternal</q> to <q>electric</q> would suggest, the
               line from <title rend="quotes">Bardic Symbols</title> was transformable when he wrote
               it and remained so even after it was printed. He orchestrated several transformations
               of both wording and appearance between 1860 and the final printing of the line in his
               lifetime in the 1891-2 <title rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</title>. To mark the line
               with TEI does not alter its ontological status, but it does produce new options for
               transformability in a digital environment. We might say that digital transformation
               is simply an extension of the imagination of transformability that, for Whitman, was
               a basic condition of textual production. </p>
            <p>The syntax of transformation provides a surprisingly poetic point of continuity. The
               transformation of XML, like the original markup, is an interpretive act, introducing
               display and navigation elements that structure the reader’s experience of a text. A
               primary language of transformation in such cases is Extensible Stylesheet Language
               Transformations (XSLT), one of three recommendations that make up the broader
               language family XSL.<note>These include XSL-FO, XSLT, and XPath <ptr target="#xslw3c"
                  />.</note> XSL depends on kinship as its metaphor for expressing locations,
               finding nodes in a document tree hierarchy based on paths articulated as a matter of
               succession. In the case of XML Path Language (XPath), the expression language used by
               XSLT, succession is a means of expressing relationships between elements or
                  nodes.<note>This language of succession was inherited from earlier markup and
                  stylesheet languages: the development of XSL syntax was influenced by SGML and its
                  stylesheet language DSSSL, which in turn had been based on earlier programming and
                  query languages. On the history and development of XSL, see <ref target="#kay2008"
                     loc="26-40">Kay (2008), 26-40,</ref> and <ref target="#w3c">“Transformation.”</ref> For a general
                  discussion of lineal trees (and other metaphors) in relation to algorithms and
                  computational data structures, and within a longer history of graph theory, see
                     <ref target="#knuth1973" loc="305–406">Knuth (1973), 305-406</ref>.</note> The
               road from XML to HTML is navigated with siblings, parents, children, ancestors, and
               descendants. In order to select all of the <code>&lt;rdg&gt;</code> nodes to render a
               particular reading in a TEI file with an XPath that locates them in their relation to
               their parent <code>&lt;app&gt;</code> elements, for instance, you might use the
               notation: <code>&lt;xsl:apply-templates select="child::rdg"/&gt;</code>. In plain
               (more or less) English, you could say that you are instructing the stylesheet to
               apply a series of transformations to any reading (<code>&lt;rdg&gt;</code>) that is a
               child of the current node. </p>
            <p>The logics and syntax of modern markup and transformation languages used for editing
               depend on a set of technical metaphors, terms for describing relationships that, in
               the case of XSL and many other languages, draw from family and nature — the stuff of
               poetry. And Whitman thought in machine logic, too, although his machine was the
               printing press. The kinds of material transformations that Whitman’s texts underwent
               in the nineteenth century bear some resemblance to the file transformations and
               structural logics of the electronic age. Whitman’s poetic transformations often
               involved cutting and pasting.<note>For further discussion of Whitman’s collaging as
                  fundamental to his poetry composition, see <ref target="#miller2010">Miller
                     (2010)</ref>.</note> Modularity was key, and Whitman, a former printer, often
               composed with the structure of the printed text in mind. When he received proofs of a
               set of notes about Elias Hicks that would form part of his 1888 volume <title
                  rend="italic">November Boughs</title>, for instance, Whitman noted to the printer
               that he wanted the section to begin on an odd-numbered page:</p>

            <figure>
               <head>Page proof of <title rend="quotes">Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias
                     Hicks.</title> Walt Whitman Papers in the Charles E. Feinberg Collection.
                  Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            </figure>


            <p>This move made logical sense for situating the Hicks essay as a new section of the
               prose in the volume — but it also reflected Whitman’s practice of repurposing
               sections and binding them into later book issues.<note>In an entry in <title
                     rend="italic">With Walt Whitman in Camden</title> dated July 31, 1888, Horace
                  Traubel noted as much: <quote rend="inline">W. has an idea of putting the
                     Hicks-Fox matter eventually into a special pamphlet. Made many changes of the
                     make-up in order to get the Hicks started on an odd page. This is one of his
                     memorandums to the printer: <quote rend="inline">begin making up Elias Hicks on
                        page 119 I will supply something for page 118</quote></quote>
                  <ptr target="#traubel1906" loc="2:64"/>. For another example of sheets that
                  Whitman published independently and had bound into other volumes, see the entry
                  for <title rend="italic">Passage to India</title> (1871) in <ref
                     target="#winship1991" loc="36">Winship (1991), 36</ref>.</note> He habitually
               arranged for the printing of poems and other materials independently on slips of
               paper, using them as the basis for proofing, sending them out for publication,
               circulating them among friends and acquaintances, and in some cases adding them into
               books. In ways that anticipated the concerns of twenty-first-century information
               scientists, Whitman designed his chunks of poetry and prose to be materially
               interoperable. If they were arranged such that they could be printed on separate
               sheets or gatherings, they could be assembled into other books or bound and
               distributed independently.<note>See <ref target="#winship1991">Winship (1991)</ref>,
                     <ref target="#myerson1993">Myerson (1993)</ref>, <ref target="#stallybrass2019"
                     >Stallybrass (2019)</ref>, and <ref target="#grossman2019">Grossman
                     (2019)</ref> for inventories and descriptions of Whitman’s publications and
                  printed slips. This comparison is not meant to gloss over Tara McPherson’s
                  important points about the racial and political implications of the <quote
                     rend="inline">lenticular</quote> logic of modularity and interoperability in
                  the development of modern computing <ptr target="#mcpherson2012"/>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Like XML-marked data today, Whitman’s modular text could be used for a number of
               (multimedia) futures. Both books and languages like XML depend on structured
               relations, definitions, hierarchies, and dependencies. And yet the imagination that
               selects and designs particular transformations is, as tools and books develop, an
               increasingly crucial component of digital processing. Whitman’s imagination of text
               and its possible transformations was shaped by the technologies of his time. We face
               a similar effect today, as critical and creative imaginations are challenged by
               machines that enable new forms of transformation, as humanities texts and machine
               languages combine in novel and interesting ways, and as practitioners are
               increasingly conversant in the logics of both. Conceived as a language whose
               use-value and sustainability were grounded in the possibility of transformation, XML
               is in certain ways an investment in the future of both technology and imagination.
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head><q>In the ruin, the sediment:</q> Poetic Dreams and Electric Failures</head>
            <p>In Whitman’s early, much-revised and much-discussed poem <title rend="quotes">The
                  Sleepers,</title> the dreaming poet begins out of sorts: <quote rend="inline">I
                  wander all night in my vision, / ... / Wandering and confused . . . . lost to
                  myself . . . . ill-assorted . . . . contradictory</quote>
               <ptr target="#whitman1855" loc="70"/>.<note>The poem is untitled (or assigned the
                  recurring title <title rend="quotes">Leaves of Grass</title>) in the 1855 edition.
                  It appeared in the 1856 <title rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</title> as <title
                     rend="quotes">Night Poem</title> and in the 1860-1 and 1867 editions as <title
                     rend="quotes">Sleep-Chasings.</title> It was first titled <title rend="quotes"
                     >The Sleepers</title> in 1871.</note> And yet the poet is capable, in this
               dream vision, of acts of acrobatic transcendence and identification. In <title
                  rend="quotes">The Sleepers,</title> Whitman first included and then edited out
               arguably his most striking identification across racial boundaries, lines in which
               the poet speaks as an enslaved person.<note>For a discussion of this poem and related
                  manuscript drafts, see <ref target="#folsom2001">Folsom (2001)</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Whitman had explored dreams as a space for transcending boundaries as early as his
                  pre-<title rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</title> fiction, and he may have been
               tapping into a genre of dream visions in literature. The unsettled mental state of
               the dreamer at the start of the dream in Whitman’s <title rend="quotes">The
                  Sleepers</title> and in his fiction is like that of other dream-vision narrators.
               The space of the dream for Whitman is liminal, in the sense that it seems to exist
               somewhere between pure presence and pure transcendence. In it the world of
               possibility is expanded, sometimes alarmingly.<note>A murder is juxtaposed to dream
                  and sleeping scenes in Whitman’s temperance novel <title rend="quotes">Franklin
                     Evans.</title></note> Critics have argued that the redemptive vision at the
               close of <title rend="quotes">The Sleepers,</title> in which the poet describes the
               sleepers <q>hand-in-hand</q> in a restorative sleep through which the illnesses and
               inequities of the world are healed, is a classic <q>dream vision</q> culmination of
               wandering in greater understanding and a sympathetic poetic enlightenment.<note>See,
                  for instance, <ref target="#french1990">French (1990)</ref>. </note>
            </p>
            <p>Another way to think about Whitman’s dreamspace — one quite out of time — would be to
               think of it as a kind of poetic namespace. In computer and information science,
               namespaces denote distinctions among objects (entities) or vocabularies, establishing
               boundaries around a specific collection of symbolic terms and related definitions.
               The use of namespaces allows for combinatory worlds in which the same word, element
               or object might mean something different in a specified context, or have a different
               relationship to other words, elements, or objects. Namespaces are often expressed
               using prefixes. One might, for instance, distinguish between the dreamspace <q>I</q>
               (ds:I) of <title rend="quotes">The Sleepers</title> and the waking space poetic
                  <q>I</q> (ws:I) of the other poems in the first edition of <title rend="italic"
                  >Leaves of Grass</title>. Let us say <code>&lt;ds:I&gt;</code> experiences
               discomfort, but possesses an ability to see and identify with the population of
               sleepers that extends beyond even as it informs the ability of
                  <code>&lt;ws:I&gt;</code>. </p>
            <p>The premise of namespaces and elements is the ability to declare entities like
                  <code>&lt;ds:I&gt;</code> and distinguish them from other entities both within a
               namespace and outside of it. The striking thing about Whitman’s dreamspace in <title
                  rend="quotes">The Sleepers,</title> however, is the very impossibility of that
               activity. In dreamspace, the night is a spatial as well as a temporal setting: of the
               sleepers, the poet writes, <quote rend="inline">The night pervades them and enfolds
                  them</quote>
               <ptr target="#whitman1855" loc="70"/>. The poet, too, both penetrates and enfolds the
               sleepers he describes. The poem begins with description: the poet, <quote
                  rend="inline">Pausing and gazing and bending and stopping,</quote> simply looks at
               the sleepers. Next, he comes closer — <quote rend="inline">I pass my hands soothingly
                  to and fro a few inches from them</quote> — but still the restless sleepers sleep
               fitfully <ptr target="#whitman1855" loc="71"/>. He then joins them, sleeping and
               dreaming with them — <quote rend="inline">I sleep close with the other sleepers, each
                  in turn; / I dream in my dream all the dreams of the other dreamers</quote>
               <ptr target="#whitman1855" loc="71"/>. Finally, his dreaming produces a deeper
               identification: <quote rend="inline">And I become the other dreamers.</quote> In this
               state the poet pervades the dreamers like the night, taking on their identities —
                  <quote rend="inline">I am the actor and the actress</quote> — and acting in their
               stead. The poet of dreamspace transcends the boundaries between himself and the
               people he describes. The descriptive work of dividing the sleepers into individuals
               becomes the work of drawing them together through the consciousness and the
               transformative dream-vision of the poet. As the poem concludes, the sleepers rest
                  <quote rend="inline">hand in hand,</quote> unified and beautiful in sleep, and the
               poet passes from night into day <ptr target="#whitman1855" loc="76–7"/>. </p>
            <p><quote rend="inline">Elements merge in the night,</quote> Whitman writes in <title
                  rend="quotes">The Sleepers.</title>
               <quote rend="inline">The antipodes, and every one between this and them in the dark,
                  / I swear they are averaged now . . . . one is no better than the other, / The
                  night and sleep have likened them and restored them</quote>
               <ptr target="#whitman1855" loc="75"/>. If the work of descriptive markup or the
               creation of distinct entities as part of XML namespace vocabularies involves breaking
               things down into parts, dreamspace might serve as an impetus to imagine ways of
               bringing them back together — or to recognize the artificiality of their separation.
               Like night in <title rend="quotes">The Sleepers,</title> dreamspace enables the
               existence, or the imagination of the existence, of two simultaneous possibilities: a
               difference and a cosmic averaging. Dreamspace brooks mathematical experimentation,
               perhaps because its elements and entities are defined contingently, in relation to
               deep, incomprehensible forces — not the natural forces of physics and institutional
               agency that guide the elements and entities of waking life, but something more
               inward-looking and subjective. In Whitman’s dreamspace, imaginative forays begin to
               mediate difference, bridging the gap between entities, even those posed as binary
               opposites. Transformability has both conceptual and material dimensions for Whitman,
               informing his dreams of poetic identification as well as his practices of revision
               and bookmaking.</p>
            <p> If the digital humanities represents a field in which the logics of programming and
               machines are called upon to revise the patterns of humanistic and philosophical
               inquiry, where multiple namespaces may coexist and serve co-articulated purposes,
               perhaps dreamspace can be cast as a foil to the functional side of programming, an
               invocation of the vocabulary of experimentation, of margins, of imagination, and of
               failure. In an essay on the methodological potentials of repair, Steven Jackson casts
               breakdown as a starting point in thinking about new media. Noting the role of
               shipbreaking in Bangladesh, where the raw materials of old ships are recycled into
               usable products, Jackson situates failure as one stage in a longer story, one in
               which breakdown and decay form constitutive components of existence in the
               twenty-first century, and in which imagination and reconfiguration are key to
               building sustainable practice <ptr target="#jackson2014"/>. </p>
            <p>In science and technology worlds, failure (in moderation) has long held a special
               status. As journalists and media scholars have pointed out, the vision of failure as
               a preliminary step in success continues to be lionized in the <q>fail fast, fail
                  often</q> mantra associated with Silicon Valley, however well the mantra
               corresponds to actual conditions of employment and production.<note>See, for
                  instance, <ref target="#surowiecki2014">Surowiecki (2014)</ref>, <ref
                     target="#draper2017">Draper (2017)</ref>, and <ref target="#newman2017">Newman
                     (2017)</ref>. See also <ref target="#liu2004a">Liu (2004a)</ref>.</note>
               Stories of failure in a rapidly developing media world have an analogue in the
               newspapers and periodicals of the nineteenth-century. Frank Luther Mott’s histories
               of early American newspapers and magazines showcase the way such productions went
               under with sometimes bewildering regularity. Newspapers were not the only industry
               full of folds, of course — Scott Sandage, tracing the ubiquitous failures of
               merchants in the nineteenth-century U.S., notes that <quote rend="inline">in addition
                  to those who went broke or bankrupt, thousands of businessmen teetered on the
                  brink for years</quote>
               <ptr target="#sandage2005" loc="7"/>. Failure, according to Sandage, is the substory
               of the idea that came to be known as the American Dream. Constituting a central part
               of stories and experiences of life in the U.S., but never quite fitting into the
               vision the republic had of itself, failure lingered uncomfortably at the boundaries
               of success and identity for the American nineteenth century.</p>
            <p>In the economic sense that would be associated with failure in the nineteenth-century
               United States, Whitman’s first edition of <title rend="italic">Leaves of
                  Grass</title>, self-published in 1855, was undeniably a failure. An unusual book
               in both size and manufacture, the first edition of <title rend="italic"
                  >Leaves</title> lacked a formal publisher and was set in type between other
               non-literary jobs at Andrew Rome’s Brooklyn printing shop. Whitman’s friend Horace
               Traubel reported in <title rend="italic">With Walt Whitman in Camden</title> that
                  <quote rend="inline">W[hitman] spoke about the first edition of the Leaves: <quote
                     rend="inline">It is tragic — the fate of those books. None of them were sold —
                     practically none — perhaps one or two, perhaps not even that many. We had only
                     one object — to get rid of the books — to get them out someway even if they had
                     to be given away</quote></quote>
               <ptr target="#traubel1906" loc="1:92"/>.<note>Whitman probably exaggerated here, as
                  often in his discussions with Traubel.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Today, copies of Whitman’s first edition of <title rend="italic">Leaves of
                  Grass</title> are listed for sale at prices that range from $50,000 to
                  $270,000.<note> Estimates are based on prices and sales figures for copies listed
                  on AbeBooks.com and sold at rare book auctions between 2018 and 2020.</note> The
               books that once failed to sell are now the most expensive and sought-after of the
               editions of <title rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</title>. Failure has a place in the
               narrative of literary production, which like that of technology often centers on
               dreams, succession, and innovation. For Whitman, the arc of the future and its
               changing literary preferences fueled the popularity of his work over a century and a
               half of massive historical and technological changes. In the wake of a transformation
               in the value readers found in the poems that comprised his <title rend="italic"
                  >Leaves of Grass</title>, the first edition has re-emerged as a site of interest.
               Its rarity, combined with critical and popular consensus about the value of Whitman’s
               poems, has helped to make it one of the most expensive books of American literature
               on the market today. In the same economic sense that once rendered it a failure, one
               might say that the 1855 <title rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</title> has become a
               resounding success. </p>
            <p>Discussions of the digital humanities, too, are threaded throughout with tales of
               failure. Failures in the collection of essays titled <title rend="italic">A New
                  Companion to Digital Humanities</title>, updated in 2016, include the failures of
               collaboration <ptr target="#edmond2016"/>, of fabrication <ptr target="#sayers2016"
               />, of interdisciplinarity <ptr target="#mccarty2016"/>, of technology/hardware, of
               the imaginers of design fictions to account for humanities concerns about ethics and
               culture <ptr target="#jorgensen2016"/>, of data to interoperate, of the search string
               to correspond exactly with the search meaning, and so on. Happily, in none of these
               cases is failure conceived as a reason not to attempt. Indeed, the failure often
               produces different insights and, in some cases, visions with more comprehensive
               impact. </p>
            <p>Whitman splintered his poetry and prose into pieces, but like the shipbreakers he
               also brought it back together again in diverse and imaginative ways. One of his
               friends, Harrison S. Morris, recollected a story about the poet: <cit><quote
                     rend="block">He said an idea would strike him which, after mature thought, he
                     would consider fit to be the <quote rend="inline">special theme</quote> of a
                        <quote rend="inline">piece.</quote> This he would revolve in his mind in all
                     its phases, and finally adopt, setting it down crudely on a bit of paper, — the
                     back of an envelope or any scrap, — which he would place in an envelope. Then
                     he would lie in wait for any other material which might bear upon or lean
                     toward that idea, and, as it came into his mind, he would put it on paper and
                     place it in the same envelope. After he had quite exhausted the supply of
                     suggestions, or had a sufficient number to interpret the idea withal, he would
                     interweave them in a <quote rend="inline">piece,</quote> as he called it. I
                     asked him about the arrangement or succession of the slips, and he said, <quote
                        rend="inline">They always fall properly into place.</quote></quote>
                  <ref target="#kennedy1896" loc="24">(Qtd. in Kennedy [1896], 24)</ref></cit> Did
               Whitman ever think about failure, as he scratched out lines, cut and pasted, shuffled
               scraps in envelopes, relying on, in place of the muse, the seemingly mutual
               co-determinative pull of randomness and data? Do we think of failure as we gather,
               create, and transform data, trying not to let the questions determine the answers,
               trying not to let the machine be too much a reflection of our own biases and
               preconceptions? Is there any creative or analytical work that is not haunted by
               failure? </p>
            <p>As he walks the shore, the poet of Whitman’s <title rend="quotes">Bardic
                  Symbols</title> ponders the deposits of the waves, <quote rend="inline">In the
                  ruin, the sediment, that stands for all the water and all the land of the
                  globe.</quote> The detritus or sediment cast onto the shore is not random (being at least in part
               the product of known and ordered industries or natural phenomena like shipbuilding,
               trade, and weather). Neither is it fully recognizable. The poet laments his inability
               to understand the meaning of the debris — <quote rend="inline">Oh, I think I have not
                  understood anything, — not a single object, — and that no man ever can!</quote>
               The signs or bardic symbols represent a momentary configuration, but also a cosmic
               and historical culmination. Recognition in this poem occurs when the poet stops
               trying to read, to find a pre-determined meaning, and embraces the transformative
               work of metaphor.</p>
            <p>Struck shortly into <title rend="quotes">Bardic
                  Symbols</title> by an <quote rend="inline">old thought of likenesses,</quote> the
               poet begins to think about poetry as he observes the detritus. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Bardic Symbols</title> becomes a poem about printing and inscription as much as
               it is about a poet observing the sea. <quote rend="inline">I wish I could impress
                  others,</quote> the speaker begins, using language drawn from the technology of
               inscription of his time — the printed impression, the pressure of metal type on the
               page exerted by the printing press. Later, in an ecstasy of recognition, he exclaims
                  <quote rend="inline">I, too, leave little wrecks upon you, you fish-shaped
                  island!</quote> and concludes by looking up from the page to the reader: <quote
                  rend="block"><lg>
                     <l>We, capricious, brought hither, we know not whence, spread out before you,
                        —<lb/>you, up there, walking or sitting,</l>
                     <l>Whoever you are, — we, too, lie in
                        drifts at your feet.</l>
                  </lg></quote> Capricious, brought hither, through space and time, the drifts take
               the shape of the inked characters on the page or — now — the pixels or dots on the
               screen. The <quote rend="inline">semiotic ecology</quote> of poetry encompasses the
               cast-off detritus of the ocean as well as of print, and all the forms future
               likenesses take <ptr target="#drucker2013" loc="74"/>. Whitman’s drift, a complicated
               co-articulation of randomness and intentionality, offers a proleptic vision of
               digital textuality.<note>On Whitman’s concept of drift and its relation to the
                  distribution and circulation of his writing, see <ref target="#cohen2017">Cohen
                     (2017)</ref>.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head><q>Seized by the spirit that trails in the lines underfoot:</q> Re-scripting Race </head>
            <p>Guided by transformability and repair, we might break Whitman’s <title rend="quotes"
                  >Sleepers</title> back down into draft segments and imagine them further, beyond
               the familiar ground of TEI and namespaces, into Python, one of today’s most powerful
               and widely used programming languages.<note>GitHub’s 2019 <title rend="quotes"
                     >Octoverse Report</title> ranked Python as the second most-used language in Git
                  repositories, based on number of unique contributors <ptr target="#zhou2019"/>.
                  Python, like other programming languages and software platforms, has recently
                  begun to reckon with its metaphors. See <ref target="#oberhaus2018">Oberhaus
                     (2018)</ref> on the use and removal of the terms <q>master</q> and
                     <q>slave.</q> These terms have long been used (and recently, in some cases,
                  deprecated) in other engineering and computational contexts, including as
                  references to central and backup servers, primary and secondary drives, and
                  primary and replica databases. For further discussion, see <ref
                     target="#eglash2007">Eglash (2007)</ref> and <ref target="#landau2010">Landau
                     (2020)</ref>.</note> Like Emily Dickinson’s description of reading poems
               backward, seized by Samuels and McGann as a provocation for deformance, transforming
               or translating poetry into a programming script defamiliarizes elements of both,
               opening the door — or unscrewing it entirely — inviting insights at the intersection
               of digital and poetic logics.<note>Samuels and McGann quote Dickinson’s note, from
                     <quote rend="inline">an undated fragment on a leaf of stationery:</quote>
                  <quote rend="inline">Did you ever read one of her Poems backward, because the
                     plunge from the front overturned you? I sometimes (often have, many times)
                     have–a Something overtakes the Mind–</quote>
                  <ptr target="#samuels1999" loc="26"/>.</note> With particular force, this
               operation helps to demonstrate the ways in which what Ivy Wilson has described as
                  <quote rend="inline">the presence of African Americans — suspended between the
                  material and the apparitional, as it were — within the poetic space of [Whitman’s]
                  verse and other writings</quote> could be made to speak back to both the
               containment of Black U.S. citizens and deterministic, abstract narratives of
               technological development <ptr target="#wilson2014a" loc="ix"/>.</p>
            <p>The culminating dramatic moment in the poem that would be titled <title rend="quotes"
                  >The Sleepers,</title> more dramatic in the form of one of several manuscript
               drafts, has a striking conditional: <quote rend="block"><lg>
                     <l><hi rend="strikethrough">I am a hell-name and a Curse:</hi></l>
                     <l><hi rend="strikethrough">The</hi> Black Lucifer was not dead;</l>
                     <l>Or if he was, I am his sorrowful, terrible heir</l>
                  </lg></quote>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>Manuscript draft of lines eventually used in <title rend="quotes">The
                     Sleepers.</title> Papers of Walt Whitman, 1838-1987. Clifton Waller Barrett
                  Library of American Literature, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections
                  Library, University of Virginia.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            </figure>

            <p>From the narrative present of the poem, the speaker looks back to a past time: <quote
                  rend="inline">Black Lucifer <emph>was</emph> not dead.</quote> As Ed Folsom has
               written, the possible sources for Whitman’s Lucifer are many, from the Biblical
               Isaiah’s reference to <quote rend="inline">a fallen king of Babylon,...a reference
                  that led to the mistaken notion that Lucifer was the fallen angel from heaven,
                  Satan,</quote> to an ignitable match, to a nineteenth-century <title rend="italic"
                  >Webster’s Dictionary</title> description of Lucifer as <quote rend="inline">the
                  planet Venus, when appearing as the morning star</quote>
               <ptr target="#folsom2001"/>
               <ptr target="#folsom2000" loc="49"/>. Folsom notes that in one early notebook, <quote
                  rend="inline">Whitman lists gods, including Lucifer, who are defined as <q>made up
                     of all that opposes hinders, obstructs, revolts</q></quote>
               <ptr target="#folsom2000" loc="48"/>. Lucifer was not dead, the poet-historian,
               poet-interpreter, asserts — only to undercut the assertion. <emph>Or if he
                  was...</emph> Neatly bifurcating historical or spiritual time with a possibility,
               the poet-historian-slave follows one conditional path and moves confidently into the
               present: <quote rend="inline">I am his sorrowful, terrible heir.</quote></p>
            <p>Folsom situates this manuscript as one of several draft versions in which the speaker
               ceases to speak for the enslaved person and instead speaks <emph>as</emph> the
               enslaved person, in a culminating act of identification. The deleted line in this
               draft shows the speaker beginning with a declaration of identity that is at once
               naming and invective: <quote rend="inline">a hell-name and a Curse.</quote><note>
                  Whitman works through this line in other drafts. For a complete list of
                  transcriptions of the known drafts of these lines, see <ref target="#gray2020"
                     >Gray (ed.; 2020)</ref> line 1775 <ref
                     target="https://whitmanarchive.org/published/LG/1855/variorum/main.html#l1775"
                     >https://whitmanarchive.org/published/LG/1855/variorum/main.html#l1775</ref>.
               </note> The fracture or bifurcation of historical/spiritual time introduces the
               capacity for the speaker to transform, fully, into the divine. As (possible) heir of
               Black Lucifer, the speaker becomes <quote rend="inline">the God of Revolt — deathless
                  sorrowful vast.</quote> The draft moves then into the future: <quote rend="inline"
                  >I will either destroy <hi rend="strikethrough">them</hi><hi rend="superscript">him</hi> or <hi rend="strikethrough">they</hi><hi rend="superscript">he</hi> shall release me.</quote></p>
            <p>The published versions of the lines that appeared in the 1855 edition of <title
                  rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</title> incorporate several revisions, among them
               the first word of the <q>Lucifer</q> line: <cit><quote rend="block"><lg>
                        <l>Now Lucifer was not dead . . . . or if he was I am his sorrowful terrible
                           heir;</l>
                        <l>I have been wronged . . . . I am oppressed . . . . I hate him that
                           oppresses me,</l>
                        <l>I will either destroy him, or he shall release me.</l>
                     </lg></quote>
                  <ptr target="#whitman1855" loc="74"/></cit> Whitman’s substitution of <q>Now</q>
               for <q>Black</q> is one example of his removal of explicit references to race that
               appeared in the manuscripts.<note>See <ref target="#folsom2014">Folsom (2014)</ref>;
                     <ref target="#price2004" loc="17–8">Price (2004), 17-18</ref>; and <ref
                     target="#sandler2014">Sandler (2014), 71-74</ref>.</note> Functioning as a
               transitional word, <q>Now</q> emphasizes the temporal disjunction of this passage,
               moving to a new section of dreamspace in this poem about sleepers. But it also opens
               the door to another apparitional development: the historical moment and the
               institution of slavery have provoked an emergence that resurrects the God of Revolt,
               as undead (deathless) or in the form of succession. </p>
            <p>The revision between manuscript draft and published poem situates the lines within
               the larger temporal frame of the poem, which flits, dreamlike, among past, present,
               and future. Other words already in the draft describe the complicated conditions of
               both genealogical and temporal succession. The operators in the lines of this
               manuscript — OR, IF — form the axes of legibility for many programming languages. If
               these lines were a script written in Python, they might look like: <eg lang="python"><![CDATA[def us_slavery(year):
   year = int(year)
   if 1619 <= year <= 1863:
      self = 'enslaved'
   else:
      self = 'free'
      return self
def heir(I):
   I = 'his sorrowful, terrible heir'
   return I
def lucifer(state):
   I = 'self'
   if state == 'no':
      lucifer = 'Black_Lucifer'
      return lucifer
   else:
      I = heir(I)
      return I
def sleepers():
   I = 'hell-name'
   self = 'Curse'
   year = int(input('What year is it? '))
   self = us_slavery(year)
   if 1849 <= year < 1881:
      state = input('Was Black Lucifer dead? ')
      I = lucifer(state)
      if I != 'Black_Lucifer':
         print('I am',I)
         I = ['the God of Revolt','deathless','sorrowful','vast']
         for i in I:
            print('I am',i)
      else:
         if not self:
            print('REVOLT')
   elif year >=1881:
      print('A show of the summer softness\na contact of something unseen\nan amour of the
               light and air')
   elif 1776 <=year < 1849:
      print('We hold these truths to be self-evident\nthat all men are created
                  equal')
   else:
      print('Replica of the Great Hole of history')
sleepers()]]></eg><note>For the line <code>elif year&gt;=1881:</code>, if the user enters a year
                  later than or equal to 1881, she returns another line from the version of <title
                     rend="quotes">The Sleepers</title> published in the 1881 edition of <title
                     rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</title>, since the <title rend="quotes"
                     >Lucifer</title> lines are no longer present. For the line <code>elif 1776
                     &lt;=year &lt;1849:</code>, if the user enters a year after the date of U.S.
                  independence (1776) and prior to the approximate earliest probable date of the
                  manuscript (1849), she returns a line from the Declaration of Independence. On the
                  final print command, see <ref target="#parks1995" loc="159">Parks (1995),
                     159</ref>.</note></p>
            <p>Segments of the <title rend="quotes">Sleepers</title> manuscript can be produced by
               the Python script, which enacts executable parts of the poem. Depending on the date a
               user enters, the execution of the script might generate parts of the draft lines of
               the manuscript version, or it might generate other lines completely. The parameters
               are time, history, and the state of existence of Black Lucifer. In this
               transformation, succession returns to somewhere just short of its biological roots:
               Lucifer’s conditional successor is a function and a refraction of American slavery. As a
                  <quote rend="inline">hell-name and a Curse,</quote> Lucifer or his heir is handed
               down across borders of time and space, iterations of manuscript and print, evolutions
               of communicative machinery, to emerge briefly and dramatically in a peculiar, failed,
               breakthrough book of American poetry — or on your computer screen. </p>
            <p>The kinship of languages is framed as relations of history (origin, reproduction),
               but recast as a matter of space, execution, and transformation within the specific,
               limited temporality of the script, or of dreamspace, or of the boundaries of the
               logics declared in our interpretations. The program points to the significance and
               the operability of the conditional. The poem points to the significance and the
               inoperability of the past tense. For the loop, something is or is not. <q>Was</q> is
               not operable or definable within the space of the loop. It could be argued that it is
               enacted by the space outside the loop, and the variables are handed down. But what
               must come outside the loop to begin to approximate the meaning? The entire history of
               U.S. slavery and oppression, condensed into a series of expressions? Would they be
               definitions, or descriptions, or conditionals?</p>
            <p>That computers can draw critical attention to patterns that sometimes go overlooked
               by the human eye has formed the appeal behind many digital methods. One of the most
               powerful characteristics of computational analysis tools like text mining
               classification algorithms is that they can be trained or tweaked by programmers based
               on specific data or results sets. Can the attention of researchers also be trained to
               look more closely at the kinds of words that machines would find actionable or
                  significant?<note>For text mining purposes, as Jockers and Underwood point out,
                     <quote rend="inline">we know from years of authorship-attribution research that
                     the most effective features for distinguishing one author’s style from
                     another’s are high-frequency features such as the words <q>the,</q>
                     <q>of,</q>
                     <q>him,</q>
                     <q>her,</q> and <q>and,</q> as well as common marks of punctuation</quote>
                  <ptr target="#jockers2016" loc="293"/>.</note> What would it mean to experiment
               with training as a mutual process, a kind of projection by a human into a
               computational mode of processing? In a world of posthumanist criticism, the insights
               of macroanalysis may be used to conduct even closer readings — to see the value in
               Whitman’s <q>the</q> and his <q>or</q> as well as his <q>leaves</q> and his
                  <q>grass.</q> Such attention may, as Matthew Wilkins has noted, <quote
                  rend="inline">suggest that there’s a low-level linguistic basis for the category
                  distinctions we’ve long been inclined to draw.</quote> It might also help us to
               produce new readings of well-traveled passages. </p>
            <p>Book historians and bibliographers have demonstrated that the formal and linguistic
               interference of the editor is a crucial component of the afterlife of the work, and
               therefore its continued life in time. <quote rend="inline">Acts of translation and
                  editing are especially useful forms of critical reflection,</quote> McGann writes,
                  <quote rend="inline">because they so clearly invade and change their subjects in
                  material ways</quote>
               <ptr target="#mcgann2016" loc="368"/>. The heart of the way text is increasingly
               imagined today — the product of our data-vision — is its
                  <term>transformability</term>. This transformability is a matter of succession,
               but not always of success. Whitman, an early exponent of modularity or
               transformability as a fundamental characteristic of textual production, serves as an
               instructive precursor. His transformational approach is visible in the scraps he
               shuffled in envelopes, the many editions of <title rend="italic">Leaves of
                  Grass</title>, and his re-making of books more generally.</p>
            <p> Programming, perhaps for everyone, but particularly for those of us not formally
               trained in the art, becomes a study in errors. In writing the sleepers.py script, I
               encountered a series of errors:<eg lang="python"><![CDATA[
TypeError: us_slavery() missing 2 required positional arguments: 'self' and 'year'
NameError: name 'slave' is not defined
NameError: name 'I' is not defined
Traceback (most recent call last):
   File "sleepers.py", line 21, in sleepers
      lucifer = Black_Lucifer
NameError: name 'Black_Lucifer' is not defined
Traceback (most recent call last):
   File "sleepers.py", line 40, in sleepers
      lucifer = lucifer(input("Was Black Lucifer dead? "))
UnboundLocalError: local variable 'lucifer' referenced before assignment]]></eg> The errors — TypeErrors,
               NameErrors, UnboundLocalErrors — that I produced in the making of sleepers.py mostly
               had to do with variables, either undefined or not included as part of the execution
               of a function that required them. In the case of a finished, working script, of
               course — or a script developed by an experienced, trained programmer — one may be
               less likely to encounter errors. Nor is it necessarily clear after the fact, unless a
               log or versioning system is associated with the development and made accessible as a
               complement to the resource, that they existed. Such data often fades into an
               invisible history of development, or it vanishes by virtue of being overwhelmed by an
               avalanche of incremental changes, commits, updates, migrations, transformations,
               deletions, and additions.<note>On the role of this kind of invisibility in the
                  capitalistic exploitation of creativity, see <ref target="#liu2004b">Liu
                     (2004b)</ref>.</note> In this case, perhaps as a conceit, one might argue that
               the errors formed a layer of the transformation, the undefinedness of the variable
               part of its poetic interpretation. The missing definitions represent segments of
               American history as it is performed in Whitman’s poems: the specific identity of the
               reader, the ambiguity of the designations of <q>slave</q> and <q>I.</q> Somewhere
               between the failures of the programmer and the untranslatability of the poem fragment
               lurks the impossible largeness of poetry, its ambiguities and its historical roots,
               the unexecutable complicating presence of the undefined and the undefinable. </p>
            <p>Before the publication of the 1881 edition of <title rend="italic">Leaves of
                  Grass</title>, Whitman returned to pages from an earlier edition to revise <title
                  rend="quotes">The Sleepers</title> for republication. On those pages, Whitman
               created a textual event, a deletion of the <title rend="quotes">Lucifer</title>
               passage:</p>

            <figure>
               <head>A page from <title rend="quotes">The Sleepers,</title> with Whitman’s edits.
                  Walt Whitman Papers in the Charles E. Feinberg Collection. Library of
                  Congress.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
            </figure>

            <p>Editing these and other lines out of his dreamspace, Whitman produced a final version
               of the poem tuned to a different historical present and different priorities on the
               part of the poet.<note>For a discussion of this deletion and other omissions as
                  related to Whitman’s increasing concern about the role of Blacks in the
                  Reconstruction and post-Reconstruction U.S., see <ref target="#folsom2000"
                     loc="52–77">Folsom (2000), 52-77</ref>. See also <ref target="#klammer2006"
                     >Klammer (2006)</ref>. Whitman deleted other sections from the poem, as well:
                  see, for instance, the two sections beginning <quote rend="inline">O hot-cheek’d
                     and blushing! O foolish hectic!</quote></note> For Whitman, it would seem, the
               moment for the conjunction of experimental dreamspace with historical possibility had
               passed. If all you looked at was the 1891, <q>authorized</q> edition of <title
                  rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</title>, you would never know the self of <title
                  rend="quotes">Bardic Symbols,</title> now titled <title rend="quotes">As I Ebb’d
                  With the Ocean of Life,</title> had once been eternal — or that Lucifer had ever
               been there at all. </p>
            <p>Luckily, Whitman’s was not the final word on the matter. Transformation is one path
               to the other side of determinism — a methodology that resurrects fragments, writes
               dysfunctional scripts, and attends to errors, absences and deletions. Media have
               always had to do with light and darkness, shadow and space, figures, icons, and
               projections. They can affect the visibility of history, passion, identification or
               difference. Perhaps media technologies become most apparent when the binaries break
               down in the act of translation, transformation, or remediation: in error, or,
               sometimes, in deletion. Moments at which multiple possibilities exist, suspended in
               space, can look suspiciously like moments of failure to the backwards glance of
               history: <emph>Or if he was</emph>. From this vantage point we watch Whitman on the
               verge, pencil in hand, weighing the path of erasure. The penciled bars of his
               hashmark deletion bought <title rend="quotes">The Sleepers</title> into a new
                  <q>Now,</q> a post-war moment in which the promise of Lucifer’s heir — <quote
                  rend="inline">I will either destroy him, or he shall release me</quote> — may have
               echoed uncomfortably even for many former abolitionists, by then inclined toward
               reconciliation. The voice of the former slave and his descendants would continue to
               be locked away and suppressed from full political participation up to and beyond the
               emergence of Jim Crow in a series of criminal acts of silencing, violence, and
               oppression whose ongoing existence and implications are abundantly visible in our own
               time. But in that first conditional instant, that <q>Now</q> in which the God of
               revolt was summoned, is also <term>success</term>, if only in the form of the
               recognition that one is part of a succession, sorrowful or otherwise.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion: <q>I, too, Paumanok</q></head>
            <p>A 2007 <title rend="italic">PMLA</title> special topic forum about the digital
               editorial project <title rend="italic">The Walt Whitman Archive</title> exposed
               fundamental disagreements about the use of metaphors as substitutions for precise
               descriptions of digital tools.<note>See <ref target="#folsom2007">Folsom
                  (2007)</ref>; <ref target="#mcgann2007">McGann (2007)</ref>; and <ref
                     target="#hayles2007">Hayles (2007)</ref>.</note> Demystifying the tools,
               however, does not rid us of metaphors, nor of the responsibility of navigating the
               complicated interplay of imagination, history, language, functionality, exclusion,
               and desire that defines the use and development of any technology. The transformative
               work of metaphor continues to inform the way technology functions, as well as the
               ways literary scholars can put it to work. Using imagination to cast seemingly
               competing logics against one another, to put pressure on the resonances between the
               words and the workings of poetic and machine language of the past and present, is one
               tool among many for training the attention to linger on a particular moment in a poem
               or other creative work and tease out some of its existing or potential
               implications.</p>
            <p>Creative transformations applied to materials made digitally available by projects
               like the <title rend="italic">Whitman Archive</title> can act as provocations to
               think and act and edit differently. In some cases, this may be a way to explore how
               underrepresented populations and perspectives are addressed (or erased) in historical
               documents. Recognition that race, gender, and other forms of diversity have shaped
               the historical record is finally beginning to affect textual and technological theory
               in ways that are slowly filtering back into editorial approaches, the digitization of
               literary and historical documents, and the work of thinking about the multiple
               versions of those documents in relation to the many different people whose histories
               they often imperfectly represent.</p>
            <p><quote rend="inline">If an electronic scholarly project can’t fail and doesn’t
                  produce new ignorance,</quote> John Unsworth wrote in a 1997 essay, <quote
                  rend="inline">then it isn’t worth a damn.</quote> The costs of failure or
               confessing ignorance, in the face of today’s confident, practiced users of digital
               tools and a historically bad tenure-track academic job market in the humanities, seem
               unusually high. Contingent, part-time, or adjunct positions can feel an awful lot
               like failure, without any guarantee of transformation, productive or otherwise. The
               current funding situation for the humanities and, increasingly, for education more
               broadly, is easily tied to the worst human motives — greed, racism, nativism, fear —
               and the darkest political prospects. Redefining the goals and parameters of success
               and failure for any project may be particularly necessary at such a time. Somewhere
               in theorizations like Sedgwick’s, or in Jackson’s repair, may be a glimmer of light,
               in the form of a call for the work of maintaining projects to become visible, for a
               broader notion of <q>success</q> to make that phenomenon visible in more places, for
               transformations of fields and texts to create the space for new voices and insights,
               and for the role of creation to be recognized in forms of labor other than authorship
               or innovation.</p>
            <p>Is it time for the digital humanities to fail? As the humanities increasingly engages
               computation as a practice fundamental to the production of scholarship, or as the
               field called the digital humanities continues to splinter into method-specific
               approaches, we might resolutely cultivate one of its most exciting vectors: the
               emergence of a recuperative, radically experimental critical mode. In this mode, the
               imagination that fuels transformability is key, and failure holds a place of crucial
               importance. As Whitman’s <q>self</q> became electrified over the course of the
               nineteenth-century manifestations of <title rend="quotes">Bardic Symbols,</title> so
               might we find in the digital detritus of our own day an electrifying vision of the
               future, a set of new critical possibilities to build out of the ships and the
               shipwrecks of history, as well as the transformable lines of poetry and prose to
               which they give rise. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>My thanks to Brett Barney, Matt Cohen, Mike Cohen, Ken Price, and Steve Ramsay for
               their thoughtful comments on drafts of this essay. Thanks also to the anonymous
               reviewers for their helpful suggestions.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="allington2016" label="Allington et al. 2016">Allington, Daniel, Sarah
               Brouillette, and David Golumbia. <title rend="quotes">Neoliberal Tools (and
                  Archives): A Political History of Digital Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Los Angeles Review of Books</title> (May 1, 2016). <ref
                  target="https://lareviewofbooks.org/article/neoliberal-tools-archives-political-history-digital-humanities/"
                  >https://lareviewofbooks.org/article/neoliberal-tools-archives-political-history-digital-humanities/</ref>
               Accessed 13 September 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bailey2011" label="Bailey 2011">Bailey, Moya Z. <title rend="quotes">All
                  the Digital Humanists Are White, All the Nerds Are Men, but Some of Us Are
                  Brave.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 1.1 (2011).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="barnett2016" label="Barnett et al. 2016">Barnett, Fiona, Zach Blas, Micha
               Cárdenas, Jacob Gaboury, Jessica Marie Johnson, and Margaret Rhee. <title
                  rend="quotes">QueerOS: A User’s Manual.</title> Klein and Gold, 2016. <ref
                  target="dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/56"
                  >dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/56</ref>. Accessed 20 July 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cohen2017" label="Cohen 2017">Cohen, Matt. <title rend="italic">Whitman’s
                  Drift: Imagining Literary Distribution</title>. Iowa City: University of Iowa
               Press, 2017.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ccp" label="ccp">
               <title rend="italic">Colored Conventions Project</title>. University of Delaware.
               coloredconventions.org. Accessed 1 August 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dhpoco" label="dhpoco.org">dhpoco.org. Curated by Adeline Koh and Roopika
               Risam. Accessed 10 July 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="draper2017" label="Draper 2017">Draper, Nora. <title rend="quotes">Fail
                  Fast: The Value of Studying Unsuccessful Technology Companies.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Media Industries</title>, 4.1 (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2013" label="Drucker 2013">Drucker, Johanna. <title rend="quotes"
                  >From A to Screen: The Migration of Letters.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Comparative Textual Media</title>, ed. N. Katherine Hayles and
               Jessica Pressman. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2013.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2009" label="Drucker 2009">Drucker, Johanna. <title rend="italic">SpecLab: Digital
                  Aesthetics and Projects in Speculative Computing</title>. Chicago: University of
               Chicago Press, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="edmond2016" label="Edmond 2016">Edmond, Jennifer. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Collaboration and Infrastructure.</title> Schreibman et al., 54-65. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eglash2007" label="Eglash 2007">Eglash, Ron. <title rend="quotes">Broken
                  Metaphor: The Master-Slave Analogy in Technical Literature.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Technology and Culture</title> 48.2 (April 2007).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="xslw3c" label="XSL W3C"><title rend="quotes">The Extensible Stylesheet
                  Language Family (XSL).</title> W3C. <ref target="http://www.w3.org/Style/XSL/"
                  >www.w3.org/Style/XSL/</ref>. Accessed 20 September 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="folsom2007" label="Folsom 2007">Folsom, Ed. <title rend="quotes">Database
                  as Genre: The Epic Transformation of Archives.</title>
               <title rend="italic">PMLA</title> 122.5 (October 2007): 1571-9.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="folsom2014" label="Folsom 2014">Folsom, Ed. <title rend="quotes">Erasing Race: The Lost Black Presence
                  in Whitman’s Manuscripts.</title> Wilson, ed., 3-31. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="folsom2000" label="Folsom 2000">Folsom, Ed. <title rend="quotes">Lucifer and
                  Ethiopia: Whitman, Race, and Poetics before the Civil War and After.</title>
               <title rend="italic">A Historical Guide to Walt Whitman</title>, ed. David S.
               Reynolds. New York: Oxford University Press, 2000. 45-96.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="folsom2001" label="Folsom 2001">Folsom, Ed. <title rend="quotes">Walt Whitman’s
                     <title rend="quotes">The Sleepers.</title></title>
               <title rend="italic">The Classroom Electric: Dickinson, Whitman, and American
                  Culture</title>. 2001. <ref
                  target="http://bailiwick.lib.uiowa.edu/whitman/sleepers/"
                  >http://bailiwick.lib.uiowa.edu/whitman/sleepers/</ref>. Accessed 18 April
               2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="french1990" label="French 1990">French, R. W. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Whitman’s Dream Vision: A Reading of <title rend="quotes">The
                  Sleepers.</title></title>
               <title rend="italic">Walt Whitman Quarterly Review</title> 8.1 (Summer 1990):
               1-15.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gallon2016" label="Gallon 2016">Gallon, Kim. <title rend="quotes">Making a
                  Case for the Black Digital Humanities.</title> Klein and Gold, 2016. <ref
                  target="dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/55"
                  >dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/55</ref>. Accessed 10 July 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gilmore2009" label="Gilmore 2009">Gilmore, Paul. <title rend="italic"
                  >Aesthetic Materialism: Electricity and American Romanticism</title>. Stanford:
               Stanford University Press, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gray2020" label="Gray 2020">Gray, Nicole, ed. <title rend="italic">Leaves
                  of Grass (1855) Variorum</title>. The Walt Whitman Archive, 2020. <ref
                  target="https://whitmanarchive.org/published/LG/1855/variorum/index.html"
                  >https://whitmanarchive.org/published/LG/1855/variorum/index.html</ref>. Accessed
               27 September 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="greenspan2019" label="Greenspan 2019">Greenspan, Brian. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Scandal of Digital Humanities.</title> Klein and Gold, 2019.
                  <ref target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu">https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu</ref>.
               Accessed 12 September 2020. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="grossman2019" label="Grossman 2019">Grossman, Jay. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Manuprint.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Walt Whitman Quarterly Review</title>, 37.1 (Summer/Fall 2019):
               46–65.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hayles2007" label="Hayles 2007">Hayles, N. Katherine. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Narrative and Database: Natural Symbionts.</title>
               <title rend="italic">PMLA</title> 122.5 (October 2007): 1603-8.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jackson2014" label="Jackson 2014">Jackson, Steven J. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Rethinking Repair.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Media Technologies: Essays on Communication, Materiality and
                  Society</title>, ed. Tarleton Gillespie, Pablo J. Boczkowski, and Kirsten A. Foot.
               Cambridge: MIT Press, 2014.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jeffrey1992" label="Jeffrey and Morris 1992">Jeffrey, David Lyle and Leon
               Morris. <title rend="quotes">Logos.</title>
               <title rend="italic">A Dictionary of Biblical Tradition in English
               Literature</title>, ed. David L. Jeffrey. Grand Rapids, MI: William B. Eerdmans,
               1992. 459-61.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jockers2013" label="Jockers 2013">Jockers, Matthew L. <title rend="italic"
                  >Macroanalysis: Digital Methods and Literary History</title>. Champaign, IL:
               University of Illinois Press, 2013.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jockers2016" label="Jockers and Underwood 2016">Jockers, Matthew L. and
               Ted Underwood. <title rend="quotes">Text-Mining the Humanities.</title> Schreibman et
               al., 291-306. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jorgensen2016" label="Jørgensen 2016">Jørgensen, Finn Arne. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Internet of Things.</title> Schreibman et al., 42-53. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kay2008" label="Kay 2008">Kay, Michael. <title rend="italic">XSLT 2.0 and
                  XPath 2.0: Programmer’s Reference</title>. 4th ed. Indianapolis, IN: Wiley
               Publishing, Inc., 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kennedy1896" label="Kennedy 1896">Kennedy, William Sloane. <title
                  rend="italic">Reminiscences of Walt Whitman</title>. London: Alexander Gardner,
               1896.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="klammer2006" label="Klammer 2006">Klammer, Martin. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Slavery and Race.</title>
               <title rend="italic">A Companion to Walt Whitman</title>, ed. Donald D. Kummings.
               Malden, MA: Blackwell, 2006. 101-121.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="klein2012" label="Klein and Gold 2019">Klein, Lauren F., and Matthew K.
               Gold, eds. <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>.
               Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2012, 2016, and 2019. <ref
                  target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/">https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2012" label="Kirschenbaum 2012">Kirschenbaum, Matthew. <title
                  rend="quotes">Digital Humanities As/Is a Tactical Term.</title> Klein and Gold,
               2012. <ref target="dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/48"
                  >dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/48</ref>. Accessed 20 July 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2010" label="Kirschenbaum 2010">Kirschenbaum, Matthew. <title rend="quotes">What
                  Is Digital Humanities and What’s It Doing in English Departments?</title>
               <title rend="italic">ADE Bulletin</title> 150 (2010): 55-61.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="knuth1973" label="Knuth 1973">Knuth, Donald E. <title rend="italic">The
                  Art of Computer Programming</title>. Vol. 1. 2nd edition. Reading, MA:
               Addison-Wesley Publishing Company, 1973.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="koh2013" label="Koh and Risam 2013">Koh, Adeline and Roopika Risam. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Origins of #DHpoco and the Art of Play.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Postcolonial Digital Humanities</title> (20 March 2013).
               Dhpoco.org.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="landau2010" label="Landau 2020">Landau, Elizabeth. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Tech Confronts Its Use of the Labels <q>Master</q> and <q>Slave.</q></title>
               <title rend="italic">Wired</title>, 6 July 2020. <ref
                  target="https://www.wired.com/story/tech-confronts-use-labels-master-slave/"
                  >https://www.wired.com/story/tech-confronts-use-labels-master-slave/</ref>.
               Accessed 27 September 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="latour1988" label="Latour 1988">Latour, Bruno [as Jim Johnson]. <title
                  rend="quotes">Mixing Humans and Nonhumans Together: The Sociology of a
                  Door-Closer.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Social Problems</title> 35.3 (June 1988): 298-210.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="liu2004a" label="Liu 2004a">Liu, Alan. <title rend="italic">The Laws of
                  Cool: Knowledge Work and the Culture of Information</title>. Chicago: University
               of Chicago Press, 2004.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="liu2004b" label="Liu 2004b">Liu, Alan. <title rend="quotes">Transcendental Data:
                  Toward a Cultural History and Aesthetics of the New Encoded Discourse.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Critical Inquiry</title> 31 (2004): 49-84.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oed" label="OED"><title rend="quotes">logic, <hi rend="italic"
                  >n</hi>.</title>
               <title rend="italic">OED Online</title>. Oxford University Press. <ref
                  target="www.oed.com/view/Entry/109788">www.oed.com/view/Entry/109788</ref>.
               Accessed 19 April 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="liddell" label="Liddell-Scott-Jones"><title rend="quotes">λόγος.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Online Liddell-Scott-Jones Greek-English Lexicon</title>.
                  <ref target="http://stephanus.tlg.uci.edu/lsj/#eid=65855"
                  >http://stephanus.tlg.uci.edu/lsj/#eid=65855</ref>. Accessed 19 April 2018. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mancuso1997" label="Mancuso 1997">Mancuso, Luke. <title rend="italic">The
                  Strange Sad War Revolving: Walt Whitman, Reconstruction, and the Emergence of
                  Black Citizenship, 1865-1876</title>. Columbia, SC: Camden House, 1997. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mccarty2016" label="McCarty 2016">McCarty, Willard. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Becoming Interdisciplinary.</title> Schreibman et al., 67-83.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcgann2007" label="McGann 2007">McGann, Jerome. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Database, Interface, and Archival Fever.</title>
               <title rend="italic">PMLA</title> 122.5 (October 2007): 1588-92.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcgann2016" label="McGann 2016">McGann, Jerome. <title rend="quotes">Marking Texts of
                  Many Dimensions.</title> Schreibman et al., 358-76. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcgann2001" label="McGann 2001">McGann, Jerome. <title rend="italic">Radiant
                  Textuality: Literature After the World Wide Web</title>. New York: Palgrave,
               2001.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mckenzie1999" label="McKenzie 1999">McKenzie, D. F. <title rend="italic"
                  >Bibliography and the Sociology of Texts.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge University
               Press, 1999.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2012" label="McPherson 2012">McPherson, Tara. <title
                  rend="quotes">Why Are the Digital Humanities So White? or Thinking the Histories
                  of Race and Computation.</title> Klein and Gold, 2012. <ref
                  target="dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/29"
                  >dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/29</ref>. Accessed 20 July 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="miller2010" label="Miller 2010">Miller, Matt. <title rend="italic">Collage
                  of Myself: Walt Whitman and the Making of Leaves of Grass</title>. Lincoln, NE:
               University of Nebraska Press, 2010.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mott1939" label="Mott 1939-57">Mott, Frank Luther. <title rend="italic">A
                  History of American Magazines</title>. 4 vols. Cambridge: Belknap Press of Harvard
               University Press, 1939-57. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mott1941" label="Mott 1941">Mott, Frank Luther. <title rend="italic">American Journalism: A
                  History of Newspapers in the United States through 250 Years, 1690 to
               1940</title>. New York: Macmillan Company, 1941.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mukurtu" label="Mukurtu">Mukurtu Archive. <ref
                  target="http://www.mukurtuarchive.org/">www.mukurtuarchive.org</ref>. Accessed 1
               August 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="myerson1993" label="Myerson 1993">Myerson, Joel. <title rend="italic">Walt
                  Whitman: A Descriptive Bibliography</title>. Pittsburgh, PA: University of
               Pittsburgh Press, 1993.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="newman2017" label="Newman 2017">Newman, Daniel. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Secret to Digital Transformation Success: Fail Fast to Innovate Faster.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Forbes</title>. 16 May 2017. <ref
                  target="http://www.forbes.com/">www.forbes.com</ref>. Accessed April 18,
               2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oberhaus2018" label="Oberhaus 2018">Oberhaus, Daniel. <title rend="quotes"
                     ><q>Master/Slave</q> Terminology Was Removed from Python Programming
                  Language.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Vice</title>. 13 September 2018. <ref
                  target="http://www.vice.com/">www.vice.com</ref>. Accessed September 30,
               2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="parks1995" label="Parks 1995">Parks, Suzan-Lori. <title rend="italic">The
                  America Play and Other Works</title>. New York: Theatre Communications Group,
               Inc., 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="posner2016" label="Posner 2016">Posner, Miriam. <title rend="quotes"
                  >What’s Next: The Radical, Unrealized Potential of Digital Humanities.</title>
               Klein and Gold, 2016. <ref target="dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/54"
                  >dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/54</ref>. Accessed 20 April 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="price2004" label="Price 2004">Price, Kenneth M. <title rend="italic">To
                  Walt Whitman, America</title>. Chapel Hill, NC: University of North Carolina
               Press, 2004. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="raley2002" label="Raley 2002">Raley, Rita. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Interferences: [Net.Writing] and the Practice of Codework.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Electronic Book Review</title> (2002). <ref
                  target="http://electronicbookreview.com/essay/interferences-net-writing-and-the-practice-of-codework/"
                  >http://electronicbookreview.com/essay/interferences-net-writing-and-the-practice-of-codework/</ref>.
               Accessed 31 July 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ramsay2011" label="Ramsay 2011">Ramsay, Stephen. <title rend="italic"
                  >Reading Machines: Toward an Algorithmic Criticism</title>. Urbana: University of
               Illinois Press, 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="samuels1999" label="Samuels and McGann 1999">Samuels, Lisa and Jerome
               McGann. <title rend="quotes">Deformance and Interpretation.</title>
               <title rend="italic">New Literary History</title> 30.1 (Winter 1999): 25-56.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sandage2005" label="Sandage 2005">Sandage, Scott A. <title rend="italic"
                  >Born Losers: A History of Failure in America</title>. Cambridge, MA: Harvard
               University Press, 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sandler2014" label="Sandler 2014">Sandler, Matt. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Kindred Darkness: Whitman in New Orleans.</title> Wilson, ed., 54-81. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sayers2016" label="Sayers et al. 2016">Sayers, Jentery, Devon Elliott,
               Kari Kraus, Bethany Nowviskie, and William J. Turkel. <title rend="quotes">Between
                  Bits and Atoms: Physical Computing and Desktop Fabrication in the
                  Humanities.</title> Schreibman et al., 1-21. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schloen2014" label="Schloen and Schloen 2014">Schloen, David and Sandra
               Schloen. <title rend="quotes">Beyond Gutenberg: Transcending the Document Paradigm in
                  Digital Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 8.4 (2014).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schreibman2016" label="Schreibman et al. 2016">Schreibman, Susan, Ray
               Siemens, and John Unsworth, eds. <title rend="italic">A New Companion to Digital
                  Humanities</title>. Chichester: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2016.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sedgwick2003" label="Sedgwick 2003">Sedgwick, Eve Kosofsky. <title
                  rend="quotes">Paranoid Reading and Reparative Reading, Or, You’re So Paranoid, You
                  Probably Think this Essay is About You.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Touching Feeling: Affect, Pedagogy, Performativity.</title>
               Durham: Duke University Press, 2003. 123-152.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stallybrass2019" label="Stallybrass 2019">Stallybrass, Peter. <title
                  rend="quotes">Walt Whitman's Slips: Manufacturing Manuscript.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Walt Whitman Quarterly Review</title>, 37.1 (Summer/Fall 2019):
               66–106.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stephenson1999" label="Stephenson 1999">Stephenson, Neal. <title
                  rend="italic">In the Beginning was the Command Line</title>. New York: Avon,
               1999.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="surowiecki2014" label="Surowiecki 2014">Surowiecki, James. <title
                  rend="quotes">Epic Fails of the Startup World.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The New Yorker</title> (19 May 2014). <ref
                  target="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2014/05/19/epic-fails-of-the-startup-world"
                  >https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2014/05/19/epic-fails-of-the-startup-world</ref>.
               Accessed 31 July 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="traubel1906" label="Traubel 1906-96">Traubel, Horace. <title rend="italic"
                  >With Walt Whitman in Camden</title>. 9 vols. 1906-1996.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="w3c" label="W3C"><title rend="quotes">Transformation.</title> W3C
               Standards (XML Technology). <ref
                  target="https://www.w3.org/standards/xml/transformation"
                  >https://www.w3.org/standards/xml/transformation</ref>. Accessed 8 August
               2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="transformdh" label="transformDH">#transformDH: This is the Digital
                  Humanities. <ref target="http://transformdh.tumblr.com/"
                  >http://transformdh.tumblr.com/</ref>, transformDH.org. Accessed 20 July
               2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="unsworth1997" label="Unsworth 1997">Unsworth, John. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Documenting the Reinvention of Text: The Importance of Failure.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Journal of Electronic Publishing</title> 3.2 (December
               1997). www.press.umich.edu/jep/03-02/unsworth.html. Accessed 22 August 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vincent1889" label="Vincent 1889">Vincent, Marvin R. <title rend="italic"
                  >Word Studies in the New Testament</title>. Vol. 2. New York: Charles Scribner’s
               Sons, 1889.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wwarchives" label="Walt Whitman Archives">
               <title rend="italic">The Walt Whitman Archive</title>. <ref
                  target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/">www.whitmanarchive.org</ref>. Accessed 27
               September 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whitman1860" label="Whitman 1860">Whitman, Walt. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Bardic Symbols.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</title> 5 (April 1860): 445-47.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whitman1842" label="Whitman 1842">Whitman, Walt. “Franklin Evans; or, the Inebriate. A
               Tale of the Times.” <title rend="italic">The New World</title> (November 1842):
               [1]-31.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whitman1855" label="Whitman 1855">Whitman, Walt. <title rend="italic">Leaves of
                  Grass</title>. Brooklyn, NY, 1855.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whitman1860-1" label="Whitman 1860-1">Whitman, Walt. <title rend="italic">Leaves of
                  Grass</title>. Boston: Thayer and Eldridge, 1860-1.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whitman1867" label="Whitman 1867">Whitman, Walt. <title rend="italic">Leaves of
                  Grass</title>. New York: W. E. Chapin &amp; Co., Printers, 1867.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whitman1871" label="Whitman 1871">Whitman, Walt. <title rend="italic">Leaves of
                  Grass</title>. Washington, DC, 1871.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whitman1881" label="Whitman 1881-2">Whitman, Walt. <title rend="italic">Leaves of
                  Grass</title>. Boston: James R. Osgood and Company, 1881-2.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whitman1891" label="Whitman 1891-2">Whitman, Walt. <title rend="italic">Leaves of
                  Grass</title>. Philadelphia: David McKay, 1891-2.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whitman1888" label="Whitman 1888">Whitman, Walt. <title rend="italic">November
                  Boughs</title>. Philadelphia: David McKay, 1888.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wilkins2013" label="Wilkins 2013">Wilkins, Matthew. <title rend="quotes"
                  >An Impossible Number of Books: Matthew L. Jockers’s <q>Macroanalysis.</q></title>
               <title rend="italic">Los Angeles Review of Books</title>. 16 August 2013. <ref
                  target="https://lareviewofbooks.org/">https://lareviewofbooks.org</ref>. Accessed
               18 April 2018. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wilson2014a" label="Wilson 2014a">Wilson, Ivy G. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Looking with a Queer Smile: Walt Whitman’s Gaze and Black America.</title>
               Wilson, ed., vii-xix.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wilson2014b" label="Wilson 2014b">Wilson, Ivay G., ed. <title rend="italic">Whitman
                  Noir: Black America and the Good Gray Poet</title>. Iowa City: University of Iowa
               Press, 2014.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="winship1991" label="Winship 1991">Winship, Michael. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Walt Whitman.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Bibliography of American Literature</title>, compiled by Jacob
               Blanck. Vol. 9. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1991. 28-103. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zhou2019" label="Zhou 2019">Zhou, Cathy. <title rend="italic">The State of
                  the Octoverse 2019.</title> The GitHub Blog, 6 November 2019. <ref
                  target="https://github.blog/2019-11-06-the-state-of-the-octoverse-2019/"
                  >https://github.blog/2019-11-06-the-state-of-the-octoverse-2019/</ref>. Accessed
               27 September 2020. </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
