<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!-- article title in English -->Introduction:
                    Questioning <emph>Collaboration</emph>, <emph>Labor</emph>, and
                        <emph>Visibility</emph> in Digital Humanities Research</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Tarez Samra <dhq:family>Graban</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Florida State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>tgraban@fsu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Tarez Samra Graban is an Associate Professor of English at Florida State
                            University, where she also leads an interdisciplinary reading group in
                            the digital humanities, and serves as co-director of the Demos Project
                            for studies in the data humanities. Her research interests include
                            feminist data ethics and redrawing disciplinary boundaries in the face
                            of emergent digital historical practices. Some of this work appears in
                                <title rend="italic">Networked Humanities</title> (2018), <title
                                rend="italic">African Journal of Rhetoric</title> (2017), <title
                                rend="italic">Rhetoric and the Digital Humanities</title> (2014),
                            and <title rend="italic">College English</title> (2013).</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Paul <dhq:family>Marty</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Florida State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>marty@fsu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Paul F. Marty, Ph.D is Professor in the School of Information, and
                            Associate Dean in the College of Communication and Information at
                            Florida State University. His research and teaching interests include
                            museum informatics, technology and culture, innovation and design, and
                            information and society. His professional service includes the editorial
                            boards and committees of national and international organizations such
                            as Museum Management and Curatorship, Museums and the Web, and the
                            Museum Computer Network. Dr. Marty has a background in ancient history
                            and computer science engineering, and his Ph.D. is from the School of
                            Information Sciences at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.
                        </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Allen <dhq:family>Romano</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Florida State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>aromano@fsu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Allen J. Romano is Associate Teaching Professor in the Department of
                            Interdisciplinary Humanities at Florida State University. His teaching
                            and research interests range widely over ancient literature, language,
                            and culture, including digital methods for studying ancient Greek
                            literature. He runs the digital humanities graduate program at Florida
                            State, co-directs the Demos Project for studies in the data humanities,
                            and regularly teaches courses on humanities data, history of technology,
                            and digital pedagogy.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Micah <dhq:family>Vandegrift</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>NC State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>mlvandeg@ncsu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Micah Vandegrift’s research focuses on the evolution of research policies
                            and technologies that maximize the dissemination and impact of publicly
                            engaged scholarship. Specifically, he is developing a concept of <title
                                rend="quotes">translation</title> as a form of scholarly
                            communication, and exploring evaluation of new forms of scholarly
                            output. As NC State University Libraries first Open Knowledge Librarian,
                            Micah is dedicated to building programs and processes for the research
                            and learning community to embrace a more open scholarly praxis. He is
                            the lead Principal Investigator for <title rend="italic">Visualizing
                                Digital Scholarship in Libraries and Learning Spaces</title>
                            (Immersive Scholar) funded by a grant from the Andrew W. Mellon
                            Foundation, and studied open science policy and infrastructure in The
                            Netherlands and Denmark as a Fulbright-Schuman Research Fellow in
                            2018-2019.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000416</idno>
                <idno type="volume">013</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2019-08-01">01 August 2019</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="GP" when="2019-04-22">c/e started and completed except for author info and
                missing citations</change>
            <change who="CC" when="2019-08-11">Grammatical edits</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p/>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Introduction to a special issue of DHQ on <term>Invisible Labor</term></p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Two Days in Tallahassee: Articulating New Grounds for a Recurring Set of
                    Problems</head>
                <p>Beginning in 2015, a group of colleagues in the humanities, information sciences,
                    and libraries at Florida State University met sporadically to talk about their
                    projects, plans, and roadblocks, helping one another ask and answer a range of
                    questions, from critical to technical, without inhibition or judgment. We needed
                    this group, for the immediate and quotidian challenges for faculty pressed with
                    meeting wide-ranging institutional duties, working within balkanized
                    departments, and managing projects without explicit digital humanities
                    programming, had masked a significant yet invisible roadblock to getting our
                    projects done. The absence of a sustainable infrastructure — intellectual,
                    physical, temporal, and human — emerged more than once as the underlying
                    problem, a form of institutional invisibility always acting against our
                    interests and activities in the digital humanities. </p>
                <p>Six months later, <soCalled>invisibility</soCalled> emerged again during a
                    meeting of the <ref
                        target="https://digitalscholars.wordpress.com/2016/01/12/730/">Digital
                        Scholars Reading &amp; Discussion Group</ref>, where we were all in
                    attendance, this time to consider discussions from the prior year surrounding
                    the boycott of academia.edu, various instances of cybercolonialism, and building
                    repository environments — all topics that texturized the need for large public
                    research universities like our own to understand and practice the digital
                    humanities as a way of critically questioning our working philosophies. It
                    became clear that <soCalled>invisibility</soCalled> was not a simple matter of
                    demanding more recognition in a particular context, but rather a key term in our
                    university ecosystem, and a problem of vital significance for the sustainability
                    of DH. </p>
                <p>In November 2016, we hosted the first symposium in our region on <title
                        rend="quotes">Invisible Work in the Digital Humanities (IWDH)</title>, based
                    on an awareness of the challenges that resource-straitened campuses face as they
                    struggle to build and maintain the collaborative infrastructures necessary to
                    sustain DH work as a humanistic endeavor <ptr target="#voss2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#shirazi2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#wernimont2013"/>. Fifty attendees from colleges, universities,
                    libraries, and/or DH centers in Florida, North Carolina, Alabama, and Georgia —
                    along with <ref target="http://iwdh.cci.fsu.edu/speakers/">three keynote
                        speakers</ref> from across the United States — convened at Florida State
                    University on November 17-18, 2016 to talk, listen, reflect, apply, and begin
                    taking action toward starting or sustaining healthier DH partnerships on their
                    own campuses or in their own locales. The resulting <ref
                        target="http://iwdh.cci.fsu.edu/schedule/">two-day symposium</ref> helped us
                    identify the unspoken assumptions that surround collaboration by exploring <ref
                        target="http://iwdh.cci.fsu.edu/themes/">questions about diverging
                        expectations, unequal labor, and invisible work</ref>. Our first keynote,
                    Mark Algee-Hewitt, Assistant Professor of English and co-Associate Research
                    Director of the Stanford Literary Lab, challenged the group to consider its
                    underlying assumptions about collaboration. Our second keynote, Cheryl Ball,
                    then Associate Professor of digital publishing studies at West Virginia
                    University, presented alternative notions of un/equal labor by examining the
                    rigors of online peer-review through a disciplinary lens. Finally, our third
                    keynote, Roxanne Shirazi, dissertation and digital research librarian at the
                    CUNY Graduate Center, interrogated visibility as a guiding concept for achieving
                    equitable work, asking us instead to adapt a documentary impulse. The Symposium
                    organizers, along with a cadre of volunteer graduate students, librarians, and
                    faculty, moderated and took notes during the various small-group and large-group
                    sessions each day.</p>
                <p>Our goal in designing and conducting this Symposium was to explore the hypothesis
                    that Digital Humanities projects involving content specialists and scholars
                    working with digital experts and technologists, frequently proceed under the
                    assumption that the collaborators share common goals; yet this is not always
                    true. For example, in a typical project between a professor of history and a
                    university digital scholarship center, does the digital scholarship center
                    simply provide a service, or are they considered equal partners in the work? Do
                    both partners necessarily share common expectations or goals, or do they have
                    conflicting desires that could influence the outcomes of the project? The
                    historian might be focused on building an online repository, and the impact of
                    such a repository on the field, how others might add to it, and how to
                    materialize several years’ worth of research that would otherwise go unmeasured,
                    while the digital scholarship center might be thinking about recycling the
                    resulting code for use in other projects, contributing to broader digital
                    scholarly efforts beyond that single project. On the surface, none of these
                    goals is inherently contradictory, but in practice, subtle differences emerge
                    that may influence (or stymie) these partnerships when they go unnoticed. </p>
                <p>Articulating these issues for DH scholars, researchers, and professionals is
                    critical for identifying and thinking carefully about the invisible work
                    underlying their projects, yet it seemed to be a topic that received little
                    explicit attention in our curriculum, our journals, and our seminars, outside of
                    discussions of student labor. Over those two days in Tallahassee, several common
                    factors emerged, pointing to what we now recognize as a predictable set of
                    institutional, disciplinary, and epistemic tensions that helped guide the
                    creation of this special issue: <list>
                        <item>problems associated with prioritizing external over internal
                            validation of DH projects <ptr target="#ball2017"/>
                            <ptr target="#brennan2016"/>
                            <ptr target="#hsu2016"/>
                            <ptr target="#ball2015"/>
                            <ptr target="#waltzer2013"/>; </item>
                        <item>problems resulting from relying on <soCalled>DH</soCalled> as an
                            umbrage or umbrella term <ptr target="#jones2016"/>
                            <ptr target="#fiormonte2016"/>
                            <ptr target="#wattrall2016"/>
                            <ptr target="#underwood2016"/>; </item>
                        <item>problems associated with making inclusion or agency the ultimate goals
                            of the Digital Humanities <ptr target="#earhart2016"/>
                            <ptr target="#risam2016"/>
                            <ptr target="#binder2016"/>
                            <ptr target="#duarte2015"/>
                            <ptr target="#fiormonte2015"/>
                            <ptr target="#risam2015"/>
                            <ptr target="#gil2014"/>; and </item>
                        <item>problems resulting from flattening disciplinary distinctions within DH
                            work <ptr target="#robertson2016"/>
                            <ptr target="#senchyne2016"/>.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>While Symposium participants represented a range of institutional types, we
                    consider these challenges primarily in the face of innovating — and then
                    sustaining critical innovation in — the digital humanities on public
                    research-intensive and -extensive campuses, when those campuses operate under a
                    dual deficit of resources and knowledge, delivered through austerity measures
                    determined by their states. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Critical Factors in In/Visibility</head>
                <p>The conversations that occurred over these two days demonstrated to us that our
                    experiences with in/visibility prior to the Symposium had been determined by its
                    use as a binary construct, if not a standpoint. (See, for example <ptr
                        target="#losh2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#mcgrail2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#spiro2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#nowviskie2011"/>. While not all of these discussions are motivated
                    by explicit complaints about in/visibility, their recurrence points to
                    visibility as a fundamental intertext in the enactment of digital humanities as
                    a discipline, and moreover as a problem of identification to scale.) Our desire
                    to identify alternative standpoints through the Symposium resulted in the
                    discovery of four paradoxes we face frequently in our work:</p>
                <div>
                    <head>How do we achieve internal validation without promoting utopian visions of
                        DH?</head>
                    <p>One of the essential questions that emerged for us was, To whom is this work
                        in/visible? Much of the work that takes place in DH projects is invisible to
                        multiple levels of authority, both external to the academy (i.e., the
                        public, state legislatures) and internal (i.e., Department Chairs, Deans,
                        Provosts). This occurs on all scales and even to varying degrees in
                        para-institutional publications, for example, in the coverage of
                            <soCalled>labor</soCalled> as a critical topic in discussions in <ref
                            target="http://hybridpedagogy.org/?s=labor">Hybrid Pedagogy</ref>, as
                        well as a special issue of <ref
                            target="http://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/issue/view/590/showToc"
                            >First Monday</ref> dedicated to <q>Feminist Perspectives on Digital
                            Labor</q>. Clearly there are ample institutional practices, ossified
                        academic hierarchies, and individual ways of thinking within different
                        academic roles and communities that contribute to making work that is
                        perfectly valuable seem perfectly invisible, and we must work against such
                        visible flattening. As Kathleen Fitzpatrick writes, <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#fitzpatrick2012">We in the humanities
                                often resist opening our work to these publics, fearing the
                                consequences of such openness…keeping our conversations private,
                                might protect us from public criticism, but it can’t protect us from
                                public apathy, a condition that is, in the current economy, far more
                                dangerous</quote>
                            <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2012"/>
                        </cit>. </p>
                    <p>However, we risk creating a kind of circularity to our discussion if we
                        always (or only) privilege invisibilities or labor practices that can be
                        solved by external validation, such as not knowing when enough recognition
                        is enough, not knowing whether there is enough credit and compensation to go
                        around, or now knowing how much of that compensation is in the hands of
                        people, institutions, or systems that are <quote rend="inline">not
                            us.</quote> Moreover, if we are concerned only with making invisible
                        work visible to external validators, we risk invalidating humanities
                        research entirely, in moves analogous to saying that the humanities matter
                        only in terms of helping STEM students become more well-rounded. We learned
                        through the Symposium that perhaps increasing transparency in DH projects
                        requires a decoupling of transparency from external validation, a recoupling
                        of transparency with internally validated assumptions, and then moving
                        beyond notions of validation as credit. </p>
                    <p>The problem of invisibility is at its core a problem of validation, where the
                        goal of visibility exists principally to make it easier to validate the
                        internal work of the DH participants. Even then, having decoupled
                        transparency from external validation, we must not, a priori, take any of
                        our activities as an unalloyed good. In a utopian vision of DH, one might
                        imagine that if we all received credit for our work, and if institutions
                        recognized and supported all the parties who worked on a DH project, then
                        all would be well. Indeed, there is much to be said and done to advance
                        those goals. But among other general concerns, saying that <quote
                            rend="inline">all DH work is by nature collaborative and thus
                            democratically realized</quote> may undercut some good work that needs
                        to be singly authored or individually completed. </p>
                    <p>Similarly, we may not all want the same things, the same rewards, or the same
                        types of credit. The utopian vision of DH as an ideally collaborative and
                        public activity makes some activities resistant to necessary criticism and
                        questioning. Thus, another reality that emerged during the Symposium was the
                        affirmation that not all DH projects need a lot of hands; often what they
                        need is more time — a commodity for which we can and should collaboratively
                        argue even when our projects have disparate goals. While such fractures in
                        the utopian vision of DH may seem threatening, we argue that they are a
                        useful interpretive lever which can expose the complexities of invisibility
                        in practice. For example, Cheryl Ball’s presentation on the evolution of the
                        open-access platform for the journal Kairos gave us options for imagining
                        how to translate that kind of work into rigorous evaluation tools/measures,
                        adaptable to other local or institutional contexts, for defining scalable
                        levels of involvement, and for accounting for different levels of
                        contribution on our reporting mechanisms, such as curriculum vitae. In other
                        words, Ball argued, we have much to gain by observing the processes of
                        activist collectives such as Kairos journal that serve open-access
                        communities while also preserving the values and ethics of particular
                        scholarly groups or disciplines. While the volunteering and mentoring models
                        underscoring Kairos journal were already reflected in the disciplinary
                        ideals of Rhetoric and Writing Studies, other disciplines may support
                        epistemologies or value systems that give us various opportunities for
                        acting visibly in DH — and thus, for transforming how we think about
                        transparency — by promoting shifts in perspective in other areas of the
                        university (e.g., research, service, and infrastructure), and by scaffolding
                        our DH projects so that they necessarily involve short- and long-term
                        training.</p>
                    <p>While Symposium discussions reflected the fact that material and technical
                        access are recurring problems across United States institutions, we
                        acknowledge that internal validation isn’t always (or exclusively) obtained
                        through idyllic notions of access, unless and until we can enable the
                        transformative nature of access as an internal goal. Doing so requires
                        thinking innovatively about how to commodify our processes and not merely
                        our projects or products for outside groups. Transformed notions of access
                        would open up spaces for rewriting involvement, for responding
                        humanistically to the market forces driving our universities, and for
                        carving out institutional positionings for our work that supersede the
                        material advantages often associated (correctly or incorrectly) with DH
                        initiatives. Transforming the nature of access also involves increasing
                        transparency of motives and goals, affirming the differences among them, and
                        defining our working communities beyond the question of who has principal
                        control over certain kinds of credit.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>How do we achieve a collaborative vocabulary for DH without letting the
                            <soCalled>Digital Humanities</soCalled> limit us?</head>
                    <p>Another essential question that emerged for us through the Symposium was, How
                        much are our problems of visibility caused by our moniker? As expected, the
                        variety of people, professions, and perspectives represented at the
                        symposium highlighted the multiplicity of definitions of Digital Humanities
                        under which we function. In some respects, <soCalled>big tent</soCalled>
                        metaphors have served the scholarly community well, establishing a
                        supra-discipline and welcoming all comers <ptr target="#wattrall2016"/>
                        <ptr target="#ridge2014"/>
                        <ptr target="#reid2013"/>. However, the big-tent paradigm may prevent
                        campuses like ours from being able to conceive of the uniquely collaborative
                        nature of the DH Laboratory both as a collective and as a group of
                        individuals. Moreover, implying the desire to name the digital humanities as
                        if it were a coherent shibboleth, rather than a set of extant and
                        contrasting methodologies, creates a stultifying vision of what DH could or
                        should be, diverting our attention from how DH can promote transformative
                        notions of access in the immediate and near future <ptr
                            target="#battles2016"/>. While definitions of DH have, often with good
                        reason, sought to situate DH in contrast to existing methods, it is equally
                        important to emphasize the continuity of humanistic modes of interrogation. </p>
                    <p>Thus, we take as a starting point the assertion that DH work is first and
                        foremost work in the humanistic tradition — the selfsame tradition that may
                        enable us to resist being defined by what we are not. It is a question of
                        humanistic thinking to ask what we value preserving, documenting, and doing
                        the work. It is also a question of humanistic method to ask corresponding
                        questions about practice. In contrast, defining DH work by what it is not
                        (i.e., the <soCalled>traditional</soCalled> print-based humanities, the
                        completion of singly-authored work) or what it aspires to be (i.e.,
                            <soCalled>empirical</soCalled> or <soCalled>data-driven</soCalled>,
                        following several lab-based sciences) has the unfortunate consequence of
                        locking us into well-worn modes of thinking about both methods and practice.
                        In that particular fantasy of the field, traditional humanities disciplines
                        might be typecast as the lone scholar toiling in the library, and
                        collaboration becomes a counterbalancing virtue of DH work <ptr
                            target="#ridge2014"/>
                        <ptr target="#anderson2016"/>. In contrast, the science/lab model of the
                        hard sciences, including conventions of generous co-authoring, would become
                        a similarly typecast hero-subject <ptr target="#keralis2016"/>
                        <ptr target="#nowviskie2011"/>. Instead, we hope to complicate this binarism
                        altogether, so as to separate out recognizable ideals from harmful truisms. </p>
                    <p>Mark Algee-Hewitt’s presentation on the nuances of the digital humanities
                        collective afforded us different perspectives between and among the roles we
                        typically name in our project teams, by articulating connections between our
                        humanities economy within the institution and the larger digital economy we
                        share with other institutions. Recommending <quote rend="inline"
                            >collaborative individualism</quote> over <quote rend="inline">mere
                            individuals collaborating</quote>, Algee-Hewitt drew on his experiences
                        in the Stanford Literary Lab to illuminate the terministic constraints with
                        certain professional roles when they fall under the DH moniker, and to share
                        his observations about who might be more focused on output as a standalone
                        product, and whose contributions to the projects are often overlooked or
                        take divergent forms that are undervalued in an academic context. What
                        emerged from his keynote presentation was this triad of intellectual
                        conditions: the need for individual goals to be brought to bear on a common
                        set of problems; the need to determine the points at which the individual
                        nature of specifically humanities research becomes at odds with the
                        cooperation that is necessary for most DH projects; and the knowledge of how
                        to respond when that is the case. </p>
                    <p>If the Symposium exposed anything to its participants, it exposed the
                        elusivity of some of our familiar working terms. Without a shared vocabulary
                        in place, we could not always make progress towards practical solutions in
                        the space of our conversations over two days. In addition to the nuances of
                            <soCalled>in/visibility</soCalled>, we found we needed more neutrality
                        in other terms, including <soCalled>service</soCalled> and <soCalled>sole
                            author</soCalled>. In the case of the former, recognizing the inherent
                        flexibility in what it means <soCalled>to serve</soCalled> exposes the more
                        expansive view we must take towards notions like <soCalled>rigor</soCalled>
                        and <soCalled>ethics</soCalled>. In the case of the latter, single-authored
                        work has historically been built on the work of others, whether acknowledged
                        or not. Thus, a more expansive notion of <soCalled>DH
                            collaboration</soCalled> would focus not on the existing conventions of
                        marking collaboration but rather on identifying and exercising a generosity
                        of spirit in academic work.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>How do we define critical agency for DH research while questioning shared
                        credit as an end goal?</head>
                    <p>A third essential question that emerged through the Symposium was, How does
                        our approach change when we acknowledge that while some forms of labor and
                        laboring bodies are deliberately overlooked by those in power, others are
                        made more vulnerable by greater exposure? More problematic than
                            <soCalled>collaboration</soCalled> for many Symposium participants was
                        the notion of <soCalled>credit</soCalled>, as credit can occur in multiple
                        forms (monetary, reputation, public acknowledgment, private acknowledgment),
                        yet without yielding participatory agency. Reifying credit in existing
                        academic structures — or, rather, in the presumption of a shared
                        understanding of what constitutes credit — makes it too easy to speak past
                        each other about what constitutes the value of work. </p>
                    <p>While we agree that credit should be discussed or assigned in the early
                        stages of DH projects and processes, we also acknowledge that it may not or
                        need not always be equal. The Symposium revealed that equal partnerships
                        rely less on equal credit and more on an open communication of goals and on
                        an understanding of cash vs. cache — that is, an understanding that equality
                        may be determined not in precisely the same outcomes for each participant,
                        but each participant should still have access to what they need, whether
                        that is in financial compensation (cash) or in project stakes (cache). Put
                        simply, there are types of credit which are often overlooked in a too-rigid
                        framework of credit equals pay or prestige. It might be more important to
                        have ongoing responsibility for a work, or rights to modify a work, than to
                        have public visibility about one’s past contribution or to have continued
                        ownership of it. Reframing the question of credit as a question of epistemic
                        agency <ptr target="#fricker2007"/> — as a way of validating others as
                        knowers, and validating their right to know — transforms the shared goal
                        from developing a precise system of attribution to recognizing the agential
                        labors through documenting work and telling the story that we want to tell. </p>
                    <p>Roxanne Shirazi’s presentation on the labor activities required by truly
                        innovative historical recovery projects challenged us to become less <quote
                            rend="inline">obsessed with consumer product thinking</quote> and more
                        willing to embrace the processes required by shared emotional labor. Drawing
                        on the work of Lewis Hine and Dorothea Lange, and arguing through the lens
                        of Arlene Daniels’ article on <soCalled>Invisible Work</soCalled>, Shirazi
                        articulated a key critical distinction between invisible work and invisible
                        worker, suggesting a four-part matrix for DH collaborative teams to use in
                        complicating their values before determining value: visible valued; visible
                        devalued; invisible devalued; and invisible valued. These interplays, as
                        Shirazi called them, should give digital humanists a clearer sense of what
                        problems to scale in their particular projects. They should further
                        demonstrate to digital humanists that not only does in/visibility not have
                        to operate as a negative binary construct in relational work between
                        librarians and their multiple collaborators, in some cases it can provide
                        critical leverage by enabling other forms of recognition, remuneration, or
                        autonomy. The balance between these interplays is fluid, requiring digital
                        humanists to think creatively and strategically about the spaces in and
                        through which they work, before determining that visibility must occur in
                        the same way for all project participants, or that invisibility is solved
                        wholly through shared attribution. </p>
                    <p>Provoking us to consider positive invisibility and guarded professionalism,
                        Shirazi ultimately challenged Symposium participants to take up a
                        documentary impulse instead. Thus, our end goal was not the foregone
                        conclusion that everyone needs more credit, but rather the question of how
                        disciplines value and preserve their labor, and what interventions could be
                        made in those values. What is at stake in valuing particular work in
                        particular ways? How do we negotiate the values of differing stakeholders?
                        What have we, in the past, chosen to preserve about our methods or about the
                        process of doing scholarship? Many participants in the room recognized the
                        problem with only using DH to produce a highly equitable labor model. Should
                        some invisible work remain invisible? Should other work be made more (if not
                        totally) visible? What kinds of invisible relationships do we assume or
                        perpetuate when using proprietary tools to do our work, without raising
                        public expectations of us and of our work? Could there be nuanced
                        distinctions between invisible and unseen work (i.e., work that is
                        behind-the-scenes but traceable as opposed to work that has been put under
                        erasure)? It became apparent during and after the Symposium that we need not
                        only decide that visibility occurs through attribution, or that all
                        attribution necessarily increases visibility, or that DH’s main task is to
                        resist the erasure of attribution structures. That kind of accounting
                        procedure — even to one another — does not advance ultimately what we are
                        after, which is the advancement of knowledge and scholarship. We became
                        interested during the Symposium in how we might use DH to articulate and
                        propagate a critique of such labor economies inasmuch as those critiques led
                        us to realize other potential mindsets.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>How do we achieve legibility without flattening disciplinary distinctions? </head>
                    <p>For many researchers and practitioners, the digital humanities are one place
                        where their discipline’s methodologies can best perform or make a critical
                        contribution. Conversely, for many disciplines, it is digital humanities
                        projects that effectively make their critical questions publicly accessible
                        or make their disciplinary approaches more textured. Conflating terms and
                        minimizing disciplinary distinctions may be holding us back from the most
                        compelling reasons why DH matters. At the Symposium, considering invisible
                        work from an ecosystemic perspective brought into deeper relief the
                        relationship between two conflated terms: visibility and value. As Shirazi
                        argued, instead of visibility, we might work toward legibility through a
                        renewed attention to documentation and to the everyday tasks of
                        recordkeeping. </p>
                    <p>The Symposium’s discussions of the critical value of legibility led two
                        participants — Will Hanley and Laurie M. Wood — to reflect on the
                        particularities of their discipline of History.<note>Our expansion on this
                            question of epistemic legibility would not be possible without the
                            significant contributions — written and otherwise — of Will Hanley and
                            Laurie M. Wood, not only during the IWDH Symposium, but also in
                            conversations preceding and following the event. We are grateful to
                            Hanley and Wood for allowing us use of this anecdote and acknowledge
                            their significant work in digital historical methods and archival
                            reconstruction, respectively.</note> The argument they make about
                        collaborative dis/appearances in History seemed important if largely
                        unvoiced at the Symposium, and its importance became easier to discern by
                        the end of the second day. As Hanley and Wood point out, the problem of
                        uncredited (hence invisible) work by collaborators and assistants is
                        somewhat remote, because the workstyle of their discipline is deeply
                        individualist, causing most historians to do their research, analysis, and
                        writing alone. However, their digital historical work involves a different
                        form of invisibility and a different set of consequences that occur when DH
                        paradigms overlay the historical. One consequence of digital history is
                        that, because historians rarely articulate the details of their work
                        process, they are impaired when they wish to share their labor, document
                        their efforts, or show others (i.e., potential research assistants) what
                        they want to do. To assign a research assistant requires, as a first step,
                        that the historian make visible the methods he or she already has in play,
                        but when it comes time to enlist librarians, archivists, graduate students,
                        or even other historians as collaborators, the invisibility of their work
                        becomes an encumbrance because they have difficulty trusting others to do
                        it. If they are not practiced in articulating their approach in ways that
                        can be reproduced by others, then relying on intuition and experience might
                        fail them when the moment comes to collaborate. This raises questions about
                        how and when to delegate work that historians would otherwise complete
                        alone, over lengthy periods of time, and informed by their particular
                        specialties. </p>
                    <p>Another consequence is that, because a historian’s labors are often made
                        invisible by the writing, much of their own work disappears in the
                        redistribution of digital labor. Historians generate a great deal of what
                        Michael Polczynski and Amy Singer have called the <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#polczynksi">intermediate product</quote>, or the research
                        materials they produce between the archival records they read and the books
                        and essays they write — notes and indexes informed by years of concentrated
                        study. These notes and indexes are typically idiosyncratic and impenetrable,
                        and thus lost to other researchers. More importantly, they are not always
                        central to the digital tool. Because the intermediate product is not
                        documented and reproducible, it gets discarded and the work must be repeated
                        by other individuals in their own idiosyncratic manners later on. This
                        outcome seems ironic in a discipline so deeply invested in empiricism, where
                        one promise of digital approaches is the opportunity for historians to
                        become more explicit and articulate about their methodology. </p>
                    <p>Here, Hanley’s and Wood’s concerns about in/visibility are twofold. First,
                        they are concerned with identifying methods (already in use or created for
                        the task) that can be explained simply to collaborators who may or may not
                        already have the needed research competencies, such as with languages or
                        metadata. Second, supervising historians want to ensure that research
                        assistants gain new or improved research competencies, which they can deploy
                        (again) in the individual mode of historical scholarship. Again, the
                        historian has to articulate the necessary skills and methods, which more
                        often remain tacit, but by entrusting the work of historical research to
                        graduate students, empirical methods may inadvertently change. False
                        cognates might be translated incorrectly for the index, or the student may
                        still be learning how to distinguish unreliable from reliable sources and
                        how to replicate complicated workflows. </p>
                    <p>Though specific to their discipline, Hanley’s and Wood’s uptake of
                            <soCalled>intermediate products</soCalled> allowed us to consider that,
                        while recognizing invisible work can be a provocative methodological path,
                        it is difficult to make all empirical involvements equally visible. This
                        difficulty, in turn, urges us consider the different burdens of diversifying
                        roles and the resulting social labors that become involved in that
                        diversification. It matters whether we think of visibility as inherently
                        valuable and invisibility in academic labor as inherently invaluable.
                        Symposium discussions made clear that those value judgments around such
                        terms can be directly misleading, and that there may be critical and
                        practical value in allowing some labor to remain invisible and aiming
                        instead for making labor legible, if it means unflattening how our own
                        disciplines operate.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Changing In/Visible Mindsets: Offering a Conceptual Framework to Move
                    Forward</head>
                <p>As co-conveners of the Symposium, we encouraged a roughly hewn discourse,
                    recognizing that a binary relationship between visibility and invisibility was
                    not our aim, and neither was a clean resolution to the problem(s) of
                    recognition. Now, we see the intellectual investment of the authors included in
                    this special issue as central to our understanding and expansion of the ideas
                    ignited at the 2016 meeting. In the following seven pieces — five full-length
                    articles describing original research, and two opinion-driven essays on critical
                    terms, perspectives, or mindsets — Shirazi’s documentary impulse echoes
                    throughout, in individual markers of collaborations, project overviews, and
                    inquiries into praxis and theory. Several of the following contributors
                    participated in the Symposium, though several did not, and together their voices
                    reflect work begun in Tallahassee that gestures toward what still needs to be
                    done across our organizational, disciplinary, and professional statuses.</p>
                <p>The issue begins with a position piece, where a call for the interdisciplinary
                    nature of digitally-minded humanistic scholarship is apparent, in Huet, Alteri,
                    and Taylor’s short manifesto <title rend="quotes">A Life on the Hyphen:
                        Balancing Identities as Librarians, Scholars, and Digital
                        Practitioners</title>.Their claim that <quote rend="inline">life on the
                        hyphen...fuels invisible work</quote> recalls discussions from the Symposium
                    that invisibility and un-seenness are not necessarily the same phenomenon, and
                    they argue that apportioning credit does not always overcome the epistemic
                    assumptions determining unequal labor. The authors ask for shared responsibility
                    with raising the visibility of hyphenated practitioners, while recognizing the
                    cultural academic changes this intersectionality will require.</p>
                <p>Community development is a throughline in many pieces that follow. Kasten-Mutkus,
                    Costello, and Chase’s <title rend="quotes">Raising Visibility in the Digital
                        Humanities Landscape: The Open Mic Event at Stony Brook University
                        Libraries,</title> illustrates a reliable model for providing space and time
                    to learn from and with one another. Establishing programmatic approaches for
                    digital humanities work is one path toward broader recognition, and the authors
                    examine their own program for that possibility. Recalling a statement from the
                    Symposium, that there are often <quote rend="inline">radically different
                        concepts of what counts as knowledge production,</quote> this piece shapes
                    the conversation by arguing that investing in the local scholar/practitioner
                    community from a library perspective is productive and generative of/for the
                    digital humanities.</p>
                <p>Also concerned with rethinking DH investments, Opel and Simeone’s <title
                        rend="quotes">The Invisible Work of the Digital Humanities Lab: Preparing
                        Graduate Students for Emergent Intellectual and Professional Work</title>
                    explores the potential that spaces and informal learning offer to sustainable
                    models of how/who works together. In framing what a DH Lab is and does, Opel and
                    Simeone interrogate and return to central questions of who is in in digital
                    humanities and how the field inculcates new members. Focusing on their Stories
                    with Data workshop series, the authors argue the need <quote rend="inline">to
                        produce graduate students who can meaningfully render visible to the public
                        how the academy contributes to [or obfuscates] knowledge production
                        vis-a-vis technology</quote>.</p>
                <p>Shifting our attention from graduate professionalization to undergraduate
                    pedagogy, Rivard, Tilton, and Arnold’s <title rend="quotes">Building Pedagogy
                        into Project Development: Making Data Construction Visible in Digital
                        Projects</title> offers a case study in using a DH method to visualize the
                    labor of a classroom-based project and learning environment. The authors offer
                    three broad strategies for making labor more visible through their experience
                    co-constructing Photogrammar, teasing out the <quote rend="inline">politics of
                        attribution</quote> within the content the project is studying, and the
                    collaborative relationships in the classroom. Throughout their argument, the
                    authors highlight the need to consider a variety of ways that collaborators,
                    especially students, may want or need their labor to be credited or made
                    valuable to their goals, which may not be the same as the goals of the
                    institutional researcher or project team. </p>
                <p>Kelly’s <title rend="quotes">Gaining Access, Gaming Access: Balancing Internal
                        and External Support for Interactive Digital Project</title> offers a brief
                    but critical interlude, using a micro case study of a single teaching experience
                        <quote rend="inline">in order to explore how the oft-invisible policies,
                        procedures, and restrictions shape the way we compose, circulate, and make
                        accessible digitally-native work</quote>. This short essay argues for a
                    logistically-minded approach, emphasizing that hurdles to digital pedagogy can
                    occur in the seemingly mundane, such as limited access to wifi, yet those
                    policies reflect boundaries whose transgression is key for activating critical
                    approaches to our own labor.</p>
                <p>Chesley argues for applying those critical approaches to a hybrid collaborative
                    space in <title rend="quotes">The In/Visible, In/Audible Labor of Digitizing the
                        Public Domain</title> — this time from LibriVox, the public domain audiobook
                    platform and a unique <quote rend="inline">public, volunteer digital humanities
                        project</quote>. The invisibility of this volunteer work <quote
                        rend="inline">is part of the project’s strength and persistence</quote> and
                    resists the generalization that the academy owns all of the digital humanities.
                    Chesley’s inclusion of a citizen-humanities, public service project reveals our
                    utopian biases and divergent expectations toward cultural knowledge production
                    as an academic affair.</p>
                <p>Finally, in <title rend="quotes">Affective Absence: Risks in the
                        Institutionalization of the FemTechNet Archive</title>, Austin details the
                    dual challenge of re-presenting the labor of others in an archival collection,
                    and the risky work of archival institutionalization. Writing against erasure,
                    Austin says, <quote rend="inline">The small tasks of addressing power are
                        frequently unseen, unstated, or fed back through institutional lenses —
                        often resulting in approaches that are sanitized or obscured</quote>. Their
                    essay complicates any easy concept of validation, reminding us that some
                    scholarly activities are not subject to, dependent on, or interested in the
                    credentialing system within which we continue to dwell. </p>
                <p>Thus, a conceptual framework for continued forward motion is threaded within
                    these works. Taken together, these ideas, provocations, and inquiries mirror and
                    refract the conversation that began at Florida State University in 2016.
                    Together, the Symposium on Invisible Work in Digital Humanities and this special
                    issue make the case that:</p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>care is a first, essential collaborative tool;</item>
                    <item>scales of credit and recognition are varied and variable for every
                        individual connected to the work;</item>
                    <item>the documentary impulse is a useful method for beginning to make labor
                        legible;</item>
                    <item>acknowledging a spectrum of <soCalled>works</soCalled> (e.g., volunteer
                        efforts, workflows, and community development) offers an expansive
                        understanding of scholarly activity; and</item>
                    <item>the inherent paradoxes of DH work, often simultaneously
                            <soCalled>collaborative</soCalled> and
                            <soCalled>singly-authored,</soCalled> are a great strength, if also a
                        great challenge.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Our hope is that the discovery and uncovering we attempted through this shared
                    project will illuminate many more curious and careful complexities in the
                    digital humanities and that, as individuals together, we will make, ask, and
                    interpret in new and more open ways.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="anderson2016" label="Anderson 2016">Anderson, K., et al. <title
                        rend="quotes">Student Labour and Training in Digital Humanities</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 10.1 (2016).<ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/1/000233/000233.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/1/000233/000233.html</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ball2017" label="Ball 2017">Ball, C. E. <title rend="quotes">Building
                        a Scholarly Multimedia Publishing Infrastructure</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Journal of Scholarly Publishing</title> 48.2 (2017):
                    99-115.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ball2015" label="Ball and Eyman 2015">Ball, C. E., and Eyman, D.
                        <title rend="quotes">Editorial workflows for multimedia-rich
                        scholarship</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Electronic
                        Publishing</title> 18.4 (2015). <ref
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.3998/3336451.0018.406"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.3998/3336451.0018.406</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="battles2016" label="Battles 2016">Battles, M., and Maizels, M. <title
                        rend="quotes">Collections and/of Data: Art History and the Art Museum in the
                        DH Mode</title>. In M. K. Gold and L. F. Klein (eds), <title rend="italic"
                        >Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016</title>, University of Minnesota
                    Press, Minneapolis (2016).<ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/78"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/78</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="binder2016" label="Binder 2016">Binder, J. M. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Reading: Text Mining, Language Standardization, and the Humanities</title>.
                    In M. K. Gold and L. F. Klein (eds), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities 2016</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2016).
                        <ref target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/69"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/69</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brennan2016" label="Brennan 2016">Brennan, S. A. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Public, First</title>. In M. K. Gold and L. F. Klein (eds), <title
                        rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016</title>, University of
                    Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2016). <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/83"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/83</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="duarte2015" label="Duarte and Belarde-Lewis 2015">Duarte, M. E., and
                    Belarde-Lewis, M. <title rend="quotes">Imagining: Creating Spaces for Indigenous
                        Ontologies</title>, <title rend="italic">Cataloging &amp; Classification
                        Quarterly</title> 53:5-6 (2015): 677-702. <ref
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/01639374.2015.1018396"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/01639374.2015.1018396</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="earhart2016" label="Earhart and Taylor 2016">Earhart, A. E., and
                    Taylor, T. L. <title rend="quotes">Pedagogies of Race: Digital Humanities in the
                        Age of Ferguson</title>.In M. K. Gold and L. F. Klein (eds), <title
                        rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016</title>, University of
                    Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2016). <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/72"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/72</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fiormonte2015" label="Firomonte 2015">Fiormonte, D. <title
                        rend="quotes">Towards Monocultural (Digital) Humanities?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Infolet</title>. Issue 7 (2015).<ref
                        target="https://infolet.it/2015/07/12/monocultural-humanities/"
                        >https://infolet.it/2015/07/12/monocultural-humanities/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fiormonte2016" label="Fiormonte 2016">Fiormonte, D. <title
                        rend="quotes">Toward a Cultural Critique of Digital Humanities</title>. In
                    L. Klein and M. K. Gold (eds.), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities 2016</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2016).
                        <ref target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/86"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/86</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fitzpatrick2012" label="Fitzpatrick 2012">Fitzpatrick, K. <title
                        rend="quotes">Giving It Away: Sharing and the Future of Scholarly
                        Communication</title>.” <title rend="italic">kfitz.info</title> (2012).<ref
                        target="https://kfitz.info/giving-it-away/"
                        >https://kfitz.info/giving-it-away/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fricker2007" label="Fricker 2007">Fricker, M. <title rend="italic"
                        >Epistemic Injustice: Power and the Ethics of Knowing</title>. Oxford and
                    New York: Oxford University Press (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gil2014" label="Gil 2014">Gil, A. <title rend="quotes">The (Digital)
                        Library of Babel</title>. Keynote Address at DH Summer Institute, Victoria,
                    B.C. (2014).<ref target="http://www.elotroalex.com/digital-library-babel/"
                        >http://www.elotroalex.com/digital-library-babel/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hsu2016" label="Hsu 2016">Hsu, W. F. <title rend="quotes">Lessons on
                        Public Humanities from the Civic Sphere</title>. In M. K. Gold and L. F.
                    Klein (eds), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities
                    2016</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2016). <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/75"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/75</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jones2016" label="Jones 2016">Jones, S E. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Emergence of the Digital Humanities (as the Network is Everting)</title>. In
                    M. K. Gold and L. F. Klein (eds), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities 2016</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2016).
                        <ref target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/52"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/52</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="keralis2016" label="Keralis 2016">Keralis, S. D. C. <title
                        rend="quotes">Disrupting Student Labor in the Digital Humanities
                        Classroom</title>. <title rend="italic">Researchanddestroy.net</title>
                        (2016).<ref
                        target="https://researchanddestroy.net/2016/03/18/disrupting-student-labor-in-the-digital-humanities-classroom/"
                        >https://researchanddestroy.net/2016/03/18/disrupting-student-labor-in-the-digital-humanities-classroom/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="losh2016" label="Losh 2016">Losh, E., Wernimont, J., Wexler, L., and
                    Wu, H-A. <title rend="quotes">Putting the Human Back into the Digital
                        Humanities: Feminism, Generosity, and Mess</title>.In M. K. Gold and L. F.
                    Klein (eds), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities
                    2016</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2016). <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/61"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/61</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcgrail2016" label="McGrail 2016">McGrail, A. B. <title>The
                            <soCalled>whole Game</soCalled>: Digital Humanities at Community
                        Colleges</title>. In M. K. Gold and L. F. Klein (eds), <title rend="italic"
                        >Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016</title>, University of Minnesota
                    Press, Minneapolis (2016). <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/53"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/53</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nowviskie2011" label="Nowviskie 2011">Nowviskie, B. <title
                        rend="quotes">Where Credit is Due</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Nowviskie.org</title> (2011).<ref
                        target="http://nowviskie.org/2011/where-credit-is-due/"
                        >http://nowviskie.org/2011/where-credit-is-due/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="polczynski" label="Polcynzski (forthcoming)"><title rend="quotes">The
                        OpenOttoman Initiative and the Challenge of Building an Ottoman
                        Gazetteer</title>. In C. H. Roosevelt (ed.) <title rend="italic">Spatial
                        Webs: Mapping Anatolian Pasts for Research and the Public</title>, Research
                    Center for Anatolian Civilizations, Istanbul (forthcoming).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="reid2013" label="Reid 2013">Reid, A. <title rend="quotes">Graduate
                        Education and the Ethics of the Digital Humanities</title>. In M. K. Gold
                    (ed), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities 2012</title>,
                    University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2013). <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/19"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/19</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ridge2014" label="Ridge 2014">Ridge, M. <title rend="italic"
                        >Crowdsourcing our Cultural Heritage</title>. London: Taylor &amp; Francis
                    (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="risam2015" label="Risam 2015">Risam, R. <title rend="quotes">Beyond
                        the Margins: Intersectionality and the Digital Humanities</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 9.2 (2015). <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/9/2/000208/000208.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/9/2/000208/000208.html</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="risam2016" label="Risam 2016">Risam, R. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Navigating the Global Digital Humanities: Insights from Black
                        Feminism</title>. In M. K. Gold and L. F. Klein (eds), <title rend="italic"
                        >Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016</title>, University of Minnesota
                    Press, Minneapolis (2016). <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/80"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/80</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="robertson2016" label="Robertson 2016">Robertson, S. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Differences between Digital Humanities and Digital
                        History</title>. In M. K. Gold and L. F. Klein (eds), <title rend="italic"
                        >Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016</title>, University of Minnesota
                    Press, Minneapolis (2016). <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/76"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/76</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="senchyne2016" label="Senchyne 2016">Senchyne, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Between Knowledge and Metaknowledge: Shifting Disciplinary Borders in
                        Digital Humanities and Library and Information Studies</title>. In M. K.
                    Gold and L. F. Klein (eds), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities 2016</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2016).
                        <ref target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/81"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/81</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shirazi2014" label="Shirazi 2014">Shirazi, R. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Reproducing the Academy: Librarians and the Question of Service in the
                        Humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">Roxanneshirazi.com</title>
                        (2014).<ref
                        target="https://roxanneshirazi.com/2014/07/15/reproducing-the-academy-librarians-and-the-question-of-service-in-the-digital-humanities/"
                        >https://roxanneshirazi.com/2014/07/15/reproducing-the-academy-librarians-and-the-question-of-service-in-the-digital-humanities/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="spiro2013" label="Spiro 2013">Spiro, L. <title rend="quotes">This Is
                        Why We Fight: Defining the Values of the Digital Humanities</title>. In M.
                    K. Gold (ed), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities
                        2012</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2013). <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/13"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/13</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="underwood2016" label="Underwood 2016">Underwood, T. <title
                        rend="quotes">Hold on Loosely, or Gemeinschaft and Gesellschaft on the
                        Web</title>. In M. K. Gold and L. F. Klein (eds), <title rend="italic"
                        >Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016</title>, University of Minnesota
                    Press, Minneapolis (2016). <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/92"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/92</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="voss2015" label="Voss 2015">Voss, J., Wolfenstein, G., and Young, K.
                        <title rend="quotes">From Crowdsourcing to Knowledge Communities: Creating
                        Meaningful Scholarship through Digital Collaboration</title>. In N. Proctor
                    N. and R. Cherry (eds), <title rend="italic">Museums and the Web 2015</title>.
                    Silver Spring, MD: Museums and the Web (2015). <ref
                        target="http://mw2015.museumsandtheweb.com/paper/from-crowdsourcing-to-knowledge-communities-creating-meaningful-scholarship-through-digital-collaboration/"
                        >http://mw2015.museumsandtheweb.com/paper/from-crowdsourcing-to-knowledge-communities-creating-meaningful-scholarship-through-digital-collaboration/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="waltzer2013" label="Waltzer 2013">Waltzer, L. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Digital Humanities and the <soCalled>Ugly Stepchildren</soCalled> of
                        American Higher Education</title>. In M. K. Gold (ed), <title rend="italic"
                        >Debates in the Digital Humanities 2012</title>, University of Minnesota
                    Press, Minneapolis (2013). <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/33"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/33</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wattrall2016" label="Watrall 2016">Watrall, E. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Archaeology, the Digital Humanities, and the <soCalled>Big
                        Tent</soCalled></title>. In M. K. Gold and L. F. Klein (eds), Debates in the
                    Digital Humanities 2016, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2016). <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/79"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/79</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wernimont2013" label="Wernimont 2013">Wernimont, J. <title
                        rend="quotes">Whence Feminism? Assessing Feminist Interventions in Digital
                        Literary Archives</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</title> 7.1 (2013). <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/7/1/000156/000156.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/7/1/000156/000156.html</ref>
                </bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
