<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
	xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
	xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
	xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
				<title type="article" xml:lang="en">The Stories
					We Tell: Project Narratives, Project Endings, and the Affective Value of
					Collaboration</title>
				
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					
					<dhq:author_name>Claire <dhq:family>Battershill</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3712-5865</idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>University of Toronto</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>claire.battershill@utoronto.ca</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Claire Battershill is an Assistant Professor in the Faculty of Information and the Department of English at the University of Toronto and a Fellow at Victoria College. She is the author of a collection of short stories, <title rend="italic">Circus</title> (McClelland &amp; Stewart, 2014); two academic monographs, <title rend="italic">Modernist Lives: Biography and Autobiography at Virginia and Leonard Woolf's Hogarth Press</title> (Bloomsbury, 2018) and <title rend="italic">Women and Letterpress Printing 1920-2020: Gendered Impressions</title> (Cambridge University Press, 2022); two collaboratively written academic books (<title rend="italic">Scholarly Adventures in Digital Humanities</title>, Palgrave, 2017, and <title rend="italic">Using Digital Humanities in the Classroom</title>, Bloomsbury, 2017 (revised second edition, 2022)); and is a co-director of the Modernist Archives Publishing Project (MAPP).</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
				<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
				<!--This information will be completed at publication-->
				<idno type="DHQarticle-id"
					><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000665</idno>
				<idno type="volume"
					>017<!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
				<idno type="issue">1<!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
				<date when="2023-05-26">26 May 2023</date>
				<dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
				<availability status="CC-BY-ND">
					
					<cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Article written by Claire Battershill for the special issue on Project Resiliency. The papers in this special issue were first presented at a symposium organized by the Endings Project team at the University of Victoria.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
					<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en" extent="original"/>
				
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
					
					<list type="simple">
						<item>digital humanities</item>
						<item>literary studies</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
					
					<list type="simple">
						<item>project resiliency</item>
						<item>collaboration</item>
						<item>project management</item>
						<item>ethics</item>
						<item>literary studies</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
					<list type="simple"/>
						
					</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
					target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000665/000665.xml"
					>GitHub </ref>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en" type="original">
		<front>
			<dhq:abstract>
				<p>This paper considers the the affective and narrative dimensions of
					considering project lifespans. How do collaborators feel about endings and
					how does that impact project outcomes and project planning? How might we
					consider digital projects as temporal and narrative forms deserving of
					analysis? How do professional relationships, team dynamics, and precarious
					labour conditions impact the longevity of projects? I argue in this paper
					that in addition to thoughtful sustainability planning on the technical
					side, there is value in thinking from a literary perspective about digital
					humanities projects, about the stories and relationships we are making
					along with the websites, digital archives, databases, tools, marked-up
					texts, maps, and innumerable other digital artifacts that arise from
					large-scale collaborations in this field. The provocation I offer is that
					applying some of the discursive analytical structures of literary genres to
					the construction of a digital project and foregrounding its human
					components of affect and relation can also show a team its ideal duration
					and ending. Thinking about these matters requires a multi-dimensional
					approach: we need to think beyond institutional repositories and mirror
					sites and consider the lived experience of project making and about the
					structure of the stories we tell about digital work. The paper uses
					examples from two collaborative projects of different types and durations
					that I have undertaken. </p>
			</dhq:abstract>
			<dhq:teaser>
				
				<p>Digital projects as temporal and narrative forms</p>
			</dhq:teaser>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div>
				
			<head></head>
			<p>In a story beloved by many kindergarteners, <title rend="italic">We are in a Book!</title>, by Mo Willems,
				early readers are introduced to an Elephant named Gerald and his friend Piggie.
				Gradually, Elephant and Piggie come to the realization that they are in fact
				characters in a book. They peer curiously out of their pages and stare at the
				reader before them. At first the whole situation seems amusing and they play
				games with the reader, exhorting them to say silly words out loud and to turn
				the pages. However, after an initially carefree time joking around about the
				absurdity of narrative, poor Gerald comes to a terrible recognition: that the
				story will come to an end. He proceeds to work his way through a crisis of
				completion, worrying that the ending will come too soon for him to tell his
				story in its fullness. As is the case with many brilliant works of children’s
				literature, a lot of us can probably relate to Gerald. His cartoonish anguish at
				the prospect of an ending is familiar. A lot of academics who begin digital
				humanities projects start out just like this little elephant: enjoying a new way
				of doing scholarly work, relishing the collaborative possibilities that digital
				projects can offer, enjoying good company, and not thinking much about how the
				project will end or even acknowledging, really, that it will inevitably be over
				sooner or later <ptr target="#carlin2018"/>.<note> See <ptr target="#carlin2018"/> for an analysis of
					surveys and interviews of project directors, which indicated that the
					majority of those surveyed had not considered a specific end point for
					their DH project when they began to work on it. </note>
			</p>
			<p>The Endings Project initiative whose work occasioned this cluster of essays and
				the symposium on which they were based is asking those involved in DH projects
				to think deeply on hard questions. DH projects often begin with specific
				scholarly goals in mind, whether these are editorial, theoretical, archival, or
				methodological. When projects begin, all is promise, potential, and excitement.
				The grant funding structure on which many larger projects are founded also
				demands that projects begin with an optimistic view and a future-oriented
				perspective. Until recently, very little in the grant application process, at
				least in the Canadian context, had to do with sustainability.<note> See Jessica
					Otis’s essay in this issue for an analysis of the American context.</note>
				The emergence of data management requirements at the Social Sciences and
				Humanities Research Council (SSHRC), for example, is a relatively recent
				phenomenon, and goes some way to address the open-ended futurity that throughout
				the 2010s was often a hallmark of many DH projects.<note> For the most recent
					information about data management requirements in the Canadian context, see
					<title rend="quotes">Research Data Management.</title> </note> Before such requirements and before the
				Endings Project suggestions, a team dreamt up a vision and created a plan for
				executing it, and it could be difficult both practically and epistemologically
				to think about an ending while constructing a beginning. Even with more
				stringent requirements for sustainability, these projects still begin in
				heightened moments of collegiality, collaboration, and shared vision among
				scholars; they’re premised on new and exciting relationships as much as they are
				on research materials and anticipated scholarly outcomes. By devising this
				innovative and much-needed framework of <q>endings compliance,</q> <ptr target="#endingsprinciples"/> the Endings Project team offers future new projects the opportunity to
				think on their own sustainability from the very start of any DH workflow. The
				Endings project team is also making difficult questions easier by offering a set
				of technical standards that can help emergent projects conceive of their endings
				right from the start without taking the many common missteps (expensive
				technical contracts, unreliable server-side software requiring endless updates)
				that they otherwise might.</p>
			<p>In this paper I’d like to argue that in addition to thoughtful sustainability
				planning on the technical side, there is value in thinking with a literary
				perspective about digital humanities projects, about the stories and
				relationships we are making along with the websites, digital archives,
				databases, tools, marked-up texts, maps, and innumerable other digital artifacts
				that arise from large-scale collaborations in this field. The provocation I
				offer here is that applying some of the discursive analytical structures of
				literary genres to the construction of a digital project and foregrounding its
				human components of affect and relation can also show a team its ideal duration
				and ending. These matters require a multi-dimensional approach: we need to think
				beyond institutional repositories and mirror sites to consider the lived
				experience of project making and the structure of the stories we tell about
				digital work.</p>
			<p>If we think about endings and about projects in a literary sense, we can analyze
				and read digital projects as the creative and multifaceted texts that they are
				and become. We can perhaps approach them with intention and care not only as
				technical artifacts but also as works that we’ve made, often along with a number
				of collaborators. Thinking through stories and endings also necessitates
				thinking about, with, and through time and then about how time manifests in
				projects. Here, too, narratives and genres can be illuminating. Some notable
				projects in my own field of literary modernist studies, The Modernist Journals
				Project <ptr target="#latham2011"/> and The Orlando
				Project, <ptr target="#brown2007"/> have
				decades-long stories involving hundreds of contributors and thousands of
				digitized artifacts. These are the digital humanities <q>epics</q>: they are long,
				they are ambitious, and they carry on sometimes through several generations of
				scholars. They are the kinds of resources that might be almost impossible for
				users ever to know in their totalities. Others, again drawing from modernist
				studies, like the Mina Loy project’s digital <q>flash mob,</q> are momentary. These
				can perhaps be seen as the <q>lyrics</q>: short in duration, beautiful in their
				immediacy, able to be apprehended, perhaps, in a sitting. Is your project more
				like an 800-page Victorian doorstopper, or is it an aphorism? Perhaps even a
				haiku? There might of course be a wide array of other genres to consider: what
				might a digital humanities comedy look like, for instance? In more practical
				terms, how does the project relate to the PI and other collaborators’ own
				academic autobiographies? Will the project span a 35-year academic career and
				beyond, or a semester? Will the collaborators be life-long friends or collegial
				fleeting workplace acquaintances? If you know the type of project you’re making,
				not only in the more practical sense of TEI standards or approaches to
				versioning, but also the more epistemological questions about why this project
				exists and how its story will be shaped, it becomes possible to orient labour
				and personnel and even affective connections to the project <ptr target="#evalyn2020"/> in
				a more intentional fashion that serves a clear purpose and design and, yes, has
				an ending in mind that suits its overall form.</p>
			<p>One of the important points to make about the different possibilities for project
				genres is that they do not all have to be big, or long, or consuming in order to
				make significant contributions. During a panel discussion in the symposium that
				gave rise to this cluster of papers, Jessica Otis and Jim McGrath expressed the
				<q>liberation</q> that they both had individually felt upon creating smaller projects
				<q>for fun</q> that might be completed in <q>a season.</q> These short-duration projects
				contrast with what Otis in her remarks during the discussion identified as the
				tacit expectation in DH of always undertaking <quote rend="inline">huge career shaping long term
				project[s].</quote> Small projects can be beautiful, and they can be freeing.</p>
			<p>Here I’m offering a more general meditation on the matter of project genres, of
				the narrative endings of digital projects, and of the characters involved in the
				stories of DH. However, my remarks are informed by having worked on different
				types of projects in recent years. Two in particular have led me to my thinking
				in this piece: The Modernist Archives Publishing Project (MAPP) (which I would
				consider, in this framework, an epic) and Make Believe: The Secret Library of M.
				Prudhomme (which feels more like a lyric). MAPP is a critical digital archive of
				early 20th-century publishing materials. The project began in 2013 and is
				ongoing. The team consists of six Co-Directors (Nicola Wilson, Alice Staveley,
				Helen Southworth, Elizabeth Willson-Gordon, and Matthew Hannah) who have formed
				friendships through this work. As literary scholars, we have been conscious of
				the need for narrative in the project from the start: we wrote a book together,
				<title rend="italic">Scholarly Adventures in Digital Humanities</title> (2018), that told the scholarly story
				of how the project came to be and of the vision for our field that we wanted to
				realize in making it. We thought a lot about where we would store our images,
				our metadata, and our born-digital content for the long haul. We built in
				deliberate redundancies and we wrote sustainability plans. We thought very
				little, however, about the life of the project as a whole, beyond the digital
				<q>stuff</q> we were creating and beyond the sorts of things that are generally
				considered in technical terms when thinking about digital sustainability. We
				thought very little, in other words, about what it would mean for us personally
				to be five or ten or even fifteen years into a project like this. Like Elephant
				Gerald, we found and still find ourselves a little alarmed at the prospect of
				closing the metaphorical book, and the prospect has become more challenging the
				more our friendships have developed over the years. MAPP’s story has a happy
				continuation: we want to keep this thing going, we have all committed to it, and
				we have agreed that every five years we will reassess. We’ve also created a
				strong network of feminist intergenerational mentorship above and beyond the
				day-to-day requirements of the project. We support each other’s individual
				writing, we talk about our lives outside of work, and we look out for each
				other. We still want to keep this going, because we are having fun. As Sara
				Diamond put it in the discussion following our session at the Endings
				colloquium, <quote rend="inline">The affective bonds that form in creating these kinds of projects
				and archives are a really fundamental piece of the connective tissue and the
				survival [of the projects].</quote> So fundamental that we can imagine, perhaps, that
				we may not in fact need to talk about endings to the affective or relational
				aspects of this kind of project work. Even if a website is no longer in active
				use, friendships and intergenerational mentorships can endure. </p>
			<p>Nowhere was this more true for me than with the Make Believe project, a research
				creation/creative research/historical fiction/conceptual art project and was
				funded by a Canada Council New Chapter Grant 2017-19 and consisted of an
				in-person exhibition that took place over the course of a summer in 2019,
				accompanied by a digital exhibition to supplement the site-specific in-person
				experiences. There were over a hundred artists, writers, students, translators,
				librarians, and others who worked on the project in various capacities, but at
				the core was the intimacy of female friendship. Heather Jessup, Jillian
				Povarchook, and I made the project sitting at each other’s kitchen tables with
				babies in our laps. Heather and I had already been dear friends for many years,
				and the project came out of that friendship rather than the other way round. For
				that project, the ending was built into the project’s story from the start and
				we recognized it when it came: we knew that when we took down the physical
				exhibition from the Vancouver Public Library in August 2019, that was it. It was
				wild and exhausting and wonderful and fleeting, and making it with Heather and
				all of our amazing collaborators opened a little locked door inside me. It felt,
				in other words, like a perfect lyric.</p>
			<p>While I hope the broader ideas in this short essay about the narrative and
				affective dimensions of project work will resonate beyond these two specific and
				personal examples, all of my work and thinking in DH has been informed by the
				sustaining collaborations at the core of each of these very different
					projects.<note> And through the equally rich collaboration on the topic of
					DH pedagogy that I’ve shared for several years now with Shawna Ross.
				</note> In her call to action for a more humane approach to academic work,
				Kathleen Fitzpatrick suggests that <quote rend="inline">Grounding our work in generous thinking
				might […] lead us to place a greater emphasis on — and to attribute a greater
				value to — collaboration in academic life, and to understand how to properly
				credit all our collaborators. It might encourage us to support and value various
				means of working in the open, of sharing our writing at more and earlier stages
				in the process of its development, and of making the results of our research
				more readily accessible and usable by more readers</quote> <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2019" loc="37"/>. Part of this openness,
				I think, can be found in narrating some of these lived experiences. Openness of
				course is not always ideal, and complexity is always attendant on even the most
				fruitful and fulfilling of collaborations: <q>Genuine generosity,</q> Fitzpatrick
				reminds us, <quote rend="inline">is not a feel-good emotion, but an often painful, failure-filled
				process related to what Dominick LaCapra has called ‘empathetic unsettlement,’
				in which we are continually called not just to feel for others but to
				simultaneously acknowledge their irreconcilable otherness</quote> <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2019" loc="42"/>. Lest I seem too
				optimistic about collaboration and its affective rewards, I would like to turn
				now to some of the fears and vulnerabilities that also can attend DH project
				work. As Jim McGrath pointed out in his symposium presentation, <quote rend="inline">actually liking
				your collaborators</quote> is tremendously important, but <quote rend="inline">the challenge is making sure
				our employers are aware of our value/the value of those collaborations.</quote> Too
				often the intangible values of collaborative practice are left out of
				discussions altogether.</p>
			<p>No matter the genre, a digital project begins, and then its life proceeds and gets
				complicated. Of course, as project teams devise digital methods for exploring
				humanistic questions, they are often confronted with challenges and
				opportunities they would not have encountered were they writing a single-author
				monograph or creating a print edition. One such challenge, as the Endings
				Project team acknowledges, is defining the endpoint of the project in a digital
				environment that is by nature iterative and surrounded by a mythology of
				ongoingness and perpetuity. The print publishing process, conversely, naturally
				produces a moment of completion: a book is published and then it is out in the
				world and often that’s the end of the active day-to-day work on that particular
				project (leaving aside the “unfinished” nature of published textual artifacts
				which of course as a book historian I can never really leave aside). The
				developmental arc of the monograph is so well-established at this point that
				we’re used to it; it does not possess the same complexity as discussions of
				digital project endings. Much as the author might wish to continue to revise and
				augment a book after it’s done, the illusory fixity of the printed object at
				least imposes an artificial endpoint on the active work of the project. The
				existence of a physical object can also seem more definitive than any ending a
				digital project might devise or arrange for itself. The milestones in the life
				of a digital project — the launch of a website, say — are often possessed of a
				more malleable quality. One often launches a website with the idea that it will
				change and grow over time. However, the discourses of ongoingness and iteration
				in digital project work, while they do point to a truth about the type of media
				in question, have their limits. The edition release model <note> See <title rend="quotes">Release
					Management</title> in Holmes and Takeda in this volume for details of this
					approach. </note> proposed by the Endings team creates, among other things,
				some narrative closure on particular phases of the project. It allows for the
				satisfaction of completion that is often absent from a more <q>agile</q> approach.
				The edition release also prevents slippage as digital project team members move
				through their careers — from PhD to postdoc to demanding jobs both within and
				outside the academy — and finding space for an ever-expanding and
				ever-continuing digital project within the team members’ individual careers can
				be a further challenge. Grant cycles come to an end, program centres open and
				close, and resources run out. Thinking about the long life of a project is
				twinned with thinking about the long future of an academic career, and even,
				these days, of the discipline.</p>
			<p>One of the major factors that can turn DH practitioners into nervous <q>Elephant
				Geralds,</q> reluctant to engage in future thinking and afraid of endings, is
				precarious labour conditions. These conditions, of course, are not specific to
				DH, nor are they particular to the academic profession, though they are endemic
				in it. Contract faculty now outnumber tenure-track faculty in Canada, and as
				Deidre Rose notes, <quote rend="inline">non-regular faculty constitute a reserve of low-paid and
				marginalized academic workers, and an increase in the number of doctorates
				granted each year in Canada guarantees a continuous supply of highly exploitable
				workers</quote> <ptr target="#rose2020" loc="7"/>. The situation is even worse in the United States,
				as amply documented in scholarly literature and online <ptr target="#childress2019"/>. This of course is not a new problem of capitalist work
				structures, though it is intensifying. In a 1997 talk at a gathering of
				economists in Grenoble, Pierre Bourdieu articulated the affective significance
				of increasing precarity in a capitalist system: <quote rend="inline">casualization,</quote> he writes,
				<quote rend="inline">profoundly affects the person who suffers it: by making the whole future
				uncertain, it prevents all rational anticipation and, in particular, the basic
				belief and hope in the future that one needs in order to rebel, especially
				collectively, against present conditions, even the most intolerable</quote> <ptr target="#bourdieu1998" loc="82"/>. While Bourdieu is speaking in part of the difficulty and even
				danger for precarious workers in engaging in strikes and other labour actions,
				the effect can be more general too: preventing <q>rational anticipation</q> is also
				preventing considered approaches to futurity. Precarious labour conditions,
				Bourdieu suggests, have more than an economic effect: they lead at their most
				extreme to what he describes as <quote rend="inline">the destructuring of existence, which is
				deprived among other things of its temporal structures, and the ensuing
				deterioration of the whole relationship to the world, time and space</quote> <ptr target="#bourdieu1998" loc="82"/>.
				Narrative and endings are so deeply reliant on their connections to and
				structuring of time that any threat to that kind of order is necessarily
				perilous. Precarious conditions threaten to cut stories off before they can even
				begin. </p>
			<p>Here, as in the domain of collaboration, affect becomes crucial to consider in
				thinking about digital projects as whole entities. However, the feelings
				associated with precarity are fearful and vulnerable ones that are more
				difficult to discuss and disclose. These are the tragedies of academia, the
				stories so painful they are hard to tell (although not speaking about them, as
				Bourdieu also notes, does not make them go away). Sometimes, as in my own
				experience through seven years of precarious work, the divergent affective
				dimensions of digital project work can create complexity: the constant fear and
				uncertainty of precarious labour can be counterbalanced by the positive
				collegial and friendly relations that collaborative work can foster. It becomes
				possible to survive precarious conditions with the help of friends, as Gerald
				the Elephant also finds in his sweet and affirming relationship with Piggie. And
				yet, the fear of endings looms large for all precarious workers. How can it be
				possible to plan for a reasonable project ending when doing so requires
				confronting the reality of an uncertain personal future? If we want sustainable
				projects, we need sustainable labour practices.</p>
			<p>In the end, Gerald and Piggie devise a solution to their endings conundrum: they
				ask the reader to start the book again from the beginning, creating an endless
				loop of repetition. Starting again from the beginning would seem like a genuine
				nightmare for most digital project PIs and collaborators and is obviously not an
				advisable sustainability plan, so perhaps this is where the analogy between
				digital projects and the genre of comic children’s literature must end. It
				might, however, still be possible to draw encouragement from Elephant and
				Piggie’s collaboration: they make their way from the first page to the last in
				one another’s good company, finding their way together.</p>
			
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<listBibl>
				<bibl xml:id="researchdata" label="Research Data Management"> <title rend="quotes">Research Data Management</title>, <title rend="italic">Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council</title>,
					Government of Canada. Available at: <ref
						target="https://www.sshrc-crsh.gc.ca/funding-financement/nfrf-fnfr/transformation/research_data_management-gestion_des_donnees_de_recherche-eng.aspx"
						>https://www.sshrc-crsh.gc.ca/funding-financement/nfrf-fnfr/transformation/research_data_management-gestion_des_donnees_de_recherche-eng.aspx</ref>.
				</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="endingsprinciples" label="Endings Principles for Digital Longevity"> <title rend="quotes">Endings Principles for Digital Longevity</title>, <title rend="italic">The Endings Project</title>. Available at: <ref
					target="https://endings.uvic.ca/principles.html"
					>https://endings.uvic.ca/principles.html</ref>.
				</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="bourdieu1998" label="Bourdieu 1998"> Bourdieu, P. 
					(1998). <title rend="quotes">Job Insecurity is Everywhere Now</title>, <title rend="italic">Acts of Resistance: Against the
						New Myths of Our Time</title>. Translated by R. Nice. Polity Press, Cambridge. pp. 81–87.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="brown2007" label="Brown et al. 2007"> Brown, S. et al. (2007) <title rend="quotes">The Story of The Orlando Project: Personal Reflections</title>, <title rend="italic">Tulsa
					Studies in Women’s Literature</title> 26.1 pp. 135–143. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="carlin2018" label="Carlin et al. 2018"> Carlin, Claire et al.  (2018) <title
						rend="quotes">Endings: Concluding, Archiving, and Preserving, Digital
						Projects for Long-Term Usability</title>, <title rend="italic"
						>KULA: Knowledge Creation, Dissemination, and Preservation Studies</title>, 2(1),
					p.19. DOI:<ref target="http://doi.org/10.5334/kula.35">
						http://doi.org/10.5334/kula.35</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="childress2019" label="Childress 2019">Childress, H. (2019) <title rend="italic">The Adjunct Underclass: How America’s Colleges
					Betrayed Their Faculty, Their Students, and Their Mission</title>. University
					of Chicago Press, Chicago.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="evalyn2020" label="Evalyn et al. 2020"> Evalyn, L., et al. (2020) <title rend="quotes">One Loveheart at a Time: The Language of Emoji and the
					Building of Affective Community in the Digital Medieval Studies Environment</title>,
					<title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 14.3. Available at: <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/3/000474/000474.html">http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/3/000474/000474.html</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="fitzpatrick2019" label="Fitzpatrick 2019"> Fitzpatrick, K. (2019) <title rend="italic">Generous Thinking: A Radical Approach to Saving the University</title>.
					Johns Hopkins UP, Baltimore. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="latham2011" label="Latham 2011"> Latham, S. (2011) <title rend="quotes">The Mess and Muddle of Modernism: The Modernist Journals Project and
					Modern Periodical Studies</title>, <title rend="italic">Tulsa Studies in Women’s Literature</title> 30(2), pp.
					407–428. </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="rose2020" label="Rose 2020">Rose, D. (2020). <title rend="quotes">A Snapshot of Precarious Academic Work in Canada</title>, <title rend="italic">New Proposals: Journal of Marxism and Interdisciplinary Inquiry</title> 11(1) (Summer 2020), pp. 7–17.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="willems2010" label="Willems 2010"> Willems, M. (2010) <title rend="italic">We Are in a Book!</title> Hyperion Books, New York
					.</bibl>
			</listBibl>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
