<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt><!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Automatic Identification of Types of Alterations in Historical Manuscripts</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo><!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>David <dhq:family>Lassner</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Technische Universität Berlin</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>lassner@tu-berlin.de</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>N/A</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo><!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Anne <dhq:family>Bailot</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Le Mans Université</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>anne.baillot@univ-lemans.fr</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>N/A</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo><!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Sergej <dhq:family>Dogadov</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Technische Universität Berlin</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>s.dogadov@tu-berlin.de</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>N/A</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo><!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Klaus-Robert <dhq:family>Müller</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Technische Universität Berlin</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>klaus-robert.mueller@tu-berlin.de</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>N/A</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo><!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Shinichi <dhq:family>Nakajima</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Technische Universität Berlin</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>nakajima@tu-berlin.de</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>N/A</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000576</idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->015</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->4</idno>
            <date when="2021-11-12">November 12, 2021</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords"><!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords"><!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc><!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract><!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>Alterations in historical manuscripts such as letters represent a promising field of research. On the one hand, 
               they help understand the construction of text. On the other hand, topics that are being considered sensitive at the 
               time of the manuscript gain coherence and contextuality when taking alterations into account, especially in the case
               of deletions. The analysis of alterations in manuscripts, though, is a traditionally very tedious work. In this paper,
               we present a machine learning-based approach to help categorize alterations in documents. In particular, we present a 
               new probabilistic model (Alteration Latent Dirichlet Allocation, <emph>alterLDA</emph> in the following) that categorizes content-related
               alterations. The method proposed here is developed based on experiments carried out on the digital scholarly edition <title rend="italic">Berlin
               Intellectuals</title>, for which <emph>alterLDA</emph> achieves high performance in the recognition of alterations on labelled data. On unlabelled 
               data, applying <emph>alterLDA</emph> leads to interesting new insights into the alteration behavior of authors, editors and other manuscript
               contributors, as well as insights into sensitive topics in the correspondence of Berlin intellectuals around 1800. In addition
               to the findings based on the digital scholarly edition <title rend="italic">Berlin Intellectuals</title>, we present a general framework for the analysis of 
               text genesis that can be used in the context of other digital resources representing document variants. To that end, we present 
               in detail the methodological steps that are to be followed in order to achieve such results, giving thereby a prime example of 
               an Machine Learning application the Digital Humanities.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser><!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>In this paper,
               we present a machine learning-based approach to help categorize alterations in documents</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
            <div>
            <head>Editorial prolegomenon</head>
            <p>Classical scholarly editing has a long-standing tradition in
                    distinguishing between different types of editions <ptr target="#witkowski1924"/>. The
                    characteristics of specific edition forms usually align with the intended
                    readership, but they also take into account a bibliographic history that tends
                    to differentiate more and more along time according to linguistic areas. In the
                    German-speaking area, historical-critical editions that comprise an extensive
                    historical-critical apparatus are often distinguished - with a clear
                    hierarchical difference - from so-called study editions <ptr target="#plachta2006"/>. The common
                    denominator between these two types of editions is that they aim to offer a
                    <q>reliable text</q> as a central component <ptr target="#plachta2006"/>. In contrast to these types of editions, it
                    is also possible to publish a reproduction of the manuscript image (facsimile
                    edition). Plachta points out, however, that a facsimile edition is no substitute
                    for the above two types of editions <ptr target="#plachta2006"/>.</p>
            <p>Another way of differentiating between types of editions is to
                    compare the intention in the text construction, which corresponds to the
                    philosophy according to which the anglo-saxon area has mainly structured their
                    approach. According to Andrews, <quote rend="inline">the <q>old</q> methods that have their root in
                    classical philology</quote> strive to assemble the <q>ideal</q> text, while the <q>new
                       philology</q> seeks to find the <q>real</q> text <ptr target="#andrews2013"/>. In this conception, the ideal text tries to
                    approach the author's intention, while the real text seeks to emulate the
                    existing sources.</p>
            <p>The type of edition an editor goes for is often defined by
                    economic factors in printed editions, while in digital editions, this limitation
                    can be obsolete in terms of the amount of pages available, or located on a
                    different level (for instance due to the price of specific, cost-expensive
                    technologies). More generally, in digital scholarly editions, differentiation
                    characteristics can be renegotiated. As Andrews states, there are hardly any
                    technical limitations in digital editions with regard to the size of the
                    apparatus, and the number and resolution of facsimiles provided <ptr target="#andrews2013"/>.</p>
            <p>This is not the only specificity that distinguishes digital from
                    print editions. They also are machine-readable. With digital editions being
                    available in digital formats, computers can not only handle repetitive tasks in
                    the creation of the edition <ptr target="#andrews2013"/>, they can also be used to perform tasks that use the
                    edition as source material. The most obvious example for this type of use is the
                    full-text search, but the machine-readable form also allows the creation of a
                    multitude of statistics and customed visualizations with very little effort
               <ptr target="#ralle2016"/>.
                    Furthermore, Ralle emphasizes that the digitization of editions and scholarly
                    editing in general allow to pay special attention to the processual aspects of
                    the edition <ptr target="#ralle2016"/>. An edition can be extended or enriched after it
                        has been initially published and does not need to be <q>finished</q> at a
                        specific moment in time. A digital edition can be modified dynamically, for
                        instance like the Carl-Maria-von-Weber-Gesamtausgabe with a front page field
                        called <title rend="quotes">What happened today?</title> that connects to all instances of the current
                        date in the corpus and highlights them - a content that changes from day to
                        day and offers a different approach to the corpus than the traditional
                        keyword search. Also, user interaction can be funneled back into the
                        edition, for example when subsequent publications that are based on the
                        edition are listed there. Interaction in and of itself can also be included:
                        the search behaviour of users can be analyzed for better future suggestions
                        or the edition can be enriched by third-party data. Every user of a digital
                        edition, whether computer or human, is thus potentially able to engage in
                        one form of editorial participation or the other <ptr target="#schlitz2014"/> <ptr target="#siemens2012"/> <ptr target="#shillingsburg2013"/>.</p>
            <p>These special features of digital
               editions allow for paleography  <ptr target="#baillot2015b"/> to reach out to
                        research questions hence unexplored in the Humanities due to the lack of
                        tools and corpora allowing an automatic evaluation of alteration phenomena.
                        It enables for instance to thoroughly reconstruct the history of a document
                        by considering physical traces of alterations, meaning any smaller or larger
                        text modifications on the manuscript, performed either by the author himself
                        or herself or by others (see Methods). This approach provides insights into
                        the way in which authors, editors and other contributors work together,
                        hence impacting our understanding of text genesis as a collaborative
                        process.</p>
            <p>In order to achieve substantial results
                        in this field of research, fast and well-structured access to the document
                        variants is required. Digital editions presenting the manuscript alterations
                        allow to focus on diplomatic transcription or facsimile, as opposed to print
                        editions where the focus is on a single copy text, itself usually optimized
                        for readability. Examples of digital editions representing the document
                        history include faustedition.net  <ptr target="#goethe2017"/>, bovary.fr <ptr target="#leclerc2009"/>, 
               beckettarchive.org <ptr target="#beckett2011"/> and the edition that provided the
                        background for the methodology we propose here: the digital scholarly
                        edition <title rend="quotes">Letters and texts. Intellectual Berlin around 1800</title>,
               berlinerintellektuelle.eu  <ptr target="#baillot"/>,
                        <title rend="italic">BI</title> in
                        the following. </p>
            </div>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p><title rend="italic">Letters and Texts. Intellectual
                        Berlin around 1800</title> is a digital scholarly
                        edition of manuscripts by men and women writers of the late 18th and early
                        19th
                        century. The connection these writers have to the intellectual networks in
                        the Prussian capital city are either direct (authors living and writing in
                        Berlin) or indirect (editorial or epistolar relationship with Berlin-based
                        intellectuals). The originality of this digital scholarly edition is that it
                        is neither author-centered nor genre-based, but presents different types of
                        selected manuscripts that shed light on the intellectual activity of Berlin
                        at the turn of the 18th to the 19th century. This editorial choice is
                        presented at length in  <ptr target="#baillot2014"/>, where light is also shed
                        on the uniqueness of the Prussian Capital City in the context of the
                        period. While
                        correspondences play a key role in the edition, they are considered as a
                        part of the circulation of ideas that is at the core of the project, so that
                        letters, and more generally egodocuments, are complemented by drafts of
                        either literary works (among which two major romantic texts), scholarly
                        writings (one dissertation) or administrative documents (related to the
                        development of the Berlin University). A first editorial phase (2010-2016)
                        allowed to publish manuscripts that cover different thematic areas and
                        historical phases of the development of intellectual Berlin. They were
                        selected based mainly on their scholarly relevance and on their
                        accessibility (the publication policy of archives holding manuscripts having
                        a major impact on their integration to a digital edition that displays a
                        facsimile like this one does). Four main topics have emerged in this first
                        phase: French, e.g. Huguenot Culture, Berlin University, Literary
                        Romanticism and Women Writers. Depending on the topics, the letters
                        published were complemented by other types of texts that document the
                        circulation of ideas and of literary and scholarly works in the late
                        18th and
                        early 19th
                        century. </p>
            <p>The edition can be browsed by theme, by
                        author, by period, by holding institution, or by date. The single document
                        can be displayed on one or two columns presenting at the user’s choice a
                        facsimile of the current manuscript page, a diplomatic transcription, a
                        reading version, the metadata, the entities occurring on the page and the
                        XML file corresponding to the document. In this first development phase,
                        248 documents and 17 authors were encoded and presented in BI. In Figure
                            1, a quantitative summary of the BI
                        corpus is given, which consists of introductory figures for the whole corpus
                        in terms of size, temporal span and number of alterations and detailed
                        information about individual authors.</p> 
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Quantitative summary
                     of the BI corpus. Subfigure (a) shows the number of documents grouped
                     by each author. Adelbert Chamisso holds the largest share of documents. In
                     (b), the
                     actual number of characters by author shows a slightly different picture,
                     instead of Chamisso, J. Euler has the largest portion. In Subfigure (c), the
                     alterations in terms of <q>number of changed characters</q> between different
                     versions of the documents are depicted for each author. A Large number of
                     total characters of an author does not necessarily mean a lot of
                     alterations. Although Euler encompasses the largest number of characters
                     there are close to no alterations in the documents he authored. In (d),
                     total counts for the whole BI corpus are stated to show the extent of the
                     annotational effort. In (e), the temporal distribution of the creation of
                     the documents is shown for the whole corpus (top) and for each individual
                     author (bottom). In this subfigure ((e), bottom), the number of documents
                     created in each year is encoded in the intensity of the color.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/10000201000001F4000001609B9B749EFB92CBC3.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Picture of various bar charts</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            
            <p>A major novelty about the BI edition is 
                        that it combines genetic edition and entity annotation in order to gain
                        insight in intellectual networks, on the actual editing process of manuscripts (of
                        literary and scholarly works) and on the discourse about this editing
                        process (letters – most letters are interestingly also partly transformed
                        into literary works in their own right and subject to editing). The genetic
                        encoding gives precise information regarding deletions and additions in the
                        manuscript text. The BI encoding guidelines make extensive use of the
                        following specific sections of the the TEI (P5)<note>The encoding guidelines can
                            be found at
                           <ref target="berliner-intellektuelle.eu/encoding-guidelines.pdf">berliner-intellektuelle.eu/encoding-guidelines.pdf</ref></note> guidelines additionally to the standard structure
               (Chapter 1-4): Manuscript Description (Chapter 10, <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html">https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html</ref>), Representation of Primary Sources (Chapter 11,
               <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/PH.html">https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/PH.html</ref>) and Names, Dates, People, and Places (Chapter 13,
               <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ND.html">https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ND.html</ref>), which offers
                        the possibility to markup text alterations with tags such as <q>add</q> and
                        <q>del</q>.</p>
            <p>As already mentioned, the BI Edition
                        features annotations on the genesis of the documents (genetic edition),
                        which, being a digital edition, are machine-readable. The core question we
                        will address in the following is therefore whether machine learning
                        models <ptr target="#wainwright2008"/> <ptr target="#rasmussen2006"/> <ptr target="#nakajima2019"/>
                     that analyze the alterations within the documents can
                        be used to gain new insights into author, editor, and archivist practices,
                        as well as practices of the intellectual societies in the document’s
                        creation time. The investigation of this question is only made possible by
                        the meticulous (digital) annotation of the historical documents that
                        provides previously unavailable enrichments and perspectives on the sources.
                    </p>
            <p>From the perspective of edition theory Ehrmann stresses that the
                    importance of analyzing the alterations in manuscripts for literary studies and
                    scholarly editing lies not only in the fact that they allow an insight into the
                    author's writing process in the case of author-made changes, but also in the
                    fact that they help identify the respective contribution in the case of
                    co-authorships <ptr target="#ehrmann2016"/>. The first question that arises when examining every alteration is
                    the question of the underlying reason, be it for a minor correction of mistakes
                    or a wide-ranging content-related alteration. This leads to the question of the
                    originator of the alteration and, as Ehrmann stresses, whether the alteration is
                    wanted by the author <ptr target="#ehrmann2016"/>. In the specific case of an edition of correspondence,
                    the intended readership is bound to change dramatically in the aftermath of
                    publication. A letter that was originally written to a friend is made public to
                    a large readership and in the process of preparation, the editor applies
                    alterations to the original letter, most of the time with a correction phase on
                    the original manuscript itself. This is the case for many manuscripts in the BI
                    edition, commented on as follows by the editors:</p>
            <p><quote rend="block">One characteristic of letters is that you generally are not the
                    first one to read them when you discover them in an archive. Not only have they
                    been addressed to a person or a group of persons in the first place [..], many
                    of the letters we at least are working on have already been edited in the last
                    centuries. But not in extenso, no: they have been abridged, overwritten,
                    corrected according to the expectation of the audience in the time that they
                    were edited. <ptr target="#baillot2015a"/></quote></p>
            <p>Moreover, the novel machine learning
                        method (alterLDA) presented here also offers new
                        opportunities for many other areas of automated analysis of variants of
                        sources, especially within the Digital Humanities. AlterLDA is based on the
                        topic model latent Dirichlet allocation (LDA). <quote rend="inline">Topic Modeling has proven immensely popular in
                           Digital Humanities</quote> <ptr target="#schoch2017"/>. LDA is particularly popular in
                        the DH because it is suitable for explorative text analysis. With the
                        automated compilation of word lists by LDA, new topics can be identified in
                        large text corpora whose existence was previously unknown. In this context,
                        it almost always forms the first analysis step on text data, but it can in
                        fact also be used for non-textual data <ptr target="#jelodar2019"/> <ptr target="#liu2016"/>.
               In addition to LDA, which provides the identification of the overall
                        relevant topics of the corpus to be examined and the specific topics of the
                        individual documents of the corpus, alterLDA is particularly concerned with
                        the variants of the documents. The starting
                        conditions for this work are as follows: from the point of view of edition
                        theory, the question of document variants is of major importance, and this
                        has not yet been sufficiently investigated with Distant Reading methods.
                        From a methodological point of view, there is a very widespread Topic Model
                        (LDA), which is already recognized and accepted practice in the Digital
                        Humanities. In this paper we therefore close the gap by adapting LDA in
                        order to model document variants.</p>
            <p>The processual aspects of text genesis in the sources
                        underlying the edition are thus highlighted and supported by the
                    processual aspects of the edition itself. If a document in its past has already
                    been prepared for publication by an editor, then his or her notes in the TEI-XML
                    are annotated in the same way as when the editors of the BI Edition leave notes:
                    with the <code>&lt;note&gt;</code>-tag.</p>
            <p>Parts may be deemed inappropriate for publishing to a broader
                    readership at a certain place and time due to their political or religious
                    context, or for revealing private information about a person or a group.</p>
            <p>The application on the BI corpus is particularly interesting
                    because the latter consists mainly of letters, which, especially around 1800 in
                    Germany, exhibit a strong tension between public and private sphere. The
                    framework presented here includes four methods that range from basic, well
                    established, rule-based methods to a specialized, novel machine learning method
                    (alterLDA) that was developed for exactly this purpose. From a methodological
                    point of view, this is a challenge for all disciplines involved, conceived as a
                    scenario optimized so that all sides benefit from each other. Finally, the newly
                    introduced method is also applied to discover alteration candidates in the
                    documents that are not yet altered. These findings led to, and hopefully will
                    continue to fuel, interesting discussions on parts of the edition that were
                    unnoticed thus far.</p>
            <p>Due to machine readability, documents in
                        digital editions can be modified by computer programs in such an algorithmic
                        way that they are transformed into something else. This transformation is
                        described by Stephen Ramsay in the concept of Algorithmic
                    Criticism:</p>
            <p><quote rend="block">Any reading of a text that is not a
                        recapitulation of that text relies on a heuristic of radical transformation.
                        The critic who endeavors to put forth a <q>reading</q> puts forth not the text,
                        but a new text in which the data has been paraphrased, elaborated, selected,
                        truncated, and transduced <ptr target="#ramsay2011" loc="16"/>.</quote></p>
            <p>The methods to which Ramsay refers here,
                        e.g. tf-idf normalization, are mostly deterministic methods. In this work,
                        however, a probabilistic method is used to transform the documents and their
                        variants, which uses previously collected data and relates the observations
                        to it. Thus, these statistical transformations resemble human reading more
                        than purely deterministic approaches and therefore foster the methodological
                        concept of the <quote rend="inline">radical transformation</quote> described within the Algorithmic
                        Criticism towards a more general criticsm that includes non-explicit
                        algorithms.</p>
            <p>This transformation in an algorithmic
                        way is a very standard technique (e.g. counting co-appearances of speakers
                        in scenes of a play). However in recent years Machine Learning models are
                        being used more broadly for e.g. Named Entity Recognition <ptr target="#dalenoskam2016"/> <ptr target="#jannidis2015"/>.
               The patterns that are used to identify entities
                        are not stated explicitly by a programmer but are learned from the data at
                        training time. In general, Machine Learning methods would then be
                        methodologically less strict than classical explicit algorithmic
                        transformations and therefore be possibly also more human-like. However,
                        when giving up this explicitness there has to be a more rigorous evaluation
                        of the machine’s output. For many applications, like the one presented in
                        this work, we therefore rely on the evaluation by machine learning and
                        humanities scholars, who can employ methods for interpreting and explaining
                        machine learning models <ptr target="#samek2019"/>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Methods
            </head>
            <p>In this section, the machine learning methods for identifying the
                    reason for a given alteration are presented, by first introducing the general
                    data analysis pipeline. Then, we specify precise definitions of the most
                    relevant concepts for alterations. After specifying the preprocessing steps, the
                    novel alterLDA model is introduced. It is designed to analyze the most
                    interesting, yet most complex types of alterations. Before the methodologies of
                    each step are explained in further detail, the definitions for the most
                    important and most frequently used terms are given here.</p>
            <p>Given an arbitrary version of a
                        document, we define an alteration to be a local group of added and/or
                        deleted symbols that is performed by the author of an alteration. Basically,
                        any symbol appearing in the document could be regarded as a single addition,
                        but the state of the manuscript at the time of the investigation often makes
                        it impossible to identify beyond doubt which groups of symbols belong to a
                        particular writing session. The same problem exists with deletions: Was the
                        sentence completed first, or did the author pause in the middle and correct
                        something before completing the sentence? In BI, additions and deletions are
                        considered as such when they clearly stand out, for example when they are
                        crossed out or written to the margin. Sometimes co-occurring additions and
                        deletions are also referred to as replacements. The alteration may
                    range from a single character to whole passages of the document and can even be
                    a local group with non-altered symbols in between. An alteration author is a
                    single person or institution that alters the document, possibly the primary
                    author him or herself. The alteration author has an alteration reason for which
                    he or she decides to alter the document. This is a very specific reason, for
                    example <quote rend="inline">the alteration author thinks that a particular word is spelled
                    differently</quote> or <quote rend="inline">a real person which is referred to in the document may not want
                    to be recognized by the readers, so this part is censored</quote>.</p>
            <p>Each alteration has a formal and content-related portion with
                    varying emphasis. For example, if the author of an alteration changes the
                    spelling of a single word this would not change the meaning of the document in
                    most cases. On the contrary, adding multiple sentences to a document may change
                    the content of the document significantly. Of course, whether an alteration is
                    rather positioned on the form side or on the content side of the axis depends on
                    the point of view of the recipient. Hence, the proposed method takes into
                    account the formal changes of the document as well as the content-related
                    changes. Smaller alterations tend to have a rather formal aspect, where longer
                    alterations almost always are content-related.</p>
            <p>The set of alterations can be broken down into different
                    categories with respect to their alteration reason. One group of alterations is
                    (1) the group of paratexts, for example archival notes, such as numberings or
                    dates, or stamps and seals of the library or archival institution. Another group
                    of alterations is (2) corrections of mistakes which consists in spelling
                    alterations, grammatical changes and other corrections. (3) The third group
                    contains stylistic alterations, for example replacing a token with its synonym
                    or rearranging the word order. Of course, changing the word order is sometimes
                    more than just a stylistic change, but one could e.g. begin a sentence with <foreign xml:lang="de"><quote rend="inline">Es
                    bedarf daher [..]</quote></foreign> as well as with <foreign xml:lang="de"><quote rend="inline">Daher bedarf es [..]</quote></foreign> with very similar
                    intentions. The last group of alterations which we call (4) content-related
                    alterations incorporate alterations that either add new information to the
                    document or suppress information that was present in the document before.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Flow chart of machine
                     learning pipeline with four example alterations. The stream of documents is analysed in four
                     steps that identify different reasons of alterations as depicted in the panel at
                     the top. In the panel at the bottom, the details of the individal alterations
                     are presented. Each alteration has a unique appearance and unique
                     characteristics, like the type of ink and the way in which it fits into the
                     surrounding script. The presented preview of the facsimiles are shown in greater
                     detail in Figure 9, Figure 10, Figure 11 and Figure 12.
            </head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/10000201000003FC000004E2BAB1C5D02A0A72E5.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Images of manuscript handwriting</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p> 
              <p>
               Figure 2
                    illustrates how the identification method works. All alterations are put into
                    the analysis pipeline, and after the initial distinction between author
                    alterations and non-author alterations, the four tests for different types are
                    performed on each alteration. As an example, there are four alterations depicted
                    in the illustration that are fed into the model. A detailed explanation for an
                    identification of the three non-content-related types of modifications is given
                    in the appendix. By elimination of all other possible categories, the remaining
                    alterations are of the content-related category. There are still a variety of
                    reasons in this category worthwhile to identify. Rather than the general
                    category we aim for providing a distinct reason for each alteration. The fourth
                    alteration which is marked in red is a longer deletion and a detailed facsimile
                    is shown in Figure 2. It is
                    performed with a pencil which is different from the primary ink of the letter.
                    It deals with the author’s sickness and with the sickness of the author’s
                    mother. The extent of the alteration already indicates that this is not a
                    correction of a mistake and since the part that is deleted is not replaced by
                    anything else, it can be assumed that this alteration changes the amount of
                    information provided. It is thus to be classified as a content-related
                    alteration. At this point it is still to be identified for which specific reason
                    the document has been altered. With alterLDA, the alteration is assigned to one
                    of a set of candidate reasons as a final step, in this case <emph>Sickness</emph>-reason.</p>
         </div>
            <div>
               <head>Related Work</head>
               <p>We convey a generative topic model, that is based on Latent
                  Dirichlet Allocation <ptr target="#blei2003"/> and that is able to take into account the
                        structural information of alterations. LDA is a widely used topic model that
                        extends Latent Semantic Indexing <ptr target="#deerwester1990"/> which is capable of assigning a
                        distribution of topics to a document instead of only a single topic. LDA
                        takes advantage of the fact that a text is organized in documents. This
                        structural information is the reason for LDA to function. Based on this
                        structure of documents, LDA can learn which words tend to co-occur and thus
                        have a relation. Words that often occur with each other form a topic. In
                        this context, a topic is merely a distribution of word frequencies.</p>
               <p> 
                  <figure>
                     <head>Graphical representation of the LDA model. The plate notation visualizes the generative process
                        of a probabilistic model by following the directions of the arrows. Given &#x03B1; and &#x03B7;, one initially draws &#x03B2;, 
                        a distribution over words for each topic and &#x03B8;, a topic distribution for each document. Then, for each 
                        token within a document, one draws a topic assignment and only then (because w has input arrows from both, &#x03B2;
                        and z, one can draw w from the topic in , that was assigned in z.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/10000201000001F40000006F91B28DE18B58784D.png"/>
                     <figDesc>Image of the LDA model</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p> 

               <p>In Figure 3, the LDA model is shown in plate notation. An overview over the used symbols is given in the
                  appendix. The plate notation shows the graphical representation of the LDA model. An open circle denotes 
                  a model variable and a shaded circle denotes an observed variable. Symbols without circle denote a hyper 
                  parameter. A rectangle indicates repetitions of the included variables. In this model, &#x03B2; represents the 
                  topic histograms, &#x03B8; represents the topic mixture for each document, z represents the topic assignment for 
                  each token position and w denotes the token itself. LDA has no notion of the order of words within a document, 
                  which is referred to in the literature as a <term>bag-of-words</term> for each document. </p>
               <p>There exists a wide range of topic models that customize LDA
                        by taking into account additional structural information. To replace the
                        bag-of-words approach by introducing structural information about the word
                        order is a major field of LDA research <ptr target="#rosenzvi2004"/> <ptr target="#gruber2007"/> <ptr target="#wallach2006"/>.
                  In addition, there is a broad
                        research community that addresses the recognition and arrangement of
                        hierarchies of topics <ptr target="#blei2010"/> <ptr target="#paisley2015"/>. LDA has also been
                  modified to work with graph-structured documents <ptr target="#xuan2015"/>. However,
                        we are not aware of any literature that shows how to model alteration
                        reasons in a corpus of natural language. Therefore, this paper is an
                        important contribution to close this gap, i.e. to provide the literary
                        scholarly community with a novel method and to open up another field of
                        application for the machine learning community.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Alteration Latent Dirichlet Allocation</head>
               <p>In Figure 4,
                        the alterLDA model is described in plate notation. The upper part is
                        standard LDA whereas the lower right part contains the newly introduced
                        variables to model alterations.</p>
               <p>In standard LDA, the observed variable (the input) is just the words within
                        each document. In the alterLDA setting, the additional structural
                        information about the alteration of each word is provided as input. With
                        that, the alterLDA model tries to infer the tendency for each topic to be an
                        alteration topic.</p>
               <p> 
                  <figure>
                     <head>Plate notation of the new alterLDA generative model. Newly introduced is the lower
                        branch with variables c, &#x03D2; and &#x03BE; that deal with alterations. There exist M documents with N<hi rend="subscript">m</hi> 
                        tokens each, Also, there exist K topics and for each topic, there exist a tendency for it to be a reason for alteration (&#x03D2;).</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/10000201000001F40000010E1ABF1BD5462D5CD6.png"/>
                     <figDesc>Image of the alterLDA model</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>

               <p>The generative model detects reasons by taking into account
                        all text, inside and outside the alterations. From alterations that were
                        gone through manually, we expect to see alteration suggestions that mainly
                        relate to the privacy of a person, political or religious topics may appear
                        as well. In order to make the model description as clear as possible, we try
                        to keep the mathematical formulations to a minimum. Therefore, we only
                        include an explanation of the symbols used (see appendix), a graphical
                        representation and the derivation of how the model can be algorithmically
                        captured using a Collapsed Gibbs Sampler. Similar to LDA, in alterLDA there
                        exists no feasible algorithm to compute the posterior distribution of the
                        latent variables. Instead, approximate methods need to be applied to find a
                        solution in reasonable time.</p>
               <p>A Collapsed Gibbs Sampler is one of the possible approaches to
                        find an approximate solution to the objective. Generally, a Gibbs Sampler
                        iteratively samples the configuration of a specific latent variable based on
                        the current configuration of all other model variables. An introductory
                        tutorial on Gibbs Sampling LDA is presented by <ptr target="#carpenter2010"/>.
                        This algorithm can also be understood as an instance of a Markov Chain, a
                        constrained iterative probabilistic model itself, where the current state
                        only depends on the previous. From this perspective, the stationary of the
                        Markov Chain represents the solution of the Gibbs Sampler. The source code
                        of our implementation of the Collapsed Gibbs Sampler for the alterLDA model
                        is <ref target="gitlab.tubit.tu-berlin.de/david.lassner/shipping_alterLDA">publicly available</ref>. In the
                        appendix, derivation of the Collapsed Gibbs Sampler for the alterLDA model
                        is given.</p> 
            
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Results</head>
            <p>In this section, we present three experiment settings which mainly
                    differ in the splitting between training and test data. As shown in Figure 5, three settings are
                    chosen, S1 as a straightforward explorative demonstration, S3 to comply with the methodological standards
                    of data splitting for the performance report, as well as S2 for offering
                    additional explorative results specific for this data set. We will first present
                    the evaluation results that investigate the performance of alterLDA on the given
                    data set and afterwards present explorative results that will be reconciled with
                    expert knowledge. Apart from these experiments on the BI data set, the first
                    experiments were performed on synthetic data, some results from these
                    experiments are listed in the appendix.</p> 
            <p><figure>
               <head>Visualization of the
                  data splitting setup for all settings. For each experiment a different data
                  setting is used. The different Settings are shown in the leftmost column
                  (S1, S2, S3). Within each setting, the row at the bottom depicts the final
                  setting of the data. Setting 1 (only one row) does not require test sets,
                  Setting 2 (only one row) aims at finding alteration candidates in texts with
                  no alterations. For Setting 3, the process of creating the setting is
                  depicted in multiple rows. First, only documents that contain alterations
                  are chosen. Then, each individual document is shuffled and split into a
                  training and a test part.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/10000201000001F4000001066228DCD27A7C7452.png"/>
               <figDesc>Image of rows with text in them</figDesc>
            </figure></p>
            
         
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Performance Evaluation</head>
               <p>In this experiment, in which alterLDA is applied to the entire
                        training data, it is to be determined whether the model in principle
                        delivers plausible results. It will be verified whether &#x03D2; finds a meaningful topic composition that represents sensitive
                        topics. This means that alteration topics may be a convolution of private
                        and maybe political and religious matters.</p>
               <p>With alterLDA, various parameters must be set which influence
                        the outcome. These are the same parameters as for LDA: Number of topics and
                        the Dirichlet prior for the topic distribution &#x03B7; and the topic mixture &#x03B1;. There is also another parameter, the Dirichlet prior for the
                        alteration tendency &#x03BE;. The default value for a Dirichlet prior is 1, but it can take any
                        value greater than 0. The smaller the value, the more the variable tends to
                        be focussed on single values, the larger the value, the more different
                        values are considered. Using the topic mixture as an example, a small &#x03B1; would mean that LDA is looking for a solution where each document
                        consists of only a few topics, a large &#x03B1; finds a solution with mixtures of many topics. AlterLDA is initialized in this setting
                        with &#x03B1; = (.1, .1, …), &#x03B7; = (.1, .1, …) and &#x03BE; = (.05, .05, …) as well as K=10. We choose &#x03BE; small in this setting to create a sparse 
                        &#x03D2; so that alterLDA only learns one alteration topic.</p>
               <p>The resulting topic learned in this naive approach as
                        alteration-sensitive is visualized as a word cloud in Figure 6. It is very
                        difficult to put a single label on this <q>topic</q>. The most probable words are
                        strongly influenced by global word frequencies, the strongest four words
                        describe it: <quote rend="inline"><foreign xml:lang="de">Sie Ich Brief schreiben</foreign></quote> this does not come as a surprise
                        since the corpus consists mainly of letters. However, it is also possible to
                        find terms from any subject area that was suspected in advance of being
                        altered: <emph>Sickness</emph> terms are for example <q>Operation</q>,
                        <q><foreign xml:lang="de">Bett</foreign></q>, <q><foreign rend="de">fürchten</foreign></q>, <emph>Financial</emph> terms are e.g.
                        <q><foreign xml:lang="de">Geschäft</foreign></q>, <q><foreign xml:lang="de">Geld</foreign></q> and regarding <q>Love Story</q> there is
                        for example <q><foreign xml:lang="de">lieb</foreign></q> and <q><foreign xml:lang="de">schön</foreign></q>.</p>
               <p>Beforehand, we assumed to also find political, religious
                        topics but these do not appear in the naive setting whereas diverse private
                        topics do occur.</p>
               <p><figure>
                  <head>The strongest words of
                     the topic that has a high alteration tendency after training alterLDA in the
                     naive setting (Setting 1). The stronger the word, the larger the font.
                     Strongest words are very general words on the topic of letters, words from
                     the Financial, Sickness and Love Story are also weakly present.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/10000201000001F40000011DEC24AAA6D6436AEE.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of a word cloud</figDesc>
               </figure></p>
            
               <p>As visualized in Figure 5, the BI corpus consists of documents with alterations
                        and documents without alterations. If we want to measure the performance of
                        alterLDA in predicting the tendency for alteration, documents with
                        alterations are much more helpful.</p>
               <p>In Setting 3, we only use documents with alterations to
                        produce the training and test set. We split every document individually into
                        training and test set after shuffling to increase the chance that
                        alterations are present in both sets <ptr target="#muller2001"/>. After training, we use the topic mixture &#x03B8; of the corresponding document.</p>
               <p>In this setting, alterLDA is initialized with &#x03B1;= (1, 1, …), &#x03B7; = (1, 1, …) and &#x03BE; = (1, 1, …) as well as K=20. We explicitly chose the Dirichlet
                        priors all equal to 1 as this can be considered the default. To allow for
                        more topic diversity, we chose the number of topics a little bit higher than
                        in the naive setting. This parameter combination will be used throughout the
                        rest of the paper.</p>
               <p>The performances on the total test set as well as for each
                        individual author are shown in Table 1. The performance varies considerably across different
                        authors where D. Tieck, L. Tieck and Ad. Chamisso work well above chance
                        level, the performance for Hoffmann and especially H. Finckenstein is
                        weaker. In case of H. Finckenstein, this may be due to the fact that in the
                        corpus there is only a single letter. For E.T.A. Hoffmann, there is also
                        only one document in the corpus, but it presents two specialties. It is
                        considerably longer than most documents in the corpus: it is not a letter,
                        but the novella <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="de">Der Sandmann</foreign></title>. The larger size and the
                        differing properties due to the genre seem to trade off to a slightly better
                        performance than in the case of H. Finckenstein. We thus argue that the
                        performance of alterLDA depends on the size of the training set and on the
                        homogeneity of the documents.</p>
               <p>The results of this setting are not meant produce new domain
                        insights as it only aims at reproducing the alteration tendencies of already
                        altered documents. However, screening performance difference across
                        viewpoints such as <emph>authors</emph> still reveals properties
                        of the underlying data set.</p>
               <table>
                  <head>Test set performance
                     for documents with alterations. The test set is grouped by author and two
                     performance measures are given. Balanced Accuracy and Area under Receiver
                     Operating Characteristic. In both cases, the sklearn implementation is used.
                     <ref target="http://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/classes.html#sklearn-metrics-metrics
                        version 0.20.0.">http://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/classes.html#sklearn-metrics-metrics
                     version 0.20.0.</ref></head>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell role="label">
                        Grouping
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Balanced Accuracy
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Area under ROC
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Adelbert von Chamisso
                     </cell>
                     <cell>.60</cell>
                     <cell>.57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Henriette v.
                                Finckenstein
                     </cell>
                     <cell>.38</cell>
                     <cell>.07</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Immanuel v. Fichte
                     </cell>
                     <cell>.49</cell>
                     <cell>.64</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        E.T.A. Hoffmann
                     </cell>
                     <cell>.5</cell>
                     <cell>.53</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Dorothea Tieck
                     </cell>
                     <cell>.61</cell>
                     <cell>.65</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Ludwig Tieck
                     </cell>
                     <cell>.69</cell>
                     <cell>.65</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell role="label">
                        Total
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        .67
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        .66
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>

            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Explorative Analysis</head>
               <p>In the explorative experiment (S2), the corpus is divided into
                        two parts: On the one hand, all documents that contain changes and, on the
                        other hand, all documents that do not contain any changes. The aim of the
                        experiment is to train the model on the part of the corpus that contains
                        changes and then let the model suggest which parts of the unchanged corpus
                        may be changed in a similar way. There may be different reasons why some
                        documents contain alterations and others do not. Assuming that all documents
                        were reviewed by the same person and that person was also so diligent that
                        he or she did not overlook a single passage, then alterLDA should at
                        best-case scenario not propose an additional passage to be altered. We
                        assume in this experiment that either not all documents have been reviewed
                        for the same criteria or that relevant positions have been overlooked.</p>
               <table>
                  <head>The table shows the
                     number of suggested alterations for different authors/editors. Only
                     documents that were not truly altered are included. The number of suggested
                     alterations represents the number of positions in dochuments that the method
                     suggests to alter. Euler and Buch mainly wrote in French, which influenced
                     the prediction a lot for these authors. Chamisso wrote in German although
                     his mother tongue is French. Therefore there may be many minor mistakes that
                     are suggested to be altered. Dorothea Tieck wrote about her mothers’
                     sickness which the method recognized as a sensible topic and therefore as a
                     reason for alteration.</head>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell role="label">
                        Author
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Suggested alterations
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Immanuel Hermann von
                                Fichte
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Karl August Varnhagen von
                                    Ense
                     </cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Friedrich Wilhelm
                                Neumann
                     </cell>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Helmina von Chézy
                     </cell>
                     <cell>59</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Adelheid Reinbold
                     </cell>
                     <cell>73</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Henriette Herz
                     </cell>
                     <cell>76</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Friedrich von
                                Schuckmann
                     </cell>
                     <cell>118</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Antonie von Chamisso
                     </cell>
                     <cell>258</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Friedrich Wilken
                     </cell>
                     <cell>340</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Ludwig Tieck
                     </cell>
                     <cell>389</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        August Boeckh
                     </cell>
                     <cell>540</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Adolf Friedrich von
                                Buch
                     </cell>
                     <cell>907</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Dorothea Tieck
                     </cell>
                     <cell>929</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Adelbert von Chamisso
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1075</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Jean Albert Euler
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2558</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>

               <p>In Table 2
                        the counts of the positions in documents with no alterations that have been
                        suggested by the method are displayed for each author/editor. The rows in
                        the table are sorted by the total amount of suggested alterations.
                        Interestingly, the authors with many suggested alterations are not
                        necessarily the ones that have a large share of total tokens of the corpus
                        (see Figure 1, (b) and
                        (c)). In the case of Euler and von Buch, this is due to the fact that their
                        documents are mostly in French, whereas the alterLDA model in this case is
                        primarily trained on German texts. For Boeckh, this is mainly due to the
                        fact that the corpus encompasses only a few yet long documents and
                        consequently there are not many documents present in the test set. Of
                        course, there are other reasons for each author's ratio of corpus portion
                        and number of suggested alterations. A person that altered all positions in
                        the training set also diligently edited all documents in the test set and
                        simply did not find any position that should be altered for the same reason:
                        That the method did not find the respective amount in the test set can
                        either mean that it was not able to find the right positions or that there
                        were none.</p>
               <p>For further analysis, we will ignore the texts by J. A. Euler
                        and A. F. Buch and focus on the other four authors for which alterLDA
                        suggested most alterations. As said, the texts by J. A. Euler and A. F. Buch
                        were mainly written in French which influenced the number of suggested
                        alterations. In Table 3,
                        the most common words that were suggested to be altered for individual
                        authors are listed. For all authors except A. Boeckh, the majority of words
                        seem to relate to the overall <emph>letter</emph> topic, however
                        for D. Tieck the keyword <q><foreign xml:lang="de">Krankheit</foreign></q> <emph>Sickness</emph>
                        appears. For Ad. Chamisso, words like e.g. <q><foreign xml:lang="de">schön</foreign></q> and <q><foreign xml:lang="de">begehren</foreign></q> can
                        be observed that may relate to the topic <emph>Love Story</emph>.
                        In the case of L. Tieck, a distinct convoluted alteration topic is not
                        immediately conceivable. In the case of A. Boeckh, the topic of the
                        documents in the corpus are mostly academia-related.</p>
               <table>
                  <head>Most common words that
                     were suggested to be altered in texts from individual authors.</head>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell role="label">
                        Author
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        25 most common suggested alteration words
                                    (descending order)
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Dorothea Tieck
                     </cell>
                     <cell><foreign xml:lang="de">Sie, Brief, schreiben, Ich, schön, gewiß, denken, einig, lesen,
                                all, gleichen, Düsseldorf, Agnes, Krankheit, Freund, kennen,
                                erhalten, Arbeit, Dresden, halten, weiß, Die, Leben, Berlin,
                                Lüttichau</foreign></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Adelbert v
                        .
                        Chamisso
                     </cell>
                     <cell><foreign xml:lang="de">Brief, schreiben, Ich, de, Die, weiß, kennen, all, wissen, schön,
                                4, Freund, denken, Sie, gleichen, halten, 3, neu, ton, erhalten,
                                begehren, bleiben, einig, lesen, Sache</foreign></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        Ludwig Tieck
                     </cell>
                     <cell><foreign xml:lang="de">Sie, Freund, Ich, Geist, Brief, Tieck, Dresden, Von, Ihr, umarmen,
                                Juli, halten, sogleich, erleben, Die, schwach, schweigen, sprechen,
                                Mich, Herrn, Vergnügen, fordern, Masse, gleichen, eintreten</foreign></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        August Boeck
                     </cell>
                     <cell><foreign xml:lang="de">Mitglied, Seminar, Sie, Prämie, Fichte, erhalten, Arbeit, 1813, 2,
                                Verfasser, 1812, Übung, hiesig, 4, Fähigkeit, welch,
                                außerordentlich, Nummer, zahlen, Prüfung, Wernike, Anstalt,
                                anfangen, Gedicht, Studiosus</foreign></cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               
               <p>For a better understanding of alteration suggestions, a closer
                        look into the individual authors is provided. D. Tiecks’ documents reveal a
                        sequence of letters that she wrote to F. Uechtritz in the years between 1831
                        and 1840. In the letters she repeatedly mentions her mother’s sickness until
                        her death in February 1837. Later, in March 1837, the father of F. Uechtritz
                        passed away as well, D. Tieck writes about this in Letter 28.</p>
               <p>By manually reviewing this series of letters, the editors of
                        the BI edition agreed in many cases with the classification of the alterLDA
                        model that D. Tieck’s mother’s sickness plays a role for the alteration
                        tendencies of the documents. In some cases, however, human experts and the
                        model disagreed about the reason for alteration. The following excerpt from
                        letter 12 is identified by our proposed method as a stylistic
                        alteration.</p>
               <p><quote rend="block"><foreign xml:lang="de"><p>Meine arme Mutter</p>
               <hi rend="bold"><p>leidet schon seit längerer Zeit an Unter=</p>
               <p>leibsbeschwerden, der Arzt sagt es seyen</p>
               <p>Verhärtungen und Anschwellungen der Drü=</p></hi>
               <p><hi rend="bold">sen, sie</hi> hat schon seit längerer Zeit viel zu
                        leiden, <hi rend="bold">braucht schon</hi></p>
               <p><hi rend="bold">seit 3 Monathen,</hi> trinkt seit 4 Wochen hier</p>
               <p>Karlsbad, und <hi rend="bold">alles</hi> bis jetzt ohne den</p>
               <p>mindesten Erfolg.</p>
               <p>(BI, Dorothea Tieck to v. Uechtritz, Letter 12, p. 2)</p></foreign></quote></p>
               
               <p>And one can argue that this is actually a stylistic
                        alteration, because the information about the mother’s sickness is preserved
                        after the alteration. However, the detail that her mother has pelvic
                        complaints is suppressed in the second version - this discrepancy in detail
                        can be decisive for classification as a content-related alteration.</p>
               <p>In Figure 7,
                        the number of suggested alterations (for the test set) and the number of
                        actual alterations (for the training set) are displayed for each document by
                        Ad. Chamisso. Most of the letters are addressed to L. La Foye (Ad.
                        Chamisso’s best friend), some are addressed to Antonie von Chamisso (Ad.
                        Chamisso’s wife). For each of the addressees, the letters are ordered by
                        date. There are two letters (letter 10 and 11) which stand out significantly
                        with regard to the number of alterations, letter 10, actually encompasses a
                        large number of alterations, whereas letter 11 is part of the test set and
                        thus does not have any (content-related) alterations. The alterLDA model
                        suggests an almost equally high number of alterations for letter 11,
                        presumably because it consists of topics that the alterLDA model estimates
                        to be altered accordingly - this shows that the alterLDA model captures
                        subtle changes of topics by the same author.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>The letters are
                        divided into documents containing content-related alterations (white
                        background) and documents without content-related alterations (purple
                        background). The alterLDA model is trained on the white part and predicts
                        possible alterations on the purple part, so the blue line shows the number
                        of real alterations and suggested alterations, depending on the background.
                        Left of the dotted separator, we find letters addressed to L. La Foye, on
                        the right side letters addressed to An. Chamisso. There are two consecutive
                        outliers with significantly higher numbers of alteration words. One is part
                        of the training set, one is part of the test set, the temporal proximity may
                        indicate a content-related proximity that the model was able to capture.</head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/10000201000001F40000017688B3590AA9C05ADE.png"/>
                     <figDesc>image of a line graph</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
              
               <p>In Figure 8,
                        the correspondence from L. Tieck to F. Raumer that is depicted ranges from
                        years 1815 to 1840. The left panel showing the number of letters that were
                        sent during that year grouped by whether they contain content-related
                        alterations. The right panel shows the number of tokens that were altered
                        (blue) and the number of tokens that alterLDA suggests to be altered
                        (orange).</p>
               <p>Just comparing the blue bars of the two panels reveals that
                        despite the fact that in 1836 there was only one letter written, there
                        occurs the third-highest number of altered tokens. By examining the letter,
                        it turns out that Tieck wrote about his financial problems and his plans to
                        sell his book collection to the Count Yorck von Wartenburg.<note> <quote rend="inline"><foreign xml:lang="de">[..] Tieck plante aus finanzieller
                            Bedrängnis heraus den Verkauf seiner Bibliothek an den Grafen Yorck von
                            Wartenburg[..]</foreign></quote> BI, comment by Johanna Preusse in letter from Ludwig
                            Tieck to Friedrich von Raumer (Dresden, 11. November 1836)</note>
               </p>
               <p>Referring back to Table 3, Financial terms are not present in the most common
                        alteration suggestions for L. Tieck. This could indicate that the person
                        editing L. Tieck’s letters did not miss parts that refer to this financial
                        struggle.</p>
               <p>When also considering the suggestions by alterLDA (the orange
                        bars of the panel on the right), one letter from 1838 draws the most
                        attention just by the sheer number of suggested alterations. In this letter,
                        L. Tieck refers to disputes between the Catholic Church and the Prussian
                        state at that time.<note> <quote rend="inline"><foreign xml:lang="de">Kontext der von
                            Tieck angedeuteten Vorgänge waren Machtstreitigkeiten zwischen der
                            katholischen Kirche und dem preußischen Staat. [..]</foreign></quote> BI, comment by
                            Johanna Preusse in letter from Ludwig Tieck to Friedrich von Raumer
                            (Dresden, 27. März 1838)</note> By arguing about this political
                        controversy, L. Tieck chooses his wording in such a way that alterLDA
                        suggests alterations. This could indicate that across the training corpus
                        there might be the same tendency to alter parts of the documents that deal
                        with a political controversy. The fact that alterLDA highlights a document
                        containing a mixture of political and religious topics supports the
                        hypothesis that the alterations in the BI corpus do not only consist of
                        privacy matters, but also involve a wider political dimension. This result
                        confirms and gives a novel dimension to the assertion that letters as a text
                        genre evolve, especially in the German context of the 1800s, at the
                        interface between private and public matters. In that sense, the role played
                        by alterations aiming at balancing private and public dimensions is central
                        and needs to be further delved into. AlterLDA provides a systematic approach
                        to this major issue in literary studies.</p>

               <p><figure>
                  <head>Left panel shows the
                     timeline with counts of letters from Ludwig Tieck to Friedrich von Raumer. The
                     right panel shows the number of tokens that were altered (blue) and the number
                     of suggested tokens (orange). The comparison between the number of letters and
                     the number of alterations for each year shows that there are times where the
                     letters were altered more (e.g. 1836). The letters with suggested alterations
                     deal with financial, political and religuous topics.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/10000201000001F4000000CA8B1C18FE443AB0D7.png"/>
                  <figDesc>image of two bar graphs</figDesc>
               </figure></p>
            </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>This paper presented a general framework for analyzing alterations
                    in historical documents, ranging from simple error corrections to stylistic
                    changes and even to content-related alterations. In addition to established
                    methods such as regular expressions, string distances and vector space
                    comparison, a new probabilistic model for the classification of reasons for
                    alterations has been introduced (alterLDA). </p>
            <p>This work contributes to the understanding of text genesis, as it
                    provides insight into the layers of changes in documents. It also offers a
                    quantitative way of evaluating which topics are at what times prone to be
                    altered and are therefore sensitive. </p>
            <p>From a machine learning point of view, the BI data set posed
                    special challenges because, on the one hand, the data set is very small and, on
                    the other hand, it comprises several languages, which also differ greatly from
                    the ones used today. Nonetheless, alterLDA was able to confidently find
                    alterations on unseen, labelled data. Exploratively, the method was able to find
                    characteristics on unseen, unlabeled data that in many cases match the expert
                    analysis. The method hence proves to be useful to draw the human reader's
                    attention to specific parts of the large corpus that may otherwise be unnoticed,
                    and by doing so serves as an example of how a machine learning method may assist
                    a scholar as a collaborating reader and a potential collaborating editor.</p>
            <p>With regard to the editorial issues
                        first presented here, it is to be noted that the machine-readability of the
                        BI edition makes it possible to serve problem-specific, individualised
                        editions tailored to the research question of a reader/scholar. This project
                        showcases how machine learning methods radically transform the way in which
                        scholars engage historical documents, by taking advantage of the quality of
                        deeply-annotated data: editorial and machine learning expertise can be
                        brought together to explore in depth Humanities research questions.</p>
            <p>This research benefited greatly from
                        expert knowledge on the corpus as well as from novel ML methods that were
                        designed for this corpus. This collaboration therefore presents important
                        guidelines for practical and methodological steps that will help other
                        projects to enrich their digital editions with automated annotation or
                        ML-guided corpus exploration.</p>
            <p>To achieve further progress, highly interdisciplinary research is
                    mandatory where novel ML models are conceived, and domain knowledge from
                    literary studies is interacting with statistical inference. </p>
         </div>
         
                  <div>
            <head>Appendix</head>
 
                     <div><head>Non-content-related Alteration Processing</head>
               <p>To identify the non-content-related alteration categories, existing methods
                        are used, however, for the identification of the specific content related
                        reasons on the right, the novel alterLDA method is used. As the main
                        contribution of this work lays in introducing the new alterLDA model, the
                        description of the non-content-related alterations. In this section, the
                        description of the established methods is shortly summarized, whereas the
                        description of alterLDA is given more space in the forthcoming
                        subsections.</p>
                     </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Paratexts</head>
                  <p>In Figure 2: Flow chart of
                                machine learning pipeline with four example alterations. , the
                            excerpt of the facsimile marked as archival note (orange) has the number
                            6 written in the top right corner of the sheet, this detail is shown in
                                Figure 9. The
                            corresponding xml transcription is the following:</p>
                  <p><code>&lt;note type="foliation" place="margin-right inline"
                            hand="#pencil_1"&gt;6&lt;/note&gt; </code></p>
                  <p>As the header reveals, this pencil numbering has been performed by an
                            archivist:</p>
                  <p><code>&lt;handNote xml:id="pencil_1" scope="minor" medium="pencil"
                            scribe="archivist"&gt;</code></p>
                  <p> <code>&lt;seg xml:xml:lang="de"&gt;Hand eines Archivars, in
                            Bleistift.&lt;/seg&gt;</code></p>
                  <p> <code>&lt;seg xml:xml:lang="en"&gt;Hand of an archivist, in
                            pencil.&lt;/seg&gt;</code></p>
                  <p> <code>&lt;seg xml:xml:lang="fr"&gt;Main d'un archiviste, crayon de
                            papier.&lt;/seg&gt;</code></p>
                  <p><code>&lt;/handNote&gt;</code></p>
                  <p>For the second pencil note in Figure 9 there is no scribe annotated although it also
                            contains nothing but a numbering:</p>
                  <p><code>&lt;note type="foliation" place="align(center)" hand="#pencil_2"&gt;</code></p>
                  <p> <code>&lt;hi rend="underline"&gt;99&lt;/hi&gt;</code></p>
                  <p><code>&lt;/note&gt; </code></p>
                  <p>The additions that have been performed by a different hand than the
                            primary author and that contain numberings or dates, we consider to be
                            archivists notes. Such archivist’s or editor’s additions can be
                            identified with a very basic set of rules.
                  </p>
            
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Archival note. BI,
                     Adelbert von Chamisso to Louis de La Foye. Nachlass 239, Blatt 6.
                     Staatsbibliothek Berlin / Manuscripts section. Reuse subject to prior
                     approval by Staatsbibliothek Berlin.<lb/>Published in: Letter from
                     Adelbert von Chamisso to Louis de La Foye (fragment) (without place, 26
                     june 1804). Ed. by Anna Busch, Sabine Seifert. Prepared by Janine
                     Katins. In collaboration with Sabine Seifert, Sophia Zeil. In: "Letters
                     and texts: Intellectual Berlin around 1800". Ed. by Anne Baillot.
                     Berlin: Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin.
                     <ref target="http://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/manuscript?Brief005ChamissoandeLaFoye">http://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/manuscript?Brief005ChamissoandeLaFoye</ref>.
                     Last modified: 27 April 2015.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/10000201000001F4000001045C1BB1A5A52EEEE1.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of manuscript handwriting</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Corrections
                  </head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Correction of
                     mistake of <q><foreign xml:lang="de">wurde</foreign></q> to <q><foreign xml:lang="de">würde</foreign></q>. BI, Adelbert von Chamisso to Louis de La
                     Foye. Nachlass 239, Blatt 85. Staatsbibliothek Berlin / Manuscripts
                     section. Reuse subject to prior approval by Staatsbibliothek Berlin.
                     Published in: Letter from Adelbert von Chamisso to Louis de La Foye
                     (Geneva, at the beginning of 1812). Ed. by Anna Busch, Sabine Seifert.
                     Prepared by Lena Ebert. In: <title rend="quotes">Letters and texts: Intellectual Berlin
                     around 1800</title>. Ed. by Anne Baillot. Berlin: Humboldt-Universität zu
                     Berlin.
                     <ref target="http://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/manuscript?Brief047ChamissoandeLaFoye">http://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/manuscript?Brief047ChamissoandeLaFoye</ref>.
                     Last modified: 27 April 2015.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/10000201000001F400000034897D417914648059.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of manuscript handwriting</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            
                  
                  <p>The alteration marked in green replaces a single character of a word, for
                            which the corresponding part of the facsimile is shown in Figure 10.</p>
                 <p><quote rend="block"><foreign xml:lang="de"> <p> [..]Geschichte wuürde lang</p>
                  <p>und schal ausfallen[..]</p>
                  <p>BI, Adelbert von Chamisso to Louis de La Foye. Letter 47, p. 1</p></foreign></quote></p>
            
                  <p>This alteration is a correction of a mistake and
                            conceptually, it is worth noting that the words before and after the
                            alteration are very similar. This characteristic will be exploited for
                            the identification of corrections. Identifying corrections is a
                            considerably more difficult task because the corrected version does not
                            necessarily have to be correct from what we know today. The fact that
                            the alteration author corrected the text only means that he or she
                            thought that his or her version is correct. We thus cannot rely on
                            comparing the second version of the text with what an automatic spell
                            checker would the first version correct to. Instead, we divided the
                            problem even further into spelling alterations and grammatical
                            alterations. For identifying spelling mistakes, the tokens of both
                            versions are fuzzy-string matched against the common dictionary of
                            lemmas. If both tokens match closely to the same lemma according to the
                            Levenshtein distance, the two tokens are considered two different
                            spellings of the same word. Fuzzy string matching of multiple tokens
                            against a large vocabulary can be costly in terms of computing time and
                            memory. For a larger data set an adjustment to this approach may be
                            necessary. However, this approach gave better results than simply
                            comparing Levenshtein distance of the tokens of both versions with each
                            other, due to smaller tokens that are very similar but mean different
                            things (e.g. <q>hate</q> and <q>fate</q> have Levenshtein distance of 1 but have a
                            very different meaning.) For identifying grammatical alterations, we
                            assume that the forms of the tokens in the sentence change and probably
                            punctuations are added or deleted, but the set of lemmas is preserved
                            for the most part. Hence, if the forms or the part of speech of the
                            tokens in the span change but the set of lemmas do not, this alteration
                            is a grammatical correction.</p>
               </div>
              
                  <div><head>Stylistic Alterations</head>
                  <p><quote rend="block"><foreign xml:lang="de"><p> [..] DaherEs bedarf esdaher hier eines [..]</p>
                  <p>BI, About the notion of philosophy PP. by Immanuel Hermann von Fichte, p.
                            14</p></foreign></quote></p>
                  <p>For identifying stylistic alterations, we assume that all
                            corrections and paratexts are already labelled according to the
                            described method. Thus, there are only stylistic alterations and moral
                            censorships left to be labelled. In our understanding, a stylistic
                            alteration preserves the meaning of the text by only changing the way it
                            is posed which includes rearranging of words, the use of synonyms and
                            rephrasing. In recent years, a method gained a lot of attention that
                            strive to find a vector-space representation of words that capture its
                            meaning. Words or sentences projected to this space reveal a high
                            similarity (for example cosine-similarity) if they have the same
                            meaning. We introduce a threshold and consider all alterations for which
                            the vector-space embedding of the text before and after the alteration
                            reveal a smaller distance to be a stylistic alteration.</p>
                  <p>The alteration marked in blue (Figure 2: Flow chart of machine learning pipeline with
                                four example alterations. ) which is shown in higher
                            resolution in Figure
                                11, reorders the words at the beginning of a sentence without
                            changing the meaning.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Stylistic
                     alteration of <q><foreign xml:lang="de">Daher bedarf es</foreign></q> to <q><foreign xml:lang="de">Es bedarf daher</foreign></q>. Immanuel Hermann
                     Fichte: Über den Begriff der Philosophie, Humboldt-Universität zu
                     Berlin, Universitätscharchiv, HU UA, Phil.Fak.01.Prom., No. 210, Page
                     14. Reuse subject to prior approval by the Universitätsarchiv.Ed. by Eva
                     Schneider. Prepared by Eva Schneider, Anne Baillot, Denny Becker. In
                     collaboration with Johanna Preusse. In: <title rend="quotes">Letters and texts: Intellectual
                     Berlin around 1800</title>. Ed. by Anne Baillot. Berlin: Humboldt-Universität
                     zu Berlin.
                     <ref target="http://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/manuscript?IHFichte_Die_Aufgabe_der_Philosophie">http://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/manuscript?IHFichte_Die_Aufgabe_der_Philosophie</ref>.
                     Last modified: 12 January 2015.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/10000201000001F400000034897D417914648059.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of manuscript handwriting</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            
                 
                  <p>For completeness, we also provide the individual facsimile of the content
                            related alteration example in <ref target="#id__Ref532487849" type="text">Figure 12</ref>.</p>
                  
                  
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Content-related
                     alteration. Nachlass Uechtritz. Oberlausitzische Bibliothek der
                     Wissenschaften Görlitz. Reuse subject to prior approval by
                     Oberlausitzische Bibliothek der Wissenschaften Görlitz. Letter from
                     Dorothea Tieck to Friedrich von Uechtritz (Dresden, 10 April 1835). Ed.
                     by Sophia Zeil. Published in: <title rend="quotes">Letters and texts: Intellectual Berlin
                     around 1800</title>. Ed. by Anne Baillot. Berlin: Humboldt-Universität zu
                     Berlin.
                     <ref target="http://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/manuscript?Brief16DorotheaTieckanUechtritz">http://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/manuscript?Brief16DorotheaTieckanUechtritz</ref>.
                     Last modified: 24 January 2015.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/10000201000001F40000017BF2AC9A4C6C0DB0C8.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of manuscript handwriting</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            

                  <p>Used Symbols</p>
                  <table>
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell role="label">Identifier</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Meaning</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Type</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Dimensionality</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>V</cell>
                        <cell>Number of unique tokens in the dictionary</cell>
                        <cell>Int</cell>
                        <cell/>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>W</cell>
                        <cell>Number of tokens in the corpus</cell>
                        <cell>Int</cell>
                        <cell/>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>M</cell>
                        <cell>Number of documents</cell>
                        <cell>Int</cell>
                        <cell/>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>N<hi rend="subscript">m</hi></cell>
                        <cell>Number of tokens in document m</cell>
                        <cell>Int</cell>
                        <cell/>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>K</cell>
                        <cell>Number of topics</cell>
                        <cell>Int</cell>
                        <cell/>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           &#x03B1;
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Concentration of &#x03B1;</cell>
                        <cell>Hyper parameter</cell>
                        <cell>K</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           &#x03B7;
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Concentration of &#x03B7;</cell>
                        <cell>Hyper parameter</cell>
                        <cell>V</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           &#x03BE;
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Concentration of &#x03BE;</cell>
                        <cell>Hyper parameter</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           &#x03B2;
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Topic-term variable</cell>
                        <cell>Dirichlet</cell>
                        <cell>K x V</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           &#x03B8;
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Document-topic variable</cell>
                        <cell>Dirichlet</cell>
                        <cell>M x K</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           &#x03D2;
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Topic-alteration-tendency variable</cell>
                        <cell>Dirichlet</cell>
                        <cell>K x 2</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <emph>z</emph>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Token-topic variable</cell>
                        <cell>Categorical</cell>
                        <cell>W x K</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <emph>w</emph>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Tokens </cell>
                        <cell>Observed (Categorical)</cell>
                        <cell>W x V</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <emph>c</emph>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Alteration</cell>
                        <cell>Observed (Categorical)</cell>
                        <cell>W X 2</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table></div>
               
            
               <div><head>Collapsed Gibbs Sampler of the AlterLDA Model</head>
               <p>For the Collapsed Gibbs Sampler of the alterLDA model it is
                        shown how to derive the posterior for the topic assignment at a current
                        position, given the current configuration. First, the joint probability of
                        the whole model is given before showing how to compute the topic assignment
                        based on count statistics.</p>
 <p>The joint probability of the model is given
                        by
               
                  <formula notation="tex" rend="block">$$\begin{align*}
	p(\mathbf{w}, c, z, \gamma, \beta, \theta~|~\alpha,\eta, \xi) =&amp; p(c~|~z) \cdot p(\mathbf{w}~|~z,\beta) \cdot p(\gamma~|~\xi) \cdot p(\beta~|~\eta)\cdot p(z~|~\theta)\cdot p(\theta~|~\alpha)\\
	=&amp; \prod^{M,N}\text{cat}(c~|~c,\gamma) \times \prod^{M,N}\text{cat}(\textbf{w}~|~z,\beta)\times\prod^{M,N}\text{cat}(z~|~\theta)\\
	&amp;\times\prod^{M}\text{dir}(\theta~|~\alpha)\times\prod^{K}\text{dir}(\gamma~|~\xi)\times\prod^{K}\text{dir}(\beta~|~\eta)\\
\end{align*}$$</formula>
             </p>  
            <p>We introduce a counter variable c which can be indexed in four dimensions, the current topic (<emph>k</emph>), the current document
               (<emph>m</emph>), the current alteration mode (<emph>a</emph>) and the current token (<emph>w</emph>).
               
            <formula notation="tex" rend="block">$$
c_{k,m,a,\mathbf{w}} = \sum_{n=1}^N \mathbf{I}(
    z_{m,n}=k
    \quad\&amp;\quad w_{m,n} = \mathbf{w} 
    \quad\&amp;\quad     c_{m,n} = a )
$$</formula>
             </p>  
               
               <p>In this setting, the desired computation is the probability of
                        a topic assignment at a specific position given a current configuration of
                        all other topic assignments. This probability can be formalized by
            <formula notation="tex" rend="block">$$\begin{align*}
	p(z_{m,n}~|~z_{-_{(m,n)}},\mathbf{w},c,\alpha,\eta,\xi)&amp;\propto~p(z_{m,n},z_{-_{(m,n)}},\mathbf{w},c~|~\alpha,\eta,\xi)
\end{align*}$$</formula>
            
            </p>
            <p>Adopting Equation 16 from the Carpenter paper, this probability can be written by marginalizing θ,β,γ and  from the joint probability. 

            <formula notation="tex" rend="block">$$\begin{align*}
	p(z_{m,n},z_{-_{(m,n)}},\mathbf{w},c~|~\alpha,\eta,\xi) = &amp; \int\int\int~p(\mathbf{w},c,z,\gamma,\beta,
	\theta~|~\alpha,\eta,\xi)d\theta~d\beta~d\gamma\\
	= &amp; \underbrace{\int~p(\theta~|~\alpha)\cdot~p(z~|~\theta)d\theta}_A\\
	&amp; \times \underbrace{\int~p(\mathbf{w}~|~z,\beta)\cdot~p(\beta~|~\eta)d\beta}_B\\
	&amp; \times \int~p(c~|~z,\gamma)\cdot~p(\gamma~|~\xi)d\gamma\\
	= &amp; \prod_{k=1}^K\int~p(\gamma_k~|~\xi)\prod_{m=1,n=1}^{M,N_m}p(c~|~\gamma_{\text{argmax}(z_{m,n})})d\gamma_k \times A \times B
\end{align*}$$</formula></p>
            
               <p>A and B are substituted here because their derivation is
                        identical to the one in Carpenter et al. Analogue to Equation 27 of
                        Carpenter et al., after inserting the definitions of the Dirichlet
                        distribution the result is proportional to three factors.

            <formula notation="tex" rend="block">$$\begin{align*}
	\propto (\mathbf{c}^-_{z_{m,n},*,*,*}+\alpha_{z_{m,n}})\left(
		\frac{
			\mathbf{c}^-_{z_{m,n},*,*,\mathbf{w}_{m,n}}+\eta_{w_{m,n}}
		}{
			\mathbf{c}^-_{z_{m,n},*,*,*}+\sum_v^V\eta_{v}
		}
	\right)\left(
		\frac{
			\mathbf{c}^-_{z_{m,n},*,c_{m,n},*}+\xi_{w_{m,n}}
		}{
			\mathbf{c}^-_{z_{m,n},*,*,*}+\sum_i^2\xi_{i}
		}
	\right)
\end{align*}$$</formula>


            where .-  denotes the counter disregarding the current position <emph>m, n</emph>.</p>
               </div>
            
         
               <div><head>Results on Synthetic Data</head>
               <p>A big advantage of generative models is that they can be used
                        to generate new data. The generated documents themselves may not be too
                        interesting in the case of topic models, but they can be used to evaluate
                        the functionality of the model. To do this, first, the variables of the
                        model are initialized, and documents are generated. Now the variables are
                        initialized again and based on the previously generated documents the old
                        variable configurations are reconstructed. The performance of the inference
                        can be measured by the accuracy of the reconstruction.</p>
               <p>In Figure
                        13, the results of such an evaluation over 324 different experiment
                        runs is shown, within the sparsity of the hyper-parameters as well as the
                        number of tokens were varied. Each cell shows the mean reconstruction of c
                        over two runs with a given set of parameter choices. The brighter the color
                        of the cell, the better the reconstruction. Overall, a smaller alpha yields
                        better results, independent of the size of the data set and the choice of
                        the other concentration factors. Interestingly, for fewer documents and &#x03B1; = 0.1, a smaller concentration factor &#x03B7; performs better, wheras for either a larger number of documents or
                        a larger &#x03B1; = 0.1 a larger &#x03B7; is to be preferred. The explanation for this result is that with
                        more documents, the exact proportions of the topics can be inferred more
                        accurately, wheras for fewer documents, there is the chance of getting a few
                        (sparse) topics right.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Grid search result for
                     training accuracy of &#x108; parameter on synthetic data. Even with a small total number of
                     tokens, the accuracy can be very high. Interestingly, the accuracy depends
                     strongly on the sparsity of &#x03B1;, &#x03BE;, and &#x03B7;</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/10000201000001F4000002A26ED912E0C23572AD.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of manuscript handwriting</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p></div>

         </div>
         
      </body>
      <back>
         
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="andrews2013" label="Andrews 2013">Andrews, T., 2013. <title rend="quotes">The third way: philology and critical edition in the digital
                    age.</title> <title rend="italic">Variants, </title>pp. 61-76.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baillot2014" label="Baillot and Busch 2014">Baillot, A. &amp; Busch, A., 2014. <title rend="quotes">Berliner Intellektuelle um 1800</title> als
                    Programm. Über Potential und Grenzen digitalen Edierens. <title rend="italic">Romantik Digital</title>, 1 9.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baillot2015a" label="Baillot and Busch 2015">Baillot, A. &amp; Busch, A., 2015. <title rend="italic">Editing for man and machine: The digital
                    edition Letters and texts. Intellectual Berlin around 1800 as an example</title>. <title rend="italic">Variants, </title>Volume 13.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baillot" label="Baillot n.d.">Baillot, A., ed., n.d. <title rend="italic">Letters and texts. Intellectual Berlin
                        around 1800. </title>s.l., Berlin: Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baillot2015b" label="Baillot and Schnöpf 2015">Baillot, A. &amp; Schnöpf, M., 2015. <title rend="quotes">Von wissenschaftlichen Editionen als
                    interoperable Projekte, oder: Was können eigentlich digitale Editionen?</title>. <title rend="italic">Historische Mitteilungen der Ranke-Gesellschat, </title>Volume
                    Beiheft 91, pp. 139-156.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="beckett2011" label="Beckett 2011-2018">Beckett, S., 2011-2018. <title rend="italic">Digital Manuscript Project. A digital
                        genetic edition, </title>Brussels: University Press Antwerp.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bishop2006" label="Bishop 2006">Bishop, C. M., 2006. <title rend="italic">Pattern Recognition and Machine Learning
                        (Information Science and Statistics). </title>s.l.:Springer Science+Business
                    Media, LLC.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="blei2010" label="Blei et al. 2010">Blei, D. M., Griffiths, T. L. &amp; Jordan, M. I., 2010. <title rend="quotes">The Nested Chinese
                    Restaurant Process and Bayesian Nonparametric Inference of Topic Hierarchies.</title>
                        <title rend="italic">J. ACM, </title>Volume 57, pp. 1-30.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="blei2003" label="Blei et al. 2003">Blei, D., Ng, A. &amp; Jordan, M., 2003. <title rend="quotes">Latent Dirichlet allocation</title>. <title rend="italic">JMLR.</title>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bojanowski2017" label="Bojanowsku et al. 2017">Bojanowski, P., Grave, E., Joulin, A. &amp; Mikolov, T., 2017. <title rend="quotes">Enriching Word
                    Vectors with Subword Information</title>. <title rend="italic">Transactions of the
                        Association for Computational Linguistics, </title>Volume 5, pp. 135-146.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="carpenter2010" label="Carpenter 2010">Carpenter, B., 2010. <title rend="quotes">Integrating out multinomial parameters in latent Dirichlet
                    allocation and naive Bayes for collapsed Gibbs sampling</title>. <title rend="italic">Rapport Technique, </title>Volume 4, p. 464.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dalenoskam2016" label="Dalen-Oskam 2016">Dalen-Oskam, K., 2016. <title rend="quotes">Corpus-based approaches to Names in Literature</title>. In: C.
                    Hoigh, ed. <title rend="italic">The Oxford Handbook of Names and Naming.
                    </title>Oxford: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="deerwester1990" label="Deerwester 1990">Deerwester, S. et al., 1990. <title rend="quotes">Indexing by latent semantic analysis</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of the American society for information science,
                    </title>Volume 41, p. 391.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ehrmann2016" label="Ehrmann 2016">Ehrmann, D., 2016. <title rend="quotes">Textrevision — - Werkrevision. Produktion und Überarbeitung im
                    Wechsel von Autoren, Herausgebern und Schreibern</title>. <title rend="italic">Editio,
                    </title>Volume 30.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="goethe2017" label="Goethe 2017">Goethe, J. W., 2017. <title rend="italic">Faust. Historisch-kritische Edition..
                    </title>Frankfurt am Main / Weimar / Würzburg: s.n.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gruber2007" label="Gruber et al. 2007">Gruber, A., Rosen-Zvi, M. &amp; Weiss, Y., 2007. <title rend="italic">Hidden Topic
                        Markov Models. </title>s.l., JMLR.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jannidis2015" label="Jannidis et al. 2015">Jannidis, F. et al., 2015. <title rend="italic">Automatische Erkennung von Figuren
                        in deutschsprachigen Romanen. </title>Graz: ADHO.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jelodar2019" label="Jelodar et al. 2019">Jelodar, H. et al., 2019. <title rend="quotes">Latent Dirichlet allocation (LDA) and topic modeling:
                    models, applications, a survey</title>. <title rend="italic">Multimedia Tools and
                        Applications, </title>78(11), pp. 15169-15211.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="leclerc2009" label="Leclerc 2009">Leclerc, Y., ed., 2009. <title rend="italic">Les Manuscrits de Madame Bovary.
                    </title>Rouen, s.n.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="liu2016" label="Lie et al. 2016">Liu, L. et al., 2016. <title rend="quotes">An overview of topic modeling and its current applications
                    in bioinformatics</title>. <title rend="italic">SpringerPlus, </title>Volume 5.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="muller2001" label="Müller et al. 2001">Müller, K.-R.et al., 2001. <title rend="quotes">An introduction to kernel-based learning algorithms</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks, </title>12(2), pp.
                    181-201.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nakajima2019" label="Nakajima 2019">Nakajima, S., Kazuho, W. &amp; Masashi, S., 2019. <title rend="italic">Variational
                        BAyesian Learning Theory. </title>s.l.:Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="paisley2015" label="Paisley 2015">Paisley, J., Wang, C., Blei, D. M. &amp; Jordan, M. I., 2015. <title rend="quotes">Nested hierarchical
                    Dirichlet processes</title>. <hi rend="italic">IEEE transactions on pattern analysis and
                        machine intelligence, </hi>Volume 37.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="plachta2006" label="Plachta 2006">Plachta, B., 2006. <title rend="italic">Editionswissenschaft: eine Einführung in
                        Methode und Praxis der Edition neuerer Texte. </title>2nd ed. Stuttgart:
                    Reclam.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ralle2016" label="Ralle 2016">Ralle, I. H., 2016. <title rend="quotes">Maschinenlesbar — - menschenlesbar. Über die grundlegende
                    Ausrichtung der Edition</title>. <title rend="italic">Editio, </title>Volume 30.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ramsay2011" label="Ramsay 2011">Ramsay, S., 2011. <title rend="italic">Reading Machines: Toward and Algorithmic
                        Criticism. </title>s.l.:University of Illinois Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rasmussen2006" label="Rasmussen 2006">Rasmussen, C. E. &amp; Williams, C. K. I., 2006. <title rend="italic">Gaussian
                        Processes for Machine Learning. </title>s.l.:MIT Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rosenzvi2004" label="Rosen-Zvi 2004">Rosen-Zvi, M., Griffiths, T., Steyvers, M. &amp; Smyth, P., 2004. <title rend="italic">The author-topic model for authors and documents. </title>s.l.,
                    s.n., pp. 487-494.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="samek2019" label="Samek et al. 2019">Samek, W. et al. eds., 2019. <hi rend="italic">Explainable AI: Interpreting,
                        Explaining and Visualizing Deep Learning. </hi>s.l.:Lecture Notes in
                    Artificial Intelligence. Volume 11700.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schoch2017" label="Schöch 2017">Schöch, C., 2017. <title rend="quotes">Topic Modeling Genre: An Exploration of French Classical and
                    Enlightenment Drama</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly,
                    </title>11(2).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schlitz2014" label="Schlitz 2014">Schlitz, S., 2014. <title rend="quotes">Digital Texts, Metadata, and the Multitude. New Directions in
                    Participatory Editing</title>. <title rend="italic">Variants, </title>Volume 11, pp.
                    71–-89.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schmidt2016" label="Schmidt 2016">Schmidt, D., 2016. <title rend="quotes">Using standoff properties for marking-up historical documents
                    in the humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">Information Technology: Human Computation,
                    </title>Volume 58, pp. 63-69.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shillingsburg2013" label="Shillingsburg 2013">Shillingsburg, P., 2013. <title rend="quotes">Development Principles for Virtual Archives and
                    Editions</title>. <title rend="italic">Variants, </title>pp. 61-76.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="siemens2012" label="Siemens et al. 2012">Siemens, R. et al., 2012. <title rend="quotes">Toward modeling the social edition: An approach to
                    understanding the electronic scholarly edition in the context of new and
                    emerging social media*</title>. <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing,
                    </title>Volume 27, pp. 445-461.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wainwright2008" label="Wainwright 2008">Wainwright, M. J. &amp; Jordan, M. I., 2008. <title rend="italic">Graphical Models,
                        Exponential Families, and Variational Inference. </title>s.l.:now
                    publishers.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wallach2006" label="Wallach 2006">Wallach, H., 2006. <title rend="italic">Topic Modeling: Beyond Bag-of-words.
                    </title>New York, ACM.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="witkowski1924" label="Witkowski 1924">Witkowski, G., 1924. <title rend="italic">Textkritik und Editionstechnik neuerer
                        Schriftwerke. </title>Leipzig: Haessel.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="xuan2015" label="Xuan et al. 2015">Xuan, J., Lu, J., Zhang, G. &amp; Luo, X., 2015. <title rend="quotes">Topic model for graph mining</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">IEEE transactions on cybernetics, </title>Volume 45.</bibl>
         </listBibl>

      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
