<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt><!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">The Humans and Algorithms of Music Recommendation: A Review of Computing Taste (2022)<!--article title in English--></title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo><!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Jacos <dhq:family>Pleasants</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Oklahoma</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>jacob.pleasants@ou.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Jacob Pleasants is an Assistant Professor of Science
                     Education at the University of Oklahoma. Through his teaching and research, he works
                     to bring issues that lie at the intersection of science, engineering, technology,
                     and society into STEM education.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000576<!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND"><!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords"><!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors--><!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
              <term corresp="#music"></term>
              <term corresp="#anthropology"></term>
              <term corresp="#media_history"></term>               
               
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords"><!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>algorithms</item>
                  <item>anthropology</item>
                  <item>technology studies</item>
                  <item>sociotechnical systems</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc><!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000576/00576.xml">GitHub
                   </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract><!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>In <hi rend="italic">Computing Taste</hi>, Nick Seaver conducts an anthropological
               study of the technologists who design algorithmic music recommendation systems. He
               explores their ways of thinking and talking about music, taste, and computation to
               better understand their technological design approaches. By highlighting the humans
               behind the machines, <hi rend="italic">Computing Taste</hi> shows how to think about
               computer algorithms as sociotechnical systems.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser><!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>Jacob Pleasants publishes book review of The Humans and Algorithms of Music Recommendation: A Review of Computing Taste (2022)</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      
      <body>
         
      <div>
         
         <head>Introduction</head>
         
         <p>Streaming services such as Spotify have changed the way that many (if not most)
                people listen to music. Those services do much more than just provide access to
                massive searchable libraries; they actively shape what users listen to via their
                recommendation systems. Music recommendation comes in many forms, from basic
                suggestions to playlists to personalized <q>radio stations,</q> all of which now rely on
                algorithmic computing technologies. Much has been written about how those
                technologies have transformed the media landscape and have created significant
                issues for users [e.g., <ptr target="#gaw2022"/>; <ptr target="#pajkovic2022"/>] as well as creators [e.g., <ptr target="#giblin_doctorow2022"/>]. Seaver’s <hi rend="italic">Computing Taste</hi> <ptr target="#seaver2022"/>
                lies within those conversations, but approaches the space from a different angle.
                Rather than offer yet another social critique of the modern state of algorithmic
                recommendation, Seaver focuses on the designers of those technological systems.</p>
         
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Computing Taste</hi> is an anthropological study, based on field
                work that Seaver conducted over several years in the early 2010s. He spent time
                within a company he calls <q>Whisper</q> and conducted interviews with a wide variety of
                technologists across the industry. Seaver’s aim is not primarily technology
                criticism (though he does offer critiques) but rather to illuminate the cultural
                practices of those who design recommendation technologies. What do the designers aim
                to accomplish through their work? How do they understand music? And perhaps most
                centrally, how do they think about taste? <hi rend="italic">Computing Taste</hi>
                reveals that the answers to those questions are anything but simple.</p>
         
         <p><quote rend="block">This book is about those humans — people who occupy a paradoxical position within algorithmic systems and in discourse about them. Although they are often figured as unfeeling agents of rationality, they
                    describe themselves as motivated by a deep care for music. Like many of their
                    critics, the makers of music recommendation recognize that there is something
                    strange about their aspirations — a tension between the closed, formal rationality
                    of technology and the open, contingent subjectivity of taste. <ptr target="#seaver2022" loc="8"/></quote>
            </p>
         
         <p>Given the abundance of scholarship that examines and critiques algorithmic
                recommendation systems, what does Seaver’s anthropological approach offer? When
                analyzing these technologies, there is a tendency to either overlook the designers
                entirely or to flatten them into simple caricatures. <hi rend="italic">Computing
                    Taste</hi> challenges such perspectives by providing a far more complex portrait
                – one that Seaver did not necessarily anticipate from the outset.</p>
         
         <p><quote rend="block">I came to Whisper looking to understand how people like Ed
                    and his colleagues thought about taste… I assumed that theories of taste would
                    map neatly on to techniques and data sources: if you thought that people liked
                    music because of how it sounded, then you’d make a system that analyzed audio
                    data; if you thought they liked music to fit in with their friends, then you
                    might try to acquire social network data… But what I found at Whisper, and
                    across the industry, was not so straightforward. <ptr target="#seaver2022" loc="xiii"/></quote>
            </p></div>
         
         <div>
            <head>Major Themes</head>
            
         <p>Each of the six chapters of the book examines a facet of how the designers of music
                recommendation systems think about music, taste, and the computational systems they
                develop. Chapter topics include the need to assist users in navigating <q>too much
                music,</q> the capture of users’ attention, the mathematical nature of music, and the
                <q>space</q> of musical genres. Each chapter begins with an illustration of each theme
                that draws from Seaver’s field work, followed by extended analysis and
                interpretation that leverage constructs and insights from a broad body of humanities
                scholarship. For example, in Chapter 1 he connects the origins of music
                recommendation in the mid-20th century to
                contemporaneous developments in computing, particularly the emergence of
                Cybernetics. In Chapter 5 he compares the ways that technologists conceptualize the
                <q>space</q> of music genres to anthropological and sociological theories of cultural
                spaces (such as those of Bourdieu). A theoretical thread that runs throughout the
                book is the insight from Technology Studies that we ought to think of technologies
                as sociotechnical systems: assemblages of human and technical components <ptr target="#pinch_bijker1984"/>. Talk of <q>computer algorithms</q> too often obscures the human actors that
                not only design the technical components but actively and continuously manage and
                maintain them.</p>
            
            
         <p>All six chapters bring insights, but several are particularly worth highlighting. The
                first two chapters provide a careful and novel analysis on the tensions that exist
                in how designers think about the <q>captivating algorithms</q> that they create. In
                Chapter 1, Seaver describes how recommendation systems are often positioned as
                assisting audiophiles navigate the overwhelming catalog of music that they can
                access. The concern that humans are practically drowning in a sea of information
                (musical or otherwise) is, as Seaver points out, a perennial one, and he traces the
                development of music recommendation services, since the early 1990s, that have
                sought to help users navigate the problem of <q>too much music.</q> Contemporary
                algorithmic methods are largely continuous with their predecessors, though their
                technical methods differ. Their designers employ similar rhetoric about the goal of
                helping users navigate a bewildering array of options. The enduring promise is that
                recommendation systems will help users not only find the music they already like,
                but discover new music that they never would have otherwise encountered.</p>
         
            
            <p>Yet for all the rhetoric about helping users navigate and make new discoveries, there
                is also a discourse about using algorithms to get users <q>hooked</q> on the music
                service. This is not the algorithm of musical discovery, but the <q>captivating
                algorithm </q>of the attention economy. Much, of course, has been written on the
                subject of attention-capturing algorithms [e.g., <ptr target="#zuboff2019"/>], and Seaver
                acknowledges and discusses that work. But rather than critique the social
                consequences of the algorithms, Seaver works to understand how their designers
                square their captivating function with their goal of empowering users to explore the
                vast <q>musical landscape</q> (Chapter 5 specifically addresses spatial metaphors of
                music). </p>
            
            
         <p>In Chapter 2, Seaver uses anthropological studies of traps as a lens to interpret how
                designers approach the task of captivation (building on work that he previously
                published in 2019). The key insight is that the designer needs a model of
                that-which-is-to-be-trapped, because the trap needs to be able to lure its intended,
                and only its intended, prey. This is why designers of recommendation algorithms need
                to model their users, including the different kinds of users that might exist. The
                trap metaphor is also instructive because it draws attention to the array of traps
                that can be made. A trap need not kill or even injure or even extensively confine
                its prey. In fact, recommendation algorithms might be best conceptualized as the
                <q>pastoral</q> form of trap:</p>
            
            
         <p><quote rend="block">Pastoral enclosure is a kind of nonlethal, ongoing
                    relationship aimed at growing the number of creatures enclosed through the
                    careful social organization of animal and environment… Like reindeer
                    pastoralists, the makers of recommender systems do not want to annihilate their
                    prey. They want to keep them around and grow their numbers, through the artful
                    production of captivating environments that at once limit and facilitate life.
                    <ptr target="#seaver2022" loc="71"/></quote></p>
            
            
         <p>From this perspective, the algorithmic trapper/designer is not a jailer working to
                constrain human autonomy, but a persuader trying to coax music listeners to <q>hang
                around</q> <ptr target="#seaver2022" loc="50"/>. So, if you want users to hang around, do you give them
                what is familiar, or try to broaden their horizons? Perhaps some users are content
                to just stay in familiar territory while others actively want to discover new music.
                Building the right pastoral enclosure means that designers need to model those
                different user orientations – the subject of Chapter 3.</p>
            
            
         <p>This brief overview illustrates the approach that Seaver takes throughout <hi rend="italic">Computing Taste</hi>. He draws connections between how the
                technologies are designed, the designers’ beliefs and intentions, and humanities
                perspectives that provide insight into how the pieces fit together. He does not
                hesitate to critique the technologists’ perspectives and beliefs when critique is
                warranted, drawing attention to inconsistencies, blind spots, and misguided
                assumptions. At the same time, he does not set the designers up as antagonists
                (like, say, <ptr target="#rushkoff2022"/>). Rather, Seaver creates a portrayal of earnest people
                who are passionate about music and who believe wholeheartedly in the value of their
                work. <hi rend="italic">Computing Taste</hi> shows how those technologists use their
                beliefs to navigate the challenges and complications of their technical projects.
                And while they may often be naïve about the social effects of the technologies they
                create, the way that they think about their work is anything but simplistic or
                cynical.</p>
         </div>
         
         
         <div>
            <head>Contributions to Digital Humanities</head>
            
         <p>The domain of music brings its own peculiarities, but <hi rend="italic">Computing
                    Taste</hi> offers many tools and insights that are useful for digital humanities
                scholarship more broadly, especially for inquiries into now-ubiquitous algorithmic
                systems. Perhaps the most wide-reaching contribution is its call to take seriously
                the beliefs, ways of thinking, and ways of talking (including the metaphors) of
                technology designers. Those ways of thinking and speaking matter a great deal
                because they wind up being knitted into the technical systems they create. And yes,
                they are worthy of scrutiny and critique, but they are also worthy of being
                understood. As Seaver shows, they are often far more complex than they at first
                appear.</p>
            
            
         <p>Exemplifying this point is Seaver’s examination (in Chapter 4) of the use of machine
                learning to create systems that can detect musical genre. Machine learning systems
                are often described as <q>black boxes</q> because it is extremely difficult to comprehend
                why they produce the classifications (e.g., genre) that they do. And yet, Seaver’s
                analysis reveals how machine learning remains a sociotechnical system. Human
                designers decide not only what to feed into the machine learning algorithm, but
                <q>tune</q> its outputs so that they conform to their expectations. The ways that the
                designers think about genre and hear music become intertwined with the algorithm.
                They use their ways of thinking and listening to detect, interpret, and correct
                unexpected results. The designers are also <q>tuned</q> by their technologies as they
                strain to listen for and comprehend what the algorithm is <q>hearing.</q></p>
            
            
         <p>Careful considerations of the complex and ongoing interactions between technology and
                designer need to be central to our analyses and critiques of algorithmic systems
                (machine learning or otherwise). Those systems are shaped and continuously
                maintained by the beliefs, approaches, and discourses of the technologists who
                develop them. A deeper understanding of those designers’ cultures can not only
                enrich our analyses and critiques, but also point the way toward alternative
                futures. What kinds of music streaming services might we have if they were built up
                from a different set of beliefs and metaphors about music, taste, and computing? </p></div>
         
      </body>
      

      
      <back>
         <listBibl>
          
               
               <bibl xml:id="gaw2022" label="Gaw 2022">Gaw, F. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Algorithmic Logics and the Construction
                  of Cultural Taste of the Netflix Recommender System</title>, <hi rend="italic">Media,
                     Culture &amp; Society</hi>, 44(4), pp. 706-725.
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/01634437211053767">https://doi.org/10.1177/01634437211053767</ref></bibl>
               
               
               <bibl xml:id="giblin_doctorow2022" label="Giblin and Doctorow 2022">Giblin, R., and Doctorow, C. (2022)
                  <title rend="italic">Chokepoint Capitalism: How Big Tech and Big Content Captured Creative Labor Markets and How We’ll Win Them Back.</title> Boston,
                  MA: Beacon Press.</bibl>
               
               
               <bibl xml:id="pajkovic2022" label="Pajkovic 2022">Pajkovic, N. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Algorithms and Taste-making:
                  Exposing the Netflix Recommender System’s Operational Logics</title>, <hi rend="italic">Convergence</hi>, 28(1), pp. 214-235. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/13548565211014464">https://doi.org/10.1177/13548565211014464</ref></bibl>
               
               <bibl xml:id="pinch_bijker1984" label="Pinch and Bijker 1984">Pinch, T. J. and Bijker, W. E. (1984) <title rend="quotes">The
                  Social Construction of Facts and Artefacts: Or How the Sociology of Science and the
                  Sociology of Technology Might Benefit Each Other</title>, <hi rend="italic">Social Studies
                     of Science</hi>, 14(3), pp. 399– 441.</bibl>
               
               
               <bibl xml:id="rushkoff2022" label="Rushkoff 2022"> Rushkoff, D. (2022)
                  <hi rend="italic">Survival of the Richest: Escape Fantasies of the Tech Billionaires. </hi>New
                  York, NY: W. W. Norton &amp; Company.</bibl>
               
               
               <bibl xml:id="seaver2019" label="Seaver 2019"> Seaver, N. (2019). <title rend="quotes">Captivating Algorithms:
                  Recommender Systems as Traps</title>, <hi rend="italic">Journal of Material Culture</hi>,
                  24(4), pp. 421-436. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1359183518820366">https://doi.org/10.1177/1359183518820366</ref></bibl>
               
               
               <bibl xml:id="seaver2022" label="Seaver 2022"> Seaver, N. (2022) <hi rend="italic">Computing Taste:
                  Algorithms and the Makers of Music Recommendation.</hi> Chicago, IL: University
                  of Chicago Press.</bibl>
               
               
               <bibl xml:id="zuboff2019" label="Zuboff 2019"> Zuboff, S. (2019) <hi rend="italic">The Age of
                  Surveillance Capitalism: The Fight for a Human Future at the New Frontier of
                  Power.</hi> New York, NY: Public Affairs.</bibl>
            
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
