<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">An Integral Web-map for the Analysis of Spatial
               Change over Time in a Complex Built Environment: Digital Samos</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Estefanía <dhq:family>López Salas</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2889-6465</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Universidade da Coruña</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>estefania.lsalas@udc.es</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Estefanía López Salas is Assistant Professor at the Department of Architectural
                     Design, Urbanism and Composition, Universidade da Coruña (UDC, Spain). BA
                     (hons) in Architecture (2009), MA in Architectural Restoration (2010) and PhD
                     (hons) from Universidade da Coruña (2015). Her research is currently devoted to
                     the study of Galician cultural heritage sites through digital technologies in
                     order to face new art-historical questions as well as to promote the
                     understanding of their historical and cultural significance.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000652</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               >017</idno>
            <idno type="issue">2</idno>
            <date when="2023-05-26">26 May 2023</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>Digital Art and Architectural History</item>
                  <item>Digital Visualization</item>
                  <item>Spatiotemporal Web-Mapping</item>
                  <item>Spanish Monastic Architecture</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000652/000652.xml"
               >GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>The paper focuses on a prototype interactive web-map developed for the presentation
               and dissemination of architectural transformations at the monastic site of San Julián
               de Samos in north-western Spain. The paper’s central argument offers a response to
               questions regarding why and how to create an interactive web-map in the field of
               architectural history through a particular case study. The paper is organized into
               three main parts. It first presents the project focus on spatiotemporal analysis of a
               centuries-old Spanish monastic site. Second part is devoted to the specific domain of
               web-mapping tools and why they can help us to better make sense of complex built
               environments that humans have formed and re-formed over time. After that, we explain
               how we faced the process of creating an integral scientific web-map that goes beyond
               static 2D representations of a multi-layered past physical realm in a definitive
               publication, the challenges we faced, and the proposed future developments. The
               prototype web-map of Digital Samos integrates the graphic features of spatial objects
               with source data in a web publication platform where the reader is granted accessed
               to fully uncover, interact with, and learn about a historically rich monastic
               palimpsest.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>The paper focuses on a prototype interactive web-map of the monastic site of San
               Julián de Samos in north-western Spain and offers a response to questions regarding
               why and how to create an interactive web-map in the field of architectural history
               through a particular case study.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>The project Digital Samos is devoted to study the monastic site of San Julián de
               Samos, which is one of the most ancient and largest monasteries in Spain. We examine
               the evolving nature of the monastic architecture along with its surrounding
               environment, the sacred precinct, and the nearby village. This monastic compound has
               been written and re-written through continuous spatial changes over the course of
               centuries. As a consequence, Samos is currently a palimpsest, that is, a complex
               built environment defined by multiple historical layers. </p>
            <p>Despite the monastery as a single entity has been largely examined by scholars since
               the late 19th century onwards,<note> For the history of the monastery of San Julián
                  de Samos see: <ptr target="#ariasarias1950"/>, <ptr target="#ariascuenllas1992"/>,
                     <ptr target="#castro1912"/>, <ptr target="#duran1947"/>, <ptr
                     target="#folgardelacalle2006"/>, <ptr target="#folgardelacalle_goydiz2008"/>,
                     <ptr target="#lopezpelaez1894"/>, <ptr target="#portillacosta1978"/>, <ptr
                     target="#portillacosta2003"/>.</note> the monastic site as a totality of the
               religious buildings and their agricultural plots, the nearby urban tissue, the
               geographical setting, and the surrounding landscape, was not previously addressed
               when the present project began. This is probably due to the difficulties that
               spatiotemporal analysis involves in the case of built environments defined by layers
               that cross millennia.</p>
            <p>To uncover and reconstruct those historical layers in spatial and temporal terms, we
               utilize a multidisciplinary approach that combines historical sources, evidence-based
               investigation, and digital technologies. Historical sources related to monastic
               architecture and landscape at Samos are diverse and, sometimes, scarce, incomplete,
               or uncertain. The extant fragments of past monastic compounds may appear currently
               decontextualized, dispersed, hidden, or even lost. As a consequence, to investigate
               and reconstruct those multiple layers poses a set of challenges that concerns both
               urban history and architectural history. Digital tools can help us to overcome those
               challenges.</p>
            <p>Through computer-aided design (CAD) tools we created a series of phased 2D maps and
               3D models that visualize the main stages of the monastic site evolution from the High
               Middle Ages to the early 21st century. These digital visualizations help us, as
               scholars, to gain a better understanding of the processes by which the monastic site
               of San Julián de Samos was designed, understood, changed, and experienced over time
               as a totality of topography, architecture, and human history.<note> The research
                  project was started in: <ptr target="#lopezsalas2015"/>.</note> A number of
               initiatives has also demonstrated in recent decades that the communication of
               knowledge with digital methods in academia can promote the understanding of cultural
               heritage and spread awareness of the importance of preserving and protecting
               historical architecture along with its context outside academia.<note> See, for
                  example: <ptr target="#borin2016"/>
                  <ptr target="#calabi2009"/>
                  <ptr target="#harris_2015"/>
                  <ptr target="#kingetal2016"/>
                  <ptr target="#monteleoneetal2016"/>
                  <ptr target="#svalduz2013"/>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In June 2018, we began a new in-process work for the project with the creation of an
               interactive web-map, hosted by Universidade da Coruña at <ref
                  target="https://digitalsamos.udc.es/interactive_map.html"
                  >https://digitalsamos.udc.es/interactive_map.html</ref>.<note> The Digital Samos
                  project is accessible at: <ref target="https://digitalsamos.udc.es/index.html"
                     >https://digitalsamos.udc.es/index.html</ref>. In August 2018, it was selected
                  by the Getty Foundation to feature its Digital Art History Initiative page, <ref
                     target="https://www.getty.edu/foundation/initiatives/current/dah/index.html"
                     >https://www.getty.edu/foundation/initiatives/current/dah/index.html</ref>. In
                  February 2020, it was awarded with a special mention in the second edition of the
                  Hispanic Digital Humanities Prizes, HDH 2020.</note> This new stage emerged from
               our participation in the Getty Summer Institute <title rend="quotes">Advanced Topics
                  in Digital Art History: 3D (Geo)Spatial Networks</title>
               <ptr target="#dukeuniversity2018"/>, where instructors and participants illustrated
               how web-based platforms have become essential vehicles for presentation and
               dissemination of research about architectural heritage. They can be also thought and
               designed as tools to ensure the intellectual integrity of computer-based
               visualization outcomes in research and communication of urban and architectural
               history <ptr target="#jaskotetal2018"/>.</p>
            <p>In addition, an issue of major concern in the architectural community and virtual
               heritage domain at large is how we can publish graphic materials such as vector
               plans, 3D models, or geospatial historical maps in such a way that their rigor is
               clear to their full consideration as research arguments. Print and online
               publications not only put a limit on the number of figures or illustrations to be
               published per article, but they also establish specific types of image file formats,
               which are generally raster graphics. The first issue — number — gives priority to
               prose in scientific publications. This fact usually leads to the consideration of
               graphic materials or multimedia outputs as an accompaniment to the text, but not the
               research arguments themselves <ptr target="#chattopadhyay2012"/>
               <ptr target="#staley2015" loc="p. 123–127"/>
               <ptr target="#sullivanetal2017"/>. </p>
            <p>As Freddolini recently pointed out, <quote rend="inline">… the activity of writing
                  involves diverse aspects that include the possible ways to visualize and
                  disseminate my research… Tools for data visualization, to cite only one example,
                  are not only a corollary –or a demonstration– of what I <q>write</q>, but
                  essential components of the arguments I aim to create…</quote>
               <ptr target="#helmreich2021" loc="p. 176"/>. However, the use of common image file
               formats force researchers in those fields to convert their original vector CAD
               architectural plans, graphic 3D models reconstructions, or geospatial GIS historical
               maps into fixed images when they aim to publish their work. As a consequence,
               historical data and the different types of thinking and interpretation that were made
               and integrated in the computer-aided design visual materials, through layers,
               categories, or attributes, are generally lost. </p>
            <p>This is a common challenge we faced when we tried to communicate the results of our
               research about the monastic site of San Julián de Samos. The interactive web-map of
               Digital Samos is created to overcome that challenge through the use of web-mapping
               tools, while it also promotes the understanding of the historical site among scholars
               and public. It displays the extensive knowledge we acquired about this complex built
               environment through on-site and archival research into a digital publication, in
               which the <q>reader</q> is granted access to the evolution of the historical site. In
               addition to cartographic display showing detailed information about the setting
               topography and the compound of the monastic site (buildings, precinct, and village),
               the web-map aims to become a more scientific successor to the phased CAD maps we
               previously created. By taking advantage of the potentials of the digital domain, we
               try to overcome the limitations of the traditional series of fixed images in which we
               converted the CAD maps for prior dissemination of our research. Instead of static
               phased maps that revealed the complexity of spatiotemporal changes by means of time
               fragmentation or color coding design, the prototype web-map we present in this paper
               walks toward a more integral and effective online interface, where the final user is
               able to interact with space, time, scale, layers, and sources. All spatial entities
               are displayed in the form of web graphic features with attributes with historical
               data and interpretation within one single digital output. </p>
            <p>The paper is organized into three main parts. First, we present the project focus on
               the spatiotemporal analysis of a centuries-old Spanish monastic site and its main
               outcomes so far. Second part is devoted to the specific domain of web-mapping tools.
               Based on related works and projects in the field, we show how web-mapping can help us
               to better make sense of complex built environments that humans have formed and
               re-formed over time. As this point we also connect our project to existing literature
               in Spatial Humanities on deep mapping, thereby contextualizing the present case
               study. Then, we explain how we faced the process of creating an integral scientific
               web-map for Digital Samos that goes beyond static 2D representations of a
               multi-layered past physical realm in a definitive publication. We present the
               workflow, its potential, and pitfalls. Finally, we discussed the challenges, the
               present limitations, and the future developments of what we consider a functional
               prototype web-map for spatiotemporal analysis, presentation, and dissemination in the
               field of digital art and architectural history, while we also summarize why this
               project is valuable as a case study. The web-map is here conceived as a means for
               public outreach, a self-explanatory visual product, in which accessibility,
               transparency, legibility, and integrity of visual and textual spatial data in a
               digital environment aims to promote a fuller understanding of the process that
               defined the past monastic site(s).<note> By following the principles of the: <ptr
                     target="#londonchapter2009"/> and <ptr target="#sevilleprinciples2011"
                  />.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>San Julián de Samos beyond historical practice </head>
            <p>The main art historical question in the project San Julián de Samos is spatial change
               over time of a historical monastic site that includes the monastic buildings, the
               sacred precinct, the nearby village, and the surrounding rural area (Figure 1). The
               monastery was founded before the 7th century and, like most religious houses, it
               changed across its long life through constant constructions and re-constructions.
               Studying the question of spatial change over time is crucial to analyze how the site
               was conceived, understood and experienced, as a sum of different pieces (monastic
               buildings, topography, urban tissue, geographical features) instead of as a single
               artifact (Figure 2).</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Google Satellite maps showing the location of the monastery of San Julián de
                  Samos in progressive closeness to the country (Spain), the province (Galicia) and
                  the place (Samos).</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>A set of three Google map screencaps showing the location of the monastery
                  of San Julián de Samos, increasingly zoomed in from left to right.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>The monastery of San Julián de Samos and its present context. Photograph: June
                  2011, the author.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>A color photograph of the monastery of San Julián de Samos. The site is seen
                  at a distance and form slightly above, as though the photographer is on a hill
                  above the site. A group of buildings of various layout and construction are seen
                  in a small valley between green forested hills.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>The first part of our research process comprised the collection of historical and
               contemporary sources. Historical ones are very disparate from each other, such as
               building contracts, rental agreements, books of demarcations, cadasters, historical
               photographs, old maps, expropriation records, and civil engineering projects.
               Contemporary sources collected are images, plans, on-site investigation, measure
               surveys, remains, testimonies, scientific papers, book chapters, etc.</p>
            <p>The second part of the research process was focused on generating 2D maps and 3D
               models with Computer-Aided Design programs, that is digital tools, to recreate the
               multiples phases of spatial change of this monastic site over time. The monastic site
               was re-created and then visualized through static images of plans/maps and
               renderings, one per each main phase of transformation (Figures 3 and 4). We used a
               code for 2D map drawing that is comprised of different colored lines. Each colored
               line has a different meaning about the knowledge it represents. For example, dark and
               grey lines visualize buildings that are extant nowadays, that is evidence. On the
               contrary, brown and orange lines are used to draw hypothetical parts of the monastic
               site. We also used a different color to represent those monastic proposals that were
               planned but not built (Figure 5). </p>
            <figure>
               <head>A selection of phased computer-aided design 2D maps of the monastic site of San
                  Julián de Samos from Middles Ages to early 18th century. Images: the
                  author.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>A selection of phased 3D reconstructions of the monastic site of San Julián de
                  Samos from Middles Ages to early 18th century. Images: the author.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>Vector map/plan generated with AutoCAD of the monastic site at Samos in the
                  second half of the 16th century along with the associated layers of entities and
                  colors classified in accordance with the status of the knowledge that they
                  represent (evidence vs hypothesis). Images: the author.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>Through this methodology we were able to recover the lost monastic compound of the
               Late Middle Ages from which only some remains are extant currently <ptr
                  target="#lopezsalas2013"/>. We could analyze the reasons behind the architectural
               reform that took place in the late 15th century and its consequences on the
               definition of a new monastic site <ptr target="#lopezsalas2017a"/>. We discovered the
               role of monks in the creation and evolution of the sacred precinct and the immediate
               village of Samos, as urban planners <ptr target="#lopezsalas2017b"/>
               <ptr target="#lopezsalas2017c"/>. We came to understand the multiple processes that
               surrounded the replacement of the Romanesque church and cloister by bigger buildings,
               and the role that context, topography, and geographical features played in the
               monastic design of the 18th century. We also analyzed through digital representation
               how a proposed but unbuilt fourth cloister would have changed completely the
               historical monastic realm, as well as the losses that secularization brought to
               architecture and monastic landscape in the 19th century <ptr
                  target="#lopezsalas2017d"/>
               <ptr target="#lopezsalas2017e"/>
               <ptr target="#lopezsalas2017f"/>. </p>
            <p>The new knowledge was acquired in the process of making the maps and models due to
               the reasoning that was applied to create them from sources and interpretations while
               also filling the gaps caused by ambiguity, uncertainty, or absence of data. This is
               what Elena Svalduz called <quote rend="inline">a new form of intellectual reasoning
                  through modeling</quote> or representation of past spaces by means of digital
               visualization tools <ptr target="#svalduz2018" loc="p. 36"/>. We also consider that
               most of this new knowledge in the form of visual products must be communicated from
               scholars to the scientific community and general public without losing the potential
               of the visual sense. However, scientific publications prioritize textual analysis as
               it also happens in the evaluation of knowledge production within academia, where
               images, videos, maps, or models that results from serious research are rarely
               considered as rigorous as texts. The inclusion of visual data in publications is
               usually restricted to a specific number of figures and its presentation is also
               limited by widely used raster image formats instead of vector graphics.</p>
            <p>In our case, the project outcomes reveal the potential of digital visualization for
               art-historical academic research as we have largely published in paper conferences,
               journal articles, and book chapters.<note> A comprehensive list of publications and
                  communications related to the research carried out in Digital Samos is available
                  at the project website: <title rend="quotes">Articles and Book Chapters,</title>
                  <ref target="https://digitalsamos.udc.es/research_publications.html"
                     >https://digitalsamos.udc.es/research_publications.html</ref>, <title
                     rend="quotes">Congresses, Workshops, Seminars and Conferences,</title>
                  <ref target="https://digitalsamos.udc.es/research_congresses.html"
                     >https://digitalsamos.udc.es/research_congresses.html</ref>.</note> However,
               the lack of funds and the high cost of print publication prevented us from presenting
               the project along with its sources and results in any complete fashion so far. The
               creation of a web presence could provide, we think, an ideal solution to not only
               make the research outcomes about Samos accessible and better known in and outside
               academia, but also to test a new form of publication beyond the limits of scientific
               journals in what refers to the dissemination of visual-centered projects, where
               drawings, maps, images, and digital graphic outputs are not a complement of the text,
               but a new form of scholarly production to be recognized as rigorous as textual
               research <ptr target="#chattopadhyay2012"/>
               <ptr target="#staley2015" loc="p. 123–127"/>
               <ptr target="#sullivanetal2017"/>. In addition, we should not forget that each form
               of communication can do something that the other cannot and, for that reason, both
               should be considered complementary, and neither superior, as Ethington and Toyosawa
               point out in their comparison of cartography, which operates by simultaneity and
               juxtaposition, and semantic text, which is syntactically linear and narratological
                  <ptr target="#ethington_toyosawa2015" loc="p. 75"/>. In this way the idea of
               creating an interactive web-map of the spatiotemporal changes at the monastery of San
               Julián de Samos was born.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>References and goals for Digital Samos web-map</head>
            <p>Working with 2D maps and 3D models poses a set of challenges in publication. The main
               one is the file format. While maps and models that reconstruct past spaces are
               usually created with computer-aided design or 3D computer graphics software toolsets,
               print and online scientific journals mainly display these types of digital products
               in the form of images, that is, fixed visual representations of real or imagined past
               spaces. None of the data on which the generation of the digital product was based on,
               or the interpretations the scholars made through various types of thinking, are
               usually published along with the images. They may be explained in the prose narrative
               that the images accompany, but as two entities separately <ptr
                  target="#mcclure_worthey2019"/>. </p>
            <p>This fact leads to a main difference between the map or model made by the scholar
               with the final map or model to be published in what refers to information and
               interpretation. It also shows another difference, which is not always visible,
               between the way we display and read text and images in scientific publications. While
               we are able to quote any excerpt of the text to cite the source or sources in which
               our argument is based, such quotation is not possible in the case of spatial features
               that define the image of a 2D map or a 3D model. As a consequence, the connection
               between our visual arguments and their evidence is lost <ptr
                  target="#mcclure_worthey2019"/>, although it is fundamental to guarantee the rigor
               and transparency of scholarly publication. </p>
            <p>This is an issue of major concern in the computer-based visualization of cultural
               heritage research community that both the London Chapter (2009) and the Principles of
               Seville (2011) highlight <ptr target="#londonchapter2009"/>
               <ptr target="#sevilleprinciples2011"/>
               <ptr target="#lanjouw_waagen2021"/>. Sufficient information to document and
               disseminate computer-aided visualization outcomes is needed to enable the
               understanding of the relationship between research sources, implicit knowledge,
               explicit reasoning, and visualization-based outcomes, but also to facilitate the
               recognition of accuracy in the field. </p>
            <p>The London Chapter (2009) points out that a first way to accomplish this challenge is
               through the publication of a two-dimensional record of the computer-based
               visualization outputs along with the methods used, and the interpretations made <ptr
                  target="#londonchapter2009"/>. However, in this paper we propose to create a
               web-map were data and interpretations embedded during the generation of phased CAD
               maps for spatiotemporal analysis at Samos are also displayed when the online
               publication is faced. </p>
            <p>This challenge has already been accomplished by a number of research teams in
               historical studies about complex built environments with different purposes and
               results. Such is the case of the <title rend="quotes">Digitally Encoded Census
                  Information and Mapping Archive</title> (DECIMA), which was designed as a research
               tool for historians interested in early modern Florence.<note> University of Toronto,
                  DECIMA, <ref target="https://decima-map.net/"
                  >https://decima-map.net/</ref>.</note> DECIMA website is an open-access platform.
               In the so-called mapping tool, users can interact with mapped data from three
               censuses of 1551, 1561, and 1563. These are displayed on a historical map of the city
               from 1584 georeferenced onto a contemporary one <ptr target="#pecile2018"/>. The
               design of DECIMA database and web platform enables users to display one census data
               layer or a group of them. As we zoom in the map, it is also possible to click on
               projected points with a cursor and a data table with associated census information
               about residents and properties will be displayed. In addition to that, DECIMA offers
               a data query tool for interactive analysis about ownership, shops, occupation,
               property values, or gender. It has already proved to be a powerful analytical tool
               that, even from simple questions, leads to new interpretations and knowledge about
               the modern Florence, its social conditions and relations <ptr
                  target="#terpstra_rose2018"/>. However, spatial features are simplified in the
               form of dots which is enough for the analysis of human movement or economic activity
               in the past city, but not for the study of the built environment in spatial
               terms.</p>
            <p>In this sense, another relevant example is the project <title rend="quotes"
                  >Visualizing the Mountain Estate: Landscape, Architecture and Experience in
                  Chengde.</title> Their authors are developing an interactive web platform thought
               and designed as a tool for evolving research and discovery in a historical
                  environment.<note> Office of Information, Knowledge and Library Services (OIKLS),
                  NTU Singapore. Visualizing the Mountain Estate. Landscape, Architecture, and
                  Experience in Chengde, <ref target="https://blogs.ntu.edu.sg/bssz/"
                     >https://blogs.ntu.edu.sg/bssz/</ref>.</note> The project is devoted to study
               an important Qing Dynasty Imperial Park in Chengde (China) that was built in multiple
               phases over the most part the eighteenth century and then deconstructed and
               reconstructed in the following two centuries. To approach how this imperial park was
               conceived, understood and experienced, the web-map of this project visualizes the
               whole built park environment along with its topography and hydrology over a current
               orthophotograph. The platform provides users with a layer control to select the type
               of landscape feature to visualize (buildings, walls, rivers, islands, lakes...).
               Moreover, data can be filtered by structure type, construction data and reign for
               selected display. As we interact with the map, it is also possible to click on each
               building and a pop-up with associated data is opened. Each pop-up shows organized
               relevant information as well as a link to extended textual data and non-textual
               outputs about the selected building to explore the spatial environment at will. This
               is a work in progress and its results are still to come, but the main aim is to
               enable researchers and users to query the database in the future and, by doing so, to
               address new questions of the historical environment through computational analysis
               and interactive presentation <ptr target="#whitemanetal2018"/>. </p>
            <p>In the particular field of monastic architecture, Wulfman, Mylonas, Loyer, Bonde, and
               Maines developed the MonArch Project website to explore the ways in which complex
               relationships among textual, architectural, and archaeological evidence can be
               represented in non-traditional formats to create a new form of scholarly expression
               for their work about the Abbey of Saint-Jean-des-Vignes in Soissons (France) <ptr
                  target="#wulfmanetal2007"/>. They realized that archaeological evidence supports
               and illustrates the textual narrative at the same time that the latter contextualizes
               the archaeology and monastic architecture, so they proposed a web infrastructure that
               allows authors to present their arguments and also users of the website to develop
               their own interpretations around monasticism, the abbey’s structures, place,
               community, and economy based on an interactive interface.<note> Brown University, The
                  MonArch Project, <ref target="http://monarch.brown.edu/"
                     >http://monarch.brown.edu/</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This project demonstrates the potential of digital representation in a web-context to
               publish detailed corpora of material findings, to present the spatial dimensions of
               social relationships, and to recover the human actions performed in the past <ptr
                  target="#bondeetal2009"/>. However, in what refers to the presentation and
               dissemination of the past architectural spaces the results are limited. They created
               an interactive site plan of the Romanesque abbey with a time slider and clickable
               phases showing some evidence options for that period, but the user is not able to
               directly interact with each spatial element or to have access to historical or
               excavated data from the visual argument, so the exploratory possibilities are somehow
               restricted as well as the provision of information to understand the nature of
               evidence and hypothesis.</p>
            <p>Another promising project is an in-process collaborative platform, called SIG 4D,
               presented by Rollier-Hanselmann, Petty, Mazuir, Faucher, and Coulais for the case
               study of Cluny Abbey (France), considered the greatest building of European
               Christendom in the 12th century <ptr target="#rollierhanselmannetal2014"/>. By using
               the TerraExplorer Pro software, they try to integrate 2D maps and 3D models created
               from historical data and archaeological excavations into one single GIS database and
               research system. Their aim is to offer scholars a digital tool for research analysis,
               where the access to disparate data is possible as well as its comparison to better
               understand the Cluniac site. The project is focused on studying the relationship
               between the abbey and the surrounding landscape through the hybrid nature of the
               archaeological artefacts. For this purpose, they argue that it is essential the
               collaboration and the combination of data coming from different disciplines. In the
               digital realm, the authors also recognize that the diversity of data and its
               integration in a single geographic system bring technical difficulties they still
               have to solve. Web-mapping and online dissemination of the SIG 4D seem to be
               additional aims as they presented in the project workflow <ptr
                  target="#rollierhanselmannetal2014" loc="p. 174"/>, but no access to the system is
               accessible yet.</p>
            <p>The third and last case study that this state of the art comprises is the Sera
               project, led by José Ignacio Cabezón <ptr target="#budapesti2019" loc="p. 28–29"
                  />.<note> The Tibetan &amp; Himalayan Library, Sera Monastery, <ref
                     target="https://www.thlib.org/places/monasteries/sera/"
                     >https://www.thlib.org/places/monasteries/sera/</ref>
               </note> It is focused on Sera, one of the largest and most important monasteries in
               the Tibetan world. Cabezón created a multimedia, interactive database that allows
               users to explore different aspects of Sera: its physical layout, history, material
               culture, educational system, and ritual life that, on the whole, defined what he
               called the richness and complexity of Tibetan monastic life.<note> Cabezón, J. I.,
                     <title rend="quotes">Sera Monastery Project Overview,</title>
                  <ref
                     target="https://www.thlib.org/places/monasteries/sera/about/wiki/sera%20monastery%20project%20overview.html"
                     >https://www.thlib.org/places/monasteries/sera/about/wiki/sera%20monastery%20project%20overview.html</ref>
               </note> The project includes a section devoted to the physical space of the
               monastery. Sera buildings are classified according to their form into: compounds,
               complexes, or freestanding structures.<note> Cabezón, J. I., <title rend="quotes">The
                     Space of Sera (Se ra’i khor yug),</title>
                  <ref
                     target="https://www.thlib.org/places/monasteries/sera/spaces/%23!essay=/cabezon/sera/spaces/s/b4"
                     >https://www.thlib.org/places/monasteries/sera/spaces/#!essay=/cabezon/sera/spaces/s/b4</ref>
               </note> A compound is said to be an enclosure, that is, a single building or a group
               of adjoining buildings with an interior courtyard, such as the main regional houses,
               apartments, or lama residences. A complex is a group of buildings that share some
               kind of association, but no necessarily adjoining and enclosed. Freestanding
               buildings are single structures with no association to nearby ones and with no
               perimeter wall. </p>
            <p>The architecture of Sera is represented in an interactive web-map.<note> The Tibetan
                  &amp; Himalayan Library, Sera Interactive Map, <ref
                     target="https://www.thlib.org/places/monasteries/sera/spaces/map/"
                     >https://www.thlib.org/places/monasteries/sera/spaces/map/</ref>
               </note> They gathered data of mayor structures within the monastery, images, GPS
               readings, and field notes during a field trip that, later on, were the foundation to
               develop an image catalogue and the narrative descriptions of each building, compound,
               and complex of the monastery. Then, they created a digital map of the monastic site
               using a GIS software that was finally converted into a web-deliverable, flash map of
               the monastic architecture. The map is said to integrated the narrative descriptions
               and the image database, however it is no longer working after Adobe Flash Player was
               retired in 2020. This is also what happened with the MonArch Project website.<note>
                  Brown University, The MonArch Project, <ref target="http://monarch.brown.edu/site"
                     >http://monarch.brown.edu/site</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The previous examples demonstrate the potentials of a web-map, not only as a means to
               access and showcase a project, but also as a research tool that allows public to
               explore, interpret, and analyze data in the wholeness of each case study, to pose
               novel questions, and to create new ways to engage with and gain knowledge about
               historical built environments. They also illustrate different ways to address the
               representation of architectural space and spatiotemporal analysis in a web context
               mainly from archaeological excavations and historical data. Different software tools
               were used in each case study in accordance with data and purposes of analysis, but
               also depending on funding. Moreover, while web-maps of DECIMA and Mountain Estate are
               fully functional, the MonArch and Sera Projects are deprecated and the SIG 4D for
               Cluny Abbey seems to be a desktop system on the way to being transformed into a
               web-map. A common concern in these projects is looking for new forms of publication
               in what refers to 2D maps that, first, enables interaction with different source of
               data, and secondly, aims to open new paths for query and exploration (Figure 6). </p>
            <p>The four examples are efforts to build increasingly more complex maps of visible and
               invisible aspects of a place. They aspire to be more-than-representational and they
               put emphasis on one particular user interaction: exploration. Anyone who approaches
               these maps is given various possible paths to <q>dive within</q> them and explore
               different questions. We argue that they are attempts to move towards more integrated
               spatial frameworks for research while they also illustrate some challenges and
               potentials of what has recently emerged as deep mapping practices in the field of
               Spatial Humanities <ptr target="#bodenhamer2010"/>
               <ptr target="#bodenhameretal2013"/>
               <ptr target="#bodenhameretal2015"/>
               <ptr target="#murrietaflores_martins2019"/>
               <ptr target="#roberts2016"/>.<note> This brief historiographic context related to
                  deep mapping was added to the paper based on the suggestions provided by reviewers
                  to which we want to express our gratitude for their constructive thoughts. Deep
                  maps or deep mapping are not terms we have found ourselves using to any great
                  extent in Digital Samos work to date, but we have certainly identified some common
                  threads in recommended literature to which our web-map is in conversation
                  with.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Although there is no scholarly consensus on what deep mapping entails as a practice
               or what a deep map is as a product <ptr target="#earleyspadoni2016" loc="p. 96"/>
               <ptr target="#roberts2016"/>, the four previous examples do aim to <quote
                  rend="inline">record and represent the grain and patina of place through
                  juxtapositions and interpretations of the historical and the contemporary… the
                  conflation of oral testimony, anthology, memoir, biography, natural history and
                  everything (their authors) might ever want to say about a place</quote>
               <ptr target="#pearson_shanks2001" loc="p. 64–65"/>. They are not simply digital maps,
               but <quote rend="inline">subtle and multilayered views of small area(s) of the
                  earth</quote>
               <ptr target="#bodenhamer2010" loc="p. 27"/>
               <ptr target="#bodenhameretal2013" loc="p. 174"/> that take advantage of the digital
               tools to comprise layers of meaning and process and to develop routes for new forms
               of spatial narratives. They are also <quote rend="inline">shaped by a particular
                  scholarly vision but offering an open-ended, exploratory environment</quote> that
               is only limited by available data, framework design, query tools, and the end user’s
               critical eye, knowledge, and imagination <ptr target="#ridge2013" loc="p. 177"/>.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Four examples of scientific web-maps for research and dissemination in Art and
                  Architectural History: 1. DECIMA WebGIS (<ref
                     target="https://utoronto.maps.arcgis.com/apps/webappviewer/index.html?id=d9692905ff41436d99cf7c398552ca39"
                     >https://utoronto.maps.arcgis.com/apps/webappviewer/index.html?id=d9692905ff41436d99cf7c398552ca39</ref>);
                  2. Visualizing the Mountain Estate. Landscape, Architecture, and Experience in
                  Chengde (<ref target="https://blogs.ntu.edu.sg/bssz/"
                     >https://blogs.ntu.edu.sg/bssz/</ref>); 3. The MonArch Project – The site of
                  Saint-Jean-des-Vignes (Figures 3 and 7 published by <ptr target="#bondeetal2009"
                  />, <ref target="http://monarch.brown.edu/">http://monarch.brown.edu/</ref>); 4.
                  Sera Interactive Map – Sera Project (Figure 2 published by <ptr
                     target="#budapesti2019" loc="p. 29"/>).</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>They allow us to set the goals of the interactive web-map for our Digital Samos
               project in accordance with our research questions. First, through the web-map we
               aimed to make the spatiotemporal analysis of the monastic site at Samos accessible to
               a broader audience. Besides, we considered important to allow interaction between the
               user and the platform, not only as a way to engage new audiences, but also to enable
               them to learn about this historical site at its own pace. Another goal was to make
               readable the relations between sources upon which the research was built and any
               project output in order to create a reliable web environment, where intellectual
               integrity is guaranteed. In addition, we prioritized a fully functional result in
               what refers to the final representation of change over time in the web context. To
               achieve a detailed web-display of spatial features was considered a high issue along
               with their embedded data and topographical context, instead of a simplification of
               the original geometries into points, or ideal shapes. This implies a series of
               difficulties from a technical perspective, as we will explain in the following
               section. </p>
            <p>Digital Samos is in conversation with many concerns in literature about deep mapping,
               as not only aspires to delineate and give shape to the locational properties of a
               particular monastic place. It also tries to go deep in the horizontal surface and to
               embrace the verticality of spatiotemporal analysis along with multimedial
               navigability for critical reflection and open-ended exploration <ptr
                  target="#bodenhamer2010" loc="p. 26–29"/> ] <ptr target="#ridge2013" loc="p. 178"/>
               <ptr target="#roberts2016" loc="p. 3"/>. By going deeper there are more layers we
               discover and Digital Samos aims to give an answer to how we can hold them all
               together, that is, how we can frame them as a map, as deep mappers seek [Roberts
               2016, 3]. All in all, the web-map of Digital Samos aims to renew the interest in the
               monastic past realm through accessibility and dissemination, interaction and public
               engagement, transparency and rigorousness, all of which is inside an integral
               platform, a new research tool to further our knowledge about this site in its
               intactness by means of interactive visual presentation and interpretation. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>From fixed CAD to an integral web-map</head>
            <p>The next step of the process was to deal with how to make all these goals possible.
               This was not only a technical challenge and an experiment in a new way of
               communicating this project about monastic architecture, urban history and landscape,
               but it was also an iterative process of thinking and learning through web development
               in an intellectual way. This is what we aim to explain next.</p>
            <p>To understand the process of making the integral web-map demands, first, to remind
               that the project has a conceptual focus on space and on its dynamic transformation
               over time. Therefore, space and time are two key factors to be represented in our
               web-based environment. All maps and models previously generated in the project
               visualize spatiotemporal changes by using computer-aided design (CAD) technologies.
               Therefore, the first step was to explore how it might be possible to turn the
               existing visualizations of past spaces into a web-map that meets all the goals set
               before.</p>
            <p>A first way to approach this challenge could be to generate one image per each phase
               of the evolving monastic complex and to display all of them in a website created with
               a content management system (CMS), even in relation with a timeline. When a map or
               plan is displayed in a website as a fixed image or as a series of images showed in
               chronological order, they do not usually have associated data to each feature
               represented, beyond the one we may add manually through embedded external hyperlinks,
               for instance. In addition to that, if we showed maps or architectural plans in this
               way, they would not be georeferenced either. As a result, the historical site would
               not dialogue with current physical realm. We would not enable audience to interpret
               and understand the relations between present and past monastic compounds by looking
               at both at the same time. These were some of the limits that early attempts in the
               sphere of website representation of urban history projects dealt with, lack of
               geo-referencing and accuracy of dependency relationships between documentation and
               visualizations, weak user interaction options, and short-term sustainability <ptr
                  target="#cardesindiaz2018"/>.</p>
            <p>Our aim is to push the concept of CAD maps that revealed the complexity of spatial
               changes over time by means of phased representations much further, toward a more
               integral and effective interface (Figure 7). We considered creating a digital and
               interactive two-dimensional map to portray spatial changes over time in permanent
               relationship with: previous and following realms, the present monastic complex,
               research sources, and extant physical remains. For the first attempt, we left the
               incorporation of the existing three-dimensional models pending for a future scale-up
               of the project. Although the sense of space provided by a two-dimensional map is
               limited, it is generally best to start simple and expand the project in following
               developments. As for time, the aforementioned two-dimensional web-map in the singular
               was conceived, actually, as many maps overlapped. Each one will represent a main
               phase of the process of changes at San Julián de Samos over time. We aimed that the
               multiple maps might be displayed or hidden by the user at will as a way to explore
               and discover spatial changes and relations between them in the interaction. In order
               to simplify the process of making, we also selected the most relevant stages to be
               represented. For that reason, each stage would be an abstraction that does not
               visualized changes on a short-term time basis. Although we are aware that the
               analytical nature of the project showed is reduced with this decision, to increase
               the number of stages will be possible and easier in future developments of the
               web-map, after learning how to face the whole process for a lower number of them.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>First conceptual model for an integral web-map showing spatiotemporal changes
                  in the historical site of San Julián de Samos. Image: the author.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>Each single spatial feature in our existing phased maps and models shapes a building,
               a property, a road, or any other part of the monastic built environment in the past
               according to historical sources and current physical remains. We always try to show
               how it actually was. When sources or remains are scarce, ambiguous or even
               non-extant, hypotheses had to be developed by forcing a dialogue between available
               evidence. The hypothetical parts of our maps were made visible by means of
               color-coded lines. However, connections between spatial features and historical
               documentation or physical remains that supported the reconstruction were missing in
               the definite maps and models. The reason was that the software application used to
               generate them, AutoCAD. When this project started, this CAD program did not offer the
               possibility to associate non-spatial information to each spatial feature. In other
               words, there were no attributes appended to features displayed in our maps and
               models, although all of them were classified in layers according to their type, the
               level of knowledge and the source. However, historical data that supported the
               reconstructions was not readable within the 2D or 3D graphic outputs, unlike
               text-based research findings where we can quote any reference to a book or an
               archival document, for instance, by embedding its text directly in our written
               argument <ptr target="#mcclure_worthey2019"/>. This sort of quotation would be
               fundamental to create a transparent and rigorous visual output, where integrity is
               ensured, as we previously pointed <ptr target="#hatchwelletal2019"/>. It would also
               end up in the creation of self-explanatory digital maps and models about historical
               sites opened to scientific evaluation, again like research scholarship in the form of
               text <ptr target="#munsteretal2018"/>.</p>
            <p>With all this in mind, the next step towards the web-map was to resort to a
               geographic information system (GIS). They are designed to store, manage, analyze, and
               display spatial data, either past or present. In research about historical built
               environments and urban history, GIS has already been proved as a powerful tool to
               track and analyze changes in time. Historical maps created with GIS have many
               potentials: to define shapes, to create layers, to assign attributes to those shapes
               and layers, to represent the passage of time to some extent, and to use visualization
               as a means of inquiry, both in desktop and online applications <ptr
                  target="#camerlenghi_schelbert2018"/>. In particular, we decided to use QGIS, a
               free and open source geographic information system.</p>
            <p>At this point, the following question could arise: why not simply use a GIS system
               since the very beginning? This is a question that often appears in the discussions
               about the best approach to historical 2D/3D drawing, mapping and modelling of past
               architectural spaces. The short answer is that computer-aided design (CAD) and
               drafting applications (e.g. AutoCAD) and 3D computer graphics software (e.g. Blender,
               3D max) offers much more degree of freedom with regards to freehand design and 3D
               modelling that is not possible in GIS or in HBIM <ptr target="#lanjouw2021"/>
               <ptr target="#boeykens2018" loc="p. 72–75"/>. CAD tools and 3D graphics software
               better allow the process of reasoning or intellectual representation that is needed
               for the understanding and rigor reconstruction of complex past architectures. For
               instance, they enable the scholar to properly describe the actual irregularities of
               historical complex built environments, which are much more difficult to be
               represented with GIS or HBIM applications <ptr target="#lanjouw2021"/>
               <ptr target="#boeykens2018" loc="p. 72–75"/>. On the contrary, GIS, as well as HBIM
               software, do integrate various types of data, so vector features may have associated
               datasheets with historical information that can be finally turned into web-maps.</p>
            <p>To move the project from AutoCAD to QGIS was not an immediate process. We had to
               adapt the existing CAD files to a new program and way of working within it, along
               with continuous thoughts regarding how to improve the representation of
               spatiotemporal changes in a new web-based context as well as how to manage and
               structure textual data and spatial features in accordance with the proposed aims
               (Figure 8).</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Project workflow from 2D CAD maps of the monastic site to the web-map of
                  Digital Samos. Image: the author.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>The first step was to geo-reference the CAD files so in the web output they will be
               displayed in relation with present cartography. The following step was to turn CAD
               files into shapefiles (SHP) to be readable by QGIS.<note> GISConvert, <ref
                     target="https://www.gisconvert.com/">https://www.gisconvert.com/</ref>. There
                  are also QGIS plug-ins to insert topographic lines from CAD to QGIS, as well as
                  information related to natural resources as rivers. Both topography and natural
                  resources at each stage of the monastic site evolution represent the historical
                  compound that is not exactly the same as the present one. </note> This was not a
               direct step. Each map generated with CAD represents one phase of the monastic site’s
               biography through multiple overlapped layers. Each layer comprises diverse types of
               geometries: lines, circles, polylines, points... and each geometry might represent a
               single spatial feature or just one part of it. This is an important issue to clearly
               distinguished, for instance, between remains and hypothesis by using CAD tools. In
               QGIS each SHP file or layer of the project is only able to comprised one type of
               geometry: points, lines, or polygons. This difference between both programs forced
               the creation of a series of individual CAD files to later represent each stage of the
               monastic site at a distinct moment in time within QGIS. Each of them only comprises
               one type of geometry readable in QGIS. For instance, in the case of the CAD map that
               represented the monastic site from the twelfth century to the fifteenth century, we
               generated nine CAD files that were converted into SHP files in a following step:
                  <q>contour_lines</q> (lines), <q>guest_house</q> (polygons),
                  <q>Romanesque_church</q> (polygons), <q>Romanesque_cloister</q> (polygons),
                  <q>Chapel_of_the_Cypress</q> (polygons), <q>hospital</q> (polygons), <q>roads</q>
               (polygons), <q>rivers_1</q> (polygons), <q>rivers_2</q> (lines).</p>
            <p>However, this initial division of each phased CAD map into multiple layers prior to
               their conversion into SHP files was not only due to one technical reason. It also
               resulted from thinking about: what type of historical information supported each
               graphic reconstruction; how we aimed to structure it; and in which way spatial
               features should be visualized to ensure a clear and friendly understanding,
               interpretation, and evaluation of the final interface by users. To find a proper
               answer to all these questions was the result of an iterative process of thinking,
               making, checking the results and moving the process forwards or backwards to test
               other ways of making through all of which we learnt and advanced the project.</p>
            <p>For instance, the files called <q>contour_lines</q> and <q>rivers_2</q> in the group
               of SHP files of the monastic site from the twelve to the fifteenth centuries only
               comprise one type of geometry: lines. Therefore, the initial thought could be to
               merge them in a single file if we only consider it as a technical issue. However, if
               we also reflect about how they should be displayed for an easy visual understanding
               by means of color-coded lines and fills, the separation between the two files is
               needed.</p>
            <p>The layers called <q>Romanesque_church</q> and <q>Romanesque_cloister</q> could also
               perfectly be within a single SHP file called <q>monastic_buildings</q> along with the
               QGIS layers of <q>guest_house</q>, <q>Chapel_of_the_Cypress</q> and <q>hospital</q>.
               All of them just comprise one type of geometry (polygons). Besides, the attribute
               table with information on spatial features of the layer can be organized with the
               same structure, as they are all under the consideration of monastic buildings.
               However, if we think about how to display the question of change over time in the
               web-based map without forgetting the diverse evolving nature of each monastic
               building, we come to the conclusion that their separation is also needed for an
               integral and legible visual reading and understanding of the resulting interface.
               Although it is possible to assign diverse attributes to each spatial feature within
               the same layer, we cannot follow the same path in what refers to their visualization
               yet, as the styling options (color, fill, type of line...) of a vector layer will be
               applied to all its spatial features.</p>
            <p>To go in depth in this issue, the next example is a reflection about how to best
               represent a historical fact with spatial consequences, which is the fire of 1534 in
               the Romanesque cloister, in the web-map. It affected one part of the monastic complex
               and monks decided to rebuild it immediately. Based on sources, the shape of the
               spatial feature was not altered. So to visualize it by means of changes of shape in a
               two-dimensional representation is not possible. To make easier the legibility of this
               change in the period corresponding to the monastic site in the first half of the
               sixteenth century beyond the addition of a textual annotation, the cloister is
               represented by a different line-coded polygon. As a result, one historical fact with
               architectural consequences is somehow made visible to the observer (Figure 9).</p>
            <figure>
               <head>From left to right: 1. the monastery in the Late Middle Ages with the cloister
                  represented with a contour line and a fill color; 2. the monastery in the first
                  half of the 16th century after the fire of 1534, with the cloister represented
                  with a contour line but without a fill color to graphically display the historical
                  fact; 3. the monastery in the first half of the 16th century after the fire of
                  1534 with displayed historical data in a pop-up. Image: the author.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>After the first four groups of layers called <q>The Place,</q>
               <q>Pre-twelve century,</q>
               <q>From twelve to fifteenth centuries,</q> and <q>First half of the sixteenth
                  century</q> were created and georeferenced onto a contemporary cartography in
                  QGIS,<note> National Air Orthophotography Programme (PNOA). Spanish National
                  Geographic Institute (IGN), <ref target="https://www.ign.es/iberpix2/visor/"
                     >https://www.ign.es/iberpix2/visor/</ref>.</note> the following step was to
               learn how this simple GIS map could be turned into a web-map. For this purpose, we
               made some trials with two QGIS plug-ins: QGIS Cloud Free and QGIS2WEB. The first
               plug-in was tested in QGIS 3.4. The free application is presented as a web-GIS
               platform for publishing unlimited public maps and data on the internet for
               non-commercial and non-government uses, but with storage for their databases limited
               up to 50Mb.<note> QGIS Cloud Plans, <ref
                     target="https://qgiscloud.com/en/pages/plans"
                     >https://qgiscloud.com/en/pages/plans</ref>.</note> The process to create and
               publish a QGIS project is quite easy by taking just a few steps.<note> Sourcepole AG,
                  QGIS Cloud, <ref target="https://qgiscloud.com/en/pages/quickstart"
                     >https://qgiscloud.com/en/pages/quickstart</ref>.</note> However, the trials
               made with our databases were not fulfilling as the plug-in worked unstable in the
               latest release of QGIS, as the QGIS Cloud Support Team confirmed. Besides, we soon
               realized that the storage limit of 50Mb to upload the local database of our maps in
               QGIS Cloud Free would not be enough once we have created the missing groups of
               layers.</p>
            <p>In regards to QGIS2WEB, it also enables users to create an OpenLayers/Leaflet web-map
               from a QGIS project, but this is not automatically published in an online platform,
               as it happens with QGIS Cloud. In other words, we can generate the HTML, CSS and
               JavaScript files that defined the web-map with QGIS2WEB, but then we need a web
               hosting to release it. Trials carried out with this plug-in allowed us to create a
               simple interactive map in a quick way. It is possible to set what layers or group of
               layers will be visible or hidden in the web-map as well as to select the base-map
               onto which they will be georeferenced. We can also add a series of tools for user’s
               interactivity, such a scale and zoom, an address search for locations, a layers list,
               a measure tool, the option to highlight features, and to show pop-ups when mouse
               hovers over features.<note> Morales A. <title rend="quotes">Publica tus mapas en la
                     web con qgis2web,</title>
                  <ref
                     target="https://mappinggis.com/2016/03/crea-aplicaciones-webmapping-con-qgis/"
                     >https://mappinggis.com/2016/03/crea-aplicaciones-webmapping-con-qgis/</ref>.</note>
               However, we also checked that QGIS2WEB did not represent all the spatial features
               defined in our QGIS project and, above all, it has many limitations to control and
               customize the resulting web-map according to the project requirements, unless we
               manually enhance the basic template generated by the plug-in (Figure 10).</p>
            <!-- webmap to replace figure 10 goes here! -->
            <figure>
               <ptr type="dhq-annex-embed" style="width: 100%; min-height: 600px;"
                  target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq-annex/000652/figure10/#15/42.7327/-7.3294"/>
               <head>Result of the second trial to create a web-map with the QGIS2WEB plug-in.
                  Webmap: the author. Interface controls may be hidden depending on the size of your
                  browser window. Navigate using map scroll bars or open the map in a new window to
                  access interface controls.</head>
               <!--<graphic url="resources/images/figure10.jpg"/>-->
            </figure>
            <p>In any case, the exploration of these two ways to create a web-map from a QGIS
               project led us to learn about Leaflet. Leaflet is one of the two powerful web-mapping
               libraries used by QGIS2WEB developers. It is an open-source JavaScript library
               designed to create friendly interactive maps that work efficiently in all major
               desktop and mobile platforms.<note> Agafonkin V. <title rend="quotes">Leaflet: an
                     open-source JavaScript library for mobile-friendly interactive maps,</title>
                  <ref target="https://leafletjs.com/">https://leafletjs.com/</ref>.</note> Leaflet
               API is said to be simple to read and easy to use even for beginner JavaScript
               developers. It is well-documented in its website, where we also found tutorials to
               get started with Leaflet basics as well as lots of plug-ins to extend its
               functionalities.</p>
            <p>Another relevant feature of Leaflet is that we can create a web-map from map vectors
               defined by GeoJSON objects.<note> Leaflet. <title rend="quotes">Using GeoJSON with
                     Leaflet,</title>
                  <ref target="https://leafletjs.com/examples/geojson/"
                     >https://leafletjs.com/examples/geojson/</ref>.</note> GeoJSON is a JSON format
               that encodes a geometry (one geographical feature) or a collection of geometries by
               defining their coordinates along with their non-spatial attributes <ptr
                  target="#crickard2014" loc="p. 41–44"/>. The features include points, line
               strings, polygons, and multipart collections of these types (multi-points, multi-line
               strings, and multi-polygons). The non-spatial attributes are similar to the attribute
               table with textual information associated to a layer in QGIS.</p>
            <p>For several months, the in-process work of Digital Samos was focused on learning how
               to use Leaflet and what potentials it offers for the interactive map of the monastic
               site at Samos. In addition to that, the in-process work revealed that if we aimed to
               meet all the aforementioned goals for free, we would need to design a custom-built
               platform; that is, a manually coded web-map (Figure 11). Otherwise, its future
               capabilities would be limited. However, making the decision of custom-designing the
               website to display our research involves dealing with a series of challenges that we
               also discovered in the in-process work. </p>
            <!-- webmap to replace figure 11 goes here! -->

            <!--<p><ptr type="dhq-annex-embed" target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq-annex/000652/figure11/" style="width: 100%; min-height: 600px;"/></p>-->
            <figure>
               <ptr type="dhq-annex-embed"
                  target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq-annex/000652/figure11/"
                  style="width: 100%; min-height: 600px;"/>
               <head>Manually coded interactive web-map showing the basics of Digital Samos spatial
                  framework: visual, multilayered, multi-scalar, time-based and structurally
                  open-ended. Webmap: the author. Interface controls may be hidden depending on the
                  size of your browser window. Navigate using map scroll bars or open the map in a
                  new window to access interface controls.</head>
               <!--<graphic url="resources/images/figure11.jpg"/>-->
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Struggling with integrity of visual and textual data in web-mapping: challenges
               and opportunities</head>
            <p>The web-map of Digital Samos is hosted by the Universidade da Coruña, as a way to
               guarantee its future sustainability in addition to a custom-design solution (Figure
               12). Its code is written with three programming languages: HTML, CSS and JavaScript.
               HTML provides a means to create the structure of the website: the main sections and
               their content. The interactive web-map was created with Leaflet, which is a
               JavaScript mapping library, as we previously said. CSS was used for describing the
               presentation of the HTML structure and the interactive map; that is, its layout or
               graphic design (format, fonts, style, colors...). </p>
            <figure>
               <head>Image of the interactive web-map of the Digital Samos project, <ref
                     target="https://digitalsamos.udc.es/interactive_map.html"
                     >https://digitalsamos.udc.es/interactive_map.html</ref>. Image: the
                  author.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure12.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>In the present article, we are not going to explain how we developed the code for the
               interactive web-map, but we will reflect about the functionalities implemented in the
               web-based map to meet our goals, some of the problems we faced in the process, a
               critical evaluation of the current solutions and some thoughts about what things we
               had left out in this first cut of the web presence and how we aim to move it forward
               in the future. </p>
            <p>The interactive web-map layout is divided into two main parts. The left one is
               devoted to long-form textual narrative. The spatial data is showcased in the right
               container. The latter is much wider as a way to visually highlight the focus of the
               project on spatiotemporal changes by using digital representation. When we open the
               interactive map we find a short, but needed explanation about how to use it in the
               left side, and the empty topography and hydrology of the place we study is shown on
               the right part.</p>
            <p>The very first functionality of the map is the layers control in its upper right side
               (Figure 13). It is opened or closed if we move the mouse over it. It comprises two
               groups of layers. The first one displays the sub-web-maps that visualize each stage
               of the monastic site evolution in chronological order. The second group, separated by
               a grey line, is composed of the base-maps used to geo-reference the previous layers.
               None of the layers are displayed by default, so if we want to start our exploration
               of the map, we have to click the radio button corresponding to one of them. In brief,
               this is explained in the non-textual left container of the map, where we recommend
               beginning the exploration by clicking on the first layer called <q>The Place.</q> If
               we do so, the area where the monastery was built is visualized in a two-dimensional
               representation in the website. We can learn about it if we scroll the textual
               narrative to the section with the same title. The platform always tries to make it
               easy, but subtle, to follow the recommended exploration by representing the same
               structure in the layers control and in the sections of the narrative left trail.
               These first features give user freedom to explore the web-based spatial environment
               at will, but it also provides a clear and simple path through the spatial and data
               content by the addition of an accompanying textual narrative. In a future
               development, we aim to create one-to-one connections between the name of each layer
               within the layers control and the narrative section by the same name, so whether you
               click on one or the other, both textual and non-textual parts of the web-map will be
               displayed at the same time. This way integrity and legibility will be enhanced.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Sequence of eight screenshots of the interactive web-map of Digital Samos
                  Project, <ref target="https://digitalsamos.udc.es/interactive_map.html"
                     >https://digitalsamos.udc.es/interactive_map.html</ref>, showing: the
                  sub-web-map by default, the first layer <q>The Place,</q> the second layer
                     <q>Pre-twelfth century,</q> the third layer <q>From twelfth to fifteenth
                     century,</q> the fourth layer <q>First half of the sixteenth century,</q> the
                  fifth layer <q>Second half of the sixteenth century,</q> the sixth layer <q>First
                     half of the seventeenth century,</q> and the seventh layer <q>Second half of
                     the seventeenth century</q> in the present version, November 2021. Image: the
                  author.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure13.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>Another functionality of the present platform is that we can always display a phased
               map of the monastic site onto the current cartography due to the addition of two
               base-maps: Google Satellite and Google Street View. This way, the website enables
               users to visualize any re-created past realm of the monastery, the village and their
               context in relation with the present built environment (Figure 14). We can discover
               what artefacts are preserved, altered or lost, for instance, by means of visual
               comparison. We think it would be also an effective tool to better understand the
               spatial changes between consecutive time periods if we could visualize two or more
               phased web-maps at the same time. However, the basic layers control of Leaflet just
               comprises two groups of layers: layers within the first group are displayed one by
               one, but layers of the second group can be showed all together or even along with one
               layer of the first group.<note> Leaflet, <title rend="quotes">Leaflet
                     Plugins,</title>
                  <ref target="https://leafletjs.com/plugins.html"
                     >https://leafletjs.com/plugins.html</ref>.</note> However, the ability to
               display a number of phased web-maps would of course be essential to make clearer the
               spatial change over time to human eye. This could be done by means of a multi-mode
               viewer that allows user to study overlapped transparent layers or synchronized
               multiple side-by-side maps <ptr target="#henel2019"/>.<note> See, for example:
                  Institut Cartogràfic i Geològic de Catalunya. <title rend="quotes">Changes in the
                     territory,</title>
                  <ref
                     target="https://www.icgc.cat/es/Aplicaciones/Visores/Cambios-en-el-territorio"
                     >https://www.icgc.cat/es/Aplicaciones/Visores/Cambios-en-el-territorio</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>Screenshots of the interactive web-map of Digital Samos Project, <ref
                     target="https://digitalsamos.udc.es/interactive_map.html"
                     >https://digitalsamos.udc.es/interactive_map.html</ref>, showing the phase
                  called <q>From twelfth to fifteenth century</q> onto two current base-maps: Google
                  Satellite and Google Streets. Image: the author.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure14.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>All previous features give an answer to how to represent space and time in a
               web-based environment, by starting simple with a two-dimensional map that we aim to
               expand to a three-dimensional model integrated in the platform somehow in the future.
               For now, we show what was where and when. This is the basic spatiotemporal knowledge
               for any historical exploration of the past monastic site. Each layer of the web-map
               is defined by discrete, measurable elements that represent the space, the answer to
               what was where and how the different elements were related to each other. However, we
               also pointed out previously that we aimed to create a self-explanatory web-map
               through the integration of historical non-textual data within the two-dimensional
               context in order to ensure transparency, legibility and evaluation.</p>
            <p>For this purpose, we implemented functionalities of highlighting features and pop-up
               windows. When the user hovers the cursor on the map, most of its spatial features
               change their color. It means that they have assigned attributes with embedded
               historical data to display and explore by clicking on a particular highlighted
               object. These one-to-one connections aim to extend the interaction between user and
               the map as well as to create an integrated platform. Pop-up windows were designed to
               not obscure the visibility of the underlying map by means of transparent backgrounds
               when they are opened. This way, not only do they favor the integration of textual
               data within the map with immediacy, but they also ensure a permanent vision of the
               spatial feature within its context.</p>
            <p>In this part of the in-process work, we ruminated on what textual information should
               be showed and how to structure it at length. So far we have created three main
               different types of pop-ups. The first type is used in the case of spatial features
               such as roads, rivers, bridges, dams and the hypothetical area of the first monastic
               settlement (Figure 15). Historical data about them is scarce, so the pop-up window is
               designed to only display the name of the feature.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Screenshot displaying the first type of pop-up windows created for spatial
                  features with scarce historical data. Interactive web-map of Digital Samos
                  Project, <ref target="https://digitalsamos.udc.es/interactive_map.html"
                     >https://digitalsamos.udc.es/interactive_map.html</ref>. Image: the
                  author.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure15.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>The second type of pop-up window was defined for monastic buildings (Figure 16). In
               their current layout, data is displayed starting with the name of the building. Next
               we show the main art history style period and the construction date, if known. We
               also indicate whether the selected entity is extant or not currently. We gathered
               references to events that caused spatial changes in the period visualized, such as a
               fire, an ongoing reconstruction... As the present layers embrace long-term time
               periods, we considered it relevant to highlight what spatial changes were taking
               place at the moment and why, beyond the knowledge we gain through the spatial feature
               that recreates them. Finally, there is a hyperlink called <q>View more.</q> The
               creation of this linked information is still a work in progress, but the idea is,
               when clicked, user could extend their knowledge through: detailed maps of the
               selected building, three-dimensional models to be able to experience the space,
               access to historical and contemporary photographs, brief historical descriptions...
               all of which expand the understanding and analysis of the question of change over
               time.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Screenshot displaying the second type of pop-up windows created for the
                  monastic buildings. Interactive web-map of Digital Samos Project, <ref
                     target="https://digitalsamos.udc.es/interactive_map.html"
                     >https://digitalsamos.udc.es/interactive_map.html</ref>. Image: the
                  author.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure16.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>The third main type of pop-up window was created for the spatial features that
               represent farming properties and residential plots located in the surroundings of the
               monastery and in the village (Figure 17). It is the most complex pop-up as data come
               from very disparate sources in each time period, among which we find or not the name
               of the property, the name of the owner, the name of the tenant or subtenant, their
               jobs, the location, the tenancy year, the holding type, etc. As for now, the third
               type of pop-up is actually designed with four possible displays that better structure
               and show data related to farming and residential plots in accordance with the most
               relevant historical documents in four of the seven phases already represented in the
               platform. Each pop-up is a rich subset of data that comes mainly from two types of
               archival documentation: rental agreements and books of demarcations from the
               sixteenth and seventeenth centuries. We can find up to twenty different variables
               displayed in the third type of pop-ups. We tried to structure historical information
               in a similar order to enable the integration of web tools for spatial data query and
               analysis within the platform in the future. For instance, simple questions regarding
               the names of tenants or the rents of their properties face with tools that read
               multiple data sets at a time might reveal new insights into the evolving nature of
               the monastic site and its human and socioeconomic history.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Screenshot displaying one sub-type of pop-up windows created for residential
                  and farming plots in the second half of the sixteenth century. Interactive web-map
                  of Digital Samos Project, <ref
                     target="https://digitalsamos.udc.es/interactive_map.html"
                     >https://digitalsamos.udc.es/interactive_map.html</ref>. Image: the
                  author.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure17.jpg"/>
               <figDesc/>
            </figure>
            <p>Last but not least, although we can learn about what artefacts in the historical
               site/s are extant today through the information gathered in the pop-ups, the web-map
               in its current form does not provide, we admit, a clear but needed graphic
               distinction between evidence and hypothesis, or even between different levels of
               probability regarding the recreation of lost built entities or plot tissues. To
               overcome this weak point in terms of an accurate communication of the visual outcome,
               one solution would be to use color-coded lines as we previously created for the CAD
               maps. In the present form of our web-based environment, graphic design already
               contributes to convey conceptual issues regarding spatial changes, for instance,
               through different types of lines to distinguish between ended monastic buildings
               (solid lines) and works in progress (dash lines) within each phase. In future
               developments, we will go on working in the map layer styling as it impacts visual
               analysis and, therefore, it is an essential and constant consideration for producing
               web-maps both for individual and public viewing.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusions</head>
            <p>This article introduced the Digital Samos interactive web-map, an online 2D
               representation of spatiotemporal changes implemented for one of the largest and most
               ancient monastic sites in Spain, San Julián de Samos. Digital Samos web-map was first
               released in late April 2019 and it offers fully functional access to six main stages
               of the site’s biography: the empty place prior to the foundation of the monastery;
               the monastic settlement before the 12th century; the monastery of the Late Middle
               Age; the transformations of the monastic site in the first half of the 16th century
               along with the formation of the nearby Samos village; the spatial changes that took
               place in the second half of the same century; and its ending in the early 17th
               century. In November 2019 we added a new spatiotemporal layer, the one corresponding
               to the first steps towards the mayor transformation of the monastic site from the
               late 17th century that were not completed until the 18th century. The latter is still
               pending to be added to the interactive map, as well as the complex monastic compound
               of the early 19th century prior to secularization.</p>
            <p>Unlike existing web-map displays for monastic architecture, the Digital Samos
               prototype addresses an open representation of past compounds without compromising
               interaction with each feature, the accuracy of geometries and the integration of
               historical data in the web output. We offer a practical solution to create a
               self-explanatory or <q>self-speaking</q> virtual product due to the integration of
               both visual (graphic) and textual (written) data that complement each other in a
               novel and friendly digital environment. We show a way to overcome some limitations of
               fixed images for the interpretation and presentation of research outcomes in urban
               and architectural historical studies in and outside academia. We make use of the
               potentials of digital vectorised maps that may inspire others to dream big by working
               gradually with spatial and temporal data in the study of built environments that,
               like this web-map, were not built in a day. </p>
            <p>The present article documents the project workflow, pitfalls and challenges to
               convert two separate initial research outputs (vector maps/plans) and historical data
               into one integral virtual product for presentation and dissemination of our
               spatiotemporal analysis in the field of architectural history where not only
               buildings, but also topography, geographical features and monasticism history play a
               role that is visualized in the web context. </p>
            <p>The process reveals some technical challenges for non-technical backgrounds as well
               as some needed improvements to be implemented in future development. We tried to
               communicate both effectively from the particular subdomain of architectural history
               research in and through web technology. We situated our argument within a broader
               context of research and we included explanations of the significance of our web-map
               in a way that could be easily applied in other case studies. We also offer a
               cost-effective and sustainable solution to overcome limitations caused by the lack of
               funding or the use of specific commercial software that may affect the continuation
               of digital projects over time, its evolution towards new stages, or the possibility
               to involve specialists with technical backgrounds. </p>
            <p>Digital Samos is woven with some common threads and complex requirements that are
               under consideration in the wider discussions and debates around deep maps. It
               develops a multilayer and multi-scalar spatial structure for a view of a particular
               monastic area that is meant to be <quote rend="inline">visual, time-based and
                  open-ended</quote>
               <ptr target="#bodenhameretal2013" loc="p. 174"/>. It is designed as an exploratory
               environment where scholars and public alike might gain knowledge through the
               exploration of a particular place or pursue their own questions <ptr
                  target="#ridge2013" loc="p. 177"/>. It has a capacity for thick expert description
               that might be unstable and changing in response to new data or insights <ptr
                  target="#bodenhamer2010" loc="p. 27"/>
               <ptr target="#roberts2016" loc="p. 5"/>. It also embraces the spatiotemporal
               contingent to incorporate time into analyses that are spatially contextualized <ptr
                  target="#bodenhameretal2013" loc="p. 172"/>
               <ptr target="#roberts2016" loc="p. 5"/>. It calls into the question the primacy of
               texts as the foundation of knowledge by taking advantage of the potential of
               technology and it walks towards an alternative construction of spatial narratives
               that embraces complexity, multiplicity, and simultaneity <ptr
                  target="#bodenhamer2010" loc="p. 28–29"/>. During the process of constructing this
               prototype, we can learn and understand what works best in this new arena and make the
               most of thinking through making. The case study offered identifies a gap in the way
               spatial change over time in complex built environments is approached and disseminated
               in academia, and it proposes a solution that might help unravelling or getting at
               least a better understanding of a complex monastic site. With this approach we are
               able to integrate the complexity of the spatial transformations over time at San
               Julián de Samos, allowing us to present and make readable the large variety of
               information and interpretation the research contained, through explorable layers of
               meaning and process that lead to new forms of spatial narratives in a web context. In
               sum, it is another effort to move forward a more integrated spatial framework for
               humanities research as literature about deep mapping demands <ptr
                  target="#bodenhameretal2013" loc="p. 175"/>.</p>
            <p>Through the work we present in this article, its open-ended results, the challenges
               we posed and the opportunities we approach, we hope to contribute, both conceptually
               and technically, to move forward the application of web-mapping tools in urban
               history and architectural history for a better understanding, presentation and
               dissemination of complex built environments. We expect this web-map to favor the
               engagement of a broader audience in and out academia through its attractive, clear
               and integrated appearance that, undoubtedly, makes visible to the observer eyes the
               complexity of one monastic built environment while it changed over time. We think it
               opens new possibilities for publication of visual research beyond traditional raster
               graphics that, on the whole, aims to no longer be considered just a visual
               demonstration or end visual product, but essential pieces of the research arguments
               themselves.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>The author would like to thank the instructors and participants in the Visualizing
               Venice Summer Institute <title rend="quotes">Advanced Topics in Digital Art History:
                  3D (Geo)Spatial Networks</title> 2018-2019 for their theoretical and technical
               visions and feedback upon which this new adventure was born and owes a lot.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ariasarias1950" label="Arias Arias 1950">Arias Arias, P. <title
                  rend="italic">Historia del Real Monasterio de Samos</title>. Santiago de
               Compostela, Imprenta, Lib. y Enc. Seminario Conciliar (1950). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ariascuenllas1992" label="Arias Cuenllas 1992">Arias Cuenllas, A. <title
                  rend="italic">Historia del monasterio de San Julián de Samos</title>. Samos,
               Monasterio de Samos (1992).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="boeykens2018" label="Boeykens 2018">Boeykens, S., S. Maekelberg and K. De
               Jonge. <title rend="quotes">(Re-)creating the past: 10 years of digital historical
                  reconstructions using BIM.</title>
               <title rend="italic">International Journal for Digital Art History, Digital Space and
                  Architecture</title>, 3 (2018): 62–85.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bondeetal2009" label="Bonde et al. 2009">Bonde, S., C. Maines, E. Mylonas,
               and J. Flanders. <title rend="quotes">The Virtual Monastery: Re‐Presenting Time,
                  Human Movement, and Uncertainty at Saint‐Jean‐des‐Vignes, Soissons.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Visual Resources: an international journal on images and their
                  uses</title>, 25-4 (2009): 363-377.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bodenhamer2010" label="Bodenhamer 2010">Bodenhamer, D. J. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Potential of Spatial Humanities.</title> In D. J. Bodenhamer,
               T.M. Harris, and J. Corrigan (eds.), <title rend="italic">The Spatial Humanities. GIS
                  and the future of Humanities Scholarship</title>, Bloomington, Indiana University
               Press (2010), pp. 14-30.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bodenhameretal2013" label="Bodenhamer et al. 2013">Bodenhamer, D. J., T.M.
               Harris, and J. Corrigan. <title rend="quotes">Spatial Narratives and Deep Maps: a
                  special report.</title>
               <title rend="italic">International Journal of Humanities and Arts Computing</title>,
               7 1-2 (2013): 170-175.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bodenhameretal2015" label="Bodenhamer et al. 2015">Bodenhamer, D. J., T.M.
               Harris, and J. Corrigan. <title rend="italic">Deep maps and Spatial
                  Narratives</title>. Bloomington, Indiana University Press (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="borin2016" label="Borin 2016">Borin, P. <title rend="quotes">An integrated
                  information management system for consistent historic narratives and
                  visualizations. Ghett/App for the Venetian ghetto.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Disegnarecon</title>, 9-17 (2016): 4.1–4.9.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="budapesti2019" label="Budapesti 2019">Budapesti, I. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Past, Present, and Future of Digital Buddhology.</title> In D. Veidlinger (ed.),
                  <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities and Buddhism</title>, Berlín/Boston, De
               Gruyter, pp. 25-40.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="calabi2009" label="Calabi 2009">Calabi, D. <title rend="quotes">Memory,
                  narrative and display – city museums in recent initiatives and debates.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Planning Perspectives</title>, 24-3 (2009): 385–390. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="camerlenghi_schelbert2018" label="Camerlenghi and Schelbert 2018"
               >Camerlenghi, N. and Schelbert, G. <title rend="quotes">Learning from Rome: Making
                  Sense of Complex Built Environments in the Digital Age.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians</title>, 77-3
               (2018): 256-266.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cardesindiaz2018" label="Cardesín Díaz 2018">Cardesín Díaz, J. M. <title
                  rend="quotes">Historia urbana multimedia: entre los Sistemas de Información
                  Históricos (HIS) y la realidad virtual.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Ayer. Revista de Historia Contemporánea</title>, 110-2 (2018):
               141-175.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="castro1912" label="Castro 1912">Castro, M. <title rend="quotes">Un
                  monasterio gallego,</title> in <title rend="italic">Boletín de la Comisión
                  Provincial de Monumentos Históricos y Artísticos de Orense</title>, IV (1912):
               82-83-84-85-86, 113-120, 136-143, 163-171, 189-195, 201-208.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chattopadhyay2012" label="Chattopadhyay 2012">Chattopadhyay, S. <title
                  rend="quotes">Architectural representations, changing technologies, and conceptual
                  extensions.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians</title>, 71-3
               (2012): 270–272.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crickard2014" label="Crickard 2014">Crickard III, P. <title rend="italic"
                  >Leaflet.js Essentials</title>. Birmingham, Packt Publishing (2014).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dukeuniversity2018" label="Duke University 2018">Duke University. <title
                  rend="quotes">Advanced Topics in Digital Art History: 3D (Geo)Spatial Networks. A
                  Getty Foundation-Sponsored Summer Institute sponsored by the Visualizing Venice
                  Team.</title> Available at: <ref
                  target="https://sites.duke.edu/duke_arthist_3dgeo/"
                  >https://sites.duke.edu/duke_arthist_3dgeo/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="duran1947" label="Durán 1947">Durán, M. <title rend="italic">La Real
                  Abadía de San Julián de Samos: estudio histórico-arqueológico</title>. Madrid
               (1947).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="earleyspadoni2016" label="Earley-Spadoni 2016">Earley-Spadoni, E. <title
                  rend="quotes">Spatial History, deep mapping and digital storytelling:
                  archaeology’s future imagined through an engagement with the Digital
                  Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Archaeological Science</title>, 84 (2017): 95-102. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ethington_toyosawa2015" label="Ethington and Toyosawa 2015">Ethington, P.
               J. and N. Toyosawa. <title rend="quotes">Inscribing the Past: Depth as Narrative in
                  Historical Spacetime.</title> In D. J. Bodenhamer, J. Corrigan, and T. M. Harris
               (eds.), <title rend="italic">Deep maps and Spatial Narratives</title>, Bloomington,
               Indiana University Press (2015), pp. 72-101.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="folgardelacalle2006" label="Folgar de la Calle 2006">Folgar de la Calle,
               M. C. <title rend="quotes">A construcción do gran mosteiro de San Xulián de Samos.
                  Cen anos de transformacións arquitectónicas.</title> In E. Fernández Castiñeiras,
               and J. M. Monterroso Montero (eds.), <title rend="italic">Arte benedictina nos
                  camiños de Santiago. Opus Monasticorum II,</title> Santiago de Compostela, Xunta
               de Galicia (2006), pp. 149-178.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="folgardelacalle_goydiz2008" label="Folgar de la Calle and Goy Diz 2008"
               >Folgar de la Calle, M. C. and A. E. Goy Diz. <title rend="italic">San Xulián de
                  Samos: Historia e arte nun mosteiro. Opus Monasticorum III</title>. Santiago de
               Compostela, Xunta de Galicia (2008).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="harris_2015" label="Harris 2015">Harris, D. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Architectural history’s futures.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians</title>, 74-2
               (2015): 147–151.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hatchwelletal2019" label="Hatchwell et al. 2019">Hatchwell, S., Insh, F.
               and Leaper, H. <title rend="quotes">Born Digital: Early Career Researchers Shaping
                  Digital Art History.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Visual Resources: an international journal on images and their
                  uses</title>, 35 1-2 (2019): 171-179.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="helmreich2021" label="Helmreich 2021">Helmreich, A. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Introducción a la Historia del Arte Digital: un conversación
                  colaborativa.</title>
               <title rend="italic">H-ART. Revista de historia, teoría y crítica de arte</title>, 9
               (2021): 161-182.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="henel2019" label="Henel 2019">Henel, J. <title rend="quotes">JHNA’s
                  Enhancements (or <q>JHNA 2.0</q>).</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Historians of Netherlandish Art</title>, 11-2
               (2019).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jaskotetal2018" label="Jaskot et al. 2018">Jaskot, P. B., H. Jacobs, V.
               Szabo, M. Olson, and E. Triplett. <title rend="quotes">Shaping the Discipline of
                  Digital Art History. A recap of an advanced summer institute on 3-D and
                  (geo)spatial networks.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Iris. Behind the Scenes at the Getty</title>, Dec.
               (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kingetal2016" label="King et al. 2016">King, L., J. F. Stark, and P.
               Cooke. <title rend="quotes">Experiencing the digital world: the cultural value of
                  digital engagement with heritage.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Heritage &amp; Society</title>, 9-1 (2016): 76–101.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lanjouw2021" label="Lanjouw 2021">Lanjouw, T. <title rend="quotes">Some
                  thoughts about integrating documentation, modelling and publication for historical
                  3D models.</title> Available at: <ref
                  target="https://pure3d.eu/index.php/2021/10/26/4d-research-lab-blog-post/"
                  >https://pure3d.eu/index.php/2021/10/26/4d-research-lab-blog-post/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lanjouw_waagen2021" label="Lanjouw and Waagen 2021">Lanjouw, T. and J.
               Waagen. <title rend="quotes">Making 4D: principles and standards for virtual
                  reconstruction in the humanities by the 4D Research Lab</title>
               <title rend="italic">4D Research Lab Report Series</title>, 1 (2021): 3-31.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="londonchapter2009" label="London Chapter 2009"><title rend="italic">London
                  chapter for the computer-based visualization of cultural heritage</title>, version
               2.1, Feb. 2009. Available at: <ref target="http://www.londoncharter.org/index.html/"
                  >http://www.londoncharter.org/index.html/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lopezpelaez1894" label="López Peláez 1894">López Peláez, A. <title
                  rend="italic">El monasterio de Samos: estudio histórico</title>. Lugo, Imprenta a
               cargo de Juan M. Bravos (1894).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lopezsalas2013" label="López Salas 2013">López Salas, E. <title
                  rend="quotes">Methodological proposal in order to reconstruct the plans of a
                  disappeared medieval architecture: the Romanesque church of St. Julian’s Monastery
                  at Samos (Lugo).</title>
               <title rend="italic">Arqueología de la Arquitectura</title>, 10 (2013), e002.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lopezsalas2015" label="López Salas 2015">López Salas, E. <title
                  rend="italic">The monastery of San Julián de Samos (Lugo-Spain), a study and
                  interpretation of the monastic space and its evolution</title>. Ph.D. thesis,
               Universidade da Coruña (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lopezsalas2017a" label="López Salas 2017a">López Salas, E. <title
                  rend="quotes">The reform of Samos Abbey between 1491 and 1637: uncovering the
                  logic of the architectural changes.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Imago Temporis. Medium Aevum</title>, 11 (2017): 345-383;
               519-543.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lopezsalas2017b" label="López Salas 2017b">López Salas, E. <title
                  rend="quotes">Decoding the planning rules of the monastic urban and rural forms
                  around Samos Abbey.</title> In M. Abel, Mickey (ed.), <title rend="italic"
                  >Medieval Urban Planning: The Monastery and Beyond</title>. Newcastle upon Tyne:
               Cambridge Scholars Publishing (2017), pp. 46-74.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lopezsalas2017c" label="López Salas 2017c">López Salas, E. <title
                  rend="quotes">The role of the regular clergy in the planning of the landscape. The
                  case of San Julián de Samos.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Hispania Sacra</title>, 69-139 (2017): 19-29.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lopezsalas2017d" label="López Salas 2017d">López Salas, E. <title
                  rend="quotes">Descubriendo un paisaje histórico. El espacio cercado del monasterio
                  de San Julián de Samos en el siglo XIX.</title>
               <title rend="italic">RHA. Revista da História da Arte. Série W</title>, 5 (2017):
               168-182.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lopezsalas2017e" label="López Salas 2017e">López Salas, E. <title
                  rend="quotes">Seeking the traces of a former monastic landscape in the vicinity of
                  Samos Abbey (Galicia, Spain).</title> In W. Kobylińska-Bunsch, Z. Kobyliński and
               L. D. Nebelsick (eds.), <title rend="italic">Archaeologica Hereditas, 10</title>,
               Warsaw, Institute of Archaeology of the Cardinal Stefan Wyszyński in Warsaw/Art
               History of the University of Warsaw (2017), pp. 195-211.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lopezsalas2017f" label="López Salas 2017f">López Salas, E. <title
                  rend="quotes">Organización, elementos y estado del espacio cercado de San Julián
                  de Samos a través de una escritura de toma de razón de 1836.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Studia Monastica</title>, 59-1 (2017): 163-187.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcclure_worthey2019" label="McClure and Worthey 2019">McClure, D. and G.
               Worthey. <title rend="quotes">Colophon. Grapl, the Graves Platform.</title> In T. S.
               Mullaney (ed.), <title rend="italic">The Chinese Deathscape. Grave Reform in Modern
                  China</title>, Stanford, Stanford University Press (2019).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="monteleoneetal2016" label="Monteleone et al. 2016">Monteleone, C., I.
               Friso, and F. Panarotto. <title rend="quotes">For the fifth centenary of the ghetto
                  in Venice: virtual transformations of architecture and city at the Doge’s
                  Palace.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Disegnarecon</title>, 9-17 (2016): 3.1–3.12. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="munsteretal2018" label="Münster et al. 2018">Münster, S., K. Friedrichs,
               and W. Hegel. <title rend="quotes">3D Reconstruction Techniques as a Cultural Shift
                  in Art History?</title>
               <title rend="italic">International Journal for Digital Art History. Digital Space and
                  Architecture</title>, 3 (2018): 39-60.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="murrietaflores_martins2019" label="Murrieta-Flores and Martins 2019"
               >Murrieta-Flores, P. and B. Martins. <title rend="quotes">The geospatial humanities:
                  past, present and future.</title>
               <title rend="italic">International Journal of Geographic Information Science</title>,
               33-12 (2019): 2424-2429. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pearson_shanks2001" label="Pearson and Shanks 2001">Pearson, M. and M.
               Shanks. <title rend="italic">Theatre/Archaeology</title>. London, Routledge
               (2001).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pecile2018" label="Pecile 2018">Pecile, E. <title rend="quotes">Respecting
                  Historical Spatial Integrity: Building a Historical 3D Florence and Avoiding the
                  Video Game.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Disegnarecon</title>, 11-21 (2018): 10.0-10.8.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="portillacosta1978" label="Portilla Costa 1978">Portilla Costa, P. de
               la. <title rend="italic">Monasterio de Samos Guía histórico-artística</title>. Lugo,
               Monasterio de Samos (1978).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="portillacosta2003" label="Portilla Costa 2003">Portilla Costa, P. de la.
                  <title rend="italic">Monasterio de San Julián de Samos. Historia de dos
                  restauraciones (1880 y 1951)</title>. A Coruña, Fundación Caixa Galicia
               (2003).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ridge2013" label="Ridge 2013">Ridge, M., D. Lafreniere, and S. Nesbit.
                  <title rend="quotes">Creating Deep Maps and Spatial Narratives through
                  Design.</title>
               <title rend="italic">International Journal of Humanities and Arts Computing</title>,
               7 1-2 (2013): 176-189.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="roberts2016" label="Roberts 2016">Roberts, L. <title rend="quotes">Deep
                  Mapping and Spatial Anthropology.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Humanities</title>, 5-5 (2016): 1-7. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rollierhanselmannetal2014" label="Rollier-Hanselmann et al. 2014"
               >Rollier-Hanselmann, J., Z. Petty, A. Mazuir, S. Faucher, and J. F. Coulais. <title
                  rend="quotes">Développement d’un SIG pour la ville médiévale de Cluny.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Archeologia e Calcolatori</title>, 5 (2014): 164-179.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sevilleprinciples2011" label="Seville Principles 2011"><title
                  rend="italic">The Seville principles. International principles of virtual
                  archaeology</title>, 2011. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://icomos.es/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/Seville-Principles-IN-ES-FR.pdf"
                  >https://icomos.es/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/Seville-Principles-IN-ES-FR.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="staley2015" label="Staley 2015">Staley, D. J. <title rend="italic"
                  >Computers, visualization, and history: how new technology will transform our
                  understanding of the past</title>. Hoboken: Taylor and Francis (2015). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sullivanetal2017" label="Sullivan et al. 2017">Sullivan, E., A. D. Nieves,
               and L. M. Snyder. <title rend="quotes">Making the model: scholarship and rhetoric in
                  3-D historical reconstructions.</title> In J. Sayers (ed.), <title rend="italic"
                  >Making things and drawing boundaries: experiments in the Digital
                  Humanities</title>, Minneapolis, University of Minnesota Press (2017), pp.
               301–316.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="svalduz2013" label="Svalduz 2013">Svalduz, E. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Researching, interpreting and representing: reflections on a few experiences (M9,
                  Carpi, VV and the Accademia).</title> In D. Calabi (ed.), <title rend="italic"
                  >Built city, designed city, virtual city. The museum of the city,</title> Rome:
               Croma - Università degli studi Roma Tre (2013), pp. 121–135. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="svalduz2018" label="Svalduz 2018">Svalduz, E. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Architectural and urban change over time. The school, church and monastery of
                  Santa Maria della Carità.</title> In K. L. Huffman, A. Giordano and C. Bruzelius
               (eds.), <title rend="italic">Visualizing Venice. Mapping and modeling time and change
                  in a city</title>, New York: Routledge (2018), pp. 36–42.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="terpstra_rose2018" label="Terpstra and Rose 2018">Terpstra, N. and C.
               Rose. <title rend="italic">Mapping Space, Sense, and Movement in Florence. Historical
                  GIS and the early modern city</title>. New York, Routledge (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="whitemanetal2018" label="Whiteman et al. 2018">Whiteman, S., B.
               Dhanapalan, and H. Sum. <title rend="italic">Visualizing the Mountain Estate.
                  Landscape, Architecture, and Experience in Chengde</title>, 2018. Available at:
                  <ref
                  target="https://sites.duke.edu/duke_arthist_3dgeo/projects/visualizing-the-mountain-estate/"
                  >https://sites.duke.edu/duke_arthist_3dgeo/projects/visualizing-the-mountain-estate/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wulfmanetal2007" label="Wulfman et al. 2007">Wulfman C.E., E. Mylonas, A.
               Loyer, S. Bonde and C. Maines. <title rend="quotes">The Abbey Inside the Machine: The
                  MonArch Project.</title> Digital Humanities 2007, University of Illinois,
               Urbana-Champaign, June 2007.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
