<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Theatre analytics: developing software for theatre
               research</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Clarisse <dhq:family>Bardiot</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Université Polytechnique Hauts-de-France</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>clarisse_bardiot@me.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>A historian of contemporary theatre, specialized in digital humanities and
                     digital performances, Clarisse Bardiot is an associate professor at the
                     Université Polytechnique Hauts-de-France. Her research focuses on digital
                     humanities, the history and aesthetics of contemporary performing arts, the
                     relationship between art, science and technology, the preservation of digital
                     works, and experimental publishing. <ref target="www.clarissebardiot.info/"
                        >www.clarissebardiot.info</ref></p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000476</idno>
            <idno type="volume">014</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2020-09-25">25 September 2020</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2020-06-26" who="jmurel">Finished encoding</change>
         <change when="2020-06-25" who="jmurel">Created file; began encoding</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>How can digital traces of the performing arts be interpreted? What methodologies can
               be proposed to <soCalled>make them talk</soCalled>? The specificity of these traces
               leads to specific methodological responses, especially as the aim here is to
               interpret the traces in both directions of understanding and replayability. It is as
               much a question of advancing a reflection on the conditions for the recovery of work,
               as it is of analyzing an artistic approach based on its digital traces. Starting from
               these epistemological issues, I present the development of two softwares, Rekall and
               MemoRekall. These tools are part of a larger trend which I call <quote rend="inline"
                  >theatre analytics</quote>. Theatre analytics is based on data from the traces of
               the performing arts. Unlike the general approach of <q>big data in the social
                  sciences and humanities,</q> where we seek to determine general, average, profile
               categories or repeatable (or even predictable) patterns, our primary concern remains
               to capture the singular, the detail, the difference, the anomaly, in a constant round
               trip between the micro and the macro dimensions. The ambition of theatre analytics is
               to offer a different way of looking at big data, more oriented towards complexity
               than the quantity of data.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>This article discusses the trend of theater analytics and the author's software
               Rekall and MemoRekall.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>Introduction</head>
         <p>Digital technology has flooded the theatre. On stage, it is omnipresent: image
            projections, real-time transformations of the actors' voices, interactions between the
            performers and the stage enhanced by all kinds of devices. Behind the scenes, there is
            no longer a single sound or light control room that is not digital, with the exception
            of shows in the dark, in daylight or flickering candlelight or even the rare
            performances without a sound broadcasting system. However, it is not just about the
            shows. Creative processes are also impacted, as are other aspects of theatrical
            activity: distribution of works, criticism, public reception, communication, financing.
            If one wants to study the performing arts today, it is impossible not to take into
            account companies' websites, blog and online newspaper articles, recordings broadcast on
            Youtube or Vimeo, social networks, email exchanges, budget tables, ticketing software.
            Today, directors' notebooks also take the form of Word files, image-based blogs on
            Tumblr or Instagram, posts on Facebook, Evernote notebooks, Pinterest tables, task lists
            in Trello, exchanges in Slack. The traces of the performing arts have become digital
            traces. This phenomenon has been driven by two major trends: the emergence of the
            born-digital heritage and theatre archives digitization. </p>
         <p>The digital traces of the performing arts irremediably change not only the nature of the
            sources on which we rely to analyze works and write the history of performing arts but
            also how these studies are conducted and their results. The transformation of the trace
            into data-based information, making data a new type of source, is fraught with
            consequences for the memory of the ephemeral theatre, consequences that are not yet
            fully measured by the various actors, be they cultural institutions, librarians or
            researchers. Historiography in a digital context is not a revival of quantitative
            history in the strict sense of the term. It calls first and foremost for practices, and
            it is also in this practice that the narrative is housed. It is because it is a question
            of practice, and not just of exposing traces, but instead of exposing them to
            manipulation that a paradigm shift is taking place, inviting us to <q>make history
               differently.</q> Because the traces are transformed, they invite a renewal of the
            critique of sources that we thought we knew and make research questions evolve and lead
            to other epistemologies. The <q>digital turn</q> proposes a paradigm shift in how we
            build the memory of performing arts by renewing source criticism, methodological
            thinking, and narratives, moving beyond traditional methods of close reading to
            computational assisted reading and contributing to the general reflection on digital
            history.</p>
         <p>How can performing arts digital traces be interpreted? What methodologies can be
            advanced to <q>make them talk?</q> The specificity of these traces leads to specific
            methodological responses, especially since the aim here is to interpret the traces in
            both directions of understanding and replayability. This is as much a question of
            developing a reflection on the conditions for the recovery of creative work as it is of
            analyzing an artistic approach based on its digital traces. Traditional methods, in
            particular close reading, i.e., a reading, a precise analysis of each of the traces,
            have to be combined with new approaches.</p>
         <p>This growing awareness lead me to the creation of a software prototype, Rekall, and a
            web application, MemoRekall, which I am still developing today. Both environments are
            free and open source. Rekall and MemoRekall provide new opportunities of interpreting
            digital documents for performing arts research. They offer different and unexpected
            points of view on a dataset, either from a distant or a close reading approach, either
            by extracting metadata or by linking documents. Furthermore, the softwares take into
            account the open nature of the digital archive, which reconfigures itself as new
            documents are added, new links are created, and allow collaborative research.</p>
         <p>From an epistemological point of view, the creation of these tools is anchored in the
            emergence of a new field of research that can be called <q>theatre analytics.</q>
            Theatre analytics are based on data from the traces of the performing arts. In line with
               <q>culture analytics,</q> the term refers to the calculation and emphasizes the
            analysis of works, which is the foundation for the preservation and historiography of
            the performing arts. In both cases it is a matter of following in detail a process to
            show why and how a work is constituted by observing its various components and of
            borrowing from mathematics to study, preserve and write a history of the performing
            arts. Theatre analytics does not challenge existing methodologies but allows them to be
            supplemented by taking into account what is generally discarded, namely, digital traces,
            considered too complex, too numerous, too fragile, with dubious authenticity. The aim is
            not to promote an approach that would be purely quantitative or statistical but on the
            contrary to see how qualitative analyses can also be conducted in a digital context.
            Unlike the general approach of <q>big data in the social sciences and humanities,</q>
            where we seek to determine general, average, profile categories or repeatable (or even
            predictable) patterns, our primary concern remains to seize the singular, the detail,
            the difference, the anomaly in a constant round trip between the micro and the macro
            dimensions, and looking for mesoscales. In the tracking of the singular at the core of
            big data, the deviation from the mean is made visible as such and no longer as an error
            against a standard. Nor is it a question of considering that singularity would be
            calculable, as some research on emotions or creativity seems to state by reducing
            digital traces to mathematical artifacts. On the contrary, we argue for an approach
            where the singular, the ideosyncraric <hi rend="italic">via</hi> computational methods,
            be the focus of a qualitative interpretation. Data visualisation is ultimately
            qualitative and must give rise to an accurate and informed reading. As Johanna Drucker,
            who calls for a <quote rend="inline">visual epistemology,</quote> points out <quote
               rend="inline">Visualizations are always interpretations — data does not have an
               inherent visual form that merely gives rise to a graphic expression</quote>
            <ptr target="#drucker2014" loc="7"/>. In this light, the ambition of theatre analytics
            is to offer a different way of looking at big data that is more oriented towards
            complexity, rather than the quantity of data, with a diversity of computer approaches
            depending on the nature of the data and the research questions asked. Alongside other
            methodologies less specific to the performing arts but which can also beRekall and
            MemoRekall afforts such an approach. Part of the text is missing : Alongside other
            methodologies less specific to the performing arts but which can also be convened (NLP,
            network analysis, machine learning, algorithm creation, ...) Rekall and MemoRekall
            afforts such an approach.</p>
         <p>This paper will explicate the development context of Rekall and MemoRekall and provide
            lessons learnt from this experiment. The detailed technical functions of the two
            softwares can be found elsewhere <ptr target="#bardiot2014"/>
            <ptr target="#bardiot2015"/>
            <ptr target="#bardiot2017"/>. The question can be asked how a performing arts researcher
            comes to develop new software applications? To explain this, first, I will set out the
            specificity of the problems generated by the digital traces of the performing arts.
            Second, main objectives of the project and the choices that result from it are
            explained. Third, the different stages of development and in particular the
            collaborations with artistic teams, programmers and designers are laid out.</p>
         <div>
            <head>The digital traces of the performing arts</head>
            <p>Compared to non-digital traces, what do digital traces change for the preservation,
               analysis of works and the performing arts history? Let us take the tip of the
                  <q>iceberg</q> of technological obsolescence and big data. A creative process,
               from its initial ideas to the <term>première</term>, lasts an average of four years -
               the same length as that of a technological cycle. In other words, at the moment of
               the <term>première</term>, it is necessary to update the management software and
               computer systems accompanying the tour, to save and sort the hundreds, sometimes
               thousands, of documents related to the work in a new version. As soon as the work is
               created, the artistic and technical team is confronted with problems of technological
               obsolescence and a quantity of information that may have a decisive impact on the
               production and its distribution of the work and can even, in the medium term, make it
               impossible to tour. </p>
            <p>The preservation of performances is not the only phenomenon concerned by these
               issues. The creative processes are also affected. To take the example of the
               director's notebooks, in 20 years, who will remember applications such as Trello,
               Slack, Evernote or Tumblr? Will we be able to read the digital traces that have been
               stored and have access to the data they contain while guaranteeing their
               authenticity? Not only are performances ephemeral, which is inherent to the
               performing arts, but their digital traces seem even more evanescent. They are also
               increasingly numerous, overwhelming us with a continuous flow of data, in an
               unprecedented disproportion. These questions are not all new, but their amplification
               gives them a new acuity. How can we write the history of the performing arts from not
               only fragile and variable traces, but also too numerous at for researcher or
               archivist? </p>
            <p>It is undeniable that, today, digital technology involves radical, and even
               irreversible, changes in our relationship to memory, history, and what is left as a
               legacy. Given this, one can but note that memory and the digital seem to oppose each
               other. This need not be so. Reconciling them is essential. Digital traces cannot be
               ignored in building and safeguarding the memory of the performing arts. These issues
               are complex and urgent. If nothing is done, the technological obsolescence of digital
               technology will overtake all other considerations, and an entire part of our culture
               will vanish.</p>
            <p>To take a concrete example, under the title <title rend="italic">Re: Walden</title>,
               are regrouped different avatars of the same creative work, developed by the French
               director Jean-François Peyret from 2006 to 2014. This involved two installations
               (2010 and 2013 at Le Fresnoy, France), performances in the installation, four scenic
               versions (including one for the Avignon 2013 festival, France), a concert at EMPAC
               (USA) and an extension in the virtual environment <title rend="italic">Second
                  Life</title>. Between 2012 and 2013, I collected several hard disks from the
               artistic team. These were those of Thierry Coduys (electroacoustic and computer
               devices), Agnès de Cayeux (virtual world) and Julie Valéro (dramaturgy). Although
               this collection is mostly incomplete (ideally, access to all the digital data of each
               member of the artistic team would have been required), the data collected were 10,360
               files for 20.5 GigaBytes. </p>
            <p>The files collected include the following elements: scores<note>In Jean-François
                  Peyret's vocabulary, scores are a montage of texts that serve as a basis for
                  rehearsals and then become the central theme of the performance.</note>,
               photographs and video recordings of rehearsals and performances, sound recordings for
               voice synthesis, sound files as well as computer programs (Max/MSP and Pure Data
               patches), images, management documentation (contacts, schedules...), technical
               sheets, room plans, communication documents (playbills, press releases, reviews
               published in newspapers or blogs), archived e-mails, screenshots of <title
                  rend="italic">Second Life</title>, texts for each of the actors or texts from the
               automatic translator developed for the project, meeting minutes, notes of intent from
               the artistic team.</p>
            <p>This example is symptomatic of digital traces of the performing arts, even if it
               concerns a complex creation that takes place over several years. They are
               heterogeneous, numerous but incomplete and fragile. The digital traces of the
               performing arts are heterogeneous, both in terms of the type of file (image, sound,
               text, video, computer program) and their content. All is happily mixed without any
               distinction and with the elements of the show such as aspects about the creative
               process or publicity compaigns, and the tour. These three aspects make it possible to
               define three main categories of digital traces that correspond to the main
               chronological stages in the life of a performance: the creative process, the work,
               audience reception. We can add a fourth one, not represented here: the administrative
               digital traces of cultural institutions and companies, i.e., everything related to
               the production of shows. </p>
            <p>There are many digital traces, so much so that the term <q>big data</q> is used. We
               have counted several thousand files for <title rend="italic">Re: Walden</title>. The
               situation is nothing new, and we can only observe the inflation of digital traces.
               However, despite their impressive volume, the traces are far from being exhaustive.
               Besides, some tasks left only minimal traces, for example there were only a few
               photos and patches in the Pure Data software for the residency at the École Régionale
               d'Acteurs de Cannes. Finally, digital traces do not take into account a large part of
               the exchanges, actions, and reflections taking place on and off the set, if they had
               not been systematically recorded or were in the form of reports and notes. Part of
               the digital activity itself rarely leads to the creation of preserved traces, like
               the one that takes place on electronic networks, such as documents shared on Google
               drive, conversations on Skype or applications such as Slate or Trello, images made
               available on Tumblr. </p>
            <p>Digital traces are fragile. The duration of access and readability of a digital file
               might be five years. So that not only are we faced with ephemeral works, but also
               with traces increasingly fragile. For a large part of them, in a few years,
               especially those from proprietary software (Word for example), we will probably no
               longer be able to open them and therefore read them. The loss of traces seems to be
               an unavoidable phenomenon. In fact, many artists have already lost not only traces
               but also creative works. </p>
            <p>In this overview, we understand that digital traces exacerbate both the properties of
                  <q>analogical</q> traces, while at the same time differentiating themselves from
               them. As for the first observation, linked to heterogeneity, number or fragility, it
               is ultimately <q>merely</q> a question of accentuating phenomena already well
               identified in the analogical world. The great diversity of the nature of documents in
               the performing arts collections; the inflation of archives is a recurring problem
               identified, notably by Krzystof Pomian <ptr target="#pomian1992"/>, where paper ends
               up being reduced to dust, inks are erased, magnetic strips become electronic snow.
               Despite the appearance of continuity, in fact digital technology fundamentally
               changes the ontology of the trace. To use Bruno Bachimont's expression, we have gone
               from a <q>graphic reason</q><note>In French, the translation of the title of Goody’s
                  book is <title rend="italic">La raison graphique : la domestication de la pensée
                     sauvage</title>.</note>
               <ptr target="#goody1977"/> to a <quote rend="inline">computational reason</quote>
               <ptr target="#bachimont2008"/>. As they become numerical, traces are coded and
               presented as numbers, which allows for computational calculation. This makes the
               question of reading traces and their authenticity complex (for they must be
                  <q>decoded</q>) while opening up to being manipulated. In other words, digital
               traces are <quote rend="inline">analyzable</quote>, in the triple sense of
               discretization (the decomposition of a thing into its elements), computer calculation
               and data visualization. Analytical geometry, attributed to Descartes that allows a
               graphic representation of algebra, is the prelude to contemporary data
               visualizations. The digital traces of the performing arts thus presents several
               paradoxes: technological obsolescence versus full archiving, authenticity versus
               modification, and repetition versus ephemerality. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>At the crossroads</head>
            <p>In 2006, as a performing arts researcher, I conducted a case study on Belgian
               choreographer Michèle Noiret on technological obsolescence issues about the
               performing arts at the margins, given that the works are inherently ephemeral. The
               case study was part of the DOCAM research program (2005-2010) led by the Daniel
               Langlois Foundation in Montreal on the documentation and preservation of media arts.
               The programme includes numerous partners, including museums. It builds on the
               pioneering work of the Langlois Foundation and John Ippolito on the variable media
               approach <ptr target="#depocas2003"/>. Jon Ippolito will then publish with Richard
               Rinehart <title rend="italic">Re-Collection</title>
               <ptr target="#rinehart2014"/>. In museums, the very concrete question of
               technological obsolescence of works was raised. Pip Laurenson proposed new
               conservation paradigms in questioning the central notions of state and authenticity
                  <ptr target="#laurenson2006"/>. Faced with these questions, the researcher's
               natural reflex is to identify existing solutions. Best practice guidelines and case
               studies were published as part of international projects (Interpares, DOCAM, Caspar)
                  <ptr target="#bardiot2012"/>; researchers worked on specific ontologies <ptr
                  target="#rinehart2007"/>; some artists - particularly choreographers - in
               collaboration with scientists, proposed solutions for a work or set of works <ptr
                  target="#bleeker2017"/>. However, no existing solution seemed able to solve the
               concrete problems identified in the performing arts field. They can be summarized as
               follows: </p>
            <list type="unordered">
               <item>How can technical teams be enabled to take quick notes during rehearsals and to
                  aggregate all technical documents? The different control rooms are separate, each
                  one (lighting designer, general manager, video director, sound engineer) has its
                  documentation system in digital or paper format, more or less structured with each
                  participant defines his or her working method, his or her guide to <q>best
                     practices.</q></item>
               <item>How can a show a few months or a few years later be restaged while respecting
                  as carefully as possible the initial artistic intentions? Due to built-in digital
                  obsolescence, technologies must be continuously adapted during the show tour. In
                  addition, when the creative team is not the same as the touring team, rigorous
                  documentation is required. </item>
               <item>How can we compensate for the memory loss caused by digital technology? It
                  becomes difficult to trace the history of the creative processes, especially since
                  the documents they generate are themselves ephemeral, if nothing else, in their
                  intended use. </item>
               <item>What status and place should be given to video recording? A widespread
                  practice, with varying results regarding the quality of video recording
                  implementation, it systematically calls for comment. Video recordings <hi
                     rend="italic">per se</hi> are not self-sufficient. Most often produced by the
                  company itself (for promotional purposes), they are nevertheless one of the most
                  significant traces of the art work. </item>
               <item>How can one move through the hundreds, sometimes thousands of documents to
                  reconstruct the creation process? How can data visualization contribute to the
                  analysis of a creative work's genetic analysis? By comparing different processes,
                  is it possible to identify forms, patterns? </item>
               <item>The digital traces of the works are very numerous and the reading of each trace
                  is almost impossible. The question becomes rather: what information, what
                  knowledge about the works is it possible to extract from all the traces for
                  preservation purposes? What data should be used to reconstruct a creative process?
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In order to respond, at least partially, to these challenges, I published a first
               paper <ptr target="#bardiot2009"/> proposing a conceptual model of a computer
               solution articulating documents around the video recording of a performance. In
               contrast to the practice of creating a specific interface for each performance, I
               designed a software that can be applied to as many creative works as possible. As my
               concerns increasingly met those of cultural institutions confronted with the
               obsolescence of technologies - and the costs that this entails in addition to the
               difficulty of presenting works to the public - I decided to develop the software by
               myself. At the end of 2012, I raised the first funds that enabled me to hire a team
               of developers. Five years after the first draft, the situation had changed. The
               issues of big data and digital traces mentioned above could no longer be ignored. It
               was necessary to go beyond the articulation of a documentary corpus around a video
               recording. In the preparatory meetings that followed, the guiding principles of the
               project, first entitled <title rend="italic">Éclats</title> (in reference to the
               fragmentation and multiplicity of documents) and then <title rend="italic"
                  >Rekall</title> (in reference to the memory company in K. Dick's <title
                  rend="italic">We Can Remember It for You Wholesale</title>), were clarified. From
               the outset, Open Source was a self-evident option. Indeed, some funders such as the
               French Ministry of Culture imposed the Open Source option. Beyond that, Open Source
               is a prerequisite for the sustainability of the solutions developed. It would have
               been antinomic and counterproductive to proceed otherwise in a project dedicated to
               the preservation of art works. </p>
            <p>Rekall is an environment prototype to document and analyze creative processes, and to
               simplify the preservation of performances. It uses the metadata present in all
               documents of a performance in order to extract crucial data (author, date, place,
               keyword) then used by data visualization tools to indicate behaviors. In this way,
               Rekall provides an overview of the creation process and identifies the most important
               documents (which will then have to undergo specific preservation measures). The
               software can also be used during rehearsals (for example, to annotate documents,
               review the history of a plot sheet), or once the creation is completed (to understand
               its process, distinguish documents related to the work from those related to its
               production). Rekall is cross platform. It is developed with the Qt development
               framework. For each version of a document, Rekall extracts all available metadata
               using the open source tool exiftool. The interface is in HTML5 and CSS3.</p>
            <p>Two primary objectives guided Rekall's design: to help artists (the first curators of
               their works) to document their creations in order to ensure their retrieval and
               overcome the obsolescence of digital technologies; to help researchers study the
               genetics of performances in a context of born-digital heritage and Big Data. These
               two objectives may seem very distant at first sight. However, it is the same
               materials (digital traces of the works) that are collected, analyzed and visualized
               based on different modalities and time scales. In this way, the collection can take
               place for the artists during the creative process itself, as the work stages
               progress. A living archive emerges in perpetual movement. The researcher intervenes
               once the process is completed, once the documents have somehow stabilized, frozen to
               become the traces of what has happened. Rekall must, therefore, be able to be used
               from the onset of the first ideas of a show, during the creative process and then
               after its creation, with a dual perspective of preservation of the work and
               historiography.</p>
            <p>Very quickly, it became clear to us that we had to develop a multimodal environment
               that included both digitized documents and natively digital documents. The digital
               traces of the performing arts include texts, images, sounds, videos, computer
               programs. A common practice of big data is to separate documents by file type and
               work in the form of <q>silos</q> (e.g. text, image). Such processing prevents us from
               obtaining an overview of the traces collected and from examining many phenomena such
               as the evolution of an idea through different documents, from image to text, from
               text to table, from table to video recording. Besides, it is essential to navigate
               between the micro and macro dimensions, between close reading and distant reading,
               between diachronic and synchronic representations. In other words, being able to
               represent a process without erasing its complexity; to switch from data to file and
               back again. Often, distant reading and data visualization involve a break between the
               source file and the data from which it is extracted. Maintaining this link is
               fundamental for several reasons. The data are always reductive fragments and it is
               important to be able to recontextualize them in order to interpret them better. The
               transition from a trace to data is a reductive and interpretive operation. Reduction
               also means making a precipitate of traces, which makes it possible to amplify and
               exhale a phenomenon that would otherwise have remained invisible. The transformation
               affords new insights into the tracks and allows us to detect clues that would
               otherwise have gone unnoticed. The use of data visualization is essential in the case
               of performance preservation to capture the main steps of the creative process and to
               identify the main files that will then need to be actively preserved, often on a
               case-by-case basis. In a very concrete way, in a corpus of 10,000 documents, the
               process of visualization must make it possible to identify the 50 documents that the
               researcher must read in detail to analyze the work or that the artistic team must
               migrate or emulate to continue touring.</p>
            <p>Among the traces of the performing arts, the video recording is a particular type of
               document. It has long been - and is still often - considered as a panacea regarding
               documentation of the ephemeral performing arts. Provoking many debates since the
               1960s, often considered as a <q>betrayal</q> of the original work <ptr
                  target="#melzer1995a"/>
               <ptr target="#melzer1995b"/>, video recordings have now become commonplace. A video
               recording is both an essential and a fragmented document. In its essential form, it
               records bodies in movement and thus transforms performances into documents. In its
               fragmented form, it gives only one point of view, presenting only a part of what
               takes place on stage, generating temporal collusion through editing, adapting stage
               lighting to the lighting conditions of the cameras. A commentary, that is to say, an
               annotation must necessarily accompany these modifications. Two types of strategies
               are developed in order to overcome the shortcomings or biases of video recording:
               inter-documentary (connecting the video-capture to a larger documentary corpus) and
               intra-documentary (annotating the video-capture). These two approaches can be
               usefully combined. They simultaneously play different roles with the document,
               between the deepening and connecting roles. </p>
            <p>In a first phase, Rekall was developed not only as a document management tool in a
               multimodal environment, but also as a video annotation software, with three
               complementary strategies: the creation of links between multiple documents offering
               the possibility of commenting and illuminating the documents between them; the choice
               of video recording as a backbone from which all other documents would be organized;
               and the possibility of adding textual comments. Subsequently, these two aspects were
               separated. The video annotation part about of Rekall has now become MemoRekall. </p>
            <p>MemoRekall offers a reading of a major document: video recordings. The software is a
               user-friendly web application that explains a video by annotating it and linking it
               to external documents or web pages. The arrangement of documents, links and
               annotations creates a new document, called a <soCalled>capsule</soCalled>, that can
               be embedded into a web page. The capsules organization is developed from and around
               video recordings in a hypertextual logic. MemoRekall can be used to create a
               multimedia educational booklet, run a digital spectator school, edit a scientific web
               documentary or simplify the distribution of works. MemoRekall is developed in HTML5 /
               CSS3 with a backend using PHP/MySQL technologies. The video player is developed in
               HTML5, allowing it to be integrated into the main web browsers (Firefox, Safari,
               Google Chrome). The personal user account was developed with the Symfony
               framework.</p>
            <p>Rekall and MemoRekall are complementary platforms aimed at preserving and analysing
               the digital traces of the performing arts. They allow to organize and visualize in a
               multimodal environment all the traces of a creative processe (Rekall) or only a
               selection of the traces (MemoRekall), paying special attention to the video recording
               of the works (MemoRekall). With Rekall, it’s possible to retrace the historic of a
               file (but not the versioning, which can be done with complementary tools). In terms
               of research, Rekall and MemoRekall are platforms suited to genetic analysis, close
               and distant reading of a work, documentation and preservation of a performance.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Developping Rekall and MemoRekall : collaborate, test, adapt</head>
            <p>In 2012, Guillaume Marais (ergonomics and interface design), Guillaume Jacquemin (IT
               development) and Thierry Coduys (consultant, designer of electronic devices for the
               performing arts) joined the project. They already had a first common experience of
               software development with IanniX, a real-time sequencer for digital art inspired by
               UPIC (a former project by Iannis Xenakis). Throughout his artistic career, which led
               him to IRCAM, Thierry Coduys has developed electroacoustic and computer devices for
               numerous directors, composers (including Luciano Berio, Ivan Fedele, and Pascal
               Dusapin) and choreographers. He was regularly confronted with the question of
               touring, restaging and transmitting works with particularly complex technological
               caracteristics. Guillaume Jacquemin and Guillaume Marais created the Buzzing Light
               agency in 2009. Guillaume Jacquemin is an embedded systems engineer and is trained
               through multiple experiences in interactive multimedia and digital art. Guillaume
               Marais is an ergonomist and interaction designer and is trained in information
               systems engineering. In addition to their complementary skills in programming and
               ergonomics, Guillaume Marais and Guillaume Jacquemin were used to contributing to
               artistic projects and had a keen appetite for contemporary music. It was an essential
               factor: to develop Rekall, it was crucial to establish a dialogue around the key
               issues of the software. We used an AGILE approach and progressed incrementally based
               on user feedback.</p>
            <p>I am often asked why I have not chosen instead to work with a computer science
               research laboratory. There are several answers to this question. One is that I needed
               to be in a very operational, fluid and fast environment. Furthermore, it did not
               appear that the project raised computer research issues. In 2012, in France, a
               computer development project led by a theatre studies researcher was not always well
               accepted by the academic community. Finally, on one hand, the funding obtained came
               from funds for innovation in the field of culture (Pictanovo) and from cultural
                  institutions.<note>In 2014 the French Ministry of Culture, MA national scene of
                  Montbéliard, Le Fresnoy, Le phénix national scene of Valenciennes then in 2015 the
                  National Centre for Circus Arts, the International Institute of Puppetry and the
                  Rhône Alpes region, in collaboration with the Maison de la Danse, the Hexagone
                  national scene of Meylan, the Lux national scene of Valence, the Théâtre Nouvelle
                  Génération and the École Nationale Supérieure d'Arts et Techniques du
                  Théâtre.</note> This gave great flexibility in hiring service providers. On the
               other hand, the lack of research funding and the administrative management of the
               project by a theatre (the Phénix scène nationale Valenciennes) and then, in 2015, by
               a publishing house (Subjectile) did not allow the hiring of a Ph.D. student or a
               postdoc. Today, with the development of the digital humanities and the resulting
               cultural change, the software development framework would probably be different. So
               indeed, the contribution of Thierry Coduys, Guillaume Jacquemin and Guillaume Marais
               were crucial. The results we obtained would have been very different with another
               team that wouldn’t have had any experience with artistic creative processes. For
               example, creating software that can be used by artists has several consequences. The
               main point is that it must be as easy to use as possible and still meet the rigorous
               requirements of researchers. This involved a reflection on interface design and
               ergonomics and two essential decisions. The first is that Rekall had to operate
               discreetly in the background on the assumption that artists have very little time to
               archive their work even if they are aware of its importance. The artistic team works
               on its usual tools while Rekall records in the background all the manipulations that
               are done as well as the users' working environment (the version of their OS, the open
               applications, and their version) in order to collect all fundamental information from
               a preservation perspective. It is essential to keep the most exact trace possible of
               the technological components and of the aesthetic and historical dimensions. At the
               same time, it is important to describe the effects of these same components, in line
               with the variable media approach in order to make them evolve and update <ptr
                  target="#depocas2003"/>. The artistic team only opens the software when it needs
               to have an overview, annotate certain documents, or go back over the history of the
               files. The second decision is the lack of a specialized ontology. Past experiences
               show that these ontologies are difficult to apply by non-specialists and, to
               underline the point, they do not respond to all the situations encountered. The tool
               has to be as labile as possible and able to accommodate all types of artistic
               approaches. The only scheme used is the simplified Dublin Core scheme to describe the
               files (this scheme is expected to be implemented soon). In the same spirit, even if
               we are open to the possibility of importing thesauri to index the files, we initially
               favored folksonomy.</p>
            <p>Once the team and the first funding were gathered, the keywords of our working method
               became collaboration, testing, and adaptation. During a first step, it took the form
               of face-to-face working meetings on a monthly basis, and then less frequently. The
               first exchanges were in the form of drawings and graphs. At the heart of our
               discussions were the issues mentioned above and to which we tried to provide concrete
               solutions in the form of usage scenarios. In other words, how were we to reconcile
               theory and practice? A state of the art study was carefully examined, in particular,
               the work initiated by William Forsythe and the research carried out at IRCAM, were
               discussed at length. Once the issues and objectives were clearly defined, a first
               development phase began, leading to a beta version at the end of 2013. There were
               many iterations, Guillaume Marais and Guillaume Jacquemin working together on the
               development and interface, Thierry Coduys and myself giving feedback. If I brought a
               researcher's point of view, Thierry Coduys brought the artistic team’s point of
               view.</p>
            <p>We also associated two artistic teams to the project, in the theatre (Jean-François
               Peyret) and dance (Mylène Benoit) domains, in residence respectively at Le Fresnoy
               and Le Phénix scène nationale Valenciennes (France). There both were the initial
               partners of the project. On the one hand, we needed <q>real</q> data to work on a
               tangible case. This was made possible by the <title rend="italic">Re: Walden</title>
               project mentioned above. On the other hand, I wanted to be involved in a creative
               process from the beginning to understand better how Rekall could fit in and what its
               contributions could be. Mylène Benoit opened the doors of the rehearsals of <title
                  rend="italic">Notre Danse</title>, a choreography created in 2014. Many informal
               interviews with these artists and their teams have allowed us to clarify many aspects
               of Rekall. Finally, workshops, as well as public presentations (study days,
               conferences, talks), allowed us to confront different audiences (researchers,
               artists, technicians) and to fine-tune the project. A new use, which we had not
               considered, emerged: the possibility of using Rekall as a writing tool. This confirms
               the flexibility of the platform. Nonetheless, to consider all the implications of
               this new use would be a very important shift. At this stage of the project, we
               decided not to address it directly. We took the idea into account for MemoRekall and
               mentioned this possibility during workshops.</p>
            <p>Several specialists were invited to share their feedback on Rekall during
               brainstorming sessions with the entire team. In particular, we met with: Alain
               Bonardi (musicologist and composer, Paris 8), Pierre Couprie (musicologist, Paris 4),
               Émeline Brulé (design researcher, ENSAD), Cécile Obligi (BnF) and Sébastien Peyrard
               (metadata standards, BnF), Frédéric Bevilacqua (IRCAM), Lev Manovich (CUNY), Annick
               Bureaud (Leonardo/Olats), Scott Delahunta (Motion Bank), amongst others. Listening to
               users so as not to develop a solution only for my personal use and to respond to as
               wide a range of uses as possible remains a constant concern, even today. </p>
            <p>By working with others and listening, the development team were led to adapt the
               initial project. Rekall has known several versions - and we hope so, will know more.
               The first phase, from the end of 2012 to November 2013, was based on the case study
               of Jean-François Peyret's <title rend="italic">Re: Walden</title> project. The Rekall
               team has been collecting documents, as well as those related to the different stages
               of the creative process since 2006. This made it possible to develop the
               data-visualization part of Rekall. Indeed, it quickly became apparent that the
               software had to offer two main uses: data visualization and a timeline. The data
               visualization interface presents the entire corpus in a multimodal environment and
               allows the user to play with different views from the extraction of metadata from the
               files. The timeline interface allows organizing a selection of documents on a time
               axis. One or more video recordings are used as the primary document to define the
               time axis. It is then possible to play several video streams in parallel, which
               allows for example to compare several rehearsals or a front and a zenithal view.
               Timeline mode uses only a small selection of documents. It is principally designed
               for document annotation purposes, to complement information that is not perceptible
               and intelligible through data visualization.</p>
            <p>With Thierry Coduys, we tested an alpha version from November 2013. He focused on
               artistic uses, I studied related research issues. Another development phase on the
               timeline began in February 2014. In May 2014, a workshop at Le Fresnoy brought
               together developers, technicians, and artists to discuss the development. Many points
               were validated, notably on metadata processing and the general interface. Specific
               functionalities related to the documentation of the creation process were specified,
               some interface details were revised, and some functionalities simplified. This work
               allowed the beta version to be released online on June 13, 2014 (see Figure 1). </p>
            <figure>
               <head>Rekall <q>timeline</q> interface with split screen. Beta version, 2014.</head>
               <figDesc>A screenshot from the Rekall interface, showing a split screen with various
                  data visualizations.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Following various tests, we decided to change the development methods and integrate
               an interface in HTML5 and CSS3 in order to anticipate the uses and development of an
               online version. This new development took place in the fall of 2014. The code was
               completely rewritten, and a V0 was published in November 2014. The user feedback and
               beta test on the V0 led us to refine and simplify the interface and the various
               functionalities, with a clear separation between data visualization and timeline. A
               V1 of the prototype was available at the end of 2015 (see Figure 2).</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Rekall interface. V1 prototype, 2015.</head>
               <figDesc>A screenshot from the Rekall interface showing various files.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The initial version of Rekall was aimed at a professional audience. Nevertheless, a
               demand for the general public and schoolchildren quickly appeared. The school
               partners of the Phénix scène nationale Valenciennes wanted to have access to the
               content created with Rekall on a website available to students. They also wanted
               students to be able to document the works themselves collaboratively and directly,
               either from documents provided by the theatres and artistic teams hosted or from
               documents created by the students themselves. At the same time, a team of young
               writers contacted us. They wanted to renew theater criticism by having a
               collaborative writing tool that could be superimposed on a video recording available
               and broadcasted on the Internet. </p>
            <p>This is why we started to develop MemoRekall at the end of 2014, with funding from
               the French Ministry of Culture and other cultural institutions that joined the
               project. All the work done on the timeline part of Rekall was used and simplified to
               the utmost. While Rekall remains for the moment a standalone software, MemoRekall is
               designed from the beginning as a web application accessible from a browser (see
               Figure 3). In order to validate the software design, various workshops and training
               sessions were organized in September 2015 with middle school and high school
               students, higher education students, teachers and cultural professionals (more than
               100 people participated in this phase of the project). Edwige Perrot, a theater
               researcher and a teacher, joined the team to create capsules and lead the workshops
               for school pupils. MemoRekall was made available to the public at the end of
               September 2015. The web application has allowed us to solve codec problems that were
               not solved with Rekall. We decided to release a Version 2 of the prototype in 2017
               without the timeline interface. Rekall now focused on the data visualization part and
               processed a more significant number of documents simultaneously (about 6,000). This
               first scaling up must be continued as it is not rare to gather more than 10 000
               documents for one work as we have seen with <title rend="italic">Re: Walden</title>.
               Also in 2017, Estelle Senay, network engineer, joined the team. A personal user
               account to MemoRekall was added and a new website was deployed at the end of the
               year. In 2018 the usage scenarios were fine tuned and training provided for
               MemoRekall. If the web application is taken as an operational tool, Rekall is still
               at the advanced prototype stage. A search for funding is underway to scale up the
               system. Many features remain to be developed. For example, the performing arts
               involve collaborative teams, it would therefore be useful to have different people
               working together on a same Rekall project. At this stage, Rekall allows a
               collaborative collection of the traces but lends itself to an individual analysis of
               these traces. This necessitates that collaborative tools be developed further for
               Rekall. </p>
            <figure>
               <head>MemoRekall interface, 2015.</head>
               <figDesc>A screenshot of the MemoRekall interface showing the application being
                  used.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion: Outlook</head>
            <p>The preservation of the performing arts in the digital age does not call for a
               univocal solution but for a complementarity of strategies: diachronic documentation
               of works based on documentation that is as rigorous as it is precise, preserving a
               historical and material anchorage; inter and intra-documentary annotation of video
               recording, this trace that is now omnipresent; circulation between different reading
               distances. The complex nature of performing arts makes it irreducible to a single
               approach; any attempt at documentation is characterized by its incompleteness. What
               these different strategies have in common is the redocumentarisation of traces. Each
               time a reader consults, links or extracts data from digital traces, it re-documents
               them. Re-playing, <soCalled>re-enacting</soCalled> a performance is necessarily today
               to go through a performative act carried out within the digital traces. This
               performativity is synonymous with instrumentation. We have thus proposed two
               complementary tools, Rekall and MemoRekall, which could be used in wider fields such
               as time based media art preservation, digital art history or electronic
               publishing.</p>
            <p>The reception of Rekall and MemoRekall is enthusiastic. As soon as it appeared in
               2015, theatres and classes seized MemoRekall for their activities. Today, more than 1
               500 capsules have been produced. Since its first version in 2014, Rekall has been
               downloaded several thousand times. The whole project has given rise to numerous
               articles, talks, and workshops, in France and abroad. There are many development
               opportunities, and new functionalities must be implemented to get as close as
               possible to an answer to the questions raised by the digital traces of the performing
               arts. Moreover, if the project was initially designed for the performing arts, its
               scope may cover other artistic practices.</p>
            <p>The development of this project, based in a specific field and in the French context,
               leads to several reflections. On the one hand, Rekall changes the genetic studies of
               the performing arts. It is now possible to take into account all the digital traces
               of a creation process in a multimodal environment. Retreiving metadata with Rekall
               allows distant reading and at the same time while a keeping a link to the original
               file. It also allows close reading of the most important documents identified through
               distant reading. For researchers of the performing arts this provides a new way to
               circulate between micro and macro dimensions of a corpora. On the other hand,
               MemoRekall provides for researchers a new publishing tool, articulating
               video-recording, documents (archives or documents created by the researcher) and
               annotations, and allows co-editing. The connection and complementarity between Rekall
               and MemoRekall is a project in its own right, but certain <q>bricks</q> have already
               been laid (common development core, compatible interfaces). Indeed, we are seeking to
               reconcile two approaches often considered to be opposed in digital history and the
               treatment of digital traces. The first one shows the sources and superimposes
               different strata to make them explicit. We find here the question of annotation and a
               critical work specific to the humanities. This approach is anchored in a practice of
               editorialization. The second approach extracts data sources and proposes to analyse
               them by applying different computational methods. This approach is based on the école
               des annales and the quantitative approach.</p>
            <p>The question of the sustainability of digital technology is not only a technological
               issue. It is also an institutional and cultural issue. For Rekall and MemoRekall,
               this would mean finding a framework that allows for the maintenance, development, and
               hosting of open source and free software solutions. It is not the role of cultural
               institutions that financed the project to put this responsibility on a small team
               made up, by in large, of self-employed workers in, invarariably, precarious economic
               situations. MemoRekall is now hosted by Huma-num (a French <q>Very Large Research
                  Infrastructure</q> - <q>Très Grande Infrastructure de Recherche</q>, TGIR) that
               provides long term preservation of the capsules created with the web-application. </p>
            <p>Clarisse Bardiot, Université Polytechnique Hauts-de-France</p>
         </div>

      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bachimont2008" label="Bachimont 2008">Bachimont, B., 2008. <title
                  rend="quotes">Formal Signs and Numerical Computation: Between Intuitionism and
                  Formalism. Critique of Computational Reason</title>, in: Schramm, H., Schwarte,
               L., Lazardzig, J. (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Instruments in Art and Science: On the
                  Architectonics of Cultural Boundaries in the 17th Century</title>. Walter de
               Gruyter, Berlin, New York, 362-382.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bardiot2017" label="Bardiot 2017">Bardiot, C., 2017. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Organiser et conserver la mémoire de l’éphémère : les capsules de
                  MemoRekall</title>. <title rend="italic">Culture et Musées</title>,
               159–174.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bardiot2015" label="Bardiot 2015">Bardiot, C., 2015. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Video recording and documentation of scenic arts: from the annotation to the
                  visualization of metadata, the example of the Rekall software</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Acoustic Space : Data Drift. Archiving Media and Data Art in the
                  21st Century</title> 14, 159–168.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bardiot2012" label="Bardiot 2012">Bardiot, C., 2012. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Eclats : un projet de logiciel pour annoter des captations vidéo</title>, in:
               Martinez Thomas, M., Proust, S. (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Hispania : La Notation
                  Du Travail Théâtral : Du Manuscrit Au Numérique</title>. Presented at the La
               notation du travail théâtral: du manuscrit au numérique, Lansman, Toulouse, France,
               131–148.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bardiot2009" label="Bardiot 2009">Bardiot, C., 2009. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Noter, annoter. Comment documenter les arts de la scène à composante
                  technologique</title> - <title rend="quotes">Noting/Annotating. Documenting the
                  technology-based performing arts</title>. <title rend="italic">Art Press</title> 2
               30–36.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bardiot2014" label="Bardiot et al. 2014">Bardiot, C., Marais, G.,
               Jacquemin, G., Coduys, T., 2014. <title rend="quotes">Rekall : un environnement
                  open-source pour documenter, analyser les processus de création et simplifier la
                  reprise des œuvres scéniques</title>, in: <title rend="italic">Captation,
                  Transformation, Sonification</title>. Presented at the Les Journées d’Informatique
               Musicale, AFIM, Talence, France, pp. 119–129.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bleeker2017" label="Bleeker 2017">Bleeker, M. (Ed.), 2017. <title
                  rend="italic">Transmission in Motion: The Technologizing of Dance</title>.
               Routledge, London ; New York.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="depocas2003" label="Depocas et al. 2003">Depocas, A., Ippolito, J., Jones,
               C. (Eds.), 2003. <title rend="italic">Permanence Through Change: The Variable Media
                  Approach</title> = <title rend="italic">La Permanence par le changement :
                  l’approche des médias variables</title>. Guggenheim Museum Publications ;
               Fondation Daniel Langlois pour l’art, la science et la technologie, New York;
               Montréal.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2014" label="Drucker 2014">Drucker, J., 2014. <title rend="italic"
                  >Graphesis: Visual Forms of Knowledge Production</title>, MetaLABprojects. Harvard
               University Press, Cambridge (MA).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="goody1977" label="Goody 1977">Goody, J., 1977. <title rend="italic">The
                  Domestication of the Savage Mind</title>. Cambridge University Press,
               Cambridge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="laurenson2006" label="Laurenson 2006">Laurenson, P., 2006. <title
                  rend="quotes">Authenticity, Change and Loss in the Conservation of Time-Based
                  Media Installations</title> Tate Papers. <ref
                  target="https://www.tate.org.uk/research/publications/tate-papers/06/authenticity-change-and-loss-conservation-of-time-based-media-installations"
                  >https://www.tate.org.uk/research/publications/tate-papers/06/authenticity-change-and-loss-conservation-of-time-based-media-installations.</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="melzer1995a" label="Melzer 1995a">Melzer, A., 1995. <title rend="quotes"
                     ><q>Best Betrayal</q>: The Documentation of Performance on Video and Film, Part
                  1</title>. <title rend="italic">New Theatre Quarterly</title> 11, 42,
               147–157.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="melzer1995b" label="Melzer 1995b">Melzer, A., 1995. <title rend="quotes"
                     ><q>Best Betrayal</q>: The Documentation of Performance on Video and Film, Part
                  2</title>. <title rend="italic">New Theatre Quarterly</title> 11, 43,
               259–76.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pomian1992" label="Pomian 1992">Pomian, K., 1992. <title rend="quotes">Les
                  archives. Du trésor des chartes au Caran</title>, in: Nora, P. (Ed.), <title
                  rend="italic">Les Lieux de Mémoire</title>. T. III, Vol. 3. Gallimard, Paris,
               163-233.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rinehart2007" label="Rinehart 2007">Rinehart, R., 2007. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Media Art Notation System: Documenting and Preserving
                  Digital/Media Art</title>. <title rend="italic">Leonardo</title> 40, 181–187. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1162/leon.2007.40.2.181"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1162/leon.2007.40.2.181</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rinehart2014" label="Rinehart and Ippolito 2014">Rinehart, R., Ippolito,
               J., 2014. <title rend="italic">Re-Collection: Art, New Media, and Social Memory,
                  Leonardo</title>. The MIT Press, Cambridge (MA).</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
