<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Why Digital Humanists Should Emphasize Situated Data
               over Capta</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Matthew <dhq:family>Levin</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation/>
               <email/>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000556</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date/>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>As we pass the ten-year anniversary of Johanna Drucker’s “Humanities Approaches to
            Graphical Display” (2011), I believe it is an opportune time to revisit Drucker’s call
            to “reconceive all data as capta” (Drucker, 2011).<note>I would like to thank Sam
               Cowling, John Ladd, Rebecca Lee, and Scott Weingart for reading drafts of this essay
               at various stages of the writing process, as well as the peer reviewers of this piece
               for generously providing constructive criticism and suggestions for revision.</note>
            Drucker’s argument for such a reimagining is based on “the etymological roots” of data
            and capta — data comes from the Latin “given,” and capta from the Latin “taken” — and
            raises a larger point about the differences between scientific realism and
            constructivist critiques of realism.<note>In making this claim, Drucker gestures at two
               well-known positions on the relationship between “theoretical claims” and “knowledge
               of the world.” However, these polarities can be divided into numerous subcategories,
               and many such positions do not fit neatly into the category of realism or
               constructivism. For a detailed summary of such responses, see Anjan Chakravartty,
                  <title rend="quotes">Scientific Realism</title>, <title rend="italic">The Stanford
                  Encyclopedia of Philosophy</title> (Summer 2017 Edition), Ed. Edward N. Zalta,
                  <ref
                  target="https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/sum2017/entries/scientific-realism"
                  >https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/sum2017/entries/scientific-realism</ref>.</note>
            Realist approaches to visualization, Drucker argues, assume “transparency and
            equivalence, as if the phenomenal world were self-evident and the apprehension of it a
            mere mechanical task.” Drucker goes further in stating, “Nothing in intellectual life is
            self-evident or self-identical, nothing in cultural life is mere fact, and nothing in
            the phenomenal world gives rise to a record or representation except through constructed
            expressions.” Drucker lays out a lexical argument between data and capta that more or
            less parallels the realist and constructivist modalities of thought as she describes
            them (i.e., data suggests realism and capta suggests constructivism).<note>In this
               essay, I have chosen to treat data and capta primarily as singular nouns when
               discussing either the term <hi rend="italic">data</hi> or the concept of data. When
               referring to that which is signified by the term data, I have maintained the norm of
               treating data as plural. I have italicized when making statements that refer directly
               to key terms but not when referring to corresponding concepts. </note>
         </p>
         <p>In this piece, I want to argue in favor of embracing some of Drucker’s points about
            humanistic inquiry while simultaneously arguing against capta as a term to be used in
            place of data. As a humanist, I do see value in emphasizing that data are taken and not
            given, but I believe there is a richer etymological narrative, and a richer history of
            the word <hi rend="italic">data</hi> in English, to be described. There is also the more
            complicated question of whether all forms of empiricism require proceeding “as if the
            phenomenal world were self-evident,” and the degree to which social constructions
            mediate our experiences and understanding of the world. I will gesture at these larger
            questions in this essay, but my primary concern is with how scholars in digital
            humanities should approach conversations about data. </p>
         <p>The bulk of my essay is a revised and expanded etymology for the terms <hi rend="italic"
               >data</hi> and <hi rend="italic">capta</hi>, which considers their Latin roots, as
            well as the close ties of the word <hi rend="italic">data</hi> to the publishing history
            of <hi rend="italic">Euclidis Data </hi>(1625) and subsequent translations and editions
            of that work. Euclid’s own use of the term “given” was a subject for discussion and
            debate, as was the degree to which his use of “given” resembled other Greeks’ use of the
            term. A fully fleshed out history of the term <hi rend="italic">data</hi> in English
            includes its use in two related but distinct senses: geometrical and empirical, the
            latter of these emerging from the prior. To appreciate the difference between these
            senses, we must understand the degree to which early modern thinkers synthesized
            geometrical and numerical thought into what is now regarded as the singular discipline
            of mathematics. Further, these thinkers adapted and extended mathematical thinking to
            translate observations of or measurements from the natural world into generalizations
            and explanatory systems.</p>
         <p>In the closing section of this essay, I will turn to the benefits of embracing concepts
            such as situated data over capta. Such an approach allows humanists to contest
            oversimplifications of poorly executed data-driven inquiry and simultaneously to create
            more opportunities for conversation with other disciplines. The tone of these
            conversations could be positively affected, as well, with digital humanities speaking
            and listening in equal proportion. Lastly, I will discuss the new possibilities that
            this rhetorical shift could create for how we teach data analysis, which has the
            potential to advance digital humanities as a discipline.</p>
         <div>
            <head>Drucker’s Conceptual and Terminological Intervention</head>
            <p>My response to Drucker begins with a certain degree of puzzlement about how
               “Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display” has been received in digital humanities.
               Generally, I take it to have made a strong, positive impression. Drucker was not the
               first scholar to point out that capta might be a more appropriate term than data, but
               her work is arguably the most influential to make this point, especially in digital
                  humanities.<note> See, for example, Stan Kelly-Bootle, <hi rend="italic">The
                     Computer Contradictionary</hi> (MIT Press, 1995); H.E. Jensen, “Editorial Note”
                  (1950) in H Becker, <hi rend="italic">Through Values to Social Interpretation</hi>
                  (Duke UP, 1952): vii-xi.</note> This essay, or the corresponding material in
               Drucker’s book <hi rend="italic">Graphesis</hi> (2014), is widely referenced in
               digital humanities, and I have seen it listed on many DH course syllabi.<note> At the
                  time of writing this essay, “Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display” had 399
                  citations on Google Scholar, and <hi rend="italic">Graphesis</hi> had 348.
                  Examples of syllabi raising this topic directly or assigning Drucker on this topic
                  include: <ref target="https://cms633.github.io/assets/cms-633-syllabus.pdf"
                     >https://cms633.github.io/assets/cms-633-syllabus.pdf</ref>; <ref
                     target="http://benschmidt.org/HDA19/syllabus__syllabus.html"
                     >http://benschmidt.org/HDA19/syllabus__syllabus.html</ref>; <ref
                     target="https://dhcu.ca/portfolio/syllabus/"
                     >https://dhcu.ca/portfolio/syllabus/</ref>; and <ref
                     target="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~dbamman/courses/76829/schedule.html"
                     >http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~dbamman/courses/76829/schedule.html</ref>.</note> There
               appear to have been numerous conference presentations, blog posts, and discussions of
               capta on social media. In various contexts, public displays of one’s agreement with
               Drucker might take the form of statements like, “There is no such thing as ‘data’.
               There are only ‘capta’.”<note> Shawn Graham, syllabus for graduate seminar in DH,
                     <ref target="https://dhcu.ca/portfolio/syllabus/"
                     >https://dhcu.ca/portfolio/syllabus/</ref>. On the original syllabus, the word
                     <hi rend="italic">capta</hi> is hyperlinked to Drucker’s piece for <hi
                     rend="italic">DHQ</hi>.</note> Broadly speaking, Drucker has set the terms of
               the debate on the subject of data and capta, and this influence has been both
               descriptive and normative. Simultaneously, I have not seen signs of a large-scale
               movement to purge documents of the word <hi rend="italic">data</hi>, nor have the
               word <hi rend="italic">capta</hi> or its cognates become especially prevalent in
               digital humanities scholarship.<note> It is conceivable that DH would begin
                  publishing papers on captabases and metacapta, but many who would prefer the term
                     <hi rend="italic">capta</hi> are probably using data cognates and phrases out
                  of convenience or preference. Kelly-Bottle satirically raises the possibility of
                  terms like capta entry, capta processing, and captabase in <hi rend="italic">The
                     Computer Contradictionary</hi> (1995). When I attempt a Google search for
                  metacapta, I get the response, “Did you mean metacarta, metacipta, metacapital,
                  metacafe?” On Google Scholar, I get results for metacaptcha and metacapita.
                  (Results collected in Summer 2020.) </note>
            </p>
            <p>One might argue that Drucker makes a conceptual intervention and not a terminological
               one. I would concede that the essay is most concerned with reconceptualizing data as
               capta, and the importance of such a shift. With regard to data visualization, Drucker
               argues that “the rendering of statistical information into graphical form gives it a
               simplicity and legibility that hides every aspect of the original interpretative
               framework on which the statistical data were constructed.” Data do not “pre-exist
               their parameterization” because they are “constructed as an interpretation of the
               phenomenal world, not inherent in it” (Drucker, 2011). Drucker does not explicitly
               argue that humanities scholars should never say or write the word <hi rend="italic"
                  >data</hi>, but she does claim that “all data is capta” and that because of the
               etymological roots of the terms, <hi rend="italic">capta</hi> “is ‘taken’ actively
                  while <hi rend="italic">data</hi> is assumed to be a ‘given’ able to be recorded
               and observed.” As a result, I reject the idea that one can so easily separate
               Drucker’s conceptual intervention from the terminological one supporting it. </p>
            <p>Another way of looking at Drucker’s influence would be to say that there is
               widespread agreement with her views on data and capta, but practical considerations
               outweigh other concerns. Such practical considerations include (1) maximizing clarity
               for particular audiences, (2) limits on space that would make it difficult to explain
               the choice to use <hi rend="italic">capta</hi>, and (3) the question of how to invoke
               concepts like big data, data visualization, databases, datasets, metadata, and open
               data. One might attempt to stake out a rhetorical middle position by mentioning that
               data are really capta and to proceed with the word <hi rend="italic">data</hi>
               thereafter, as Rob Kitchin does in <hi rend="italic">The Data Revolution: Big Data,
                  Open Data, Data Infrastructures and Their Consequences</hi> (2014). Kitchin adds,
               “since the term data has been so thoroughly ingrained to mean capta, rather than
               confuse the matter further it makes sense to continue to use the term data where
               capta would be more appropriate” (Kitchin, 2014). This seems like it would be an
               appealing option for many people, and I suspect it is widespread, although I have not
               investigated this question in any serious way. </p>
            <p>Regardless, I am aware of no published work that disputes Drucker’s core points. That
               is: <list>
                  <item>the word <hi rend="italic">data </hi>connotes something given and</item>
                  <item>reconceptualizing data as capta is integral to rejecting realist assumptions
                     of transparency and equivalence between data and the phenomena they purport to
                     represent. </item>
               </list></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>A Revised and Expanded Etymology for Data and Capta</head>
            <p>In direct response to Drucker, I hope to demonstrate that the word <hi rend="italic"
                  >data </hi>does not assume a given that can be transparently and unproblematically
               recorded and observed. If this first point can be satisfactorily established, it
               should follow that one can say and write the word <hi rend="italic">data</hi>,
               embrace “the situated, partial, and constitutive character of knowledge production,”
               and recognize that “knowledge is constructed, <hi rend="italic">taken</hi>, not
               simply given as a natural representation of pre-existing fact” (Drucker, 2011). This
               line of reasoning is crucial to how digital humanists understand and talk about the
               concept of data, as well as how we teach computational methods. However, making such
               an argument first requires revisiting the origin of <hi rend="italic">data </hi>as a
               term of use in English and discussing how the meaning of the term <hi rend="italic"
                  >data</hi> has changed over time. </p>
            <p>To begin, the word <hi rend="italic">data</hi> indeed comes from the Latin for
               “given,” but the etymology of the English language word is less straightforward than
               Drucker suggests. A more detailed account of “the early history of the concept of
               ‘data’” is Daniel Rosenberg’s “Data Before the Fact” (2013), which discusses much of
               the early history of data’s English usage. As Rosenberg describes, “In English,
               ‘data’ was first used in the seventeenth century. Yet it is not wrong to associate
               the emergence of the concept and that of modernity. The rise of the concept in the
               seventeenth and eighteenth centuries is tightly linked to the development of modern
               concepts of knowledge and argumentation” (15). Rosenberg emphasizes the “specifically
               rhetorical” status of the word <hi rend="italic">data </hi>as something both
               “pre-analytical” and “pre-factual,” more so even than the related concepts of “facts”
               and “evidence” (19). As he further explains, “When a fact is proven false, it ceases
               to be a fact. False data is data nonetheless” (18). Rosenberg’s telling of the early
               history of data in English adequately distinguishes between the two earliest senses
               of the term <hi rend="italic">data,</hi> the first in “the realm of mathematics,
               where it retained the technical sense that it has in Euclid, as quantities <hi
                  rend="italic">given </hi>in mathematical problems, as opposed to the <hi
                  rend="italic">quaesita</hi>, or quantities <hi rend="italic">sought</hi>” and the
               second “in the realm of theology, where it referred to scriptural truths — whether
               principles or facts — that were given by God and therefore not susceptible to
               questioning” (19). However, I want to argue that these two senses are more closely
               related than one might first assume, and there is a third early sense of the word
               that Rosenberg does not fully distinguish. </p>
            <p>First, the <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary </hi>provides an entry for
               data as “something given or granted; something known or assumed as fact, and made the
               basis of reasoning; an assumption or premise from which inferences are drawn”
               (“data,” n., <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>). We might call this “data in the geometrical
               sense.” This phrasing is intended to echo Rosenberg’s definition, except for the
               distinction that our contemporary concept of mathematics depends on a synthesis of
               geometrical and numerical paradigms of thought that had not yet fully unfolded in
               Europe circa 1600.<note> The <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> cites the earliest use of
                  mathematics as “(a collective term for) geometry, arithmetic, and certain physical
                  sciences involving geometrical reasoning, such as astronomy and optics” to
                  Christopher Langton, circa 1545. For more on the unification of geometrical and
                  numerical thought, see Patrick Suppes et. al., <hi rend="italic">Foundations of
                     Measurement Volume 2</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Geometrical, Threshold, and
                     Probabilistic Representations</hi> (Elsevier, 2014): 80-81.</note> The story of
               the data’s entry into English must include some history of the translation of
               Euclid’s work from Greek to Latin and English, a story Rosenberg alludes to but does
               not detail in full. The Greek word δεδομένα (dedoména) means “given.” Δεδομένα (<hi
                  rend="italic">Dedoména</hi>) is the title of a work by Euclid, which remains
               extant in manuscript form in Greek and Arabic. It was translated into Latin by the
               French mathematician Claude Hardy and printed alongside its original Greek as a
               volume titled <hi rend="italic">Euclidis Data </hi>in 1625. An English translation
               with the title <hi rend="italic">Euclid’s Data</hi> was included with an edition
                  of<hi rend="italic"> Euclid’s Elements of Geometry</hi> (John Leeke &amp; George
               Serle) in 1661.<note> English language translations of Euclid’s <hi rend="italic"
                     >Elements of Geometry</hi> date as far back as 1570. See Adam Clarke, <hi
                     rend="italic">The Bibliographical Miscellany</hi> (London: W. Baynes, 1806):
                  77-78.</note> The <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> traces this sense of the word <hi
                  rend="italic">data</hi> to Henry Hammond’s <hi rend="italic">A copy of some papers
                  past at Oxford, betwixt the author of the Practicall catechisme, and Mr. Ch.</hi>
               in 1646, which refers to “a heape of data,” but, as Rosenberg points out, this heap
               “is not a pile of numbers but a list of theological propositions accepted as true for
               the sake of argument” (20). It may seem counter-intuitive to associate the
               Greek-to-Latin geometrical usage of <hi rend="italic">data</hi> with what Jonathan
               Furner calls “data as gifts from God,” but the theological or ecclesiastical notion
               of data is a direct antecedent of how Euclid used the term <hi rend="italic"
                  >data</hi>/<hi rend="italic">dedoména</hi> (Furner, 2016, 292). Furner elaborates
               that such uses go back to Thomas Tuke’s <hi rend="italic">Nevv Essayes</hi> of 1614,
               and that the Latin word <hi rend="italic">data </hi>is found in other Latin phrases
               in “religious texts of early seventeenth-century England — for example, <hi
                  rend="italic">gratia gratis data </hi>(‘grace freely given’), and <hi
                  rend="italic">data desuper</hi> (‘given from above’)” (292). Like Rosenberg,
               Furner differentiates between <hi rend="italic">data </hi>in the geometrical sense
               and <hi rend="italic">data</hi> in the ecclesiastical sense, but they both owe their
               meaning to a fairly literal translation of the Latin word as “given.”</p>
            <p>Quite different from this first cluster is what we might call “data in the empirical
               sense.” The <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> refers to datum “chiefly in plural” (i.e.,
               data), which describes “an item of (chiefly numerical) information obtained by
               scientific work, a number of which are typically collected together for reference,
               analysis, or calculation” with first use listed as 1630 (“data”, n.<hi rend="italic">
                  OED</hi>).<note> The <hi rend="italic">OED </hi>credits William Batten’s <hi
                     rend="italic">A MOST PLAINE and easie way for the finding of the Sunnes
                     Amplitude and Azimuth, and thereby the Variation of the Compasse, by
                     Logarithme</hi> (1630) under a truncated title. Note, also, that the word <hi
                     rend="italic">data</hi> appears in keyword searches of databases like Early
                  English Book Online (EEBO) before these 1630 because editions in Latin, or English
                  language editions with Latin quotations or epigraphs, were quite common. In
                  Rosenberg’s words, “the Latin word <hi rend="italic">data</hi>, as a conjugation
                  of the verb <hi rend="italic">dare</hi>, was in constant use during the
                  seventeenth and eighteenth centuries … but <hi rend="italic">data</hi> in Latin
                  rarely translates to ‘data’ in English” (20). </note> This sense of the word seems
               to relate to the <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>’s entry for data “as a count noun: an
               item of information; a datum; a set of data” (first use listed as 1645) and later, as
               “a mass noun,” meaning “related items of (chiefly numerical) information considered
               collectively, typically obtained by scientific work and used for reference, analysis,
               or calculation” with its first use listed as 1702 (“data”, n.<hi rend="italic">
                  OED</hi>).<note> The<hi rend="italic"> OED</hi> credits T. Urquhart’s <hi
                     rend="italic">Trissotetras</hi> (1645) as the earliest known example of data as
                  a count noun, and credits Robert Morden’s <hi rend="italic">An Introduction to
                     Astronomy, Geography, Navigation, and other mathematical sciences, made easie
                     by the description and uses of the cœlestial and terrestial globes</hi> (1702)
                  as the earliest known example of data as a mass noun.</note> There are likely
               examples of historic usage where data appears to be something in between the
               geometrical sense and the empirical sense, but the difference between the two in
               their sharpest forms is quite significant, and assuming the associations of the first
               sense carry over to the second sense would be a mistake. To better understand the
               dissimilarities between these senses, we must reexamine the first English translation
               of Euclid’s <hi rend="italic">Data</hi>.</p>
            <p>How Euclid had used <hi rend="italic">dedoména/data</hi> is the subject of a
               commentary by Marinus of Neapolis, translated and included in Leeke and Serle’s
               edition, for “the Ancients have defined it in one manner, and later Writers after
               another” (Marinus, 1661, 533). For Marinus, the question was whether Euclid’s notion
               of data could be defined as a combination of <hi rend="italic">ordinatum</hi>
               (regulated or orderly) and <hi rend="italic">poriman</hi> (available or provided) or
               as a combination of <hi rend="italic">cognitum</hi> (infamous or known) and <hi
                  rend="italic">porimon</hi>. Marinus’ two candidate definitions may appear to map
               directly to the English language senses of geometrical data and empirical data, but
               this is not the case. Neither of Marinus’ notions would have been used as a term to
               describe aspects of the natural world, only for abstractions like the following:
                  <list type="ordered">
                  <item>The length of a line C when line C equals the length of line A minus the
                     length of line B, and the lengths of lines A and B are both given. </item>
                  <item>The length of line Z connecting two points A and B, when the positions of
                     points A and B are given. </item>
               </list></p>
            <p>Drawing on examples from Euclid and other ancient texts, Marinus concludes that
               Euclid is referring to data as a combination of <hi rend="italic">porimon</hi>, “that
               which may be exhibited by Demonstration, or which is apparent without Demonstration”
               and <hi rend="italic">cognitum, </hi>that which is “clear and comprehended of us”
               (535; 534). However, his recognition of a second candidate definition, describing
               data as a combination of <hi rend="italic">ordinatum</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                  >poriman</hi> should be noted, as it could point to others forming a similar
               impression. </p>
            <p>More recently, Christian Taisbak notes that Euclid’s use of the word <hi
                  rend="italic">data</hi> means both the clear and comprehended premise, and the
               demonstrated conclusion. </p>
            <p>When I started to translate the <hi rend="italic">Data, </hi>I found it very
               longwinded that a certain phrase kept popping up time and again, several times in
               every proposition: <hi rend="italic">if this item is given, that item is </hi>also
                  <hi rend="italic">given. </hi>I decided to cancel all those <hi rend="italic"
                  >alsos</hi> and restore them only where they were absolutely necessary. But then I
               discovered that I was leaving out an essential feature of the <hi rend="italic">Data:
               </hi>the Givens hang together in chains, the purpose of any proposition being to
               produce more links to them. (Taisbak, 2003, 14)</p>
            <p>Taisbak is essentially describing deductive reasoning, “that if some items are given,
               some other items are also given, <hi rend="italic">into the bargain </hi>so to speak”
               (13). For Euclid, <hi rend="italic">dedoména</hi> referred “not only to the input of
               a problem, but also to the output” (13). In this context, one might also compare
               Euclid’s use of <hi rend="italic">data</hi> to <hi rend="italic">akolouthia</hi>
               (ἀκολουθία), a term favored by Aristotle and others, which “indicates the necessary
               relationship between two propositions when one of them is the consequence of the
               other” (Seco and Maspero, 2010, 15).<note> See Michael Frede, “Stoic vs. Aristotelian
                  Syllogistic.” In <hi rend="italic">Essays in Ancient Philosophy</hi> (U of
                  Minnesota P, 1987). 99–124; John Spangler Kieffer, <hi rend="italic">Galen’s
                     Institutio Logica: English Translation, Introduction, and Commentary</hi>. (JHU
                  Press, 2020); and Lucas Francisco Mateo Seco and Giulio Maspero. <hi rend="italic"
                     >The Brill Dictionary of Gregory of Nyssa</hi>. (Brill, 2010). </note> This
               perspective complicates Rosenberg’s gloss of<hi rend="italic"> data</hi> as
               quantities given and <hi rend="italic">quaesita</hi> as quantities sought, since
               quantities sought can in fact become given through demonstration or deduction (ὅπερ
               ἔδει δεῖξαι / hóper édei deîxai).<note> See David Dunér and Christer Ahlberger, <hi
                     rend="italic">Cognitive History: Mind, Space, and Time</hi> (Walter de Gruyter
                  GmbH &amp; Co KG, 2019). 100.</note> These nuances remain specific to the
               geometrical rather than the empirical concept of data that I have so far discussed,
               but they are important aspects of the history of the term <hi rend="italic"
               >data</hi>, as well as the history of how that term became associated with
               quantitative reasoning. As a result, these details already suggest the beginnings of
               a pedagogical intervention in digital humanities, where the “given-ness” of data is
               more complex that it might initially appear. </p>
            <p>Data in the empirical sense appears to draw upon aspects of data as a geometrical
               given and extend these qualities to features of the natural world. For the likes of
               Apollonius, Euclid, and Marinus, the concept of data would never imply collecting
               information in this way. Observations of the sort said to be described in
               Eratosthenes’ <hi rend="italic">Γεωγραφία</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Geografíka</hi>),
               would be called φαινόμενο (fainómeno), or phenomenon, which translates to “that which
               appears or is seen.”<note> The <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>’s etymological entry for
                  phenomenon describes, “things that appear, appearances, phenomena, celestial
                  phenomena (title of a work by Eudoxus, versified by Aratus), use as noun of neuter
                     of <hi rend="italic">ϕαινόμενος</hi> appearing, apparent (to the senses or
                  mind), passive present participle of <hi rend="italic">ϕαίνειν</hi> to show, cause
                  to appear.” For more on Eratosthenes’ <hi rend="italic">Geography</hi>, see
                  Eratosthenes, <hi rend="italic">Eratosthenes’ “Geography”</hi> (Princeton
                  University Press, 2010).</note> Phenomena included anything that appeared to be
               true, such as illusions, mirages, and dreams. James Evans and J. Lennart Berggren
               explain that “the word ‘phenomena’ is a participle of the passive verb <hi
                  rend="italic">phanomai</hi>, which carries the meanings of ‘to come to light, come
               to sight, be seen, appear.’” They add, “The last two are definitive for the
               astronomical sense of the word, which is ‘things that are seen/appear in the
               heavens’” (Evans and Berggren, 2018, 5). An entire genre of Greek philosophical
               thought was dedicated to the idea that, from careful observation of the heavens, one
               could understand the positions of the earth, the planets, and the stars, as well as
               explain the circular motions of all celestial bodies. Hence the notion, originating
               in Greek astronomy, of σωζειν τα φαινόμενα (sozein ta fainómena) or “save the
               phenomena” (Heath, 1921, 7). Works within this genre included Euclid’s <hi
                  rend="italic">The Phenomena</hi>, Autolykos’ <hi rend="italic">On the Moving
                  Sphere</hi>, Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">On the Heavens</hi>, Gemino’s <hi
                  rend="italic">Introduction to the Phenomena</hi>, and Theodesius’ <hi
                  rend="italic">Sphaerics</hi>, which is thought to extend the work of Eudoxos.
               Contributions to this genre continued into the Middle Ages. </p>
            <p>These writers did not appear to distinguish between their observations and the way
               they were structured or recorded. Much later, the genre of “Almanack of Ephemeris” or
               “Ephemerides” seems to suggest a potential term that makes this distinction. The
               earliest use of the term <hi rend="italic">almanac</hi>, meaning “an annual table, or
               (more usually) a book of tables,” can be traced to <hi rend="italic">The Equatorie of
                  the Planetis</hi> (circa CE 1392), whereas the term <hi rend="italic"
                  >ephemeris</hi> was used as early as the mid-16th century (“almanac”, n. <hi
                  rend="italic">OED</hi>). According to Arthur L. Norberg, an almanac of ephemeris,
               by the nineteenth century, “contained information on the phenomena for that year:
               eclipses of the Sun, Moon, and Jupiter’s satellites; the orientation of Saturn’s
               rings and the apparent discs of Venus and Mars” (Martin Campbell-Kelly et al., 2003,
               196). For whatever reason, neither of these terms caught on as a more generalized
               word for the kind of structured information one might generate by making and
               recording observations. As with Taisbak’s point about givens, for Euclid, functioning
               as the inputs and outputs of problems, the seeds of a pedagogical intervention are
               here planted. Phenomena were recorded and published with the expectation that future
               observations might supplement, refine, or replace previous ones, which suggests a
               fundamental awareness that representations of phenomena were partial and imperfect.
               Certainly, at almost any moment in history, some were expressing their belief in a
               unified, coherent reality just beyond our reach, as well as their confidence that
               their tabulations would allow them to decipher its governing dynamics. I will return
               to this subject in this essay’s conclusion but, for now, it should suffice to say
               that this belief is best understood not as a position on the distinguishing
               properties of data, but rather a position on the possibility of obtaining objective
               knowledge through empirical means. </p>
            <p>It is also crucial to note that the idea of a table as a textual and material device
               for structuring numerical information is at least 4,500 years old. According to
               Martin Campbell Kelly and his co-authors, “While the list has been hailed as a major
               breakthrough in cognitive history … the table as a pre-modern phenomenon of
               structured thought has been completely neglected” (13). In ancient Sumer, Babylonia,
               and Assyria, clay tablets were often if not primarily a repository of numerical
               information, often used as a memorization or calculation aid. Etymologically, the
               word <hi rend="italic">table</hi> comes from the Latin<hi rend="italic"> tabula</hi>,
               which in turn, originates with the Greek term τάβλι (<hi rend="italic">tabl</hi>a),
               meaning a plank or board (Austin, 1934, 202-5). The term was used to refer to a
               particular board game that is thought to be the ancestor of backgammon, and was also
               a general term for a tablet, a slate, or any flat piece of wood. In English, it
               eventually a particular piece of furniture “on which food is served, and at or around
               which people sit at a meal” (circa CE 1300). The English word <hi rend="italic"
                  >table</hi> meaning “a schematic arrangement of information” or “an orderly
               arrangement of particulars” can be traced as far back as Byrhtferth of Ramsey’s<hi
                  rend="italic"> Enchiridion </hi>(CE 986-1016), but the association between a
               tablet/slate and structured information recorded upon it appears to be much older
               (“table, n.” <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>). </p>
            <p>Today, the phrase “tabular data” suggests a strong association between tables and
               data, and the term <hi rend="italic">observation </hi>is widely used to denote “all
               values measured on the same unit (like a person, or a day, or a race) across
               attributes” or, in the context of rectangular data, a row of values.<note> See Hadley
                  Wickham, “Tidy Data,” <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Statistical Software</hi>,
                  vol. 59 (August 2014). 1-23. In contrast to an observation, values are specific
                  numbers or string, and a variable “contains all values that measure the same
                  underlying attribute (like height, temperature, duration) across units” (Wickham
                  3). </note> As Lisa Gitelman notes, the idea of converting that which one observes
               into data — a conceptual object that structures and represents that which has been
               perceived — seems like second nature to us. “When phenomena are variously reduced to
               data, they are divided and classified, processes that work to obscure — or <hi
                  rend="italic">as if </hi>to obscure — ambiguity, conflict, and contradiction”
               (Gitelman, 2013, 9). For Gitelman, this relationship suggests both a dependency on
               hierarchy, and a kind of epistemological cover that protects “users who perform
               logical operations on the data … from having to know how the data have been
               organized” (9). When terms like “data-driven” are invoked, there is often an
               assumption of order, imposed or revealed, by those engaging in analysis.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, the idea of ordering and standardizing information for the purposes of
               facilitating numerical operations is much older than the English word <hi
                  rend="italic">data</hi>. What seems to have changed is that the term <hi
                  rend="italic">data</hi> adopted a secondary meaning in addition to the geometrical
               sense of term associated with Euclid. An entry in Ephraim Chambers’ <hi rend="italic"
                  >Cyclopædia</hi> (1728) offers two definitions for the term <hi rend="italic"
                  >data</hi>. First, it continued to refer to a geometrical given. Second, “From the
               primary Use of the Word <hi rend="italic">Data </hi>in mathematicks, it has been
               transplanted into other Arts; as Philosophy, Medicine, &amp;c. where it expresses any
               Quantity, which for the Sake of a present Calculation, is taken for granted to be
               such, without requiring an immediate Proof for its Certainty” (Chambers, 1728, 64).
               According to Chambers, data had come to be used to describe a quantity, in a wide
               range of contexts, that was meant to be treated as a given for the purposes of
               analysis. This definition reinforces the distinction between data in the strictly
               geometrical sense and data in other contexts, and it is compatible with religious
               uses of the term, since information from scripture would qualify as data of the
               geometrical sort, or knowledge beyond question. </p>
            <p>This explanation does not describe a specific process by which phenomena become data.
               However, the clause “for the Sake of a present calculation” seems to limit why and
               how the data are permitted to be taken for granted, which undercuts the idea that
               data would be regarded as natural or pre-existing facts. In turn, it contradicts the
               idea that data in this sense could ever be viewed as pre-factual, as Rosenberg
               describes. Among the natural philosophers of the 17th and 18th centuries, the idea
               that Nature would reveal its hidden structure or laws to those who spoke its language
               was predominant.<note> See Peter H. Reill, <hi rend="italic">Vitalizing Nature in the
                     Enlightenment</hi> (University of California Press, 2005); Lorraine Daston and
                  Peter Galison, <hi rend="italic">Objectivity</hi> (Zone Books, 2010); Edward
                  Dolnick, <hi rend="italic">The Clockwork Universe: Isaac Newton, The Royal
                     Society, and The Birth of the Modern World</hi> (Harper Collins, 2011).</note>
               In this light, it seems likely if not obvious that empirical observations would be
               considered facts given by God. However, if data were available or provided because
               Nature had provided them for us to analyze, then there would be no need for Chambers’
               qualifying phrase. The entry in Chambers’ <hi rend="italic">Cyclopædia</hi> seems
               more compatible with the idea that phenomena become data, or are granted provisional
               status as data, which suspends the need for “an immediate proof” and permits
               calculation to occur.<note> For more on early modern associations between knowledge
                  and sin, as well as associations between epistemological errors and sin, see Peter
                  Harrison, <hi rend="italic">The Fall of Man and the Foundations of Science</hi>
                  (Cambridge University Press, 2007).</note>
            </p>
            <p>Returning to Marinus’ two candidate definitions for Euclid’s notion of data — as <hi
                  rend="italic">porimon</hi> plus <hi rend="italic">cognitum</hi> or <hi
                  rend="italic">porimon</hi> plus <hi rend="italic">ordinatum</hi>—we can see a case
               for either or both.<note> Taisbak translates πορίσαοθαι (porizesthai) cognate to the
                  verb “to provide”, as “available” in this context (24). </note> Imposing Marinus’
               analysis on Chambers’ definition is potentially problematic, but I would argue that
               our contemporary use of the term <hi rend="italic">data </hi>is best explained by
               starting with the notion of data as <hi rend="italic">porimon</hi> plus <hi
                  rend="italic">ordinatum</hi>. Recall that this sense — as a combination of
               something provided in a way that gives it order — was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> the
               sense Euclid was not using, according to Marinus. As Taisbak notes, however, <hi
                  rend="italic">ordinatum</hi> for Marinus was the Greek word τεταγμένων
               (tetagmenon), literally “fixed,” but also used to mean “organized according to some
                  <hi rend="italic">taxis</hi>, ‘order’” (242). Regarding the Latin <hi
                  rend="italic">porimon</hi>, the Greek term πορίσαοθαι (porizesthai), Taisbak
               explains that Euclid uses the term to describe “several operations,” including “put
               together,” “draw,” “describe,” “make,” or “produce” (242).<note> Taisbak adds that
                     <hi rend="italic">porimon</hi> is “vital to the interpretation of the <hi
                     rend="italic">Data</hi>,” but Euclid “uses the word as being self-explanatory.
                  It seems to be imported from everyday market prose meaning ‘procure’, ‘furnish’,
                  ‘get (for oneself)’: any kind of purchase without specification of method and
                  currency” (242). </note> By this logic, defining <hi rend="italic">data</hi> as
               both <hi rend="italic">porimon</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ordinatum</hi> would
               emphasize its being available, collected, or made, as well as being brought to order
               or revealed to have latent order by the act of demonstration.</p>
            <p>Broadly speaking, then, a full-fledged etymology of the term <hi rend="italic"
                  >data</hi> suggests a narrative much more complex than data as “given” and capta
               as “taken.” The Latin word for “given” was used by Euclid in a manner very different
               from how data was used by the mid-18th century, and the true meaning of the Euclidian
               concept of dedoména/data has disputed definitions among classical thinkers, as
               Marinus summarizes. Concepts such as saving the phenomena, an almanac of ephemeris,
               and tabular information suggest an ancient and longstanding tradition of making
               precise observations, placing them a structured format, and using that structure to
               facilitate calculation. Taking Chambers into account, it seems likely that facts
               became eligible to be regarded as data by being provided or made available by a
               person or group of people who had made observations or measurements, and then imposed
               some form of order or structure upon them in order to facilitate analysis. Drucker’s
               advocacy for capta as a key term and a guiding principle is rooted in the notion that
               the term <hi rend="italic">data</hi> assumes a pre-existing given that can be naively
               recorded without being shaped by the observer. The story I have told suggests a more
               nuanced history of data, both as a term and a concept. There is room to embrace the
                  word<hi rend="italic"> data</hi> and understand data to be inevitably fragmentary,
               imperfect, and tentative, yet simultaneously useful in their ability to organize
               knowledge and facilitate modes of analysis that would otherwise be impossible. In the
               section that follows, I will make the case for embracing concepts like situated data
               and data-rich literary history to convey this message, which includes potential
               benefits to scholarly discourse and digital humanities pedagogy.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Situating Data for the Sake of Interdisciplinarity and Digital Humanities
               Pedagogy</head>
            <p>Up to now, I have attempted to show that the term <hi rend="italic">data</hi> has a
               much more nuanced history that its translation to the English word <hi rend="italic"
                  >given</hi>. This revised etymology leaves room for an understanding of both the
               term and concept as less closely linked to naive realism than Drucker suggests. As
               S.I. Hayakawa once famously wrote, “the writer of a dictionary is a historian, not a
               lawgiver” (Hayakawa, 1990, 35). The meaning of <hi rend="italic">data</hi> has
               changed over time and, at any given time, no singular meaning for the term was
               universal. I have pointed to one important sea change, by which data came to have
               special prominence in the context of empiricism. A longer essay could say much more
               on the subject of additional changes in prevailing notions of the term, or additional
               meanings that persist in specific contexts or among specialized groups. Along with
               the accepted range of definitions for <hi rend="italic">data</hi>, their various
               connotations and their preferred rhetorical uses, have also changed over time. I
               think Drucker is right to point out that many today use the term <hi rend="italic"
                  >data</hi> to suggest a kind unimpeachable concreteness rather than something
               partly born out of the assumptions made when selecting and organizing said data. I
               suspect that there is widespread disagreement among self-proclaimed empiricists about
               the degree to which data are “natural representations” as opposed to “situated,
               partial, and constitutive”, but I agree that scientific rhetoric often downplays or
               denies the artificial, conditional, and fragmentary aspects of data (Drucker, 2011). </p>
            <p>As an alternative to avoiding the term <hi rend="italic">data</hi>, I would argue
               that digital humanities should focus on challenging and complicating beliefs about
               the purity, objectivity, or totality of data, all the while using the word <hi
                  rend="italic">data</hi> frequently, and without any shame. There is a strong
               defense for using the word <hi rend="italic">data</hi> mindfully and unapologetically
               based on the understanding that data are collected, assembled, and recorded by people
               (or their instruments). Data have structure, but this structure comes (at least in
               part) from how observations are gathered and organized, as well as shaped by the
               interpretive decisions made at their inception. Contextual information about these
               interpretive decisions is a vital component of a dataset. Many in digital humanities
               have already moved in this direction, shifting from notions of “good data” and “bad
               data” to concepts like data as situated knowledge, as described in Catherine
               D’Ignazio and Lauren F. Klein’s <hi rend="italic">Data Feminism</hi> (2020) or
               data-rich literary history as described in Katherine Bode’s <hi rend="italic">A World
                  of Fiction: Digital Collections and the Future of Literary History</hi> (2019).
               The benefits of these strategies are both discursive and pedagogical.</p>
            <p>The first benefit of this approach is to move away from an argument based on word
               origin. A word’s origins seldom tell an accurate story of a word’s historical use or
               contemporary valences. There are numerous Latin words with English homographs, and
               often their meanings have changed over time. Words such as <hi rend="italic"
                  >plastic</hi>, <hi rend="italic">stigma</hi>, <hi rend="italic">campus,
               focus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">versus</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> stimulus</hi>, and <hi
                  rend="italic">sinister</hi> all have Latin antecedents with meanings that differ
               greatly from their contemporary use in English. With the word <hi rend="italic"
                  >data</hi>, there is added ambiguity because the English word <hi rend="italic"
                  >given</hi> has more than one meaning. Describing an idea as “a given” or “a
               warrant” in the context of a rhetorical argument remains common, and seems to carry
               no implication of pre-factualness or ineligible for questioning.<note> The word <hi
                     rend="italic">plastic</hi> comes from the Latin for “capable of shaping or
                  molding” (Sullivan 165) while <hi rend="italic">stigma </hi>conveys the “mark of a
                  pointed instrument, puncture, tattoo-mark, or brand” (Sullivan 206). C<hi
                     rend="italic">ampus</hi> is Latin for “field,” <hi rend="italic">focus </hi>is
                  Latin for “hearth,” and <hi rend="italic">versus</hi> is Latin for a line of
                  poetry (Sullivan 194, 103, 220). A <hi rend="italic">stimulus </hi>was a prod or a
                  goad, which is to say a sharp stick used to urge livestock forward (Vaan 587). <hi
                     rend="italic">Sinister</hi> comes from the Latin word for “left,” and
                  eventually came to mean evil or unlucky, but was purportedly used by the Romans
                  “in the opposite sense,” such that am “<hi rend="italic">avis sinistra</hi>” or
                  “bird in the left hand … was esteemed a happy omen” (<hi rend="italic"
                     >Encyclopaedia Perthensis</hi>, 1816, 7). If the frame is widened to include
                  linguistic doublets and cognates, the list balloons to the point of absurdity. The
                  words <hi rend="italic">dose</hi>, <hi rend="italic">antidote</hi>, <hi
                     rend="italic">anecdote</hi>, <hi rend="italic">date</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                     >donation</hi>, <hi rend="italic">addendum</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                     >addition</hi>, <hi rend="italic">edition</hi>, <hi rend="italic">editor</hi>,
                     <hi rend="italic">mandate</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">mandatory</hi> all share
                  the Greek or Latin root word for the verb “to give,” but they have a vast range of
                  meanings and associations today (Shipley 73). Perhaps most ironically, the
                  portmanteau <hi rend="italic">anecdata</hi> replaces part of the Greek root word
                  for given with the Latin word for given. See Anu Garg, “A.Word.A.Day,” <hi
                     rend="italic">wordsmith.org</hi>
                  <ref target="http://www.wordsmith.org/words/anecdata.html"
                     >http://www.wordsmith.org/words/anecdata.html</ref> for a summary of the term
                     <hi rend="italic">anecdata</hi> and Shipley 73 for a summary of how <hi
                     rend="italic">anecdote </hi>originates with the Greek <hi rend="italic"
                     >didonai</hi>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Capta, likewise, is Latin for taken and therefore has a certain surface appeal as a
               mirror term for data. However, capta can also mean “caught,” “captured,” and
               “captive.” The phrase “Judæa capta” refers to the siege and capture of Jerusalem by
               the Romans, as well as a series of coins issued by the Roman Emperor Vespasian to
               celebrate these actions (Elizabeth, 1845). In the Roman Empire, the phrases “manu
               capta” (Sandars, 1917, xlvii) and “praeda manu capta” denoted that which was
               “captured by hand” or “acquired by force of hands” from among Rome’s enemies.<note>
                  Such phrases referred especially “properties taken in war” and could describe
                  compensation paid by “the vanquished … either in kind (<hi rend="italic"
                     >vectigal</hi>), with money (<hi rend="italic">stipendium</hi>), or with a
                  tribute (<hi rend="italic">tributum</hi>)” (Vico, 2000, 492). </note> Further,
               some enslaved people (<hi rend="italic">servi</hi>) were “so called from the fact
               that commanders are used to <hi rend="italic">sell</hi> their captives, and by this
               means to <hi rend="italic">preserve </hi>(servare) rather than kill them (<hi
                  rend="italic">Justinian Institutes</hi>, qtd. in Cameron, 1972, 5).<note> They are
                  also said to be <hi rend="italic">mancipia</hi>, because they were taken by hand
                  (manu capta) from the enemy” ( <hi rend="italic">Justinian Institutes</hi>, qtd.
                  in Cameron, 1972, 5).</note> These potential associations are important because
               they complicate the idea that data straightforwardly means “given” and capta
               straightforwardly means “taken” as we think of those terms today. Moreover, these
               examples underscore the broader point that it can be a mistake to use a word’s
               denotation in its language of origin (or its historic denotation in English) as the
               primary criteria by which to judge its contemporary meaning or appeal. </p>
            <p>Denotations, connotations, and rhetorical uses change over time, and this is good
               news. Such associations can change once again, and scholars of the humanities can
               help change them. As Helen Longino has argued, the notion of objectivity in
               scientific inquiry is bound up in two different senses of the term, the first
               emphasizing scientific realism, or the idea that science provides an “accurate
               description of the facts of the world as they are” (Longino, 1990, 62). The second,
               associated with modes of inquiry, stresses “reliance on nonarbitrary and
               nonsubjective criteria for developing, accepting, and rejecting the hypotheses and
               theories that make up the view” (62). Further, scientists will often “speak of the
               objectivity of data” but objectivity in this sense should be taken as a claim of
               reliability (63). What makes data objective is “the relationship of measurements to
               one another within a particular dimension or kind of scale” (63). According to
               Longino, it should not be assumed that these measures “are real properties of real
               entities” or “that their measurements provide us with an unmediated view of the
               natural world” (63). In other words, there is an important difference between an
               etymologically inspired belief that data are natural representations of the world —
               given rather than taken — and the idea that scientific observation generates
               objective information by providing epistemological order. The two positions are based
               on competing definitions of objectivity. Adopting the perspective that phenomena
               become data only when they are structured by an investigative agent invites an
               important debate about the objectivity of data once they are standardized and
               assembled, and that is a debate that I would be glad take part in. </p>
            <p>I would not deny the merit of distinguishing between the idea of data-as-given and
               capta-as-taken. However, this distinction may be more a matter of emphasis than
               definition. Whatever the etymological roots and contemporary associations of data, we
               can take capta to emphasize that the measurements, readings, observations have been
               taken. As I have suggested, the word <hi rend="italic">capta</hi> may stir
               connotations of human bondage and violence. This association may be appropriate in
               some cases, especially in a moment when for-profit companies are covertly monetizing
               and selling data on the open market, often in direct conflict with the interests of
               its users. On the other hand, many data do not fit this description, and I think
               regarding all data as captive or hostage to their stewards is provocative, but
               ultimately misguided, especially where there is strong potential for unintended
               consequences. </p>
            <p>As previously suggested, there are matters of utility to consider when deciding
               between data and capta as conceptual signposts. Many in digital humanists are likely
               using the term <hi rend="italic">data</hi> at least some of the time, either as a
               standalone key term, or in cognates or phrases like metadata, database, or data
               visualization. Going further down this path would allow digital humanists to compete
               more effectively for search engine keyword searches, which could make digital
               humanities scholarship more visible to audiences from the sciences. This would
               include direct searches, as well as related searches like “data analysis,” “data
               analytics,” and “data usage,” all of which are top “related to data” searches on
               Google Trends. It would also encourage digital humanities to continue any previous
               efforts to engage directly with specialized topics such as data pedagogy, data
               literacy, open data, data management, and data curation. </p>
            <p>Along these lines, thinking differently about the word <hi rend="italic">data</hi>
               may lead to new exchanges of information among and between disciplines. Digital
               humanities, as a field, has a deeply interdisciplinary history, but a precondition to
               such interdisciplinarity is the premise that different disciplines can learn from one
               another. By engaging directly with concepts related to data, we have opportunity to
               shifts scholarly focus from the nature of data to strategies that promote engaging
               critically, theoretically, and computationally with data. </p>
            <p>Catherine D’Ignazio and Lauren F. Klein take an approach of this sort in <hi
                  rend="italic">Data Feminism</hi> (2020). They define data as “information made
               tractable,” which I immediately associate with Marinus’ discussion of <hi
                  rend="italic">ordinatum</hi>. In various passages, D’Ignazio and Klein cite Donna
               Haraway, whose essay “Situated Knowledges: The Science Question in Feminism and the
               Privilege of Partial Perspective” (1988) called for “a doctrine of embodied
               objectivity that accommodates paradoxical and critical feminist science projects”
               (581). Core to Haraway’s “feminist objectivity” is the principle of situated
               knowledges. Adapting and extending Haraway’s intervention, D’Ignazio and Klein argue
               that “one of the central tenets of feminist thinking is that all knowledge is
               situated” (152). There is a more complicated discussion to be had about whether all
               knowledge is inherently situated or whether it is the work of feminism that situates
               it. Haraway seems to be arguing for the latter when she contrasts situated knowledges
               with “unlocatable, and so irresponsible, knowledge claims” (583). Either way, all
               data have important contexts of creation and organization, and situating them (or
               emphasizing them as situated) includes critical examination of those contexts.<note>
                  See also Jill Walker Rettberg, “Situated Data Analysis: A New Method for Analysing
                  Encoded Power Relationships in Social Media Platforms and Apps.” <hi rend="italic"
                     >Humanities and Social Sciences Communications</hi> 7, no. 1 (June 17, 2020):
                  1–13. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1057/s41599-020-0495-3"
                     >https://doi.org/10.1057/s41599-020-0495-3</ref>. Rettberg also frames
                  “situated data analysis” as an extension of Haraway’s concept of “situated
                  knowledge.” </note>
            </p>
            <p>D’Ignazio and Klein describe numerous practices related to examining the context of
               data. These practices begin with understanding the conditions of production
               associated with data, including information about those who constructed the data.
               “When approaching any new source of knowledge,” they write, “it’s essential to ask
               questions about the social, cultural, historical, institutional, and material
               conditions under which that knowledge was produced, as well as about the identities
               of the people who created it” (152). Like Gitelman, D’Ignazio and Klein argue against
               the existence of anything that might be called raw data (159). They advocate for
               considering the “functional limitations of the data” and “any associated ethical
               obligations” (153); “exploring and analyzing what is missing from a dataset” (160) ;
               attending to “power differentials” that have shaped and/or continue to be present in
               collected data (160); and interrogating a dataset’s validity — that is, the degree to
               which it can be said to represent the concept being analyzed (160). They emphasize
               the importance of context at the stages of data acquisition, data analysis, and
               “framing and communication of results” (164). Their advocacy is empowered rather than
               hindered by their adoption of a precise vocabulary that practitioners in a range of
               disciplines can recognize and quickly understand.<note> For a further indication of
                  such terminological compatibility, see Timnit Gebru et. al. “Datasheets for
                  Datasets.” <hi rend="italic">ArXiv:1803.09010 [Cs]</hi>, March 19, 2020. <ref
                     target="http://arxiv.org/abs/1803.09010">http://arxiv.org/abs/1803.09010</ref>.
                  The authors note, “Despite the importance of data to machine learning, there is no
                  standardized process for documenting machine learning datasets” (1). They propose
                  a standard to “encourage careful reflection on the process of creating,
                  distributing, and maintaining a dataset, including any underlying assumptions,
                  potential risks or harms, and implications of use” and to ensure that “dataset
                  consumers … have the information they need to make informed decisions about using
                  a dataset” (2). </note>
            </p>
            <p>Similarly, Katherine Bode has argued in <hi rend="italic">A World of Fiction</hi>
               (2019) for an intervention in computational literary studies based on the argument
               that “distant reading and macroanalysis construct and seek to extract meaning from
               models of literary systems that are essentially deficient,” which to say, “inadequate
               for representing the ways in which literary works existed and generated meaning in
               the past” (5). Bode does not advocate that we reject data-driven literary history, as
               others have argued, nor does she endorse the adoption of “new, more elaborate forms
               of computational analysis” as a way around the conflict (6).<note> Bode does not
                  eschew methodological rigor altogether. She writes, “Although it is a premise of
                  the book that data- rich literary history should not focus on the methods of
                  analysis used to the detriment of the object analyzed, in a field that attempts to
                  understand literature and culture by applying techniques devised for other
                  purposes a critical approach to methodology is essential” (9). Her critique of
                  methodological emphasis lies in a tendency of others to rely on “trialing the
                  newest or most innovative digital methods” instead of those best suited to the
                  subject matter and “to responding to the requirements of humanities inquiry” (9).
               </note> Instead, she anchors her intervention around the idea of “a scholarly edition
               of a literary system” — which engages explicitly with modeling practices — as “a
               mechanism through which to interrogate and refine conceptions of literary works and
               systems” (6). As with D’Ignazio and Klein, Bode calls for increased
               contextualization, for “a data-rich model of a literary system is inevitably an
               argument shaped by not only the scholar’s perception of cultural artifacts and
               phenomena but the complex history by which those artifacts and phenomena are
               transmitted to and by us in the present” (6). Bode’s use of the key phrase
               “data-rich” is important to her argument, in that she presents it as an alternative
               to labels like “distant reading,” “macroanalysis,” and “computational literary
               history” (2). It is structurally reminiscent of “data-driven” but the adjectival <hi
                  rend="italic">rich</hi> has a strong contrast to the past participle <hi
                  rend="italic">driven</hi>, both in terms of connotation and its symbolic rejection
               of that idea that data ostensibly occupy the driver’s seat. D’Ignazio &amp; Klein and
               Bode make very different interventions, but they share a common position that the
               term <hi rend="italic">data</hi> has purchase, especially when that term is qualified
               with productively descriptive modifiers. Further, they base their work, in part, on
               the premise that data-driven inquiry can be executed more effectively if instilled
               with feminist and/or humanistic values. </p>
            <p>If this premise is to be accepted, our conversations about how to improve upon
               computational inquiry can go further. Most immediately, there are implications for
               digital humanities pedagogy. As Ted Underwood has argued, “digital humanities
               classes, as currently defined, don’t really teach students how to use numbers. … So
               it’s almost naive to discuss ‘barriers to entry.’ There is no entrance to this field”
               (Underwood, 2018). Underwood argues that the cultural analytics subfield, in
               particular, operates primarily as a social network. In such a context competency and
               fluency come as a result of participants’ tacit knowledge and through
               person-to-person or small group interactions. In contrast, a well-defined curriculum
               with explicit pedagogies for teaching research design, data collection, data
               modeling, programming, and data analysis (including but not limited to quantitative
               analysis) would help create pathways to entry that are currently hidden for or
               unavailable to many people. Overt teaching of methods, Underwood argues, allows
               facility with methods to be more equally distributed. Discussing data literacy openly
               and critically strikes me as a key component of the curricular and pedagogical
               intervention Underwood has described. </p>
            <p>There are wide-ranging benefits to speaking and writing about data, openly and often,
               with implications from the practical to the profound. As part of this strategy, we
               should ask our students to read about the history of the word <hi rend="italic"
                  >data</hi>, but to include how Euclid used the word <hi rend="italic"
                  >dedoména</hi>, how Marinus described two different potential definitions for the
               word, and how natural philosophers of 17th-century England, in particular,
               appropriated <hi rend="italic">dedoména</hi>’s Latin alternative <hi rend="italic"
                  >data</hi>. We should ask them to discuss why such thinkers saw similarities
               between the Greek notion of data and how they were collecting and structuring
               information they observed and recorded. We should speak openly about crucial concepts
               related to data-driven inquiry, including practices aimed at contextualizing and
               situating data and datasets. We should press the idea that social constructions
               foreground and pervade what many think of as neutral or natural measures of reality,
               and we should openly question paradigms of thought that emphasize data as
               self-evident or unproblematically objective. In short, with a sense of pride and
               purpose, let us say and write data, all the while remaining humanists. </p>
         </div>


      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl>“almanac, n.”. <hi rend="italic">OED Online</hi>. (Oxford University Press, June
               2020), accessed October 16, 2020. <ref target="https://www.oed.com/view/Entry/5564"
                  >https://www.oed.com/view/Entry/5564</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl>“ephemeris, n.”. <hi rend="italic">OED Online</hi>. (Oxford University Press, June
               2020), accessed October 16, 2020. <ref target="https://www.oed.com/view/Entry/63209"
                  >https://www.oed.com/view/Entry/63209</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Austin, Roland G. “Zeno’s Game of Τάβλη (A. P. ix. 482),” <hi rend="italic">The
                  Journal of Hellenic Studies</hi> 54 (1934): 202–5. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.2307/626864"
               >https://doi.org/10.2307/626864</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Bode, Katherine. <hi rend="italic">A World of Fiction: Digital Collections and the
                  Future of Literary History</hi>. Ann Arbor: U of Michigan P, 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl>Campbell-Kelly, Martin, et al., <hi rend="italic">The History of Mathematical
                  Tables: From Sumer to Spreadsheets</hi>, Oxford, Miss.: OUP, 2003.</bibl>
            <bibl>Chambers, Ephraim. <hi rend="italic">Cyclopædia, or, An Universal Dictionary of
                  Arts and Sciences</hi> (1728). ARTFL Reference Collection. <ref
                  target="https://artfl-project.uchicago.edu/content/chambers-cyclopaedia"
                  >https://artfl-project.uchicago.edu/content/chambers-cyclopaedia</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>D’Ignazio, Catherine, and Lauren F. Klein, <hi rend="italic">Data Feminism</hi>.
               Cambridge, MIT Press, 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl>“data, n.”. <hi rend="italic">OED Online</hi>. (Oxford University Press, June
               2020), accessed July 01, 2020. <ref target="https://www.oed.com/view/Entry/296948"
                  >https://www.oed.com/view/Entry/296948</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl>Drucker, Johanna. “Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display” <hi rend="italic"
                  >Digital Humanities Quarterly </hi>5.1 (2011): n.p. <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org//dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>—-. <hi rend="italic">Graphesis: Visual Forms of Knowledge Production</hi>.
               Cambridge: Harvard UP, 2014.</bibl>
            <bibl>Elizabeth, Charlotte. <hi rend="italic">Judæa Capta: An Historical Sketch of the
                  Destruction of Jerusalem by the Romans</hi> London: W.H. Dalton, 1845. </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia Perthensis, Or, Universal Dictionary of the Arts,
                  Sciences, Literature, Etc.: Intended to Supersede the Use of Other Books of
                  Reference</hi>. Edinburgh: J. Brown, 1816: </bibl>
            <bibl>Evans, James, and J. Lennart Berggren, <hi rend="italic">Geminos’s Introduction to
                  the Phenomena: A Translation and Study of a Hellenistic Survey of Astronomy</hi>
               Princeton: Princeton UP, 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl>Furner, Jonathan. “‘Data’: the data” <hi rend="italic">Information Cultures in the
                  Digital Age.</hi> Eds. M. Kelly, J. Bielby, Wiesbaden: Springer, 2016. 287-306.
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-658-14681-8_17"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-658-14681-8_17</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gitelman, Lisa. Introduction, “<hi rend="italic">Raw Data” is an Oxymoron</hi>,
               ed. by Lisa Gitelman. Cambridge: MIT Press, 2013. 1-14. </bibl>
            <bibl>Haraway, Donna. “Situated Knowledges: The Science Question in Feminism and the
               Privilege of Partial Perspective,” <hi rend="italic">Feminist Studies</hi> 14, no. 3
               (1988): 575–99, <ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/3178066"
                  >https://doi.org/10.2307/3178066</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Hayakawa, Samuel Ichiyé. <hi rend="italic">Language in Thought and Action</hi>.
               New York: Houghton Mifflin Harcourt, 1990.</bibl>
            <bibl>Heath, Sir Thomas. <hi rend="italic">A History of Greek Mathematics Volume 1: From
                  Thales to Euclid</hi>. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1921. </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <hi rend="italic">Justinian Institutes</hi>, Lib. 1, Tit. 3., “De Jure Personarum.”
               Qtd. in Archibald Alexander Cameron, <hi rend="italic">Protestantism and Its Relation
                  to the Moral, Intellectual and Spiritual Developments of Modern Times</hi>.
               Ottawa: Joseph Loveday, 1972.</bibl>
            <bibl>Kitchin, Rob. “1. What Are Data?” section on “Conceptualizing Data”, <hi
                  rend="italic">The Data Revolution: Big Data, Open Data, Data Infrastructures and
                  Their Consequences</hi>. Sage Publications e-book edition, 2014.</bibl>
            <bibl>Longino, Helen E. <hi rend="italic">Science as Social Knowledge: Values and
                  Objectivity in Scientific Inquiry</hi>. Princeton: Princeton UP, 1990.</bibl>
            <bibl>Marinus, “Euclides Data, a Commentary or Preface Written by the Phylosopher
               Marinus on Euclides Data,” in <hi rend="italic">Euclid’s Elements of Geometry</hi>.
               London: John Leeke &amp; George Serle, 1661.</bibl>
            <bibl>“phenomenon, n.”. <hi rend="italic">OED Online</hi>. (Oxford University Press,
               June 2020), accessed October 15, 2020. <ref
                  target="https://www.oed.com/view/Entry/142352"
                  >https://www.oed.com/view/Entry/142352</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl>Rosenberg, Daniel. “Data Before the Fact,” <hi rend="italic">“Raw Data” is an
                  Oxymoron,</hi> ed. by Lisa Gitelman (Cambridge: MIT Press, 2013): 15-40.</bibl>
            <bibl>Sandars, Thomas Collett. <hi rend="italic">The Institutes of Justinian</hi>. New
               York: Longmans, 1917.</bibl>
            <bibl>Seco, Lucas Francisco Mateo, and Giulio Maspero. 2010. <hi rend="italic">The Brill
                  Dictionary of Gregory of Nyssa</hi>. BRILL.</bibl>
            <bibl>Shipley, Joseph Twadell. <hi rend="italic">The Origins of English Words: A
                  Discursive Dictionary of Indo-European Roots</hi>. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins UP,
               2001.</bibl>
            <bibl>Sullivan, Robert. <hi rend="italic">A Dictionary of Derivations; Or, An
                  Introduction to Etymology: On a New Plan.</hi> Dublin: Marcus and John Sullivan,
               1860.</bibl>
            <bibl>“table, n.”. <hi rend="italic">OED Online</hi>. (Oxford University Press, June
               2020), accessed October 25, 2020. <ref target="https://www.oed.com/view/Entry/196785"
                  >https://www.oed.com/view/Entry/196785</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl>Taisbak, Christian Marinus. <hi rend="italic">Dedomena: Euclid’s Data or The
                  Importance of Being Given, </hi>The Greek Text translated and explained by
               Christian Maris Taisbak. Copenhagen: Museum Tusculanum Press, University of
               Copenhagen, 2003.</bibl>
            <bibl>Vico, Giambattista. <hi rend="italic">Universal Right</hi>. Trans. and ed. by
               Georgio Pinton &amp; Margaret Diehl. Amsterdam: Ridopi, 2000. </bibl>
            <bibl>Underwood, Ted. “A Broader Purpose,” Varieties of Digital Humanities Panel, MLA,
               Jan 5, 2018. <ref target="https://tedunderwood.com/2018/01/04/a-broader-purpose/"
                  >https://tedunderwood.com/2018/01/04/a-broader-purpose/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Vaan, Michiel de. <hi rend="italic">Etymological Dictionary of Latin and the Other
                  Italic Languages</hi>. 2008. Leiden, Boston: Brill, 2018.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
