<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Sight and Sound:
               Counter-mapping the U.S.-Mexico Border Crisis</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Lacey <dhq:family>Schauwecker</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Southern California </dhq:affiliation>
               <email>lschauwe@usc.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Lacey Schauwecker, PhD, is a scholar and educator who works as a Learning and Development Specialist for the USC Shoah Foundation.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000626</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->3</idno>
         	<date when="2022-06-25">25 June 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2022-08-05"	who="BRG">added teaser, resolved encoding errors</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>Jason De León’s Undocumented Migration Project and Valeria Luiselli’s <title
                  rend="italic">Lost Children Archive</title> are two archival studies of the
               U.S.-Mexico border crisis that challenge hegemonic practices of documentation,
               including those historically privileged by the U.S. Department of Homeland Security,
               human rights activism, and the field of digital humanities alike. Though De León and
               Luiselli have participated in human rights work while identifying migrant corpses and
               collecting detainees’ testimonies, both use counter-mapping to interrogate the
               dominant humanitarian move of restoring visibility and voice, or sight and sound, to
               human victims. After investigating the ways in which De León and Luiselli privilege
               visual and sonic counter-mapping, respectively, I model a more multi-sensory
               counter-mapping practice. Though this practice remains far from perfect, I argue that
               such digital counter-mapping crosses sight and sound in ways that defy historical
               divisions among humans and nonhumans. Accordingly, it decenters humans as the sole
               victims of the U.S.-Mexico border crisis.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>Investigating methods for counter-mapping and proposing a more multi-sensory practice.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
       <div>
         <head>I. Introduction</head>
         <p>The field of digital humanities defines itself by a capacity for interrogating and
            innovating the traditional humanities. More than a mere transference from material to
            analog to digital, this field claims to function as a <quote rend="inline">subversive force</quote> with its own
            creations and challenges <ptr target="#hayles2012"/>. Distinguishing digital humanities as not better
            or worse, but different, from its predecessor, N. Katherine Hayles states that such
            <quote rend="inline">differences can leverage traditional assumptions so they become visible and hence
               available for rethinking</quote> <ptr target="#hayles2012"/>. Yet, this very assertion demonstrates one of
            the field’s central challenges, for Hayles here replicates an age-old assumption that
            something must first <q>become visible</q> for it then to be <q>available for rethinking.</q>
            Multiple digital humanities scholars have acknowledged the field’s difficulty in defying
            such visual hegemony or, stated otherwise, interrogating and innovating vision as itself
            historically dominant. </p>
         <p>Observing that <quote rend="inline">the digital humanities is today overwhelmingly visual,</quote> Sari Altschuler
            and David Weimer claim this imbalance to <quote rend="inline">have inadvertently exacerbated a tendency to
               privilege sight as the sense through which knowledge is accessible</quote> <ptr target="#altschuler2020"/>.
            Such privileging largely results from the Scientific Revolution and subsequent Age of
            Enlightenment. With the development of seeing and printing technologies in the 15th and
            16th centuries, visual mapping and charting assumed central roles in understanding the
            world on small and large scales. In <title rend="italic">Hypercities: Thick Mapping in the
               Digital Humanities</title>, Todd Samuel Presner, David Shepard, Yoh Kawano note such
            mapping to have been critically involved in the establishment and expansion of European
            nation-states, including colonial conquest <ptr target="#presner2014"/>. Yet while mapping never has
            been, and never will be, a neutral representation of knowledge, many scholars celebrate
            the shift to digital mapping as a potentially more multi-sensory and malleable practice. </p>
         <p>According to Clancy Wilmott, digital mapping has upended <quote rend="inline">the assumption that ‘the map’
            is a static representational object</quote> <ptr target="#cooper2016"/>. More than artifactual maps made with
            permanent ink and parchment, <q>the map</q> now commonly functions less as an object and more
            as a dynamic, interactive process. Such functionality is inevitably transformational, if
            not exactly subversive, prompting the skeptical attention of humanities and digital
            humanities scholars alike. In <title rend="italic">Literary Mapping in the Digital
            Age</title>, David Cooper, Christopher Donaldson, and Patricia Murrieta-Flores emphasize
            the need to evaluate <quote rend="inline">how the process of digital mapping and map-making alters the way
               we perceive and engage with the geographies that surround us</quote> <ptr target="#cooper2016"/>. Such
            evaluation interrogates what digital mapping reveals, conceals, and remains unable to
            convey, perhaps facilitating <quote rend="inline">new spatial practices and spatial imaginings.</quote> </p>
         <p>In this article, I engage debates on critical cartography with particular attention to
            how digital mapping influences humans’ understandings of landscape, as well as
            themselves. Specifically, I investigate the subversive potential of digital mapping the
            Sonoran Desert in the context of an ongoing U.S.-Mexico border crisis, where hegemonic
            practices of seeing, knowing, and surveilling continue to shore up colonization and its
            violent legacy. As U.S. border militarization implicates, and intentionally disappears,
            multitudes of humans and nonhumans each year, questions of mapping preoccupy government
            agencies, international corporations, on-the-ground activists, and interdisciplinary
            scholars alike. In what follows, I join multiple humanities and digital humanities
            scholars in thinking about the possibility of mapping the unmappable, including that
            which remains invisible by design. Additionally, I ask, <q>How might such counter-mapping
            facilitate a rethinking of the U.S.-Mexico border crisis, beyond anthropocentrism?</q> </p>
         <p>To address these questions, I first provide historical and theoretical background on the
            necessity, as well as difficulty, of mapping and counter-mapping this region. Next, I
            analyze two well-known examples of counter-mapping, namely Jason De León’s Undocumented
            Migration Project and Valeria Luiselli’s <title rend="italic">Lost Children Archive</title>.
            After investigating the ways in which De León and Luiselli privilege visual and sonic
            counter-mapping, respectively, I model a more multi-sensory counter-mapping practice.
            Though this practice remains far from perfect, I argue that such digital counter-mapping
            crosses sight and sound in ways that challenge historical divisions among humans and
            nonhumans. Accordingly, it decenters humans as the sole, and most important, victims of
            the U.S.-Mexico border crisis.</p></div>
         <div>
         <head>II. Mapping and Counter-mapping </head>
         <p>I focus on the Arizona-Sonora region of the U.S.-Mexico border: home to Apache, Hopi,
            Maricopa, Mayo, Pima, Navajo, Yaqui, Hohokam, and Tohono O’odham peoples, as well as
            exceptionally biodiverse mountain regions known as sky islands.<note> This list is not
               exhaustive but includes a sampling of indigenous populations known to have existed in
               Sonora, Mexico <ptr target="#zaratevaldez2016"/> and Southern Arizona <ptr target="#arizonastatemuseum2016"/>.</note> Throughout the arrival of Spanish missionaries in the early 18th
            century, the Mexican-American War (1846-47), the Gadsden Purchase (1854), and the Apache
            Wars (1849-1924), indigenous and colonial settler populations violently negotiated and
            renegotiated control of these borderlands. After the annexation of U.S. territories
            including Texas, New Mexico, Arizona, and Southern California from Mexico in the
            mid-1800s, migration northward was incentivized or illegalized depending on the U.S.’
            political and economic need.<note> For example, U.S. policy facilitated migration during
               natural resource booms and labor shortages but impeded it during The Great Depression
               and Cold War proxies throughout Latin America starting in the 1960s.</note> Still,
            enforcement remained relatively lax until the <q>Border Patrol Strategic Plan of 1994 and
            Beyond,</q> which heightened the militarization of the border through increasingly brutal
            uses of land and surveillance technology. Since its implementation, such policy has
            resulted in 7,000 to 8,000 migrants dying while crossing Southern Arizona <ptr target="#colibri2020"/><note> Two reports that use this phrasing are The Binational Migration
               Institute’s <title rend="quotes">A Continued Humanitarian Crisis at the Border: Undocumented Border
               Crosser Deaths Recorded by the Pima County Office of the Medical Examiner, 1990-2012</title>
               <ptr target="#continued2013"/> and the American Civil Liberties Union and Mexico’s National
               Commission of Human Rights’ <title rend="quotes">Humanitarian Crisis: Migrant Deaths at the U.S.-Mexico
                  Border</title> <ptr target="#jimenez2009"/>. </note>. By design, many of these deaths remain
            unidentifiable, if not altogether invisible. In turn, mapping practices in this area now
            indicate not just who wins the war and owns the land, but what life remains in this
            undeclared killing zone.</p>
         <p>Currently, the only map on the U.S. Department of Homeland Security’s website is that of
            its <q>Border Wall System,</q> depicted in Figure 1. </p>
         
            <figure>
               <head>U.S. Department of Homeland Security’s digital map of its “Border Wall
                  System”</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpeg"/>
               <figDesc>Image of a map of western USA with a line along the border</figDesc>
            </figure>
           
         <p>Looking at this digital ArcGIS map with a thick, but noticeably partial, line along the
            U.S.-Mexico border, viewers can click on highlighted parts of the line for more
            information about ongoing wall construction and associated photos <ptr target="#customs2020"/>.
            However, those interested in other forms of <q>border security</q> need to look elsewhere for
            data on drone technology, scope stations, and ArcGIS live monitoring software. Knowledge
            of this largely invisible surveillance system exposes border wall-building as mere
            spectacle, for DHS policy is not designed to prevent migration per se, but rather to
            ensure its profitability. Instead of stopping migrants from crossing at all, for
            example, Prevention Through Deterrence intentionally pushes migrants out into the remote
            and dangerous desert, where they are more likely to die or, alternatively, to be
            apprehended, detained, and eventually deported. On its website, however, DHS
            misrepresents itself as benign, wall-building protector, and the Sonoran Desert as
            brutal murderer.</p>
         <p>Given the high stakes of mapping in this and other areas of conflict, scholars and
            activists have employed varied practices of counter-mapping. Coined by sociologist Nancy
            Peluso, the term <q>counter-mapping</q> refers to processes in which communities appropriate
            and repurpose institutional techniques of map-making in order to create alternatives to
            hegemonic representations <ptr target="#peluso1995"/>. Anthropologist Jason De León, who has studied
            migration and violence in Southern Arizona since 2009, draws on fellow migration scholar
            Martina Tazzioli’s elaboration of counter-mapping as having two specific purposes of 1)
            making visible the effects of authority and 2) challenging the very possibility of
            mapping these effects <ptr target="#tazzioli2015"/>. This definition is notable for exhibiting a
            tension similar to that of digital humanities insofar as it simultaneously relies on and
            resists <q>making visible</q> as a principal source of knowledge.</p>
         <p>Like Hayles, Tazzioli here implies that she intends to rethink the very concepts to
            which she appeals, including visibility and mapping. Noting the humanities and digital
            humanities’ dominant reliance on visual and textual methods, multiple scholars have
            recently turned to sound and listening as part of a heretofore neglected epistemology.
            For example, Mary Caton Lingold, Darren Mueller, and Whitney Trettien, editors of <title
               rend="italic">Digital Sound Studies</title>, wonder what forms of knowledge and embodied
            experience are going unheard in the digital turn <ptr target="#lingold2018"/>. Turning to sound as an
            under-utilized mode of study within digital humanities, this collection challenges not
            just the hierarchization of senses, but also their very separation. Since this
            separation emerged over time, as part of Enlightenment thinking, sound studies scholars
            such as Jonathan Sterne and Michael J. Kramer claim we can use the <q>flexible modularity</q>
            of digital data to both understand and reverse this history <ptr target="#lingold2018"/>.</p>
         <p>As I will elaborate in my study of counter-mapping the U.S.-Mexico border crisis,
            undoing this separation of senses can also challenge the historical division of
            nation-states and species. For while much discussion of counter-mapping emphasizes the
            visualization of space, and even De León claims his work to <quote rend="inline">foster alternative forms of
            understanding, visualizing, and producing <emph>space</emph>,</quote> I read his work
            as especially important for the ways in which it sets up a rethinking of the Sonoran
            Desert as a space of invisible and indiscriminate violence. In <title rend="italic">Lost
               Children Archive</title>, a novel that also studies migration and disappearance in
            Southern Arizona, Valeria Luiselli furthers such rethinking by privileging sound as a
            mode of knowledge with counter-mapping capabilities. Reading these scholars’ work
            together exposes the stakes of counter-mapping to be not simply a rethinking of sight
            and sound as they relate to space, but also as they relate to the humans <emph>and</emph> nonhumans traversing such space. In other words, the stakes
            are ways of witnessing the U.S.-Mexico border crisis that decenter visuality and
            anthropocentrism simultaneously. </p></div>
         <div>
         <head>III. Visual Counter-mapping</head>
         <p>The similarities between Jason De León’s <title rend="italic">The Land of Open Graves</title>
            (2015), his first book about the Undocumented Migration Project, and Valeria Luiselli’s
               <title rend="italic">Lost Children Archive </title>(2019) become more obvious upon
            considering the latter’s translated title, <title rend="italic">El Desierto Sonoro</title>
               (2020).<note> While discussing this title in an interview, Luiselli translates
               <q>sonoro</q> as sonorous and highlights the double meaning of <q>sonorous desert</q> as
               referencing both a desert full of sound and a desert devoid of sound. This title also
               appears to riff on El Desierto de Sonora, the Spanish translation of the Sonoran
               Desert, but <title rend="italic">Lost Children Archive</title> largely takes place in the
               Chiricahua Mountains, which lie east of the Sonoran Desert and predominantly consist
               of sky islands and grasslands <ptr target="#eloriente2020"/>.</note> Both books are about the
            Arizona desert, and principally the Sonoran Desert, which is a biodiverse region
            covering large parts of the Southwestern United States and Northwestern Mexico. More
            specifically, these books are about the many thousands of migrants that have attempted
            to cross this dangerous landscape, especially since the Department of Homeland
            Security’s implementation of its <q>Prevention Through Deterrence</q> policy, part of the
            aforementioned <title rend="quotes">Border Patrol Strategic Plan of 1994 and Beyond.</title> Entailing heightened
            militarization and surveillance in urban sections of the border such as San Diego,
            California and Nogales, Arizona, this policy intentionally pushes traveling migrants
            into rural areas that increase their chances of turning themselves in, getting lost, or
            dying. Since the early 2000s, the Pima County Office of the Medical Examiner has
            reported doing upwards of 150 autopsies on undocumented border corpses annually
            <ptr target="#continued2013"/>. Furthermore, Dr. Gregory Hess, Pima County’s current Chief Medical
            Examiner, estimates that these self-disclosed numbers likely represent just 1/3 of
            actual migrant deaths in this area <ptr target="#hess2019"/>.</p>
         <p>As De León’s title indicates, this terrain is truly a land of open graves. Yet, the
            desert’s intense heat, strong wind, and flash floods quickly decompose and disperse
            migrant bodies, making finding and identifying them still difficult. De León, both an
            archaeologist and anthropologist by training, started the <ref
               target="https://www.undocumentedmigrationproject.org/">Undocumented Migration
               Project</ref> in 2009 in order to better understand the causes, as well as physical
            experiences, of undocumented border crossing <ptr target="#deleon2015"/>. Using ethnographic,
            archaeological, forensic, and visual anthropological methods to collect evidence of such
            crossing, De León distinguishes his interdisciplinary work as taking <q>sideways glances</q>
            that <quote rend="inline">foster new ways of thinking about border crossings and the routinized pain and
            suffering that accompany them</quote> (<ref target="#deleon2015">17</ref>). These sideways glances, a concept originally
            proposed by Slavoj Žižek in <title rend="italic">Violence: Six Sideways Reflections</title>, entail zooming out
            beyond a mere focus on the human subjects of violence in order to think more broadly and
            critically about the structural causes of such violence <ptr target="#deleon2015"/>. For De León,
            this means witnessing what remains otherwise overlooked, including the socioeconomic
            factors that cause migrants to leave their homelands, as well as those that have made
            their journey increasingly dangerous.</p>
         <p>In <title rend="italic">The Land of Open Graves</title>, such witnessing involves both
            narrating and counter-mapping in ways that put pressure on hegemonic forms of
            documentation, principally those of the U.S. Department of Homeland Security, but
            sometimes also those of fellow human rights activists. Acknowledging the graphic nature
            of his work, for example, De León recounts instances in which critics have claimed his
            photos of decayed migrant corpses to rob their subjects of human dignity. His refusal to
            instead make migrant bodies visible as whole and uninjured is striking for its refusal
            to rehumanize such victims, as many human rights archives and organizations profess to
               do.<note> The Colibrí Center, for example, describes its work as building <quote rend="inline">on a
               legacy of humanitarian work in Southern Arizona done by organizations such as
               Coalición de Derechos Humanos, No More Deaths, and Tucson Samaritans, all concerned
               with upholding human rights and human dignity throughout the borderlands</quote> <ptr target="#colibri2020"/>.</note> In his words, <quote rend="inline">The deaths that migrants experience in the Sonoran
            Desert are <emph>anything</emph> but dignified. <emph>That</emph> is
                  the point</quote> <ptr target="#deleon2015" loc="emphasis added"/>. For De León, such dehumanization, both in
            life and in death, is the precise point of policies including Prevention Through
            Deterrence. Identifying such decomposition as a form of structural, postmortem violence,
            he elaborates that the seeming <q>natural</q> processes of dying and decaying in the desert
            are actually <quote rend="inline">political facts representative of the value placed on the lives and deaths
               of undocumented people</quote> <ptr target="#deleon2015"/>. </p>
         <p>These claims are noteworthy for their simultaneous reliance upon and rejection of
            Enlightenment-based practices of seeing, knowing, and valorizing the human. For while De
            León does privilege visual and material evidence, he also stubbornly casts his glance
            askew of the very subjectivity, or indeed humanity, associated with such epistemology.
            This move corresponds with Elizabeth Anker’s critique of how Enlightenment-based notions
            of the human body and mind still inform dominant notions of humanitarianism and human
            rights activism. As she observes, these discourses predicate human dignity on corporeal
            integrity; for an individual to be a human worthy of rights, they must first have a body
            that is <quote rend="inline">whole, autonomous, and self-enclosed</quote> <ptr target="#anker2012"/>. This is because, according
            to Enlightenment-based liberalism, only this type of body meets related ideals, such as
            reason, conscience, and freedom. Yet Anker points out that this idealized human body and
            subject is paradoxically <q>decorporealized,</q> for it negates core dimensions of embodied
            experience, including <q>vulnerability</q> and <q>decay</q> <ptr target="#anker2012"/>. </p>
         <p>When De León foregrounds migrants’ partially decayed corpses as <quote rend="inline"><title rend="italic"
               >anything</title> but dignified,</quote> he likewise acknowledges and critiques hegemonic
            standards of human rights subjectivity. Making visible a commonly overlooked reality,
            his photos are graphic reminders of the human body’s limits: the very limits that leave
            it susceptible to both violence <emph>and</emph> ignorance. If bodies are not
            whole, they also cannot see whole pictures, or know whole stories. Yet, denying these
            limits in the name of human dignity is one way humans separate themselves as physically
            and mentally superior to other animals <ptr target="#anker2012"/>. In this sense, De León’s images
            challenge visuality and anthropocentrism simultaneously, serving his noted interest in
            <quote rend="inline">troubling human-nonhuman binaries</quote> <ptr target="#deleon2015"/>. Furthermore, they help show how
            <q>structural agency</q> both commits and conceals violence in the U.S.-Mexico borderlands. </p>
         <p>According to De León’s counter-mapping research with the Undocumented Migration Project,
            such structural agency involves the dehumanization of humans, as well as the
            humanization, or <q>denaturalization,</q> of nonhumans such as the Arizona desert. Prevention
            Through Deterrence, which is just one policy, for example, involves human,
            technological, geographical, animal, mineral, and meteorological actants. Drawing on
            Michel Callon and John Law’s theory of <q>hybrid collectif,</q> which identifies agency as a
            property that emerges from the interaction of various heterogeneous actants, De León
            refers to this combination of human and nonhuman agents involved in the U.S.-Mexico
            border crisis as the <q>Sonoran Desert hybrid collectif.</q> To fully account for this
            collectif, De León stresses the need to abandon dualist thinking, including that which
            relies on simplistic human-nonhuman binaries. On one hand, he wants to expose how the
            U.S. Department of Homeland Security <quote rend="inline">can draw on the agency of animals and other
            nonhumans to do its dirty work while simultaneously absolving itself of any blame
            connected to migrant injuries or loss of life</quote> <ptr target="#deleon2015"/>. Yet, on the other hand,
            he is careful of falling back into an anthropocentrism that myopically frames humans as
            the only perpetrators, as well as victims, involved in this complex crime scene.</p>
         <p>In his counter-mapping work, De León often draws on data from the Arizona OpenGIS
            Initiative for Deceased Migrants map, which is represented here in Figure 2 and is the
            result of an ongoing partnership between the Pima County Office of the Medical Examiner
            and Humane Borders, Inc. </p>
            
            <figure>
               <head>Arizona OpenGIS Initiative for Deceased Migrants map</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpeg"/>
               <figDesc>Image of a map of western USA in OpenGIS</figDesc>
            </figure>
        
            
            
         <p>A counter-map in its own right, this map challenges hegemonic representations of the
            U.S.-Mexico border crisis by repurposing geographic information system (GIS) software
            similar to that which DHS uses in conjunction with remote sensors, lookout towers, and
            agent-carried GPS units <ptr target="#deleon2016"/>.<note> In contrast to DHS’ use of GIS technology,
               the Arizona OpenGIS Initiative for Deceased Migrants map involves open source
               software and readily available data. </note> For DHS, these technologies provide
            immediate information on suspected migrant activity in remote areas that appear
            otherwise unsurveilled, or simply <q>natural</q> <ptr target="#deleon2016"/>. In contrast, the Deceased
            Migrants map implements GIS software with the mission of raising awareness about the
            entirely unnatural quantity of migrant deaths in the Arizona desert and, when possible,
            also identifying the deceased so that remains may be returned to families. Accordingly,
            the map charts the locations of found corpses, as well as related information such as
            postmortem interval, body condition, cause of death and — if identifiable — name, sex,
            and age <ptr target="#arizonaopengis"/>. A dynamic digital map with numerous search functions, it also
            allows searches by migrant name, land corridor, and year of death.</p>
         <p>As a viewer who repurposes these GIS tools and information once more, De León
            foregrounds not only human victims’ suffering, but also the hybrid collectif implicated
            in it. In <title rend="quotes">Scales of Suffering in the US-Mexico Borderlands,</title> an article published after
               <title rend="italic">The Land of Open Graves</title> and with anthropologist co-authors
            Cameron Gokee and Haeden Stewart, De León plots migrant deaths and belongings against
            multiple representations of the Sonoran Desert, specifically the Nogales-Sasabe
            corridor. The Undocumented Migration Project’s expansive archive of discarded objects
            includes intimate items such as bibles, love letters, and photos, as well as practical
            items such as backpacks, water bottles, and shoes. Here, De León specifically plots
            aid-related artifacts against geography models, showing how the use of bandages,
            anti-infectives, and analgesics corresponds to changing contours of the terrain. Figure
            3 depicts a map of aid-related artifacts and associated land covers documented in the
            Nogales-Sasabe corridor by the Undocumented Migration Project from 2009-2013 <ptr target="#gokee2020"/>.</p>
            
            <figure>
               <head>Aid-related artifacts and associated land covers documented in the
                  Nogales-Sasabe corridor by the Undocumented Migration Project from 2009-2013 <ptr target="#gokee2020"/></head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpeg"/>
               <figDesc>Image of a map of Arizona with bar charts over five geographical locations</figDesc>
            </figure>
            
         
            
            
         <p>Especially in cases where migrant corpses have decomposed to the point of complete
            destruction, discarded belongings function as the only clues to one’s demise out in the
            remote desert. Therefore, De León and his co-authors view these <q>scales of analysis</q> as
            able <quote rend="inline">to let the suffering of migrants ‘speak’ in different ways</quote>: ways that expose
            humans’ victimization and the desert’s weaponization simultaneously <ptr target="#gokee2020"/>.</p>
         <p>When counter-mapping, De León is forthright about the <quote rend="inline">seemingly paradoxical attempt to
            use spatial data and spatial analysis to critique and undermine spatial data and spatial
            analysis</quote> <ptr target="#deleon2016"/>. While DHS employs private mapping and analytics software, such
            as Esri’s ArcGIS, De León draws from the Arizona OpenGIS Initiative for Deceased
            Migrants map, which uses open source software to make data readily available. Yet, this
            information on migrants’ deaths could simultaneously serve as valuable data on the
            efficacy of border enforcement, and how to strengthen it. Given this possibility, De
            León elsewhere notes a resistance to publishing such data and touches on a central
            debate in digital humanities about the possibility of dismantling the master’s house
            with the master’s tools <ptr target="#deleon2016"/>. Analyzing the risks of using GIS software that
            produces data, as well as money, for ethically dubious companies, Safiya Noble advises
            the public to stay vigilant of how such software further entrenches them in the very
            systems they may be critiquing <ptr target="#noble2011"/>. Since Noble also notes how these same GIS
            technologies often help improve communities, she urges critical yet creative
            applications. Yet, I contend that part of De León’s conundrum is his maps’ reliance on
            not just the same GIS tools, but also the same visual media and human categories, that
            are readily recognizable to DHS.</p>
         <p>For this reason, I am most interested in where and how De León also repurposes the
            master’s tools beyond the point of easy recognition. Though he views his counter-maps as
            able to let the suffering of migrants <q>speak,</q> he claims <quote rend="inline">they also contain their own
               silences and elisions</quote> <ptr target="#gokee2020"/>. Here, De León notably switches from framing his
            work as predominantly visual to also vocal in order to point out how it is only
            partially revelatory. Yet, he elaborates on his maps’ incapacity to represent everything
            in every way as <quote rend="inline">critical to countering the scalar projects, including maps, that
            obscure decades of migrant suffering at the hands of PTD [Prevention Through Deterrence]
            policies along the US- Mexico border</quote> <ptr target="#gokee2020"/>. In this sense, such silences are
            part of his maps’ functionality, not flaws. In fact, they also <q>speak,</q> as they further
            expose the ways in which migrants have been intentionally disappeared, both in life and
            death.</p>
         <p>At the same time, such silences remain absolute insofar as they represent absence: the
            absence of a body, testimony, identifiable human subject. Throughout the humanities and
            digital humanities, multiple scholars continue to grapple with how to account for such
            absence, which is endemic to archives about systemic violence and erasure. Thinking
            specifically about the archive of American slavery, Lauren Klein notes how the silences
            of slaves expose a <q>true</q> archive that <q>encompasses impossibility,</q> including the
            impossibility of knowing <ptr target="#klein2013"/>. Against Enlightenment-based epistemological
            biases that elevate <quote rend="inline">what is observable to the status of fact,</quote> Klein values the archive
            as a tool for exposing the limits of our knowledge, limits that even digital methods
            such as data visualization fail to surpass <ptr target="#klein2013"/>. In failing, however, they force
            us to think about other ways of seeing and knowing, such as speaking and listening.
            While De León’s work briefly mentions these possibilities, I now turn to Valeria
            Luiselli’s <title rend="italic">Lost Children Archive</title> as a counter-mapping model that
            instead privileges the auditory. Such an approach, I argue, enables her to further
            challenge epistemological biases and human/nonhuman binaries. </p></div>
         <div>
         <head>IV. Sonic Counter-mapping </head>
         <p>Contrary to De León’s appeal to visual and material evidence in the form of migrant
            bodies and their belongings, Luiselli’s <title rend="italic">Lost Children Archive</title>
            centralizes a lack of such evidence. Or, rather, the uncertainty of all evidence. The
            mother-protagonist, a radio journalist by profession, is never quite sure of what she
            sees or hears, making her story largely about the impossibility of narration, as well as
            traditional mapping. At first, she helps record child migrants’ oral testimonies in the
            New York immigration court, where she volunteers as a translator <ptr target="#luiselli2019a"/>. But
            when her husband insists on going westward to record auditory echoes of the Apache, who
            were disappeared in the Sonoran Desert long before the current U.S.-Mexico border
            crisis, she begins adjusting her own work to be able to accompany him. As she proceeds
            to research, <q>slowly build an archive,</q> and extend her focus on the child refugee crisis
            to <q>the southern borderlands,</q> the book becomes about her process of trying to connect
            multiple ideas, images, voices, and lack thereof into a new project. </p>
         <p>Explaining the archival nature of this novel, Luiselli distinguishes its <quote rend="inline">textual,
            musical, visual, and audio-visual</quote> references as central <quote rend="inline">voices in the conversation
               that the book sustains with the past</quote> <ptr target="#luiselli2019a"/>. In addition to history, <title
               rend="italic">Lost Children Archive</title> engages the fields of law, anthropology,
            cartography, and acoustics, among others. As a result, one can read Luiselli’s book as a
            specific type of interdisciplinary archive: a sound map. Encouraging interdisciplinarity
            and experimentation within archival studies, Marlene Marnoff claims that <q>thinking
            through making</q> is key to finding new ways of <q>interrogating archival silence</q>
            <ptr target="#foscarini2016"/>. In <title rend="italic">Lost Children Archive, </title>the
            mother-protagonist specifically practices a thinking through listening and mapping, as
            she continually tries to chart the sounds and spaces that both envelop and elude her.
            Lacking a visual and digital interface, such counter-mapping requires readers to
            likewise navigate the Sonoran Desert through her ears, a methodology that often
            conflates present and absent, as well as human and nonhuman, subjects. </p>
         <p>While <title rend="italic">Lost Children Archive</title> does publish images of multiple
            visual, and in this sense hegemonic, maps, it also consistently calls such maps into
            question. For example, the mother-protagonist’s archive includes a version of the very
            Arizona OpenGIS Initiative for Deceased Migrants map that De León draws upon. Depicted
            in Figure 4, this particular version charts migrant deaths against the Sonoran Desert,
            as well as the distance they likely had walked each day after crossing the border, in
            order to warn potential border crossers of the perilous journey. </p>
            
            <figure>
               <head>Luiselli’s reprinted and annotated version of Arizona OpenGIS Initiative for
                  Deceased Migrants map <ptr target="#luiselli2019a"/></head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpeg"/>
               <figDesc>Image of a map of Arizona With three semicricles at the bottom</figDesc>
            </figure>
     
            
         <p>As aforementioned, this map functions as a counter-map insofar as it charts deaths that
            have been both caused, and erased, by policies such as Prevention Through Deterrence.
            Yet, Luiselli cues a reading of this map as also inevitably exclusionary and, in this
            sense, complicit with invisibility. Noting how maps can <quote rend="inline">make visible what is usually
            unseen,</quote> the mother-protagonist nevertheless concludes that <quote rend="inline">To map is to include as
               much as to exclude</quote> <ptr target="#luiselli2019a"/>. More than associate excluded remains with
            invisibility, however, she connects them specifically to sound. A section of the book
            titled <title rend="quotes">Undocumented,</title> for example, begins with the epigraph, <quote rend="inline">An exile feels that the
               state of exile is a constant, special sensitivity to sound</quote> <ptr target="#luiselli2019a"/>. In the
            context of the U.S.-Mexico border crisis, <q>undocumented</q> thus takes on multiple
            meanings, including unmapped, unseen, and yet still potentially audible.</p>
         <p>Auditory studies of the U.S.-Mexico border are far less abundant than visual ones, yet
            multiple artists, activists, and scholars have likewise observed this area’s sonic
            dimensions to be uniquely boundless. In an analysis of how composer Guillermo Galindo
            turns objects found along the U.S.-Mexico border, including the border wall itself, into
            musical instruments, culture and music scholar Josh Kun observes sound to be more
            permeable than sight. Noting how we can readily hear the border’s other side, even
            without full vision, Kun states, <quote rend="inline">What walls and fences are meant to divide, sounds can
            move through and resonate across. What looks monumental to the eye sounds unmonumental
            to the ear. There are no borders for vibrations</quote> <ptr target="#misrach2016"/>. Here, Kun touches on
            the material <emph>and</emph> immaterial nature of sound, for such vibrations
            only become audible, even amplified, through the very objects they contact. This makes
            containing sound very difficult, as even ostensible silence often involves resonant
            vibrations. In auditory encounter, something usually escapes, perceived or unperceived.
            Given this unmonumental medium and sense’s historic subordination to sight as form of
            knowledge, however, such sound often fails to adequately capture human ears, let alone
            imaginations.</p>
         <p>For this reason, multiple humanities and digital humanities scholars frame listening as
            an acquired, not default, sense. As Jonathan Sterne explains, listening is a technique
            that <quote rend="inline">connotes practice, virtuosity, and the possibility of failure and accident […] It
               is a learned skill</quote> <ptr target="#sterne2003"/>. For the mother-protagonist in <title rend="italic">Lost
               Children Archive</title>, listening evolves from simply hearing sound, namely that of
            migrants’ oral testimonies, to sonically counter-mapping a landscape of unbounded
            phenomena. During a moment of revelation, she realizes that both her and her husband’s
            research projects entail <q>chasing ghosts and echoes</q> <ptr target="#luiselli2019a"/>. Her husband’s
            ghosts and echoes are those of the last Apache leaders, including Chief Cochise,
            Geronimo, and the Chiricahuas. As the final indigenous Americans to surrender to
            settler-colonists and their Indian Removal Act, which forced remaining tribes onto
            federal reservations, these people were exiled from their own homeland just like many
            migrant refugees and deportees. The mother-protagonist draws this parallel most closely
            as she watches a plane of child refugees head back to their ostensible homeland, yet
            only by departing from the land of their probable ancestors, as well as current family
            (<ref target="#luiselli2019a">191</ref>). Because migrant and indigenous populations have been effectively disappeared, one
            through <q>removal</q> and another through <q>deportation,</q> both the mother-protagonist and her
            husband necessarily take a spectral approach to sound.</p>
         <p>According to Ana María Ochoa Gautier, the <q>spectrality of sound</q> refers to that which
            remains inaudible, at least to humans, as <quote rend="inline">excesses of the acoustic</quote> <ptr target="#steingo2019"/>.
            Another sense in which sound is boundless, for example, involves the fact that it
            reverberates well beyond human hearing, including in acoustic <emph>and</emph>
            ultrasonic forms. If a bat chirps or cactus falls in the Sonoran Desert and no human
            hears it, it still does make a sound. Furthermore, that sound may interact with and turn
            into other sounds, commonly called echoes. In <title rend="italic">Lost Children
               Archive</title>, both the husband and wife appeal to echoes as a trope for spectral
            listening to that which they both can and cannot hear. However, only the wife practices
            such listening as a dynamic and disorienting mode of counter-mapping. For her, such
            counter-mapping entails contextualizing sounds, as well as related ideas, against
            hegemonic maps of time, space, and subjects as singular and absolute. </p>
         <p>According to the wife, her husband claims his project to be an <q>inventory of echoes</q>
            <ptr target="#luiselli2019a"/>. Yet, he never elaborates more than that, since his understanding of
            sound as self-evident affords him a rather literal definition of echoes. An
            <q>acoustemologist</q> trained in <q>soundscaping,</q> the husband follows the work of R. Murray
            Schafer and shares his interest in acoustic ecology as <quote rend="inline">the study of sounds in
               relationship to life and society</quote> <ptr target="#schafer1977"/>. For Schafer, as well as <title
               rend="italic">Lost Children Archive</title>’s husband, the bulk of this study entails
            recording, naming, and cataloging sounds in an effort to capture, and thereby
            understand, <quote rend="inline">the general acoustic environment of a society</quote> <ptr target="#schafer1977"/>. While most
            sound scholars recognize Schafer as pivotal in establishing sound as another way of
            knowing, they also criticize his presumptuous appeal to <q>the general,</q> or universal, as
            neglectful of sound’s multivalent, and highly contextual, meanings <ptr target="#novak2015"/>.<note>
               According to David Novak and Matt Sakakeeny, who call R. Murray Schafer <q>sound
               studies’ de facto founder,</q> his influential work treats sound as a stable object with
               predictable effects on a <quote rend="inline">generalized perceptual consciousness,</quote> rather than a
               multivalent field that varies with individual, social, and environmental diversity
               <ptr target="#novak2015"/>. </note> Similarly, the wife assesses her husband’s work as crudely
            matter-of-fact. For him, bird chirps, arroyo babbles, snake rattles, wind gusts, etc.
            heard in the present are, inevitably and indubitably, reverberations of sound waves from
            foregone times and peoples. Given the mother-protagonist’s attention to uncertainty and
            exclusion, however, she interprets his inventory of echoes as <quote rend="inline"><emph
               >trying</emph> to capture their [the Apaches’] past presence in the world, and making
               it audible, despite their current absence</quote> <ptr target="#luiselli2019a" loc="emphasis added"/>. </p>
         <p> Instead of presuming presence, she is inclined to chart and interrogate it. Thinking of
            her husband’s inventory as a form of sound-mapping, therefore, she imagines that each
            echo temporarily <quote rend="inline">illuminate[s] an area of a map, a soundscape, in which Geronimo once
               was</quote> <ptr target="#luiselli2019a"/>. Here, the wife crosses sight and sound in conceptualizing an
            illuminative echo, one that appears and disappears simultaneously. Using the spectrality
            of sound to trace the spectrality of removed populations makes sense to this
            cartographer, especially as she refuses to organize her own recorded material into a
            <quote rend="inline">clean narrative sequence</quote> <ptr target="#luiselli2019a"/>. As she states, <quote rend="inline">We haven’t understood how
               space and time exist now, how we really experience them</quote> <ptr target="#luiselli2019a"/>. In her
            evaluation, archivists such as her husband often fail to acknowledge the way all
            hearing, including all recording, is contextual: that is, it takes place in a particular
            time and space, neither of which are entirely singular or absolute. Situating all
            recording as a type of echo, Mark M. Smith similarly emphasizes the need to think of
            both as simultaneously historical and ahistorical. Rather than capture sounds from the
            past exactly as they were, recordings and echoes reproduce sounds from the past in the
            present, inevitably altering them <ptr target="#novak2015"/>. For the wife in <title rend="italic">Lost
               Children Archive</title>, this means that sounds, as well as the times and spaces in
            which they reverberate, take on multiple, ever-changing meanings. They are dynamic and,
            for this very reason, also disorienting.</p>
         <p>As such, her mode of listening closely corresponds with Nicole Brittingham Furlonge’s
            <q>aural literacy,</q> which she claims to entail <quote rend="inline">listening as an artistic, civic, and
            interpretive practice that emerges from a place of wonder, curiosity, and <title
               rend="italic">not knowing</title></quote> <ptr target="#furlonge2018"/>. Drawing from a multimedia archive of
            work by black authors and artists, Furlonge examines how literary texts can shift
            reading from a strictly visual practice to one that <q>demands an aural sensory
            engagement</q> in which readers <q>think with their ears</q> about historical constructions of
            racial difference.<note> These texts include Zora Neale Hurston’s <title rend="italic"
                  >Their Eyes Were Watching God</title> and Ralph Ellison’s <title rend="italic">Invisible
                  Man</title>, among others. </note> Although, or perhaps <emph
               >because</emph>, literary texts are technically silent, they can guide readers in
            hearing and thinking about sound in innovative ways, including as an <q>epistemic site</q>
            for questioning historical hierarchies and identities <ptr target="#furlonge2018"/>. Acknowledging the
            close connection between <emph>how</emph> we know and <emph
               >who</emph> we understand humans to be, or not be, <title rend="italic">Lost Children
               Archive</title>’s mother-protagonist likewise listens from a position of inquiry.
            Instead of distinguishing and labeling sounds, for example, she hears them together as a
            collective victim of history, or what she calls <quote rend="inline">beautiful things falling apart</quote> <ptr target="#luiselli2019a"/>
            .</p>
         <p> Attune to the very lack of visual and material evidence concerning migrants, the
            mother-protagonist instead listens for additional unknowns, mostly in the form of other
            historical instances of disappearance. Hearing spectral sounds of the Apache, missing
            border crossers, and surrounding desert landscape all at once, she observes <quote rend="inline">the chaos
            of history repeated, over and over, reenacted, reinterpreted, the world, its fucked-up
            heart palpitating underneath us [...] And in the middle of it all, tribes, families,
            people, all beautiful things falling apart, debris, dust, erasure</quote> <ptr target="#luiselli2019a"/>. This
            description is highly reminiscent of philosopher Walter Benjamin’s <title rend="quotes">Angel of History,</title>
            which recognizes the past, present, and future as <q>one single catastrophe</q> in constant
            risk of oblivion, especially under the pressure of <quote rend="inline">what we call progress</quote> <ptr target="#benjamin2007"/>. Like this angel, and more critically than her husband, Luiselli’s
            mother-protagonist thus hears bird chirps, arroyo babbles, snake rattles, wind gusts,
            etc. as <q>reenactments</q> and <q>reinterpretations</q> of loss: the loss, yes, of child migrants
            but also the indigenous populations that preceded them and likewise endangered wildlife
            that accompany them. Elsewhere elaborating that <quote rend="inline">perhaps my children’s voices were like
            those bird songs that my husband helped Steven Feld record once, which function as
            echoes of people who have passed away,</quote> she effectively collapses human-nonhuman
            binaries <ptr target="#luiselli2019a"/>. Yet, she maintains her uncertainty, as well as curiosity,
            through her insistent use of <q>perhaps.</q> In doing so, she shows the practice of <q>aural
            literacy,</q> or interdisciplinary listening without knowing, to function as a viable mode
            of counter-mapping against categorical understandings of time, space, and subject.</p></div>
         <div>
         <head>IV. Digital Humanities Counter-mapping: A Case Study </head>
         <div>
            <head>Background</head>
        
         <p>Thus far, I have examined a variety of visual, sonic, textual, and digital counter-maps.
            While De León and Luiselli make use of the Arizona OpenGIS Initiative for Deceased
            Migrants map, which plots migrant deaths against the Sonoran Desert in order to expose
            the violence that policies such as Prevention Through Deterrence attempt to conceal,
            neither of them replicate this map’s digital interface or related humanitarian
            maneuvers. Rather than try to restore migrant victims’ visibility and voice, either in
            life or death, De León and Luiselli take more reflexive approaches to witnessing.
            Questioning their own use of sight and sound while consulting visual, material, and
            sonic evidence, these scholars practice <q>sideways</q> seeing and spectral listening, both
            of which serve to witness the complexity of this U.S.-Mexico border crisis. Such
            complexity, as De León and Luiselli illustrate, is largely due to the involvement of
            human and nonhuman, as well as present and absent, agents. Since this border violence
            also implicates settler colonialism and imperialism, as well as the hegemony of
            visuality and human rights politics, it requires multiple, novel ways of knowing,
            including of mapping.</p>
         <p>Accordingly, De León and Luiselli counter-map this crisis in ways that decenter the
            human, both as sensate being and liberal human rights subject. Building off of the
            counter-mapping possibilities evident in De León and Luiselli’s work, I now tap into the
            <soCalled>subversive force</soCalled> of digital humanities as a tool for <q>rethinking</q> traditional
            assumptions and practices, including those of the U.S. Department of Homeland Security
            and human rights activism alike <ptr target="#hayles2012"/>. In particular, I remain curious about how
            multi-sensory counter-mapping helps readers and listeners further disorient themselves
            and, in the process, also the Sonoran Desert as a land that has been so forcefully
            oriented around the human, both as aggressor and as victim. Rather than centralize the
            human in witnessing the U.S.-Mexico border crisis, is it possible to listen from the
            perspectives of the many nonhuman agents involved, including those of dirt, animal, and
            wind? In other words, is it possible to hear what the desert hears?</p>
         <p>Informed by Luiselli and De León, as well as other interdisciplinary cartographers and
            my own fieldwork in Southern Arizona, I have initiated a pilot project for
            counter-mapping the U.S.-Mexico border crisis as both a humanitarian crisis and a crisis
            of humanitarianism, or the centering and privileging of human victimhood. To be clear,
            my project is far from the first digital counter-mapping project about this crisis. Yet,
            many of these projects are principally visual and anthropocentric in nature. In addition
            to the aforementioned Arizona OpenGIS Initiative for Deceased Migrants map, <title
               rend="italic">Torn Apart / Separados</title> is a scholar-activist intervention that has
            circulated widely since 2018. A response to the Trump administration’s zero-tolerance
            family separation policy, <title rend="italic">Torn Apart / Separados</title> includes digital
            maps about ICE facilities, political funding, and deportations, as well as allied
            organizations for migrants. The <title rend="italic">Torn Apart / Separados</title> team
            claims this work <quote rend="inline">peels back layers of culpability behind the humanitarian crisis of
            2018</quote> and exposes otherwise overlooked agents in the border crisis, such as the amount
            of ICE contracts awarded per congressional district. These cartographers also note the
            inevitably <q>imprecise</q> and <q>contingent</q> nature of data visualizations, including maps,
            but do not detail their exclusions <ptr target="#tornapart2018"/>.</p>
         <p>Though humanitarian maps about the U.S.-Mexico border crisis tend to exclude data on
            nonhuman victims, land and wildlife studies of this region do often make some mention of
            disappeared migrants. In a recent joint press release from the Center for Biological
            Diversity, Sierra Club, and Sky Island Alliance, Tucson-based environmental activists
            critique border militarization as detrimental to all local communities, including
            transitory ones. Protesting border wall construction for further impeding <quote rend="inline">the natural
            migrations of people and wildlife that are essential to healthy diversity,</quote> these
            activists called for an immediate halt to such construction <ptr target="#jordahl2020"/>.<note> In
               January of 2021, President Joe Biden signed an executive order pausing border wall
               construction.</note> Laiken Jordahl, Borderlands Campaigner for the Center for
            Biological Diversity, and Emily Burns, Program Director for Sky Island Alliance, are two
            such activists who regularly publish field research documenting life and loss along the
            border. For example, Jordahl has published multiple photos and videos of bulldozing and
            blasting through Organ Pipe Cactus National Monument, which decimated endangered animal
            habitat and Tohono O’odham sacred sites for wall building. Focusing on the nearby
            Patagonia and Huachuca Mountains, Burns directs a binational Border Wildlife study
            catalogs species in the area through clandestine cameras.</p>
         <p>While much research and activism along the border is multi-sensory insofar as it
            utilizes sight and sound, as well as other senses, to document ongoing violence and
            resistance, I contend that crossing senses can further decenter the human in this border
            crisis. In <title rend="quotes">A sensory approach for multispecies anthropology,</title> Natasha Fijn and Muhammad
            A. Kavesh defend the combination of sensory ethnography and multispecies anthropology as
            part of a <q>post-humanist analysis</q> that is ecological, not anthropocentric, in nature
            <ptr target="#fijn2021"/>. Following fellow anthropologist Anna Tsing, they advocate a practice of
            observing and contemplating relationships among humans and nonhumans, including their
            shared precarity. Against human exceptionalism, this practice aims <quote rend="inline">to think beyond the
               boundary of the human, beyond ‘anthropos’ or ‘ethnos’</quote> <ptr target="#fijn2021"/>. My counter-mapping
            project shares this aim, with the practical purpose of exposing the humanitarian crisis
            as the U.S.-Mexico border as also ecological in nature.</p></div>
            <div>
        
            <head>Methods</head>
        
         <p> While multiple scholars have considered the possibility of witnessing beyond the human
            using an anthropological or philosophical approach, I here adopt a digital humanities
            approach, with a particular focus on pedagogy and practice.<note> Kate Jenckes’ <title
                  rend="italic">Witnessing Beyond the Human: Addressing the
                  Alterity of the Other in Post-coup Chile and Argentina </title>and Jane Bennett’s <title
                  rend="italic">Vibrant Matter: A Political Ecology of Things</title> are two relevant
               philosophical studies.</note> As such, my remaining concerns closely align with those
            of Steph Ceraso, author of <title rend="italic">Sounding Composition: Multimodal Pedagogies
               for Embodied Listening</title>. In this book, Ceraso investigates how multimodal
            pedagogies and projects, including digital sound maps, facilitate <quote rend="inline">a reeducation of our
            senses — a bodily retraining that can help listeners learn to become more open to the
            connections among sensory modes, environments, and materials</quote> <ptr target="#ceraso2018"/>. Like
            Furlonge and Luiselli, Ceraso advocates for an interdisciplinary, or <q>multimodal,</q>
            practice of listening that involves thinking critically about the experience of sound,
            which she understands to be a <quote rend="inline">contextual […] sonic event</quote> <ptr target="#ceraso2018"/>. While
            <q>multimodal</q> implies that there are discrete modes of knowing and being, for example,
            Ceraso recognizes such separation of the senses to be historically and culturally
            learned. </p>
         <p>In turn, her practices of multimodal listening and digital sound mapping involve
            attending to the ways senses interact with, and even subvert, each other in creating an
            embodied experience of place. More than simply <q>listen</q> with their ears, Ceraso’s
            students record the time of day and weather conditions of their audio recordings; look
            for visual and tactile proof of sonic vibrations; write textual descriptions of
            fieldwork experiences; and reflect on the limits of a digital interface such as
            Soundcities <ptr target="#ceraso2018"/>. By crossing multiple senses while collecting data, students
            gradually recognize such sensory knowledge as both contextual and partial. At stake,
            therefore, in this <quote rend="inline">reeducation of our senses</quote> is not just a newfound attunement to the
            complex connections among humans’ own sensory modes, but also among those modes and
            surrounding <q>environments</q> and <q>materials.</q> Such attunement, according to Ceraso,
            challenges visual approaches to knowing, <q>ear-centric</q> approaches to listening, and, in
            my evaluation, also anthropocentric approaches to the humanities, including related
            humanitarian concerns <ptr target="#ceraso2018"/>. </p>
         <p>Informed by Ceraso, Luiselli, and De León, as well as the interdisciplinary scholars
            mentioned throughout this article and my own fieldwork in Southern Arizona, I have
            created a digital counter-map that decenters humans as the sole victims of the
            U.S.-Mexico border crisis. In this ArcGIS project, accessible <ref
               target="https://arcg.is/41PDy">here</ref> and represented in Figure 5, I combine
            sonic, visual, and literary evidence, sometimes together, at the same geotag, and
            sometimes apart. Such evidence, or proof of existence, includes descriptions of deceased
            migrants’ <q>body condition,</q> audio recordings of animals, photos of desert landscapes,
            outlines of endangered species ranges and border walls, and excerpts from multiple
            texts, including De León’s <title rend="italic">The Land of Open Graves</title> and Luiselli’s
               <title rend="italic">Lost Children Archive</title>. As my practice of <title rend="quotes">Counter-mapping the
            U.S.-Mexico Border Crisis,</title> these map layers and survey points work against hegemonic
            practices of documentation, including those historically privileged by the U.S.
            Department of Homeland Security, human rights activism, and the field of digital
            humanities alike. As previously explained, hegemonic practices separate and hierarchize
            species and senses, privileging humans and their vision simultaneously. In contrast, my
            practice crosses species and senses alike, showing all to be in relation, and also in
            danger. </p>
               
               <figure>
                  <head><title rend="quotes">Counter-mapping the U.S.-Mexico Border Crisis</title> in full view,
                     with selected layers in sidebar</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of a map of the border of the US with multicolored dots along the edge</figDesc>
               </figure>
          
               
               
               
         <p>I first recognized the need for this counter-mapping methodology in March of 2019, while
            co-leading a university trip to Southern Arizona called <emph
               >Conocimiento</emph>, or <q>awareness.</q> To expose students to the complexities of the
            U.S.-Mexico border crisis, this trip included meetings with various on-the-ground
            actors, including border residents, patrol agents, activists, and unauthorized day
            laborers. Depending on the actors’ differing interests, they referenced maps
            foregrounding border wall construction, military checkpoints, humanitarian aid stations,
            or, most commonly, the discovery of human remains. Throughout this trip, we saw at least
            three versions of Humane Borders’ <title rend="quotes">Map of Migrant Mortality,</title> which De León and Luiselli
            both reference in their work. Because my students had not read these authors’ depictions
            of the Sonoran Desert hybrid collectif, I feared that their perception of this landscape
            would be reduced to the hostile, even criminal, terrain that policies like Prevention
            Through Deterrence situate it as. It was during this trip, therefore, that I began
            brainstorming ways to map this landscape differently.</p>
         <p>Like Ceraso, I wanted to put my students into a collaborative, even conversational,
            interaction with their surroundings. What did they hear as they took photos of
            Normandy-style vehicle barriers, Cottonwood trees, and a horizon often dotted with at
            least one memorial cross? How might this hearing change if they simultaneously recalled
            Luiselli’s onomatopoeic depiction of desert dust-clouds appearing and disappearing as
            <quote rend="inline">Shrrrrrr, sssssssss, hsssssss, sss, hhhhh,</quote> or Jason De León’s graphic description of a
            mummified migrant corpse with a face <quote rend="inline">replaced by a stone-colored ghoul stuck in
            mid-scream</quote>? And what if they could digitally return to this location months later to
            hear the nocturnal chirp of a Whippoorwill that escaped their notice while they were
            previously there in person? To begin investigating these questions, I consulted the
            Institute for Digital Arts and Humanities (IDAH) at Indiana University Bloomington about
            multimedia map tools. A group of faculty, graduate students, and staff who specialize in
            digital methods, IDAH recommended Esri’s ArcGIS Online and ArcGIS Survey 123 for their
            institutional availability and ease of use.<note> A mobile phone app for data
               collection, ArcGIS Survey 123 facilitates collaborative map-making among multiple
               parties, including professors and students.</note>
         </p>
         <p>Yet, while Esri is the industry standard for commercial Geographic Information Systems
            (GIS) software, its open partnerships with numerous private and public agencies,
            including the U.S. Department of Homeland Security, initially give me pause. As the
            software that connects DHS’ vast system of remote sensors, lookout towers, drones, and
            other agent-carried GPS technologies, ArcGIS both facilitates and maximizes security
            enforcement along the U.S.-Mexico border <ptr target="#deleon2016"/>. Yet, these very same
            technologies can likewise map and critique the systemic violence of such enforcement.
            Like De León, I thus began experimenting with co-opting <q>the master’s tools</q> by
            uploading various online resources into a map titled <title rend="quotes">Counter-mapping the U.S.-Mexico
            Border Crisis.</title> </p>
         <p>The first resource was the open source data from the Arizona OpenGIS Initiative for
            Deceased Migrants, from which I selected <q>unidentified</q> remains and created color-coded
            survey points based on the <q>body condition</q> upon discovery. Such anonymity, along with
            conditions that range from <q>fully fleshed</q> to <q>skeletonizaton w/ mummification</q> to
            <q>complete skeletonization w/ bone degradation,</q> emphasize the postmortem dehumanization
            of these human corpses. Especially in death, migrant bodies become indistinguishable
            from the landscape that both witnesses and facilitates their gradual decomposition. To
            further challenge human-nonhuman binaries, I next searched online for digital sounds and
            images representing the natural environment implicated in the U.S.-Mexico border crisis.
            This search yielded multiple relevant materials, including those from Sky Island
            Alliance’s Border Wildlife Study, Charles Bogert’s <title rend="italic">Sounds of the
               American Southwest</title>, The Western Soundscape Archive, and The Acoustic Ecology Lab
            at Arizona State University.</p>
         <p>While I was pleased with the variety of visual and auditory resources available online,
            an essential part of producing my counter-map was field photography and sound recording.
            When initially conceptualizing this project, I was set to lead additional <title
               rend="italic">Conocimiento</title> trips and planned on including those students in
            on-the-ground data collection using the aforementioned ArcGIS Survey 123. The COVID-19
            pandemic cancelled those plans, yet I was able to make multiple solo visits to Southern
            Arizona in 2020, including to Chiricahua National Monument in early March, Organ Pipe
            Cactus National Monument in late March, and the Huachuca Mountains in late September.
            Each of these places has a history of forced displacement, including the Apache Wars
            taking place around Chiricahua National Monument and ongoing border militarization
            happening throughout Organ Pipe Cactus National Monument and the Huachuca Mountains. I
            visited Organ Pipe Cactus National Monument as the Trump administration expedited border
            wall construction along its southern edge, destroying local flora, animal habitat, and
            Tohono O’odham sacred sites in the process. Similar construction eventually reached the
            Huachuca Mountains in 2021, after I had already visited the area. </p>
         <p>During these respective visits, I camped, hiked, and recorded what I encountered. With
            the continued support of IDAH, I was able to borrow their Sony IC recorder for short
            audio samples. While relatively basic, and prone to picking up wind sounds, this
            recorder still captures the spectrality that interests me most about soundscapes. Like
            the mother-protagonist in Luiselli’s <title rend="italic">Lost Children Archive</title>, I
            listened for presence and absence, appearance and disappearance. And unlike the U.S.
            Department of Homeland Security, I did not map such listening with the purpose of
            definitively locating, tracking, or identifying anything. Instead, I aimed to use
            digital data and GIS software to record a multi-sensory experience of a landscape that
            humans cannot readily understand. For this reason, I recorded sonic environments that
            spontaneously intrigued me. There was never any recording schedule or inventory, though
            I did keep track of the date, time, and location of each recording. I did this because I
            would like to eventually return to these same places and listen for changes in the
            soundscape.</p></div>
            <div>
        
            <head>Results and Discussion</head>
         
         <p>Joining Sterne, as well as Furlonge and Ceraso, in conceptualizing listening as <q>a
            learned skill,</q> I see the purpose of this counter-map to be practice: that is, the
            interminable practice of witnessing human bodies, as well as human-made maps, as in
            dynamic relation with environments that both includes and exceeds them. Against
            simplistic representations of the Sonoran Desert as hostile terrain rife with
            humanitarian crisis, <title rend="quotes">Counter-mapping the U.S.-Mexico Border Crisis</title> thus situates this
            landscape as endangered, biodiverse, and complex beyond absolute comprehension. While my
            ArcGIS map is still informative, especially to those who have not visited Southern
            Arizona in person, its multiple layers orient and disorient viewers simultaneously.
            Firstly, the diversity and quantity of information is overwhelming, as this digital map
            includes images, sounds, textual excerpts, animal ranges and migratory routes, border
            wall models, and hundreds of data points marking unidentified migrant remains. Secondly,
            many geotags include multiple types of media, thereby facilitating <q>sideways glances</q> in
            which map visitors think critically about this landscape, its history, and their sensory
            relationship to it all.</p>
         <p>Given the continued disappearances and deaths of migrants crossing the Sonoran Desert,
            as well as the expedited construction of a new border wall system through wildlife
            corridors including the Organ Pipe Cactus National Monument and Madrean Sky Island
            Region and, structural violence in this region clearly affects humans and nonhumans
            alike. The Lesser Long-nosed Bat, one of many animals endangered by the habitat loss
            resulting from border crossing and militarization, migrates among various locations
            throughout Mexico and Southern Arizona, including the aforementioned wildlife corridors.
               <note> Threats to the Lesser Long-nosed Bat include drug and human-traffickers using
               their caves, the destruction of the cacti they feed on, and the construction of a
               border wall tall enough to disrupt their flight patterns. Though this bat was first
               listed under the Endangered Species Act in 1998, and subsequently delisted in 2018,
               it remains especially vulnerable to the heightened border militarization currently
               underway. </note> The northern part of this route consists of the Chiricahua National
            Monument, one of my field research sites and a place referenced extensively by family
            members in Luiselli’s <title rend="italic">Lost Children Archive</title>. Like this fictional
            family, I traced the Echo Canyon Trail, which descends into a dizzying maze of rhyolite
            hoodoos, or igneous rock spires. Since Luiselli’s father character claims you can listen
            to the voices of fallen Apaches in Echo Canyon, the son enters its depths, eagerly
            shouts Geronimo, and hears <quote rend="inline">it bouncing back even stronger and longer, Geronimo,
               eronimo, onimo, onimo</quote> <ptr target="#luiselli2019a"/>. Yet, as I traversed this same location, I tried
            to be as silent as possible while extending my small Sony IC recorder in the air,
            pushing record, and appearing to capture nothing but wind gusts, audible <ref
               target="https://services.arcgis.com/tKsJAIiLjd90D5q2/arcgis/rest/services/survey123_7cdf7e1c0f894bdc88def05f618c89cd/FeatureServer/0/19/attachments/16"
               >here</ref>. </p>
               
               <figure>
                  <head>Echo Canyon, part of Chiricahua National Monument</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Image of Echo Canyon</figDesc>
               </figure>
        
               
               
         <p>Had I not added a photo, represented in Figure 6, to this same geotag on the map, it
            would be hard to hear the audio recording as also documenting hoodoos, or rock spires,
            standing en masse. Had I not added the audio recording to this same geotag, however, map
            visitors likely would miss the uncanny experience of not knowing all they are witnessing
            or, stated otherwise, all that is present, absent, and spectral here. Given Echo
            Canyon’s location along Lesser Long-nosed Bat migratory routes, for example, my
            recording could include ultrasonic echoes of last night’s echolocation calls.
            Technically, the chance of this happening is very low, if non-existent. Imaginatively,
            however, this chance is nevertheless enough to be politically and ethically relevant.
            For knowing the possibility of <emph>not</emph> knowing, or indeed hearing the
            possibility of <emph>not</emph> hearing, is disorienting. Interacting with
            this digital map, therefore, visitors do not necessarily lose their sense of direction,
            but they very likely lose their sense of being at the center of all action and
            knowledge, including that of the U.S.-Mexico Border crisis. </p>
         <p>Just as De León claims that <quote rend="inline">people have to be decentered in the agency equation</quote> of
            this crisis, I maintain that humans ought to be decentered from witnessing practices,
            including mapping. Yet, such decentering is admittedly difficult, especially given the
            anthropocentrism and anthropomorphism also prominent in sound studies. According to
            Deborah Kapchan, sound studies is still asking the key question of, <quote rend="inline">And how might
            attention to sound and affect produce a body unfettered by the dualisms of the
            Enlightenment — mind/body, nature/culture, man/woman, human/animal, spirit/material?</quote>
            <ptr target="#novak2015"/>. Acknowledging the field’s focus on humans, however, Sterne encourages
            continual <q>interrogation</q> of our own hearing, as well as our access to nonhuman hearing,
            including that of animals, land, and technology <ptr target="#novak2015"/>. For example, is it
            appropriate to say that land, and the geophones that pick up ground vibrations, <q>hear</q>
            anything at all? When an exhausted migrant falls to the desert floor, delirious from
            extreme dehydration, do the dirt, rocks, and nearby creatures even take notice? And when
            an ultrasonic recorder makes bat echolocation audible to humans, who, in fact, is doing
            the hearing? For Sterne, refraining from idealizing human and nonhuman hearing opens up
            new sets of questions about knowledge, subjectivity, and politics, namely politics that
            involve <quote rend="inline">hearing the hearing of others,</quote> or at least trying <ptr target="#novak2015"/>.</p>
         <p>Following the Lesser Long-nosed Bat’s migratory route southward, towards Mexico, on my
            ArcGIS map, I include a likewise multivalent audio recording from Organ Pipe Cactus
            National Monument, which houses Tohono O’odham burial sites and other endangered animals
            such as the Sonoran Pronghorn and Quitobaquito Pupfish. Upon first listen of this
            recording, audible <ref
               target="https://services.arcgis.com/tKsJAIiLjd90D5q2/arcgis/rest/services/survey123_7cdf7e1c0f894bdc88def05f618c89cd/FeatureServer/0/28/attachments/21"
               >here</ref>, one may vaguely hear bird chirps, footsteps, a trickle of water, and
            some kind of traffic. Only the expert ear would be able to identify the specific sound
            of steamrollers cruising along Highway 85, having just left the site of border wall
            construction near Lukeville, Arizona, where they likely aided the hasty removal of local
            flora and fauna. Similarly, only the expert ear would be able to identify the
            specificities of a morning birdsong medley recorded from inside a nearby camping tent,
            audible <ref
               target="https://services.arcgis.com/tKsJAIiLjd90D5q2/arcgis/rest/services/survey123_7cdf7e1c0f894bdc88def05f618c89cd/FeatureServer/0/33/attachments/28"
               >here</ref>. The point of this map, however, is not to train the expert ear, or even
            engage strictly ear-centric modes of listening. Rather, the point is to get map visitors
            thinking about what the human, including the human with digital technology, can and
            cannot witness in the Arizona desert: a landscape layered with historical, political,
            and environmental significance.</p>
         <p>Like De León and Luiselli, I use this map to show that restoring the sight and sound, or
            voice and visibility, of human victims is insufficient to addressing the U.S.-Mexico
            border crisis. Rather than replace one mode of witnessing with another, however, this
            map models and facilitates a multi-modal, interdisciplinary interrogation of witnessing.
            As visitors navigate through images of landscapes, sounds of wildlife, and textual
            excerpts about local violence, they continually confront the challenge of comprehension,
            or understanding in an inclusive and absolute sense. Instead of providing easy or
            exhaustive answers, this digital counter-map invites participants into the ongoing
            question of hearing what the Sonoran Desert hears, as assassin, witness, and victim.
            Such inquiry is both orienting and disorienting, as it prompts viewers to engage the
            sensory and epistemological limits inherent to humanhood. Engaging these limits,
            however, also draws witnesses into closer, more attentive connection with the nonhuman
            ecosystems that both envelop and elude them. </p>
         <p>Chances are that map visitors will never actually answer the complex question of hearing
            what the desert hears, yet asking it reminds them that such unknowns are also in crisis,
            and also worth protecting. As the Prevention Through Deterrence policy and other border
            militarization efforts remain in full effect, it is especially important to remember
            that the U.S.-Mexico border crisis necessitates epistemological and social, not just
            political, paradigm shifts. Indeed, it requires a decentering of visuality and
            anthropocentrism simultaneously, wherein witnesses recognize humanitarian and ecological
            issues as interrelated. As I have shown, this counter-mapping project contributes to
            such decentering by offering a practice of crossing the senses, leaning into
            disorientation, and collapsing human-nonhuman binaries. This practice is difficult and
            interminable, yet digital humanities pedagogies and projects like those I have
            demonstrated here also render it accessible, interactive, and impactful. At stake in
            such projects are not just “a reeducation of our senses” but also a reconfiguration of
            the world: a world that can better protect humans and nonhumans alike, together.</p>
               
            </div>
         </div>
       <div>
          <head>Acknowledgments</head>
          <p>The research presented here greatly benefitted from the guidance and support of the Institute for Digital Arts and Humanities (IDAH) at Indiana University Bloomington. Thanks are due to their talented staff and scholars.</p>
       </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="altschuler2020" label="Altschuler 2020"> Altschuler, S. and Weimer, D. <title rend="quotes">Texturing the Digital Humanities: A
               Manifesto</title>, <title rend="italic">PMLA</title>, 135.1 (2020): 74-91. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="anker2012" label="Anker 2012"> Anker. <title rend="italic">Fictions of Dignity: Embodying Human Rights in World Literature</title>. Cornell
               University Press, Ithaca (2012). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="arizonaopengis" label="Arizona OpenGIS"> Arizona OpenGIS Initiative for Deceased Migrants, viewed 19 June 2020,
               https://humaneborders.info</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="arizonastatemuseum2016" label="Arizona State Museum 2016"> Arizona State Museum map of Federally Recognized Tribes in
               Arizona, viewed 25 June 2020, <ref
                  target="https://statemuseum.arizona.edu/programs/american-indian-relations/tribes-arizona"
                  >https://statemuseum.arizona.edu/programs/american-indian-relations/tribes-arizona</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="benjamin2007" label="Benjamin 2007"> Benjamin. <title rend="italic">Illuminations</title>. Shocken Books, New York, 2007. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bogert1959" label="Bogert 1959"> Bogert. <title rend="italic">Sounds of the American Southwest</title>. Folkways Records and Service
               Corporation, New York (1959).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ceraso2018" label="Ceraso 2018"> Ceraso, S. <title rend="italic">Sounding Composition: Multimodal Pedagogies for Embodied
               Listening</title>. University of Pittsburgh Press, Pittsburgh (2018). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="colibri2020" label="Colibrí 2020"> Colibrí Center for Human Rights, viewed 19 June 2020, <ref
               target="https://colibricenter.org/about/">https://colibricenter.org/about/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="continued2013" label="Continued 2013"> <title rend="quotes">A Continued Humanitarian Crisis at the Border: Undocumented Border
               Crosser Deaths Recorded by the Pima County Office of the Medical Examiner, 1990-2012</title>,
               The Binational Migration Institute (2013):
               <ref target="https://bmi.arizona.edu/sites/default/files/publication-files/Martinez%20et%20al.%202013%20A%20Continued%20Humanitarian%20Crises.pdf">https://bmi.arizona.edu/sites/default/files/publication-files/Martinez%20et%20al.%202013%20A%20Continued%20Humanitarian%20Crises.pdf</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cooper2016" label="Cooper 2016"> Cooper, D., Donaldson C., and Murrieta-Flores P. <title rend="italic">Literary Mapping in the
               Digital Age.</title> Routledge, New York (2016). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="degenova2013" label="De Genova 2013"> De Genova, N. <title rend="quotes">Spectacles of migrant ‘illegality’: the scene of
               exclusion, the obscene of inclusion</title>, <title rend="italic">Ethnic and Racial Studies</title>, 36.7 (2013):
               1180-1198.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="deleon2016" label="De León 2016"> De León, J. <title rend="quotes">Surveilling Surveillance: Counter-mapping Undocumented
               Migration in the USA-Mexico Borderlands</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Contemporary Archaeology</title>, 3.2
               (2016): 121-294.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="deleon2015" label="De León 2015"> De León, J. <title rend="italic">Land of Open Graves: Living and Dying on the Migrant Trail.</title>
               University of California Press, Berkeley (2015). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eloriente2020" label="El Oriente 2020"> El Oriente Todo Oaxaca. <title rend="quotes">Valeria Luiselli presenta Desierto Sonoro.</title>
               YouTube (2019). Viewed on July 5, 2020, <ref
                  target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yP8sfh3LF9I"
                  >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yP8sfh3LF9I</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fijn2021" label="Fijn 2021"> Fijn, N. and Kavesh, M. <title rend="quotes">A sensory approach for multispecies anthropology</title>,
               <title rend="italic">The Australian Journal of Anthropology</title>, (2021).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="foscarini2016" label="Foscarini 2016"> Foscarini, F., MacNeil H., Oliver G., and Mak B. <title rend="italic">Engaging with Records
               and Archives: Histories and Theories</title>. Facet Publishing, London (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="furlonge2018" label="Furlonge 2018"> Furlonge, N.B. <title rend="italic">Race Sounds</title>. University of Iowa Press, Iowa City,
               2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gokee2020" label="Gokee 2020"> Gokee, C., Stewart, H., and De León, J. <title rend="quotes">Scales of Suffering in the
               US-Mexico Borderlands</title>, <title rend="italic">International Journal of Historical Archaeology</title>, (2020).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hayles2012" label="Hayles 2012"> Hayles, N. K. <title rend="italic">How We Think: Digital Media and Contemporary Technogenesis.</title>
               University of Chicago Press, Chicago (2012). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hess2019" label="Hess 2019"> Hess, D. <title rend="quotes">Management of Undocumented Border Crosser (UBC) Remains</title>, Pima
               County Office of the Medical Examiner, presented March 13, 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jimenez2009" label="Jimenez 2009"> Jimenez, M. <title rend="quotes">Humanitarian Crisis: Migrant Deaths at the U.S.-Mexico
               Border</title>, ACLU.org (2009): <ref
                  target="https://www.aclu.org/legal-document/humanitarian-crisis-migrant-deaths-us-mexico-border"
                  >https://www.aclu.org/legal-document/humanitarian-crisis-migrant-deaths-us-mexico-border</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jordahl2020" label="Jordahl 2020"> Jordahl, L., Millis, D., and Burns, E. <title rend="quotes">Trump’s Border Wall Would End
               Jaguar Recovery, Bulldoze Sky Island Mountains</title>, skyislandalliance.org (2020): <ref
                  target="https://skyislandalliance.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/Trump%E2%80%99s-Border-Wall-Would-End-Jaguar-Recovery-Press-Release-May-14-2020.pdf"
                  >https://skyislandalliance.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/Trump%E2%80%99s-Border-Wall-Would-End-Jaguar-Recovery-Press-Release-May-14-2020.pdf</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="klein2013" label="Klein 2013"> Klein, L. <title rend="quotes">The Image of Absence: Archival Silence, Data Visualization, and
               James Hemings</title>, <title rend="italic">American Literature</title> 85.4, (2013). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lingold2018" label="Lingold 2018"> Lingold, M. C., Mueller, D. and Trettien, W. <title rend="italic">Digital Sound Studies</title>. Duke
               University Press, Durham (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="luiselli2017" label="Luiselli 2017"> Luiselli, V. <title rend="italic">Tell Me How It Ends: An Essay in 40 Questions.</title> Coffee House
               Press, Minneapolis (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="luiselli2019a" label="Luiselli 2019a"> Luiselli, V. <title rend="italic">Lost Children Archive: A Novel.</title> Alfred A. Knopf, New York
               (2019). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="luiselli2019b" label="Luiselli 2019b"> Luiselli, V. <title rend="italic">Lost Children Archive: A Novel</title>. Narrated by Valeria
               Luiselli, Kivlighan de Montebello, William DeMeritt, Maia Enrigue Luiselli. Random House
               Audio, New York (2019).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcmurray2018" label="McMurray 2018"> McMurray, P. <title rend="quotes">Ephemeral cartography: on mapping sound.</title> <title rend="italic">Sound Studies</title>,
               4.2 (2018): 110-142.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="misrach2016" label="Misrach 2016"> Misrach, R., Galindo, G. and Kun, J. <title rend="italic">Border Cantos</title>. Aperture, New York
               (2016). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="naturalresources2020" label="Natural Resources 2020"> Natural Resources Committee, <title rend="quotes">Subcommittee
                  Hearing: Destroying Sacred Sites and Erasing Tribal Culture: The Trump
                  Administration’s Construction of the Border Wall,</title> viewed 20 July 2021, <ref
                     target="https://naturalresources.house.gov/hearings/destroying-sacred-sites-and-erasing-tribal-culture-the-trump-administrations-construction-of-the-border-wall"
                     >https://naturalresources.house.gov/hearings/destroying-sacred-sites-and-erasing-tribal-culture-the-trump-administrations-construction-of-the-border-wall</ref>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="noble2011" label="Noble 2011"> Noble, S.U. <title rend="quotes">Geographic Information Systems: A Critical Look at the
                  Commercialization of Public Information</title>, <title rend="italic">Human Geography</title>, (2011). </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="novak2015" label="Novak 2015"> Novak, D. and Sakakeeny, M. (eds)<title rend="italic"> Keywords in Sound.</title> Duke University
                  Press, Durham (2015).</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="peluso1995" label="Peluso 1995"> Peluso, N. <title rend="quotes">Whose Woods Are These? Counter-Mapping Forest Territories
                  in Kalimantan, Indonesia</title>, <title rend="italic">Antipode</title>, 27.4 (1995): 383-406.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="presner2014" label="Presner 2014"> Presner, T., Shepard, D., and Kawano, Y. <title rend="italic">Hypercities: Thick Mapping in
                  the Digital Humanities.</title> Harvard University Press, Cambridge (2014). </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="schafer1977" label="Schafer 1977"> Schafer Murray, R. <title rend="italic">The Soundscape: Our Sonic Environment and the
                  Tuning of the World</title>. Destiny Books, Rochester, Vermont (1977). </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="skyislandalliance2021" label="Sky Island Alliance 2021"> Sky Island Alliance, <title rend="quotes">Border Wildlife Study,</title> viewed 19
                  July 2021, 
                  <ref target="https://skyislandalliance.org/our-work/wildlife-program/borderwildlife/"
                     >https://skyislandalliance.org/our-work/wildlife-program/borderwildlife/</ref>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="simulation2020" label="Simulation 2020"> Simulation, <title rend="quotes">AAA #654 Dr. Jason De León – Hostile Terrain 94.</title>
                  YouTube (2020). Viewed on June 2020, <ref
                     target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qman4zfYgwk&amp;feature=youtu.be"
                     >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qman4zfYgwk&amp;feature=youtu.be</ref>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="steingo2019" label="Steingo 2019"> Steingo, G. and Sykes, J. (eds) <title rend="italic">Remapping Sound Studies</title>. Duke
                  University Press, Durham (2019).</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="steintrager2018" label="Steintrager 2018"> Steintrager, J. and Chow, R. (eds) <title rend="italic">Sound Objects</title>. Duke University
                  Press, Durham (2018).</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="sterne2003" label="Sterne 2003"> Sterne, J. <title rend="italic">The Audible Past: Cultural Origins of Sound Reproduction.</title>
                  Duke University Press, Durham (2003).</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tazzioli2015" label="Tazzioli 2015"> Tazzioli, M. <title rend="quotes">Which Europe? Migrants Uneven Geographies and
                  Counter-Mapping at the limits of Representation.</title> <title rend="italic">Movements</title>, 1.2 (2015):1-20. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tornapart2018" label="Torn Apart 2018"> <title rend="quotes">Torn Apart / Separados.</title> viewed 12 July 2021,
                  <ref target="http://xpmethod.columbia.edu/torn-apart/credits.html">http://xpmethod.columbia.edu/torn-apart/credits.html</ref></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="customs2020" label="U.S. Customs 2020"> U.S. Customs and Border Protection, <title rend="quotes">Border Wall System,</title> viewed
                  19 June 2020, <ref target="http://xpmethod.columbia.edu/torn-apart/credits.html">https://www.cbp.gov/border-security/along-us-borders/border-wall-system</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zaratevaldez2016" label="Zárate Valdez 2016"> Zárate Valdez, J. L. <title rend="quotes">Grupos étnicos de Sonora: territorios y
                  condiciones actuales de vida y rezago.</title> <title rend="italic">Región y sociedad</title>, 28.65 (2016).</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
