<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt><!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English--></title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo><!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>first name(s) <dhq:family>family name</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation/>
               <email/>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND"><!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords"><!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors--><!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
               <term corresp=""/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords"><!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc><!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/NNNNNN/NNNNNN.xml">GitHub
                   </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract><!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser><!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>Digital Sankofa: Understanding the Past and Futures of Black Digital Humanities</p>
         <p>Rebecca Y. Bayeck and Joseph Bayeck</p>
         <p>The journey to conceptualizing this special issue started in a summer seminar organized by the <ref target="https://www.clir.org">Council on Library and Information Resources</ref> (CLIR).  Since 2004, CLIR through its postdoctoral fellowship program has recruited, trained and established cohorts of talented researchers steeped in the materials and methods of their disciplines for work in library and cultural organizations. In recent years, the program has endeavored to advance a sophisticated understanding of production, management, and re-use of research data and to contribute to a sustainable infrastructure for future research. Beginning in 2019, CLIR initiated the recruitment of postdoctoral researchers with a focus on methods and processes pertaining to the execution of research in African American and African Studies. <ref target="https://www.clir.org/2018/09/clir-receives-grant-for-data-curation-fellowships-in-african-american-and-african-studies/">The Data Curation Fellowships for African American and African Studies (AAAS)</ref> provided an opportunity for scholars to explore AAAS in the digital world; to contribute to the curation of data using approaches that are mindful of issues such as privilege, identity, access, erasure, privacy, and technology.  </p>
         <p>CLIR’s seminar created a space for these fellows and their supervisors to engage in conversations related to various topics. Participants discussed topics such as   a) understanding the emerging field of Black digital humanities; b) defining the future of Black digital humanities; and c) the intersection of emerging technologies with Black experiences. CLIR’s postdoctoral fellowships in data curation for AAAS built on the work of researchers like Kim Gallon, Catherine Knight Steele, André Brock, and Moya Bailey in defining the field. Fellows also benefited from the works of scholars such as Gabrielle Foreman, Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie, and Safiya U. Noble in our discussions about the future of Black digital humanities.</p>
         <p>As Prince and Messina (2022) argue, more work still needs to be done to center Black digital humanities. Similarly, we contend that there is also a critical need to center Black voices in Black digital humanities. We acknowledge that the field has gained much ground and is in the process of establishing itself as a field of research in its own right. The death of George Floyd increased interest in Black experiences. It brought more light to the work that scholars like those mentioned above have been doing for years. In an increasingly wired, digitized lives, interactions, culture, and society, Black digital humanities is rightly situated to be the space that explores emerging technologies and Blackness; the space that shapes new methods and practices in fields seeking to address and understand issues of race, power, and access. This field is a space to examine how technology is used to present, tell, define, and even study Black people's experiences, culture, and history in various settings.</p>
         <p>More than any other field, we contend that inherent to Black digital humanities work is information, formation, transformation, and crosspollination of scholars and the public that engage with this work. By informing, we mean educating on the work of Black scholars, innovative approaches to digital spaces, and projects that center Black people in digital humanities (Prince &amp; Messina, 2022). Formation implies situating Black digital humanities as a field of its own right and providing a space for individuals to make sense of Blackness in the digital age. We conceive transformation as shaping research and practices to reflect the joy, fun, and Black lives in their multiple forms. With cross-pollination, we imply the free-flow of concepts, practices, and thoughts from Black digital humanities to other fields, and vice versa, which encourages knowledge sharing and dialogue (Cramer &amp; Tichenor, 2023). This special issue builds on previous research to advance and situate Black digital humanities in relation to other fields. It also points to the practice of learning and teaching inherent to Black digital humanities.  </p>
         <p>For this special issue, we situated Black digital humanities in different contexts. In doing so, we intended to avoid the creation of a "single story"; to refrain from presenting Blackness “as one thing, as only one thing, over and over again” in a digital world. Connecting with the history or past that inform Black digital humanities to advance the field and shape its future, we drew on Sankofa, which is an Akan proverb as well as a philosophical perspective from the broader Ashanti language group in Ghana, West Africa. Sankofa means "we must go back and reclaim our past so we can move forward; so, we understand why and how we came to be who we are today." (Aboagye, 2022, p. 8). Digital Sankofa is therefore about reclaiming how Blackness and Blacks have been constructed in digital spaces to define, but also develop new ways of thinking about Blackness and Blacks as time passes in the field of Black digital humanities.  Hence, we think of Blackness and Black people's past and future intersection with technology and other fields. This approach reduces the barriers posed by the complexity and specialized language typical of academic articles, thereby enhancing the dissemination of ideas beyond common Black digital humanities circles.</p>
         <p>Articles included in this special issue</p>
         <p>The result is a collection of six articles that are both conceptual and practical in nature. The papers, which are described briefly below, represent ongoing and current efforts to engage in the practice of Black digital humanities in today’s environments as well as learning contexts. It is our hope that these articles will offer insight into how scholars are defining Black Digital Humanities and attend to issues of technology from a Black lens.  </p>
         <p>The six articles that make up this special issue are organized into three distinct themes: Perspectives on Black Digital Humanities and its future; Centering Blackness in digital spaces; and Owning the stories and experiences of Black people. </p>
         <p>Debates in #BlackDH: Key Moments and Queer Directions in Black Studies Scholarship by Faithe J. Day situates the critical role of Black Digital Humanities (Black DH) at the intersection of identity and digital studies. Drawing on the histories of research and researchers within and outside Black Studies, the article shows how Black DH can expand by including Black feminist, queer, Black Queer Studies, and justice-oriented perspectives.  For the author, by engaging with the past, present, and future of Black Studies, the Black Digital Humanities will only continue to grow and spread through its own social and scholarly networks as a transformative assemblage of critical and queer work.  </p>
         <p>Bridging the gap of Exhibition Design, Instructional Design, and the Learning Sciences for the future of Black Digital Humanities by Rebecca Y. Bayeck in which the author examines the connection between Black digital humanities and fields such as the learning sciences, instructional design, and exhibition design. Focusing on key elements of these fields, this paper shows the relevance of these to the Black digital humanities. The author also argues that Black Digital Humanities has at its core principles and practices that call for equity and inclusion.  Finally, the author speaks to how the dialogue Black DH with the fields of learning sciences, instructional design, and exhibition design can create new frameworks for inclusion, design, and learning for all. </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Library Professionals: Instrumental in Black Digital Humanities by</hi> Jina DuVernay reflects on the current divide between library professionals and scholars in Black Digital Humanities. Drawing on her experience as a librarian, the author argues that bridging the gap between library professionals and Black Digital Humanities scholars will benefit scholars in the emerging field of Black Digital Humanities. Library professionals engage in digital humanities related projects; thus libraries and librarians can be the source that Black Digital Humanities scholars need to advance their work.   </p>
         <p>Decolonial by Design: Building Sekuru's Stories by Jennifer Kyker emerges from co-authored digital humanities project that contributes toward the decoloniality of knowledge through the music and oral histories of Zimbabwean mbira player Sekuru Tute Chigamba. Through the history of Sekuru, the author shows how digital humanities projects can serve as a tool to highlight and tell often unheard or ignored stories of Black people because of colonization.</p>
         <p>Community-Driven Linked Data Approaches in Builders &amp; Defenders: Nashville’s Historical Black Civil War Database by Angela Sutton and Jessica Fletcher is a co-authored paper that discusses the development of the database that collects biographical information on Black Civil War era population of Fort Negley in Tennessee. The authors in this piece reflect on the creation of this database which included critical collaboration with the community, and the intentional engagement in collective decisions and conversations with the descendants, public, academic historians, computer scientists, and software developers. The article centers Black people and their experiences and is an example of how centering Black voices, histories, and experiences, can offer fresh insights into the interpretations and meanings surrounding the history of Fort Negley. </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Infrastructural Sovereignty in the Black Atlantic</hi> by Dhanashree Thorat focuses on the June 2019 Google announcement of a new undersea fiber-optic cable line connecting Portugal and South Africa, it named ‘Equiano’ after Olaudah Equiano, an eighteenth-century Black man who was kidnapped from his Igbo village and sold into slavery. This article reads Google’s infrastructural initiative against the grain of Equiano’s autobiographical narrative to locate how the violent afterlives of slavery and colonialism manifest in and undergird Internet infrastructure projects today.</p>
         <p>The editors of this special issue hope our readers find value in the articles chosen and welcome any feedback. </p>
         <p>In conclusion, we want to recognize the contributions of several individuals who played crucial roles in the development of this special issue, especially Dr. Christa Williford and the staff of Digital Humanity Quarterly.</p>
         <p>References</p>
         <p>Aboagye, K. (2022). Restoring Black/Indigenous Relations in Australia. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Global Indigeneity</hi>, <hi rend="italic">6</hi>(1), 1-24. https://www.jstor.org/stable/48717560 </p>
         <p>Cramer, S., &amp; Tichenor, M. (2023). Collaboration and cross-pollination: teaching garden-based learning through PDS partnerships. PDS Partners: Bridging Research to Practice, 18(3), 191-202.</p>
         <p>Prince, A., &amp; Messina, C. M. (2022). Black Digital Humanities for the Rising Generation. <hi rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi>, <hi rend="italic">16</hi>(3).</p>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl/>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
