<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>
               <q>It May Change My Understanding of the Field</q>: Understanding Reading Tools for Scholars and Professional Readers</title>
            <author>Ray Siemens</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Ray <dhq:family>Siemens</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>siemens@uvic.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Ray Siemens (U Victoria) is Canada Research Chair in Humanities Computing and Professor of English at the University of Victoria with cross appointment in Computer Science. Siemens is also Visiting Senior Research Fellow at the Centre for Computing in the Humanities at King's College London, and Visiting Research Professor at Sheffield Hallam University.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <author>Cara Leitch</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Cara <dhq:family>Leitch</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>cmleitch@uvic.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Cara Leitch (U Victoria) is a PhD candidate in English and a Research Assistant at the Electronic Textual Cultures Lab.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <author>Analisa Blake</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Analisa <dhq:family>Blake</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Analisa Blake was a Graduate Research Assistant with the Electronic Textual Cultures Lab.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <author>Karin Armstrong</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Karin <dhq:family>Armstrong</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>karindar@uvic.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Karin Armstrong was Lab, Project, &amp; Resource Manager at the Electronic Textual Cultures Lab (ETCL), University of Victoria.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <author>John Willinsky</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>John <dhq:family>Willinsky</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of British Columbia/Stanford</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>john.willinsky@ubc.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>John Willinsky (UBC) is Pacific Press Professor of Literacy and Technology at the University of British Columbia and Principal Investigator of the Public Knowledge Project. </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000075</idno>
            <idno type="volume">003</idno>
            <idno type="issue">4</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2010-03-20">20 March 2010</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace" rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2009-11-10" who="Alyssa">initial encoding</change>
         <change when="2013-06-20" who="Tassie Gniady">Changed "dhq:caption" to "head."</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>As the amount of scholarly material published in digital form increases, there is growing pressure on content producers to identify the needs of expert readers and to create online tools that satisfy their requirements. Based on the results of a study conducted by the Public Knowledge Project and introduced at Digital Humanities 2006 (Siemens, Willinsky and Blake), continued and augmented since, this paper discusses the reactions of Humanities Computing scholars and graduate students to using a set of online reading tools. The results of our study reveal both the potential strengths and perceived weaknesses of online reading environments. Understanding how users read and evaluate research materials, anticipating users’ expectations of the reading tools and resources, and addressing user concerns about the availability of online material will lead to improvements in the design and features of online publishing.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>
               <q>Domain-Expert Readers Read for Context</q> and other observations from a study of PKP reading tools.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <q>It May Change My Understanding of the Field</q>: Understanding Reading Tools for Scholars and Professional Readers</head>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>In 2001, the Public Knowledge Project at the University of British Columbia began work on a series of <q>reading tools</q> under the direction of John Willinsky. These tools were intended to provide readers of online scholarly journal articles with access to relevant related materials. The reading tools (originally called Research Support Tools) were incorporated into the open source software designed to manage and publish journals being developed by the Public Knowledge Project. In concept, the tools draw on the sets of links that accompany the journal articles made available online by Highwire Press, PubMed, ScienceDirect, and other online journal portals. These links enable readers to find related studies and other papers by the authors, typically from within the portal’s database.</p>
            <p>In developing these tools, however, the goals of the Public Knowledge Project are somewhat broader than those of other journal sites. This follows directly from the project’s interest in supporting <emph>open access</emph> to research and scholarship through the development of open source software systems. Open access, after all, implies <emph>public</emph> access to a body of work. The Public Knowledge Project’s tools were intended not only to support scholars reading in their area of expertise, but also to support relatively inexperienced readers of research, including students, readers from other professions, and members of the public. For that reason, these tools were designed to draw on open access sources of scholarly work, as well as to connect the user to media, government, and other non-scholarly sources.</p>
            <p>This study examines the use of these reading tools by thirteen humanities computing
               scholars and graduate students. Our inquiry focuses on the degree to which, and the
               ways in which, such tools can contribute to the reading practices of
               domain-experts.<note>Additional studies are being conducted within the Public
                   Knowledge Project on the value of such tools for readers who are not domain
                   experts: e.g., Twomey, Willinsky and Quint-Rapoport, and Willinsky.</note> In the
               course of the study, readers were asked about the value of readily being able to
               check related studies not cited in the article; to examine work that has followed on
               the study reported in the article; to consider additional work that has been done by
               the same author; and to consult additional sources on the topic outside of the
               academic literature. The choice of humanities computing was based on the tendency of
               this field to bring together scholars with a strong understanding of critical textual
               practices as part of a humanities tradition along with a strong interest in new
               text-related systems. Those working in humanities computing have, for example, been
               active in creating a number of digital tools for textual analysis  (e.g., TaPOR) and
               other forms of research and scholarly work <ptr target="#schreibman2004"/>. This involvement in the conceptualization, design, and creation of  reading tools is one of the factors that distinguishes humanities computing scholars from their colleagues. Like all scholars in the humanities, domain-expert readers in humanities computing are concerned with acquiring, assessing, and building on existing research material. Where Humanities Computing scholars differ, however, is in their tendency to evaluate their own research and reading habits alongside their research material. Every act of reading becomes another opportunity for the researcher to refine his or her understanding of textual practices.</p>
            <p>Our interviews with domain-expert readers revealed that reading tools can make a definite, if limited, contribution to readers’ critical engagement with journal articles. Participants made it clear that the tools’ abilities to bring well-established, reputable scholarly sites within reach was an important benefit, given their apprehensions about the quality of materials available online. While the tools helped readers to position an article and its author in relation to other work in the field, participants felt the tools did little to further their comprehension or understanding of the article itself. This was largely because these readers already have critical methods and sources in place, which the tools were emulating with less-than-perfect accuracy or precision. These readers did see as much, if not more, value in these tools for their students in terms of helping them to evaluate an article and position it within a larger field. In sum, participants made it clear that reading tools could contribute to their reading of an academic article. The degree of usefulness of the tools depends on how well the tools can assist them in (a) evaluating and placing an author’s work within the larger field, (b) gaining a sense of that field from the online discussion of issues, (c) organizing the retention of the relevant research materials they encountered, and (d) taking full advantage of the library resources to which these readers have access.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Prior Studies</head>
            <p>The reading practices of expert readers have been the focus of a number of prior
                studies. The results of this study speak to aspects of domain-expert reading that
                have not been previously addressed. In particular, our analysis has been motivated
                by Sam Wineburg's claim that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#wineburg1991">to understand the
                    <q>historic sense</q>, we must study people as they engage in the
                    process of historical enquiry</quote>
                  <ptr target="#wineburg1991" loc="73"/>
               </cit>.
                The act of using the reading tools seemed to prompt participants to think about how
                they usually did things. During the course of our study, we found that participants
                spent as much time reporting about their own reading practices as they did
                commenting on the reading tools. The current literature largely focuses on
                comprehension strategies at the level of the article rather than on how readers
                develop their understanding of a field by positioning articles and authors within
                that field. For example, in a study with close parallels to this one, Wyatt et al.
                studied fifteen social science professors who, on choosing a journal article to
                read, provided a commentary on what they felt was important about their approach to
                reading the work <ptr target="#wyatt1993"/>. These readers drew upon a rich body of background knowledge to assist them in comprehending the article. The researchers found that these readers also had reading strategies that involved a continual process of anticipation and prediction. Their reading process called for self-regulation and self-monitoring as they jumped back and forth within the text in search of particular pieces of information, formed conclusions, evaluated research methods, assessed the quality of writing, and weighed the relevance of the topic. In this way, these readers tackled an article’s main ideas and tested the adequacy of its claims as part of a largely self-contained system.</p>
            <p>In a study that compared how historians and students read, Sam Wineburg notes that
                scholars possess <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#wineburg1991">knowledge of how to establish warrant and determine the validity
                of competing truth claims in a discipline</quote>
                  <ptr target="#wineburg1991" loc="83"/>
               </cit>. Wineburg also uses the example of a historian reading outside her own area of historical specialization to demonstrate that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#wineburg1991">her expertise lay not in what she knew, but in what she was able to do when she did not know</quote>
                  <ptr target="#wineburg1991" loc="83"/>
               </cit>. The sense is that these readers focused on utilizing reading strategies
                that determine the validity of the content in the text they are reading. In a later
                piece, Wineburg discusses how two historians engage in <quote rend="inline" source="#wineburg1998">the
                active processes of creating historical contexts</quote> to further their
                understanding of the history at issue, while the study reported here reveals an
                additional concern among domain-experts in actively establishing the disciplinary
                context within which to place what they are reading <ptr target="#wineburg1998" loc="339"/>.</p>
            <p>Pressley and Afflerbach report findings of particular relevance to this study, namely
                that skilled readers are <q>opportunistic</q> in the sense of being prepared to exploit
                all available textual clues (of which the reading tools might be thought to provide
                an additional set) while seeking to identify consistencies and inconsistencies
                between the text being read and their prior knowledge (which might be said to
                involve adjusting their evaluation of an author’s position within a field). In a
                similar vein, Patricia A. Alexander sums up the result of a number of studies of
               <quote rend="inline" source="#alexander2003">highly competent learners</quote> as demonstrating that these
                learners engage in a goal-directed behavior that is personally satisfying by
                bringing <quote rend="inline" source="#alexander2003">a body of relevant prior knowledge</quote> matched by <quote rend="inline" source="#alexander2003">a rich repertoire of both surface-level and deep processing strategies,</quote> again focused on comprehending the text being read. To this, our study would add the satisfaction gained by readers when they increase their hold on the larger field and those working within it. This focus on the comprehension of content from within the text has to do with the goals of this research, which involves helping novice readers improve their comprehension in school disciplines. It is often assumed that learning who is doing what within a field is of less importance to students than to expert readers. That may be an assumption worthy of further examination.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Reading Tool Design</head>
            <p>The reading tools developed by the Public Knowledge Project sit in a frame to the right of an article or a paper after it has been published using Open Journal Systems or Open Conference Systems. (The longer-term vision for the reading tools is that they would be able to serve other systems, as a browser plug-in or part of a library’s portal.) The tools are organized into two sets. The top set of tools provides information about the article itself: its authors, indexing information, the sponsors of the research, supplementary files accompanying the article, and definitions of unfamiliar words. There are also email links to contact the author or notify a colleague, as well as the ability to leave a comment on the article for other readers to consider.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure01">
               <head>An article abstract with reading tools listed to the right.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Screenshot
            of a sample article, with various reading tools in a sidebar on the right.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>The second set of tools, which appears below the first set, provides access to
                related items drawn principally from open access databases that do not require
                readers to belong to a particular research institution. These tools, which are
                subject specific in most cases, have been created in 19 disciplinary fields, from
                agriculture to social sciences, and have been designed so that journal editors can
                select the appropriate set for their journals. Each of the tools in this second set
                is made up of relevant searchable databases.<note>The tools and databases in this
                    second set were initially chosen and have been maintained by Chia-Ning Chiang, a
                    doctoral student in information science, as part of the Public Knowledge Project
                    team.</note> If the editor has selected the Humanities reading tools set, the
                Related Studies tool allows the reader to search The English Server, Voice of the
                Shuttle, NetSERF: The Internet Connection for Medieval Resources, and five other
                relevant databases.<note>The Humanities pose something of a challenge in terms of comprehensive searching, as the field lacks a <q>PubHum,</q> comparable to PubMed, as a single comprehensive database for searching the life sciences.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The second set of reading tools also includes tools that reach outside the scholarly community. These tools connect readers to government databases, newspapers and media sites, as well as to teaching sites aimed at a broad range of educational levels. These tools also provide a broader context for all readers, both lay and expert, by including material such as media coverage of a topic or subsequent development of related government policies. Although this material is directly applicable to a limited range of research, it might be of interest to researchers working in related areas.</p>
            <p>Another crucial factor in delivering relevant materials to readers is the accuracy
                and suitability of the search terms used by the reading tools. The search terms,
                which appear when the reader clicks on a reading tool, are based on the first two keywords provided by the author of the article. Readers can edit the terms, as well as substitute search terms that focus on a specific aspect of the article or a single concept within it. Still, the author’s keywords provide a strong starting point not only for the search, but also in identifying the intended thrust and focus of the work. As might be expected, the search conducted by the Author’s Work tool uses the name of the author (or authors), while the Definition tool uses any word that the reader selects in the body of the article.</p>
            <p>What these reading tools contribute to this new reading environment is an extension
                of the traditional <emph>paratexts</emph> that domain-experts are so adept at
                reading, such as the title page, copyright information, table of contents,
                footnotes, indexes, appendices, and references <ptr target="#stanitsek2005"/>. The
                paratexts of print have long contributed to strengthening the internal coherence of
                a text while also connecting the text to a greater body of work by identifying its
                position within a field. In the online world, one review of hypermedia studies
                suggests that the domain-experts’ greater command of the content means that they are
                interested in <quote rend="inline" source="#stanitsek2005">the location of detailed information related to
                specific entities,</quote> while non-expert readers are in need of a
                <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#chen2006">global picture of the material</quote>
                  <ptr target="#chen2006" loc="262"/>
               </cit>. This study suggests that, for domain-expert readers, the detailed information provided by reading tools is directed toward a more global picture of the field.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Method</head>
            <p>This study of the reading tools is concerned with their potential value to
                domain-expert readers in the field of Humanities computing. In designing the study,
                our goal was to recruit between 12–15 participants. Because of the small community
                within Humanities computing, several colleagues of the investigators were contacted
                via email to participate in the study. If an individual did not respond, a follow up
                email was sent. Fourteen Humanities academics from U Victoria and U British Columbia
                were eventually selected to participate in the study, ten during the initial
                recruitment and four more at a later stage of the project.<note>One interview was eliminated because of very poor sound quality in the interview recording and because the interview was incomplete.d</note> Respondents who were interested in participating in the study were sent a consent form via email to sign and return by mail or fax. At this time, respondents were also asked to recommend articles related to Humanities computing they might like to see in the test journal. A shortlist was created from these suggestions and PDF documents of each article were found or created. These PDFs were then placed in the OJS Humanities computing Test Journal that had been installed for research purposes on the local network using a PostGreSQL database.  Within the OJS test journal environment, the investigators were assigned roles as editors or managers. Each participant was manually enrolled in the system and sent email notification of his or her user name and password (which could be changed by the participant). This username and password allowed participants to use any of the reading tools that involved email, such as Send Link to Colleague. The test journal was then placed under a second level of password protection that would prevent the public from being able to access the copyright protected documents.</p>
            <p>With a few exceptions, the interviews were conducted in the participants’ private
                offices on their personal computers. In cases where the participants did not have a
                private office, interviews were held in a quiet public computer lab. During the
                interviews, the participants were asked whether or not they had been able to spend
                some time reading an article and exploring the reading tools before the interview. 
                After returning to the article they read on the OJS, participants were taken through
                the reading tools one by one and asked a question, or series of questions, regarding
                the tool’s value in enhancing their understanding of the article, evaluating the
                quality of an article, and providing materials for use in teaching or research. The interviews were summarized and the response to each tool categorized as either positive or negative. These responses were placed in a matrix<note>The matrix is available with this article.</note> with, where possible, supporting extracts from the associated interview.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Results</head>
            <p>We have organized the results of the interviews around a number of themes that
                emerged in the course of this study. These themes speak both to participants’
                reading processes and to the potential value of the tools.</p>
            <div>
               <head>Domain-Expert Readers Read for Context</head>
               <p>Most participants felt that the About the Author and Author’s Work tools helped
                    them to evaluate the article they read by providing them with a basis for
                    judging the position and contribution of the author. While a number of
                    participants did recognize the author of the article they were reading, ten
                    participants commented that if they did not recognize an author’s name, they would be interested in gaining more information about the author’s background and current research activities. Ten participants commented specifically on the usefulness of the About the Author tool in evaluating the article, and author, in question. Seven users also commented favorably on the Author’s Work tool. While these domain-expert readers clearly trust their own judgment of an article, they are also interested in checking those judgments against easily ascertained signs or markers of expertise in the author’s record. When using About the Author, a participant pointed out, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">it can lend credibility to the article knowing who the author is, because – and for me specially this is an area that I don't know – I know the big names but I didn't know for example [this author’s] name before reading this article</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P5</ref>
                  </cit>. In response to the Author’s Work tool, this participant stressed the importance of the venue in which the work was published but this was not the participant’s only concern: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">It’s a question of credibility and knowing what he's working on. And the fact that he's published in other respectable venues[;] that he's somebody that does interesting stuff. I mean just reading a rather long abstract told me that . . . this is a guy who is doing important work</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P5</ref>
                  </cit>. This telling comment reflects how a domain-expert reader arrives at a judgment by working through multiple signals, from the name-recognition of the journal to the careful assessment of an abstract from one of the author’s other pieces. Two other participants <ref type="offline">P3 and P9</ref> commented that they were more likely to look to the abstract than the metadata for certain kinds of information, such as keywords. It is worth noting that the abstract is a rather recent phenomenon in humanities journals (given this field’s reliance on the literary tradition of the essay rather than the writing up of an experiment). This participant’s ability to conduct a relatively quick check on the overall quality of the author’s work, with the help of <quote rend="inline" source="#private">a rather long abstract,</quote> speaks to the potential value of the abstract to the creation of indexing information when the full text is not available.</p>
               <p>Paying attention to the <quote rend="inline" source="#private">respectable venues</quote> in which
                    authors publish proved a common theme across a number of tools that involve
                    searching the journal literature, including the Related Studies, Databases, and
                    other tools. Eight participants commented on publication venue as being a factor
                    in their evaluation of the author’s article and other works. It became very
                    apparent that where an article is published matters a good deal to these
                    readers. Initially, a journal’s peer-review process provided domain-expert
                    readers with a pre-review and preliminary screening. And this pre-review – that
                    is, prior to readers coming to their own judgment about an article – becomes all the more reliable through the readers’ rating and rankings of journals within their field.<note>Those working in the humanities are less likely than those in the sciences to track the ISI Web of Science citation index, which ranks journals within fields by their Impact Factor, based on the average number of times an article is cited across two years of a journal’s publication. Many journals in the sciences advertise their impact factor, with authors closely attending to this ranking process, in the belief that it will affect the take-up of their work.</note> These readers place a great deal of emphasis on the journal’s assessment of an article when performing their own evaluation: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">I evaluate quality and significance partly by where things appear, which is the major problem that online publishing has</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P1</ref>
                  </cit>.</p>
               <p>The growth of online publishing has challenged many of the assumptions readers
                    hold about <quote rend="inline" source="#private">where things appear.</quote> Peer-reviewed work
                    is appearing in new sort of a journal (e.g., <title rend="italic">Borderlands
                    eJournal: New Spaces in the Humanities</title>; <title rend="italic">Computing in the Humanities Working Papers</title>). This new realm may pose a challenge to domain-expert readers who have been trained within a print culture: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">Personally, I have [a] fair amount of skepticism of what's available there on the web unless I'm quite familiar with the sites and if they're discipline specific and created by academic institution or trusted institutions</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P12</ref>
                  </cit>. There’s reason enough for such skepticism. This wariness only adds to the work of arriving at a judgment about the article being read, as well as to the chance that one is wasting one’s time with it.</p>
               <p>The problem of online credibility has been compounded, particularly in the case
                    of the humanities, by the relative slowness with which the standard journals in
                    this field have become available on the Web. Many in the humanities today
                    continue to believe that <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">online publication is still
                    having real trouble getting accepted as... first rank</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P1</ref>
                  </cit>.
                    Fortunately, journal-hosting services such as Project Muse are now providing
                    online access to a greater proportion of the peer-reviewed literature in the
                    humanities even as the journals also remain in print for the present
                    time.<note>Project Muse is a division of the Johns Hopkins University Press in
                        collaboration with The Milton S. Eisenhower Library and currently offers
                        over <quote rend="inline" source="#http://muse.jhu.edu/">300 high quality humanities, arts, and social
                        sciences journals from 60 scholarly publishers,</quote> according to its
                        website, <ref target="http://muse.jhu.edu/">http://muse.jhu.edu/</ref>.</note> Eventually, scholars will be able to settle back into their trusted ranking schemes. In the meantime, it is clear that the reading tools need to do more to identify the standards that govern its sources, as noted by one of the participants:
                    <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#private">What is peer-reviewed or not, we're not always sure. What is a good article or not in the field, it's very hard to define – much of it is . . . either password protected [or requires] pay. So, it's difficult to find and get to certain resources that might help me evaluate this article. Certainly, you can get to tools that might help to analyze this article, but evaluate – that's really a knowledge issue, not much of a tools issue.</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P12</ref>
                  </cit>
                    The participant’s point is well taken. The actual evaluation of the article
                    depends not on the tools but on the reader’s knowledge and experience. This
                    point was reinforced by yet another participant in the study, who concluded that
                    using the reading tools <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">reinforced an opinion [he]
                        already [has] that throwing automated processes at text is not very
                        valuable. Whereas having humans read text and make judgments and decisions
                        about them is a) useful [and] b) what we're supposed to be doing</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P9</ref>
                  </cit>. However, it might be noted that as the reading tools provide
                    readers with related open-access peer-reviewed articles, the tools augment
                    rather than hinder the reader’s ability to <quote rend="inline" source="#private">[make] judgments
                    and decisions</quote> about the work being read. Of course, more can be done to enable readers to gather background information readily on the sources used in the reading tools. As one participant pointed out, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">that's what people check, they check editorial boards to see if they recognize the names and if they seem to be people from well known places</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P1</ref>
                  </cit>.</p>
               <p>The reading tools link to information about each database in order to provide readers with the means to evaluate each source. This link takes the reader to the database’s homepage where in many, but not all, cases readers can discover more about how materials have been selected to be included in the database. While the About link works to describe the database, information about individual journals must come from other sources. Many online journals, however, carry with them the authority attached to their print-based origins.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Domain-Expert Readers Discuss Their Reading</head>
               <p>For all their apprehensions about the status of online publishing, readers
                    expressed support for other web-based means of communication such as online
                    forums where scholars can gather for informal exchanges and commentaries. In the
                    humanities, online discussions through such services as H-Net have long been a
                    vital part of the field’s use of online resources. The Online Forums tool
                    directed readers to discussions thematically related to the article they read.
                    Participants considered online forums to be more current and less <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">stilted</quote> 
                     <ref type="offline">P4</ref>
                  </cit> than other publication venues. Regardless
                    of the article’s publication date, the reading tools allow readers to tap into
                    the most current discussions of the article’s themes as well as any archived conversations. Online discussions reassured readers that they are part of a community. One participant commented, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">you're not alone in front of your computer and that's why I like all these sites where you can comment and you can add and so on . . . it’s very good to be part of a community on the internet</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P6</ref>
                  </cit>. Another participant noted that this tool provided access to a level of engaged and incisive discourse that could not be found in the journals and described the value of such timely and current discussion in the evaluative process: 
                    <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#private">There's open discussion and informal discussion on a wide variety of areas that you just won't find in some of the other academic publications . . .. It'll give you some insight on academic questions around the discipline that again you may not find in formal academic publications. So I think the Forums give you, in some ways, a more cutting edge insight into the people involved in the discipline, the things that are occupying them right now versus their book that published two years ago, three years ago, and who is within the community.</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P12</ref>
                  </cit>
                    This participant made a connection between comprehending an article and
                    understanding a field. The reader commented that seeing <quote rend="inline" source="#private">other works by the author,</quote> as well as coming across
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#private">other people and disciplines who might be discussing works
                    of this kind</quote> and <quote rend="inline" source="#private">discussions or arguments for
                    this particular topic</quote> in online discussion forums would <quote rend="inline" source="#private">help you to understand your article</quote> before concluding
                    that <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">the more that you can find within this context .
                        . . the more you will learn about the discipline and the more you are able
                        to fit this article within that context</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P12</ref>
                  </cit>. The community
                    nature of an online forum could help users understand both articles and the
                    field by fostering a dialogue with other researchers in the field, as they might
                    take a moment to add to the discussion as a result of their current
                    reading.<note>Not everyone participating in the study had an accurate notion of how online forums were being used, as one participant suggested that particle physics researchers <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#private">don’t publish articles, they just go [to] online forums</quote>
                        <ref type="offline">P4</ref>
                     </cit>, thinking in all likelihood of <ref target="http://arxiv.org">http://arxiv.org</ref>, where particle physicists post their working papers, pre-prints, and post-prints, with such a level of daily activity among them on the site, including the posting of comments, that it must seem like an extended forum.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Despite the favourable comments on online discussions, opinions on the Comment
                    tool, which enables readers to leave comments on the article they were reading,
                    were mixed. Five participants felt that being able to read opinions from other
                    readers would be beneficial. One participant noted that leaving a comment could <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">create a scholarly conversation</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P5</ref>
                  </cit>. Six participants, however, were skeptical as to how often they would use such a feature. As one participant noted, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">I would very rarely want to bother making comments unless there's an active discussion already going on or there is likely to be an active discussion going on. I think the idea of accumulating layer after layer [of] interpretive, reactive stuff around articles is a bit, I mean it sounds cute, but how much of that stuff would anybody ever wade through in real life?</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P9</ref>
                  </cit>. In a similar vein, while most participants seemed willing to email the author of an article with ideas they had about the work, the built-in Email Author tool was not felt to be necessary. One user, for example, commented that he would expect to find that link at the end of the author’s biography rather than as a separate tool <ref type="offline">P12</ref>. Another participant suggested the possible use of an <q>add comment</q> feature that is configured to notify the author through email <ref type="offline">P4</ref>, revealing a familiarity with content management software that is increasingly common.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Domain-Expert Readers Are Teachers</head>
               <p>A number of participants commented on the value of the reading tools for teachers
                    and students. One participant stated, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">I can see that
                        some of these tools might be more useful to a student, than they would be to
                        somebody who already has a fair understanding of the field</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P3</ref>
                  </cit>. Another participant noted, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">if I’m using [an article] for teaching . . . I like to put it in a larger context. So then [the Literary Critics tool] would help me relate it to other materials and to show how it was evaluated by other people</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P10</ref>
                  </cit>. Other participants praised the Literary Critics tools as a valuable resource for students looking for supplementary material. One commented, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">it’s often very difficult to find good secondary references especially in a field like Humanities computing that’s growing and in essence the last body of work [made digital] is criticism</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P12</ref>
                  </cit>, while another felt that <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">being able to click on and find the other works of an author, the critic, that they’re interested in is extremely helpful [for students]. And it helps [students] realize the scholarly context in which the person is working</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P5</ref>
                  </cit>. Finally, a participant felt that access to dissertations would be of value to students who could use them to find out what research is currently being done in an area without waiting until the work reaches a published state <ref type="offline">P2</ref>.</p>
               <p>Students were also seen as the major beneficiaries of the Define Terms and
                    Dictionaries tools, which allow readers to look up individual terms in online sources: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">I loved the [Define Terms] tool for student reading of academic writing and I would find that a wonderful tool, and I think I might really enjoy it for myself too in reading a more technically complex article</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P3</ref>
                  </cit>. There was also a relatively rare instance of a participant seeing a crossover value for the tools between domain-expert and non-expert readers. For example, a second participant made it clear that she had already worked out a way to define terms readily online, but that these reading tools would benefit students <ref type="offline">P6</ref>.</p>
               <p>The question of scholarly quality and restricted access was raised again,
                    pointing to expert readers’ emphasis on open access to research tools: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">All
                        you can do [with the Define Terms tool] is search Miriam [sic] Webster which is
                        not a particularly good dictionary...if I were looking up a word, I
                        would go to the <title rend="italic">OED</title> [<title rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</title>] online which my university
                        has access to</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P1</ref>
                  </cit>. The same participant expressed similar concerns about the Dictionaries tool (which should rightly be renamed the Encyclopedia tool as was pointed out by P10), making it clear that the range of reference material made possible by library subscriptions was far superior to what was currently available through the reading tools. This shortcoming in the reading tool’s ability to take full advantage of these readers’ online resources is now in the process of being addressed.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Domain-Expert Readers Have Reading Methods</head>
               <p>As domain-expert readers, participants exhibited techniques for augmenting and
                    supporting the judgments they make about what they are reading. Some were
                    already in the habit of turning to Google and Google Scholar. One asked,
                    <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">rather than bothering going through all the separate
                        tools [if] I wanted to find out books on the same topic, why wouldn’t I just
                        go to Google Scholar and be done with it?</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P7</ref>
                  </cit>. A
                    second participant put it plainly: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">[rather than use the Author’s Works tool] I would have done actually something simpler than going through all these searches . . . I would have gone through to Google Scholar or the online catalogue or library</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P6</ref>
                  </cit>. Finally, a third participant commented, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">so it's just giving me a different way of searching</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P2</ref>
                  </cit>. The value of the tools for the domain-expert reader would seem particularly limited for those possessing more than a modicum of web savvy. Participants with less web experience were correspondingly less likely to compare the reading tools to Google. For them, however, the tools posed their own technical challenges. One participant commented that despite wanting <quote rend="inline" source="#private">to be really positive here,</quote> we had to recognize that introducing these tools was <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">just making [his] life more difficult</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P3</ref>
                  </cit>.</p>
               <p>However, the participant who felt the tools just provided a different way of
                    searching, which she knew how to do well enough, went on to pose something of a
                    challenge for the design and reach of the tools. She pointed out that the tools
                    did not open up new ways of reading for her; they were <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">a useful idea, but it doesn't change my perception of what's
                        possible</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P2</ref>
                  </cit>. This prospect of changing the
                    domain-expert readers’ sense of connections and contexts had been a hope with
                    the tools. The change was intended in particular through the tools that
                    connected the research article to government policies, media stories and
                    instruction sites, and that connect readers to these themes in a focused way
                    that is often difficult to obtain from broad Google searches. While none of these participants identified the Media Stories and Government Policy tools as particularly useful to their own research, which is understandable in most cases – <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">there's nothing in the government of Canada archives that's relevant to me on… Chaucer's text, right?</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P1</ref>
                  </cit> – four participants saw these tools as being of potential use to researchers in other fields. At least one participant recognized the value of these tools for the very difference it introduced: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">I think that the media report, or the notion of having media articles there to see what the kind of public or the press is saying about the area is useful because it gives a very different perspective</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P2</ref>
                  </cit>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Domain-Expert Readers Generate Search Terms</head>
               <p>Nine of the participants commented on the inadequacy of the provided search
                    terms. These terms, you may recall, are normally drawn from the first two
                    keywords the author provides for indexing the work in the process of submitting
                    it to the journal, but in this case they were based on our reading of the
                    article. Participants felt the terms provided were either too general to be
                    useful or were actually misleading. In addition, one of the distinguishing
                    features of domain-expert readers reading in their own field is how they <quote rend="inline" source="#afflerbach1990">automatically constructed the main idea significantly more
                        often when reading texts about familiar topics,</quote> which is to say that
                    they are capable of generating very accurate keyword searches on their own <ptr target="#afflerbach1990" loc="43"/>.</p>
               <p>One participant commented on the lack of focus in the search terms: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">The key words both in the search scenario and in the metadata
                    material I found almost too broad to be of assistance with this particular
                    article</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P2</ref>
                  </cit>. Another observed that viewing the metadata provided
                    for her article <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">[explained] why most of the search
                        tools later on failed as [abysmally] as they did, because it’s improperly
                        categorized</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P1</ref>
                  </cit>. This participant added,
                    <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">the
                            direct link [to Google from the OJS] isn’t so useful because the search
                            terms in his case probably wouldn’t be the ones I’d choose to use
                            anyways</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P1</ref>
                  </cit>. What needs to be noted here is that readers,
                    before clicking <q>search</q> with any of the reading tools, are able to edit, delete or add search terms. Apart from overlooking this feature of the tools, one participant did go on to suggest that we should incorporate metadata automatically generated from the words used in the article <ref type="offline">P4</ref>.<note>This comparison of language is a feature that Google Scholar uses to find <q>related articles,</q> along with co-citation and other comparative aspects, with an ability to use Google Scholar’s <q>related articles</q> to be incorporated into a later version of the reading tools.</note> Another felt it was the responsibility of professional cataloguers to read each article and determine categories and key words <ref type="offline">P5</ref>, which would greatly increase the accuracy of the reading tools, without question, while adding to the expense of running a journal.</p>
               <p>Certainly, there is more that can be done to improve the indexing of the
                    articles, and thus the precision of the searches. The journals' editors are able
                    to provide authors with examples of indexing terms specific to their field, and they have the option of including a link to a thesaurus (e.g., ERIC Thesaurus in education) or classification scheme (e.g., Mathematics Subject Classification) that can further guide authors. It is in the authors’ self-interest to learn more about how to accurately index their work. Another approach would be to draw on <q>folksonomy</q> tagging – used with blogs and social networking websites – in which readers can collaboratively suggest indexing terms for a work. These indexing terms can be used to create a word cloud which reflects the frequency with which each tag is used. Readers using the tools would then select tags or indexing terms from the cloud as their search terms.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Domain-Expert Readers Check References</head>
               <p>One feature of reading research articles online that the project did not yet have
                    in place when this study was conducted was found to be basic to the work done by
                    researchers reading journal articles. Researchers check the works which the author references not only to see if the reference has been quoted and otherwise treated fairly, but because the references to an article provide one of the best sources of additional information on the topic. The reading tools operate independently of the article’s references in the sense that the reading tools find related materials that have appeared after the article was published and that are potentially from a greater variety of perspectives on a topic than the list of references that an author assembles in writing an article.</p>
               <p>Nonetheless, one participant in this study pointed out the value of having
                    similar sorts of links from the reference in the article to the work referenced
                    in the context of teaching a class on the original article: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">[If] you have one
                    text and the author is comparing it to another . . . you might zip over to have
                    a look at the other text to see whether you want to discuss that one as well</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P14</ref>
                  </cit>.<note>In the next release of the journal software, Open Journal Systems, journals will be able to link an author’s references to the article the author has cited through a number of strategies. The simplest of these is, in fact, a reading tool that takes the title of the cited article and feeds it into Google Scholar, a strategy that holds out the possibility for readers who do not have library access that there may be an open access copy of the article available online.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Domain-Expert Readers Access Research Libraries</head>
               <p>What became very clear from our interviews with the participants is that offering
                    them the best of what was available in an open access format for their field
                    fell well short of what they were used to, even in online environments. As
                    faculty members and graduate students at research universities, they were able
                    to log into their library’s online resources from their offices and their homes,
                    not to mention hotel rooms and airports. As a result, some participants compared
                    the databases offered by the reading tools to those available through their
                    library’s subscription: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">There are much better tools
                    than the ones that are included [in the reading tools]. Now, if this included the MLA, then sure it would be useful, it’s just that right now, the tools that are there aren’t the ones that would give a complete listing of his work</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P1</ref>
                  </cit>. One participant summed up the reading tools’ open access limits this way: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">I think it’s an insurmountable problem . . . until this stuff really becomes free, because everything that’s free is incomplete . . . and I care about complete</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P1</ref>
                  </cit>. Dissertation Abstracts International, <title rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</title>, and Project Muse were among the other subscription services that the participants felt were sorely lacking from the reading tools, given their dependence on open access databases. Another participant questioned the choice of the Internet Public Library as the only resource accessed by the Literary Critics tool and wondered why journal databases were not included <ref type="offline">P2</ref>.</p>
               <p>However, there is a solution to this problem. To address this obvious and
                    substantial shortcoming for domain-expert readers, the project is developing an OpenURL framework for the tools. This is what Google Scholar has done, enabling faculty members and students to register their library with Google Scholar, which then, with each search, identifies the items found that are in the library. It will take an extra step, but then so does logging into one’s library from a remote location. The result will be, to use the words of one participant, a <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">comprehensive list [with] an indication of which items I can get at my desktop, and which ones I actually have to go to the library for</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P1</ref>
                  </cit>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Domain-Expert Readers Care About Access</head>
               <p>At least a few of the participants showed great sensitivity to the access
                    question. They were interested in providing a way for more than just scholars
                    and students to be able to take advantage of these scholarly resources. That is,
                    they were supporters of the <emph>open access</emph> movement in scholarly
                    publishing: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">What I'd hope [is] that . . . you could
                        get academics hooked into the system so they'd publish copyright free
                        articles under this system[;] in that [sense,] information will be free</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P4</ref>
                  </cit>. Another participant drew the distinction of the university’s obligation to the larger public, within the economic reality of publishing: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">I'm very sensitive to the notion that publishing, even electronically, can cost money… but we're also working in a university environment where what we're doing is usually made available to the public; . . . the fact that I couldn't get this for free anywhere at all is problematic to me, philosophically speaking</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P5</ref>
                  </cit>. This participant also stated on using this tool that <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">I think most of us . . . have a preference for . . . stuff that’s open…. I don’t object to having it on here and if people do want to pay I guess they ought to be able to [but] at the same time I would hate to encourage this sort of thing</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P5</ref>
                  </cit>. There were also participants who responded negatively to the Pay-Per-View tool, which was the name of the only non-open access tool included among the reading tools: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">I’d probably have to be pretty desperate to use [the Pay-Per-View tool] . . . even if we click on it, we don’t seem to be getting very much</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P3</ref>
                  </cit>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Domain-Expert Readers Organize their Readings</head>
               <p>As this was the participants’ first experience with the reading tools and there were limits to how thoroughly the use of the tools could be reasonably explained to them, there were times when what the tools could do were misunderstood. Still, these misunderstandings provide insights into domain-experts’ reading habits: 
                    <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#private">I have my own way of organizing my information on my screen and one of the things would be to bookmark something. . . . so if I lose my ability to bookmark, because I'm within this window that's not giving me those features, then I can't save for myself a lot of material that I would want to be able to come back to.</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P2</ref>
                  </cit>
                    The ability to bookmark the databases provided by the reading tools, as well as
                    the individual articles found within any one database, could have been done at any point by using the browser’s Bookmark feature, which of course operates independently of the reading tools. Still, this participant’s interest in archiving and organizing the results of reading-tool searches does suggest that more could be done to facilitate this process. In an earlier version of the reading tools, readers could establish an online archive in which an article’s metadata could be stored, whether readers were on their own computers or not. Highwire Press includes a Personal Archive link for articles as part of, for example, the <title rend="italic">New England Journal of Medicine</title>. The point is that domain-expert readers are always in the process of building resources as a result of their reading. These readers keep an eye on the long-term utilization of the knowledge they encounter.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>In Sum, Domain-Expert Readers Map Meaning and Value</head>
               <p>What this study makes clear in relation to earlier studies of the cognitive
                    processes that domain-expert readers apply to reading within their domain is
                    that this reading process includes positioning and assessing the author and his
                    or her ideas in relation to the larger field. The reader follows the flow of
                    ideas within the article, all the while mapping and judging those ideas in
                    relation to work with which they are already familiar and new work they have
                    encountered through the reading tools. The judgment side of this process relies
                    on finely tuned measures of hierarchical ranking. These measures are
                    continuously recalibrated as the reader evaluates the author’s other work, where
                    the author’s work is published, the author’s institutional affiliation, and
                    other external factors. This aspect of the reading process is aided by the use
                    of the reading tools, much as the field-mapping and evaluative footnote championed by Edward Gibbon aided readers during the Enlightenment.<note>Consider Keith Windschuttle’s celebration of a new Penguin 3-volume edition of Gibbon’s <title rend="italic">History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</title> for, among other things, including all of the original footnotes: <quote rend="inline" source="#windschuttle1997">Gibbon uses his footnotes not only to source his references but also to make lengthy, sometimes acrimonious, sometimes witty, commentaries on the veracity of both his primary and secondary sources. (A sample: <quote rend="inline" source="#windschuttle1997">The Dissertation of M. Biet seems to have been justly preferred to the discourse of his more celebrated competitor, the Abbé le Boeuf, an antiquarian, whose name was happily expressive of his talents.</quote>).</quote>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Within the scope of this domain-expert reading process, a number of tools, such
                    as Author’s Work, Author Bio, and Related Studies, have proven capable of
                    providing additional, readily accessible indicators or signals of the potential
                    value of article they are reading. If not in every case, some readers used the
                    tools to consult a number of sources, virtually on the fly, without losing sight, as it were, of the original article they were reading. Once having read the article, they may have come to reassess the initial judgments made on the basis of what they found through Author Bio and Author’s Work. However, constant self-reflection is what distinguishes such readers <ptr target="#wyatt1993"/>. Still, we should not assume that acts of reading scholarly articles always coincide with making sense of disciplinary fields, even for domain-experts. One participant drew this very distinction between comprehending the article and learning more about the field: <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#private">I read an article and I understand it . . . finding out more doesn't change my understanding of the article. It may change my understanding of the field, which is a bit different</quote>
                     <ref type="offline">P1</ref>
                  </cit>. The participant’s reflections reiterate the interest of such readers in learning about who is doing what and where. This added contextual material makes for a complex reading, learning, and evaluation process.</p>
               <p>For the domain-expert reader, learning to read a field means attaching ideas to
                    people and vice versa. It means doing so within an evaluative framework that
                    critically identifies not only who is associated with whom, but also which ideas
                    are most promising and which are passé. These readers fix ideas to people, as
                    well as to particular works, in part because this is necessary for utilizing the
                    ideas within their writing and teaching; they are distinguished as readers, in
                    other words, by their adherence to rules of attribution and to notions of
                    intellectual propriety and property. Further design work on the reading tools,
                    as has been suggested above, will seek to improve the tools’ ability to assist
                    domain-expert readers in learning more about the author and the work being read.
                    The tools seek to augment, however slightly, these readers’ deep knowledge of
                    how their field is structured. In this way, the tools are intended to extend
                    these readers’ critical engagement with their field of expertise.<note>While
                        this evaluative cataloging of people and ideas is not something that applies
                        to those reading outside of their domain-expertise, we have found in other
                        studies that a knowledge of the author also plays its part. For example, the
                        author’s background played an important role in the reading of non-expert
                        readers, in terms of the prestige of the institution they work for, we found
                        with policymakers <ptr target="#willinsky2003"/>, while the name
                        recognition from appearances at conferences came up in our research with
                        Registered Massage Therapists and chiropractors <ptr target="#willinsky2007"/>.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusions</head>
            <p>We believe that with this new publishing medium comes an opportunity and an
                obligation. That is, it falls to researchers of the digital transformation of text
                to experiment with how online reading environments can extend more readers’ critical engagement with text. The focus here, we would reiterate, is not on all forms of reading or all types of texts. The reading tools described here are not intended, for example, to diminish or displace what is achieved through <emph>close reading</emph>, as a major contribution of the humanities to scholarship. The reading environment at issue in this study, and in our related work, is that of the scholarly research article published in the online edition of a journal. What is clear is that journals have moved online. Although access is still limited, these journal articles are now open to an increasing number of readers. By providing a greater context for the reading of a given article, we can support the critical engagement of domain-experts, as well as increase the comprehension and interest of those reading outside their areas of expertise.</p>
            <p>One participant in this study stressed the importance of reaching out to those
                working in the humanities in rethinking how we will read online, because of their
                very expertise in this area: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#private">The people who need to work
                  at this, need to be people who are very familiar with the book and its possibilities. . . . And a lot of those people . . . [are] staying away. Because they are familiar with the book and its possibilities and they don’t really want to look at this</quote>
                  <ref type="offline">P2</ref>
               </cit>. At the same time, there was at least one participant in the study who was also imagining the possibilities for an improved reading environment. It took the form, for him, of a <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#private">highly developed information management forum that would incorporate a lot of these tools, but would really be towards . . . a kind of dialogue, a collective development of knowledge</quote>
                  <ref type="offline">P4</ref>
               </cit>. Reading often leads to the formation of communities (which is one way of very briefly encapsulating the history of the university). Changes in reading habits and practices, on this scale, are not going to proceed in a simple or straightforward way; they are also not going to be dictated by website designs or research results.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Appendix 1</head>
            <p>This appendix contains the full text of a report on the results of a study funded by the Canadian Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council, entitled <title rend="italic">A Study of Professional Reading Tools for Computing Humanists</title>.  </p>
            <p>
               <emph>Executive Summary:</emph> A good deal of the emerging research literature concerned with online 
                information resources focuses on information retrieval, which is concerned 
                with the use of search engines to locate desired information. Far less 
                attention has been paid to how the found materials are read and how that 
                critical engagement can be enhanced in online reading environments. This 
                paper reports on a study examining the question of whether a set of well- 
                designed reading tools can assist humanities computing scholars in 
                comprehending, evaluating and utilizing the research literature in their area. 
                Thirteen computing humanists were interviewed regarding their experience 
                using the reading tools. They were asked which tools, if any, and to what 
                degree, these tools contribute to their comprehension, evaluation, and 
                interest in utilizing the work they are reading. Responses varied widely 
                among users but it was found that overall, the reading tools had the 
                potential to lead to a variety of useful additional materials that would help 
                one come to a better understanding of a particular article. The reading tools 
                were deemed to be an exceptionally good resource for students or beginners 
                in the field. Participants also identified several issues with the tools 
                themselves and the web as a whole that affect the online reading and 
                research experience.</p>
            <p>
               <ref target="resources/images/appendix1.pdf">Download PDF</ref> (864 pages).</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Appendix 2</head>
            <p>This appendix contains the original interview data on which this article is based. The source files are provided both as a compressed archive containing the original NVivo files, and also as plain text.</p>
            <p>Download the interviews: <ref target="resources/source/appendix2a.txt">as plain text</ref>, <ref target="resources/source/appendix2b.zip">as a ZIP archive</ref>, <ref target="resources/source/appendix2b.tgz">as a tar archive</ref>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label="">
         
     </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="afflerbach1990" label="Afflerbach 1990" key="afflerbach1990">Afflerbach, Peter P. <title rend="quotes">The Influence of Prior Knowledge on Expert Readers' Main Idea Construction Strategies.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Reading Research Quarterly</title> 25.1 (1990): 31-46.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="alexander2003" label="Alexander 2003" key="alexander2003">Alexander, P. A. <title rend="italic">Expertise and Academic Development: A New Perspective on a Classic Theme</title>. Invited keynote address to the Biennial meeting of the European Association for the Research on Learning and Instruction (EARLI). Padova, Italy. August 2003.</bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="chen2006" label="Chen, Jing-Ping &amp; Macredie 2006" key="chen2006a">Chen, S., F. Jing-Ping, and R. Macredie. <title rend="quotes">Navigation
         in Hypermedia Learning Systems: Experts vs. Novices.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Computers in Human Behavior</title> 22.2 (2006): 251-266.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kopak2006" label="Kopak 2006" key="kopak2006">Kopak, Rick, and Chiang Chiang. <title rend="italic">Linking and Thinking: The Use of Typed Informational
     Relationships in Aid of Semantic Navigation</title>. Paper presented at ASIS&amp;T Annual Meeting, Austin, November 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pressley1995" label="Pressley 1995" key="pressley1995">Pressley, M., and P. Afflerbach. Verbal Protocols of Reading: The Nature of Constructively Responsive Reading. Hillsdale NJ: Erlbaum, 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schreibman2004" label="Schreibman, Siemens &amp; Unsworth 2004" key="schreibman2004">Schreibman, Susan, Ray Siemens, and
         John M. Unsworth, eds. <title rend="italic">A Companion to Digital Humanities</title>. Oxford, UK: Blackwell, 2004.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="siemens2010" label="Siemens et al. 2010" key="siemens2010a">Siemens, Ray, Analisa Blake, Cara Leitch, Karin
         Armstrong, John Willinsky, et al.  <title rend="italic">A Study of Professional Reading
         Tools for Humanists</title>. ETCL (Appendix 2 to this publication). 864 pp. Formerly at
         <ptr target="http://etcl-dev.uvic.ca/public/pkp_report/"/>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stanitsek2005" label="Stanitsek 2005" key="stanitsek2005">Stanitsek, Geog. <title rend="quotes">Texts and Paratexts in Media.</title> Trans. Ellen Klien. <title rend="italic">Critical Inquiry</title> 32.1 (2005): 27-42.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rockwell2011b" label="Rockwell 2011b" key="rockwell2011b">Text Analysis Portal for Research(TAPoR). Geoffrey
         Rockwell, project leader. <ptr target="http://www.tapor.ca/"/>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="twomey2007" label="Twomey 2007" key="twomey2007">Twomey, Sarah. <title rend="italic">Teacher Centered Professionalism: A Teacher Reading Group and New Forms of Access to Knowledge From a Feminist Perspective</title>. Unpublished dissertation, University of British Columbia, 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="willinsky2003" label="Willinsky 2003" key="willinsky2003">Willinsky, J. <title rend="quotes">Policymakers’ Use of Online Academic Research.</title> Education Policy Analysis Archives11.2, 2003, <ptr target="http://epaa.asu.edu/epaa/v11n2/"/>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="willinsky2007" label="Willinsky &amp; Quint-Rapoport 2007" key="willinsky2007">Willinsky, John and Mia Quint-Rapoport.
         <title rend="quotes">How Complementary and Alternative Medicine Practitioners Use
         PubMed</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Medical Internet Research</title>, 9.2
         (2007) <ptr target="http://www.jmir.org/2007/2/e19"/>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="windschuttle1997" label="Windschuttle 1997" key="windschuttle1997">Windschuttle, Keith. <title rend="quotes">Edward Gibbon and the Enlightenment.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">The New
                 Criterion</title> 15.10. June 1997. <ptr target="http://www.newcriterion.com/archive/15/jun97/gibbon.htm"/>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wineburg1991" label="Wineburg 1991" key="wineburg1991">Wineburg, S. <title rend="quotes">Historical Problem Solving: A Study of the Cognitive Processes Used in the Evaluation of Documentary and Pictorial Evidence.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Educational Psychology</title>  83.1 (1991): 73-87.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wineburg1998" label="Wineburg 1998" key="wineburg1998">Wineburg, S. <title rend="quotes">Reading Abraham Lincoln: An Expert/Expert Study in the Interpretation of Historical Texts.</title> 
               <title rend="italic">Cognitive Science</title> 22.3 (1998): 319-346.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wyatt1993" label="Wyatt et al. 1993" key="wyatt1993">Wyatt, D., M. Pressley, P.B. El-Dinary,
                 S. Stein, and R. Brown. Comprehension Strategies, Worth and Credibility Monitoring, and Evaluations: Cold and Hot Cognition When Experts Read Professional Articles That Are Important to Them. <title rend="italic">Learning and Individual Differences</title> 5 (1993): 49–72.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>