<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">DH for History Students: A Case Study at the Facultad de
                    Filosofía y Letras (National Autonomous University of Mexico) </title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Adriana <dhq:family>Álvarez
                        Sánchez</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>National Autonomous University of Mexico </dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>adralvsan@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Associate Profesor at the Faculty of Philosophy and Literature, UNAM </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Miriam <dhq:family>Peña Pimentel</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>National Autonomous University of Mexico </dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>miriampenapimentel@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Lecturer at the Faculty of Philosophy and Literature, UNAM</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000312</idno>
                <idno type="volume">011<!-- volume number, with leading zeroes: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue">3<!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date when="2017-10-02">02 October 2017</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>Digital Humanities</item>
                        <item>History</item>
                        <item>Humanities</item>
                        <item>Digital Culture</item>
                        <item>Education</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="DD" when="2017-05-03">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>Digital Humanities (DH) is a field of research in which humanists at the National
                    Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM) can take part and about which they can
                    collaborate in debates and projects. Introducing DH in the academic programs at
                    an undergraduate level can be a difficult path to traverse. Even so, for the
                    academic year 2016, we managed to include a Specialized Seminar-Workshop on this
                    field of study within the History Course at the <foreign xml:lang="es">Facultad
                        de Filosofía y Letras</foreign> at the UNAM. This article shows and analyzes
                    the context, the methods and the academic, technical and specialization
                    implications DH has in the History field (and in Humanities in general), and
                    also presents the results of our teaching work, of the research project in
                    teaching to which it is connected, and of some other activities which aim at
                    establishing an academic digital culture in this School’s community.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>This article shows and analyzes the context, the methods and the academic,
                    technical and specialization implications DH has in the field of history through
                    a case study on a Specialized Seminar-Workshop at the UNAM.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction<note> Even though the concept of <foreign xml:lang="es">Humanidades Digitales</foreign> (<term>HD</term>) is not culturally
                        equivalent to that of Digital Humanities (DH), we have decided, out of
                        consideration to readers of this journal, to translate <term>HD</term> as
                        DH.</note><note>
                        <foreign xml:lang="es">Facultad de Filosofía y Letras</foreign> is the
                        equivalent to the American model of School (or Faculty) of Arts &amp;
                        Humanities.</note></head>
                <p>The following pages shall begin by describing the institutional context of the
                        <ref target="http://historia.filos.unam.mx/plan-de-estudios1999/"><foreign xml:lang="es">Plan de Estudios de la Licenciatura en
                        Historia</foreign></ref><note>
                        <term>Plan de Estudios</term> is the description of the curriculum and the
                        statements of its methods, as well as the conception of the level and the
                        area of study. In this case, we are referring to the undergraduate course in
                        History</note> (<term>PE</term>, its acronym in Spanish). Next, the features
                    of the subject by the name of <foreign xml:lang="es">Seminario Taller
                        Especializado</foreign> (Specialized Seminar-Workshop) shall be explained,
                    as well as the way in which this space has been able to become a laboratory for
                    the introduction of digital humanities in the History Course. Section 3 shall
                    present a study case combining the teaching experience and the pedagogical work
                    in the classroom. Some of the digital objects produced in the Seminar-Workshop
                    will be introduced in Section 4.</p>
                <p>This model for a course and its orientation towards the digital humanities is a
                    first attempt at including this area of study at an undergraduate level, which
                    made it necessary to describe the complementary work carried out outside the
                    classroom (section 5). From the experience with the Seminar-Workshop, however
                    successful it may have been, the authors were able to identify a series of
                    shortages in the use of technology and of the internet by the undergraduate
                    students of History. For this reason, an introductory course was offered to the
                    students of the Class of 2016 before the beginning of the school year (section
                    6). In the final section, the authors suggest strategies for the inclusion of
                    digital humanities in updating the university curricula at the UNAM –this,
                    within the context of an expansion process of DH in Latin America.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>1. Institutional background</head>
                <p>The current <ref target="http://historia.filos.unam.mx/plan-de-estudios1999/"><foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Plan de Estudios de la Licenciatura en
                                Historia</term></foreign></ref>was approved–after several
                    discussions, surveys and debates–in 1998, and implemented the following year.
                    Even though by then computers, as well as the internet, were starting to become
                    everyday use tools in the academic field, throughout the eighty-three pages of
                    the first volume in which the <term>PE</term> is described, no mention is made
                    of the need to include specific subjects in the curricular map that would allow
                    students to acquire digital skills in the four years of the course.</p>
                <p>The <term>Plan de Estudios</term> students have to go through includes a series
                    of seminar-workshops that center their goals in research abilities. In
                    particular, the <term><foreign xml:lang="es">Seminario Taller
                            Especializado</foreign></term> owes its name to the fact that its
                    contents focus on the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#programa1999">use and application of specific research techniques,
                            particular ways of teaching and media for the circulation of historical
                            knowledge, such as video, films, CD-ROMs, the theater, radio scripts,
                            etc.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#programa1999" loc="60"/>
                    </cit>.<note> Direct quotations have been translated into English.</note> As a
                    result of these guidelines, the Seminar-Workshop must ensure the conclusion of
                    concrete products for two spheres: teaching and the circulation of knowledge.
                    Thematic flexibility has allowed the renovation of the specific contents of each
                    of the seminars. This has brought about a constant introduction of innovative
                    themes and methods in the classroom. For instance, at the <term>Facultad de
                        Filosofía y Letras</term>, a traditional place as regards infrastructure for
                    the Humanities–i.e. classrooms, blackboards, seats for students and desks for
                    the teachers–there is audiovisual equipment available; however, there is not an
                    efficient wireless network, which creates some challenges.</p>
                <p>The <term>PE</term> has undergone two certification processes–evaluations carried
                    out by outside institutions authorized by the state–but its structure remains
                    the same. In 2015, a commission of teachers and students began its revision,
                    though the whole process will take about two years. The flexibility of the
                        <term>PE</term> allows, on the other hand, the existence of a wide thematic
                    offer of subjects for students in their third year of the History Course: from
                    Museum or Heritage Studies to contents for the radio or the press.</p>
                <p>In this context, the Head of the <hi rend="italic">Colegio de Historia</hi>
                    (History Department), Dr. Lucrecia Infante Vargas, shared with us her interest
                    in setting up a seminar in order to train students in ‘the digital world’. This,
                    as well as the previously mentioned characteristics of the <hi rend="italic">Plan de Estudios</hi>, brought an opportunity to bring forward a
                    Specialized Seminar-Workshop, which we called “Digital Humanities and History”.
                    Its syllabus includes epistemological considerations and, of course, the
                    practice with, and the analysis of, resources and digital tools for the
                    historical research.</p>
                <p>It is worth stating that the <term>PE</term> is based on two elements of the
                    discipline: Historiography and research. Not being provided with a teaching
                    model of its own due to the academic autonomy the university has had ever since
                    the first decades of the twentieth century, academic freedom constitutes one of
                    its most important symbols. Even though the History <term>PE</term> establishes
                    a graduate profile and some goals, these have been set by a community more
                    interested in the development of historiography, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#programa1999">the questions, the methods and the conclusions of the
                            historians of the past</quote>
                        <ptr target="#programa1999" loc="5"/>
                    </cit>, than in the teaching of guidelines to train future historians. While the
                    body of research and the considerations on the teaching of history are scarce,
                    some investigations are actually beginning to emerge, though not always from
                    this specific field, but mostly from pedagogy. The <term><foreign xml:lang="es">Secretaría de Educación Pública (SEP)</foreign></term><note>
                        <term>SEP</term> is the equivalent to Ministry of Education.</note> accepts
                    university studies provided that some basic criteria are met, such as a certain
                    amount of class hours, a number of credits, some mandatory and also
                    supplementary requirements, equivalent to those of the other undergraduate
                    courses in the country. The use of the internet within the academic context has
                    brought about its inclusion in national educational policies. For this reason,
                    even though our students have high quality training as humanists–which implies
                    reading and critical thinking–it has become necessary for them to be able to
                    apply this training to the digital world. </p>
                <p>During our research on formal DH programs, we found the <title rend="italic">Short Guide to the Digital Humanities</title>, by Burdick et al. <ptr target="#burdick2012"/>. There, they mention the practice and the
                    institutional aspects of DH teaching. Following this approach, our proposal is
                    also linked to the fact that both of us teachers belong to the <ref target="http://www.humanidadesdigitales.net/">RedHD</ref>(DHNetwork) and are
                    members of a research team within this field in which we organize seminars,
                    colloquia and research projects. In Mexico, DH has had significant development
                    in the last few years [Svensson 2014], this being part of the context in which
                    our course proposal and the teaching of digital humanities emerged. The <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Facultad de Filosofía y Letras</term></foreign> at the
                    UNAM includes in its academic offer this DH Seminar, a space for discussion for
                    the <ref target="http://www.humanidadesdigitales.net/"><emph>RedHD</emph></ref>,
                    attended by academicians from various disciplines and different Mexican and
                    foreign institutions. Since 2015, the Seminar has had a schedule of itinerant
                    meetings, which opens up the dialogue with students and teachers from the
                    universities in the city and its outskirts.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. Definition of the Specialized Seminar-Workshop</head>
                <p>Originally, we were reluctant to include <soCalled>Digital Humanities</soCalled>
                    in the title of the Seminar-Workshop. Despite the recent boom this field has had
                    in the Mexican academy, it still remains quite unknown in undergraduate programs
                    of study, which implies that the students to whom the seminar is directed are
                    initially unaware of what they will be dealing with throughout the academic
                    year. This is why we decided to profit from such bewilderment with the aim of
                    arousing curiosity among students, and thus include this relatively new field of
                    study in the university curriculum.</p>
                <p>We also faced the never-ending debate between DH and Information and
                    Communication Technologies (ICTs). Among university staff and administration,
                    the mere mention of <soCalled>technology</soCalled> in the description of a
                    course takes us to the use of technologies from the point of view of pedagogy or
                    of teaching in the different areas of knowledge and the different educational
                    levels. Such reductionist use of these concepts makes the students assume that
                    the Seminar-Workshop will be a space where they will learn how to use the tools,
                    but not where they will discuss about them or develop reflective abilities
                    and/or practices. Fyfe has pointed out that this fact causes two problems: the
                    first one is the belief that the training is restricted to the command of a
                    digital tool, and the second one is the idea that only already known mechanical
                    tasks can be performed with it <ptr target="#fyfe2011"/>. The aforementioned
                    limits the analysis of this kind of resources in the learning process.</p>
                <p>For this reason, from the start, the proposal of our seminar implied the presence
                    of two teachers from different humanistic disciplines–Philology and History–who
                    would teach the course in a computer lab, the idea being this does not only
                    involve the use of digital tools.</p>
                <p>Following Fyfe, the Specialized Seminar-Workshop has several aims <ptr target="#fyfe2011"/>. At an institutional level, we believe that the biggest
                    university in the country should have students who, besides knowing the methods
                    and debates specific to the majors they follow, should be able to profit from
                    the tools and resources available, among which are the digital ones, and to take
                    part in the debates about their use.</p>
                <p>For this purpose, some goals were set: when finishing the academic year, students
                    should know about the main discussions on the use of DH tools and models applied
                    to the historical research, as well as about different digital tools for
                    humanistic research. Besides, the students would get guided training for the
                    reflection upon the methodological problems related to knowledge-building in
                    digital contexts, especially from the design of a digital research product,
                    which would be studied in the second semester of the academic year.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3. Experience and case study</head>
                <p>From the beginning of the academic year, experience has shown us that students
                    had unsystematic empirical knowledge of digital tools and platforms, which
                    seldom is the result of a full knowledge or of the reflection upon the changes
                    in the creation of knowledge in the area of the humanities. Every now and then,
                    for example, it became necessary to clarify, for example, the difference between
                    an operating system and software, or the differences between various publishing
                    licenses. Students use, on an everyday basis, several social networks for
                    recreational purposes; some follow blogs for leisure; however, few use the
                    internet to carry out academic tasks. This is due, in part, to the prohibition
                    of the use of information from the internet throughout their previous studies,
                    which causes a series of misconceptions about this matter.</p>
                <p>The first group of students who attended the Seminar-Workshop–who was used to a
                    working dynamics of discussion in the classroom, but also to attending
                    lectures–was initially puzzled, for our Seminar was at a computer laboratory, a
                    space they only used when they needed to print something or to use the internet,
                    or even to write their papers, but not to attend a formal class.</p>
                <p>Once the dynamics of the class–readings, debates, and above all, enquiry–was
                    explained, students became active users. First, we talked about what DH is and
                    its origins, its different aspects and the main debates about it. Then, we read
                    and reflected upon what the historical discipline has done in this field of
                    research, with an emphasis on the generalized view on digital, digitizing and
                    original production processes–what D’Iorio and Barbera <ptr target="#diorio2011"/> call <q>conditions of possibility,</q> summarized as <q><emph>quote,
                            consensus and preservation</emph></q>–which have preserved the
                    humanistic academy throughout history. The change in humanistic work is not
                    precisely in the principles of the discipline, but it suggests the correct
                    inclusion of appropriate technologies and trends at each step in the process of
                    knowledge-building. This debate remained constant in the Seminar-Workshop
                    throughout both semesters.</p>
                <p>We also dealt with some aspects regarding the evaluation of websites and digital
                    tools. For this, we resorted to one of the forms put forward by members of the
                        <ref target="http://www.humanidadesdigitales.net/"><emph>RedHD</emph></ref>,
                    though other options were also explored. At the beginning of the semester, the
                    students started a practical evaluation activity which revealed their lack of
                    awareness about the different elements that should be taken into consideration;
                    however, this made them realize about the importance of this task in order to
                    check whether digital publications and projects follow the same criteria as
                    products edited and printed in paper. Later on, when we analyzed projects
                    connected to the historical discipline, students always did some research and
                    found other similar projects to compare. We realized that students are actually
                    both curious and fully capable of analyzing digital projects; however, for this
                    to be carried out they need a school environment which encourages them to
                    explore and also offers them the necessary tools to differentiate and evaluate
                    information. In fact, third year students of History already have this kind of
                    training, applied only to publications in paper: they can identify types of
                    works, degree of specialization, publishing houses, and academic journals. We
                    believe it is essential to offer students, on the one hand, the basic tools for
                    analysis; and, on the other, the confidence for them to develop their abilities
                    in such a way that the result of their training should be the critical reading
                    of any kind of text or project.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4. Creativity and products</head>
                <p>The next step in the development of the Seminar-Workshop was to encourage our
                    students’ creativity, taking into account the basic publication norms, such as
                    the use of the <soCalled>physical</soCalled> and the digital content, production
                    licenses and the circulation of knowledge, collaborative and interdisciplinary
                    work, etc. Their own use of the network and their consumption of information
                    created conflict when faced against the way they would carry out their projects.
                    Would they like to offer open or restricted access to a particular content?
                    Would they rather carry out a collaborative or an individual project? Such
                    questions were meant to raise awareness in students as users of digital
                    resources and tools. It is important to generate a digital culture, a series of
                    good practices that will allow them to profit from the means available to them
                    in order to grow as historians and users.</p>
                <p>The result of the first year, besides the impact on their perspective regarding
                    their training, was a series of individual projects that showed a certain
                    attachment to a <soCalled>traditional</soCalled> way of producing historical
                    knowledge. Students decided to undertake the construction of blogs, and one
                    student even suggested the development of a network for historians, initially in
                    Mexico City.</p>
                <p>In the first case, after some evaluation, the students chose the blog platform of
                    their preference according to the type of contents they wished to publish;
                    whereas, in the second case, the student had to carry out a detailed inquiry on
                    the platforms that would allow her to materialize such project. Her solutions
                    were conditioned by the logistical need of a server, which the institution was
                    not able to provide. The decision of using the account one of the teachers had
                    in a commercial server was made in order make her project possible. Despite the
                    setbacks, we managed to carry out the students’ proposals, and two of them are
                    currently starting to bring forward further digital projects, which they will
                    provide in written form as their undergraduate theses and afterwards at their
                    defense.</p>
                <p>As a guide for the evaluation of the products of undergraduate dissertation
                    examinations, we had the work by Koh, in which she describes her own course: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#koh2014">you and your students are all already digital
                            humanists, because you all use technology in your daily lives</quote>
                        <ptr target="#koh2014"/>
                    </cit>. Given the fact that we needed to demonstrate to the academic community
                    what students are capable of producing, we selected three outstanding
                    projects:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>The project <title>History of Japan in the 20th Century</title> shows,
                        through the use of various circulation tools and the option to an open and
                        free of charge publication, some aspects of the history of contemporary
                        Japan. Students worked collaboratively and were able to produce analytical
                        contents, which came from different documentary sources, such as video,
                        documents, photographs and timelines. Even though the analysis follows a
                        traditional methodology, the students were able to express its content with
                        simple vocabulary intended for a wider audience without sacrificing their
                        academic training.</item>
                    <item>The personal blog <ref target="http://lacasadelobreromundial.blogspot.mx/"><term>La casa del obrero mundial</term></ref> (The House of the
                        World Laborer) deals with the anarchist movement in Mexico and its
                        consolidation at the World Workers’ Chamber. The student analyzes historical
                        documents, including contemporary newspaper clippings, and dwells on some
                        events that took place at that building, offering a critical analysis of the
                        historical movement. Even though the student was more inclined to making a
                        traditional piece, he used the methodology of history as well as his own
                        point of view in order to make a blog that would appeal to a wider audience,
                        and overcame the fear that often comes with the first open
                        publication.</item>
                    <item>The social network <ref target="http://miriampena.com/">ConectaHD</ref><note> The site was temporarily taken down due to
                            problems with the server.</note> (DHConnect) was developed with the
                        intention of creating thematic groups of history students and teachers from
                        the various universities in Mexico City, which would allow their members to
                        exchange digital objects, bibliographical information and guidance regarding
                        historians (university professors) that might be of their interest.</item>
                </list>
                <p>After this first experience teaching the Seminar-Workshop, it became necessary to
                    perform a self-evaluation on the contents as well as on the level of efficiency
                    in the fulfillment of our goals. This made us adjust our syllabus and we thought
                    that the next time we taught the Seminar-Workshop, it would be beneficial to
                    create not different projects, but a single, collaborative project. As a result
                    of the revision and the comparison of our syllabus with others focused on DH and
                    digital culture, and based on the results published by Rockwell and Sinclair, we
                    decided it was necessary to broaden the scope, which now included the students’
                    acquisition of competences oriented to the management and development of digital
                    projects <ptr target="#rockwell2012"/>.</p>
                <p>Having said that, our students managed to fulfill the goals set at the beginning,
                    they presented products and brought forward new projects; however, the History
                    student population amounts to over a thousand. The Seminar’s success in the
                    general context could be seen as a grain of sand in the desert, though not less
                    significant for this reason: we believe that the training of students in the
                    creation of digital objects remains the best way making DH known, and their
                    application in undergraduate courses, a necessity.</p>
                <p>However, we need to mention that the infrastructure in our <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Facultad</term></foreign> does not always allow the availability
                    of proper spaces for a seminar like this one. Not so long ago, only the
                    Geography Department–and, occasionally, the Pedagogy Department–made use of the
                    computer laboratories for teaching. Although there are other computer rooms,
                    these are set aside for the use of the whole community of teachers and students,
                    which renders them unable to be used exclusively during teaching hours. At the
                    moment, the <term>Facultad</term> has three computer laboratories specifically
                    used for teaching: at the main building, there are the <soCalled>Giordano
                        Bruno</soCalled> room and room 313, provided with sixteen and twenty-five
                    computer equipments respectively; at the annexed building, there is a bigger
                    laboratory, with a total of thirty computers. These spaces are meant to meet the
                    needs of a population that, according to official data, consists of <ref target="http://www.filos.unam.mx/sobre/directorio/">8129</ref>students of
                    the thirteen different undergraduate courses offered at the
                        <term>Facultad</term>. It becomes too clear that such demand cannot be
                    satisfied only with the three laboratories available now. What is more, even
                    though there exists a wireless network system (RIU, its acronym in Spanish), it
                    does not have the capacity required to provide service to such a vast community.
                    Academic activities, which require the use of a stable network, exceed the
                    current conditions at our <term>Facultad</term>. The everyday-use classrooms do
                    not have a wireless network; neither do they have nodes for ethernet. This
                    limits the development, not only of seminars such as ours, but also of other
                    subjects which need the use of the internet and of audiovisual equipment. This
                    shortage has yet to be solved due to the relation between the resources and the
                    size of the academic community; this is why there is not a detailed assessment
                    of this situation. The effort that has been put into having some computer rooms
                    and laboratories is important, but it is clear that the <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Facultad de Filosofía y Letras</term></foreign> shows some
                    backwardness in comparison to other <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Facultades</term></foreign>, be them of Social Sciences, or
                    Engineering, or similar disciplines. Perhaps the Romantic idea of a philosopher,
                    historian or philologist sitting alone holding a printed book is one of the
                    reasons why the <term>Facultad</term>’s community does not believe a
                    twenty-first century humanist requires new spaces such as computer laboratories
                    or services such as an efficient network in order to carry out his/her
                    activities.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5. Complementary work</head>
                <p>In 2014, we requested the UNAM the funding of a project the purpose of which
                    would be to make a guide on digital tools and resources for humanists. The
                    project’s methodology implied the development of research that would improve
                    student-centered teaching. This way, besides the impact on the curricular area,
                    we set out to launch the creation of a digital culture, which would imply an
                    increase in responsible users and content creators. Four teachers took part in
                    this project, together with four students, three of whom did the
                    Seminar-Workshop and were granted a scholarship to finish their courses, and
                    another one who had an internship as a requisite to finish his studies.<note>
                        The teachers who collaborated with the authors in this project are Cristina
                        Ratto and Érika Adán; and the students, Claudia Muñoz, Diego Salgado, María
                        Fernanda López and Bryan Gómez.</note></p>
                <p>The website developed is called <ref target="http://elaborahd.filos.unam.mx/">eLaboraHD</ref> (a word game between <soCalled>elaborate</soCalled> and
                    laboratory [e-lab/ora] HD stands for Digital Humanities acronym in Spanish), and
                    is addressed to the whole community at the <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Facultad
                            de Filosofía y Letras</term></foreign>; that is, to humanists at the
                    UNAM, even though it emphasizes guidance to historians. The management of this
                    product began with the request for an institutional server that would allow us
                    to have an official extension connected to the <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Facultad</term></foreign>. The creation process took several
                    months, due to the fact that we have no Department devoted to the development of
                    digital projects. The setting up of a platform within the institutional space
                    demanded the consultation and collaboration with several engineers and computer
                    technicians who granted us part of their time from daily work (the correlation
                    between any research and this Department is focused mainly on connectivity
                    matters for video conferences and lab maintenance) in order to help us set up a
                    basic website management system whose use would be both flexible and simple
                        (<ref target="https://es.wordpress.com/">Wordpress</ref>). This way, we
                    ensured content update and basic maintenance work on the website, which would
                    also allow us to keep an institutional structure and meet the necessary
                    evaluation standards. Despite the fact that a resource such as this one should
                    be relatively simple, the minimum requirements of the system implied joint work
                    with the <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Facultad</term></foreign>’s IT Department,
                    for the physical access to the server is restricted to the company of one of the
                    people responsible there.</p>
                <p>Because these types of activities are quite rare in our line of work, we
                    experienced some technical setbacks that delayed the development of the site.
                    Nevertheless, since last March, several weekly meetings were held in a computer
                    laboratory so as to define the name of the site, its structure and the type of
                    contents that would be published there. Discussion and consensus defined our
                    decision-making. At the same time that technological difficulties were being
                    solved, contents were being planned as well. Once the site had been set, and a
                    URL had been assigned, we were able to devote ourselves to the task of building
                    static web pages and entries at the blog on the evaluation of sites and
                    projects, digital resources and tools to carry out works shared by the thirteen
                    disciplines taught at our <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Facultad</term></foreign>.</p>
                <p>The site took its definitive shape in June, and even though today we still are at
                    the content creation phase, there are a few pending chores, such as the site’s
                    promotion from the main Institution’s site, for we are sharing resources and
                    spaces with 130 research projects, and from the <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Facultad</term></foreign>’s site, because it is the <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Facultad</term></foreign>’s responsibility to guarantee
                    the circulation of all its research projects–and for this, each must
                        <soCalled>wait for one’s turn.</soCalled> We certainly have not put aside
                    circulation through social networks, but this is not replicated by the accounts
                    at the institution itself, which limits the knowledge such a large university
                    population as ours may have about our contents. Again, our digital
                        <soCalled>grain of sand</soCalled> seems to disappear in the desert of
                    institutional infrastructure.</p>
                <p>All in all, we believe that the most important thing is to create interest in the
                    community regarding the use of digital tools and resources in every possible
                    way: at conferences within the context of research colloquia, through our
                    classes, at teachers’ meetings, etc. We are fully aware that it will not be easy
                    to change the academic culture at a School that, traditionally, is used to
                    reading on paper; however, we do believe that the ability to establish
                    dialogues, also traditional and inherent to the Humanities, will at least allow
                    us to cause curiosity in its population.</p>
                <p>The funding we have received forces us to review the site in pairs, and even
                    though we can count on two teachers who are willing to perform an assessment, it
                    has become necessary to elaborate an evaluation guide, for historians are not
                    used to analyzing this kind of products. For the time being, the site is being
                    used by the teachers who belong to the project, within the classes we teach, and
                    we have invited teachers from other institutions and levels to add the contents
                    of the site as an additional support for their teaching activities.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>6. Academic renewal: Taking DH to the Introduction to History</head>
                <p>The constant debate on the students’ training becomes evident in the initiative
                    of the Head of the <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Colegio de
                        Historia</term></foreign>, who organized a series of meetings with the
                    teachers in order to know the problems they had detected on this matter. In
                    general terms, the teachers mentioned basic problems with reading and writing,
                    but they also emphasized the lack of knowledge on the digital resources the
                    university makes available to its community.</p>
                <p>The Head office turned to us once again to ask us for some sort of course or
                    workshop addressed to those students who would begin their studies in August.
                    This course would not be compulsory, but the importance of attending it was
                    stressed to them. So, we created a four-hour syllabus and divided the 270 new
                    students into groups. Four teachers, including ourselves, took on the task of
                    designing the syllabus and teaching it. Besides the academic life at the
                        <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Facultad</term></foreign>, we dealt with the
                    digital resources and catalogues that the 134 libraries at the university offer
                    their community. We explained that, as students, they have the right to get an
                    account at the <ref target="http://bibliotecas.unam.mx/">BidiUNAM</ref> (the
                    library’s site) in order to access electronic resources, which consist of
                    databases and allow them access to texts and indexes of articles and specialized
                    journals at an international level.</p>
                <p>The course included the implementation of a survey to the Class of 2016 about
                    different aspects. We would like to highlight here part of the results on the
                    knowledge about, and the use of, digital devices and the internet in their
                    academic training. We discovered that 234 of the students beginning their
                    undergraduate course have laptops, 137 have tablets and 175 have smartphones,
                    and that 94% of them make use of these devices to carry out academic work.
                    Although they did not state which particular tasks they did, from individual
                    conversations with them we were able to infer that the use of these devices
                    tended to be for basic search of information. Despite previous restrictions over
                    the use of the internet in their studies, 89% of the first-year students are in
                    favor of the use of the internet to perform their research throughout their
                    undergraduate course, although they are not aware of the names of resources and
                    applications; i.e., they are familiar with the use of text editors, blog
                    management software or social networks platforms, but they do not know the
                    differences between the various digital objects.</p>
                <p>These surveys have allowed us to conclude our first diagnosis and to identify
                    several aspects that should be incorporated to the <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Plan de Estudios</term></foreign> of the undergraduate History
                    Course. First, we believe that the use of the internet and of structured data
                    should be included, for they allow both the macro- and microanalysis of our
                    objects of study. We also maintain that, within the graduate profile at the
                        <term>PE</term>, we should include students’ abilities to broaden the field
                    with the search of theoretical, monographic and documentary information in order
                    to carry out research work that would allow them to solve problems.</p>
                <p>Even though interdisciplinary work is still pending, it could be made real by
                    means of the joint elaboration of digital projects. The relationship among the
                    different <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Facultades</term></foreign> at the UNAM,
                    and even among the different undergraduate courses within our own <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Facultad</term></foreign>, could offer humanists the
                    ability to develop collaborative and interdisciplinary work, because faculty
                    members must actively participate in the digital training of their students.
                    Certainly, for this, it will also be necessary to spread the use of updating
                    software for those teachers who are currently working there. It would be
                    desirable for teaching staff to include in their syllabuses some activities
                    involving the use of digital resources or tools in order to develop academic
                    products within the theme and the objectives of each subject.</p>
                <p>To implement the inclusion of these aspects, it seems necessary to sensitize both
                    teachers <ptr target="#trinkle2004"/> and students regarding the importance not
                    only of digital technologies, but also of the reflection about the implications
                    that their use has in each of the disciplines, as well as of the advantages of
                    using them properly. It will definitely be necessary to have the infrastructure
                    required so as to achieve these goals, which is already part of the policies and
                    working plans of the administration.</p>
                <p>While the debate develops and the appropriate decisions on the changes in the
                        <term>PE</term> are made, we have brought forward two workshops addressed to
                    teachers, the academic technical staff and teaching assistants within the
                        <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Programa de Actualización y Superación
                            Docente</term></foreign> (<hi rend="italic">PASD</hi>, its acronym in
                        Spanish)<note> Teaching Updating and Improvement Program.</note> from the
                        <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Dirección General de Asuntos del Personal
                            Académico</term></foreign> (<term>DGAPA</term>, its acronym in
                        Spanish)<note> General Administration of Academic Staff Affairs.</note> at
                    the UNAM: an introductory one and another one for the development of digital
                    projects. This entails a new challenge: we believe that it is now imperative to
                    broaden the impact of our proposal of creating this digital academic culture
                    which will have an effect not only on the way knowledge is produced within our
                    university to this day, but also on the criteria for the evaluation of the
                    teaching-learning process as well as of teachers’ productivity. And, even though
                    this is an aspect that requires an open debate among academicians, it goes
                    beyond the scope of this article. The active involvement of teachers, now and in
                    the near future, in the development of digital products and projects as part of
                    their teaching work will depend on this debate.</p>
                <p>The case of study here presented and the efforts made within the UNAM classrooms
                    owe much to the existence of the <term>RedHD</term>, which was created in
                    Mexico, though together with members from different parts of the world. Several
                    collaborators in this network have taught workshops to various academic groups,
                    both at a national and at an international level. One way or the other, these
                    workshops have begun to make an impact in the development of projects –some of
                    which were already being carried out, though they were still not identified as
                    DH work. The spreading of DH, as well as of the responsible use of the internet
                    and of digital tools have been some of the main goals. In fact, the authors of
                    this article, together with Ernesto Priani Saisó, have collaborated with
                    institutional projects, such as <foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Comunidades
                            Digitales para el Aprendizaje en Educación Superior</term></foreign>
                        (<ref target="http://www.codaes.mx/inicio.htm">CODAES</ref>, its acronym in
                    Spanish), which was coordinated by the University of Veracruz. As mentioned
                    above, the need of training teachers as well has been acknowledged, but some
                    workshops have been offered in other institutions outside the UNAM. For
                    instance, in South America, within the context of the <ref target="https://hastac2014.wordpress.com/conference-program/">HASTAC
                        2014</ref> Congress (Lima, Peru), the workshop <title rend="quotes">On
                        Arriving at the Digital: Describing Critical Paths into the Digital
                        Humanities</title> was organized by the University of Illinois at
                    Urbana-Champaign and taught with guests from Mexico, Peru and Argentina. What is
                    more, some workshops have been carried out in the <ref target="http://aahd.com.ar/novedades/6682"><foreign xml:lang="es"><term>Primeras Jornadas Nacionales de Humanidades
                            Digitales</term></foreign></ref> (Buenos Aires, Argentina 2014) <ptr target="#pena2015"/>. In Central America, some workshops have been organized
                    at the University of San Carlos de Guatemala and at the National Autonomous
                    University of Honduras, as well as at the Latin American Social Sciences
                    Institute of Honduras <ptr target="#dominguez2016"/>. Therefore, the case study
                    at the <term>Facultad de Filosofía y Letras</term> is part of an expansion
                    process of DH–for the time being, within the Mexican and Latin American academic
                    institutions. Isabel Galina has discussed this issue in several texts since 2013
                        <ptr target="#galina2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#galina2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#galina2017"/>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="alvarez2015" label="Álvarez 2015"> Álvarez, Adriana and Miriam Peña.
                        <title rend="italic">eLaboraHD</title>
                    <ref target="http://elaborahd.filos.unam.mx/?lang=en">http://elaborahd.filos.unam.mx/?lang=en</ref> (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blackwell2009" label="Blackwell and Martin 2009">Blackwell,
                    Christopher and Thomas R. Martin. <title>Technology, Collaboration, and
                        Undergraduate Research</title>, <title rend="italic">DHQ</title>, Volume 3,
                    Number 1, (2009). <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/1/000024/000024.html">http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/1/000024/000024.html</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burdick2012" label="Burdick et. al. 2012">Burdick, Anne (et. al.).
                        <title rend="quotes">Institutions and Pragmatics,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities</title>, Massachucetts-London: The MIT
                    Press-Cambridge (2012), pp. 126-128. <ref target="https://mitpress.mit.edu/sites/default/files/9780262018470_Open_Access_Edition.pdf">https://mitpress.mit.edu/sites/default/files/9780262018470_Open_Access_Edition.pdf</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="diorio2011" label="D'Iorio and Barbera 2011">D’Iorio, Paolo and
                    Michele Barbera. <title rend="quotes">Scholar Source: A Digital Infrastructure
                        for the Humanities,</title> Thomas Bartscherer (ed.), <title rend="italic">Switching Codes. Thinking Through Digital Technology in the Humanities and
                        the Arts</title>, Michigan: University of Chicago Press (2011), pp.
                    61-88.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="direccion" label="Dirección General de Bibliotecas">Dirección General
                    de Bibliotecas. UNAM<ref target="http://bibliotecas.unam.mx/">http://bibliotecas.unam.mx/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dominguez2016" label="Domínguez 2016">Domínguez Herbón, David. <title rend="quotes">#RedHD: el verano de las convergencias</title> (September 4th
                    2016) <ref target="http://humanidadesdigitales.net/blog/2016/09/04/el-verano-de-las-convergencias/">http://humanidadesdigitales.net/blog/2016/09/04/el-verano-de-las-convergencias/</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="facultad" label="Facultad de Filosofía y Letras">Facultad de Filosofía
                    y Letras. UNAM <ref target="http://www.filos.unam.mx/">http://www.filos.unam.mx/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fyfe2011" label="Fyfe 2011">Fyfe, Paul. <title rend="quotes">Digital
                        Pedagogy Unplugged,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">DHQ</title>, Volume 5, Number 3 (2011). <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/3/000106/000106.html">http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/3/000106/000106.html</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galina2011" label="Galina 2011"> Galina, Isabel. <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="es">Formulario de evaluación para proyectos de
                            Humanidades Digitales, Red de Humanidades Digitales.</foreign></title>
                    <ref target="http://humanidadesdigitales.net/evaluacion/eng/">http://humanidadesdigitales.net/evaluacion/eng/</ref> (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galina2013" label="Galina 2013"> Galina, Isabel. <title rend="quotes">Las Humanidades Digitales Globales</title> (November 8th 2013). <ref target="http://humanidadesdigitales.net/blog/2013/11/08/las-humanidades-digitales-globales/">http://humanidadesdigitales.net/blog/2013/11/08/las-humanidades-digitales-globales/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galina2015" label="Galina 2015">Galina, Isabel. <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="es">La RedHD y contextos latinoamericanos:
                            auto-representación y geopolíticas en las HD</foreign></title> (February
                    2nd 2015). <ref target="http://humanidadesdigitales.net/blog/2015/02/02/la-redhd-y-contextos-latinoamericanos-auto-representacion-y-geopolitica-en-las-hd/">http://humanidadesdigitales.net/blog/2015/02/02/la-redhd-y-contextos-latinoamericanos-auto-representacion-y-geopolitica-en-las-hd/</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galina2017" label="Galina 2017">Galina, Isabel. <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="es">Las Humanidades Digitales en
                        expansión</foreign></title> (January 5th 2017). <ref target="http://humanidadesdigitales.net/blog/2017/01/05/las-humanidades-digitales-en-expansion/">http://humanidadesdigitales.net/blog/2017/01/05/las-humanidades-digitales-en-expansion/</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gonzalez2014" label="González 2014"> González López, Luis Miguel.
                        <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="es">La casa del obrero
                            mundial,</foreign></title>
                    <ref target="http://lacasadelobreromundial.blogspot.mx/">http://lacasadelobreromundial.blogspot.mx/</ref> (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="koh2014" label="Koh 2014">Koh, Adeline. <title rend="quotes">Introducing Digital Humanities Work to Undergraduates: An Overview,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Hybrid Pedagogy</title>, (2014).<ref target="http://www.hybridpedagogy.com/journal/introducing-digital-humanities-work-undergraduates-overview/">http://www.hybridpedagogy.com/journal/introducing-digital-humanities-work-undergraduates-overview/</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="munoz2015" label="Muñoz 2015"> Muñoz, Claudia. <title rend="quotes">ConectaHD,</title> unavailable (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pena2015" label="Peña 2015">Peña Pimentel, Miriam. <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="es">I Jornadas de Humanidades Digitales
                            Culturas, Tecnologías, Saberes Asociación Argentina de Humanidades
                            Digitales. Buenos Aires, 17-19 de noviembre de 2014</foreign></title>
                    (January 25th 2015).<ref target="http://humanidadesdigitales.net/blog/2015/01/25/aahd/">http://humanidadesdigitales.net/blog/2015/01/25/aahd/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="programa1999" label="Programa de la Licenciatura en Historia 1999"><title rend="quotes">Programa de la Licenciatura en Historia. Facultad de
                        Filosofía y Letras.</title> UNAM. <ref target="http://historia.filos.unam.mx/plan-de-estudios1999/">http://historia.filos.unam.mx/plan-de-estudios1999/</ref>(1999).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="red2011" label="Red de Humanidades Digitales 2011"><title rend="italic">Red de Humanidades Digitales.</title> website: <ref target="http://www.humanidadesdigitales.net/">http://www.humanidadesdigitales.net/</ref> (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rockwell2012" label="Rockwell and Sinclair 2012">Rockwell, Geoffrey
                    and Stéfan Sinclair. <title rend="quotes">Acculturation and the Digital
                        Humanities Community,</title> Brett D. Hirsch (ed.), <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Pedagogy: Practices, Principles and Policies</title>,
                    Cambridge, UK: Open Book Publishers (2012). DOI: 10.11647/OBP.0024. <ref target="http://www.openbookpublishers.com/htmlreader/DHP/chap07.html#ch07">http://www.openbookpublishers.com/htmlreader/DHP/chap07.html#ch07</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="salgado2015" label="Salgado and Dorantes 2015">Salgado Muñoz, Diego
                    and Eduardo Dorantes. <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="es">Historia de
                            Japón en la segunda mitad del siglo XX</foreign></title>, <ref target="https://historiajpnacdmc.wordpress.com/">target="https://historiajpnacdmc.wordpress.com/</ref> (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="trinkle2004" label="Trinkle 2004">Trinkle, Dennis A. <title rend="quotes">Guidelines for Evaluating Digital Media Activities in Tenure,
                        Promotion, and Review,</title> Deborah Lines Andersen (ed.), <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Tenure, Promotion, and Review
                        Process</title>, USA: ME Sharp Inc. (2004), pp. 211-213.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="svensson2014" label="Svensson 2014">Svensson, Anna. <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="es">El término Humanidades Digitales y los
                            Estudios Latinoamericanos: una revisión bibliográfica,</foreign></title>
                    <title rend="italic">Anuario Americanista Europeo, Issue 12</title>, (2014), pp.
                    1-28.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="unesco" label="Unesco">Unesco. <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="es">TICs: definición</foreign></title>
                    <ref target="http://www.unesco.org/new/es/unesco/themes/icts/">http://www.unesco.org/new/es/unesco/themes/icts/</ref></bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>