<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Black waves: Vaziri (2023) tracing African enslavement in the Persian gulf through film</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Zeinab <dhq:family>Parishani</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Missouri</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>zpmmd@missouri.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                 <p>Zeinab is a Ph.D. student and Graduate Research Assistant at the School of Information Science &amp; Learning Technologies (SISLT) 
                    iSchool at the <name>University of Missouri</name>. She is studying the use of innovative technologies such as virtual reality and 
                    video games, and she is interested in digital, media, and archival studies and human-computer interaction.
                 </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000748</idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <term corresp="#moving_images"/>
               <term corresp="#race"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>Iranian cinema</item>
                  <item>Indian Ocean slavery</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000748/000748.xml">GitHub</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p/>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p/>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head/>
            <p>Parisa Vaziri’s book begins with a sentence from one of Marc Nichanian’s  books, The historiographic perversion [Nichanian 2009]. Marc Nichanian's concept of "historiographic perversion" foreshadows a book deeply entrenched in the critical examination of historical objectivity. Parisa Vaziri wants to show the reader, by choosing this sentence at the very beginning of her book, that the work will scrutinize the very foundation of what is commonly accepted as historical truth, questioning the neutrality and assurance of established history. In opening with such a notion, the book is expected to offer a profound inquiry into the writing of history, exploring the influence of power, ideology, and conflict on the construction of historical narratives. 
            </p>
            <p>Parisa Vaziri’s Racial Blackness and Indian Ocean Slavery: Iran’s Cinematic Archive [Vaziri 2023] is a profound exploration of the representations of blackness and the historical undercurrents of slavery within Iranian cinema. Vaziri, a Comparative Literature expert, delves into the complex layers of fīlmfārsī  from the '50s and '70s, siyāh bāzī: the Indigenous theatrical tradition of Persian Black play, and the portrayal of the zār ritual, offering a nuanced reading of how those films reflect and obscure the ties to African enslavement.
            </p>
            <p>The origins of this book can be traced back to its author's PhD dissertation during a time of social upheaval in Iran. The 2022 protests over Mahsa Amini's tragic death provided a poignant backdrop, influencing Vaziri's approach to gender representation in Iranian cinema. That personal connection adds a layer of urgency and authenticity to her work.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Indian Ocean Slavery</head>
            <p>Vaziri's examination is particularly striking in its critique of the historiographical neglect of Indian Ocean slavery, which starkly contrasts with the attention given to Atlantic and trans-Saharan slavery. That lacuna in historical discourse, compounded by the scarcity of archival sources, is a silent testimony to the marginalized narratives of the enslaved. Related scholarship [Rajan 2011; Think Africa 2021] show both African migrations across the Indian Ocean, and the differences between three slave trade routes: trans-Saharan, Atlantic Ocean, and Indian Ocean.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Lack of Archival resources</head>
            <p>In her exemplary work, the author articulates a significant challenge in the study of slavery: the scarcity of archival materials. She notes that the narrative of Indian Ocean slavery, much like that in other regions, is often pieced together from material evidence that was not created by the enslaved themselves, but rather from records shaped by bureaucratic narratives or formalized correspondence. Such indirect documentation creates a barrier to fully understanding the enslaved perspective.
            </p>
            <p>Further, the author highlights the critical role of digital media in preserving cinematic history. She reflects on how a multitude of films, pivotal to her research, would have been lost if not for the digital age. Those pre-revolutionary works, previously at the mercy of inadequate storage solutions, faced further jeopardy from the deliberate destruction during the 1979 Revolution: it not only demolished a significant portion of Iran's cinematic infrastructure but also resulted in the loss of countless historical film records. The transition to digital platforms has thus not only resurrected those films from potential obscurity but has also allowed for the conservation and continued examination of Iran's rich cinematic legacy.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Why Cinema?</head>
            <p>Vaziri presents a compelling argument against the contemporary extractive nature of content production. She posits cinema not merely as a form of entertainment but as a powerful medium for reflection and intellectual engagement. Her perspective resonates with the thoughts of philosopher Bernard Stiegler, who eloquently remarked that a "process of global unification has taken place through cinema" [Vaziri 2023, 10]. Vaziri’s book underscores the unifying power of film to transcend cultural and temporal boundaries, offering a shared space for global narratives and dialogues.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Translating Persian Words to English</head>
            <p>While it is very tricky to translate words specific to Iranian culture into English, Vaziri manages it well; e.g. words like ungendered blackness and eunuchism. Her translation of Persian words like naqqali and pardahdari (literally: screen holding) into English is more than a linguistic exercise; it is a cultural bridge that enriches the reader's understanding of Iranian cinematic and social fabric. Persian generic terms, theoretical concepts, and ideas are indicated with italics in this book.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Significance of Oil and Sugar Cane</head>
            <p>The book delves deeply into the profound impact of oil on the socio-economic fabric of Iran, underscoring its role since its discovery in the early 20th century. As the nation's premier industry, oil not only reshaped Iran’s economy but also its cultural and social landscapes. The author explores how the legacy of the slave trade is intertwined with oil’s narrative, noting that the descendants of enslaved Africans, often traded in Persian Gulf ports, still live predominantly along the coastal regions. In that way, the south of Iran becomes a dual symbol: a bastion of petroleum wealth and a silent witness to the legacy of slavery.
            </p>
            <p>The author goes beyond oil, illuminating how the region's history is rich with other forms of commerce such as date cultivation, pearling, and notably, sugarcane farming in Khuzistan — historically known as the ‘land of sugar.’ Those industries, sustained in part by slave labor, predate oil’s dominance and hint at a broader spectrum of economic activities that have shaped Iran's history.
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, the book suggests that oil and the slave labor that once bolstered the pearling industry form a subconscious thread in the tapestry of Iranian cinema. That underlying theme is presented as a metaphorical undercurrent that has, perhaps inadvertently, influenced the narratives and stories told through Iranian films. Vaziri’s insightful analysis aims to bring to light these submerged connections, suggesting that the history of slavery and the development of the Iranian film industry are not just parallel stories but are profoundly connected: “Oil is ‘the key element,’ the unconscious of the Iranian film industry. But it is also the case that pearling — and the slave labor that fueled it — is the unconscious of oil” [Vaziri 2023, 136]. Her Figure 22 [Vaziri 2023, 173] illustrates the titular child peering through an abyss of sugar cane at the opening of Beyzai’s Bashu, The Little Stranger (1989). The connection between slave labor and sugar cultivation dips into an undatable chasm that echoes through this scene in the ambiguity of stalk identification.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Siyāh Bbāzī</head>
            <p>The book delves into how the traditional Persian performance art of siyāh bāzī, or "black play," which often involves a character in blackface, has been woven into Iranian cinema before the revolution. The art form, which features a character known as the siyāh who often annoys or mocks authority figures, has not been thoroughly examined by film experts, especially regarding its transition to film and its historical links to actual slavery.
            </p>
            <p>The author points out that when siyāh bāzī moved from the stage to the screen, it lost some of its original meaning due to the way films were edited and the complex symbols used in them. Even though those films could remind us of Iran's past with African slavery, they often reduce the siyāh character to a simple stereotype, stripping away the historical context. That happens even though there is great debate about whether siyāh bāzī in films really represents the same thing as the racist practice of blackface, which is recognized globally.
            </p>
            <p>In the first chapter, the author argues that the way siyāh bāzī is shown in films highlights the problems with how we think about this tradition. Films from before the Iranian revolution show the siyāh character as less complex and more disconnected from its roots in African slavery. That is in contrast to how people in Iran today, both in academic and popular discussions, try to ignore or deny the siyah's connections to slavery. But the author suggests that the reality of slavery disrupts these comfortable views, showing that the context we put around the siyāh character in films is not as solid or trustworthy as we might think.
            </p>
            <p>In Farukh Ghafārī’s 1964 classic black and white film Shab-e Qoozi (Night of the Hunchback), there is a notable scene that encapsulates the complex layers of social commentary of siyāh bāzī that Vaziri examines. The scene features a white actor in blackface making an entrance, speaking broken Persian to inquire if his master has enjoyed the music: "With your permission, may this house-born slave [ghulām-i khānahzād] provide entertainment? Musicians, play!" he calls out, as his indifferent master leisurely inhales from his hookah. This character, referred to as a "house-born slave," performs a subservient act, gracefully pouring liquid from a pitcher atop a mantel into a diminutive cup, balancing it atop his head; and commences to dance with a backward bend so low that the master can effortlessly take the cup, as depicted in Figure 2 [Vaziri 2023, 37].
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Bashu</head>
            <p>Chapter 4 has a detailed view to the film Bashu, The Little Stranger (1984), directed by Baharm Beyzai and the most famous of Iranian films foregrounding phenotypically inflected racism. Vaziri's commentary on the representation of Blackness in the film Bashu, The Little Stranger is particularly revealing. She discusses the character's otherness and the societal reactions to his skin color, reflecting the broader societal issues regarding race and identity. In the film an Iranian boy from south of Iran is lost after fleeing home for his life; his family has been killed during the Iran-Iraq war. He is saved and trained by a middle-aged woman (Na’i) in the north of Iran.
            </p>
            <p>This film has a lot of details in its dialog that represent the mindsets of local people. At the start of the film, his mother finds Bashu in the paddy field, and expresses repulsion for Bashu’s dark skin color, wondering aloud if he has escaped from a coal mine. Town dwellers find Bashu’s Blackness a subject of derision and comedy. In the rest of the movie, we see that the village shopkeeper, insultingly, slips Na’i an extra bar of soap because of the Blackness of Bashu. During the film, there are lots of scenes where the group of young boys encircle, bully, and parody Bashu at every sighting.
            </p>
            <p>When Na’i’s relatives come to visit her, no one sees Bashu as a child of Iran, a recognizable brother or son, and they can’t resist remarking instead upon Bashu’s “charcoal” color. They gather on a carpet, palaver, and pass around the tea, reprimanding Na’i for her reckless decision to host the foreigner, while various family members molest Bashu. An aunt gropes Bashu’s head in search of lice; an uncle demands dental inspection. A small girl he had earlier glimpsed from the window with intrigued curiosity crawls toward him on the carpet and swabs his face with her finger, which she examines, disappointed. Bashu lowers his head in shame. In another famous scene, Na’i bathes her own children in the river, and then tricks Bashu into the water, furiously scrubbing away at his dark skin and nearly drowning him, hoping to remove his color as if removing a stain: “Sefid nibeh ke nibeh” (“No, he won’t become white”).
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Zār</head>
            <p>The author dedicates an entire chapter (2) to the ritual of zār, which, in the context of Iranian modernity marked by the oil boom and the official end of slavery under Reza Shah  in 1928, represents a paradoxical call for the resurgence of the Black slave as a symbol of healing. That juxtaposition suggests that the legacy of slavery has unresolved issues that continue to require healing, a theme that resonates in Iranian cinema of the 1960s, especially in narratives set in the south of Iran where Black characters often embody roles of healers.
            </p>
            <p>Zār, as a practice, is prevalent across various regions, from Southwest Asia to the Persian Gulf, and from North Africa to parts of South Asia and East Africa. It is characterized by its cathartic processes involving movement, rhythm, and secrecy, leading to a loss of consciousness and serving as a form of communal therapy rather than a descent into despair. The author points out that zār operates on the principle of equality; despite its more frequent practice in impoverished Black communities, it affects individuals universally. That egalitarian aspect of zār is also echoed in Ethiopian belief systems, where it is said that everyone possesses a zār.
            </p>
            <p>From the film Bashu, the Little Stranger, Vaziri highlights a poignant moment where Na’i, the mother figure, is desperately seeking a cure for Bashu. The local doctor’s discriminatory assertion that his treatments are not meant for "people of that color" starkly contrasts with the ethos of zār that does not discriminate. The incident is meticulously captured by director Beyzai, underscoring zār as a force that sees no color, a stark reminder of the egalitarianism deeply rooted in this cultural practice. From zār, we glean the profound lesson of inherent equality among all people.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Renaming Slaves</head>
            <p>The book delves into the historical practice of renaming slaves, highlighting how such acts were used to strip individuals of their identity, a brutal facet of dehumanization. In Southwest Asia as elsewhere, renaming individuals with nonhuman names was one means by which masters asserted control over the identity of their slaves. In her insightful commentary on the character Bashu, Vaziri unpacks the lasting psychological effects of slavery. The film Bashu, the Little Stranger encapsulates it through its opening scenes where Na’i confronts Bashu, reducing him to a nameless, inferior status by denigrating his color and intelligence, thus negating his humanity: ‘you are black, you are dumb, you have no name.’ Every human being has a name. 
            </p>
            <p>Vaziri further explores the paradox of Bashu's Blackness within the film, which is presented as neither Persian nor Arab, leaving him without a cultural anchor. The character's name, Bashu, is revealed by the director, Beyzai, to be a creative amalgamation derived from the Persian verb 'to be' [budan] and 'to reside' [bashidan]. Thereby it lends him an existence and a place albeit through a constructed identity. This intricate detail underscores the complex layers of identity and belonging, particularly for those marked by the legacy of slavery.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head><title rend="italic">The Runner</title></head>
            <p>In the second part of Chapter 4, Vaziri turns to another film, Amir Naderi’s The Runner (1984), also about a young boy (called Amiro) in the south of Iran who is not marked as Black like Bashu, but his character mirrors societal attitudes towards race and humanity, suggesting a more innocent and unprejudiced perspective that could be the key to overcoming racial biases.
            </p>
            <p>Vaziri mentions an important scene in this film in which physical power, like labor, is racialized through the presence of white American and European foreigners who come to the port to get their shoes shined and, juxtaposed with Amiro bent at their feet, reveal his imprisonment within labor. Intermittently, between scenes, Amiro, the main character of The Runner, “stares out into the ocean and fantasizes about being taken away by one of the large white ships: “How white…how beautiful” [Vaziri 2023, 197-8].
            </p>
            <p>In another poignant sequence from The Runner, we witness the young children valiantly attempting to scale rock mounds. The camera captures their endeavors from a high angle, tracking the children’s ascent only to follow their subsequent and inevitable descent each time they falter. This visual narrative eloquently conveys the Sisyphean nature of Amiro’s existence, underscoring the futility and servitude that mark his life's toil. The director employs this vantage point not merely as a cinematic technique but as a storytelling device, inviting viewers to empathize with Amiro's relentless yet unrewarding struggle.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Haji Firuz</head>
            <p>Finally, Vaziri addresses the cultural and nationalistic forces that shape the discourse on race in Iran. She critiques the persistent mythologizing of Iran’s Aryan past, which has influenced modern perceptions and discussions about race and identity. 
            </p>
            <p>Haji Firuz is a fictional character in Iranian folklore who appears in the streets by the beginning of Nowruz (Iranian New Year). His face is covered in soot, and he is clad in bright red clothes and a felt hat. He dances through the streets while singing and playing a tambourine. Vaziri’s examination of cultural figures like Haji Firuz  and the influence of Aryanism provides a critical look at how nationalism and historical narratives have been constructed and the impact they have on contemporary society.
            </p>
            <p>Haji Firuz symbolizes Iran's complex history with slavery; a figure whose performances evoke images of servitude. Contemporary Iranian culture often seeks to trace its roots to the pre-Islamic era and Zoroastrianism , driven by nationalist sentiments and a desire to validate cultural practices. That nationalistic drive stems from historical figures like Reza Shah , who promoted the idea of an Aryan Persian identity, and the belief that Cyrus the Great  abolished slavery in Iran. Vaziri's work challenges such misconceptions by highlighting Iran's history of slavery, particularly in the context of films produced after 1953, which reflect the nationalistic ideologies of early 20th-century Iran. Aryanism, a significant nationalist ideology, continues to shape Iran's identity debates, influencing its self-perception as white, racially distinct and separate from its regional neighbors in the Middle-East.
            </p>
            <p>The concluding chapter brings us to the Collective for Black Iranians, a group that emerged in the wake of the Black Lives Matter movement, which serves as a contemporary challenge to traditional historiography. The collective's digital aesthetics and the narratives they spawn push back against the denial of racial legacies in the history of Indian Ocean slavery. The book posits that such digital communities are crafting counternarratives that protest the prevailing state of unacknowledged antiblackness in Southwest Asia and North Africa.
            </p>
            <p>Vaziri’s work is a crucial contribution to media studies, offering insightful critiques and celebrating cinema’s potential as an intellectual stimulant. This book is highly recommended for those interested in the intersection of film, culture, and history, as well as for anyone seeking to understand the profound ways in which our global stories are woven together in the frames of cinema.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Addendum</head>
            <p>In delving into Parisa Vaziri's book, it is fascinating to note the resurgence of an old Iranian song in a modern Bollywood film, sparking renewed interest and appreciation. "Jamal Jamaloo Kudu," a song that first resonated with audiences in the 1950s as performed by the Kharazmi Girls High School's Shirazi Choir, has found its way back into popular culture. The song, which has been a traditional favorite at weddings, was reimagined in Sandeep Reddy Vanga’s film Animal, released on December 1, 2023, with Bobby Deol's character making a memorable entrance to its catchy tune.
            </p>
            <p>This song, with roots tracing back to a poem by the esteemed Iranian poet Bijan Samandar, is a charming duet between a white Iranian woman and a Black man from southern Iran, whose ancestry is linked to Zanzibar. The lyrics convey a tender narrative where the woman expresses her deep affection, while the man responds with lighthearted invitations to dance, admiring her beauty in a playful exchange. The juxtaposition of their distinct heritages within the song’s lyrics and the mutual admiration they express stands in poignant contrast to historical racial tensions.
            </p>
            <p>The enduring popularity of "Jamal Jamaloo Kudu" serves as a cultural bridge, illustrating the seamless assimilation of African influences into Iranian culture. It defies the divisive views often associated with historical intercultural interactions, championing the idea of unity in diversity. This song remains a vibrant celebration of cultural harmony and a poignant reminder of the significance of inclusivity in our global society.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Lyrics of the Song <title rend="quotes">Jamal Jamaloo Kudu</title></head>
           <lg>
             <l>Ahay Siyah Zangi Delamo Nakon Khun</l>
             <l>Oh black beauty don’t Play with my heart</l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
             <l>Vaay To Rafti Koja Manam Chu Majnoon</l>
             <l>You left me, and I turned into a wanderer like Majnun</l>
           </lg>
           <lg>
             <l>Jamal Jamala Jamaloo Jamal Kudu</l>
             <l>Oh my love, my beloved, my sweet love!</l>
           </lg>
        </div>
      </body>
      <back>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="nichanian_2009" label="Nichanian 2009">Nichanian, M. (2009) <title rend="italic">The historiographic perversion</title>. 
             New York: Columbia University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rajan_2011" label="Rajan 2011">Rajan, S. (2011) <title rend="italic">The African diaspora in the Indian Ocean</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Sharre Search</title>, 15 August. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://sharresearch.wordpress.com/2011/08/15/the-african-diapora-in-the-indian-ocean/">https://sharresearch.wordpress.com/2011/08/15/the-african-diapora-in-the-indian-ocean/</ref>. 
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="think-africa_2021" label="Think Africa 2021">Think Africa (2021) <title rend="italic">The slave trade in Black Africans</title>. 
             Available at: 
             <ref target="https://thinkafrica.net/atlantic-slave-trade/">https://thinkafrica.net/atlantic-slave-trade/</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="vaziri_2023" label="Vaziri 2023">Vaziri, P. (2023) <title rend="italic">Racial Blackness and Indian Ocean slavery: Iran's 
             cinematic archive</title>. Minneapolis, Minnesota: University of Minnesota Press.
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
