<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Black Waves in Digital Humanities: Vaziri's (2023) Exploration of African 
               Enslavement in the Persian Gulf through Film</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Zeinab <dhq:family>Parishani</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Missouri</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>zpmmd@missouri.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                 <p><name>Zeinab Parishani</name> is a Ph.D. student and Graduate Research Assistant at the School of Information 
                    Science &amp; Learning Technologies (SISLT) iSchool at the <name>University of Missouri</name>. She is studying 
                    the use of innovative technologies such as virtual reality and video games, and she is interested in digital, 
                    media, and archival studies and human-computer interaction.
                 </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000748</idno>
            <idno type="volume">019</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <date when="2025-03-31">31 March 2025</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <term corresp="#moving_images"/>
               <term corresp="#race"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>Iranian cinema</item>
                  <item>Indian Ocean slavery</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000748/000748.xml">GitHub</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p><title rend="italic">Racial Blackness and Indian Ocean Slavery: Iran's Cinematic Archive</title> (2023) by 
               <name>Parisa Vaziri</name> offers an in-depth exploration of the intersection of Blackness and slavery within 
               Iranian historical and cinematic contexts. The book critically examines how Iranian cinema portrays African 
               enslavement and marginalized narratives, particularly through <term xml:lang="fa">fīlmfārsī</term> and Indigenous 
               theatrical traditions. <name>Vaziri</name> underscores the historiographical neglect of Indian Ocean slavery, 
               emphasizing the forgotten stories of the enslaved. By incorporating maps that trace African migrations and the 
               routes of the slave trade, she enriches the reader's understanding of global history.
            </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Dive into this review of <name>Parisa Vaziri</name>'s <title rend="italic">Racial Blackness and Indian Ocean Slavery: 
               Iran's Cinematic Archive</title> to uncover the overlooked narratives of enslaved African people in Iranian cinema, a 
               rich tapestry of history and film that challenges established truths.
            </p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head>Digital Humanities for Analyzing Culture</head>
            <p><name>Vaziri</name>'s work engages with the historiographical neglect surrounding Indian Ocean slavery and presents a 
               nuanced critique of how cinema both reflects and obscures historical connections. The integration of digital humanities 
               plays a pivotal role in preserving those marginalized histories, and <name>Vaziri</name> emphasizes the archival 
               challenges and the importance of digital preservation in safeguarding <name>Iran</name>'s cinematic heritage from 
               political upheaval and loss. By intertwining race, history, and media, <name>Vaziri</name>'s exploration contributes to 
               broader trends in global cinema, intersectionality, and digital aesthetics, inviting readers to rethink traditional 
               cinematic narratives and embrace new methodologies in digital film studies. Through this critical lens, 
               <name>Vaziri</name>'s work offers both a preservation of marginalized histories and a path for future scholars to 
               address historiographical neglect in film and media.
            </p>
            <p>The origins of this book can be traced back to <name>Vaziri</name>'s doctoral dissertation, which was written during a 
               time of social upheaval in <name>Iran</name>. The 2022 protests over <name>Mahsa Amini</name>'s tragic death provided a 
               poignant backdrop, influencing <name>Vaziri</name>'s approach to gender representation in Iranian cinema. That personal 
               connection adds a layer of urgency and authenticity to her work.
            </p>
            <p>This book begins with a sentence from <title rend="italic">The Historiographic Perversion</title> (2009), a book 
               written by <name>March Nichanian</name>, Visiting Professor of Cultural Studies at <name>Sabanci University</name> in 
               <name>Istanbul</name>. It reads: <title rend="quotes">Historical objectivity regarding facts, the quiet assurance of 
               established history, is no more than a luxury of those who can enjoy truth without conflict</title> (qtd. in 
               <ptr target="#vaziri2023" loc="1"/>). <name>Nichanian</name>'s concept of <quote rend="inline">historiographic 
               perversion</quote> foreshadows a book deeply entrenched in the critical examination of historical objectivity. By 
               opening her book with this sentence, <name>Vaziri</name> shows readers that her work will scrutinize the very foundation 
               of what is commonly accepted as historical truth, questioning the neutrality and assurance of established history. 
               Readers can expect <name>Vaziri</name>'s book to offer a profound inquiry into the writing of history, exploring the 
               influence of power, ideology, and conflict on the construction of historical narratives.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Why Cinema?</head>
            <p><name>Vaziri</name> presents a compelling argument against the contemporary extractive nature of content production. 
               She posits cinema not merely as a form of entertainment but as a powerful medium for reflection and intellectual 
               engagement. Her perspective resonates with the thoughts of philosopher <name>Bernard Stiegler</name>, who eloquently 
               remarks that a <quote rend="inline">process of global unification has taken place through cinema</quote> (qtd. in 
               <ptr target="#vaziri2023" loc="10"/>) <name>Vaziri</name>'s book underscores the unifying power of film to transcend 
               cultural and temporal boundaries, offering a shared space for global narratives and dialogues.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Indian Ocean Slavery and the Lack of Archival Resources</head>
            <p><name>Vaziri</name>'s examination is particularly striking in its critique of the historiographical neglect of Indian 
               Ocean slavery, which starkly contrasts with the attention given to Atlantic and trans-Saharan slavery. That lacuna in 
               historical discourse, compounded by the scarcity of archival sources, is a silent testimony to the marginalized 
               narratives of the enslaved. Related scholarship shows both African migrations across the <name>Indian Ocean</name> and 
               the differences between three slave trade routes: trans-Saharan, <name>Atlantic Ocean</name>, and <name>Indian 
               Ocean</name> <ptr target="#rajan2011"/> <ptr target="#thinkafrica2021"/>.
            </p>
            <p>In her exemplary work, the author articulates a significant challenge in the study of slavery: the scarcity of archival 
               materials. She notes that the narrative of Indian Ocean slavery, as in other regions, is often pieced together from 
               material evidence that was not created by the enslaved themselves, but rather from records shaped by bureaucratic 
               narratives or formalized correspondence. Such indirect documentation creates a barrier to fully understanding the 
               enslaved perspective.
            </p>
            <p>Further, the author highlights the critical role of digital media in preserving cinematic history. She reflects on how a 
               multitude of films, pivotal to her research, would have been lost if not for the digital age. Those pre-revolutionary 
               works, previously at the mercy of inadequate storage solutions, faced further jeopardy from the deliberate destruction 
               during the 1979 Iranian Revolution, resulting in the demolition of a significant portion of <name>Iran</name>'s 
               cinematic infrastructure as well as the loss of countless historical film records. Transition to digital platforms has 
               not only resurrected those films from potential obscurity but allowed for the conservation and continued examination of 
               <name>Iran</name>'s rich cinematic legacy.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head><name>Vaziri</name>'s Contribution to Digital Film Studies</head>
            <p><title rend="italic">Racial Blackness and Indian Ocean Slavery</title> is very much in conversation with contemporary 
               trends in digital humanities, particularly in its emphasis on archival challenges, global and diverse perspectives, and 
               the intersection of media such as film with broader historical and cultural narratives. <name>Vaziri</name>'s book can 
               be seen as engaging with several contemporary directions in digital film studies, especially <name>Burghardt</name> et 
               al.
            </p>
            <p>The critical areas in digital humanities and film studies that <name>Vaziri</name>'s work explores center on archival 
               challenges, media convergence, global perspectives, intersectionality, and cinematic narratives. One of the central 
               themes is the scarcity of archival materials documenting Indian Ocean slavery, as mentioned above, and the role of 
               digital media in preserving these neglected histories. That aligns with broader trends in digital humanities, where 
               efforts to rescue fragile historical artifacts have become essential. For example, the digital preservation of 
               pre-revolutionary Iranian cinema — threatened by inadequate storage and political upheaval — highlights the crucial 
               role of digital tools in safeguarding cultural legacies.
            </p>
            <p><name>Vaziri</name> also examines the convergence of cultural and historical narratives in Iranian cinema, particularly 
               through the lens of Blackness and slavery, reflecting broader trends in digital film studies that analyze layered, 
               transnational narratives. Her focus on African diasporic influences in Iranian films demonstrates how media convergence 
               operates at the intersection of race, history, and culture, situating Iranian cinema within global histories of slavery 
               and migration.
            </p>
            <p>By critiquing the historiographical neglect of Indian Ocean slavery, <name>Vaziri</name> contributes to ongoing 
               discussions about representation and inclusion in global cinema. Her work intersects with Black Digital Humanities 
               (Black DH), which leverages digital tools to amplify marginalized voices and address historical neglect. Black DH's 
               radical and interdisciplinary approach challenges traditional historiographical practices to create more inclusive 
               narratives <ptr target="#prince_etal2022"/>. Projects such as the Real Black Grandmothers archive, the Black Beauty 
               Archives, and the Black Lesbian Archives exemplify this by preserving Black cultural histories and aesthetics 
               <ptr target="#gallon2022"/>. <name>Jenkins</name> and <name>Myers</name> further emphasize how platforms like podcasts 
               act as counter-public spheres, enabling the expression of narratives often neglected by dominant media 
               <ptr target="#jenkins_etal2022"/>.
            </p>
            <p><name>Vaziri</name>'s exploration of African-descended peoples in Iranian cinema broadens global film studies by 
               highlighting underrepresented histories, enriching discussions of intersectionality and marginalized narratives. Her 
               emphasis on digital preservation is particularly significant for films at risk of being lost due to political or social 
               upheaval. Similar to preserving <name>Iran</name>'s cinematic history, Black podcasts serve as digital archives for 
               capturing voices often overlooked by mainstream media <ptr target="#jenkins_etal2022"/>.
            </p>
            <p>In her concluding chapter, <name>Vaziri</name> discusses the Collective for Black Iranians, which emerged in the wake of 
               the Black Lives Matter movement. The collective employs digital aesthetics to challenge traditional historiography and 
               confront anti-Blackness and the legacies of Indian Ocean slavery. Such counternarratives resist the erasure of 
               marginalized histories and foster solidarity within global and digital communities.
            </p>
            <p>Finally, <name>Vaziri</name>'s theoretical approach to Iranian cinema challenges conventional narratives, offering new 
               frameworks for understanding the aesthetics and historical underpinnings of race and migration. Her work aligns with 
               post-cinema discussions in digital film studies, advancing innovative perspectives on cinematic history. By addressing 
               the intersections of race, culture, and history, her scholarship contributes significantly to global film studies and 
               digital humanities, amplifying voices and narratives long overlooked in both scholarly and cultural contexts.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Postcolonial Perspectives in Digital Humanities</head>
            <p><name>Vaziri</name>'s work in addressing the above intersections and inequalities in knowledge production suggests 
               connections to some of the formative work in digital humanities, particularly from scholars like <name>Roopika 
               Risam</name>. <name>Risam</name>'s groundbreaking work, <title rend="italic">New Digital Worlds: Postcolonial Digital 
               Humanities in Theory, Praxis, and Pedagogy</title> (2018), provides a critical framework for understanding how digital 
               humanities can confront systemic disparities in representation and knowledge creation. Putting <name>Vaziri</name>'s 
               book into conversation with <name>Risam</name> may help highlight strategic convergences as well as perspectival 
               differences between their approaches to digital humanities and their potential to foster a more inclusive scholarly 
               landscape.
            </p>
            <p><name>Risam</name>'s <title rend="italic">New Digital Worlds</title> addresses how digital humanities can confront and 
               address inequalities in knowledge production, particularly concerning marginalized communities such as the African 
               diaspora and Black radicalism. The book examines projects like those focused on <name>W.E.B. Du Bois</name>, situating 
               his work within a global context and striving to include Black voices in the digital cultural record, which has 
               traditionally been dominated by Anglophone and white perspectives. <name>Risam</name> emphasizes the need to enhance 
               digital scholarship in fields like African diaspora studies and critical ethnic studies. Her work underscores how 
               postcolonial digital humanities can rectify both historical and contemporary inequities in representation and knowledge 
               production. <name>Risam</name>'s research rethinks digital humanities as a practice that critically engages with issues 
               of race and power, advocating for the use of digital tools to create a more equitable and inclusive scholarly landscape.
            </p>
            <p><name>Risam</name> and <name>Vaziri</name>'s works converge in their focus on enhancing representation and inclusivity 
               in the digital humanities, though they explore that theme from distinct perspectives. Both scholars critique traditional 
               methodologies and frameworks, calling for innovative approaches that address historical and ongoing inequities. They 
               stress the importance of ethical representation, aiming to avoid exploitation and ensure that marginalized communities 
               are portrayed with respect and accuracy. Overall, <name>Risam</name> and <name>Vaziri</name> both view digital 
               humanities as a powerful means for fostering equity. <name>Risam</name> reimagines digital humanities as a practice that 
               confronts issues of race and power, while <name>Vaziri</name> highlights the potential of digital technologies to create 
               more representative and inclusive narratives. Their combined efforts reflect a broader movement within the field to 
               improve inclusivity and challenge established practices.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Digitally Countering Anti-Blackness</head>
            <p><name>Vaziri</name>'s work explores <name>Iran</name>'s history of slavery, particularly as reflected in films produced 
               after 1953. She discusses two iconic films in Iranian cinema that directly engage with the persistence of anti-Blackness, 
               challenging the notion that slavery has no place in <name>Iran</name>'s history. <title rend="italic">Bashu, the Little 
               Stranger</title> (1984), directed by <name>Bahram Beyzai</name>, stands out as a seminal work foregrounding racism based 
               on phenotypic differences. Similarly, <title rend="italic">The Runner</title> (1984), directed by <name>Amir 
               Naderi</name>, portrays the life of a young boy named <name>Amiro</name> in southern <name>Iran</name> whose character 
               is crafted as a reflection of societal attitudes toward race and humanity. The film suggests a perspective of innocence 
               and impartiality, presenting it as a potential pathway to overcoming racial prejudices.
            </p>
            <p>Several other works in conversation with <name>Vaziri</name>'s book have identified how anti-Blackness persists in 
               digital systems, regardless of who is programming them. So too have they highlighted how Black Computational Thought 
               aims to dismantle these systems from an ontological and epistemological standpoint. If anti-Blackness often persists 
               within digital systems, perpetuating violence through computational logics, Black Computational Thought seeks to 
               dismantle these systems by challenging their very foundations, offering a pathway towards more equitable digital 
               practices <ptr target="#morrison2022"/>.
            </p>
            <p>As <name>Vaziri</name> challenges our perception of the history of slavery in <name>Iran</name>, it becomes evident that 
               adopting ethical visualization practices is necessary to mitigate potential harm in the representation of marginalized 
               populations. Adopting an ethical workflow in digital humanities projects, as outlined by <name>Hepworth</name> and 
               <name>Church</name>, involves careful consideration at every stage of data collection, visualization, and publication to 
               minimize harm and ensure responsible representation <ptr target="#hepworth_etal2018"/>. Ethical considerations in data 
               visualization are paramount, as visual artifacts often carry implicit biases that can reinforce existing prejudices. It 
               is essential to adopt ethical visualization practices that acknowledge and mitigate potential harm while ensuring 
               accurate representation <ptr target="#hepworth_etal2018"/>.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Insights from <name>Vaziri</name> on Contemporary Debates in DH</head>
            <p>In the introduction to her book, <name>Vaziri</name> articulates a profound function of cinema: the ability to access 
               the unlived past — those dimensions of history or memory that remain unlivable or inaccessible in real life. Cinema, 
               she argues, becomes a medium for envisioning future possibilities, offering a <quote rend="inline">future 
               kinesthesia</quote>, a space where new ways of thinking and living can emerge. Such transformative power lies in its 
               capacity to record, preserve, and transmit the unlivable into the future. By deferring the unlivable, cinema not only 
               documents but reimagines cultural practices and human experiences, bridging the past and future in ways that transcend 
               the limitations of the present.
            </p>
            <p><name>Vaziri</name>'s concept of accessing the unlived past serves as a meaningful complement to the discussions 
               presented in <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities 2023</title>. In Chapter 9, <name>Frazier</name> et 
               al. argue that digital humanities must actively center the identities and lived experiences of Black communities. Their 
               emphasis on ethical representation underscores the importance of ensuring that digital projects honor and amplify Black 
               voices without exploitation. Meanwhile, <name>Gallon</name> asserts that Black DH serves to unmask racialized systems 
               of power, critically confronting how the digital world often reinforces these structures. For <name>Gallon</name>, 
               studying Black people is inherently a <quote rend="inline">deeply political enterprise</quote> that disrupts the 
               traditional foundations of the humanities <ptr target="#gallon2016"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Such perspectives, rooted in the lived realities of Black communities, complement and expand upon <name>Vaziri</name>'s 
               concept of the unlived past. While <name>Vaziri</name>'s cinema accesses what is unlivable to envision a future, Black 
               DH engages with the lived present to dismantle systems of power and advocate for ethical representation. Together, these 
               frameworks highlight the dual power of digital and cinematic tools to transform cultural narratives, first by retrieving 
               what has been inaccessible and then by centering marginalized experiences in the here and now.
            </p>
            <p><name>Vaziri</name>'s work is a crucial contribution to media studies, offering insightful critiques and celebrating 
               cinema's potential as an intellectual stimulant. This book is highly recommended for those interested in the 
               intersection of film, culture, and history, as well as anyone seeking to understand the profound ways in which our 
               global stories are woven together in the frames of cinema.
            </p>
        </div>
      </body>
      <back>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burghardt_etal2020" label="Burghardt et al. 2020">Burghardt, M. et al. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Film and 
             video analysis in the digital humanities: An interdisciplinary dialog</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 
             Quarterly</title>, 14(4). Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/4/000532/000532.html">https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/4/000532/000532.html</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="frazier_etal2023" label="Frazier et al. 2023">Frazier, N., Hyman, C., and Green, H.N. (2023) 
             <title rend="quotes">Black is not the absence of light: Restoring Black visibility and liberation to digital 
             humanities</title>., in Gold, M.K. and Klein, L.F. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Debates in the digital humanities 
             2023</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press, pp. 140–165. Available at: 
             <ref target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.ctv345pd4p.12">http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.ctv345pd4p.12</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gallon2016" label="Gallon 2016">Gallon, K. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Making the case for the Black digital 
             humanities</title>, in Gold, M.K. and Klein, L.F. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Debates in the digital humanities 
             2016</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled/section/fa10e2e1-0c3d-4519-a958-d823aac989eb">https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled/section/fa10e2e1-0c3d-4519-a958-d823aac989eb</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gallon2022" label="Gallon 2022">Gallon, K. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Looking backward and forward: Pleasure, 
             joy, and the future of Black DH</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 16(3). Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/16/3/000642/000642.html">https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/16/3/000642/000642.html</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hepworth_etal2018" label="Hepworth and Church 2018">Hepworth, K. and Church, J. (2018) 
             <title rend="quotes">Racism in the machine: Visualization ethics in digital humanities projects</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 12(4). Available at: 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1234/jdh.v7i2.123">https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/12/4/000408/000408.html</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="jenkins_etal2022" label="Jenkins and Myers 2022">Jenkins, B.M. and Myers, T.K. (2022) 
             <title rend="quotes">Digital Black voices: Podcasting and the Black public sphere</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 16(3). Available at: 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1234/dhq.v16i3.789">https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/16/3/000641/000641.html</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="morrison2022" label="Morrison 2022">Morrison, R.R. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Voluptuous disintegration: A 
             future history of Black computational thought</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 
             16(3). Available at: 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1234/jdh.v18i2.456">https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/16/3/000634/000634.html</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="nichanian2009" label="Nichanian 2009">Nichanian, M. (2009) <title rend="italic">The historiographic 
             perversion</title>. New York: Columbia University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="prince_etal2022" label="Prince and Messina 2022">Prince, A. and Messina, C.M. (2022) 
             <title rend="quotes">Black digital humanities for the rising generation</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 
             Quarterly</title>, 16(3). Avilable at: 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1234/dhq.v16i3.789">https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/16/3/000645/000645.html</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rajan2011" label="Rajan 2011">Rajan, S. (2011) <title rend="quotes">The African diaspora in the Indian 
             Ocean</title>, <title rend="italic">Share Search</title>, 15 August. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://sharresearch.wordpress.com/2011/08/15/the-african-diapora-in-the-indian-ocean/">https://sharresearch.wordpress.com/2011/08/15/the-african-diapora-in-the-indian-ocean/</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="risam2018" label="Risam 2018">Risam, R. (2018) <title rend="italic">New digital worlds: Postcolonial digital 
             humanities in theory, praxis, and pedagogy</title>. Evanston, IL: Northwestern University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="thinkafrica2021" label="Think Africa 2021">Think Africa (2021) <title rend="quotes">The slave trade in Black 
             Africans</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://thinkafrica.net/atlantic-slave-trade/">https://thinkafrica.net/atlantic-slave-trade/</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="vaziri2023" label="Vaziri 2023">Vaziri, P. (2023) <title rend="italic">Racial Blackness and Indian Ocean 
             slavery: Iran's cinematic archive</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press.
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
