<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><soCalled>Cosmopolitanism</soCalled>, <soCalled>Japaneseness</soCalled>, and Video Game Studies: A Review of Mia Consalvo's <title rend="italic">Atari to Zelda: Japan's Videogames in Global Contexts</title></title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Steven <dhq:family>Braun</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Northeastern University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>s.braun@northeastern.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio><p>Steven Braun is the Data Analytics and Visualization Specialist in
                        the Northeastern University Libraries. He specializes in information visualization
                        and its interdisciplinary applications in digital humanities. He holds an academic
                        background in molecular biophysics and Asian studies (Yale University and St. Olaf
                        College) and a professional background in data visualization. His visualization work
                        explores many different themes, including narrative, representation, language, and
                        perception.</p></dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000433</idno>
                <idno type="volume">13</idno>
                <idno type="issue">4</idno>
                <date when="2019-12-14">14 December 2019</date>
                <dhq:articleType>review</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND"><cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item></item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item></item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2019-10-12" who="murelj">Finished encoding</change>
            <change when="2019-10-11" who="murelj">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>The field of Japanese studies occupies many spaces of inquiry in popular culture and academic
                    scholarship alike, illustrating the diverse ways products of Japanese culture,
                    society, and technology have broadly influenced the global market. In <title
                        rend="italic">Atari to Zelda: Japan’s Videogames in Global
                        Contexts</title>, Mia Consalvo considers yet another lens through which to
                    understand Japan’s influence, namely video games. Exploring Japan’s video games in a
                    variety of contexts – ranging from how individual game players relate to the study
                    of Japan via encounters with video games to how the Japanese game industry designs
                    games for global consumption – Consalvo’s work considers intriguing relationships
                    between cosmopolitanism, notions of Japaneseness, and globalization which open new
                    directions of research for Japanese studies, game studies, and their
                    intersection.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>A Review of Mia Consalvo's <title rend="italic">Atati to Zelda: Japan's Videogames in Global Contexts</title></p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
         <body>
             <p>As someone who has spent extensive time collectively studying, traveling to, and
                 living in Japan, I am well-versed in the myriad ways one might engage with the study
                 of Japan across different media, consumer spaces, academic disciplines, and beyond.
                 Products like anime and manga have entered popular culture well outside Japan’s
                 borders, spurring communities of scholars to research their history and influence in
                 the consumer realm; Japanese technological industries have proven their popularity
                 and preeminence across the globe, fostering in popular imagination a conception of
                 Japan as a futuristic, advanced society; and the study of Japanese history,
                 religion, language, literature, and visual culture persists as major foci of
                 research at academic institutions around the world, areas of inquiry viewed as ways
                 to peer into questions of where Japan as a country has evolved from and where it is
                 going. This work is illustrated by the research of many scholars in the fields of
                 media studies and Japanese digital humanities, including Ian Condry, Molly Des
                 Jardin, Hoyt Long, and Jonathan Abel, to name a few. Scholarship in Japanese studies
                 continues to be defined primarily in these domains, organized around those artifacts
                 of culture, history, and society that seem most distinctly, recognizably Japanese.
                 Yet at the same time, I am also aware of the many ways we encounter Japan on a daily
                 basis in much more banal, mundane spaces, through interactions with products and
                 cultural artifacts of Japan in the global marketplace that we may not realize are
                 foreign in their origin. It is perhaps through such mundane encounters that there is
                 much yet to be discovered as the study of Japan spills into new domains.</p>
             <p>In <title rend="italic">Atari to Zelda: Japan’s Videogames in Global
                 Contexts</title>, Mia Consalvo invites the reader to focus their attention on one
                 such domain of encounters which has historically been both mundane and distinctive
                 in its expression: video games from Japan and the Japanese game industry. Though
                 (disappointingly) making little reference to neither the Atari gaming console nor
                 the <title rend="italic">Legend of Zelda</title> game series, Consalvo’s book
                 succeeds more in the task defined by the second half of its title, positioning the
                 practices of Japanese developers both within the Japanese game industry as well as
                 the global marketplace. In the process, Consalvo endeavors to interrogate the
                 evolution of Japanese games between those spaces through several lenses that assess
                 their relationship with globalization, notions of Japaneseness, and the global game
                 industry at large: how has globalization influenced the ways that video games from
                 Japan enter the global market, and in turn, how have Japanese games influenced the
                 practices of the global game industry? What makes a game distinctly <q>Japanese</q>, and
                 what might this suggest about how such practices have evolved within a rapidly
                 globalizing gaming industry that is both consumptive and agnostic of such cultural
                 differentiation? Using strategies ranging from the organization of multinational
                 development and production teams to the recruitment of specialized localization
                 expertise, the book suggests Japanese producers of video games have developed
                 practices that tug at how consumers relate to video games from Japan, the
                 <q>Japaneseness</q> of those games, and ultimately, the consequences such encounters have
                 for creating communities of players that are globally mobilized.</p>
             <p>Consalvos begins by crafting the framework that is intended to weave in and out of
                 the chapters of the book, one oriented around cosmopolitanism, monolithic
                 <q>Japaneseness</q>, and its origins in <term xml:lang="fr">japonisme</term> and
                 neo-techno orientalism <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="1–15"/>. Though each in turn is discussed as a
                 theoretical buttress for the analyses that follow, these conceptual abstractions are
                 aliases for much larger discourses that unfortunately feel more distantly removed
                 from the structure of Consalvo’s arguments in subsequent chapters than I would have
                 preferred. While Consalvo gives these concepts a basic theoretical treatment in the
                 introduction, I often found myself having to actively position the discussions that
                 appear in each chapter back within this introduced framework, building and
                 rebuilding the recurring thread of analysis along the way. In my own background in
                 digital humanities, the relationship between digital humanities and cosmopolitanism
                 is not readily apparent, particularly in the field of Japan studies where digital
                 humanities approaches are yet nascent and often tangentially attached to traditional
                 studies of history, literature, and culture. Despite wishing for a bit more guidance
                 from the author on this recontextualization, though, I came to understand by the end
                 of the book that these concepts are intended not so much as fixed waypoints but
                 rather as often-shifting concepts that scope the book’s ultimate objective – to
                 understand the study of Japan’s video games as itself an uncertain endeavor that is
                 fraught with ambiguity <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="215"/>.</p>
             <p>Perhaps recognizing this ambiguity, Consalvo proceeds to approach the study with a
                 strategy also fraught with its own shifts in boundaries. In the subsequent chapters,
                 Consalvo explores a different facet of the Japanese video game industry, positioning
                 each within a broader context of the global game industry. To begin, in chapter one,
                 Consalvo discusses her study of a group of several non-Japanese players of Japanese
                 video games, considering the extent to which those games spurred them towards
                 cosmopolitan practices in varying forms <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="20"/>. Their practices range
                 in depth and breadth, from casually studying Japanese language to living and working
                 in Japan, representing a spectrum of cosmopolitan dispositions that Consalvo argues
                 is an expression of globalization in action <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="22–37"/>. In the process,
                 Consalvo interrogates the role that video games themselves have played: are such
                 players predisposed to cosmopolitanism by other means, or did the video games these
                 individuals played cause them to engage in cosmopolitan practices? Recognizing the
                 many different ways cosmopolitan dispositions can be expressed – banal/mundane,
                 consumer, pop, esthetic – Consalvo considers what it means to think of video games
                 as a space of cosmopolitan activation, suggesting that game studies offers a new
                 lens through which to theorize historical definitions of what cosmopolitanism truly
                 means <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="38–40"/>.</p>
             <p>In reading chapter one, I found myself reflecting on my own experience playing
                 Japanese video games. Much like the many individuals profiled in Consalvo’s
                 research, I too was exposed to video games from Japan at an early age and captivated
                 by them without fully understanding what it meant for those games to be from Japan.
                 Here and in the following chapters, Consalvo discusses Koichi Iwabuchi’s notion of
                 <q>cultural odor</q> – or the sense of Japanese origin that comes attached to and has
                 been historically designed out of exports from Japan – as something that the players
                 who were interviewed either embraced enthusiastically or paid little attention to
                 <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="33"/>. For those players who were unaware of the games’ Japanese
                 origin, discovery of their Japaneseness resulted in different responses, inspiring
                 some to study the culture, language, and history of Japan in other deeper ways. As
                 someone whose own early interest in Japan was at least partially informed by
                 encounters with Japanese video games, I greatly appreciate Consalvo’s inclusion of
                 these players’ perspectives for they demonstrate that in game studies, the
                 experiences and practices of individual consumers can tell us much about the
                 industry’s evolution.</p>
             <p>After this focus on players, Consalvo then moves on to discuss the games themselves,
                 conducting an environmental scan of the variety of games produced by Japanese
                 developers across different consoles and genres <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="65–96"/>. Despite
                 Consalvo’s attempt to assert otherwise, however, I unfortunately felt as though
                 chapter three read more like the author’s description of her personal experience of
                 playing games or interacting with different conventions of gameplay in Japanese
                 games, than a holistic assessment of why an analysis of those games is important in
                 the first place. In the end, Consalvo endeavors to position discussion within a
                 larger consideration of Japaneseness, exploring the features of games that make them
                 seem distinctly and uniquely Japanese <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="93–6"/>. As the author
                 demonstrates, games’ expressions can come in many forms – by way of language,
                 cultural reference, gameplay feel, geography, genre, and platform – and as such,
                 pinning down the origins of Japaneseness in such games is as slippery as defining
                 Japaneseness in the first place.</p>
             <p>It is at this point that Consalvo pivots her analysis to respond to this apparent
                 ineffability through more indirect means. Here the discussion of Japaneseness is
                 transitioned away from defining what it is and where it comes from and toward an
                 analysis of those practices that are designed to minimize or erase that very
                 Japaneseness to enhance a game’s consumption in foreign markets – game localization
                 <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="121–3"/>. Consalvo explores the many activities that come with
                 localizing Japanese games for foreign audiences and the variable energy Japanese
                 game companies invest in that process, suggesting that a key recent evolution in
                 Japanese game developers’ practices abroad is the extent to which they work to
                 translate the cultural and linguistic <q>noise</q> of Japanese games into an experience
                 that transcends their foreign origin. It is also where Consalvo elaborates upon an
                 important concept introduced earlier, that of the <q>culture broker</q> <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="103"/>
                 who makes decisions about how to best transform the strongest signals of
                 Japanese origin (in video games) into their analogous expression in other cultures
                 <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="123"/>. In describing the translation-like art of adapting Japanese
                 video games for global markets, Consalvo writes, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#consalvo2016">localized content is never a true
                 picture of another country or culture but is usually more a pastiche of symbols,
                 icons, and broad references. The job of the localizer is more akin to [Mark]
                 Peterson’s culture broker, whose job is to create harmony from the noise or
                 discordance of another language and another culture, complete with its accents,
                 idioms, slang, and shortcuts</quote> <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="126"/></cit>. Consalvo thus suggests that localization
                 experts do precisely this work and are culture brokers themselves; localization
                 endeavors not to necessarily erase a sense of the foreign but rather translate the
                 experience of the original into an analogous experience in societies and cultures
                 outside of the one in which it was created <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="143–4"/>. Much later in the
                 book’s concluding pages, Consalvo rounds this discussion out with an intriguing
                 parallel to early principles of <term xml:lang="fr">japonisme</term>. In the
                 same way that art collectors of the nineteenth century influenced the products that
                 were exported out of Japan to serve the tastes of Western consumers, so too have
                 Japanese video games become directly influenced by and sometimes designed for the
                 desires of foreign markets <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="219"/>. Far from being something to
                 entirely eliminate, however, a game’s perceived Japaneseness can sometimes be
                 regarded by gamers as something desirable, which suggests that localization as a
                 practice can occupy a useful dialogic space between developer and consumer <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="148"/>.</p>
             <p>As we approach the end of the book, Consalvo finally invites the reader to consider
                 yet another lens of Japanese video games at a more macroscopic level, looking at the
                 practices of entire companies and the industry itself <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="149–178"/>. In
                 the same way that individuals can be assessed along a spectrum of cosmopolitan
                 dispositions, so too can video game companies. This is a lens that Consalvo had
                 opened at an earlier point in the book when discussing Square Enix in particular, a
                 Japanese game developer whose games have significant international acclaim. There,
                 Consalvo notes, <cit><quote rend="inline">The company’s activities are cosmopolitan in many ways: its
                 aggressive entry into multiple markets, expanding use of localization, acquisition
                 of Western studios, and ever-expanding portfolio demonstrate its commitment to
                 travel to multiple lands, learn about the other, take risks, and be transformed in
                 the process</quote> <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="119–120"/></cit>. Continuing this conversation against a
                 backdrop that considers Japanese games’ foreignness as an inextricable facet of
                 their mobility, Consalvo posits an intriguing idea: that Japaneseness, when not
                 regarded as something to be actively scrubbed out of Japanese video games, can
                 sometimes be used as a defensive rhetoric by Japanese video game companies to
                 minimize risk <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="178"/>. The idea is rooted in notions of Japanese
                 exceptionalism, or <term xml:lang="ja">nihonjinron</term>, and suggests that
                 since Japanese esthetic preferences in video games are so different from those of
                 Western companies, Japaneseness by default could explain when and why Japanese games
                 fail to succeed beyond Japan’s borders <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="177"/>. In this way, Consalvo’s
                 assessment of Japanese game developers is inflected by a framework that regards
                 Japaneseness and its variable expressions in a globalized, cosmopolitan industry as
                 an integral part of game developers’ practices. In chapter seven, Consalvo explores
                 how such developers use multiple senses of Japaneseness to inform their design
                 processes, noting in particular how they use one sense <cit><quote rend="inline">to refer to design elements
                 that possess an almost ephemeral quality of Japaneseness. This quality holds
                 together multiple beliefs where Japaneseness can be an invocation of the positively
                 valued, weird, wacky, and beautiful, elements of a game as well as of the perhaps
                 alienating, remote, or irreducibly foreign components that Western developers cannot
                 imitate or emulate</quote> <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="184"/></cit>. Here again the author points out how
                 Japaneseness, variably invoked as desirable or undesirable, measurable or ineffable,
                 may be a key component in understanding how Japanese video games have influenced the
                 global gaming industry at large.</p>
             <p>Reaching the concluding chapter, I find myself struggling to reorient Consalvo’s
                 wide-ranging analysis – all the way from individual game players to individual
                 games, localization teams, development companies, and finally the industry at large
                 – within the initial (specific) context that sought to consider the relationships
                 between globalization, notions of Japaneseness, and the video game industry. In
                 considering the many foci the book explores, several questions come into view: is
                 <title rend="italic">Atari to Zelda</title> primarily a study of Japanese
                 video game developers, their rhetorics, and their practices? Is it a study of how
                 those companies have affected the nature of the global video game industry? Is it a
                 study of their games, and how they are consumed in a global context? Or is it a
                 study of Japanese exceptionalism, expressed through a cultural product that has
                 become undeniably globalized in its mobility? The best answer to this question is
                 perhaps that it is all of the above. Indeed, in the penultimate chapter of the book,
                 Consalvo summarizes what feels to me to be the most that can be stated: a
                 recognition that <cit><quote rend="inline">Japanese videogames have influenced Western game developers in a
                 multitude of ways and in doing so have contributed in key ways to a global culture</quote>
                 <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="208"/></cit>. This assertion opens up new opportunities for Japanese digital
                 humanities, positioning the traditional study of Japan, its culture, and the
                 globalization of its products within a reinvented digital understanding of
                 cosmopolitanism that is made mobile by video games and related media.</p>
             <p>In the same way that an attempt to reduce a study of Japaneseness down to observable
                 characteristics would imply that Japanese video games can be characterized in
                 singular, unidimensional terms, Consalvo contends that her research makes clear that
                 it is no longer useful to speak of <q>the video game industry</q> as though it were a
                 singular, monolithic, homogeneous entity <ptr target="#consalvo2016" loc="210–213"/>. Instead, it is
                 better to speak of many industries proliferating in parallel, and in consequence, of
                 the impact of Japanese video games on the practices of specific subindustries of the
                 global market. In the discussion of many Japanese game developers – Square Enix,
                 Capcom, Level-5, Nintendo, and beyond – Consalvo describes several expressions of
                 this differentiation, including the increased permeability and gradual erasure of
                 distinctions between the borders of national and global marketplace, stratification
                 between handheld versus console games, relationships between industry localization
                 efforts and fan translators and ROM hackers, and the rapid emergence of indie game
                 studios, each inflected with the complexity of defining Japaneseness. I found the
                 concluding chapter to be the most useful of them all, for it answered most
                 concretely a lingering feeling of uncertainty that emerged in chapter one. But
                 perhaps Consalvo’s work is successful for precisely this reason, contributing to
                 Japanese and game studies alike a plethora of new questions to explore: at the same
                 time that it is impossible to precisely define the ways that Japanese video games
                 have influenced the global game industry, Consalvo’s imprecision demonstrates that
                 as the industry continues to evolve, so too will the ways in which we understand its
                 influence.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="consalvo2016" label="Consalvo 2016">Consalvo, Mia. <title
                    rend="italic">Atari to Zelda: Japan’s Videogames in Global
                    Contexts</title>. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA (2016).</bibl>
            </listBibl>
           
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
