<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Ends of Editing</title>
            <author>Peter M. W. Robinson</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Peter M. W. <dhq:family>Robinson</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Birmingham</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>p.m.robinson@bham.ac.uk</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Peter Robinson is co-director of the Institute for Textual Scholarship and
                     Electronic Editing at the University of Birmingham. He is developer of the
                     texual-editing program Collate, used by many textual editing projects
                     worldwide, and of the Anastasia electronic publishing system. He is director of
                     the Canterbury Tales Project, and was editor of its first major electronic
                     publication, <title rend="italic">The Wife of Bath's Prologue</title> on CD-ROM
                     (Cambridge UP, 1996). He acts as consultant on electronic publishing to many
                     scholarly groups. He has published and lectured on matters relating to
                     computing and textual editing, on text encoding, digitization, and electronic
                     publishing, and on Geoffrey Chaucer’s The Canterbury Tales. He is active in the
                     development of standards for digital resources, formerly as a member of the
                     Text Encoding Initiative and as leader of the EU funded MASTER project, and
                     currently as UK leader of the InterEdition project.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000051</idno>
            <idno type="volume">003</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2009-09-29">29 September 2009</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace"
                  rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword
                     taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Alyssa" when="2009-06-11">Encoded document</change>
         <change when="2013-06-20" who="Tassie Gniady">Changed "dhq:caption" to "head."</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>Many <q>ends</q> of editing in the digital world may be distinguished. One may speak
               of <q>end</q> as in the supersession of one model of editing (the
                  <q>intentionalist,</q>
               <q>definitive-text</q> model) by another (the multiple texts, multiply-intentioned
               views enabled by digital methods). One may speak of <q>end</q> as in aim: not only
               the aim of the author or authors, but also the aims of the editor or editors. These
               questions were already complicated in the print world; the advent of digital methods
               has both focussed and widened the contests around these concepts. The essay reviews
               some of these questions, with examples drawn from (inter alia) the utterances of the
               two George Bushes, from editions with which the author is associated of Chaucer,
               Dante, and of Armenian texts, from the eColi genome, and from Barack Obama's
               discussion of different viewpoints on the Constitution of the United States. The
               essay concludes that a huge shift is indeed underway in the editing world, towards a
               more open and participatory model of editing and reading.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>The many ends and purposes of editing are many beginnings, many possibilities.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>The Ends of Editing</head>

         <p>Texts, we have often been reminded over the last years, are social objects.<note>The
               arguments for texts as social objects have been given most force in recent decades by
               McKenzie (e.g. <ptr target="#mckenzie1986"/> and <ptr target="#mcgann1983"/>).</note>
            Most certainly, the practice of textual scholarship is a social activity: the concern
            and product of a community. The inaugural symposium of the textual studies working group
            at Texas A&amp;M University, held on the subject of <q>Digital Textual Studies</q> at
            College Station in October 2006, brought together many of the thinkers and actors in
            textual scholarship in the digital age. This was an opportunity to refresh the
            community, and to consider, collectively, where we are and where we are going. The title
            of this essay (which was also the title of my talk to the conference) reflects something
            of the collective purpose of this community, and this conference. The conference itself,
            and discussions around it, spoke out loud that this is an exciting time to be a textual
            scholar. Traditional boundaries are disintegrating, as new opportunities open up around
            us. It is a time of great possibility for us, the fellowship of textual scholars — but
            opportunity brings its own dangers. Times of change are also times of fear, as border
            wars spring up around the moving boundaries of our subject. We are moving, certainly,
            but to where? Do we know where we want to go and how we are going to get there? Where,
            exactly, are we heading?</p>
         <p>
            <q>Ends</q> implies not just end-places: it implies direction and intention, the point
            aimed-for as well as the point reached. For textual scholars, as indeed for literary
            scholars in general, discussion of intention has become part of a larger discourse. We
            know, rather too well maybe, that once a text leaves its author’s hands, it leaves the
            author’s control. Some textual editors, once upon a time, tried to reverse history by
            trying to recover the author’s intentions, and so to establish the text the author
            really meant. Some of us, more recently, have come to see this as a rather futile
            enterprise and have concentrated on mapping the text as social object: it is a thing
            made by many, with the author’s words being only one link in a long chain of
            circumstances. Most of us, I guess, have placed a small bet on both: we would like our
            editions to reflect the author’s words, and we would like to show all the histories of
            the text, too.<note>The most convenient summary of the different schools of textual
               scholarship is given in <ptr target="#greetham1992"/>. A superb dismantling of the
               pretensions and rhetoric of <q>intentionalist</q> and <q>definitive</q> editions is
               given in <ptr target="#shillingsburg1996"/>.</note>
         </p>
         <p>This brief outline points up a major shift in editing practice and theory over the last
            decades. It used to be that editors worried about only one set of intentions: the
            intentions of the author. If we could recover those to our satisfaction, then we could
            recover the text, we could print that, place a seal of approval on it, and feel content
            that we had made the best edition we could, according to the author’s revealed
               intentions.<note>The Committee on Scholarly Editions, within the Modern Language
               Association, may issue a seal of approval for editions which are found to meet
                  <q>professional standards.</q> It should be noted that while the first editions
               approved by the CSE’s predecessor (the Centre for Editions of American Authors) may
               be described as intentionalist, the definition of <q>professional standards</q>
               applied by the CSE has widened considerably: thus, for example, the award of the seal
               to the online Blake Archive. For the CSE, and a list of editions given the seal, see
                  <ref
                  target="http://www.mla.org/resources/documents/rep_scholarly/cse_approved_edition/cse_approved_edition_a_i"
                  >http://www.mla.org/resources/documents/rep_scholarly/cse_approved_edition/cse_approved_edition_a_i</ref>
               (accessed 22 March 2008). For a fuller statement of the history and aims of the CSE,
               see <ref target="http://www.iupui.edu/~peirce/writings/cse.htm"
                  >http://www.iupui.edu/~peirce/writings/cse.htm</ref> (accessed 22 March
               2008).</note> This view of editing rested on a chain of confident assertions. First,
            that the author had a single intention, or at least a coherent set of intentions;
            second, that we editors can recover this intention or intentions; third, that one can
            apply our new knowledge usefully to the text to produce, fourth, a text which is truer
            to the author’s now-revealed intention or intentions. It would be hard to find an editor
            now who subscribes to this set of assertions. Further, a new set of intentions has
            entered the equation. As editors, now we worry about our own intentions. Just whom are
            we making this edition for, and why?</p>
         <p>There is a further complication: texts no longer seem so simple. College Station is the
            home of the George H. Bush presidential library. The single most memorable phrase
            associated with George Bush, the phrase which arguably won him the 1988 election, was
            his declaration <q>Read my lips: no new taxes.</q>
            Millions of people did, and voted for him. But by 1990, there was a new perception:</p>
         <figure xml:id="figure01">
            <head>New York Post headline, Wednesday, June 27, 1990</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>New York Post headline, Read My Lips...I Lied.</figDesc>
         </figure>
         <p>This is the kind of text we textual scholars love. We can argue over the nature of the
            utterance. Did George Bush actually say these words? Does mouthing the words in front of
            millions of people, over many months, make it a text? Did he really mean it? George
            Bush’s statement is a candidate for that wonderful category, of very important texts
            which we all think somebody spoke, but they didn’t actually say. John Sutherland —
            sometime editor of Thackeray, and therefore at least in theory a textual editor —
            produced an attractive list of things people never did actually say: <list
               type="ordered">
               <item>Jim Callaghan: <q>Crisis? What crisis?</q>
               </item>
               <item>Captain Kirk: <q>Beam me up, Scotty.</q>
               </item>
               <item>Sherlock Holmes: <q>The game's afoot!</q>
               </item>
               <item>Rick: <q>Play it again, Sam.</q>
               </item>
               <item>Johnny Weismuller: <q>Me Tarzan, you
                     Jane.</q>
               </item>
               <item>The Bible: <q>Spare the rod and spoil the
                     child.</q>
               </item>
               <item>Hamlet: <q>Alas, poor Yorick, I knew him
                     well.</q>
               </item>
               <item>George W Bush: <q>I know that I have never said
                     there is a direct link between September 11th and al-Qaida.</q>
               </item>
               <item>Wellington: <q>A damned close-run thing.</q>
               </item>
               <item>Nelson: <q>Kiss me Hardy.</q>
               </item>
            </list> In one, and only one of these cases, according to Sutherland, did the person
            credited with saying it actually say it.<note>
               <title rend="italic">The Guardian</title> 3 October 2006, available online at <ref
                  target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/g2/story/0,,1886387,00.html"
                  >http://www.guardian.co.uk/g2/story/0,,1886387,00.html</ref>, accessed 22 March
               2008.</note> Later in the essay, I will tell you who Sutherland thinks it is.</p>
         <p>One could define the business of textual scholarship as the recovery of utterance, and
            the building of texts from utterance. We see now that it is not enough just to recover
            what was actually said: we have to discover who said it, who heard it, what those
            hearing thought they said, what the person speaking thought he or she said — and then,
            repeat that exercise for every act of repeating what was, or was not, said.</p>
         <p>Actually, I think textual scholars always knew this, but it is the business of theory to
            persuade us that what we have always been doing is a new-minted discovery. And, there is
            a distinct difference for us as editors now, a difference that was directly the result
            of technology. Our ambitions, as editors, used to be severely circumscribed by the
            printed page. Among the many things we might report, we might have space to print one,
            and one only: and usually, this was the text of the utterance that we thought we had
            recovered.</p>
         <p>Now, like Texas, the wide-open plains of digital technology lie before us. We are
            invited to fill this space with our editions: how should we do this? What did we do,
            when we first say the endless space of gigabytes of storage? A small history lesson is
            in order. Here is my first, published over ten years ago: Geoffrey Chaucer’s Wife of
            Bath’s Prologue on CD-ROM, published by Cambridge University Press in 1996 <ptr
               target="#robinson1996"/>. Rather notoriously, this gives you all the manuscripts of
            the Wife of Bath’s Prologue, in transcription; in what we now see as rather poor images,
            but which seemed marvellous then; and we also included a full word-by-word collation of
            all the manuscripts.</p>
         <figure xml:id="figure02">
            <head>The Wife of Bath’s Prologue on CD-ROM</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>The Wife of Bath’s Prologue on CD-ROM</figDesc>
         </figure>
         <p>When I look back at this edition, I do wonder: just what did I think I was doing? One
            answer is that I believed then, as I do now, in Carolyne Macé’s wonderful dictum: <q>Every text deserves to be well-edited.</q>
         </p>
         <p>Several of us heard Caroline say this in the European Society for Textual Scholarship in
            Alicante in November 2004. However, she was speaking without a written text, and denies
            that she ever used quite these words: the wonders of utterance, the magic of textual
            scholarship. To me, a <q>well-edited</q> Canterbury Tales in the electronic medium, in
            1996, meant first and foremost to make all the material available. So that is what we
            did: over a thousand manuscript images; tens of thousands of words of transcription;
            descriptions of each manuscript; massive spelling databases.</p>
         <p>But we did not ourselves provide any analysis of all this material. In retrospect, our
            strategy — of publishing materials without analysis — might have been a mistake. There
            was much rhetoric at the time about the glories of so-called <q>un-editing</q>:
            presentations of the documents which were simply that, presentations of the
               documents.<note>See <ptr target="#marcus1996"/>, which emphasizes the need for
               readers to return to the original printings, in order to free themselves from <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#marcus1996">centuries of editorial accretion</quote> (p.
               5) — though Marcus however is aware of the costs of this approach. Similar thinking
               underlies many of Randall McLeod’s writings, for example in <ptr target="#mcleod1982"
                  loc="26–55"/>, and was given a kind of practical effect in <ptr
                  target="#warren1989"/>. But even Warren admits that the editor cannot help but be
               present in the text, as he found himself having to order the text with the parallel
               texts placed first: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#warren1989">Thus I who wish to avoid editing as far
                     as possible find myself, incongruously enough, placing my version before the
                     historical documents.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#warren1989" loc="vii"/>
               </cit>.</note> We were then going through one of those periods of academic
            self-flagellation and guilt, along the lines of, who are we, as privileged, and usually
            male, academics in comfortable western universities, to impose our views on anyone else?
            (Actually, in those days we all had short-term contracts so we were not comfortable at
            all.) Who are we to privilege one text over another, by <q>foregrounding</q> it in some
            way? So welcome to the wonderful world of electronic archives, where all texts are
            equal, where editors gracefully withdraw to leave their readers the maximum freedom to
            make up their own minds about what it is they are reading. By publishing the materials
            without the analysis people thought: ha! An electronic archive! Wonderful! And, as often
            happens, I found myself praised for what seemed to me quite the wrong reasons.<note>For
               example, by Matthew Kirschenbaum in a plenary session of the Society for Textual
               Scholarship in New York, April 2001.</note>
         </p>
         <p>The truth is rather different — or at least, my intentions were different. Our real
            intention, which we declared as often and as loudly as we could but never, apparently,
            often and loudly enough — was to use all the tools at our disposal to try to understand
            the textual tradition. After we had understood the textual tradition, then we would
            think about how we might edit the text, and how we might present what we had discovered.
            By 1996, when we published the Wife of Bath’s Prologue, we had already moved somewhat
            towards this goal. But we had a lot of pressure on us to publish that year. We were not
            ready then to publish the analyses, but we were ready to publish the materials: so, that
            is what we did. We then did indeed publish the analyses in print form, the next year, in
            the project’s Occasional Papers series <ptr target="#robinson1997" loc="69–132"/>. </p>
         <p>We went further than this, in the next major project publication, Elizabeth Solopova’s
            edition of the General Prologue <ptr target="#robinson2000"/>. We included in this a
            full stemmatic analysis and commentary. With various partners, we had developed some
            remarkable tools which we used to make this analysis and commentary. We also included
            the tools we used to make the analyses: the variant database, and the evolutionary
            biology software. We included also a variant-by-variant analysis of the key variants in
            the General Prologue: altogether, many hundred pages of editorial text altogether.
            Indeed, we always intended to include all this in the Wife of Bath’s Prologue: our aim
            did not change between 1996 and 2000.</p>
         <p>But something did happen between 1996 and 2000. Along the way, too, we had found
            ourselves a new aim. When we made the Wife of Bath’s Prologue, our editorial intention
            corresponded perfectly with Caroline Macé’s dictum: we just wanted to edit the text. We
            did not think at all about who might use it, how they might use it. I suppose in this,
            we are like many editors. We start editing a text because we are curious. We want to
            know what is going on inside that text. How did it get made? Where did it come from? How
            did it get published? What happened next? Even when we do come to try to explain to
            others what we have found, we assume that anyone else who is interested in this will be
            prepared to make a fairly considerable effort to understand, as we have done. So, we do
            not have to try too hard to make our editions attractive or accessible.</p>
         <p>This view corresponds to the traditional cleavage between <q>scholarly editions</q> and
            what you might call <q>reading editions</q> — or, popular editions. Scholarly editions —
            the full-dress performances of the Center for Editions of American Authors, or of those
            published in the great Oxford and Cambridge series — were made by textual scholars for
            other textual scholars. <q>Popular editions</q> are made for ordinary readers.</p>
         <p>Many of us, around the mid ‘90s, thought that the electronic medium offered a way past
            this separation of the scholarly editor from the ordinary reader. The web had just hit
            and those digital spaces had got even vaster. Now, we could imagine that we could put
            our edition on the web and everyone everywhere — every reader — could see what we have
            done. We could cut out the middleman, the publisher, the chain of other scholars and
            editors who take our work and repurpose it for different audiences, different
            publications. No, we could do it all: we could take all we have learned, all the
            materials we have so lovingly gathered and slaved over, and we could give it to
            everyone.</p>
         <p>In our General Editor’s preface to the 2000 General Prologue CD-ROM, Norman Blake and I
            put this as follows:<note>Available online at <ref
                  target="http://www.canterburytalesproject.org/pubs/gpgenedintro.html"
                  >http://www.canterburytalesproject.org/pubs/GPGenEdintro.html</ref> (accessed 3
               May 2008).</note>
            <quote rend="block" source="#robinson2000">One might summarize the shift in our thinking in the
               last two years, underlying the differences between the two CD-ROMs, as follows: the
               aim of The Wife of Bath’s Prologue CD-ROM was to help editors edit; our aim now is
               also to help readers read.</quote> So here is a new intention indeed. And following
            this new intention, we asked ourselves, what can we do to reach all those readers who,
            we are sure, must be out there somewhere? One way is to be useful — to include
            information that might help the reader read. Another way to reach readers is to try to
            make our publications attractive. That led us to develop a whole new interface for our
            publications. We took the opportunity to remedy the other deficiencies we saw in the
            DynaText publication system: chiefly, its inability to display a single page of
            transcription at a time, or to do proper keyword in context type search reports. The
            idea behind this was to make this as easy to use as possible, as transparent as
            possible, and even beautiful. I don’t know how far we got towards that aim. But at the
            very least, we did make something which looked nicer than the DynaText interface we had
            before.</p>
         <p>This goes some way beyond just <q>making material available.</q> To speak only of the
            publications we have put out since 2000 under the Scholarly Digital Editions imprint, we
            commonly present what you could call <q>text plus</q>: one or many texts linked with
            many other texts, typically with links from every word in the text to many texts. In the
               <q>single tale</q> publications from the Canterbury Tales project, or in Prue Shaw’s
            edition of Dante’s <title rend="italic">Monarchia</title>, every word in every version
            is linked to every word in every other version. In the <title rend="italic">Parliament
               Rolls of Medieval England</title> every paragraph of transcription of the original
            roll is linked to a matching paragraph of translation into modern English, with further
            links in each parliament to introductions, appendices and images. A different approach
            to <q>text plus</q> was taken by Jos Weitenberg’s Leiden Armenian Lexical Textbase.<note>
               <ptr target="#shaw2006"/>; <ptr target="#given2005"/>; <ptr target="#weitenberg2007"
               />.</note> The Armenian and Greek lexica and wordlists within this distinguish some
            100,000 distinct lexical forms. Every one of these lexical forms is linked to every
            occurrence of any related word through the texts included in the textbase, spanning the
            major period of classical Armenian down to the eighth century. In turn, every word in
            these texts is linked back to its lexical form, and categorized by its part of
            speech.</p>
         <p>It has been pleasing to do this work, and pleasing to bring such editions to readers.
            But I confess that in one way, I am disappointed. We thought that once we had shown that
            you could make such editions like this, many people would follow. Actually, very few
            people have followed. Why is this?</p>
         <p>There are several reasons. The first reason is this: these editions are very difficult
            to make. Making a real electronic scholarly edition is far, far harder than writing a
            book, and takes far, far longer. Anyone who has had anything to do with electronic
            editions will tell you this. Of course it does not have to be that way. You can have the
            library photograph your manuscript, you can stick the photos on the web, you can make a
            transcription in HTML, or Word, or something, you can write a glowing introduction, and
            you can say that is an electronic edition. Certainly, that is much easier. But if we are
            talking about a real digital scholarly edition, one that looks at every word in every
            significant source, which transcribes every word into electronic form, which checks the
            transcript over and over again, which then collates every word in every version, which
            checks and alters and fine-tunes the collation over and over, which then corrects the
            transcription again, then the collation again, which then tries to work out what is
            going on in all those versions by looking at the collation, which then writes a
            commentary explaining all this, then prepares an edited text using the conclusions from
            the commentary, then starts checking how the transcripts, collations, commentaries,
            editorial tools all appear...if this is what you want to do, here is what I will tell
            you. Sell the family dog. Lock the door to your study and don’t come out for twenty
            years.</p>
         <p>A very few people indeed have run this course. Prue Shaw has: she started work on the
            Monarchia nearly forty years ago. She made her first electronic transcripts, using an
            ancient terminal in the Cambridge computer centre, twenty-five years ago. Jos Weitenberg
            has: he began collecting electronic data for his Armenian in the 1970s. He still has, in
            his office in Leiden, an ancient Windows computer running an antique version of Windows
            with a DOS prompt, so that he can use the same programs he has been using for twenty
            years now.</p>
         <p>But if that were the only problem, that would not be too bad. After all, many academics
            like working for irrationally long periods on obscure projects, on texts nobody has ever
            heard of, all on their own, inserting arcane codes into strings of symbols. If making
            these editions just meant working a very long time on your own, that would be fine. But
            it does not. These scholars could not make these editions on their own. At every point,
            they needed our help. For the <title rend="italic">Monarchia</title>, and now the <title
               rend="italic">Commedia</title>: I estimated that Prue Shaw and I have exchanged some
            2000 emails over nearly twenty years of collaboration. We have spent countless hours, in
            Italy, in England, in Australia, poring over the details: how do we transcribe this,
            collate that, show this and that together. As to the Leiden Armenian Lexical Textbase: I
            met Jos first in 1998, and once more have spent many weeks in Leiden; he has visited us,
            in Leicester and Birmingham. I have not even mentioned our work with the Institute for
            New Testament Research in Munster: since 1998, I have spent at least four weeks every
            year, some years more, helping them work out how to move their massive work on the 5000
            or so manuscripts of the Greek New Testament into the digital era.</p>
         <p>There is a model of collaboration which I see everywhere. The model is <q>Scholar + Tame
               Expert</q>: <list type="ordered">
               <item>The scholar does all the scholarly work</item>
               <item>Sometimes, he or she meets with the expert</item>
               <item>At many points the scholar and the expert discuss what is being done; the
                  expert reviews it; takes samples; says what is wrong or right; passes it back to
                  the scholar</item>
               <item>At the end: the scholar passes the work over the expert, who spends much time
                  putting it into publishable electronic shape and finally puts it on the web
                  (usually)</item>
            </list> This is how we worked; this is how I see that IATH works, and how Kings College
            works, and how Michigan works, and how Brown works, and indeed every place that does the
            thing called <q>humanities computing</q> works.</p>
         <p>Twenty years ago, ten years ago, when we were still in what you might call the days of
            heroic experiment, this was the way we had to do things. We did not know how to make
            editions such as these, so a few experts needed to work with a few scholars to make
            them. In Michael Sperberg-McQueen’s metaphor, we were the canaries sent into to test
            that the air was breathable.<note>Quoted by Allen Renear at <ref
                  target="http://www.stg.brown.edu/pub/local/foxinterview.htm"
                  >http://www.stg.brown.edu/pub/local/foxinterview.htm</ref>, accessed 22 March
               2008.</note>
         </p>
         <p>But we are now past this time of experiment. We now know how to make these editions. But
            the model, of many scholars dependent on a very few technical experts, still holds. Now,
            for we technical experts, for the few of us working at the few such technical support
            centres, this is a very pleasant model. In a time of expanding funding for digital-based
            research, we have done well out of this.</p>
         <p>However, this is a broken model. In this model, there are many scholars, and few
            experts. This has all sorts of consequences. It means that the only scholars who can do
            this work are those with access to the experts. Generally, that means you have to be at
            Virginia, or Kings. Or, you have to have a problem that really interests one of the
            experts. Or, you have to have a lot of money: which generally means, you are editing one
            of the <q>canonical</q> texts which everybody has heard of. If you are editing William
            Gilmore Simms, don’t bother. Or, you can marry an expert, or, if the law won’t allow
            that, you can form a stable long-term civil partnership with an expert. This means that
            we divide scholars into the very few who are able to make such editions because they
            have this access, and the very many who stand on the sidelines and watch. We should not
            be surprised if a few of the very many whisper behind their hands, saying, hmm, these
            digital editions, they cost so much, and really they aren’t worth making — the people
            who make them aren’t Real Scholars, and so on.</p>
         <p>We should be moving past experiment, to a point where everyone can do what, so far, only
            a very few of us have been able to do. But we are trapped with a model of how humanists
            work with computing tools which does not allow this. Imagine how absurd it would be, if
            every time you wanted to use email, or to write a Microsoft Word document, you had to go
            consult an expert. It should be possible for any scholar, with reasonable computer
            skills, to make an electronic edition such as those we have made. The solution to this
            is not to create more centres for humanities computing, like Kings or IATH. The solution
            is not to create more experts. What most scholars need is not IATH, and not Kings, and
            not more experts: they need tools and resources to let them do what they want to
               do.<note>I have made this plea in other places. See (for example) <ptr
                  target="#robinson2005b"/> (accessed 3 May 2008).</note>
         </p>
         <p>So: better tools. The tools for making electronic editions — and I know this, because I
            have made some of them — are usable by a very few, and only then with constant
            nursemaiding and attendance from their makers. I am not the only person to recognize
            this. There are some impressive enterprises around, which aim to provide a new
            generation of tools for scholars: the TAPOR tools now emerging from Canada; those coming
            from the NINES and related enterprises in Virginia; the EPT suite which Kevin Kiernan is
            putting together. In Europe, the TextGrid and Interedition partnerships are moving in
            the same direction.<note>For TextGrid: <ref target="http://www.textgrid.de/"
                  >http://www.textgrid.de/</ref>; for InterEdition: <ref
                  target="http://interedition.huygensinstituut.nl/"
                  >http://interedition.huygensinstituut.nl/</ref> (3 May 2008).</note>
         </p>
         <p>The aim must be, as I have put it elsewhere, that any scholar who can make a print
            edition should be able to make an electronic edition. In fact, I think we can do far
            better than this. Our aim should be that every one who can contribute something to an
            edition should be able to do so. Suppose that a knowledgeable reader sees an error or
            omission in a transcript or a commentary. He or she can correct it in his or her own
            view of that transcript or commentary. Then, in Wikipedia-like fashion, the reader could
            republish the corrected transcript or commentary, and others could read them.</p>
         <p>Take the <title rend="italic">Parliament Rolls of Medieval England</title>, for example.
            There are tens of thousands of names included in this. The editors do not provide any
            annotations on these. But other people could. Here is a task for years of work: to
            identify and annotate all these, to allow retrieval of say, all references to the earl
            of Arundel, or to the Isle of Ely, or to all documents dealing with marriage. Take the
               <title rend="italic">Commedia</title>: Shaw is not going to provide any annotation of
            the many hundreds of names which appear in the edition. But others could.</p>
         <p>This amounts to a new paradigm for scholarly editing. Here is the old paradigm: <list
               type="unordered">
               <item>The edition is made by a single scholar or single scholarly group</item>
               <item>The editor determines what is presented and how it is presented</item>
               <item>The editor controls who contributes what to the edition</item>
               <item>Only the editor can alter any word of the edition</item>
            </list>
         </p>
         <p>Here, now, is the new paradigm: <list type="unordered">
               <item>The edition is made by the reader from whatever is available</item>
               <item>The reader determines what is read and how it is presented</item>
               <item>The reader controls the choice of materials</item>
               <item>Anyone can alter any word and invite others to read the altered text</item>
            </list>
         </p>
         <p>Some time ago, I referred to this model as <q>fluid, collaborative and distributed
               editions.</q> Michael Sperberg-McQueen calls it the <q>coral reef</q> model: every
            polyp adds its bit to the whole. Peter Shillingsburg calls these <q>knowledge sites.</q>
            <note>Sperberg-McQueen’s metaphor comes from <ptr target="#sperberg1996"/>; for
                  <q>knowledge sites</q> see <ptr target="#shillingsburg2006"/>.</note> You can see
            elements of this in the blog, or in the many Wikipedia-style pages which have sprouted
            up everywhere.</p>
         <p>This will not happen on its own. Just what is going to be needed, to make all this
            happen?</p>
         <p>First of all, the lifeblood of this is going to be texts made freely available to
            everyone. I want to put the transcripts of Canterbury Tales manuscripts up out there on
            the web, for everyone. If this all works, I am very soon going to see those transcripts
            turning up all over the place, in all kinds of contexts, with all kinds of annotations,
            being used for all kinds of things I did not expect. I think this is wonderful.</p>
         <p>I have to say, not everyone feels this way. There are people who think, I transcribe a
            text. It is my transcription. I want to be the only person who changes it. I want to
            control who looks at it: only my friends can touch it, and even then, only after they
            ask me very politely. Now, the view of the dynamic text I propose cuts right across
            this. In this view, the text belongs to everyone who works on it. Further, anyone can
            work on it, without having to get the permission of anyone else. There are many people
            in the academic world who find the idea that the text they are working on is not their
            exclusive property deeply disturbing.</p>
         <p>I believe that people who think this way are backing themselves into an intellectual
            cul-de-sac. More than that, with one important exception, any texts which come with such
            restrictions are doomed. If you make it difficult for people to use your texts by
            insisting that everyone needs your permission, why, people won’t use your texts. They
            will find other texts, and that is the end of yours.</p>
         <p>I spoke of an important exception. The important exception is this: high-value,
            fully-published work which combines both exceptional scholarly effort with purposeful
            design and publication. An example of this is the Nestle-Aland text and apparatus: there
            are decades of work behind this, by the scholars in Münster, their partners, and their
            publisher. This is of such high value that, indeed, people are prepared to pay for this.
            I expect that some of the materials made by the Canterbury Tales Project, and from those
            publications I showed earlier, will also fall into this category. When our ideal reader
            of the future builds the edition they want to read, they might choose to buy one of
            these, and place it at the centre of their desktop: they will annotate this, and they
            will surround it with free texts from everywhere — some of which they might annotate,
            extend, correct, and pass onto others, also. We don’t need to imagine that everything
            will be free for everyone. Indeed, I think a healthy digital economy of editions will
            have both free materials and paid-for materials, materials which are fixed and materials
            which are fluid, working alongside in a way that has not been possible up to now.</p>
         <p>We have, in fact, a remarkable example already of how collaborative electronic editions
            can be made, read, used, and remade in an endless chain: in what is certainly the
            largest and most productive act of collective making and reading of texts there has ever
            been, and one which, in the centuries to come, is likely to transform our lives. Here is
            one of the places where this reading and making has been happening: <figure
               xml:id="figure03">
               <head>Colibase. http://xbase.bham.ac.uk/colibase/about.pl</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Screenshot of the Colibase homepage</figDesc>
            </figure> This is the ColiBase database, the genome of the E.coli bacteria at the
            University of Birmingham. Here is a fragment of the text of part of the <title
               rend="italic">Salmonella enteritidis</title> bacteria (actually, region 1-20000 of
               <title rend="italic">Salmonella enteritidis</title> PT4 Contig sePT4_219c07_q1kw.).
            This is what is called an annotated gene: <figure xml:id="figure04">
               <head>An annotated gene from Colibase</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Picture of a gene.</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </p>
         <p>Now, here below is the gene itself, with each three-letter sequence spelling out a word:
            one of the twenty amino acids, or a control code: <figure xml:id="figure05">
               <head>The text of a gene.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Picture from Colibase of gene text</figDesc>
            </figure> Over the last decades, evolutionary biologists have created an astonishing
            array of tools to read these texts. For example, you can compare the texts of genes.
            Here is a comparison of part of this gene, <title rend="italic">Salmonella
               enteritidis</title> PT4 with the related region from region from <title rend="italic"
                  >Escherichia coli</title>: <figure xml:id="figure06">
                     <head>Comparison of two genes.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Picture from Colibase of two genes</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </p>
         <p>These, of course, are not just academic exercises. On the basis of diagrams such as
            these, scientists calculate exactly what parts of the genome are responsible for which
            diseases and develop medicines to attack those diseases. This remarkable work has only
            been possible because of the agreement that the heart of this information should be
            freely available to all researchers — an agreement which has not at all excluded
            commercial agents from using this data, since tools and other data are not free. I think
            this is a good model for how we can work together. For us, digital images of original
            sources and transcripts are the raw genome data. Make those available, free, for all to
            use, change, annotate, supplement, compare, discuss, and all things will be
            possible.</p>
         <p>Finally, I want to return to my list of things which people did or did not say,
            according to Sutherland. In the year 2006 when I gave this talk in Texas, during the
            presidency of George W. Bush, it was assumed that it must be the Bush quotation which,
            according to Sutherland, is the one real quotation. Sutherland says, <q>You can hear it, live, on Neil Young's <title rend="quotes">Let's Impeach
                  the President,</title> along with the original quotation in which Bush did assert
               there was a link.</q> This sounds convincing. But actually, so far as I can
            discover from downloading the Neil Young album, it appears that, at the very least,
            Sutherland was listening to a different album from any I can find: there is lots of Neil
            Young on the album, but no George Bush. Indeed, while Young makes many accusations about
            Bush, he does not make this particular accusation. And furthermore, so far as I can
            discover, it appears that Bush never did say what Sutherland says he said. The nearest I
            can discover is this statement, by Bush in a press conference on March 20, 2006: <quote
               rend="block" source="#undocumented">I don't think we ever said — at least I know I didn't say
               that there was a direct connection between September the 11th and Saddam
               Hussein.</quote> And in fact, so far as I can discover, Bush is telling the truth: he
            never did say there was such a direct connection. Indeed, on several occasions he was
            invited by the press to make this direct connection, and each time he refused. Of
            course, he and others did say many other things about Iraq and Al-qaida, but this one
            thing, at least, he did not say. You could conclude several things from this. You could
            conclude that John Sutherland is rather careless with the facts. You could conclude too
            that Bush is not as stupid as his critics think — and maybe, that his critics are not as
            clever as they think they are. But here is where the internet is at its best: in a few
            moments, one can carry out the classic tasks of textual scholarship on this particular
            utterance and text, or rather non-utterance and non-text, and establish (as apparently
            Sutherland did not) that Bush did not say what so many of us thought he did.</p>
         <p>In fact, the story does not end here. In the last paragraphs, I presume that you, the
            reader, think that what Sutherland alleged is, Bush said that there was a direct
            connection between September 11th and Saddam Hussein. Now, turn back a few pages and see
            what Sutherland actually declares that Bush said (or, go to the <title rend="italic"
               >Guardian</title> story published on 3 October 2006, available online at <ref
               target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/g2/story/0,,1886387,00.html"
               >http://www.guardian.co.uk/g2/story/0,,1886387,00.html</ref>).</p>
         <p>What Sutherland actually has Bush say is <emph>not</emph>
            <q>I have never said there was a direct link between
               September 11 and Saddam Hussein</q> but <q>I have
               never said there is a direct link between September 11th and al-Qaida.</q> Now,
            this is a total nonsense. It is such a total nonsense that when I read this, I presumed
            that the end of the quotation was <q>Saddam
               Hussein</q> not <q>al-Qaida.</q> All who heard
            the lecture in Texas thought the same, and indeed Sutherland seems to have think too
            that he wrote <q>Saddam Hussein</q> not <q>al-Qaida.</q> Internally, we edit what we read so that
            it conforms with what we think we know. We all think we know that Bush said, many times,
            that there was a link between 9/11 and Saddam Hussein, so as soon as we see a quotation
            from George Bush beginning <q>I have never said there was
               a direct link between September 11 and...</q> we automatically the last words as
               <q>Saddam Hussein</q> — and fail to see that the
            text actually says something quite different (indeed, it seems that the author himself
            failed to spot this). It is particularly ironic as the whole of Sutherland’s article is
            about how we prefer misquotation to what people actually said — and yet Sutherland is
            guilty of misquotation in the central example of his whole article.</p>
         <p>One may ask, does this matter? Consider, again, the analogy of texts and DNA sequences I
            raised earlier. Among the billions of letters of DNA sequences, only a fraction — as
            little as 2% in the human genome — actually has a known function, in that it encodes
            proteins of clear value to their host genome. The rest is predominantly <q>junk DNA</q>:
            changes in this have no effect on the organism. As I write this, America is in the midst
            of the most hotly-contested presidential campaign in decades. The country is awash with
            words: from the candidates themselves, endlessly repeated, subtly or not so subtly
            altered as they are repeated; from commentators, across all the media, through into the
            street, the home, the workplace. Most of these words will be the equivalent of <q>junk
               DNA</q>: they will float across the airwaves, through our minds and speech, to
            nothing. But some will have a huge impact. A single catchphrase can win the election: we
            have already seen how <q>Read my lips...</q> helped
            George H. Bush in 1988; in 1992 it was <q>It’s the
               economy, stupid.</q> A single error, a single casual phrase, can lose the
            election; candidates and their staffs live in fear of waking up to yesterday’s gaffe on
            the front pages of today’s papers. It is the human equivalent of a single rogue mutation
            bringing on a catastrophic illness. Sometimes, we textual critics ask ourselves, does
            our work matter? Most of the time, the many words we broker are like junk DNA: changes
            in them have no effect. But a few words might, just might, have an effect out of all
            proportion.</p>
         <p>This brings us in a circle, back to the ends of editing: conceived not as an end-point,
            but as an aim. American presidential politics has been a tune playing throughout this
            essay, and it is apposite that we should find illumination of our aims, as textual
            editors, in an argument advanced by one of the candidates for the 2008 election, Barack
            Obama. In his book <title rend="italic">The Audacity of Hope</title>, Obama considers
            different views of the U.S. Constitution. Is it to be understood as
               <q>constructionists</q> (broadly, conservative Republicans) see it, as a fixed set of
            rules for governing a state, so that we can surely determine modern arguments by
            recognizing the original intentions of the framers, as enshrined in the Constitution? If
            so, the Constitution can tell us <emph>what</emph> to think. Or is it to be understood
            as <q>relativists</q> (broadly, liberal Democrats) see it, as a set of documents
            themselves the result of circumstance, which we must interpret in the light of our own
            knowledge and circumstances? If so, the Constitution can, at best, tell us
               <emph>how</emph> to think. Here is the same fault line as that which crosses textual
            scholarship, between editors who strive to uncover original intention towards shaping a
            fixed text and editors who seek to show the multiple contingencies bearing on text as
            process. Obama’s position is that he wants to be neither a strict constructionist nor a
            free relativist. Instead, he proposes the following: <quote rend="block"
               source="#obama2008">The answer I settle on...requires a shift of metaphors, one that
               sees our democracy not as a house to be built, but as a conversation to be had.
               ...What the framework of our Constitution can do is organize the way by which we
               argue about our future. All of its elaborate machinery — its separation of powers and
               checks and balances and federalist principles and Bill of Rights — are designed to
               force us into a conversation...<note>
                  <ptr target="#obama2008" loc="92–3"/>. The impact of his election (in November
                  2008) on textual scholarship remains to be seen.</note>
            </quote> This seems an excellent description of what textual scholarship does. We engage
            in a conversation about the text. It is not just any conversation: we recognize certain
            rules of fidelity to evidence, of respect for opposition views, and (especially) a sense
            that the exact words and the circumstances of their saying matter. This requires that we
            do not carelessly distort the texts under our care, or ignore what they say in favour of
            what we would like them to say. Being a good textual editor is not so different from
            being a good citizen: one ought to listen, ought to try to understand what is actually
            being said, then ought to try to help others understand too.</p>
         <p>In the opening paragraphs of his <title rend="italic">From Gutenberg to Google</title>,
            Peter Shillingsburg wonders at the endurance and beauty of Gutenberg’s 42 line bible,
            and asks, in 500 years, would anyone stand to look at a museum display of the first
            electronic book and would the words <q>endurance</q> and <q>beauty</q> come to mind? I
            think the digital humanities, and what we can do with them, offer something far better
            than a single book, locked in a single library. They offer us the chance to become more
            skilful, better-informed readers. They offer all of us the chance to make up our own
            minds about utterance and text, and not just accept what anyone tells us. After all,
            that was always the best function of books — and with the new electronic books of the
            future, we can do this better than print books ever could.<note>In other articles, I
               have treated more formally the implications of these ideas for textual scholarship.
               See, for example, the concept of <q>fluid, dynamic and collaborative editions</q>
               outlined in <ptr target="#robinson2003"/>, and the article arising from my
               participation in the <title rend="quotes">Ecdotica nelle rete</title> symposium, 10
               November 2006 (a few weeks after the Texas conference), published as <ptr
                  target="#robinson2007" loc="176–191"/>.</note>
         </p>

      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="robinson2007" label="Robinson 2007" key="robinson2007">
               <title rend="quotes">Current Directions in the Making of Digital Editions: towards
                  interactive editions.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Ecdotica</title> 4, 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="given2005" label="Given-Wilson et al, 2005" key="given2005">
               <title rend="italic">The Parliament Rolls of Medieval England</title>, ed. C.
               Given-Wilson et al, Scholarly Digital Editions, Leicester and Birmingham,
               2005.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="greetham1992" label="Greetham 1992" key="greetham1992">Greetham, David, in
                  <title rend="italic">An Introduction to Textual Scholarship</title>, New York:
               Garland, 1992.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="marcus1996" label="Marcus 1996" key="marcus1996">Marcus, Leah S. <title
                  rend="italic">Unediting the Renaissance: Shakespeare, Marlowe, Milton</title>,
               Routledge 1996.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcleod1982" label="McLeod 1982" key="mcleod1982">McLeod, Randall. <title
                  rend="quotes">UN <hi rend="italic">Editing</hi> Shak-<hi rend="italic">Speare</hi>
               </title>, in <title rend="italic">Sub-Stance</title>, 33/34, 1982.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcgann1983" label="McGann 1983" key="mcgann1983">McGann. <title
                  rend="italic">A Critique of Modern Textual Criticism</title>. University of
               Chicago Press, 1983.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mckenzie1986" label="McKenzie 1986" key="mckenzie1986">McKenzie, D. F.
                  <title rend="italic">Bibliography and the Sociology of Texts</title>. The Panizzi
               Lectures 1985. The British Library: London, 1986.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="obama2008" label="Obama 2008" key="obama2008">Obama, Barack. <title
                  rend="italic">The Audacity of Hope: Thoughts on Reclaiming the American
                  Dream</title>. UK edition: Canongate, 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="robinson1996" label="Robinson 1996" key="robinson1996a">Robinson, Peter M.
               W. (ed.) <title rend="italic">The Wife of Bath’s Prologue</title> on CD-ROM,
               Cambridge University Press 1996.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="robinson1997" label="Robinson 1997" key="robinson1997">Robinson, Peter M.
               W. <title rend="quotes">A Stemmatic Analysis of the Fifteenth-Century Witnesses to
                  The Wife of Bath's Prologue.</title> in N. F. Blake and P. M. Robinson (eds.)
                  <title rend="italic">Canterbury Tales Project Occasional Papers II</title>.
               London: The Office for Humanities Communication, 1997.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="robinson2000" label="Robinson 2000" key="robinson2000a">
               <title rend="quotes">Stemmatic Commentary</title> and <title rend="quotes">Analysis
                  Workshop</title> in E. Solopova (ed.) <title rend="italic">The General
                  Prologue</title> on CD-ROM. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2000.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="robinson2005b" label="Robinson 2005b" key="robinson2005b">Robinson, Peter
               M. W. <title rend="quotes">Current issues in making digital editions of medieval
                  texts — or, do electronic scholarly editions have a future?</title>, in <title
                  rend="italic">Digital Medievalist</title> 1.1 (2005), at <ptr
                  target="http://www.digitalmedievalist.org/journal/1.1/robinson/"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shaw2006" label="Shaw 2006" key="shaw2006">
               <title rend="italic">The Monarchia of Dante Alighieri</title>, ed. Prue Shaw,
               Scholarly Digital Editions, Leicester and Birmingham, 2006</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shillingsburg1996" label="Shillingsburg 1996" key="shillingsburg1996"
               >Shillingsburg, Peter, in <title rend="italic">Scholarly Editing in the Computer
                  Age</title>. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1996.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shillingsburg2006" label="Shillingsburg 2006" key="shillingsburg2006"
               >Shillingsburg, Peter. <title rend="italic">Gutenberg to Google: Electronic
                  Representations of Literary Texts</title>, Cambridge University Press, 2006</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sperberg1996" label="Sperberg-McQueen 1996" key="sperberg1996"
               >Sperberg-McQueen, Michael. <title rend="quotes">Trip report</title> on the Text
               Analysis Software Planning Meeting held at Princeton, 17-19 May 1996, at <ptr
                  target="http://cmsmcq.com/1996/ceth9605.html"/> (accessed 17 Nov 2009).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="warren1989" label="Warren 1989" key="warren1989">Warren, M.J. <title
                  rend="italic">The Complete King Lear, 1608-1623</title>, Berkeley: University of
               California Press, 1989</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="weitenberg2007" label="Weitenberg 2007" key="weitenberg2007">
               <title rend="italic">The Leiden Armenian Lexical Textbase</title>, ed. J. Weitenberg,
               Scholarly Digital Editions, Leicester and Birmingham, 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="robinson2003" label="Robinson 2003" key="robinson2003">
               <title rend="quotes">Where We Are with Electronic Scholarly Editions, and Where We
                  Want to Be</title> in <title rend="italic">Jahrbuch für Computerphilologie
                  Online</title> at <ptr
                  target="http://computerphilologie.uni-muenchen.de/ejournal.html"/>, January 2004.
               In print in <title rend="italic">Jahrbuch für Computerphilologie</title> 2004,
               123-143.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
