<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng"    type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.isosch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"     type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns=      "http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc=   "http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq=  "http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:html= "http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
     xmlns:mml=  "http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf=  "http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
    <teiHeader>
        <!-- EDITOR'S NOTE, DON'T AUTOFORMAT IN OXYGEN -->
        <!-- EDITOR'S NOTE, DON'T AUTOFORMAT IN OXYGEN -->
        <!-- EDITOR'S NOTE, DON'T AUTOFORMAT IN OXYGEN -->
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Rondo: A Minimal Single Page Application for
                    Digital Exhibits</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Nick <dhq:family>Szydlowski</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6851-7490</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>San José State University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>nick.szydlowski@sjsu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Nick Szydlowski is the Digital Scholarship Librarian at San José State
                            University’s Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Library, where he is the work
                            lead for the library’s Digital Scholarship Services department and an
                            active contributor to King Library’s Digital Humanities Center. He has
                            co-authored digital projects including <title rend="italic">Robert
                                Morris: Civil Rights Lawyer &amp; Antislavery Activist</title> and
                                <title rend="italic">The Burleigh Family of Plainfield, Connecticut:
                                An Anti-Racist Abolitionist Legacy</title>.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <!-- This information should be added when the file is created -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000805</idno>


                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="volume">019</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2025-09-26">26 September 2025</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/taxonomy.xml">https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/projects.xml">https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/wiki/DHQ-Topic-Keywords; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->

                    <!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new <term> element for each -->
                    <term corresp="#glam"/>
                    <term corresp="#infrastructure"/>
                    <term corresp="#minimal_computing"/>
                    <term corresp="#tools"/>
                    <term corresp="#project_report"/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    
                
                  <term/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>Rondo</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Replace "XXXXXX" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
            <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref type="gitHist" target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000805/000805.xml">GitHub</ref>.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>Minimal computing is a promising conceptual framework for digital humanities
                    infrastructure, but the static site architecture most commonly associated with
                    minimal computing can present a steep learning curve, particularly in a workshop
                    or classroom context. This article introduces Rondo, a new minimal framework for
                    digital exhibits which requires no software installation or command line
                    interaction. Rondo differentiates itself from static site tools by adopting a
                    single page application architecture with data stored in a Google Sheet, but it
                    includes tools to disconnect from Google Sheets and create a static site with no
                    external dependencies. Rondo’s reliance on Google Sheets reflects an approach to
                    computing which draws inspiration from Agnès Varda’s film <title rend="italic">The Gleaners and I</title>. Gleaning, the practice of collecting food or
                    other resources left behind by commercial enterprises like farming, is proposed
                    as a productive framework for exploring the relationship between digital
                    humanities and the technology industry. Rondo’s integration with the Digital
                    Public Library of America presents another way to explore the possibilities of
                    small acts of curation, criticism, and juxtaposition using resources gleaned
                    from larger institutions and corporations.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>Inspired equally by minimal computing principles and by Agnès Varda’s film <title rend="italic">The Gleaners and I</title>, Rondo is a single page application
                    for building complete digital exhibits from a Google Sheet.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <quote rend="block">"Gleaning is the spirit of years past. My mother would say, ‘Pick up
                what’s left so nothing’s wasted.’ But sadly we no longer do, because machines are so
                efficient nowadays.” From <title rend="italic">The Gleaners and I</title> by Agnès
                Varda (2000)</quote>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>While minimal computing is strongly associated with the use of static site
                    generators as a mode of web development <ptr target="#dombrowski_2022"/>, the
                    principles of minimal computing can also be applied to other website
                    architectures. Rondo is a tool for creating digital exhibits according to
                    minimal computing principles, but – in contrast to existing tools – it is built
                    as a single page application. <note>Code for Rondo is available at
                        <ref target="https://github.com/sjsu-library/rondo">https://github.com/sjsu-library/rondo</ref>, and the demonstration and tutorial
                        site for the project is available at
                        <ref target="https://sjsu-library.github.io/rondo/">https://sjsu-library.github.io/rondo/</ref>.</note> Rondo sites are primarily
                    built using a templated Google Spreadsheet that stores data about exhibit items,
                    pages, and site configuration. The Rondo site connects to the Google Sheet via
                    an application programming interface (API) and uses the data from the
                    spreadsheet to configure the site and display its content. Once the site is
                    completed, Rondo has tools to disconnect from Google Sheets and run on local
                    data files.</p>
                <p>This project is intended for practical use, but it is also an exploration of what
                    it might mean to apply the principles of minimal computing to web architectures
                    other than static sites, and, in particular, what approaches prove most
                    welcoming for users with less web development experience. As much as its
                    architecture, Rondo’s reliance on Google Sheets is a departure from typical
                    minimal computing practice. This dependency raises the question of what
                    relationship, if any, minimal computing practitioners have to the corporations
                    that make up the technology industry. At the same time, this architecture allows
                    for an approach that requires both less technical background and less
                    infrastructure than static site generator approaches.</p>
                <p>As we pursue strategies for web development that are both more inclusive and less
                    resource-intensive, I want to propose a model for thinking about the
                    relationship between individual practitioners and the tech industry. In Agnès
                    Varda’s film <title rend="italic">Les Glaneurs et La Glaneuse</title>
                    <ptr target="#varda_2000"/>, she explores the practice of gleaning or gathering
                    food or other resources that have been thrown out or left behind. In the most
                    traditional form of gleaning, gleaners follow the harvest, collecting food that
                    farmers and their employees leave behind in the field. In addition to this
                    agricultural form of gleaning, which is legally protected in France, Varda’s
                    documentary reveals a host of parallel practices in more urbanized settings and
                    goes on to posit the filmmaker herself as a gleaner, collecting left behind bits
                    of experience and beauty and transforming them into a way of life <ptr target="#king_2007"/>. </p>
                <p>As minimal computing practitioners negotiate their relationship with powerful
                    technology companies, I would argue that Varda’s re-imagination of gleaning as a
                    cultural as well as economic practice is an illuminating model. Rather than
                    becoming fully enmeshed in, and dependent on, the environments created by large
                    corporations, perhaps we can instead glean just what we need from what they
                    leave behind. As gleaners, we would know that the free food or free server space
                    is likely to be in a different place tomorrow, so we wouldn't allow ourselves to
                    become too dependent on any one tool or platform. At the same time, we would
                    acknowledge that we don’t live in a world or environment that we can fully
                    control, and that rather than trying to own everything we use, we can find a way
                    in the world by gleaning what we need from those who have more than us. In this
                    way, Rondo enables users to glean from Google Sheets and GitHub Pages, but also
                    to create sites that can stand on their own when those free resources are no
                    longer available.</p>
                <p>In describing the impetus behind Rondo, this gleaning orientation, or what <ptr target="#croft_2018"/> calls <quote rend="inline">the gleaner’s
                        gaze,</quote> pops up again and again. It is especially present in Rondo’s
                    integration with the Digital Public Library of America, a feature which
                    encourages small projects that make creative reuse of existing digital
                    collections. Particularly when combined with the principles of minimal
                    computing, the gleaner’s gaze reveals possibilities in the cracks of our
                    existing technical and scholarly infrastructure, and it is up to us to exploit
                    those cracks and look for ways of working inside them.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Precedents and Inspirations</head>
                <p>Rondo is very much inspired by the joys and challenges of attempting to practice
                    minimal computing in a digital humanities and library context. In many ways, it
                    is an homage and possible companion to Wax, the popular framework for creating
                    digital exhibits as static sites. <ptr target="#nyrop_n.d."/>, or analogous
                    tools like Collection Builder, created using University of Idaho’s Lib-STATIC
                    framework <ptr target="#wilke_2024"/>. In this section, I will describe how its
                    development and approach were shaped by this particular context and the
                    constraints it imposes.</p>
                <p>As a librarian tasked with creating and supporting new digital humanities
                    projects and digital exhibits, I eagerly adopted Wax, and I was part of teams
                    that created two projects hosted on Wax: <title rend="italic">Betita Martínez: A
                        Memorial Exhibit</title>
                    <ptr target="#blackmer-reyes_2022"/> and <title rend="italic">The Unionist
                        Unified: Connecticut's First Immediate Abolitionist Newspaper</title>
                    <ptr target="#rycenga_2023"/>. In production, on projects with small teams and
                    where I was the sole web developer, Wax was a fantastic solution. Hosting Wax
                    sites on GitHub pages solved our most significant potential problem, which was
                    that neither of these projects had any financial resources to devote to web
                    hosting, either in the short or long term.</p>
                <p>The challenges we would face with Wax became more apparent when trying to design
                    workshops on how to use Wax. It proved challenging to install development
                    environments for Wax on university-owned hardware. In an environment where users
                    are not administrators on their own hardware, it was quite challenging to get
                    the Wax environment up and running. This raised the first question that Rondo
                    tries to solve: Is it possible to do minimal computing in a way that is more
                    compatible with the restrictions that many academic users are likely to face in
                    the workplace? This would require a framework where the site creator is not
                    required to install software in order to create the site. <ptr target="#dombrowski_2022"/> and <ptr target="#brooks_2021"/> report similar
                    challenges in teaching with static site generators.</p>
                <p><ptr target="#risam_2022"/> write that <quote rend="inline">minimal computing
                        connotes digital humanities work undertaken in the context of some set of
                        constraints.</quote> The inability to install software is a frequent
                    constraint in the workplace both inside and outside academia. Content management
                    systems that can be administered within a web browser are a ubiquitous solution
                    to this constraint, and once installation or hosting is in place, platforms like
                    Omeka provide a fully-browser based solution for digital exhibits. However,
                    dedicated software requires significant IT and network resources – what if you
                    could build a digital exhibit without installing software, and without having
                    access to a dedicated platform?</p>
                <p>The next key point in the imagining of Rondo came from observing how
                    collaborators who were new to digital projects embraced the spreadsheet-based
                    workflow of Wax and applied that workflow even in unanticipated parts of the
                    project. In Wax, exhibit items are created by processing a CSV or other data
                    file, and so the workflow typically begins with a metadata spreadsheet. I
                    noticed that my collaborator then created a spreadsheet for the pages that would
                    appear on the site, and added the text and other information for each of the
                    site’s pages there. It was easy enough for me to then build those pages in
                    markdown files for the Wax site, but this also struck me as a key insight on
                    what users might expect from this kind of workflow – if items are created via
                    spreadsheet, creating pages the same way starts to make a lot of sense.</p>
                <p>The third inspiration for Rondo came during the planning of King Library’s
                    Digital Humanities Center. This center is a collaboration between SJSU’s College
                    of Humanities and the Arts, SJSU’s University Library, and the San José Public
                    Library. In imagining how we might support projects from community groups and
                    individuals that are users of the San José Public Library, the need for tools
                    that addressed a wider variety of constraints became apparent. At this point we
                    had moved the SJSU Library’s work on digital exhibits to an Omeka S installation
                    that allowed us to involve more library staff and faculty, and to support
                    student-led exhibits inside and outside the classroom. But in planning for work
                    with outside groups, we anticipated a need to create projects that were not tied
                    to university IT infrastructure, and could be maintained long term by smaller
                    organizations <ptr target="#king-library-dhc_2024"/>.</p>
                <p>These then were the three primary constraints that informed the technical
                    decisions behind Rondo:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>The architecture supports site creators and developers who cannot install
                        specific software</item>
                    <item>As much as possible, the entire site can be created via spreadsheet</item>
                    <item>The resulting site is not tied to a specific hosting environment – like
                        static sites, it can easily be moved from one server to another</item>
                </list>
                <p>These requirements informed the choice to design Rondo as a single page
                    application, and influenced many of the smaller decisions that would arise in
                    the development process.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Single Page Applications</head>
                <p>The single page application (SPA) has proved to be a durable architecture for web
                    services, used in a wide variety of contexts. In the single page model, an
                    entire site or service is delivered from one HTML document. This single page
                    retrieves and displays content based on the context and the user’s actions,
                    typically via JavaScript. Familiar single page applications include Google’s
                    Gmail, Maps, and Drive services, along with Facebook, Twitter, and Netflix <ptr target="#w3-lab_2022"/>. </p>
                <p>Single page applications are not inherently minimal, but they are also not
                    inherently “maximal” or resource-intensive. In general, the resources that SPAs
                    require can be divided between resources required within the browser, or on the
                    user’s side, and resources required to manage and provide the data, or on the
                    server side. On the browser side, SPAs generally require the user to have
                    JavaScript enabled in their web browser. Beyond this basic requirement,
                    individual applications may demand more or less processing power from the user’s
                    device – it is equally possible to design single page applications that require
                    very little processing power as it is to design applications that are so
                    demanding that they lag or perform poorly on older or less powerful devices <ptr target="#gavrila_2019"/>
                    <ptr target="#mukhiya_2018"/>
                    <ptr target="#scott_2015"/>.</p>
                <p>Similarly, the server side of an SPA may demand either a high or low level of
                    resources, as well as a high or low level of technical maintenance and
                    expertise. Many SPAs retrieve their data from one or more APIs, and the systems
                    that provide these interfaces can be complex or simple.</p>
                <p>The server side of an SPA can consist of any configuration, as long as that
                    configuration can provide the data that the browser requests. In Rondo, that
                    data can either be provided by the Google Visualization API <ptr target="#google_n.d."/> or by a small set of local data files. The
                    Visualization API is used because, unlike other options for retrieving data from
                    Google Sheets, it does not require any API keys or special configuration when
                    working with public spreadsheets.</p>
                <p>When using local data files, the suggested workflow is to first build the site
                    using a connected Google Sheet, and then to separate the site from Google Sheets
                    using Rondo’s built in localization tools. This results in a static single page
                    application which retrieves its data from three locally-stored files. These
                    files store the site data as JSON. This arrangement aims to bring some of the
                    advantages of static site generators like Jekyll to the single page
                    architecture. A localized Rondo site has no database connection and can run
                    locally on any simple web server, or on GitHub Pages. The localized site no
                    longer depends on Google Sheets or any external API. Not having to rely on a
                    database or back-end is one thing that makes static sites so attractive from a
                    maintenance and preservation perspective, and a static single page application
                    shares this advantage. However, this approach adds challenges for sites that
                    require regular updates. These trade-offs and possible approaches to address
                    them will be discussed in more detail below.</p>
                <p>On the browser side, Rondo is designed to provide the basic functionality
                    required for digital exhibits while placing relatively minimal demands on the
                    browser. The single page architecture tends to require a bit more from the
                    browser as the page loads, with the trade-off that subsequent interactions such
                    as searches or page changes require few resources. For sites with a very large
                    number of items, there may be a noticeable delay the first time a user loads the
                    site, but once the site is loaded it should respond quickly to navigation and
                    new requests.</p>
                <p>Rondo’s browser interactions and functionality rely on a small set of open-source
                    resources. Rondo uses the minimal CSS framework Pico <ptr target="#larroche_n.d."/>. It relies on the ubiquitous and well-established
                    JavaScript library jQuery <ptr target="#openjs-foundation_n.d."/>, and its
                    search functionality is provided by the jQuery plugin DataTables <ptr target="#sprymedia_n.d."/>. Another JavaScript library, Markdown it! <ptr target="#markdown-it_2024"/> enables the use of Markdown when building pages
                    in Rondo.</p>
                <p>Rondo itself is intentionally very small. The JavaScript code is currently fewer
                    than 700 lines, and the local CSS is fewer than 200. This is just enough to
                    provide the basic functionality of a digital exhibit – to organize and search
                    collection materials, to build pages and curate items thematically, and to
                    include items within pages. The next stage in developing Rondo will most likely
                    be determining the best ways to add functionality such as mapping, timelines,
                    and other data visualizations while retaining both ease of use and a small
                    footprint.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Constraints We Take for Granted</head>
                <p>By encouraging us to think about computing under constraints, the impetus to
                    minimal computing can also help to highlight those constraints that we have come
                    to take for granted. This can especially occur when practices adopted under
                    constraints become second nature - when over time our work-arounds become our
                    workflows.</p>
                <p>As an example, in a recent conversation with a student employee who was working
                    on a different project, the student asked me why the library would rely on
                    jQuery and DataTables as the architecture for a project rather than choosing an
                    application development framework like React or Next.js. I replied that the main
                    reason we were working this way is that we needed the component to be embedded
                    in multiple content management systems, rather than to function as its own
                    standalone application. While it’s possible to build that kind of widget in a
                    contemporary framework like React, it isn’t necessarily the kind of task those
                    frameworks are built to accomplish. Because we are working in an educational
                    environment where we already have to integrate a lot of different third-party
                    tools and platforms, the less structured approach tends to work for us.</p>
                <p>While not entirely satisfying, this was probably a good-enough response in that
                    moment. The question did make me reflect, though, on just how specific and in
                    some cases constrained the development environments that many of us work in are.
                    I started using jQuery and DataTables as a solution to a variety of problems in
                    a situation where our library had no real access to server resources outside of
                    the university’s content management system. We developed a journal website, a
                    federated search for prospective students, and a handful of smaller widgets, all
                    with the same basic framework, and all sitting on top of a standard webpage in
                    the university’s website. So this was how I learned to do a kind of web
                    development in a quite resource-constrained environment, and it is a way of
                    working that responds to a category of constraints that I think are present, in
                    some form or other, in most educational environments, especially for staff and
                    faculty who are not full-time web developers. </p>
                <p>This student would probably have the same question about Rondo – why doesn’t it
                    use a framework? – and in this case it would be an even better question, and I
                    would have to come up with a different self-justification, since Rondo is a
                    freestanding application and doesn’t have to be compatible with a variety of
                    content management systems. After all, frameworks like React and Angular were
                    developed specifically to make it easier to build and develop single page
                    applications like Rondo.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, not using a framework may be exactly what makes Rondo a <hi rend="italic">minimal</hi> single page application. The impacts of using or
                    not using a framework are primarily or entirely on the development and
                    maintenance process – the end user and site creator are not likely to know or
                    care how the code was assembled. In development and maintenance, using a
                    framework tends to create a higher barrier of entry to contribute or modify the
                    code. To work in JavaScript, you need to know JavaScript. To work in React, you
                    need to know JavaScript and React. In a community where many web developers are
                    also educators or students, this lower barrier to entry can make a meaningful
                    difference in who can use, maintain, and contribute to a project. </p>
                <p>In practice, minimal computing may encourage us to assess our assumptions about
                    what a web developer skill set looks like. Tools that are designed for full-time
                    developers working within industry may actually be a poor fit for digital
                    humanities practitioners, or even for web developers working in education more
                    generally. Coding languages, development frameworks, and other development tools
                    are designed with the needs of specific communities and work environments in
                    mind. Their benefits, affordances, and shortcomings can be opaque to those who
                    come to them from outside their assumed context. It is no coincidence that React
                    and Angular were developed by Google and Meta for the use of their own employees
                    – these are tools for web development at an industrial scale. </p>
                <p>Some may respond that the web itself has evolved into a commercial or industrial
                    environment, and it is hard to argue against that point of view. In that
                    context, Varga’s embrace of gleaning, of surviving on things that have been left
                    behind, of subsisting rather than competing, is even more of a model. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>But Is This Really Minimal Computing?</head>
                <p>Rondo’s most glaring departure from established minimal computing practices is
                    its dependence on Google Sheets. While it is possible to disconnect a Rondo site
                    from Google’s infrastructure, the initial site creation process assumes a user
                    who is willing and able to use Google Sheets. </p>
                <p>On one hand, a work-around for this constraint might be relatively
                    straightforward. Since Rondo is configured to work with data in the JSON format
                    output by Google’s Visualization API, any workflow that converts between a more
                    conventional CSV format and this JSON format would allow Rondo to work with
                    other spreadsheet programs, though not with the same immediacy as users
                    experience with Google Sheets. However, it may be more interesting to pause with
                    this contradiction as an example of the persistent materiality of computing, a
                    constraint that minimal computing foregrounds but does not remove. Servers must
                    exist somewhere, and they are never actually free to buy, operate, or maintain.
                    This may be a situation where adopting a gleaning approach frees us to take
                    advantage of available infrastructure while strategically avoiding
                    over-dependence on resources that we cannot own or control.</p>
                <p>It is possible to imagine and even build a computing environment constructed
                    entirely from software that is both open source and not controlled by the
                    technology industry<note>Some of the most popular open-source frameworks were
                        developed within technology companies. For instance, Android, Angular, and
                        Kubernetes from Google; and React, PyTorch, and Llama from Meta. </note>.
                    Such an environment is not likely, however, to be compatible with the additional
                    constraints that are present in most academic environments, or other workplaces,
                    such as restrictions that prevent end users from installing software. In the
                    end, we all have to choose which parts, if any, of the corporate computing
                    environment we wish to embrace and take advantage of. While static site
                    generators like Wax are not tied to any particular environment, in practice they
                    are often configured to take advantage of Microsoft’s continued provision of
                    free server space and Jekyll integration on GitHub Pages. </p>
                <p>Here, adopting the gleaner’s gaze might reveal a different side of the situation.
                    It is certainly possible to develop Rondo so as to eliminate its reliance on
                    Google Sheets. However, it is worth asking whether that would be a worthwhile
                    use of scarce technical resources. Perhaps there is something not just
                    acceptable, but positive about gleaning value - in this case a back end database
                    for our simple digital exhibits - from the free offerings and other left-behind
                    resources of large corporations.</p>
                <p>In adopting this approach, Rondo draws inspiration from the Knight Lab’s popular
                    tools, in particular TimelineJS <ptr target="#knight-lab_n.d."/>, which
                    similarly relies on Google Sheets as its data source. The interface for creating
                    a new TimelineJS embed code or link also serves as the model for Rondo’s Easy
                    Builder feature, which is being developed to make the process of creating a
                    first site in Rondo even simpler.</p>
                <p>Rondo’s reliance on Google Sheets for data storage can also be seen as a practice
                    developed in response to common constraints found in a higher education or
                    academic library environment. As discussed briefly above, many of the specific
                    methods used in Rondo have precedents in projects I was part of while working
                    for Boston College Law Library. That context provided a set of technical
                    constraints that required creating some complex user interactions purely in the
                    front end – our small team created many components that sat on a page of a
                    content management system, but accessed data from Google Sheets or local JSON
                    files. Like Rondo, most of these tools use the Datatables jQuery plugin to
                    provide search and other interactions. Some of these projects have been stable
                    in production for almost a decade, arguing for the stability and reliability of
                    these approaches. These projects are not unusual in their use of these tools,
                    but I mention them to demonstrate that the methods used in Rondo arise from the
                    specific sets of constraints that I have encountered practicing digital
                    humanities and web development more generally in an educational setting. Example
                    projects still in production at Boston College Law School include Fusion Search,
                    a federated search intended for prospective students <ptr target="#boston-college-law-school_n.d."/> and the library’s new books list
                        <ptr target="#boston-college-law-library_n.d."/>. The basic structure of
                    Rondo, and in particular the way items are handled, is drawn from these
                    projects, and I want to make this progression explicit in order to suggest that
                    methods developed under constraints in other domains may be fruitfully applied
                    in a digital humanities context as well. Additional examples might include
                    Andrew Lison’s exploration of the Gemini protocol <ptr target="#lison_2022"/> and the adoption of Tor
                    by some public libraries <ptr target="#lund_2019"/>.
                    Practices like zine making, developed under constraints in environments far
                    outside higher education <ptr target="#duncombe_1997"/> have also become widely
                    accepted as pedagogical practices <ptr target="#creasap_2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#scheper_2023"/>.</p>
                <p>Lastly, the idea of building a simple website with Google Sheets is not as new or
                    radical as it might sound. As two examples, <ptr target="#davenport_2019"/>
                    describes a process for building a site using the Google Sheets API, and <ptr target="#bradley_2023"/> reports on a library-based project with a similar
                    structure.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Small Acts of Curation</head>
                <p>The Digital Public Library of America (DPLA) is a metadata aggregator which
                    brings together digitized collections from United States libraries, archives,
                    and other cultural heritage institutions. The DPLA harvests descriptive records
                    of digital collections from state, regional, or subject hubs. These hubs in turn
                    collect and aggregate descriptive metadata from individual institutions. In
                    addition to serving metadata to DPLA, many hubs share their collections on their
                    own websites <ptr target="#sandy_2016"/>.</p>
                <p>Rondo’s features include support for a workflow or recipe for building small,
                    curated sites based partly or entirely on items selected from the DPLA. The DPLA
                    allows users to search over 50 million items, and to assign individual items to
                    personalized lists, a feature DPLA calls My Lists.</p>
                <p>Interestingly, this My Lists function is implemented without requiring users to
                    log in or provide personal information. Instead, it relies only on cookies, and
                    so is tied to a specific browser on a specific device. This is a much more
                    minimal approach to site personalization than the one pursued by most projects,
                    especially larger projects like DPLA. Importantly, this approach is fully
                    functional from the user perspective, but it does not provide the site owner
                    with the same opportunities to gather commercially valuable data about users
                    that a more conventional approach that requires users to log in would
                    create.</p>
                <p>Users of this feature can export a CSV file with basic metadata for each item on
                    a list, including a link to a thumbnail image. Rondo’s spreadsheet is arranged
                    so that users can copy and paste this metadata directly into the spreadsheet and
                    begin working with a set of items from DPLA, complete with thumbnails and basic
                        descriptions.<note> Other widely-used databases that offer similar
                        functionality include Hathi Trust and WorldCat, and it would be reasonably
                        straightforward using a spreadsheet to transform metadata exported from
                        those systems into the format expected by Rondo. It might also be fruitful
                        to explore possible integrations with open APIs like those offered by the
                        Metropolitan Museum of Art and Europeana, among others. Working with these
                        APIs would require a different workflow; one approach might be to create
                        tools for harvesting metadata from these APIs into a Google Spreadsheet
                        using Google Apps Scripts.</note>
                </p>
                <p>This workflow is intended to suggest a wide variety of possible classroom or
                    workshop assignments, inviting students to engage with, organize, and write
                    about the primary materials in DPLA. Outside the classroom this recipe suggests
                    the possibility for digital humanities projects to be small acts of curation or
                    criticism.</p>
                <p>Placing value on small projects is a different kind of intervention than the one
                    proposed through minimal computing, though the two ideas can complement one
                    another. Minimal computing is strongly associated with the adoption or
                    acceptance of constraints <ptr target="#risam_2022"/>. This framing is valuable,
                    but it is also suggestive. The foregrounding of constraints suggests that some
                    person, group, or project is being constrained – that the creator wants to go
                    farther and do more, but is held back in some way. The language of minimal
                    computing can suggest grand scholarly and curatorial ambitions which have to be
                    reined in or redirected. And what is it that constrains these ambitions? </p>
                <p>I think it is fair to say that, collectively, the ambitions of digital humanities
                    as a field of activity are heavily constrained by a lack of financial resources.
                    Compounding this challenge, funders have historically favored projects which
                    focus on White men over women or people of color, increasing the gap between
                    ambition and resources for many valuable projects <ptr target="#martin_2016"/>.
                    Even past their creation, projects require maintenance and preservation, an
                    activity for which few sources of funding or labor currently exist <ptr target="#vandecreek_2022"/>. If minimal computing attempts to address this
                    imbalance, it is by intervening on the resources side of the equation.
                    Practitioners who aspire to compute minimally have developed methods that are
                    intended to support digital humanities projects in established forms for longer
                    periods of time with fewer resources.</p>
                <p>What would it mean to address the ambition side of this imbalance instead? I
                    don’t want to make an argument about what digital humanists should or shouldn’t
                    do, but I do want to suggest that there are possibilities in small-ness – in
                    small projects, small forms, and small collections – that have not yet been
                    explored. We have many DH projects that are large, comprehensive, and seemingly
                    poised to grow indefinitely. Do we have enough projects that are small, concise,
                    and bounded? Do we have enough projects whose ambition is interpretive,
                    expressive, and individual, whose value rests on insight and criticism, and not
                    on completeness or scale? Aislin O’Donnell suggests that we take “the scavengers
                    and gleaners of Agnès Varda’s films” <ptr target="#odonnell_2017" loc="20"/> as
                    anti-heroic models, and that gleaning can be a valuable orientation in all
                    aspects of our work, not only the those that are more technical. This question
                    of scale is present in minimal computing as well. <ptr target="#gil_2015"/> asks
                    scholars, “What is enough? What’s your finished stairway,” raising the
                    possibility of a recalibration with regards to ambition. We should be cautious
                    of minimalisms that intervene only on the technical side, without also
                    questioning the way we scope and define the goals of our projects.</p>
                <p>In that spirit, Rondo’s DPLA workflow is intended to inspire small projects,
                    experimental projects, free-associative acts of curation. It is an invitation to
                    select a few objects and write about them. There are things that need saying,
                    insights and perspectives that need sharing. Our tools and the expressive forms
                    we adopt for our projects should make all of that easier, not more
                    difficult.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>A Walk-Through of Rondo</head>
                <p>Having unpacked some of the inspirations for Rondo, I want to offer a critical
                    walk-through of Rondo’s code from a technical point of view, focusing on the
                    JavaScript that runs in the browser when a user loads a Rondo site. The purpose
                    of this exercise is not primarily to explain how Rondo works, but instead to
                    examine the ways in which its specific implementation does or does not
                    correspond to the goals of minimal computing and ease of use for new site
                    builders. The goal, then, is to get deeper into the question of what a minimal
                    approach to single page application development might look like and to expose
                    the challenges of putting theory into practice in this area. </p>
                <div>
                    <head>Creating a Rondo Site</head>
                    <p>Rondo’s primary JavaScript file is called rondo.js. Site creators can build a
                        new Rondo site by forking the Rondo GitHub repository and editing the
                        rondo.js file to point to their spreadsheet.<note> The code in this
                            walkthrough is simplified and formatted for easier readability. Variable
                            names are in bold.</note><!-- EDITOR'S NOTE, DON'T AUTOFORMAT IN OXYGEN -->
<eg lang="javascript">//spreadsheet variables - edit these to point to your spreadsheet
var <hi rend="bold">spreadsheetID</hi> = "1iwIx8sqiBTqbtAI7TX4vDGDVee3dPz0wa3MazBv2fzQ";
var <hi rend="bold">siteSheet</hi> = '1569296108';
var <hi rend="bold">pagesSheet</hi> = '28080804';
var <hi rend="bold">itemsSheet</hi> = '0';</eg> This step is likely to be one of the more uncomfortable or unfamiliar aspects
                        of the site building process for many users, and it comes right at the
                        beginning of their process<note> In a workshop or classroom setting, this
                            might be a step that instructors consider taking ahead of time,
                            providing students with a new site already connected to a
                            spreadsheet.</note>. Site creators must identify not only the overall ID
                        of their Google Sheet, but the IDs of each individual sheet. However, as we
                        will see later in this section, storing all four of these IDs allows us to
                        use the Google Visualization API to access the spreadsheet. It would also be
                        possible to design an application like Rondo to use a different Google API –
                        the Google Sheets API – which would only require only the spreadsheet ID.
                        That API would make it possible to retrieve the sheet IDs programmatically,
                        but it would also require the user to set up an account with Google Cloud
                        and use an API key to access the data. The Visualization API’s greatest
                        advantage is that it is free and doesn’t require any key or account to
                        access public spreadsheet data.</p>
                    <p>This inflection point is a good example of the challenges involved in
                        designing a minimal application, because the choice of API to connect to the
                        spreadsheet strongly impacts Rondo’s ease of use at the very beginning of
                        the site-building process. Both the Google Visualization API and the Google
                        Sheets API create obstacles for new users. It is quite possible to imagine
                        tools that would help a new user create a Rondo site in the proverbial one
                        click, but those tools themselves would demand significant additional
                        resources. Within the current constraints – a small application distributed
                        via GitHub – the best we can do may be to design workflows that minimize
                        these speed bumps for new users, and to document the processes in great
                        detail in order to facilitate successful installation.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Loading Site Data</head>
                    <p>One of the first things that Rondo does once the HTML page loads is to check
                        the URL for queries. Rondo’s queries do one simple thing - they tell the
                        application which page content to load. So on the demo site, the URL for the
                        “Build Your Exhibit” page is <ref target="https://sjsu-library.github.io/rondo/?page=build">https://sjsu-library.github.io/rondo/?page=build</ref>. The function
                        that retrieves queries is:<!-- EDITOR'S NOTE, DON'T AUTOFORMAT IN OXYGEN --><eg lang="javascript">//function to get queries from the URL and get the URL slug for the requested page
function getQueries() {
   var <hi rend="bold">queryString</hi> = window.location.search;//get queries from current URL
   if(<hi rend="bold">queryString</hi>) {
      var <hi rend="bold">urlParams</hi> = new URLSearchParams(<hi rend="bold">queryString</hi>);//get queries as search parameters
      <hi rend="bold">openPage</hi> = urlParams.get('page').replace('%20',' ');//set the openPage variable to the value from the current URL
   }
};</eg> This stores the page’s URL slug in the variable <q>openPage.</q> At
                        this point, Rondo has not yet loaded the data from the spreadsheet, but once
                        that happens, it will refer to that variable to open the correct page.</p>
                    <p>This is an example of the steps involved in coding a single page application
                        without a framework. Similar code handles tasks like navigating from one
                        page to another, or ensuring that the back and forward buttons in the
                        browser work in the way the user would expect. JavaScript frameworks
                        typically have their own structures for accomplishing these tasks, but
                        working without a framework reveals that, for a smaller application, these
                        structures need not be overly complicated.</p>
                    <p>When Rondo retrieves the data, it looks to the variable <q>remote</q> to
                        determine if it will access data from Google Sheets (remote = TRUE) or from
                        local data (remote = FALSE). It retrieves the data in a specific order –
                        first it retrieves the site configuration data, then the pages data, and
                        finally the items data. </p>
                    <p>The Google Visualization API returns a datatable which is parsed into JSON.
                        That JSON data is first added to the Rondo Tools section of the page, where
                        it is available for use in the localization process or for data sharing.
                        Next, the function <q>siteConfig()</q> runs to begin building the site based
                        on the configuration data. The structure of loading the pages and items data
                        is very similar. After loading the pages data, the function <q>pages()</q>
                        runs to build the content for all pages. After the pages, the items are
                        loaded, and the function <q>itemsDataTable()</q> uses the Datatables jQuery
                        plugin to create a searchable table of the
                            items.<!-- EDITOR'S NOTE, DON'T AUTOFORMAT IN OXYGEN --><eg lang="javascript">//Connect to Google Visualization API and query the Site sheet to retrieve basic site configuration
var <hi rend="bold">query</hi> = new google.visualization.Query('https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/'+<hi rend="bold">spreadsheetID</hi>+'/gviz/tq?gid='+<hi rend="bold">siteSheet</hi><![CDATA['&headers=1');
]]><hi rend="bold">query</hi>.send(function (<hi>response</hi>) {
         //error handling
         if (<hi rend="bold">response</hi>.isError()) {
      console.log('Error in query: ' + <hi>response</hi>.getMessage() + ' ' + <hi>response</hi>());
      Return;
         };
   var <hi rend="bold">siteDT</hi> = <hi rend="bold">response</hi>.getDataTable();//get datatable from response
   var <hi rend="bold">siteJsonData</hi> = <hi rend="bold">siteDT</hi>.toJSON();//convert datatable to JSON
   <hi rend="bold">siteJsonData</hi> = JSON.parse(<hi rend="bold">siteJsonData</hi>);//parse JSON 
   siteConfig(<hi rend="bold">siteJsonData</hi>);//configure site using data from spreadsheet
   //end of site configuration</eg></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Localization</head>
                    <p>When Rondo is localized, the process of loading the data is simpler, but the
                        same functions are run to build the site from the local data. The localized
                        code makes it easier to read the structure of this part of the code. JQuery
                        is used to load the local JSON files (<q>$.getJSON</q>) and each subsequent
                        request is nested within the callback function of the request before it.
                        This ensures that the three functions are run sequentially, and don’t start
                        running before the data is loaded. This same structure is used when running
                            remotely.<!-- EDITOR'S NOTE, DON'T AUTOFORMAT IN OXYGEN --><eg lang="javascript">//run Rondo page as static page using local data
$.getJSON("json/site.json", function(<hi rend="bold">siteJsonData</hi>) {//get site data
   siteConfig(<hi rend="bold">siteJsonData</hi>);//configure site using site data
   $.getJSON("json/pages.json", function(<hi rend="bold">pagesJsonData</hi>) {//get pages data
      pages(<hi rend="bold">pagesJsonData</hi>);//create pages
      $.getJSON("json/items.json", function(<hi rend="bold">itemsJsonData</hi>) {//get items data
         itemsDataTable(<hi rend="bold">itemsJsonData</hi>);//build the items table
      });//end of items
   });//end of pages
});//end of configuration</eg>
                    </p>
                    <p>The goal of the localization process is to recreate key benefits of a static
                        site system within the single page application. The localized data allows
                        the site to run without a connection to any external API. When localized,
                        the site could be considered a static single page application. As with a
                        static site, there is no back end or database, but only a set of local files
                        stored in a way that the web browser can easily interpret.</p>
                    <p>It is important to note, however, that Rondo does not yet include dedicated
                        tools for editing localized sites. Editing the JSON files directly is
                        possible but relatively cumbersome; tools like JSON Editor Online <ptr target="#de-jong_n.d."/> may provide the best experience for simple
                        edits. Given the current tools the localization feature is most appropriate
                        for sites which need to be preserved in their current state. Developing
                        better workflows for editing localized sites is a priority for improving
                        Rondo’s functionality when disconnected from Google Sheets. One approach
                        might be to develop a tool that converts data back and forth between CSV
                        format and the JSON format that Rondo expects, enabling users to edit
                        localized sites in any spreadsheet software they choose.</p>
                    <p>Another consideration is that the static single page application relies on
                        the durability and stability of the JavaScript that tells the browser how to
                        construct the site. The use of JavaScript in artifacts intended for
                        long-term preservation is not new, particularly in domains like digital art
                            <ptr target="#fino-radin_2011"/>. Both additional research and the
                        passage of time will probably be required in order to identify specific
                        practices that will lead to stable and supportable JavaScript over the
                        longer term. At this point, practices like the use of well-established
                        libraries, the packaging of required libraries along with the project, and
                        well-documented and commented code, may provide a starting point for
                        developers working in this area. JavaScript is too ubiquitous to be written
                        off as a tool or format that is not suitable for long-term preservation – if
                        we can’t preserve JavaScript, we can’t preserve very much of the web at all.
                        Additionally, web archiving technologies are capable of preserving sites
                        that use JavaScript <ptr target="#brunelle_2016"/>. Importantly, the
                        workflow for localization allows Rondo sites to outlive the Google
                        Visualization API without requiring any changes to Rondo itself. </p>
                    <p>The question of whether to disconnect a Rondo site from Google Sheets is left
                        up to the site owner. Under current limitations, disconnecting the site is
                        primarily intended as a way to archive completed sites which no longer need
                        updates, and as a way to ensure that Rondo sites can be preserved if Google
                        Sheets or the Google Visualization API is no longer available. Even if we
                        are able to create better tools, the workflow for updating localized sites
                        is likely to be more cumbersome than for sites connected directly to the
                        spreadsheet. On the other hand, localized sites will be more durable and
                        have fewer fragile external dependencies. </p>
                    <p>In any web architecture there are likely to be some trade-offs between
                        long-term stability on the one hand and flexibility and ease of use on the
                        other. These trade-offs often exist for technical reasons, but they may have
                        parallels in the social domain; imagine a well-resourced and stable research
                        platform that places restrictions on the content or perspectives that can be
                        expressed on its servers. One of the contributions of minimal computing has
                        been to make these trade-offs legible to practitioners and site creators by
                        foregrounding the specific costs and benefits of large-scale infrastructure.
                        Alan Liu captures this tension in his description of infrastructure as
                            <quote rend="inline">the social-cum-technological milieu that at once
                            enables the fulfillment of human experience and enforces constraints on
                            that experience</quote>
                        <ptr target="#liu_2016"/>. It may not be possible to engineer or theorize
                        our way past the contradictions inherent in using the infrastructure of the
                        internet, with all that comes with it, for humanistic research. Giving
                        researchers concrete choices, none of them necessarily better than the
                        others, is one way to foreground the enabling and constraining push and pull
                        of contemporary infrastructure.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Displaying Pages and Items</head>
                    <p>On a Rondo site, all pages are always present in the Document Object Model
                        (DOM), but only the present page is displayed. This is a common method for
                        providing JavaScript-based interactions like tabbed content or carousels,
                        and it is common in single page application structures. The HTML for all of
                        the pages is created as part of loading the site, and any conversion from
                        Markdown to HTML occurs during that process. In Rondo this process is
                        typically not particularly demanding of the local device’s resources, but it
                        does illustrate the trade-offs present in working with the SPA model. The
                        initial load of the site can be slower, and is more demanding of resources.
                        However, once the site is loaded, few network resources are required and
                        performance is typically fast.</p>
                    <p>The items are displayed using Datatables, which provides both simple and
                        advanced searching via the Search Builder extension. Individual items are
                        displayed in what web developers refer to as a modal – a box that floats
                        above the standard interface, like a benevolent pop-up ad. This approach
                        favors simplicity while still providing the basic functionality needed for
                        an exhibit. In this model, items do not have their own pages with specific
                        URLs – that treatment is reserved for pages, which would typically include
                        interpretive content. Rondo includes a simple method for embedding items on
                        pages, and there too clicking on the item opens the item’s modal. This is
                        not an inherent limitation of the SPA structure – it would be just as
                        feasible to handle the items as pages rather than pop-up modals – but rather
                        a design decision in favor of simplicity and directing the user to focus on
                        the material contained in a site’s pages. All of the information about each
                        item is available in the modal, but after closing the modal, the user is
                        returned directly to their place in the narrative or interpretive material
                        represented in the pages. </p>
                    <p>Unlike the pages, the content of the modal is not stored on the page but
                        built from data stored in the Datatable of items. This implementation takes
                        advantage of the ability to store data in the Datatable that is not
                        displayed – for each item on the table, only a few fields are displayed, but
                        all are available for search and use in building the modal. When a new item
                        is selected, the modal is emptied and then rebuilt from the new item’s data.
                        This model ensures that the full-size image for each item is only loaded
                        when the user interacts with the item. This is a basic but key performance
                        consideration, as loading all full-sized images when the site loads would
                        likely cause slow loading for many users.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Styling</head>
                    <p>The modal interaction is provided by the Pico CSS library, as are all of the
                        site’s styling and basic structure. As its name suggests, Pico itself is a
                        minimal tool, intended to provide for the needs of small to medium sites
                        with a very small package of CSS. Pico relies heavily on semantic HTML,
                        meaning that, for example, Pico interprets the HTML element &lt;dialog&gt;
                        as a modal dialog window, without the need for any additional CSS classes.
                        Pico’s reliance on semantic HTML helps to keep Rondo’s HTML quite
                        straightforward, and users can customize their Rondo site using standard
                        CSS. Pico’s extensive use of CSS variables can help to simplify
                        customization via CSS.</p>
                    <p>Within Rondo’s spreadsheet template, a site configuration sheet allows users
                        to define the title and header image of their site. This sheet also includes
                        columns which set a small number of key CSS variables, giving users some
                        control over the site’s look and feel without coding. Even small decisions
                        like how many CSS variables should be exposed via the spreadsheet reveal the
                        tensions between simplicity and flexibility when designing tools for minimal
                        computing. Pico has over 130 variables, and only five of those are currently
                        implemented in the spreadsheet. Of those five, four control the accent
                        colors used in the site and one assigns a single font to be used for all
                        text. </p>
                    <p>The level of styling customization available from the spreadsheet is
                        currently quite limited. It would be possible to add more variables to the
                        spreadsheet in order to allow further customization without writing CSS, but
                        adding those variables would also make the site configuration spreadsheet
                        more complicated and possibly intimidating. Customization via CSS is also
                        preferable from a performance point of view. This is an area where further
                        usability testing with site creators might be beneficial in order to
                        identify the most appropriate balance.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Discussion and Conclusion</head>
                <p>Having described some of the specific technical choices that establish the
                    functionality and constraints of the application, I want to return to the
                    concept of gleaning as a framework for approaching minimal computing and digital
                    humanities work more generally. Imaging the researcher or student as a gleaner,
                    collecting small, forgotten bits of code, technology, and server space, left
                    behind primarily by the companies that make up the tech industry suggests a way
                    of moving beyond the valorization of resource-intensive projects, while also
                    avoiding overly moralistic or theoretical interpretations of technical choices.
                    The image of the gleaner breaks down the dichotomy between the world-beating
                    grant winner and the ascetic minimalist. </p>
                <p>Kate Ince’s (2013) reading of Varda’s films is helpful here in expanding the
                    possible resonances and associations of gleaning. Ince regards Varda as a
                    filmmaker of the “lived body and women’s embodied experience” <ptr target="#ince_2013" loc="607"/>, as exemplified by her self-identification
                    with the experience of gleaning. <ptr target="#croft_2018"/> emphasizes that
                        <quote rend="inline">according to Agnès Varda, the tilting of the body and
                        eyeline down towards the ground is what most emphatically characterises the
                        gleaner</quote> and that this attention to the ground, to the place where
                    left-behind things are to be found, constitutes <quote rend="inline">the
                        gleaner’s gaze.</quote> This gaze, for which both Ince and Croft describe as
                    haptic or focused on texture, is capable of identifying and recontextualizing
                    overlooked objects and possibilities. As an orientation to the world, gleaning
                    is rooted in the experience of women and specifically in poor and working class
                    women. As an image of our relationship to technology, this is a welcome
                    departure from portrayals which valorize the ways that powerful men relate to
                    technology. It may go without saying, but we need alternatives to the perception
                    that the executives of technology companies always have the most progressive and
                    forward-thinking relationships to technology. </p>
                <p>Adopting the gleaner’s gaze can provide a certain clarity in conceptualizing the
                    relationship between digital humanities and the tech industry. Industry
                    narratives shape our sense of what is new and innovative in technology, and the
                    tech industry’s habitual hype cycles are more and more part of our everyday
                    world and culture. The tech industry shapes the tools and services that are
                    available to researchers and students. In trending or hyped areas, free
                    resources and fresh code abound, left behind by the flows of venture capital. In
                    an economy where even large technology companies can take years to become
                    profitable, and where providing free or subsidized access to computing resources
                    is a viable strategy to attract interest from users and investors, opportunities
                    for creative gleaning abound. As a very visible example, recent reports suggest
                    that OpenAI does not expect to be a profitable business until 2029 <ptr target="#isaac_2024"/>. However, the strategy of <q>money burning</q> is one
                    employed in both large and small technology companies <ptr target="#rachmad_2022"/>.</p>
                <p>The gleaning approach also creates space for productive ambivalence about our
                    approaches and tools. We don’t have to be enthusiastic about Google Sheets, or
                    about Google as a corporation, in order to glean some value from what they
                    provide us, or what our campus IT budgets pay them for. Gleaning is not
                    aspirational – it is above all about seizing what is attainable. If technology
                    companies are going to burn money with or without us, is it wrong to stand near
                    the fire to keep warm?</p>
                <p>As an approach, gleaning complements minimal computing, but helps to expand both
                    the positionalities and the technical approaches that might fit under the
                    minimal umbrella. Single page applications, with their reliance on browser-side
                    computation using JavaScript, might seem diametrically opposed to the static
                    site approaches that are closely associated with minimal computing. Rather than
                    a collection of static HTML pages, the single page approach produces one dynamic
                    page. Both results are minimal in one dimension, and maximal in another.
                    Similarly, gleaning expands the images and metaphors that we might use to
                    explore and develop minimal approaches. The gleaner is not exactly the
                        <q>user</q> we imagine when designing technology, but more of a
                        <q>re-user</q> or even <q>mis-user</q> of technology. </p>
                <p>The metaphor or framework of digital gleaning may prove more useful with further
                    development, and in particular theoretical investigation that places pressure on
                    the ways that this form of gleaning differs from the long tradition of
                    agricultural gleaning. There is admittedly something strange about comparing
                    impeccably polished commercial products like Google Sheets or Github Pages to
                    ears of wheat left behind after a harvest or groceries retrieved from a
                    dumpster. One way of reconciling this dissonance may be to attend to the
                    material aspect of the digital. In this framing, we are not gleaning <q>Google
                        Sheets</q> as a piece of technological infrastructure. We are gleaning one
                    Google Sheet, as if it were an object that could fall off a truck. Or more
                    literally, we are gleaning a few megabytes of space in one of Google’s many
                    massive data centers. We can’t hold our left-behind resource but, perhaps
                    strangely, we can access it remotely, from any internet-connected device. From
                    another angle, maybe what we glean from Google is more like discarded packaged
                    food than agricultural produce: It comes to us with the shiny wrapper still on,
                    but we may have to get our hands dirty to pick it out and find our uses for it.
                    Wherever we land in this metaphor, it is important to remember how Varda’s film
                    expands the notion of gleaning beyond its traditional meaning to include
                    artistic and creative reuses of discarded material, and searches for these other
                    ways and contexts in which gleaning may emerge. As she states in one of the
                    film’s transitional scenes, <quote rend="inline">we continue to film people who
                        spend time around trash cans, yet they all have different reasons, and it’s
                        a different experience for each</quote>
                    <ptr target="#varda_2000"/>.</p>
                <p>Returning to Rondo, the project attempts to put this image of the gleaner into
                    practice. It takes advantage of free server space and resources from Google, via
                    Google Sheets, and Microsoft, via GitHub Pages. Through its integration with
                    DPLA, Rondo also tries to enable gleaning in the curatorial or interpretive
                    aspects of digital projects, facilitating a workflow based on re-use,
                    interpretation, juxtaposition, and contextualization of existing digital
                    collections.</p>
                <p>From a technical point of view, this project proposes that the single page
                    application model, when implemented with the goals of simplicity and ease of use
                    in mind, is a promising complement to static site models for minimal computing
                    platforms. In particular, SPAs have the potential to be easier for new users to
                    adopt because they do not require the site creator to install software or use
                    the command line. The project is also an experiment in minimizing the ambition,
                    and maximizing the simplicity, of the tool or platform itself. Rondo strives to
                    provide just what is needed for a minimal digital exhibit, and to avoid
                    cluttering its interface with non-essential features. </p>
                <p>The success of minimal computing as an intervention need not be derailed by the
                    well-documented challenges associated with using static site generators,
                    particularly in a pedagogical environment <ptr target="#brooks_2021"/>
                    <ptr target="#dombrowski_2022"/>. This project aims to suggest that the gleaning
                    approach as exemplified by an SPA which appropriates Google Sheets for data
                    storage, may be an alternate but complementary path towards a more minimal, less
                    resource-intensive digital humanities practice. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boston-college-law-library_n.d." label="Boston College Law Library n.d.">Boston College Law Library (n.d.) <title rend="italic">New Books</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://www.bc.edu/bc-web/schools/law/sites/students/library/using/new-books.html">https://www.bc.edu/bc-web/schools/law/sites/students/library/using/new-books.html</ref>
                    (Accessed: 12 October 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boston-college-law-school_n.d." label="Boston College Law School n.d.">Boston College Law School (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Fusion Search</title>.
                    Available at: <ref target="https://www.bc.edu/bc-web/schools/law/academics-faculty/fusion-search.html">https://www.bc.edu/bc-web/schools/law/academics-faculty/fusion-search.html</ref>
                    (Accessed: 12 October 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blackmer-reyes_2022" label="Blackmer Reyes and Szydlowski 2022">Blackmer Reyes, K and Szydlowski, N. (2022). <title rend="italic">Betita
                        Martínez: A Memorial Exhibit</title>. Available at <ref target="https://sjsu-library.github.io/betita/">https://sjsu-library.github.io/betita/</ref>. (Accessed: 14 October
                    2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bradley_2023" label="Bradley 2023">Bradley, J. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Using Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) and Google Sheets to
                        build a visual tool location web app</title>, <title rend="italic">code4lib</title>, 58. Available at <ref target="https://journal.code4lib.org/articles/17697">https://journal.code4lib.org/articles/17697</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brooks_2021" label="Brooks 2021">Brooks, M. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Real talk on static sites and digital literacies</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">Mackenzie K. Brooks</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2021/04/14/real-talk-static-sites.html">https://mackenziekbrooks.info/update/2021/04/14/real-talk-static-sites.html</ref>
                    (Accessed: 12 October 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brunelle_2016" label="Brunelle et al. 2016">Brunelle, J.F. et al.
                    (2016) <title rend="quotes">The impact of JavaScript on archivability</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">International Journal on Digital Libraries</title>,
                    17(2), pp. 95–117. Available at:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00799-015-0140-8">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00799-015-0140-8</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="creasap_2014" label="Creasap 2014">Creasap, K. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Zine-making as feminist pedagogy</title>, <title rend="italic">Feminist Teacher</title>, 24(3), pp. 155–168. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5406/femteacher.24.3.0155">https://doi.org/10.5406/femteacher.24.3.0155</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="croft_2018" label="Croft 2018">Croft, J. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Gleaning and dreaming on Car Park Beach</title>, <title rend="italic">Humanities </title>7(2), 33. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3390/h7020033">https://doi.org/10.3390/h7020033</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="davenport_2019" label="Davenport 2019">Davenport, M. [<ref target="https://medium.com/@calebmackdaven/integrating-google-sheets-as-a-backend-7fc6a214418d">@calebmackdaven</ref>] (2019) <title rend="quotes">Integrating Google
                        Sheets as a backend</title> [Medium] 20 March. Available at: <ref target="https://medium.com/@calebmackdaven/integrating-google-sheets-as-a-backend-7fc6a214418d">https://medium.com/@calebmackdaven/integrating-google-sheets-as-a-backend-7fc6a214418d</ref>
                    (Accessed: 12 October 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="de-jong_n.d." label="De Jong n.d." sortKey="Dejong">De Jong, J. (n.d.)
                        <title rend="italic">JSON Editor Online</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://jsoneditoronline.org/">https://jsoneditoronline.org/</ref>.
                    (Accessed 23 July 2025).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dombrowski_2022" label="Dombrowski 2022">Dombrowski, Q. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Minimizing computing maximizes labor</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 16(2). Available at:
                        <ref target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/vol/16/2/000594/000594.html">https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/vol/16/2/000594/000594.html</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="duncombe_1997" label="Duncombe 1997">Duncombe, S. (1997) <title rend="italic">Notes from Underground: Zines and the Politics of Alternative
                        Culture</title>. London: Verso.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fino-radin_2011" label="Fino Radin 2011" sortKey="Finoradin">Fino-Radin, B. (2011) <title rend="quotes">Digital preservation practices and
                        the Rhizome ArtBase</title>, <title rend="italic">Rhizome ArtBase.
                    </title>Available at: <ref target="https://media.rhizome.org/artbase/documents/Digital-Preservation-Practices-and-the-Rhizome-ArtBase.pdf">https://media.rhizome.org/artbase/documents/Digital-Preservation-Practices-and-the-Rhizome-ArtBase.pdf</ref>
                    (Accessed: 12 October 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gavrila_2019" label="Gavrilă et al. 2019" sortKey="Gavrila">Gavrilă,
                    V. et al. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Modern single page application
                        architecture: A case study</title>, <title rend="italic">Studies in
                        Informatics and Control</title>, 28(2). Available at:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.24846/v28i2y201911">https://doi.org/10.24846/v28i2y201911</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gil_2015" label="Gil 2015">Gil, A. (2015). <title rend="quotes">The
                        user, the learner and the machines we make</title>,<title rend="italic">
                        Minimal Computing</title>. Available at:<ref target="https://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2015/05/21/user-vs-learner/">https://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2015/05/21/user-vs-learner/</ref>
                    (Accessed: 12 October 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="google_n.d." label="Google n.d.">Google (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Google Visualization API Reference | Charts | Google for
                    Developers</title>. Available at:<ref target="https://developers.google.com/chart/interactive/docs/reference">https://developers.google.com/chart/interactive/docs/reference</ref>
                    (Accessed: 12 October 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ince_2013" label="Ince 2013">Ince, K. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Feminist phenomenology and the film world of Agnès Varda</title>, <title rend="italic">Hypatia</title>, 28(3), pp. 602–617. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1527-2001.2012.01303.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1527-2001.2012.01303.x</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="isaac_2024" label="Isaac and Griffith 2024">Isaac, M. and Griffith, E.
                    (2024) <title rend="quotes">OpenAI is growing fast and burning through piles of
                        money</title>, <title rend="italic">The New York Times</title>, 27
                    September. Available at:<ref target="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/09/27/technology/openai-chatgpt-investors-funding.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2024/09/27/technology/openai-chatgpt-investors-funding.html</ref>
                    (Accessed: 12 October 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="scott_2015" label="Scott 2015">Scott Jr., E.A. (2015) <title rend="italic">SPA Design and Architecture: Understanding Single-Page Web
                        Applications</title>. Shelter Island, NY: Manning.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="king_2007" label="King 2007">King, H. (2007) <title rend="quotes">Matter, time, and the digital: Varda’s <title rend="italic">The Gleaners and I</title></title>, <title rend="italic">Quarterly Review of Film and Video</title>, 24(5), pp.
                    421–429. Available at:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/10509200500536322">https://doi.org/10.1080/10509200500536322</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="king-library-dhc_2024" label="King Library’s Digital Humanities Center 2024">King Library’s Digital
                    Humanities Center (2024). <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Center
                        Community Conversations</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://library.sjsu.edu/ld.php?content_id=80034869">https://library.sjsu.edu/ld.php?content_id=80034869</ref> (Accessed: 26
                    July 2025).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="knight-lab_n.d." label="Knight Lab n.d.">Knight Lab (n.d.) <title rend="italic">TimelineJS</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://timeline.knightlab.com/">https://timeline.knightlab.com/</ref> (Accessed: 12 October 2024). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="larroche_n.d." label="Larroche n.d.">Larroche, L. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">Pico CSS • Minimal CSS Framework for semantic HTML</title>.
                    Available at:<ref target="https://v2.picocss.com/">https://v2.picocss.com/</ref>
                    (Accessed: 12 October 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lison_2022" label="Lison 2022">Lison, A. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Minimal computing</title>, <title rend="italic">COUNTER-N, </title>2022.
                    Available at: <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.18452/25607">http://dx.doi.org/10.18452/25607</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu_2016" label="Liu 2016">Liu, A. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Drafts
                        for against the cultural singularity (book in progress)</title> Available
                    at: <ref target="https://liu.english.ucsb.edu/drafts-for-against-the-cultural-singularity/">https://liu.english.ucsb.edu/drafts-for-against-the-cultural-singularity/</ref>
                    (Accessed: 26 July 2025).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lund_2019" label="Lund and Beckstrom 2019">Lund, B. and Beckstrom, M.
                    (2019) <title rend="quotes">The integration of Tor into library services: An
                        appeal to the core mission and values of libraries</title>, <title rend="italic">Public Library Quarterly</title>, 40(1), pp. 60–76. Available
                        at:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01616846.2019.1696078">https://doi.org/10.1080/01616846.2019.1696078</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="markdown-it_2024" label="markdown-it 2024" sortKey="Markdown">markdown-it (2024). <title rend="italic">markdown-it</title>. Available at:<ref target="https://github.com/markdown-it/markdown-it">https://github.com/markdown-it/markdown-it</ref> (Accessed: 12 October
                    2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="martin_2016" label="Martin III and Runyon 2016">Martin III, J.D. and
                    Runyon, C. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Digital humanities, digital hegemony:
                        Exploring funding practices and unequal access in the digital
                        humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">ACM SIGCAS Computers and
                        Society</title> 46(1). pp. 20-26. Available at
                    https://doi.org/10.1145/2908216.2908219. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mukhiya_2018" label="Mukhiya and Hung 2018">Mukhiya, S.K. and Hung,
                    H.K. (2018) <title rend="quotes">An architectural style for single page scalable
                        modern web application</title>,<title rend="italic"> International Journal
                        of Recent Research Aspects</title> 5(4), pp. 6–13. Available at: <ref target="https://www.ijrra.net/Vol5issue4/IJRRA-05-04-02.pdf">https://www.ijrra.net/Vol5issue4/IJRRA-05-04-02.pdf</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nyrop_n.d." label="Nyrop and Gil n.d.">Nyrop, M. and Gil, A. (n.d.)
                        <title rend="italic">Wax</title>. Available at:<ref target="https://minicomp.github.io/wax/">https://minicomp.github.io/wax/</ref> (Accessed: 12 October 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="odonnell_2017" label="O'Donnell 2017" sortKey="Odonnell">O’Donnell, A.
                    (2017) <title rend="quotes">For the scavengers and the gleaners: An anti-heroic
                        vision of education</title> . <title rend="italic">Other Education</title>,
                    5(2). pp. 1738. Available at: <ref target="https://mural.maynoothuniversity.ie/8603/">https://mural.maynoothuniversity.ie/8603/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="openjs-foundation_n.d." label="OpenJS Foundation n.d.">OpenJS
                    Foundation. (n.d.) <title rend="italic">jQuery</title>. Available at:<ref target="https://jquery.com/">https://jquery.com/</ref> (Accessed: 12 October
                    2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rachmad_2022" label="Rachmad_2022">Rachmad, Y.E. (2022) <title rend="quotes">The influence and impact of the money burning strategy on the
                        future of startups,</title>
                    <title rend="italic"> Proceedings of the 1st Adpebi International Conference on
                        Management, Education, Social Science, Economics and Technology</title>
                    (AICMEST), Jakarta, July 26, 2022. Available at: <ref target="https://adpebipublishing.com/index.php/AICMEST/article/view/180">https://adpebipublishing.com/index.php/AICMEST/article/view/180</ref>
                    (Accessed: 12 October 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="risam_2022" label="Risam and Gil 2022">Risam, R. and Gil, A. (2022)
                        <title rend="quotes">Introduction: The questions of minimal
                        computing</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                    Quarterly</title>, 16(2). Available at:<ref target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/vol/16/2/000646/000646.html">https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/vol/16/2/000646/000646.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rycenga_2023" label="Rycenga et al. 2023">Rycenga, J. et al. (2023)
                        <title rend="italic">The Unionist Unified: Connecticut's First Immediate
                        Abolitionist Newspaper</title>. Available at <ref target="https://sjsu-library.github.io/unionist/">https://sjsu-library.github.io/unionist/</ref> (Accessed: 14 October
                    2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sandy_2016" label="Sandy and Freeland 2016">Sandy, H.M. and Freeland,
                    C. (2016) <title rend="quotes">The importance of interoperability: Lessons from
                        the digital public library of America</title>, <title rend="italic">The
                        International Information &amp; Library Review</title>, 48(1), pp. 45–50.
                    Available at:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/10572317.2016.1146041">https://doi.org/10.1080/10572317.2016.1146041</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="scheper_2023" label="Scheper 2023">Scheper, J. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Zine pedagogies: Students as critical makers</title>, <title rend="italic">The Radical Teacher</title>, (125), pp. 20–32. Available at:
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5195/rt.2023.963">https://doi.org/10.5195/rt.2023.963</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sprymedia_n.d." label="SpryMedia n.d.">SpryMedia. (n.d.). <title rend="italic">DataTables | JavaScript table library</title>. Available at:
                        <ref target="https://datatables.net/">https://datatables.net/</ref>
                    (Accessed: 12 October 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="varda_2000" label="Varda 2000">
                    <title rend="italic">The Gleaners and I </title>(2000) Directed by Agnès Varda.
                    Kanopy. Available at: <ref target="https://www.kanopy.com/en/product/10913169">https://www.kanopy.com/en/product/10913169</ref> (Accessed: 12 October
                    2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vandecreek_2022" label="VandeCreek 2022" sortKey="Vandecreek">VandeCreek, D. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Where are they now? The 2020 status
                        of early (1996–2003) online digital humanities projects and an analysis of
                        institutional factors correlated to their survival</title>, <title rend="italic">Preservation, Digital Technology &amp; Culture</title>, 51(3),
                    pp. 91–109. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1515/pdtc-2022-0011">https://doi.org/10.1515/pdtc-2022-0011</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wilke_2024" label="Wilke and Williamson 2024">Wikle, O.M. and
                    Williamson, E.P. (2024) <title rend="quotes">Exploring Static web in the digital
                        humanities classroom: The learn-static initiative</title>, <title rend="italic">IDEAH</title>, 4(2). Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.21428/f1f23564.f88a989c">https://doi.org/10.21428/f1f23564.f88a989c</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="w3-lab_2022" label="W3 Lab 2022" sortKey="Wthree">W3 Lab (2022) <title rend="quotes">The Popularity of Single-Page Applications in 2022</title>,
                    <title rend="italic">W3 Lab</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://w3-lab.com/single-page-applications-2022/">https://w3-lab.com/single-page-applications-2022/</ref> (Accessed: 12
                    October 2024).</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>