<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt><!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English--></title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo><!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>first name(s) <dhq:family>family name</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation/>
               <email/>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000754<!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND"><!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords"><!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors--><!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
               <term corresp=""/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords"><!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc><!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000754/000754.xml">GitHub
                   </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract><!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser><!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="Title">Conceptual Modelling of the European Silk Heritage with the SILKNOW Data Model and Extension</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
         </titlePage>
         <p>Marie Puren<note> EPITA, LRE, F-94270 Kremlin-Bicêtre, France</note>
            <note> Ecole nationale des Chartes, Centre Jean-Mabillon, F-75002 Paris, France</note> and Pierre Vernus<note> LARHRA, F-69363 Lyon, France</note>
            <note> Université Lumière Lyon 2, F-69007 Lyon, France</note>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="introduction">
            <head>Abstract</head>
            <p>Silk holds significant historical importance in European history, fostering economic growth, innovation in weaving techniques, and the creation of exceptional artifacts. Despite the conservation efforts of numerous institutions, silk heritage remains at risk due to its fragile nature. This paper outlines the methodology employed by the Horizon 2020 SILKNOW project aimed at enhancing the promotion and preservation of silk-related cultural heritage collections. We present the development of a CIDOC CRM-based data model for the creation of a comprehensive knowledge graph. We also introduce the SILKNOW extension, designed to encapsulate the intricate semantics associated with the production processes of silk fabrics. Our results demonstrate the potential of Semantic Web technologies in safeguarding and enriching the visibility of silk heritage through improved data interoperability and accessibility.  </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>For the past ten years, the history of fashion has attracted a growing public (Petrov, 2019) (Stewart &amp; Marcketti, 2012). But despite the interest shown in these collections, the Textile Heritage remains under threat. This is particularly true of the Silk Heritage, whose fragility poses major conservation problems and whose protection requires substantial investment. Few materials are of such historical, cultural and artistic importance; but a significant part of the silk-related collections are preserved by small institutions, lacking generally the means to promote their collections (Portalés, et al., 2018) (Gaitán, et al., 2019) (Pagán, et al., 2020). Outside of the major events devoted to them, we also note the under-use of textile collections by visitors (Stewart &amp; Marcketti, 2012). This is why the digitization of Cultural Heritage has become one of the crucial issues for its promotion (Eastermann, 2015).</p>
            <p>When users are interested in textile Cultural Heritage online, they are generally faced with two situations. The large generalist museums have the technical, financial and human resources to disseminate their data on the Web, but they do not systematically highlight their textile collections on their websites. Conversely, small museums do not have the same resources as their better-endowed counterparts (Claerr &amp; Westeel, 2010) to promote specialized collections online, which can be particularly rich. This is particularly the case for Silk Heritage, as the example of the Rhône-Alpes region clearly illustrates (Foron-Dauphin &amp; Cano, 2016) (Fournier, Despierres, Mercandelli, &amp; Bernard, 2016). These institutions do describe their collections, but the digital data they produce is, most of the time, inaccessible online. Without a digital presence, these collections remain generally unknown, except to a few connoisseurs and specialists.</p>
            <p>The Semantic Web offers particularly interesting prospects in this domain; it proposes to Cultural Heritage institutions to increase the visibility of their metadata on the Web by “freeing” it from catalogs; to aggregate this data with others and provide access to it in a federated way; to interconnect data with each other and, ultimately, to enrich this information more easily thanks to the links created between them. By encouraging the dissemination of structured data, Semantic Web technologies indeed facilitate the creation of links between dispersed historical sources (Meroño-Peñuela, et al., 2015)The Semantic Web is not a new Web that replaces the current Web, but an extension of it (Berners-Lee, Hendler, &amp; Lassila, 2001), enabling navigation not between documents via hypertext links, but directly between data. This implies that all information is provided with a well-defined meaning, making it interpretable and reusable by data consumers, both human and machine, who will then be able to process it automatically and develop new applications and services (Bermès, 2013). Museums are particularly interested in the aggregation possibilities offered by Semantic Web technologies (Freire, et al., 2019), especially for heterogeneous metadata (Peroni, Tomasi, &amp; Vitali, 2013). For example, the <hi rend="italic">Europeana Fashion</hi> portal provides access to the collections of over thirty European institutions. However, it primarily aggregates data from major European museums only (Suls, 2017), resulting in a notable exclusion of smaller museums. This approach neglects the promotion of more specialized collections, notably those focusing on silk. To address this deficiency, the H2020 SILKNOW project<note>
                  <hi rend="italic">Silk Heritage in the Knowledge Society: from punched card to Big Data, Deep Learning and visual/tangible simulations</hi>: <ref target="https://silknow.eu/">https://silknow.eu/</ref>. </note> has developed ADASilk, an innovative exploratory search engine. This engine offers federated searches across diverse Cultural Heritage collections, with a specific emphasis on silk-related artifacts.</p>
            <p>ADASilk is based on a knowledge graph that enables data from a variety of sources to be aggregated and presented online. A knowledge graph is a set of interconnected descriptions of entities - objects, people, events, concepts or situations - which can be enriched by a retrospective acquisition of information and integrated into ontologies (Gruber, 1993). This approach has proven particularly successful for other types of Cultural Heritage data: for example, bibliographic data describing musical works for the DOREMUS project (Achichi, Lisena, Todorov, Troncy, &amp; Delahousse, 2018), archival data for the ArchOnto project (Koch, Ribeiro, &amp; Lopes, 2020), or historical data for the WarSampo project (Hyvönen, et al., 2021). The SILKNOW Knowledge Graph represents the data contained in the catalogues of 21 Cultural Heritage institutions<note> A full list of these institutions can be found here: <ref target="https://ada.silknow.org/fr/museums">https://ada.silknow.org/fr/museums</ref>. </note> , following a subset of the CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model or CIDOC-CRM. Collected online or provided directly by the institution concerned<note> Datasets have been made available to the project by <hi rend="italic">Garin1820</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Sicily Cultural Heritage</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Musée d'Art et d'Industrie de Saint-Etienne</hi>.</note>, the data describe objects that may be entirely made of silk, or incorporate other textile materials (natural fibers, metal threads), or be made of composite materials (e.g. wood in the case of furniture). The SILKNOW project focused on objects produced or consumed in Europe between the mid-15th to the middle of the 19th century.</p>
            <p>In this paper, we present the different steps that allowed us to build the SILKNOW data model. We also describe the methodology we used to create a conceptual model extending the CIDOC CRM, and to integrate the annotations produced with machine learning methods. In a first part, we discuss the contributions of Semantic Web technologies for the protection and enrichment of Silk Heritage. In a second part, we explain the approach we adopted to develop the SILKNOW data model. In the third part, we show how we used the Provenance Data Model or Prov DM to integrate the semantic annotations produced on these data thanks to the analysis of texts and images. We also propose to extend the CIDOC CRM with new classes and properties, so as to be able to express the complex semantics of the data describing the production process of silk fabrics.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="X2b6fc67a6561b191417af3efedd61fa6e423ece">
            <head>Providing access to heterogeneous data using Semantic Web technologies</head>
            <div xml:id="heterogeneous-metadata">
               <head>Heterogeneous metadata</head>
               <p>The records produced by all these institutions generally provide the same types of information: type of object, place and date of production, materials and techniques used, dimensions, and illustration(s). But the way in which this metadata is structured can vary greatly depending on the practices of its producers. These data come from institutions using various cataloguing standards and respecting their own description standards. Figure 1 illustrates this problem by comparing the list of metadata describing two objects (here, two damasks<note> For a definition of “damask”, please consult the SILKNOW thesaurus: <ref target="https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/page/168">https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/page/168</ref>. </note>) held respectively by the <hi rend="italic">Museu Tèxtil Terrassa</hi>
                  <note>
                     <ref target="Le%20catalogue%20est%20accessible%20ici%20:%20http://imatex.cdmt.es/">http://imatex.cdmt.es/</ref>
                  </note> and by the <hi rend="italic">Victoria &amp; Albert Museum</hi>
                  <note>
                     <ref target="https://www.vam.ac.uk/collections">https://www.vam.ac.uk/collections</ref>. </note> . The same types of information are used to describe these two objects, but they are expressed differently by the two museums. For example, the <hi rend="italic">Victoria &amp; Albert Museum</hi> indicates in the same field the material and technique used, whereas the <hi rend="italic">Museu Tèxtil Terrassa</hi> clearly separates this information.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image1.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Figure 1. Metadata describing the techniques and materials used: examples from the <hi rend="italic">Museu Tèxtil Terrassa</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Victoria &amp; Albert Museum</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In other words, the <hi rend="italic">Victoria &amp; Albert Museum</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Museu Tèxtil Terrassa</hi> do not use the same data model. This is because the catalogues are designed as separate data silos, which are not supposed to communicate with each other. If one wants to collect this metadata on a large scale, it will therefore be difficult to process it automatically due to the heterogeneity of its structure, but also due to the lack of structure of the metadata. Different types of information are often found in the same field (as shown in Figure 1), which makes it difficult to automatically process the data. By nature, Cultural Heritage data are heterogeneous: they are produced by various institutions, they describe various objects - which does not make them easily accessible by search engines (Freire, Meijers, Voorburg, &amp; Isaac, 2018). To improve the discoverability of this data online, Semantic Web technologies offer the possibility of aggregating and providing access to metadata from different sources (Freire, et al., 2019). This is in this context that the SILKNOW project has created an exploratory search engine that enables a federated search of 21 collections dedicated to the conservation of European Silk Heritage.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="an-ontology-to-build-a-knowledge-graph">
               <head>An ontology to build a knowledge graph</head>
               <p>Since the emergence of the Semantic Web, we have seen new changes in the use of the Web by museums, particularly the increasing openness of the data produced by these institutions (Marden, Li-Madeo, Whysel, &amp; Edelstein, 2013) (Eastermann, 2015). The Semantic Web implements linked data (Bizer, Heath, &amp; Berners-Lee, 2009), with the aim of enabling machines to understand the semantics of information published on the Web, and thus to create new, even unexpected, links between this information. The Semantic Web thus opens up new perspectives for the visibility of Cultural Heritage online, by making Cultural Heritage data available to all - and not only in a museum context -; by aggregating, publishing and enriching this data on the Web to facilitate its reuse; by linking this data to each other and to other data, so as to constitute an information network; and finally by making proposals for enriching this data.</p>
               <p>SILKNOW hypothesized that the use of Semantic Web technologies, and more specifically the creation of a knowledge graph, could facilitate the integration, exploration and retrieval of data describing historical silk artefacts. By containing this data, the SILKNOW Knowledge Graph is intended to create a single access point to this data. The implementation of the Semantic Web is based on distinct principles and standards, leading to what is known as the “Web of Data” or Linked Data (Bizer, Heath, &amp; Berners-Lee, 2009). This framework is made possible by RDF, a graph model designed by the W3C to describe Web resources and their metadata. In RDF, each unit of information is represented by a three-element assertion (or “triplet”) comprising a subject, a predicate (or property) and an object. These elements are represented as URIs (Uniform Resource Identifiers), thus becoming “resources”. These resources are then organized into "classes", conceptualized as collections of individuals or objects. The Web of Data doesn't establish fixed definitions for classes and properties; similarly, RDF's versatility doesn't dictate specific usage rules for classes and properties (Bermès, 2013). Consequently, the adoption of a knowledge representation technology becomes essential. Ontologies play a crucial role here, enabling the declaration of classes, properties, their behaviors and hierarchy in languages such as RDF Schema (RDFS) and Web Ontology Language (OWL). The selection of specific classes and properties from an ontology to represent the desired information leads to the creation of a data model (Bermès, 2013).</p>
               <p>An ontology is a mutually shared conceptual model used to represent all information in a specific application domain by means of defined hierarchical concepts (Gruber, 1993). Consequently, the use of ontologies helps to solve the problem of semantic heterogeneity arising from diverse data sources, and to improve the interoperability of systems and applications. With the expansion of the Semantic Web, ontologies have been developed for a variety of purposes (Wang, Xia, &amp; Niu, 2014). In the Cultural Heritage domain, reference ontologies have been established to detail objects and their relationships. The CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model or CIDOC-CRM, used to describe objects in museums collections, is a striking example (Doerr, 2003). When a domain-specific ontology is available, it is possible to create more restricted subsets or specializations tailored to particular sub-domains (Messaoudi, De Luca, Véron, &amp; Halin, 2019) (Kergosien, Eric, Daloz, Chaudiron, &amp; Jacquemin, 2019). </p>
               <p>In the framework of SILKNOW, data is downloaded or collected from partner institutions; and these files are converted to create the knowledge graph using the Resource Description Framework as the data model. The graph, which contains all the metadata, is then loaded into a triple store. The converted data is then accessible online via ADASilk. The creation of the knowledge graph requires an RDF conversion, which is based on a manual mapping of the data. This mapping consists in putting in equivalence the data models describing similar objects (Christen, 2012). When working with two data sources A and B, data mapping can consist of matching each field in database A with those in database B. In the SILKNOW project, we are using many different sources; we have chosen to use a pivotal data model that makes it easier to perform this mapping between all the collected datasets. We have thus created a subset of the CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model (CIDOC CRM) ontology, which is instantiated at the time of the RDF conversion (Schleider, et al., 2021) (Schleider, et al., 2021).</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="the-silknow-data-model">
            <head>The SILKNOW data model</head>
            <div xml:id="Xa19ab58b33ded14fe8f49f79e2368000bfdded7">
               <head>Expressing the semantics of Silk Heritage information with the CIDOC CRM</head>
               <p>We chose CIDOC CRM (Le Boeuf, Doerr, Emil Ore, &amp; Stead, 2015) because it is a conceptual model specifically developed for Cultural Heritage by the International Committee for Documentation (CIDOC) of the International Council of Museum (ICOM). An ISO standard since 2006, renewed in 2014<note>
                     <ref target="https://www.iso.org/standard/57832.html">https://www.iso.org/standard/57832.html</ref>
                  </note>, the CIDOC CRM is today a standard intended to ensure the interoperability of Cultural Heritage data. However, this standard is not set in stone; thus, at the time of writing this article, version 7.2.3 has been published<note>
                     <ref target="https://www.cidoc-crm.org/Version/version-7.2.3">https://www.cidoc-crm.org/Version/version-7.2.3</ref>
                  </note> . However, we used version 6.2<note>
                     <ref target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org/Version/version-6.2.3">http://www.cidoc-crm.org/Version/version-6.2.3</ref>
                  </note> - the most recent version at the time of the start of the project in 2018. CIDOC CRM is also a flexible and extensible model. If necessary, this model can be extended by creating new classes and properties to express new information, without changing the basic structure of the model. These features allow the creation of specialized extensions such as FRBRoo (Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records), a conceptual model for bibliographic data<note> IFLA Study Group on the Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records, <hi rend="italic">Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records: Final Report</hi>, IFLA, 2009. URL: <ref target="https://repository.ifla.org/handle/123456789/811">https://repository.ifla.org/handle/123456789/811</ref>. </note>, or CRMtex, a conceptual model for the study of ancient texts<note> Martin Doerr, Francesca Murano and Achille Felicetti, <hi rend="italic">Definition of the CRMtex. An Extension of CIDOC CRM to Model Ancient Textual Entities</hi>, Version 1.0, currently maintained by Francesca Murano and Achille Felicetti, June 2020. URL: https://cidoc-crm.org/crmtex/ModelVersion/version-1.0-0.</note>. There are a total of eleven compatible models on the official CIDOC CRM website<note> For the full list: https://cidoc-crm.org/collaborations.</note>.</p>
               <p>CIDOC CRM allows the underlying semantics of Cultural Heritage information to be expressed, and thus heterogeneous data to be modelled in a homogeneous way. If we take the descriptions of the two damask fabrics preserved by the <hi rend="italic">Victoria &amp; Albert Museum</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Museu Tèxtil Terrassa</hi> (Figure 1), we can express in a unique way with CIDOC CRM the information about the technique and the materials used during the weaving process. CIDOC CRM allows to model each of the descriptive fields with triplets Class (C) - Property (P) - Class (C), which can be represented as graphs as in Figure 2.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image2.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Figure 2. Graph in accordance with the CIDOC CRM conceptual model</p>
               <p>In this figure, we can see that we have chosen to use the E22_Man Made Object class to represent the object described by the museum metadata. In version 6.2 of CIDOC CRM, this class is indeed used to model “physical objects purposely created by human activity” (Le Boeuf, Doerr, Emil Ore, &amp; Stead, 2015).</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="Xc20b153af7f41b32cdd5c957beb656a6f4a9e1c">
               <head>What classes and properties to represent this information?</head>
               <p>As a conceptual model, CIDOC CRM is intended to model all kinds of Cultural Heritage data and should be able to cover most cases. CIDOC CRM thus provides a wide range of classes and properties. For example, there are 89 classes and 153 properties offered by version 6.2<note> A list of these classes and properties can be found on the OntoMe website: https://ontome.net/namespace/1</note>. In general, therefore, we do not need to use all the classes and properties offered by CIDOC CRM.</p>
               <p>To select the classes and properties needed to model the metadata collected by the project, it is first necessary to list the descriptive fields used to describe the textile objects. To do this, we analyzed and compared a large number of records, based on the documentation used by Cultural Heritage institutions to create this metadata (notably (Grant, Nieuwenhuis, &amp; Petersen, 1995)). This analysis allowed us to draw up a list of descriptive fields commonly used to describe textile objects, while eliminating descriptive fields that were not relevant to the project - namely, fields providing information on the administrative management of the object.</p>
               <p>These descriptive fields were then classified into Information Groups<hi rend="italic">,</hi> which form the Data Dictionary of the SILKNOW project. These information groups allowed us to identify the categories used by Cultural Heritage institutions to describe ancient textiles. We defined 22 Information Groups, from the most commonly used (e.g. “Object Title Information Group” or “Object Measure Information Group”) to the most rarely encountered (e.g. “Object Missing Part Information Group” or “Exhibition Information Group”). These Information Groups then allowed us to rely on the Functional Overviews provided by the official CIDOC CRM documentation<note> The functional overviews are available online: <ref target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org/functional-units">http://www.cidoc-crm.org/functional-units</ref>. </note>, and to more easily select the most appropriate classes and properties to represent these information groups. Functional Overviews classify CIDOC CRM classes and properties into information categories that can be easily aligned with the Information Groups in our data dictionary. For example, the Functional Overviews provide an “Object Title Information” category that corresponds to our “Object Title Information Group”.</p>
               <p>The SILKNOW data model consists of the classes and properties selected to represent the information groups we have previously defined. It is accessible and documented online (Puren &amp; Vernus, Silknow Generic Profile, 2021) thanks to OntoME (Beretta, 2021), which is an ontology manager developed and maintained by the LARHRA laboratory. The SILKNOW data model is mainly based on the CIDOC CRM Core version 6.2 (71 properties and 21 properties). We also selected two classes and one property from an extension of CIDOC CRM, the Scientific Observation Model (CRMsci) version 1.2.3<note> The latest version 1.5 was released in January 2022.</note> (Kritsotaki, Hiebel, Theodoridou, Doerr, &amp; Rousakis, 2017). The CRMsci, which is a conceptual model designed to integrate the metadata produced by scientific observations, seemed to us to be very appropriate for modelling the historical and technical analyses formulated by experts in the field on ancient textiles (Figure 3)<note> For example, the record describing a tapestry (“<hi rend="italic">lé de tenture</hi>” in French) preserved in the collections of the Château de Versailles includes a “History” field (“<hi rend="italic">Historique</hi>”) and a “Comment” field (“<hi rend="italic">Commentaire</hi>”). Using the CIDOC CRM and CRMsci models, we have expressed this information with the following triplets: <hi rend="italic">S4_Observation O8_observed E22_Man-Made Object; S4_Observation P2_has type E55_Type (Historique / Commentaire); S4_Observation P3_has note E62_String</hi>.</note>. We chose to use the <hi rend="italic">S4_Observation</hi> class provided by the CRMsci extension because it is defined as “the activity of gaining scientific knowledge about particular states of physical reality gained by empirical evidence, experiments and by measurements” (Kritsotaki, Hiebel, Theodoridou, Doerr, &amp; Rousakis, 2017). The observations made by the experts on ancient textiles thus seemed to us to fall under this type of scientific activity.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image3.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Figure 3. Use of the <hi rend="italic">S4</hi> class <hi rend="italic">Observation</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="evaluating-the-ontology">
               <head>Evaluating the ontology</head>
               <p>The quality and robustness of this ontology is then assessed by a mapping process. This process consists of verifying that it is possible to represent all the metadata fields using the classes and properties selected in the ontology. The mapping is produced manually by domain experts, who then provide mapping rules for each of the collected datasets. Concretely, we chose two objects described extensively<note> That is, with the highest number of descriptive fields filled in the records.</note> in the catalogues of the selected institutions. Then, we interpreted each of the descriptive fields in the form of triplets Entity (E) - Relation (R) - Entity (E). To do this, we relied on the collected metadata files, converted into an intermediate JSON format. Figure 4 shows an extract corresponding to the metadata contained in Table 1.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image4.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Figure 4. Extract from a JSON metadata file</p>
               <p>As shown in Table 1, we have therefore decomposed the whole metadata schema with Class (C) - Property (P) - Class (C) triples from the SILKNOW data model.</p>
               <table>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>Field Value</cell>
                     <cell>Value</cell>
                     <cell>Path</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>Désignation</cell>
                     <cell>Lé de tenture</cell>
                     <cell>E22_Man-Made Object P102_has title E35_Title                          </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>N° d'inventaire</cell>
                     <cell>VMB 14527</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <p>E15_Identifier Assignment P140_assigned attribute to E22_Man-Made Object</p>
                        <p>E15_Identifier Assignment P37_assigned E42_Identifier</p>
                        <p>E15_Identifier Assignment P14_carried out by E40_Legal Body (Château de Versailles)</p>
                        <p>E42_Identifier P2_has type E55_Type (N° d’inventaire)</p>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>Date de création</cell>
                     <cell>XVIIIe siècle</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <p>E12_Production P4_has time-span E52_Time-Span</p>
                        <p>E52_Time-Span P78_is identified by E49_Time Appellation</p>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>Table 1. Table containing mapping rules</p>
               <p>We then represented these triples as graphs<note> On Figure 5, we visualize the triplets modelling the information on the production conditions of the tapestry conserved at the Château de Versailles, namely the production date ( <hi rend="italic">E12_Production P4_has time-span E52_Time-Span</hi>), the producer/creator (<hi rend="italic">E12_Production P14_carried out by E39_Actor</hi>), the materials used (<hi rend="italic">E12_Production P126_employed E57_Material</hi>), and the techniques used (<hi rend="italic">E12_Production P32_use general technique E55_Type</hi>)s.</note> as in Figure 5. These graphs allow us to visualize the triplets and to check their consistency more easily. </p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image5.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Figure 5. Triplets (extracts) used to model the metadata of the record shown in Figure 3</p>
               <p>After providing these mapping rules, we found that all the metadata fields could be expressed using the SILKNOW data model. The JSON files were then converted to create the knowledge graph using an RDF converter. The graph, which contains the metadata describing 36,210 objects illustrated by 74,527 images, is finally loaded into a triple store, while the images are uploaded separately to a media server. All data is available via a faceted browser<note> https://data.silknow.org/fct/.</note> and a SPARQL endpoint<note> https://data.silknow.org/sparql.</note>. This browser can also be used via a graphical user interface which provides access to the SILKNOW multilingual thesaurus dedicated to the vocabulary of historical silk textiles<note>
                     <ref target="https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/">https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/</ref>.</note> (see “The SILKNOW extension”). All the data collected is accessible with the exploratory search engine ADASilk (<hi rend="italic">Advanced Data Analysis for Silk Heritage</hi>
                  <note>
                     <ref target="https://ada.silknow.org/fr">https://ada.silknow.org/fr</ref>. </note>) <ptr target="#schleider2021"/>(Schleider, Troncy, Ehrhart, et al. 2021). Figure 6 shows the record describing the tapestry preserved in Versailles, as it appears in ADASilk<note> To consult it directly online: <ref target="https://ada.silknow.org/object/2b347a9f-2c51-30f9-9e8d-ca9396a3228e">https://ada.silknow.org/object/2b347a9f-2c51-30f9-9e8d-ca9396a3228e</ref>.   </note>.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image6.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Figure 6. Example of a record in ADASilk</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>SILKNOW's contribution to textile heritage: the example of religious fabrics</head>
            <p>The benefits of using this type of technology are particularly apparent when it comes to religious textiles. Religious textile collections are preserved in a wide variety of institutions. While collections of "ordinary" textiles are generally preserved in fashion museums, they can also be found in ethnological or decorative art museums. Religious textiles are preserved not only in national heritage institutions, but also in small and medium-sized ecclesiastical museums. In addition, churches, cathedrals and convents may use these fabrics as part of their liturgy and daily devotions. There are also collections preserved by companies that produced these fabrics: such is the case of the Garín archives - one of the SILKNOW consortium's partners - which conserve very rich samples of religious fabrics representative of Spanish silk manufacturing in the 18th and 19th centuries (Alba, Gaitán, León, &amp; Sebastián, 2020). The integration of the inventories produced by these structures into the SILKNOW Knowledge Graph enables them to be displayed via ADASilk, thus improving the accessibility and visibility of their collections.</p>
            <p>In some cases, small heritage structures do not have a catalog or even an inventory, which makes it extremely difficult to determine the origin of the fabrics kept there. These fabrics, widely dispersed across Europe, are even incomplete<note> Religious vestments have often been conceived as ensembles: for example, a chasuble is accompanied by a stole.</note>. As a result, information is fragmented and disconnected, making it difficult in many cases to correctly identify and date these artifacts, and hence to catalogue them. ADASilk enables smaller organizations, particularly church museums and religious institutions, to trace the links between the objects they conserve and other artifacts held in distant collections, and to integrate them into a renewed chronology. This can help create new synergies for ecclesiastical collections, cathedrals and parishes that are custodians of this heritage (Alba, Gaitán, León, &amp; Sebastián, 2020).</p>
            <p>Small parishes and diocesan museums often lack the resources - both financial and human - to properly conserve these works. This information is also indispensable when these establishments want to restore the fabrics they conserve, as they rarely have experts capable of carrying out the appropriate research. This results in a lack of appropriate methodology and restoration that should stem from a thorough knowledge of weaving techniques, materials, design and historical and artistic links in order to better preserve these assets (Alba, et al., 2019). ADASilk enables them to compare the fabrics they conserve with those in other collections, and thus obtain the information they need to launch better-documented restoration campaigns. It can be very difficult to distinguish the origin and technique of certain fabrics without applying a technical analysis which, in some cases, leads to the destruction of part of the textile (Alba, Gaitán, León, &amp; Sebastián, 2020). Comparing fabrics held in other collections - and already catalogued - is therefore particularly useful when it comes to analysing and identifying old and rare fabrics without having to damage them.</p>
            <p>In addition to integrating heterogeneous data into the knowlegde graph, the SILKNOW ontology provides a structure for automatic image recognition, facilitating the discovery of similarities between several textiles preserved in various European institutions. Image recognition performed on images from Garín's collections and images from public museums (Dorozynski, Clermont, &amp; Rottensteiner, 2019) (Clermont, Dorozynski, Wittich, &amp; Rottensteiner, 2020) enabled (Alba, Gaitán, León, &amp; Sebastián, 2020) to highlight the great similarities between an 18th-century dalmatic preserved by the Centro de Documentación y Museo Textil (CDMT) in Terrassa (Spain) and Garín's 19th-century Francia model. The similarity of these two objects based on their motifs shows that Garín imitated models from Lyon to decorate its religious textiles. A comparison of these two objects through their motifs reveals that Garín drew inspiration from Lyonnais motifs for its religious textiles. These images help us to understand the link between Valencian and French motifs. On the other hand, during the 19th century, silk industries turned to revivals, reembracing ancient motifs that may have appeared obsolete and reinterpreting them to suit the tastes of each period. This complicates the process of dating and attribution. Sometimes, textiles found in geographically distant locations exhibit strikingly similar features; and the same fabric design can be observed in both secular and ecclesiastical garments. These confusing scenarios prompt researchers to question whether these designs are original or, alternatively, imitations of other textiles.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="X07e2f423f6e371063d241a96e63102f19f56ea6">
            <head>Integrating annotations into the data model</head>
            <div xml:id="prov-dm-provenance-data-model">
               <head>Prov DM: Provenance Data Model</head>
               <p>SILKNOW has developed text (Massri &amp; Mladenić, 2020) (Schleider &amp; Troncy, Zero-Shot Information Extraction to Enhance a Knowledge Graph Describing Silk Textiles, 2021) and image (Dorozynski, Clermont, &amp; Rottensteiner, 2019) (Clermont, Dorozynski, Wittich, &amp; Rottensteiner, 2020) analysis methods that infer new properties about objects from the metadata describing them, so as to enrich the existing metadata. If we examine the record shown in Figure 6, we find the following information in the “Technique” field: Damask 71% and Embroidery 52% and in the “Depiction” field: Floral motif 51% and Vegetal motif 57% (see Figure 7).</p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image7.JPG"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Figure 7. Fabric predictions and associated confidence scores: example</p>
               <p>This new information was obtained using convolutional neural networks trained on the data (texts and images) contained in the knowledge graph. Based on textual descriptions of silk objects or on images representing them, text (Rei, 2021) or image (Dorozynski &amp; Rottensteiner, SILKNOW Image Classification - final version WP6 - Multi-Task Classification (1.0), 2021) classification models are able to predict the values of certain properties: the period of production, the place of production, the technique and the material for the text classification model; the previous properties, plus the patterns represented for the image classification model. Each of these predictions is associated with a confidence score expressed as a percentage. In the previous example, the text classification model predicted the “damask” value with a confidence score of 71% for the “Technique” property; the image classification model predicted the floral motif value with a confidence score of 51% for the “Depiction” property.</p>
               <p>It was crucial to incorporate this new information into the data model, so that it could be integrated into the knowledge graph. We also aimed to make a clear distinction between these predictions and the original data. We also want to provide ADASilk users with information on the degree of reliability of the results of these analyses. To model these annotations, we have chosen to use the conceptual data model Provenance Data Model (Prov DM), recommended by the W3C (Belhajjame, et al., 2013). Figure 8 shows the entities and relationships from Prov DM that we used in graph form<note> A description of the panel preserved in the <hi rend="italic">Musée des Arts Décoratifs</hi> can be found at the following address: <ref target="https://ada.silknow.org/fr/object/99528c86-aac9-3231-a9d9-b84f6e4756fd">https://ada.silknow.org/fr/object/99528c86-aac9-3231-a9d9-b84f6e4756fd</ref>. </note> .</p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image8.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Figure 8. Integration of image analysis data with ProvDM</p>
               <p>Image or text analysis is represented as a <hi rend="italic">Prov:Activity</hi> which can be qualified by a type (image analysis or text analysis). Depending on the case, this <hi rend="italic">Prov:Activity</hi> takes an <hi rend="italic">E38_Image</hi> (image analysis) or a text or <hi rend="italic">E62_String</hi> (text analysis) as input and produces two declarations as output. In this model, the date of the analysis can be specified ; and if necessary, the analysis module can be specified with a <hi rend="italic">prov:Agent</hi> class (of type <hi rend="italic">Software Agent</hi>).</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="the-silknow-extension">
               <head>The SILKNOW extension</head>
               <p>During our examination of the metadata, we noticed that the technical and historical analyses written in free text were particularly rich. These sometimes very long blocks of text provide information about the weaving process, such as which weave(s)<note> The term “weave” refers to the way in which the weft and warp threads are interwoven. This is called satin weave, for example. For more information on this term, please consult the SILKNOW thesaurus: <ref target="https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/page/318">https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/page/318</ref>. </note> , or which type(s) of yarns were used. However, this semantic richness is difficult to capture in the CIDOC CRM<note> The SILKNOW data model proposes to use the two triplets <hi rend="italic">S4_Observation O8_observed S4_Observation</hi> and <hi rend="italic">S4_Observation P3_has note E62_String</hi> to model the data provided by the metadata fields corresponding to these analyses (cf. Figure 3).</note>. To integrate these descriptions into our data model, we use the P3_has note property, which is “a container for all informal descriptions about an object that have not been expressed in terms of CRM constructs” (Le Boeuf, Doerr, Emil Ore, &amp; Stead, 2015). It is used to model the way in which an object is characterized (e.g. its appearance, structure, etc.), but it does not allow to express “in a structured form, everything that can be said about an item”. This is one of the consequences of the CIDOC CRM formalism which does not have the function of capturing everything that can be said about an object.</p>
               <p>These blocks of free text provide particularly precise information on the techniques used to produce the textiles described; often, they also provide detailed iconographic descriptions. The textual analysis carried out on these texts has thus made it possible to extract technical information (weaves and weaving techniques) and other information relating to iconographic description (motifs and styles), as illustrated in figure 9. These different types of information may be of interest to the general public looking for particular patterns, textile specialists working on the history of techniques, or designers and creative industries wishing to draw inspiration from a historical style. Access to this information via a search engine would also offer a richer user experience by enabling the user to perform more refined queries on the data.</p>
               <p>When the data is integrated into the knowledge graph, some information (techniques and patterns) is annotated using the SILKNOW thesaurus (for more information on this thesaurus, see (Léon, Gaitán, Sebastian Lozano, Alba Pagán, &amp; Insa, 2019)). This semantic enrichment is achieved in the following way: if the value of a character string for a technique or pattern can be associated with one of the character strings proposed by the thesaurus, this value is replaced by a unique identifier. Modelling these concepts by means of a formal language would make it possible to integrate these annotations into the knowledge graph, to give access to this new data via the exploratory search engine, and to create links between these concepts and the thesaurus more easily.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image9.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Figure 9. Types of information extracted from the descriptions: examples from the catalogues of the <hi rend="italic">Palais Galliera</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Victoria &amp; Albert Museum</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Mobilier National</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The inherent flexibility of CIDOC CRM allows for the creation of new classes and properties to express new kinds of information. The aim is not to capture everything that can be said about an object, but to express some of the things that have been said about it - in this case, information about the process that led to the production of a silk fabric. Based on the results of the text analysis and the resulting data annotation, we created a CIDOC CRM-compatible model to formally express the process of creating and producing a silk fabric. This specialised extension, accessible via OntoME, offers 23 classes and 12 properties (Puren &amp; Vernus, SIKNOW 0.1., 2021). To create this extension, we adopted a bottom-up approach, relying primarily on the examination of collected data. We also worked with domain experts to verify the validity of these new classes and properties.</p>
               <p>Among these 23 classes and properties is class <hi rend="italic">T1_Weaving</hi>, which is a subclass of <hi rend="italic">E12_Production</hi>. <hi rend="italic">T1_Weaving</hi> refers to the activity of interlacing at right angles the warp threads (the threads along the length of the fabric, which are stretched on the loom) and the weft threads (the perpendicular threads that run alternately between the warp threads). This activity is usually carried out using a loom<note> The “weaving” entry can be found in the SILKNOW thesaurus: https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/page/526.</note>. The product of the weaving is a fabric, represented by the class <hi rend="italic">T7_Fabric</hi>, itself a subclass of <hi rend="italic">E22_Man-Made Object</hi>. The production of this fabric is carried out following a technical procedure(s) (<hi rend="italic">T25_Weaving Technique</hi>). The weaving process always includes the use of at least one specific weave (<hi rend="italic">T21_Weave</hi>). It then produces a fabric that is often decorated with patterns (<hi rend="italic">T18_Motif</hi>), sometimes characteristic of a style (<hi rend="italic">T11_Style</hi>) identified by experts in the field (<hi rend="italic">T13_Style Assignment</hi>). In Figure 10, we express this information with these new classes and associated properties, for a set of tapestries for the Grand salon of the apartment of the Empress<note> Marie-Louise I, Duchess of Parma, and second wife of Napoleon I.</note> in Versailles<note> Tenture, portières, cantonnières destinées au Grand salon de l'appartement de l'Impératrice à Versailles (1813, Bissardon, Cousin &amp; Bony), Collections du  <hi rend="italic">Mobilier national</hi>, URL: <ref target="https://collection.mobiliernational.culture.gouv.fr/objet/GMMP-877-001">https://collection.mobiliernational.culture.gouv.fr/objet/GMMP-877-001</ref>. </note> kept in the collection of the French <hi rend="italic">Mobilier national</hi> (see the last description on Figure 9).</p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image10.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Figure 10. CIDOC CRM and SILKNOW extension compliant graph</p>
               <p>As mentioned above, these new classes and properties facilitate the integration of semantic enrichments into the knowledge graph and allow the end user to query these annotations, but also to have access to additional contextualization elements. As shown in Figure 11, the <hi rend="italic">T32_Weave Type</hi> class, for example, is used to express the different weaves used during the weaving process and defined in the SILKNOW thesaurus. </p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image11.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Figure 11. Using the <hi rend="italic">T32_Weave Type</hi> class</p>
               <p>We have done the same for the information on patterns by creating the class <hi rend="italic">T34_Pattern Type</hi>. This class should also make it possible to create links with the definitions available in the thesaurus. For example, the user could consult the definition of the Palme motif<note> The “palm” concept is defined in the thesaurus: <ref target="https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/page/763">https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/page/763</ref>.  </note> , represented on the tapestries held in the collections of the <hi rend="italic">Mobilier national</hi>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="conclusion">
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>Silk Heritage is of crucial importance for understanding European history and culture. But some conservation institutions lack the means to promote it and make it accessible to the public. More generally, Silk Heritage suffers from a lack of visibility, especially online, which has become the preferred tool for searching and discovering new information. Semantic Web technologies, however, offer the possibility of disseminating Cultural Heritage data more easily on the Web by improving its discoverability, but also of enriching this data by linking it to other information.</p>
            <p>The SILKNOW project wished to exploit these potentialities to enhance the visibility of the European Silk Heritage, by developing the exploratory search engine ADASilk dedicated to these specialised collections. ADASilk is based on a knowledge graph, whose creation is based on the SILKOW ontology - a subset of the CIDOC CRM and CRMsci ontology. The richness of the metadata contained in the knowledge graph has also led us to develop the SILKNOW extension, a conceptual model for the description of ancient silk textiles. We believe that this specialized extension represents a first step in the development of a domain ontology for textile Cultural Heritage. Data reusers indeed play a vital role in data modeling. They can suggest collaborative and shared models to ensure this data is interoperable and completely reusable in the context of the Semantic Web. We have thus conceived the SILKNOW extension as a first step towards the creation and dissemination of a new compatible model recognized by the CIDOC CRM SIG. To achieve such recognition, it is essential to extend the SILKNOW framework to create an ontology that encompasses not only the results of textile manufacture, but also the places and methods of production, the circumstances surrounding this production and the memories associated with it. In addition, we have placed special emphasis in this article on the methodology we have used to create this specialized extension, so as to enable other research projects and institutions to adopt the same approach. We believe that such an approach could be systematized when the aim is to promote and protect an endangered heritage using the Web.</p>
            <p>By creating the ADASilk exploratory search engine, SILKNOW has demonstrated the value of using Semantic Web technologies to aggregate heterogeneous heritage data, provide access to it and increase its visibility. It follows in the footsteps of other projects that also aim to promote fragile and endangered heritage and demonstrates the validity of this type of approach for large-scale processing of Cultural Heritage data. SILKNOW also illustrates the important work that needs to be done on heritage data if the objectives of the Semantic Web are to be achieved. But to bring this kind of project to fruition, a strong institutional commitment is required. Not only from the point of view of producing open, high-quality data, which is the essential fuel for this type of project, but also from an organizational and technical point of view. Such a commitment is not accessible to small and medium-sized conservation institutions (Sebastián-Lozano, et al., 2023). Indeed, such projects require significant investments, and therefore remain inaccessible to small institutions, which would be the first to benefit from them. Having demonstrated the value of these approaches, it is therefore necessary to consider the development of tools to access these technologies, and thus make them accessible to the greatest number of people.</p>
            <p>The integration of data into the SILKNOW Knowledge Graph could be considerably facilitated by the use of automatic classification tools, based on the exploitation of Linked Open Data. Case studies have demonstrated the value of developing such methods for creating links (or properties) between entities (Bianchini &amp; Bargioni, 2021). But they have also shown the need for semantic data to be available from a high-quality standard and as complete as possible (Freire, Manguinhas, &amp; Isaac, An Observational Study of Equivalence Links in Cultural Heritage Linked Data for agents, 2020) (Bianchini &amp; Bargioni, 2021); without this, crucial aspects of the data may be left out, and links between data may thus be missing. We must be aware, however, that the diversity of cataloguing practices - and sometimes errors in metadata - as well as the inherent complexity of historical data, often unstructured or a little structured (Meroño-Peñuela, et al., 2015), can be a brake on this kind of approach, both from the point of view of automatic classification and the development of a knowledge graph based on CIDOC CRM.</p>
            <p>References</p>
            <p>
               <ref target="BIBLIOGRAPHY">Achichi, M., Lisena, P., Todorov, K., Troncy, R., &amp; Delahousse, J. (2018). DOREMUS: A Graph of Linked Musical Works. <hi rend="italic">ISWC: International Semantic Web Conference</hi>, (pp. 279-294). Monterey, CA, United States.</ref>
            </p>
            <p>Alba, E., Fernández, M., Gaitán, M., León, A., Portalés, C., Sebastián-Lozano, J., &amp; Sevilla, J. (2019). Technological tools for the conservation of silk heritage: Improving the conservation of European Religious Textile Cultural Heritage. <hi rend="italic">ESRARC 2019. 11th European Symposium on Religious Art, Restoration &amp; Conservation</hi> (pp. 150-156). Kermes.</p>
            <p>Alba, E., Gaitán, M., León, A., &amp; Sebastián, J. (2020). Spanish Religious Textiles from the 18th and 19th Centuries. The Garín Case. <hi rend="italic">European Journal of Science and Theology, 16</hi>(1), 187-197.</p>
            <p>Belhajjame, K., B'Far, R., Cheney, J., Coppens, S., Cresswell, S., Gil, Y., . . . Tilmes, C. (2013). PROV-DM: The PROV Data Model. W3C Recommendation 30 April 2013. (L. Moreau, &amp; P. Missier, Éds.) Récupéré sur https://www.w3.org/TR/prov-dm/</p>
            <p>Beretta, F. (2021). A challenge for historical research: making data FAIR using a collaborative ontology management environment (OntoME). <hi rend="italic">Semantic Web - Interoperability, Usability, Applicability, 2</hi>(2), 279-294.</p>
            <p>Bermès, E. (2013). Enabling your catalogue for the Semantic Web. Dans S. Chambers (Éd.), <hi rend="italic">Catalogue 2.0 : the future of the library catalogue</hi> (pp. 117-142). Chicago: Neal-Schuman, an imprint of the American Library Association.</p>
            <p>Berners-Lee, T., Hendler, J., &amp; Lassila, O. (2001). The Semantic Web. <hi rend="italic">Scientific American, 5</hi>(284), 28-37.</p>
            <p>Bianchini, C., &amp; Bargioni, S. (2021). Automated Classification Using Linked Open. <hi rend="italic">Cataloging &amp;, 59</hi>(8), 835-852. doi:10.1080/01639374.2021.1977447</p>
            <p>Bizer, C., Heath, T., &amp; Berners-Lee, T. (2009). Linked Data: the Story so far. <hi rend="italic">International Journal on Semantic Web and Information Systems, 5</hi>, 1-22.</p>
            <p>Christen, P. (2012). <hi rend="italic">Data Matching.</hi> Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer.</p>
            <p>Claerr, T., &amp; Westeel, I. (2010). <hi rend="italic">Numériser et mettre en ligne.</hi> Villeurbanne: Presses de l’enssib.</p>
            <p>Clermont, D., Dorozynski, M., Wittich, D., &amp; Rottensteiner, F. (2020). Assessing the semantic similarity of images of silk fabrics using convolutional neural networks. <hi rend="italic">SPRS Annals of the Photogrammetry, Remote Sensing and Spatial Information Sciences</hi>, (p. 641_648).</p>
            <p>Doerr, M. (2003). The CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model : An ontological approach to semantic interopérability of metadata. <hi rend="italic">AI Magazine</hi>(24), 75-92.</p>
            <p>Dorozynski, M., &amp; Rottensteiner, F. (2021). SILKNOW Image Classification - final version WP6 - Multi-Task Classification (1.0). doi:https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5091813</p>
            <p>Dorozynski, M., Clermont, D., &amp; Rottensteiner, F. (2019). Muti-task deep learning with incomplete training samples for the image-based prediction of variables describing silk fabrics. <hi rend="italic">ISPRS Annals of the Photogrammetry, Remote Sensing and Spatial Information Sciences, IV</hi>(2/W6), 47-54.</p>
            <p>Eastermann, B. (2015). Open data et crowdsourcing : un état des lieux du point de vue des musées. <hi rend="italic">La Lettre de l’OCIM</hi>(162), 41-46.</p>
            <p>Foron-Dauphin, N., &amp; Cano, D. (2016). Le patrimoine des Soieries Bonnet (Jujurieux, Ain) : conserver et valoriser in situ un ensemble unique de l’industrie textile. <hi rend="italic">In Situ Revues des patrimoines</hi>(29).</p>
            <p>Fournier, M., Despierres, C., Mercandelli, C., &amp; Bernard, E. (2016). Conservation et présentation des lieux et collections de patrimoine textile : l’exemple de la fédération « Transmission du savoir-faire textile en Rhône-Alpes ». <hi rend="italic">{In Situ Revues des patrimoines</hi>(29).</p>
            <p>Freire, N., Manguinhas, H., &amp; Isaac, A. (2020). An Observational Study of Equivalence Links in Cultural Heritage Linked Data for agents. <hi rend="italic">Digital Libraries for Open Knowledge : 24th International Conference on Theory and Practice of Digital Libraries, TPDL 2020, Lyon, France, August 25–27, 2020, Proceedings</hi> (pp. 62-70). Cham: Springer International Publishing.</p>
            <p>Freire, N., Meijers, E., Voorburg, R., &amp; Isaac, A. (2018). Aggregation of cultural heritage datasets through the Web of Data. <hi rend="italic">Procedia Computer Science</hi>, 120-126.</p>
            <p>Freire, N., Voorburg, R., Cornelissen, R., de Valk, S., Meijers, E., &amp; Isaac, A. (2019). Aggregation of Linked Data in the Cultural Heritage Domain: A Case Study in the Europeana Network. <hi rend="italic">Information, 10</hi>(8).</p>
            <p>Gaitán, M., Alba, E., León, A., Pérez, M., Sevilla, J., &amp; Portalés, C. (2019). Towards the Preservation and Dissemination of Historical Silk Weaving Techniques in the Digital Era. <hi rend="italic">Heritage, 2</hi>(3), 1892-1911.</p>
            <p>Grant, A., Nieuwenhuis, J., &amp; Petersen, T. (1995). <hi rend="italic">International guidelines for museum object information : the CIDOC information categories.</hi> s.l.: ICOM International Committee for Documentation.</p>
            <p>Gruber, T. (1993). <hi rend="italic">A Translation Approach to Portable Ontology Specifications.</hi> Stanford: Knowledge Systems Laboratory, Stanford University.</p>
            <p>Hyvönen, E., Ikkala, E., Koho, M., Tuominen, J., Burrows, T., &amp; Ransom, L. (2021). Mapping Manuscript Migrations on the Semantic Web: A Semantic Portal and Linked Open Data Service for Premodern Manuscript Research. <hi rend="italic">ISWC 2021: The Semantic Web – ISWC 2021</hi> (pp. 615-630). Cham: Springer.</p>
            <p>Kergosien, Eric, Daloz, A., Chaudiron, S., &amp; Jacquemin, B. (2019). Le CIDOC CRM, un modèle ontologique pour représenter les connaissances du bassin minier des Hauts de France. Premiers résultats. <hi rend="italic">6th Hyperheritage International Symposium (HIS6) ”La fabrique du patrimoine à l’ère numérique".</hi> Paris.</p>
            <p>Koch, I., Ribeiro, C., &amp; Lopes, C. (2020). ArchOnto, a CIDOC-CRMBased Linked Data Model for the Portuguese Archives. Dans M. Hall, T. Merčun, T. Risse, &amp; F. Duchateau (Éds.), <hi rend="italic">Digital Libraries for Open Knowledge. TPDL 2020. Lecture Notes in Computer Science</hi> (pp. 133-146). Cham: Springer.</p>
            <p>Kritsotaki, A., Hiebel, G., Theodoridou, M., Doerr, M., &amp; Rousakis, Y. (2017). <hi rend="italic">Definition of the CRMsci. An Extension of CIDOC-CRM to support scientific observation. Version 1.2.3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Le Boeuf, P., Doerr, M., Emil Ore, C., &amp; Stead, S. (2015). <hi rend="italic">Definition of the CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model. Version 6.2.</hi> Récupéré sur https://cidoc-crm.org/</p>
            <p>Léon, A., Gaitán, M., Sebastian Lozano, J., Alba Pagán, E., &amp; Insa, I. (2019). SILKNOW. Designing a thesaurus about historical silk for small and medium-sized textile museums. <hi rend="italic">Science and Digital Technology for Cultural Heritage: Interdisciplinary Approach to Diagnosis, Vulnerability, Risk Assessment and Graphic Information Models. Proceedings of the 4th International Congress Science and Technology for the Conservation of Cult</hi> (pp. 187-190). London: CRC Press.</p>
            <p>Marden, J., Li-Madeo, C., Whysel, N., &amp; Edelstein, J. (2013). Linked open data for cultural heritage. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 31st ACM International Conference on Design of Communication - SIGDOC ’13. the 31st ACM international conference</hi> (pp. 107–112). New York, NY, USA: Association for Computing Machinery.</p>
            <p>Massri, B., &amp; Mladenić, D. (2020). Extracting structured metadata from multilingual textual descriptions in the domain of silk heritage. <hi rend="italic">SiKDD 2020. Conference on Data Mining and Data Warehouses.</hi> Ljubjana.</p>
            <p>Meroño-Peñuela, A., Ashkpour, A., van Erp, M., Mandemakers, K., Breure, L., Scharnhorst, A., . . . van Harmelen, F. (2015). Semantic Technologies for Historical Research : a Survey. <hi rend="italic">Semantic Web, 6</hi>(6), 539-564.</p>
            <p>Messaoudi, T., De Luca, L., Véron, P., &amp; Halin, G. (2019). Vers une ontologie de domaine pour l’analyse de l'état de conservation du bâti patrimonial. <hi rend="italic">In Situ. Revue des patrimoines</hi>(39).</p>
            <p>Pagán, E. A., Gaitán Salvatella, M., Pitarch, M. D., León Muñoz, A., Moya Toledo, M., Ruiz, J. M., . . . Puren, M. (2020). From Silk to Digital Technologies: A Gateway to New Opportunities for Creative Industries, Traditional Crafts and Designers. The SILKNOW Case. <hi rend="italic">Sustainability, 12</hi>(19).</p>
            <p>Peroni, S., Tomasi, F., &amp; Vitali, F. (2013). The aggregation of heterogeneous metadata in Web-based cultural heritage collections. A case study. <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Web Engineering and Technology, 8</hi>(4), 412-432.</p>
            <p>Petrov, J. (2019). <hi rend="italic">Fashion, History, Museums. Inventing the display of dress.</hi> London: Bloomsbury Academic.</p>
            <p>Portalés, C., Sebastián, J., Alba, E., Sevilla, J., Gaitán, M., Ruiz, P., &amp; Fernández, M. (2018). Interactive Tools for the Preservation, Dissemination and Study of Silk Heritage — An Introduction to the SILKNOW Project. <hi rend="italic">Multimodal Technologies and Interaction, 2</hi>(2).</p>
            <p>Puren, M., &amp; Vernus, P. (2021). <hi rend="italic">SIKNOW 0.1.</hi> Consulté le décembre 29, 2021, sur https://ontome.net/namespace/36</p>
            <p>Puren, M., &amp; Vernus, P. (2021). Silknow Generic Profile. Récupéré sur http://ontome.dataforhistory.org/profile/7</p>
            <p>Rei, L. (2021). SILKNOW Text Classifier Models. doi:https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5070696</p>
            <p>Schleider, T., &amp; Troncy, R. (2021). Zero-Shot Information Extraction to Enhance a Knowledge Graph Describing Silk Textiles. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 5th Joint SIGHUM Workshop on Computational Linguistics for Cultural Heritage, Social Sciences, Humanities and Literature.</hi> Punta Cana, Dominican Republic (online): Association for Computational Linguistics.</p>
            <p>Schleider, T., Troncy, R., Ehrhart, T., Dorozynski, M., Rottensteiner, F., Sebastian, L., &amp; Lo Cicero, G. (2021). Searching Silk Fabrics by Images Leveraging on Knowledge Graph and Domain Expert Rules. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop on Structuring and Understanding of Multimedia Heritage Contents</hi> (pp. 41–49). New York, NY, USA: Association for Computing Machinery.</p>
            <p>Schleider, T., Troncy, R., Gaitan, M., Sebastian Lozano, J., Mladenic, D., Kastelic, A., . . . Lo Cicero , G. (2021). The SILKNOW Knowledge Graph. <hi rend="italic">Preprint</hi>.</p>
            <p>Sebastián-Lozano, J., Pagán, E., Roig, E. M., Gaitán, M., León, A., Sevilla Peris, J., . . . Mladenic, D. (2023). Open Access to Data about Silk Heritage: A Case Study in Digital Information Sustainability. <hi rend="italic">Sustainability, 15</hi>(19), 14340.</p>
            <p>Stewart, T., &amp; Marcketti, S. (2012). Textiles, dress, and fashion museum website development: strategies and practices. <hi rend="italic">Museum Management and Curatorship, 27</hi>(5), 523-538.</p>
            <p>Suls, D. (2017). Europeana Fashion: Past, present and future. <hi rend="italic">Libraries Journal, 42</hi>(3), 123–129.</p>
            <p>Wang, Z., Xia, S., &amp; Niu, Q. (2014). A novel ontology analysis tool, Applied Mathematics &amp; Information Sciences. <hi rend="italic">Applied Mathematics &amp; Information Sciences, 8</hi>(1), 255-261.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl/>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
