<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
  xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
        <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Conceptual Modelling of the European Silk Heritage with the SILKNOW Data Model
          and Extension</title>
        <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
          <dhq:author_name>Marie <dhq:family>Puren</dhq:family> </dhq:author_name>
          <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5452-3913</idno>
          <dhq:affiliation>EPITA Paris</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>marie.puren@epita.fr</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Marie Puren is an Associate Professor of History and Digital Humanities at EPITA Paris. She is a member of the
              Laboratoire de Recherche de l'EPITA (LRE) and an associate researcher at the Jean-Mabillon Centre. Her work
              focuses in particular on heritage enhancement using digital humanities methods and tools. She is currently
              interested in the contribution of artificial intelligence to the promotion and exploitation of heritage
              collections.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
          <dhq:author_name>Pierre <dhq:family>Vernus</dhq:family> </dhq:author_name>
          <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9335-7070</idno>
          <dhq:affiliation>Université Lumière Lyon</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>pierre.vernus@msh-lse.fr</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>An Associate Professor of contemporary history at Université Lumière Lyon 2/Université de Lyon, Pierre Vernus
              is a member of the Laboratoire de recherche historique Rhône-Alpes (LARHRA) in Lyon. As part of the
              laboratory's Digital History research group, he has been contributing for many years to research into
              historical studies in a digital context from a collaborative and cumulative perspective, particularly focusing
              on Open Linked Data and the Semantic Web. He has coordinated or participated in several multidisciplinary
              research projects with a strong digital dimension, notably in collaboration with cultural heritage
              institutions.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
        <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
        <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
        <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000754<!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
        <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
        <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
        <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
        <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
        <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
          <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
          <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
          <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref> </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
          <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
          <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref> </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
        <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
          <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
          <!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
          <term corresp="#cultural_heritage"/>
          <term corresp="#data_modeling"/>
          <term corresp="#semantic_web"/>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
          <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
          <list type="simple">
            <item>CIDOC CRM</item>
            <item>ontology</item>
            <item>semantic web</item>
            <item>cultural heritage</item>
            <item>silk</item>
            <item>SILKNOW</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
      <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
        target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000754/000754.xml">GitHub
        </ref> </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
    <front>
      <dhq:abstract>
        <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
        <p>Silk holds significant historical importance in European history, fostering economic growth, innovation in weaving
          techniques, and the creation of exceptional artifacts. Despite the conservation efforts of numerous institutions,
          silk heritage remains at risk due to its fragile nature. This paper outlines the methodology employed by the
          Horizon 2020 SILKNOW project aimed at enhancing the promotion and preservation of silk-related cultural heritage
          collections. We present the development of a CIDOC CRM-based data model for the creation of a comprehensive
          knowledge graph. We also introduce the SILKNOW extension, designed to encapsulate the intricate semantics
          associated with the production processes of silk fabrics. Our results demonstrate the potential of Semantic Web
          technologies in safeguarding and enriching the visibility of silk heritage through improved data interoperability
          and accessibility.</p>
      </dhq:abstract>
      <dhq:teaser>
        <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
        <p/>
      </dhq:teaser>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>For the past ten years, the history of fashion has attracted a growing public <ptr target="#petrov2019"/> <ptr
          target="#stewart_etal2012"/>. But despite the interest shown in these collections, textile heritage remains under
          threat. This is particularly true of silk heritage, whose fragility poses major conservation problems and whose
          protection requires substantial investment. Few materials are of such historical, cultural and artistic importance;
          but a significant part of the silk-related collections are preserved by small institutions, lacking generally the
          means to promote their collections <ptr target="#portales_etal2018"/> <ptr target="#gaitan_etal2019"/> <ptr
          target="#pagan_etal2020"/>. Outside of the major events devoted to them, we also note the under-use of textile
          collections by visitors <ptr target="#stewart_etal2012"/>. This is why the digitization of cultural heritage has
          become one of the crucial issues for its promotion <ptr target="#eastermann2015"/>.</p>
        <p>When users are interested in textile cultural heritage online, they are generally faced with two situations. The
          large generalist museums have the technical, financial and human resources to disseminate their data on the Web,
          but they do not systematically highlight their textile collections on their websites. Conversely, small museums do
          not have the same resources as their better-endowed counterparts <ptr target="#claerr_etal2010"/> to promote
          specialized collections online, which can be particularly rich. This is particularly the case for silk heritage, as
          the example of the Rhône-Alpes region clearly illustrates <ptr target="#foron-Dauphin_etal2016"/> <ptr
          target="#fournier_etal2016"/>. These institutions do describe their collections, but the digital data they produce
          is, most of the time, inaccessible online. Without a digital presence, these collections remain generally unknown,
          except to a few connoisseurs and specialists.</p>
        <p>The Semantic Web offers particularly interesting prospects in this domain; it proposes to cultural heritage
          institutions to increase the visibility of their metadata on the Web by <q>freeing</q> it from catalogs; to
          aggregate this data with others and provide access to it in a federated way; to interconnect data with each other
          and, ultimately, to enrich this information more easily thanks to the links created between them. By encouraging
          the dissemination of structured data, Semantic Web technologies indeed facilitate the creation of links between
          dispersed historical sources <ptr target="#merono-Penuela_etal2015"/>. The Semantic Web is not a new Web that
          replaces the current Web, but an extension of it <ptr target="#berners-Lee_etal2001"/>, enabling navigation not
          between documents via hypertext links, but directly between data. This implies that all information is provided
          with a well-defined meaning, making it interpretable and reusable by data consumers, both human and machine, who
          will then be able to process it automatically and develop new applications and services <ptr target="#bermes2013"
          />. Museums are particularly interested in the aggregation possibilities offered by Semantic Web technologies <ptr
          target="#freire_etal2019"/>, especially for heterogeneous metadata <ptr target="#peroni_etal2013"/>. For example,
          the <title rend="italic">Europeana Fashion</title> portal provides access to the collections of over thirty
          European institutions. However, it primarily aggregates data from major European museums only <ptr
          target="#suls2017"/>, resulting in a notable exclusion of smaller museums. This approach neglects the promotion of
          more specialized collections, notably those focusing on silk. To address this deficiency, the H2020 <hi
          style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> project<note><title rend="italic">Silk Heritage in the Knowledge
          Society: from punched card to Big Data, Deep Learning and visual/tangible simulations</title>: <ref
          target="https://silknow.eu/">https://silknow.eu/</ref>. </note> has developed ADASilk, an innovative exploratory
          search engine. This engine offers federated searches across diverse cultural heritage collections, with a specific
          emphasis on silk-related artifacts.</p>
        <p>ADASilk is based on a knowledge graph that enables data from a variety of sources to be aggregated and presented
          online. A knowledge graph is a set of interconnected descriptions of entities - objects, people, events, concepts
          or situations - which can be enriched by a retrospective acquisition of information and integrated into ontologies
          <ptr target="#gruber1993"/>. This approach has proven particularly successful for other types of cultural heritage
          data: for example, bibliographic data describing musical works for the DOREMUS project <ptr
          target="#achichi_etal2018"/>, archival data for the ArchOnto project <ptr target="#koch_etal2020"/>, or historical
          data for the WarSampo project <ptr target="#hyvonen_etal2021"/>. The <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;"
          >SilkNow</hi> Knowledge Graph represents the data contained in the catalogues of 21 cultural heritage
          institutions<note>A full list of these institutions can be found here: <ref
          target="https://ada.silknow.org/fr/museums">https://ada.silknow.org/fr/museums</ref>. </note> , following a subset
          of the CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model or CIDOC-CRM. Collected online or provided directly by the institution
          concerned<note>Datasets have been made available to the project by <title rend="italic">Garin1820</title>, the
          <title rend="italic">Sicily cultural heritage</title> and the <title rend="italic">Musée d'Art et d'Industrie de
          Saint-Etienne</title>.</note>, the data describe objects that may be entirely made of silk, or incorporate other
          textile materials (natural fibers, metal threads), or be made of composite materials (e.g. wood in the case of
          furniture). The <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> project focused on objects produced or consumed
          in Europe between the mid-15th to the middle of the 19th century.</p>
        <p>In this paper, we present the different steps that allowed us to build the <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;"
          >SilkNow</hi> data model. We also describe the methodology we used to create a conceptual model extending the CIDOC
          CRM, and to integrate the annotations produced with machine learning methods. In a first part, we discuss the
          contributions of Semantic Web technologies for the protection and enrichment of silk heritage. In a second part, we
          explain the approach we adopted to develop the <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> data model. In
          the third part, we show how we used the Provenance Data Model or Prov DM to integrate the semantic annotations
          produced on these data thanks to the analysis of texts and images. We also propose to extend the CIDOC CRM with new
          classes and properties, so as to be able to express the complex semantics of the data describing the production
          process of silk fabrics.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Providing access to heterogeneous data using Semantic Web technologies</head>
        <div>
          <head>Heterogeneous metadata</head>
          <p>The records produced by all these institutions generally provide the same types of information: type of object,
            place and date of production, materials and techniques used, dimensions, and illustration(s). But the way in
            which this metadata is structured can vary greatly depending on the practices of its producers. These data come
            from institutions using various cataloguing standards and respecting their own description standards. <ref
            target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref> illustrates this problem by comparing the list of metadata describing two
            objects (here, two damasks<note>For a definition of <term>damask</term>, please consult the <hi
            style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> thesaurus: <ref
            target="https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/page/168"
            >https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/page/168</ref>. </note>) held respectively by the Museu Tèxtil Terrassa
            <note><ref target="http://imatex.cdmt.es/">http://imatex.cdmt.es/</ref> </note> and by the Victoria &amp; Albert
            Museum <note><ref target="https://www.vam.ac.uk/collections">https://www.vam.ac.uk/collections</ref>. </note> .
            The same types of information are used to describe these two objects, but they are expressed differently by the
            two museums. For example, the Victoria &amp; Albert Museum indicates in the same field the material and technique
            used, whereas the Museu Tèxtil Terrassa clearly separates this information.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure01">
            <head>Metadata describing the techniques and materials used: examples from the Museu Tèxtil Terrassa and the
              Victoria &amp; Albert Museum</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>side-by-side screenshots of museum webpages</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>In other words, the Victoria &amp; Albert Museum and the Museu Tèxtil Terrassa do not use the same data model.
            This is because the catalogues are designed as separate data silos, which are not supposed to communicate with
            each other. If one wants to collect this metadata on a large scale, it will therefore be difficult to process it
            automatically due to the heterogeneity of its structure, but also due to the lack of structure of the metadata.
            Different types of information are often found in the same field (as shown in <ref target="#figure01">Figure
            1</ref>), which makes it difficult to automatically process the data. By nature, cultural heritage data are
            heterogeneous: they are produced by various institutions, they describe various objects - which does not make
            them easily accessible by search engines <ptr target="#freire_etal2018"/>. To improve the discoverability of this
            data online, Semantic Web technologies offer the possibility of aggregating and providing access to metadata from
            different sources <ptr target="#freire_etal2019"/>. This is in this context that the <hi
            style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> project has created an exploratory search engine that enables a
            federated search of 21 collections dedicated to the conservation of European silk heritage.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>An ontology to build a knowledge graph</head>
          <p>Since the emergence of the Semantic Web, we have seen new changes in the use of the Web by museums, particularly
            the increasing openness of the data produced by these institutions <ptr target="#marden_etal2013"/> <ptr
            target="#eastermann2015"/>. The Semantic Web implements linked data <ptr target="#bizer_etal2009"/>, with the aim
            of enabling machines to understand the semantics of information published on the Web, and thus to create new,
            even unexpected, links between this information. The Semantic Web thus opens up new perspectives for the
            visibility of cultural heritage online, by making cultural heritage data available to all - and not only in a
            museum context -; by aggregating, publishing and enriching this data on the Web to facilitate its reuse; by
            linking this data to each other and to other data, so as to constitute an information network; and finally by
            making proposals for enriching this data.</p>
          <p>SILKNOW hypothesized that the use of Semantic Web technologies, and more specifically the creation of a
            knowledge graph, could facilitate the integration, exploration and retrieval of data describing historical silk
            artefacts. By containing this data, the <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> Knowledge Graph is
            intended to create a single access point to this data. The implementation of the Semantic Web is based on
            distinct principles and standards, leading to what is known as the <q>Web of Data</q> or Linked Data <ptr
            target="#bizer_etal2009"/>. This framework is made possible by RDF, a graph model designed by the W3C to describe
            Web resources and their metadata. In RDF, each unit of information is represented by a three-element assertion
            (or <term>triplet</term>) comprising a subject, a predicate (or property) and an object. These elements are
            represented as URIs (Uniform Resource Identifiers), thus becoming <q>resources</q>. These resources are then
            organized into <term>classes</term>, conceptualized as collections of individuals or objects. The Web of Data
            doesn't establish fixed definitions for classes and properties; similarly, RDF's versatility doesn't dictate
            specific usage rules for classes and properties <ptr target="#bermes2013"/>. Consequently, the adoption of a
            knowledge representation technology becomes essential. Ontologies play a crucial role here, enabling the
            declaration of classes, properties, their behaviors and hierarchy in languages such as RDF Schema (RDFS) and Web
            Ontology Language (OWL). The selection of specific classes and properties from an ontology to represent the
            desired information leads to the creation of a data model <ptr target="#bermes2013"/>.</p>
          <p>An ontology is a mutually shared conceptual model used to represent all information in a specific application
            domain by means of defined hierarchical concepts <ptr target="#gruber1993"/>. Consequently, the use of ontologies
            helps to solve the problem of semantic heterogeneity arising from diverse data sources, and to improve the
            interoperability of systems and applications. With the expansion of the Semantic Web, ontologies have been
            developed for a variety of purposes <ptr target="#wang_etal2014"/>. In the cultural heritage domain, reference
            ontologies have been established to detail objects and their relationships. The CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model
            or CIDOC-CRM, used to describe objects in museums collections, is a striking example <ptr target="#doerr2003"/>.
            When a domain-specific ontology is available, it is possible to create more restricted subsets or specializations
            tailored to particular sub-domains <ptr target="#messaoudi_etal2019"/> <ptr target="#kergosien_etal2019"/>. </p>
          <p>In the framework of <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi>, data is downloaded or collected from
            partner institutions; and these files are converted to create the knowledge graph using the Resource Description
            Framework as the data model. The graph, which contains all the metadata, is then loaded into a triple store. The
            converted data is then accessible online via ADASilk. The creation of the knowledge graph requires an RDF
            conversion, which is based on a manual mapping of the data. This mapping consists in putting in equivalence the
            data models describing similar objects <ptr target="#christen2012"/>. When working with two data sources A and B,
            data mapping can consist of matching each field in database A with those in database B. In the <hi
            style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> project, we are using many different sources; we have chosen to
            use a pivotal data model that makes it easier to perform this mapping between all the collected datasets. We have
            thus created a subset of the CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model (CIDOC CRM) ontology, which is instantiated at the
            time of the RDF conversion <ptr target="#schleider_etal2021b"/> <ptr target="#schleider_etal2021c"/>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>The <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> data model</head>
        <div>
          <head>Expressing the semantics of silk heritage information with the CIDOC CRM</head>
          <p>We chose CIDOC CRM <ptr target="#leboeuf_etal2015"/> because it is a conceptual model specifically developed for
            cultural heritage by the International Committee for Documentation (CIDOC) of the International Council of Museum
            (ICOM). An ISO standard since 2006, renewed in 2014<note><ref target="https://www.iso.org/standard/57832.html"
            >https://www.iso.org/standard/57832.html</ref> </note>, the CIDOC CRM is today a standard intended to ensure the
            interoperability of cultural heritage data. However, this standard is not set in stone; thus, at the time of
            writing this article, version 7.2.3 has been published<note><ref
            target="https://www.cidoc-crm.org/Version/version-7.2.3">https://www.cidoc-crm.org/Version/version-7.2.3</ref>
            </note> . However, we used version 6.2<note><ref target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org/Version/version-6.2.3"
            >http://www.cidoc-crm.org/Version/version-6.2.3</ref> </note> - the most recent version at the time of the start
            of the project in 2018. CIDOC CRM is also a flexible and extensible model. If necessary, this model can be
            extended by creating new classes and properties to express new information, without changing the basic structure
            of the model. These features allow the creation of specialized extensions such as FRBRoo (Functional Requirements
            for Bibliographic Records), a conceptual model for bibliographic data<note>IFLA Study Group on the Functional
            Requirements for Bibliographic Records, <title rend="italic">Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records:
            Final Report</title>, IFLA, 2009. URL: <ref target="https://repository.ifla.org/handle/123456789/811"
            >https://repository.ifla.org/handle/123456789/811</ref>. </note>, or CRMtex, a conceptual model for the study of
            ancient texts<note>Martin Doerr, Francesca Murano and Achille Felicetti, <title rend="italic">Definition of the
            CRMtex. An Extension of CIDOC CRM to Model Ancient Textual Entities</title>, Version 1.0, currently maintained by
            Francesca Murano and Achille Felicetti, June 2020. URL:
            https://cidoc-crm.org/crmtex/ModelVersion/version-1.0-0.</note>. There are a total of eleven compatible models on
            the official CIDOC CRM website<note>For the full list: <ref target="https://cidoc-crm.org/collaborations"
            >https://cidoc-crm.org/collaborations</ref>.</note>.</p>
          <p>CIDOC CRM allows the underlying semantics of cultural heritage information to be expressed, and thus
            heterogeneous data to be modelled in a homogeneous way. If we take the descriptions of the two damask fabrics
            preserved by the Victoria &amp; Albert Museum and the Museu Tèxtil Terrassa (<ref target="#figure01">Figure
            1</ref>), we can express in a unique way with CIDOC CRM the information about the technique and the materials
            used during the weaving process. CIDOC CRM allows to model each of the descriptive fields with triplets Class (C)
            - Property (P) - Class (C), which can be represented as graphs as in <ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref>.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure02">
            <head>Graph in accordance with the CIDOC CRM conceptual model</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>A graphical representation of an RDF graph showing how CIDOC classes (such as “E22 Man-Made Object” and
              “E38 Image”) are related through properties (such as “P138i has representation”) to construct full RDF
              statements in the form of triplets (for instance, “E22 Man-Made Object - P138i has representation - E38
              Image”)</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>In this figure, we can see that we have chosen to use the <hi rend="monospace">E22_Man Made Object</hi> class to
            represent the object described by the museum metadata. In version 6.2 of CIDOC CRM, this class is indeed used to
            model <quote rend="inline">physical objects purposely created by human activity</quote> <ptr
            target="#leboeuf_etal2015"/>.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>What classes and properties to represent this information?</head>
          <p>As a conceptual model, CIDOC CRM is intended to model all kinds of cultural heritage data and should be able to
            cover most cases. CIDOC CRM thus provides a wide range of classes and properties. For example, there are 89
            classes and 153 properties offered by version 6.2<note>A list of these classes and properties can be found on the
            OntoMe website: <ref target="https://ontome.net/namespace/1">https://ontome.net/namespace/1</ref></note>. In
            general, therefore, we do not need to use all the classes and properties offered by CIDOC CRM.</p>
          <p>To select the classes and properties needed to model the metadata collected by the project, it is first
            necessary to list the descriptive fields used to describe the textile objects. To do this, we analyzed and
            compared a large number of records, based on the documentation used by cultural heritage institutions to create
            this metadata (notably <ptr target="#grant_etal1995"/>). This analysis allowed us to draw up a list of
            descriptive fields commonly used to describe textile objects, while eliminating descriptive fields that were not
            relevant to the project - namely, fields providing information on the administrative management of the
            object.</p>
          <p>These descriptive fields were then classified into Information Groups, which form the Data Dictionary of the <hi
            style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> project. These information groups allowed us to identify the
            categories used by cultural heritage institutions to describe ancient textiles. We defined 22 Information Groups,
            from the most commonly used (e.g. <title rend="quotes">Object Title Information Group</title> or <title
            rend="quotes">Object Measure Information Group</title>) to the most rarely encountered (e.g. <title rend="quotes"
            >Object Missing Part Information Group</title> or <title rend="quotes">Exhibition Information Group</title>).
            These Information Groups then allowed us to rely on the Functional Overviews provided by the official CIDOC CRM
            documentation<note>The functional overviews are available online: <ref
            target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org/functional-units">http://www.cidoc-crm.org/functional-units</ref>. </note>, and
            to more easily select the most appropriate classes and properties to represent these information groups.
            Functional Overviews classify CIDOC CRM classes and properties into information categories that can be easily
            aligned with the Information Groups in our data dictionary. For example, the Functional Overviews provide an
            <title rend="quotes">Object Title Information</title> category that corresponds to our <title rend="quotes"
            >Object Title Information Group</title>.</p>
          <p>The <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> data model consists of the classes and properties
            selected to represent the information groups we have previously defined. It is accessible and documented online
            <ptr target="#puren_etal2021b"/> thanks to OntoME <ptr target="#beretta2021"/>, which is an ontology manager
            developed and maintained by the LARHRA laboratory. The <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> data
            model is mainly based on the CIDOC CRM Core version 6.2 (71 properties and 21 properties). We also selected two
            classes and one property from an extension of CIDOC CRM, the Scientific Observation Model (CRMsci) version
            1.2.3<note>The latest version 1.5 was released in January 2022.</note> <ptr target="#kritsotaki_etal2017"/>. The
            CRMsci, which is a conceptual model designed to integrate the metadata produced by scientific observations,
            seemed to us to be very appropriate for modelling the historical and technical analyses formulated by experts in
            the field on ancient textiles (<ref target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref>)<note>For example, the record describing a
            tapestry (<word xml:lang="fr">lé de tenture</word>) preserved in the collections of the Château de Versailles
            includes a <title rend="quotes">History</title> field (<word xml:lang="fr">Historique</word>) and a <title
            rend="quotes">Comment</title> field (<word xml:lang="fr">Commentaire</word>). Using the CIDOC CRM and CRMsci
            models, we have expressed this information with the following triplets: <hi rend="monospace">S4_Observation
            O8_observed E22_Man-Made Object; S4_Observation P2_has type E55_Type (Historique / Commentaire); S4_Observation
            P3_has note E62_String</hi>.</note>. We chose to use the <hi rend="monospace">S4_Observation</hi> class provided
            by the CRMsci extension because it is defined as <quote rend="inline">the activity of gaining scientific
            knowledge about particular states of physical reality gained by empirical evidence, experiments and by
            measurements</quote> <ptr target="#kritsotaki_etal2017"/>. The observations made by the experts on ancient
            textiles thus seemed to us to fall under this type of scientific activity.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure03">
            <head>Use of the <hi rend="monospace">S4</hi> class <hi rend="monospace">Observation</hi></head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>A diagram showing a metadata record with a descriptive note, and an accompanying RDF representation of a
              portion of that record showing the use of the CIDOC class “S4 Observation” and property “P3 has note” to model
              that aspect of the metadata</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Evaluating the ontology</head>
          <p>The quality and robustness of this ontology is then assessed by a mapping process. This process consists of
            verifying that it is possible to represent all the metadata fields using the classes and properties selected in
            the ontology. The mapping is produced manually by domain experts, who then provide mapping rules for each of the
            collected datasets. Concretely, we chose two objects described extensively<note>That is, with the highest number
            of descriptive fields filled in the records.</note> in the catalogues of the selected institutions. Then, we
            interpreted each of the descriptive fields in the form of triplets Entity (E) - Relation (R) - Entity (E). To do
            this, we relied on the collected metadata files, converted into an intermediate JSON format. <ref
            target="#example01">Example 1</ref> shows an extract corresponding to the metadata contained in <ref
            target="#table01">Table 1</ref>.</p>
          <dhq:example xml:id="example01">
            <head>Extract from a JSON metadata file</head>
            <eg lang="json"><hi rend="monospace"><![CDATA[
"fields": [
  {
    "label": "title",
    "value": "lé de tenture"
  },
  {
    "label": "Désignation",
    "value": "lé de tenture"
  },
  {
    "label": "N° d'inventaire",
    "value": "VMB 14527"
  },
  {
    "label": "Domaine",
    "value": "Textiles"
  },
  {
    "label": "Date de création",
    "value": "XVIIIe siècle"
  }
]]]></hi></eg>
          </dhq:example>
          <p>As shown in <ref target="#table01">Table 1</ref>, we have therefore decomposed the whole metadata schema with
            Class (C) - Property (P) - Class (C) triples from the <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> data
            model.</p>
          <table xml:id="table01">
            <head>Mapping rules in the <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> data model</head>
            <row role="label">
              <cell>Field Value</cell>
              <cell>Value</cell>
              <cell>Path</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
              <cell role="label" xml:lang="fr">Désignation</cell>
              <cell xml:lang="fr">Lé de tenture</cell>
              <cell><hi rend="monospace">E22_Man-Made Object P102_has title E35_Title</hi> </cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
              <cell role="label" rows="4" xml:lang="fr">N° d'inventaire</cell>
              <cell rows="4">VMB 14527</cell>
              <cell><hi rend="monospace">E15_Identifier Assignment P140_assigned attribute to E22_Man-Made Object</hi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="monospace">E15_Identifier Assignment P37_assigned E42_Identifier</hi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="monospace">E15_Identifier Assignment P14_carried out by E40_Legal Body (Château de
                Versailles)</hi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="monospace">E42_Identifier P2_has type E55_Type (N° d’inventaire)</hi></cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data">
              <cell role="label" rows="2" xml:lang="fr">Date de création</cell>
              <cell rows="2" xml:lang="fr">XVIIIe siècle</cell>
              <cell><hi rend="monospace">E12_Production P4_has time-span E52_Time-Span</hi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="monospace">E52_Time-Span P78_is identified by E49_Time Appellation</hi></cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <p>We then represented these triples as graphs<note>On <ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>, we visualize the
            triplets modelling the information on the production conditions of the tapestry conserved at the Château de
            Versailles, namely the production date ( <hi rend="monospace">E12_Production P4_has time-span
            E52_Time-Span</hi>), the producer/creator (<hi rend="monospace">E12_Production P14_carried out by
            E39_Actor</hi>), the materials used (<hi rend="monospace">E12_Production P126_employed E57_Material</hi>), and
            the techniques used (<hi rend="monospace">E12_Production P32_use general technique E55_Type</hi>)s.</note> as in
            <ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>. These graphs allow us to visualize the triplets and to check their
            consistency more easily. </p>
          <figure xml:id="figure04">
            <head>Triplets (extracts) used to model the metadata of the record shown in <ref target="#figure03">Figure
              3</ref></head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>A graphical representation of RDF triplets modeling the metadata record shown in Figure 3</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>After providing these mapping rules, we found that all the metadata fields could be expressed using the <hi
            style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> data model. The JSON files were then converted to create the
            knowledge graph using an RDF converter. The graph, which contains the metadata describing 36,210 objects
            illustrated by 74,527 images, is finally loaded into a triple store, while the images are uploaded separately to
            a media server. All data is available via a faceted browser (<ref target="https://data.silknow.org/fct/"
            >https://data.silknow.org/fct/</ref>) and a SPARQL endpoint (<ref target="https://data.silknow.org/sparql"
            >https://data.silknow.org/sparql</ref>). This browser can also be used via a graphical user interface which
            provides access to the <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> multilingual thesaurus dedicated to the
            vocabulary of historical silk textiles<note><ref target="https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/"
            >https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/</ref>.</note> (see <title rend="quotes">The <hi
            style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> extension</title>). All the data collected is accessible with the
            exploratory search engine ADASilk (<title rend="italic">Advanced Data Analysis for Silk Heritage</title> <note>
            <ref target="https://ada.silknow.org/fr">https://ada.silknow.org/fr</ref>. </note>) <ptr
            target="#schleider_etal2021b"/>. <ref target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref> shows the record describing the tapestry
            preserved in Versailles, as it appears in ADASilk<note>To consult it directly online: <ref
            target="https://ada.silknow.org/object/2b347a9f-2c51-30f9-9e8d-ca9396a3228e"
            >https://ada.silknow.org/object/2b347a9f-2c51-30f9-9e8d-ca9396a3228e</ref>. </note>.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure05">
            <head>Example of a record in ADASilk</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>screenshot of ADASilk web-interface with image and metadata</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>SILKNOW's contribution to textile heritage: the example of religious fabrics</head>
        <p>The benefits of using this type of technology are particularly apparent when it comes to religious textiles.
          Religious textile collections are preserved in a wide variety of institutions. While collections of <q>ordinary</q>
          textiles are generally preserved in fashion museums, they can also be found in ethnological or decorative art
          museums. Religious textiles are preserved not only in national heritage institutions, but also in small and
          medium-sized ecclesiastical museums. In addition, churches, cathedrals and convents may use these fabrics as part
          of their liturgy and daily devotions. There are also collections preserved by companies that produced these
          fabrics: such is the case of the Garín archives - one of the <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi>
          consortium's partners - which conserve very rich samples of religious fabrics representative of Spanish silk
          manufacturing in the 18th and 19th centuries <ptr target="#alba_etal2020"/>. The integration of the inventories
          produced by these structures into the <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> Knowledge Graph enables
          them to be displayed via ADASilk, thus improving the accessibility and visibility of their collections.</p>
        <p>In some cases, small heritage structures do not have a catalog or even an inventory, which makes it extremely
          difficult to determine the origin of the fabrics kept there. These fabrics, widely dispersed across Europe, are
          even incomplete<note>Religious vestments have often been conceived as ensembles: for example, a chasuble is
          accompanied by a stole.</note>. As a result, information is fragmented and disconnected, making it difficult in
          many cases to correctly identify and date these artifacts, and hence to catalogue them. ADASilk enables smaller
          organizations, particularly church museums and religious institutions, to trace the links between the objects they
          conserve and other artifacts held in distant collections, and to integrate them into a renewed chronology. This can
          help create new synergies for ecclesiastical collections, cathedrals and parishes that are custodians of this
          heritage <ptr target="#alba_etal2020"/>.</p>
        <p>Small parishes and diocesan museums often lack the resources — both financial and human — to properly conserve
          these works. This information is also indispensable when these establishments want to restore the fabrics they
          conserve, as they rarely have experts capable of carrying out the appropriate research. This results in a lack of
          appropriate methodology and restoration that should stem from a thorough knowledge of weaving techniques,
          materials, design and historical and artistic links in order to better preserve these assets <ptr
          target="#alba_etal2019"/>. ADASilk enables them to compare the fabrics they conserve with those in other
          collections, and thus obtain the information they need to launch better-documented restoration campaigns. It can be
          very difficult to distinguish the origin and technique of certain fabrics without applying a technical analysis
          which, in some cases, leads to the destruction of part of the textile <ptr target="#alba_etal2020"/>. Comparing
          fabrics held in other collections - and already catalogued - is therefore particularly useful when it comes to
          analysing and identifying old and rare fabrics without having to damage them.</p>
        <p>In addition to integrating heterogeneous data into the knowlegde graph, the <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;"
          >SilkNow</hi> ontology provides a structure for automatic image recognition, facilitating the discovery of
          similarities between several textiles preserved in various European institutions. Image recognition performed on
          images from Garín's collections and images from public museums <ptr target="#dorozynski_etal2019"/> <ptr
          target="#clermont_etal2020"/> enabled <ptr target="#alba_etal2020"/> to highlight the great similarities between an
          18th-century dalmatic preserved by the Centro de Documentación y Museo Textil (CDMT) in Terrassa (Spain) and
          Garín's 19th-century Francia model. The similarity of these two objects based on their motifs shows that Garín
          imitated models from Lyon to decorate its religious textiles. A comparison of these two objects through their
          motifs reveals that Garín drew inspiration from Lyonnais motifs for its religious textiles. These images help us to
          understand the link between Valencian and French motifs. On the other hand, during the 19th century, silk
          industries turned to revivals, reembracing ancient motifs that may have appeared obsolete and reinterpreting them
          to suit the tastes of each period. This complicates the process of dating and attribution. Sometimes, textiles
          found in geographically distant locations exhibit strikingly similar features; and the same fabric design can be
          observed in both secular and ecclesiastical garments. These confusing scenarios prompt researchers to question
          whether these designs are original or, alternatively, imitations of other textiles.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Integrating annotations into the data model</head>
        <div>
          <head>Prov DM: Provenance Data Model</head>
          <p>SILKNOW has developed text <ptr target="#massri_etal2020"/> <ptr target="#schleider_etal2021a"/> and image <ptr
            target="#dorozynski_etal2019"/> <ptr target="#clermont_etal2020"/> analysis methods that infer new properties
            about objects from the metadata describing them, so as to enrich the existing metadata. If we examine the record
            shown in <ref target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref>, we find the following information in the <title rend="quotes"
            >Technique</title> field: Damask 71% and Embroidery 52% and in the <title rend="quotes">Depiction</title> field:
            Floral motif 51% and Vegetal motif 57% (see <ref target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref>).</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure06">
            <head>Fabric predictions and associated confidence scores: example</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.JPG"/>
            <figDesc>an example of <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> image analysis</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>This new information was obtained using convolutional neural networks trained on the data (texts and images)
            contained in the knowledge graph. Based on textual descriptions of silk objects or on images representing them,
            text <ptr target="#rei2021"/> or image <ptr target="#dorozynski_etal2021"/> classification models are able to
            predict the values of certain properties: the period of production, the place of production, the technique and
            the material for the text classification model; the previous properties, plus the patterns represented for the
            image classification model. Each of these predictions is associated with a confidence score expressed as a
            percentage. In the previous example, the text classification model predicted the <term>damask</term> value with a
            confidence score of 71% for the <title rend="quotes">Technique</title> property; the image classification model
            predicted the floral motif value with a confidence score of 51% for the <title rend="quotes">Depiction</title>
            property.</p>
          <p>It was crucial to incorporate this new information into the data model, so that it could be integrated into the
            knowledge graph. We also aimed to make a clear distinction between these predictions and the original data. We
            also want to provide ADASilk users with information on the degree of reliability of the results of these
            analyses. To model these annotations, we have chosen to use the conceptual data model Provenance Data Model (Prov
            DM), recommended by the W3C <ptr target="#belhajjame_etal2013"/>. <ref target="#figure07">Figure 7</ref> shows
            the entities and relationships from Prov DM that we used in graph form<note>A description of the panel preserved
            in the <title rend="italic">Musée des Arts Décoratifs</title> can be found at the following address: <ref
            target="https://ada.silknow.org/fr/object/99528c86-aac9-3231-a9d9-b84f6e4756fd"
            >https://ada.silknow.org/fr/object/99528c86-aac9-3231-a9d9-b84f6e4756fd</ref>. </note> .</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure07">
            <head>Integration of image analysis data with ProvDM</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>A graphical representation of RDF triplets reflecting the inclusion of image analysis information using
              entities and relationships from the Provenance Data Model</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>Image or text analysis is represented as a <hi rend="monospace">Prov:Activity</hi> which can be qualified by a
            type (image analysis or text analysis). Depending on the case, this <hi rend="monospace">Prov:Activity</hi> takes
            an <hi rend="monospace">E38_Image</hi> (image analysis) or a text or <hi rend="monospace">E62_String</hi> (text
            analysis) as input and produces two declarations as output. In this model, the date of the analysis can be
            specified ; and if necessary, the analysis module can be specified with a <hi rend="monospace">prov:Agent</hi>
            class (of type <hi rend="monospace">Software Agent</hi>).</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>The <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> extension</head>
          <p>During our examination of the metadata, we noticed that the technical and historical analyses written in free
            text were particularly rich. These sometimes very long blocks of text provide information about the weaving
            process, such as which weave(s)<note>The term <term>weave</term> refers to the way in which the weft and warp
            threads are interwoven. This is called satin weave, for example. For more information on this term, please
            consult the <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> thesaurus: <ref
            target="https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/page/318"
            >https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/page/318</ref>. </note> , or which type(s) of yarns were used. However,
            this semantic richness is difficult to capture in the CIDOC CRM<note>The <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;"
            >SilkNow</hi> data model proposes to use the two triplets <hi rend="monospace">S4_Observation O8_observed
            S4_Observation</hi> and <hi rend="monospace">S4_Observation P3_has note E62_String</hi> to model the data
            provided by the metadata fields corresponding to these analyses (cf. <ref target="#figure03">Figure
            3</ref>).</note>. To integrate these descriptions into our data model, we use the P3_has note property, which is
            <quote rend="inline">a container for all informal descriptions about an object that have not been expressed in
            terms of CRM constructs</quote> <ptr target="#leboeuf_etal2015"/>. It is used to model the way in which an object
            is characterized (e.g. its appearance, structure, etc.), but it does not allow to express <quote rend="inline">in
            a structured form, everything that can be said about an item</quote>. This is one of the consequences of the
            CIDOC CRM formalism which does not have the function of capturing everything that can be said about an
            object.</p>
          <p>These blocks of free text provide particularly precise information on the techniques used to produce the
            textiles described; often, they also provide detailed iconographic descriptions. The textual analysis carried out
            on these texts has thus made it possible to extract technical information (weaves and weaving techniques) and
            other information relating to iconographic description (motifs and styles), as illustrated in <ref
            target="#figure08">Figure 8</ref>. These different types of information may be of interest to the general public
            looking for particular patterns, textile specialists working on the history of techniques, or designers and
            creative industries wishing to draw inspiration from a historical style. Access to this information via a search
            engine would also offer a richer user experience by enabling the user to perform more refined queries on the
            data.</p>
          <p>When the data is integrated into the knowledge graph, some information (techniques and patterns) is annotated
            using the <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> thesaurus (for more information on this thesaurus,
            see <ptr target="#leon_etal2019"/>). This semantic enrichment is achieved in the following way: if the value of a
            character string for a technique or pattern can be associated with one of the character strings proposed by the
            thesaurus, this value is replaced by a unique identifier. Modelling these concepts by means of a formal language
            would make it possible to integrate these annotations into the knowledge graph, to give access to this new data
            via the exploratory search engine, and to create links between these concepts and the thesaurus more easily.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure08">
            <head>Types of information extracted from the descriptions: examples from the catalogues of the Palais Galliera,
              the Victoria &amp; Albert Museum and the Mobilier National</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>A diagram showing semantic enrichment through thematic annotation of object descriptions extracted from
              various museum catalogues, identifying phrases that identify weave, motif, style, and weaving
              technique</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>The inherent flexibility of CIDOC CRM allows for the creation of new classes and properties to express new kinds
            of information. The aim is not to capture everything that can be said about an object, but to express some of the
            things that have been said about it - in this case, information about the process that led to the production of a
            silk fabric. Based on the results of the text analysis and the resulting data annotation, we created a CIDOC
            CRM-compatible model to formally express the process of creating and producing a silk fabric. This specialised
            extension, accessible via OntoME, offers 23 classes and 12 properties <ptr target="#puren_etal2021a"/>. To create
            this extension, we adopted a bottom-up approach, relying primarily on the examination of collected data. We also
            worked with domain experts to verify the validity of these new classes and properties.</p>
          <p>Among these 23 classes and properties is class <hi rend="monospace">T1_Weaving</hi>, which is a subclass of <hi
            rend="monospace">E12_Production</hi>. <hi rend="monospace">T1_Weaving</hi> refers to the activity of interlacing
            at right angles the warp threads (the threads along the length of the fabric, which are stretched on the loom)
            and the weft threads (the perpendicular threads that run alternately between the warp threads). This activity is
            usually carried out using a loom<note>The <term>weaving</term> entry can be found in the <hi
            style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> thesaurus: <ref
            target="https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/page/526"
            >https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/page/526</ref>.</note>. The product of the weaving is a fabric,
            represented by the class <hi rend="monospace">T7_Fabric</hi>, itself a subclass of <hi rend="monospace"
            >E22_Man-Made Object</hi>. The production of this fabric is carried out following a technical procedure(s) (<hi
            rend="monospace">T25_Weaving Technique</hi>). The weaving process always includes the use of at least one
            specific weave (<hi rend="monospace">T21_Weave</hi>). It then produces a fabric that is often decorated with
            patterns (<hi rend="monospace">T18_Motif</hi>), sometimes characteristic of a style (<hi rend="monospace"
            >T11_Style</hi>) identified by experts in the field (<hi rend="monospace">T13_Style Assignment</hi>). In <ref
            target="#figure09">Figure 9</ref>, we express this information with these new classes and associated properties,
            for a set of tapestries for the Grand salon of the apartment of the Empress<note>Marie-Louise I, Duchess of
            Parma, and second wife of Napoleon I.</note> in Versailles<note>Tenture, portières, cantonnières destinées au
            Grand salon de l'appartement de l'Impératrice à Versailles (1813, Bissardon, Cousin &amp; Bony), Collections du
            Mobilier national, URL: <ref target="https://collection.mobiliernational.culture.gouv.fr/objet/GMMP-877-001"
            >https://collection.mobiliernational.culture.gouv.fr/objet/GMMP-877-001</ref>. </note> kept in the collection of
            the French Mobilier national (see the last description on <ref target="#figure08">Figure 8</ref>).</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure09">
            <head>CIDOC CRM and <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> extension compliant graph</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>A graphical representation of RDF triplets showing details of the T1 Weaving class and its relationship to other T classes</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>As mentioned above, these new classes and properties facilitate the integration of semantic enrichments into the
            knowledge graph and allow the end user to query these annotations, but also to have access to additional
            contextualization elements. As shown in <ref target="#figure10">Figure 10</ref>, the <hi rend="monospace"
            >T32_Weave Type</hi> class, for example, is used to express the different weaves used during the weaving process
            and defined in the <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> thesaurus. </p>
          <figure xml:id="figure10">
            <head>Using the <hi rend="monospace">T32_Weave Type</hi> class</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>A graphical representation of RDF triplets showing details of values in the T32 Weave Type class,
              including the accommodation of values in multiple languages</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>We have done the same for the information on patterns by creating the class <hi rend="monospace">T34_Pattern
            Type</hi>. This class should also make it possible to create links with the definitions available in the
            thesaurus. For example, the user could consult the definition of the Palme motif<note>The <term>palm</term>
            concept is defined in the thesaurus: <ref target="https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/page/763"
            >https://skosmos.silknow.org/thesaurus/en/page/763</ref>. </note> , represented on the tapestries held in the
            collections of the Mobilier national.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Conclusion</head>
        <p>Silk heritage is of crucial importance for understanding European history and culture. But some conservation
          institutions lack the means to promote it and make it accessible to the public. More generally, silk heritage
          suffers from a lack of visibility, especially online, which has become the preferred tool for searching and
          discovering new information. Semantic Web technologies, however, offer the possibility of disseminating cultural
          heritage data more easily on the Web by improving its discoverability, but also of enriching this data by linking
          it to other information.</p>
        <p>The <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> project wished to exploit these potentialities to enhance
          the visibility of the European silk heritage, by developing the exploratory search engine ADASilk dedicated to
          these specialised collections. ADASilk is based on a knowledge graph, whose creation is based on the SILKOW
          ontology - a subset of the CIDOC CRM and CRMsci ontology. The richness of the metadata contained in the knowledge
          graph has also led us to develop the <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> extension, a conceptual
          model for the description of ancient silk textiles. We believe that this specialized extension represents a first
          step in the development of a domain ontology for textile cultural heritage. Data reusers indeed play a vital role
          in data modeling. They can suggest collaborative and shared models to ensure this data is interoperable and
          completely reusable in the context of the Semantic Web. We have thus conceived the <hi
          style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> extension as a first step towards the creation and dissemination of
          a new compatible model recognized by the CIDOC CRM SIG. To achieve such recognition, it is essential to extend the
          <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> framework to create an ontology that encompasses not only the
          results of textile manufacture, but also the places and methods of production, the circumstances surrounding this
          production and the memories associated with it. In addition, we have placed special emphasis in this article on the
          methodology we have used to create this specialized extension, so as to enable other research projects and
          institutions to adopt the same approach. We believe that such an approach could be systematized when the aim is to
          promote and protect an endangered heritage using the Web.</p>
        <p>By creating the ADASilk exploratory search engine, <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> has
          demonstrated the value of using Semantic Web technologies to aggregate heterogeneous heritage data, provide access
          to it and increase its visibility. It follows in the footsteps of other projects that also aim to promote fragile
          and endangered heritage and demonstrates the validity of this type of approach for large-scale processing of
          cultural heritage data. <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> also illustrates the important work that
          needs to be done on heritage data if the objectives of the Semantic Web are to be achieved. But to bring this kind
          of project to fruition, a strong institutional commitment is required. Not only from the point of view of producing
          open, high-quality data, which is the essential fuel for this type of project, but also from an organizational and
          technical point of view. Such a commitment is not accessible to small and medium-sized conservation institutions
          <ptr target="#sebastian-Lozano_etal2023"/>. Indeed, such projects require significant investments, and therefore
          remain inaccessible to small institutions, which would be the first to benefit from them. Having demonstrated the
          value of these approaches, it is therefore necessary to consider the development of tools to access these
          technologies, and thus make them accessible to the greatest number of people.</p>
        <p>The integration of data into the <hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">SilkNow</hi> Knowledge Graph could be
          considerably facilitated by the use of automatic classification tools, based on the exploitation of Linked Open
          Data. Case studies have demonstrated the value of developing such methods for creating links (or properties)
          between entities <ptr target="#bianchini_etal2021"/>. But they have also shown the need for semantic data to be
          available from a high-quality standard and as complete as possible <ptr target="#freire_etal2020"/> <ptr
          target="#bianchini_etal2021"/>; without this, crucial aspects of the data may be left out, and links between data
          may thus be missing. We must be aware, however, that the diversity of cataloguing practices - and sometimes errors
          in metadata - as well as the inherent complexity of historical data, often unstructured or a little structured <ptr
          target="#merono-Penuela_etal2015"/>, can be a brake on this kind of approach, both from the point of view of
          automatic classification and the development of a knowledge graph based on CIDOC CRM.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <listBibl>
        <bibl xml:id="achichi_etal2018" label="Achichi et al 2018">Achichi, M., Lisena, P., Todorov, K., Troncy, R., and
          Delahousse, J. (2018) <title rend="quotes">DOREMUS: A Graph of Linked Musical Works</title>. <title rend="italic"
          >ISWC: International Semantic Web Conference</title>, (pp. 279-294). Monterey, CA, United States. </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="alba_etal2019" label="Alba et al 2019">Alba, E., Fernández, M., Gaitán, M., León, A., Portalés, C.,
          Sebastián-Lozano, J., and Sevilla, J. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Technological tools for the conservation of silk
          heritage: Improving the conservation of European Religious Textile Cultural Heritage</title>. <title rend="italic"
          >ESRARC 2019. 11th European Symposium on Religious Art, Restoration and Conservation</title> (pp. 150-156).
          Kermes.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="alba_etal2020" label="Alba et al 2020">Alba, E., Gaitán, M., León, A., and Sebastián, J. (2020) <title
          rend="quotes">Spanish Religious Textiles from the 18th and 19th Centuries</title>. The Garín Case. <title
          rend="italic">European Journal of Science and Theology, 16</title>(1), 187-197.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="belhajjame_etal2013" label="Belhajjame et al 2013">Belhajjame, K., B'Far, R., Cheney, J., Coppens, S.,
          Cresswell, S., Gil, Y., . . . Tilmes, C. (2013) <title rend="quotes">PROV-DM: The PROV Data Model</title>. W3C
          Recommendation 30 April 2013. (L. Moreau, and P. Missier, Éds.) Available at: <ref
          target="https://www.w3.org/TR/prov-dm/">https://www.w3.org/TR/prov-dm/</ref></bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="beretta2021" label="Beretta 2021">Beretta, F. (2021) <title rend="quotes">A challenge for historical
          research: making data FAIR using a collaborative ontology management environment (OntoME)</title>. <title
          rend="italic">Semantic Web - Interoperability, Usability, Applicability, 2</title>(2), 279-294.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="bermes2013" label="Bermès 2013">Bermès, E. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Enabling your catalogue for the
          Semantic Web</title>. Dans S. Chambers (Éd.), <title rend="italic">Catalogue 2.0 : the future of the library
          catalogue</title> (pp. 117-142). Chicago: Neal-Schuman, an imprint of the American Library Association.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="berners-Lee_etal2001" label="Berners-Lee, Hendler, and Lassila 2001">Berners-Lee, T., Hendler, J., and
          Lassila O. (2001) <title rend="quotes">The Semantic Web</title>. <title rend="italic">Scientific American,
          5</title>(284), 28-37.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="bianchini_etal2021" label="Bianchini and Bargioni 2021">Bianchini, C. and Bargioni, S. (2021) <title
          rend="quotes">Automated Classification Using Linked Open</title>. <title rend="italic">Cataloging and,
          59</title>(8), 835-852. doi:10.1080/01639374.2021.1977447</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="bizer_etal2009" label="Bizer, Heath, and Berners-Lee 2009">Bizer, C., Heath, T., and Berners-Lee T.
          (2009) <title rend="quotes">Linked Data: the Story so far</title>. <title rend="italic">International Journal on
          Semantic Web and Information Systems, 5</title>, 1-22.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="christen2012" label="Christen 2012">Christen, P. (2012) <title rend="italic">Data Matching.</title>
          Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="claerr_etal2010" label="Claerr and Westeel 2010">Claerr, T. and Westeel, I. (2010) <title rend="italic"
          >Numériser et mettre en ligne.</title> Villeurbanne: Presses de l’enssib.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="clermont_etal2020" label="Clermont et al 2020">Clermont, D., Dorozynski, M., Wittich, D., and
          Rottensteiner, F. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Assessing the semantic similarity of images of silk fabrics using
          convolutional neural networks</title>. <title rend="italic">SPRS Annals of the Photogrammetry, Remote Sensing and
          Spatial Information Sciences</title>, (p. 641_648).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="doerr2003" label="Doerr 2003">Doerr, M. (2003) <title rend="quotes">The CIDOC Conceptual Reference
          Model : An ontological approach to semantic interopérability of metadata</title>. <title rend="italic">AI
          Magazine</title>(24), 75-92.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="dorozynski_etal2021" label="Dorozynski and Rottensteiner 2021">Dorozynski, M. and Rottensteiner, F.
          (2021) <title rend="quotes">SILKNOW Image Classification - final version WP6 - Multi-Task Classification
          (1.0)</title>. doi:https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5091813</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="dorozynski_etal2019" label="Dorozynski, Clermont, and Rottensteiner 2019">Dorozynski, M., Clermont, D.,
          and Rottensteiner F. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Muti-task deep learning with incomplete training samples for the
          image-based prediction of variables describing silk fabrics</title>. <title rend="italic">ISPRS Annals of the
          Photogrammetry, Remote Sensing and Spatial Information Sciences, IV</title>(2/W6), 47-54.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="eastermann2015" label="Eastermann 2015">Eastermann, B. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Open data et
          crowdsourcing : un état des lieux du point de vue des musées</title>. <title rend="italic">La Lettre de
          l’OCIM</title>(162), 41-46.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="foron-Dauphin_etal2016" label="Foron-Dauphin and Cano 2016">Foron-Dauphin, N. and Cano, D. (2016)
          <title rend="quotes">Le patrimoine des Soieries Bonnet (Jujurieux, Ain) : conserver et valoriser in situ un
          ensemble unique de l’industrie textile</title>. <title rend="italic">In Situ Revues des
          patrimoines</title>(29).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="fournier_etal2016" label="Fournier et al 2016">Fournier, M., Despierres, C., Mercandelli, C., and
          Bernard, E. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Conservation et présentation des lieux et collections de patrimoine textile
          : l’exemple de la fédération « Transmission du savoir-faire textile en Rhône-Alpes »</title>. <title rend="italic"
          >{In Situ Revues des patrimoines</title>(29).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="freire_etal2020" label="Freire, Manguinhas, and Isaac 2020">Freire, N., Manguinhas, H., and Isaac A.
          (2020) <title rend="quotes">An Observational Study of Equivalence Links in Cultural Heritage Linked Data for
          agents</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Libraries for Open Knowledge : 24th International Conference on Theory
          and Practice of Digital Libraries, TPDL 2020, Lyon, France, August 25–27, 2020, Proceedings</title> (pp. 62-70).
          Cham: Springer International Publishing.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="freire_etal2018" label="Freire et al 2018">Freire, N., Meijers, E., Voorburg, R., and Isaac, A. (2018)
          <title rend="quotes">Aggregation of cultural heritage datasets through the Web of Data</title>. <title
          rend="italic">Procedia Computer Science</title>, 120-126.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="freire_etal2019" label="Freire et al 2019">Freire, N., Voorburg, R., Cornelissen, R., de Valk, S.,
          Meijers, E., and Isaac, A. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Aggregation of Linked Data in the Cultural Heritage Domain:
          A Case Study in the Europeana Network</title>. <title rend="italic">Information, 10</title>(8).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="gaitan_etal2019" label="Gaitán et al 2019">Gaitán, M., Alba, E., León, A., Pérez, M., Sevilla, J., and
          Portalés, C. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Towards the Preservation and Dissemination of Historical Silk Weaving
          Techniques in the Digital Era</title>. <title rend="italic">Heritage, 2</title>(3), 1892-1911.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="grant_etal1995" label="Grant, Nieuwenhuis, and Petersen 1995">Grant, A., Nieuwenhuis, J., and Petersen
          T. (1995) <title rend="italic">International guidelines for museum object information : the CIDOC information
          categories.</title> s.l.: ICOM International Committee for Documentation.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="gruber1993" label="Gruber 1993">Gruber, T. (1993) <title rend="italic">A Translation Approach to
          Portable Ontology Specifications.</title> Stanford: Knowledge Systems Laboratory, Stanford University.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="hyvonen_etal2021" label="Hyvönen et al 2021">Hyvönen, E., Ikkala, E., Koho, M., Tuominen, J., Burrows,
          T., and Ransom, L. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Mapping Manuscript Migrations on the Semantic Web: A Semantic Portal
          and Linked Open Data Service for Premodern Manuscript Research</title>. <title rend="italic">ISWC 2021: The
          Semantic Web – ISWC 2021</title> (pp. 615-630). Cham: Springer.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="kergosien_etal2019" label="Kergosien et al 2019">Kergosien, Eric, Daloz, A., Chaudiron, S., and
          Jacquemin, B. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Le CIDOC CRM, un modèle ontologique pour représenter les connaissances du
          bassin minier des Hauts de France</title>. Premiers résultats. <title rend="italic">6th Hyperheritage International
          Symposium (HIS6) ”La fabrique du patrimoine à l’ère numérique".</title> Paris.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="koch_etal2020" label="Koch, Ribeiro, and Lopes 2020">Koch, I., Ribeiro, C., and Lopes C. (2020) <title
          rend="quotes">ArchOnto, a CIDOC-CRMBased Linked Data Model for the Portuguese Archives</title>. Dans M. Hall, T.
          Merčun, T. Risse, and F. Duchateau (Éds.), <title rend="italic">Digital Libraries for Open Knowledge. TPDL 2020.
          Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title> (pp. 133-146). Cham: Springer.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="kritsotaki_etal2017" label="Kritsotaki et al 2017">Kritsotaki, A., Hiebel, G., Theodoridou, M., Doerr,
          M., and Rousakis, Y. (2017) <title rend="italic">Definition of the CRMsci. An Extension of CIDOC-CRM to support
          scientific observation. Version 1.2.3.</title> </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="leboeuf_etal2015" label="Le Boeuf et al 2025">Le Boeuf, P., Doerr, M., Emil Ore, C., and Stead, S.
          (2015) <title rend="italic">Definition of the CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model. Version 6.2.</title> Available at:
          <ref target="https://cidoc-crm.org/">https://cidoc-crm.org/</ref></bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="leon_etal2019" label="Léon et al 2019">Léon, A., Gaitán, M., Sebastian Lozano, J., Alba Pagán, E., and
          Insa, I. (2019) <title rend="quotes">SILKNOW</title>. Designing a thesaurus about historical silk for small and
          medium-sized textile museums. <title rend="italic">Science and Digital Technology for Cultural Heritage:
          Interdisciplinary Approach to Diagnosis, Vulnerability, Risk Assessment and Graphic Information Models. Proceedings
          of the 4th International Congress Science and Technology for the Conservation of Cult</title> (pp. 187-190).
          London: CRC Press.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="marden_etal2013" label="Marden et al 2013">Marden, J., Li-Madeo, C., Whysel, N., and Edelstein, J.
          (2013) <title rend="quotes">Linked open data for cultural heritage</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the
          31st ACM International Conference on Design of Communication - SIGDOC ’13. the 31st ACM international
          conference</title> (pp. 107–112). New York, NY, USA: Association for Computing Machinery.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="massri_etal2020" label="Massri and Mladenić 2020">Massri, B. and Mladenić, D. (2020) <title
          rend="quotes">Extracting structured metadata from multilingual textual descriptions in the domain of silk
          heritage</title>. <title rend="italic">SiKDD 2020. Conference on Data Mining and Data Warehouses.</title>
          Ljubjana.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="merono-Penuela_etal2015" label="Meroño-Peñuela et al 2015">Meroño-Peñuela, A., Ashkpour, A., van Erp,
          M., Mandemakers, K., Breure, L., Scharnhorst, A., . . . van Harmelen, F. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Semantic
          Technologies for Historical Research : a Survey</title>. <title rend="italic">Semantic Web, 6</title>(6),
          539-564.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="messaoudi_etal2019" label="Messaoudi et al 2019">Messaoudi, T., De Luca, L., Véron, P., and Halin, G.
          (2019) <title rend="quotes">Vers une ontologie de domaine pour l’analyse de l'état de conservation du bâti
          patrimonial</title>. <title rend="italic">In Situ. Revue des patrimoines</title>(39).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="pagan_etal2020" label="Pagán et al 2020">Pagán, E. A., Gaitán Salvatella, M., Pitarch, M. D., León
          Muñoz, A., Moya Toledo, M., Ruiz, J. M., . . . Puren, M. (2020) <title rend="quotes">From Silk to Digital
          Technologies: A Gateway to New Opportunities for Creative Industries, Traditional Crafts and Designers</title>. The
          SILKNOW Case. <title rend="italic">Sustainability, 12</title>(19).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="peroni_etal2013" label="Peroni, Tomasi, and Vitali 2013">Peroni, S., Tomasi, F., and Vitali F. (2013)
          <title rend="quotes">The aggregation of heterogeneous metadata in Web-based cultural heritage collections</title>.
          A case study. <title rend="italic">International Journal of Web Engineering and Technology, 8</title>(4),
          412-432.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="petrov2019" label="Petrov 2019">Petrov, J. (2019) <title rend="italic">Fashion, History, Museums.
          Inventing the display of dress.</title> London: Bloomsbury Academic.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="portales_etal2018" label="Portalés et al 2018">Portalés, C., Sebastián, J., Alba, E., Sevilla, J.,
          Gaitán, M., Ruiz, P., and Fernández, M. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Interactive Tools for the Preservation,
          Dissemination and Study of Silk Heritage — An Introduction to the SILKNOW Project</title>. <title rend="italic"
          >Multimodal Technologies and Interaction, 2</title>(2).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="puren_etal2021a" label="Puren and Vernus 2021a">Puren, M. and Vernus, P. (2021) <title rend="italic"
          >SIKNOW 0.1.</title> Consulté le décembre 29, 2021, sur https://ontome.net/namespace/36</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="puren_etal2021b" label="Puren and Vernus 2021b">Puren, M. and Vernus, P. (2021) <title rend="quotes"
          >Silknow Generic Profile</title>. Available at: <ref target="http://ontome.dataforhistory.org/profile/7"
          >http://ontome.dataforhistory.org/profile/7</ref></bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="rei2021" label="Rei 2021">Rei, L. (2021) <title rend="quotes">SILKNOW Text Classifier Models</title>.
          Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5070696"
          >https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5070696</ref></bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="schleider_etal2021a" label="Schleider and Troncy 2021">Schleider, T. and Troncy, R. (2021) <title
          rend="quotes">Zero-Shot Information Extraction to Enhance a Knowledge Graph Describing Silk Textiles</title>.
          <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 5th Joint SIGHUM Workshop on Computational Linguistics for Cultural
          Heritage, Social Sciences, Humanities and Literature.</title> Punta Cana, Dominican Republic (online): Association
          for Computational Linguistics.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="schleider_etal2021b" label="Schleider et al 2021b">Schleider, T., Troncy, R., Ehrhart, T., Dorozynski,
          M., Rottensteiner, F., Sebastian, L., and Lo Cicero, G. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Searching Silk Fabrics by
          Images Leveraging on Knowledge Graph and Domain Expert Rules</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 3rd
          Workshop on Structuring and Understanding of Multimedia Heritage Contents</title> (pp. 41–49). New York, NY, USA:
          Association for Computing Machinery.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="schleider_etal2021c" label="Schleider et al 2021c">Schleider, T., Troncy, R., Gaitan, M., Sebastian
          Lozano, J., Mladenic, D., Kastelic, A., . . . Lo Cicero , G. (2021) <title rend="quotes">The SILKNOW Knowledge
          Graph</title>. <title rend="italic">Preprint</title>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="sebastian-Lozano_etal2023" label="Sebastián-Lozano et al 2023">Sebastián-Lozano, J., Pagán, E., Roig,
          E. M., Gaitán, M., León, A., Sevilla Peris, J., . . . Mladenic, D. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Open Access to Data
          about Silk Heritage: A Case Study in Digital Information Sustainability</title>. <title rend="italic"
          >Sustainability, 15</title>(19), 14340.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="stewart_etal2012" label="Stewart and Marcketti 2012">Stewart, T. and Marcketti, S. (2012) <title
          rend="quotes">Textiles, dress, and fashion museum website development: strategies and practices</title>. <title
          rend="italic">Museum Management and Curatorship, 27</title>(5), 523-538.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="suls2017" label="Suls 2017">Suls, D. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Europeana Fashion: Past, present and
          future</title>. <title rend="italic">Libraries Journal, 42</title>(3), 123–129.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="wang_etal2014" label="Wang, Xia, and Niu 2014">Wang, Z., Xia, S., and Niu Q. (2014) <title
          rend="quotes">A novel ontology analysis tool, Applied Mathematics and Information Sciences</title>. <title
          rend="italic">Applied Mathematics and Information Sciences, 8</title>(1), 255-261.</bibl>
      </listBibl>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
