<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">The Pedagogical Innovations and Ethical Challenges of Integrating an Online Version of 
               the Registers of the Liberation of Senegal (1857-1903) into the Teaching of History in the Senegalese Middle Cycle Public 
               Schooling</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Mamadou Yéro <dhq:family>Baldé</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Cheikh Anta Diop University, Senegal</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>mamadouyero.balde@ucad.edu.sn</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Djibrirou Daouda <dhq:family>Ba</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>>
               <dhq:affiliation>Cheikh Anta Diop University, Senegal</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>djibriroudaouda.ba@ucad.edu.sn</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Ismaïla <dhq:family>Mbodji</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Cheikh Anta Diop University, Senegal</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>ismaila.mbodj@ucad.edu.sn</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000768</idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <term corresp=""/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000768/000768.xml">GitHub</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>This article analyzes the possibility of a pedagogical renewal in the teaching of the slave trade and slavery in the 
               Senegalese middle cycle. On the basis of the directives of the National Education orientation law of 1991, the consolidated 
               history program of 2006, and the Senegal Registers of Liberation, we identify the current limits of the teaching of the 
               slave trade and slavery and propose new avenues taking into account other pedagogical perspectives that are essential to 
               the training of students congruent with the evolution of historical science. Beyond these indicated aspects, the article
               will try to show how the digital humanities could contribute to this pedagogical renewal, which will take into account the 
               question of the ethics of the names of freed slaves appearing in the Senegal Registers of Liberation. This article 
               explores the renewal of the teaching of the slave trade and slavery on the basis of a digital resource in the era of 
               digital humanities.
            </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
           <p>Teaching the slave trade and slavery through the Senegalese liberation register is not only to put the digital humanities 
              at the center of pedagogical transmission, but it is also to inscribe Senegalese learners in the time-world of science.
           </p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>In 2006, the Republic of Senegal introduced its Consolidated History Program, which stated that the study of History in public schools must contribute to shaping independent, critical, and conscientious citizens. It should enable them not only to acquire scientific and humanistic knowledge, but also the critical thinking, interpersonal skills and understanding how the past shapes the present that will enable them to become Senegalese citizens capable of proudly assuring the country's destiny in Africa and the world. It is an understatement, to say the least, to observe that slave trade and slavery are minimally analyzed in middle cycle history curricula in Senegal<note> The middle cycle consists of four levels. It is open to students from 12 years old. At the end of this cycle, students enter secondary school at the age of 16. They obtained the Baccalaureate at the age of 18 or 19, a diploma that opens the doors to university.</note>. Improving our approach to teaching the subject is important because in the precolonial period, the Atlantic slave trade had a significant impact on Senegal, and slavery, as an institution, became common in some societies. Further, the legacy of the slave trade and of domestic slavery weighs heavy on Senegalese society today. One cannot understand the present without understand the impact of slavery and the slave trade. </p>
            <p>Today the focus of middle cycle schooling is broad and not to a great extent Senegal-specific. Students are taught about the mechanisms and circuits of the slave trade and commerce through the study of ancient African civilizations (such as Egypt, Nubia, and Ethiopia), the empires of medieval Sudan and West Africa (such as Ghana, Mali, Songhai, Sokoto, and Macina), the Mossi kingdoms, the states of the Gulf of Guinea (Yoruba and Benin) and the societies of Senegambia (such as Jolof, Gaabu, Fouladou) (Consolidated History Program, 2006). Further, under the current middle cycle curriculum teaching about slavery does not concretely promote the effective application of important pedagogical methods and approaches, such as expository writing and dialogue and task methods<note> The method of tasks requires the pupil to "take the initiative, his activity, his thinking, putting him as much as possible in situations where he will research (search for information, documentary research), surveys, interviews, reports of visits, excursions, group work, case studies, role-playing...". It is a situation where he participates in his training through practical activities related to the teaching program of his level of study. </note>, which are, after all, essential to learners.  It is at this level that the open-source, online dataset derived from the Senegal Registers of Liberation, a unique historical register of the liberations of nearly 30,000 enslaved people in Senegal between 1857 and May 1903, can be useful in pedagogical innovations in teaching about the slave trade and slavery in Africa and Senegal (For more on the Senegal Registers of Liberation see Roberts and Wall in this issue). The Registers provide information on ages, genders, categories and origins of freed slaves, their pathways towards liberation, and the evolution and dynamics of the end of slavery in West Africa. </p>
            <p>Based on the directives of the National Education Orientation Laws (1991) and the Consolidated History Program (2006), this article demonstrates how, when transcribed and made accessible online in an open-source format, these Registers can promote new pedagogical innovations in the teaching of the slave trade and slavery in Senegal. These innovations are centered on the pedagogy of what we call “discovery exploitation construction” in the digital humanities. Our approach involves the creation of new teaching paradigms that emerge from the online presentation and integration into middle cycle curricula of the Registries. </p>
            <p>Thus, our reflection will be articulated around four aspects. First, we will review the current teaching of the slave trade and slavery and its limits; second, we will analyze the possible pedagogical and didactic perspectives of the Liberation Register; third, we will look at the ethics necessary for the use of digital humanities in the teaching of the history of coercion in Senegalese middle cycle; and finally, we will explore the challenges the Liberation Registers raise.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>I. Teaching about the Slave Trade and Slavery in <name>Senegal</name>: A Status Report</head>
            <p>After independence from France in 1960, Senegal embarked on a process of curriculum reform to align public schooling with the aspirations of the nation and its newly independent people. Curricular reforms took place in 1965, 1998, and 2006 resulting in a national consolidated curriculum in 2006. In the 2006 consolidated history program for the middle cycle, the theme of the slave trade and slavery is addressed through specific and general lessons. The aim of these lessons is:</p>
            <p>to help students acquire the concepts and facts that will enable them to better understand the events, [but also] to develop specific skills in the subject; to encourage them to pose problems and (...) ask questions; to lead them to be autonomous in the development of their own knowledge (Consolidated History Program, 2006, p. 3). </p>
            <p>The objective is to form "autonomous and supportive" citizens, capable of demonstrating "mobilizable knowledge" on the history of Senegal and Africa, to be based on the historical approach and methodology, to have an irreversible patriotic and civic posture, and to assume responsibility in any circumstance and situation. This is in accordance with the Orientation Law (1991), which stipulates that National Education must aim to:
              <list type="unordered">
                <item>"Raise the cultural level of the nation” or, in other words, build the nation by training citizens who are cultured and proud of their Senegalese origins.; and</item>
                <item>“Train free men and women, capable of creating the conditions for their fulfillment at all levels, of contributing to the development of science and technology, and of providing effective solutions to the problems of national development" (National Education Orientation Laws, 1991).</item>
              </list>
            </p>
            <p>Including instruction on the slave trade and slavery in the curriculum enables learners to become aware of their past, however painful it may be, and to construct a valorizing perception of Black Africans. This historical theme links school education to current issues, which are linked to the problem of identities in a world where cultural globalization has not yet finished wreaking havoc. The goal was therefore to create in young Senegalese a sense of attachment to a community that made the Americas through its sweat and blood, and therefore, to be proud of its trajectory and shape its future. What is really sought is the need to encourage a certain social and patriotic commitment among students. A commitment that would be a useful viaticum to get rid of the colonial negation associated with the Black. The idea is, in short, to create in the student a "cultural nationalism" and a conquering black pride.</p>
            <p>Some twenty lessons and a few consolidation activities are devoted to the issue of the slave trade and slavery in the middle cycle. In most of the lessons, this phenomenon is approached from the angle of the civilizations of the great empires or kingdoms of ancient and medieval Africa (see L6 to L11 in the 6th grade; L6 to L11 and then L14 to L17 in the 5th grade; L10 to L15 in the 4th grade). Aspects of the slave trade that are covered in detail are its origins, mechanisms, evolution, and consequences. </p>
            <p>These curricula do not always make it possible for teachers to delve deeply into, among other things, the demographics of the slave trade (its volume over time, and particular from Senegal, its patterns with regard to the gender and age of enslaved people, and its differential impact on regions in Senegal and across West Africa). In addition, teachers do not have access to material that make it possible to explore the actors involved — elites who controlled processes of enslavement and, importantly, the enslaved themselves, some of whom were exported into the Atlantic and some of whom were retained as slaves in Africa itself. Apart from Toussaint Louverture, no enslaved person is ever named in the lessons on these issues. The teaching of the phenomenon has not changed in the schools: the curriculum approaches generalized populations slaves as products and not as actors. Students are exposed to historical or literary texts on the subject, they visit the Slave House on Gorée Island; and they prepare a dossier on "Gorée in the slave trade" or on research work to be presented in the form of a lecture. This means that the learners are more involved in storytelling and narration than in the analysis and critical exploration of concrete and primary historical resources. The teachers' background readings of the slave trade in the classroom reflect an embryonic conception of the facts that consists "almost exclusively in blaming exogenous factors for the fate of Africa from the 15th century onwards" (Seck, 2009, p. 72).</p>
            <p>If we want to comply with one of the recommendations of the Consolidated History Program to instill students with "a conception of history that privileges the facts of civilization, economic, [statistical], political, social and cultural data" (Consolidated History Program, 2006, p. 5), it is imperative that students be exposed to statistical resources when learning about the slave trade and slavery. It is also imperative that we humanize the study of slavery and the slave trade in Senegal, centering named people whose life histories are relatable and understandable. The Senegal Register of Liberation is, therefore, appropriate for studying and understanding the social history of this era, focusing first on the captives and only then preceding to the political, economic and institutional history of this phenomenon. This would be a history that allows students to have a panoramic vision of a dark chapter in the evolution of Africa.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>II. Pedagogical and Didactic Perspectives of the Freed Slaves Register</head>
            <p>The Registers of Liberation, an official government record of liberation of enslaved people in Senegal between 1857 and 1903, which was recorded by French colonial officials after slavery was abolished in Senegal, consists of twenty registers, containing evidence of 28,930 liberations, "the date, the identification number assigned to that specific liberation, the name of the enslaved person, place of birth, age, place of liberation in the colony of Senegal, and name and position of the colonial administrator who authorized the liberation" (Goodwin et al 2021). A team of Senegalese and American researchers have transcribed the Registers into a dataset and are making a searchable and analyzable version available (https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/5185180). As a compilation of liberations, the register is a dashboard of freed slaves, a kind of tracing of freedoms. It makes it possible to analyze the rate and pace of releases ad to better understand the geopolitical and economic restructuring in a region like Senegambia. It clearly shows that "unaccompanied minors accounted for 68% of the total number of unaccompanied women" (Goodwin et <hi rend="italic">al</hi>., 2021). Indeed, the release of young people was more frequent than that of the elderly. The period of release is also an interesting aspect studied by the register. Goodwin et <hi rend="italic">al</hi>. (2021) affirm that a "majority of releases occurred between the months of March and June (41%), the months of October to January account for only 26% of the total releases between 1894 and 1903". It is, in short, a document that traces the captives and their social and cultural history. It becomes, therefore, a pedagogical resource of paramount importance. Its use can allow for a finer analysis of the dynamics of liberation in Senegal in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries by promoting interactive teaching strategies which are at the heart of pedagogical practices. But how?</p>
            <p>Registers I, III, V, IX, XI, XIV and XVII detailing captives’ liberation from August 6, 1857 to April 14, 1903 are a rich and significant pedagogical resource in teaching 4th grade Lessons 5 (The consequences of the slave trade in Africa), 7 (The slave trade in Senegal), and 8 (The abolitionist movement). <note> See <ref target="https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/5185180">https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/5185180</ref>. </note> In classroom practices and in developing curriculum, the teachers can address the following elements:
              <list type="unordered">
                <item>In the economic consequences, they explore how the slave trade and slavery in Africa contributed to the disorganization of African economies, the depopulation of the continent, the disorganization of society, the reinforcement of social inequalities and the conflicts between kingdoms;</item>
                <item>In the trade in Senegal, they analyze the origins and evolution of enslavement and slavery in this country and how enslavement and slavery contributed to its political, social and demographic consequences by insisting on the same elements mentioned previously;</item>
                <item>In the abolitionist movement, the focus is on the causes of the suppression of this phenomenon.<note>With the register, there is a good chance that the teacher who wishes to remain in these three classic orientations can be even better equipped to strengthen or improve them.</note></item>
              </list>
            </p>
            <figure>
              <head>Administrative document with information related to freed slaves, including their civil status, origin, and the 
                 person to whom they were entrusted</head>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            </figure>
            <figure>
              <head>Administrative document with further information related to freed slaves, including their date of release, the names 
                 of their parents, those of the declarants, etc.</head>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Moreover, the content of the Registers of Liberation allows us to go beyond these aspects. A rigorous exploitation of this resource helps to see and insert into the lessons the geographic and social origins of the captives, the periods of liberation, and the actions of slaves. The Registers also allow us to create and teach both demographic histories of generalized populations and life histories of named enslaved individuals. We can at once understand broad patterns and humanize the study of slavery by piecing together shards of information recorded in the primary source to uncover histories of named enslaved people’s networks, familial relations, movements, and more. An analysis of the liberations between 1881 and 1885 shows, for example, that the captives freed by the jurisdictions of Saint-Louis, Dakar, Gorée, Dagana and Get Ndar came from various regions of Senegambia: Sudan, Brouillard, Gambia, Fouta Diallon, Ouassoulou, Ngabou, Cayor, Casamance, Haut-Niger, Guidimakha, Boundou and others. All age groups were represented, as indicated in the registry: children (1 to 14 years), adolescents (15 to 25 years), adults (27 to 50 years). And within each of those age groups, the Registers allow us to dig down to the level of the individual and understand through fragmentary data something about individual’s unique life histories.</p>
            <p>The register thus offers a panoply of teaching and learning activities including:
              <list type="unordered">
                <item>running statistical analysis of data from the registry to identify the distribution and classification of captives by gender, age, and geographic origin;</item>
                <item>computing the number of liberations by time period;</item>
                <item>discerning the leading consequences of slaves’ liberty;</item>
                <item>constructing bar, pie and semicircle diagrams according to the objectives assigned to a lesson;</item>
                <item>analyzing data to answer a wide range of issues essential to understanding the slave trade, its consequences, and its abolition in Senegal and Africa;</item>
                <item>writing life histories of enslaved people from shards of recorded information.</item>
              </list>
            These lessons are based on the manipulation of digital data in the Register of Liberation. Thus, specifically, we could have, among other things, pedagogical interventions related to the Registry such as project-based approaches and cooperative learning. </p>
            <p>Project-based approaches promote a rewarding educational experience by making it possible to highlight activities in the classroom that lead to the production of new concrete knowledge on a question. The project-based approach introduces learners to the processing of "different data to give them meaning according to the objectives pursued, defined and decided by the collective in charge of the project" (Boutet, 2016, p. 28). It is therefore a pedagogy of experience that encourages the learner to "understand reality".</p>
            <p>Cooperative pedagogy makes it possible to learn from others and promotes the strengthening of education in citizenship and critical thinking. It is promotes positive interdependence.  In other words, it is a pedagogy intended to make learners understand that the process of acquiring knowledge and knowledge is based on mutualization. And that the percentage of success is also the result of pooling in training. Cooperative learning includes the category of social interaction models. In short, the approaches described above help the teacher to be part of the objective-based pedagogy recommended in teaching-learning.</p>
            <p>It is easy to see that the advantage of the Registry is that it can promote active and guided methods. In active methods, the teacher places the student at the center of learning, encouraging him or her to construct his or her own knowledge by using a variety of teaching resources adapted from the information in the Register. Such active methods, fundamental in historical practice, fulfill the goals of the Consolidated History Program but require an "organized and methodical sequence plan" focused on situational and prerequisite (cognitive) preparation, modeling (explanatory phase), guided practice, objectification, regular revisions, and evaluation (Couerbe, 2015). This sequencing aims to motivate students, to inform them, and to encourage them to analyze data, interact with one another, and produce historical analyses. It places learners in the time frame of the history of the phenomenon studied and its multiple ramifications. Exploring, analyzing, and interpreting digital data with students allows them to become aware, from a comparative pedagogical perspective, of the multicultural and multifaceted nature of the slave trade and slavery, to grasp "the identities forged there, and to integrate into the construction of historical knowledge a community of [Black] destiny that concerns the past and the present as well as the future" (Heimberg, 2009, p. 21).</p>
            <p>Beyond the "active approach" that the Registers could promote in teaching and learning, their appropriate and practical use argues in favor of three theoretical currents: cognitivism, constructivism and socioconstructivism. "These three approaches have in common that they recognize the determining role of the learner in the construction of his or her own knowledge and skills" (Cardin, 2009, pp. 34-35). The use of evidence from the Registers of Liberation enables instructors to adapt their teaching of the slave trade to the intelligence and personality of the students. Thus, the look at the socio-cultural statistics of the phenomenon in question, through pedagogical testing (activities, tasks and confrontations), while advocating an "ethical use of the document", allows students to construct history and to get out of the straitjacket of the standard history of the slave trade and slavery, which is limited to recounting its causes, mechanisms, organization and consequences. </p>
            <p>While we know more and more about the ways in which students appropriate the history taught, and we know that the force of the lecture alone is powerless to fix passive learning and knowledge, the practices of transmitting ‘a closed knowledge to which students must adhere’ forcefully question, on the threshold of the twenty-first century, the real stakes of historical training (Hery, 2009, p. 115).</p>
            <p>The transition that can be made by the register is thus a boon for learners in the process of acquiring first-hand historical knowledge. By focusing on the slave trade and slavery from the perspective of African slaves who sought their own freedom rather than from the perspective of the capitalist slave traders in Europe and the Americas, the Register provides a new understanding of the past.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>III. Digital Humanities, Ethics, and the Teaching of Slave Trade and Slavery in <name>Senegal</name>: What 
             Postures?</head>
            <p>The Register of Liberation allows us to explore many cultural and social aspects of related to slavery and the slave trade. Who was made captive? From what geographic regions did captives come from? From what societies and cultures? What names and surnames did slaves have? Such sensitive information in a conservative society like Senegal’s where the discussions of people’s servile descent are discouraged raises ethical raises questions about the use of the Registries in the classroom. In the collective imagination, enslaved people were inferior and descendants of enslaved people continue to carry that stigma today. Thus, a kind of self-censorship around discussions of slavery has been created to avoid conflicts and divisions that could undermine national cohesion. It is attested that even in the humanistic studies the issue of slavery in Senegambian societies has been almost silenced for a long time by African historians. For Ibrahima Thioub (2009, p. 17): </p>
            <p>the relative scarcity of studies devoted to domestic slavery by African historians’ contrasts sharply with the importance of the phenomenon, its generalization across the continent, its variable scope from one era to another, the role and functions of slaves in all areas of activity, and the diversity of their social status. </p>
            <p>How, then, can we reconcile the digital humanities, which are accessible to a wide audience, with ethics and the teaching of this phenomenon, which in some societies is considered dehumanizing, to young college students?</p>
            <p>These questions, though not an exhaustive list of considerations, identify some of the critical issues to address prior to using digital resources like the Registers of Liberation. Marc Bloch (1974) called for an appropriation of the modern tools of science in history. Such tools that do not make a clean sweep of the past, but that are part of a transdisciplinary approach that allows for the forging of new formal models for achieving the objectives of teaching and learning. Far from being only a virtual library, the humanities are spaces for the construction of scientific knowledge that can be used in class and exploited in accordance with current pedagogical recommendations.</p>
            <p>Without ethics and responsibility in their use and transmission, digital humanities, applied to the teaching of slavery in conservative societies such as Senegal’s, can be destructive of cohesion and harmony between populations. For any descendant of slaves who feels dehumanized by stereotypes, whether held by those who claim to be masters or by anyone else, fosters resentment and feeds hatred. Ethics in such a case would be part of a patriotic perspective.</p>
            <p>As for responsibility, it would lie in the fact that to teach is to choose. To choose is to proceed by useful discrimination:  discrimination that would have as its goal the respect of human dignity. This would not mean ignoring historical reality. It is a question of acting with respect, morality and prudence in the process of transmission.</p>
            <p>The use of digital data in history, a strategic and sensitive discipline, especially when it comes to taking an interest in slavery, calls for the data to be appropriated pedagogically, that is to say, bearing in mind that not everything can be transmitted and said as such without subterfuge. Clearly, it is a question of to bring about the “emergence of a digital materialism” based on appropriate methods of training, learning and information transmission. In this case, the digital historical resource should be used not as a "bomb" that destroys social cohesion, but as material for reflection, science, didactics and pedagogy. It then becomes what pedagogues and didacticians would describe as toolboxes for the trainer and the teacher that are part of two levers of performance of the history curriculum: teaching through tools and sources.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>IV. Challenges of introducing pedagogical innovations using digital humanities</head>
            <p>The challenges linked to the use of digital humanities in educational pedagogy are many and varied. The development of technologies in a connected century means that no training and learning process can ignore digital technology. What's at stake is the quality of learning and the performance of pupils and students, who feel more at home with the web than with paper; hence their conception of Learners 2.0 to magnify their attachment to the digital world. The learner 2.0 is that learner of the technological and digital age. A learner who is aware of digital innovations, which are part of their experience, their activities and their daily evolution. This is why introducing pedagogical innovations using digital humanities means connecting Senegalese schools and learners to the world of today and tomorrow. This would also be in line with principles of the New School for Senegal<note> In January 1981, the General Assembly on Education and Training was convened. Echoing a deep malaise in the Senegalese education system, the participants (government, trade unions, civil society, etc.) concluded the need for a "radical overhaul of the education system, with a view to a new school more in line with the deep aspirations of the Senegalese people, to the mastery of the scientific and technical conditions of our integral development, democracy, social justice, peace, human progress" (National Education Orientation Laws, 1991). The new school is clearly a school for Senegal and its aspirations; A school rooted first, then open.</note>, a modern school serving the universal, where teachers are called upon to be in phase with the new knowledge and methods in History and commonly accepted for their relevance, originality, validity and decisive contribution to learners. It is a question of innovating for science, and society by understanding that the digital humanities promote the activity of the student, individualization and collaborative work, in practice transmissive pedagogy.</p>
            <p>Moreover, incorporating digital humanities into teaching practice means introducing both teachers and students to the concept of scripting: “entering the digital era of learning head-on" (Sauvage, 2019). The challenge, in fact, is to think of a digital pedagogy of the future applicable to History. It's a question of thinking about teaching History by the click of a mouse, which "enables us to move beyond the ancestral and obsolete (albeit etymological) association of work/suffering towards learning/pleasure” (Sauvage, 2019). It is also a question of integrating the teaching of history in Senegal into globalization, with the aim of inscribing it and the learners in the time-world of digital pedagogy, which constitutes an inevitable training imperative in a century of Information and Communication Technologies (ICT).</p>
            <p>Ultimately, if we consider that tomorrow's world is that of the virtual and of Information and Communication Technologies; if modernity inevitably involves the integration of nations into the digital world, we are called upon, within the framework of our training curricula, to give a central place to the digital humanities. Digital innovation must be a prime concern and imperative. It will be a question of pedagogical adaptation via digital didactics in History. For the educational dimension of digital humanities is expressed in "the transmission of skills within and outside educational institutions, the training of trainers and teachers, democratization and open access to culture" (Bourgatte, Ferloni et Tessier, 2017, p. 157).</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>The treatment of issues related to the slave trade and slavery in the Senegalese middle cycle is trapped in a form of academic writing of the phenomenon that privileges its mechanisms, its consequences, and its areas of action. This form of history relegates the captive as a demographic, social and cultural subject to the background. Thus, we need to make a sociological history of the captive in the turmoil of the slave trade and slavery more central to the history of Senegal. Teachers have been hindered in this task by the lack of available sources on slavery in Senegal. The open-source, online version of the Senegal Registers of Liberation allows us to fill this historiographic gap. The possible didactic transposition of the data from this register can promote the renewal of school history on this issue. In addition, it argues in favor of a lively and constructive pedagogy that allows teachers and learners to break with the liturgy and traditional rites of teaching about the slave trade and slavery in class. The implementation of activities and tasks that give a great deal of space to the analysis of figures, to the sociology of the captives and to their geographical and cultural origins not only makes it possible not to dissociate historical culture from the interests of the student, but also to make the pedagogical space the cradle of historical vocations and of the collective consciousness that is so much sought after in a century of conflicting identities. The use of this register must however be accompanied by a robust discussion of the ethics and morality of transmission of this history in order for digital humanities not to become a tool of social disarticulations.</p>
            <p>On another note, one might well ask how, in a continent marked by the digital divide, should we reconcile the teaching of history and the use of digital technology? Even if the problem has arisen in the recent past, the efforts made to equip certain schools with computer rooms are helping to encourage pedagogical innovations associated with digital technology. The requirement to be part of these innovations has become an imperative that the COVID-19 pandemic has helped to bring to light. From now on, education and training are required to be bimodal for greater effectiveness and efficiency.</p>
        </div>
      </body>
      <back>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bloch1974" label="Bloch 1974">Bloch, M. (1974) <title rend="italic">Apologie pour l'histoire ou Métier 
             d'historien</title>. Paris: Armand Colin.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bourgatte_etal2017" label="Bourgatte, Ferloni, and Tessier 2017">Bourgatte, M., Ferloni, M., and Tessier, L. 
             (2017) Communiquer en Humanités numériques: de la non-conférence aux non-actes, Les Cahiers de la SFSIC, 13, pp. 155-162.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="boutet2016" label="Boutet 2016"></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="brochier1965" label="Brochier 1965"></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cardin2009" label="Cardin 2009"></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="couerbe2015" label="Couerbe 2015"></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="goodwin_etal2021a" label="Goodwin, Ivans, Roberts, and Wall 2021"></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="goodwin_etal2021b" label="Goodwin, Ivans, and Wall 2021"></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="heimberg2009" label="Heimberg 2009"></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hery1991" label="Hery 1991"></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hery2006" label="Hery 2006"></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hery2009" label="Hery 2009"></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="sauvage2019" label="Sauvage 2019"></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="seck2009" label="Seck 2009"></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="thioub2009" label="Thioub 2009"></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
