<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">The Pedagogical Innovations and Ethical Challenges of Integrating an Online Version of 
               the Registers of the Liberation of Senegal (1857-1903) into the Teaching of History in the Senegalese Middle Cycle Public 
               Schooling</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Mamadou Yéro <dhq:family>Baldé</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Cheikh Anta Diop University, Senegal</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>mamadouyero.balde@ucad.edu.sn</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Mamadou Yéro Baldé</name> is a teacher-researcher in the Faculty of Science and Technology of Education and 
                     Training at the <name>Cheikh Anta Diop University</name> in <name>Dakar</name> (<name>Senegal</name>) and an 
                     associate researcher at the Population and Development Center (Ceped, UMR 196), a research unit of the 
                     <name>University of Paris Cité</name> and the <name>Institute of Research for Development</name> (IRD). A member 
                     of the laboratories <title rend="quotes">Study and Research Group on Marginality and Social Exclusion</title> 
                     (GERMES) and <title rend="quotes">Professions, Memory and Territories in Africa</title> (M2TA), his research 
                     focuses on the history of the Atlantic slave trade and slavery and its pedagogical and academic perspectives, 
                     mobility, student nationalism, the African (post)colonial state, etc. He is the author and co-editor of several 
                     books.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Djibrirou Daouda <dhq:family>Ba</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Cheikh Anta Diop University, Senegal</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>djibriroudaouda.ba@ucad.edu.sn</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Djibrirou Daouda Ba</name> is a Doctor of Geography from <name>Gaston Berger University</name> and a lecturer 
                     at the Faculty of Science and Technology, Education and Training of <name>Cheikh Anta Diop University</name>, 
                     <name>Senegal</name>. He was previously a secondary school teacher and teacher trainer. Former winner of the 
                     Eugène Ionescu Postdoctoral Fellowship of the UAF in <name>Romania</name>, <name>Dr. Ba</name> also holds a 
                     Certificate of Aptitude for Secondary Education in History and Geography. His publications focus on environment, 
                     climate, and sustainability in education and teacher education.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Ismaïla <dhq:family>Mbodji</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Cheikh Anta Diop University, Senegal</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>ismaila.mbodj@ucad.edu.sn</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Ismaïla Mbodji</name> is a teacher-researcher in the Faculty of Sciences and Technologies of Education and 
                     Training at the <name>Cheikh Anta Diop University</name> of <name>Dakar</name>, after having been a professor of 
                     history and geography then pedagogical advisor. Holder of a doctorate in educational sciences from the UNESCO Chair 
                     in <name>Dakar</name> (CUSE/ISE), he is the author of numerous publications in didactics and on the teaching of 
                     history and geography.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000768</idno>
            <idno type="volume">019</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <date when="2025-04-28">28 April 2025</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <term corresp="#ethics"/>
               <term corresp="#pedagogy"/>
               <term corresp="#history"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>global digital literacy</item>
                  <item>slavery</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000768/000768.xml">GitHub</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>This article analyzes the possibility of a pedagogical renewal in the teaching of the history of the slave trade and 
               slavery in middle cycle (four years of study that can begin at the age of twelve) public school classrooms in 
               <name>Senegal</name>. It does so by proposing that aspects of middle cycle curricula be built around an open-source, 
               online version of the Senegal Registers of Liberation (1857-1903) in order to achieve the National Education Orientation 
               Law of 1991 and the Consolidated History Program of 2006. In this article, we identify the current limits of teaching 
               about the slave trade and slavery and propose new approaches, taking into account innovative pedagogical perspectives 
               that are essential to the training of students congruent with the evolution of historical methodologies in the digital 
               humanities. Beyond this, the article shows the importance of addressing ethical questions around the public use of names 
               of enslaved people which appear in the Senegal Registers of Liberation. In sum, the article explores and proposes 
               revisions in the teaching of the slave trade and slavery in <name>Senegal</name> using digital resources. 
            </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
           <p>Teaching the slave trade and slavery through the Senegalese liberation register is not only to put the digital humanities 
              at the center of pedagogical transmission, but it is also to inscribe Senegalese learners in the time-world of science.
           </p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>In 2006, the Republic of Senegal introduced its Consolidated History Program, which stated that the study of history in 
               public schools must contribute to shaping independent, critical, and conscientious citizens. It should enable them not 
               only to acquire scientific and humanistic knowledge, but also the critical thinking, interpersonal skills, and 
               understanding of how the past shapes the present that will enable them to become Senegalese citizens capable of proudly 
               assuring the country's destiny in <name>Africa</name> and the world. It is an understatement, to say the least, to 
               observe that slave trade and slavery are minimally analyzed in middle cycle history curricula in 
               <name>Senegal</name>.<note>The middle cycle consists of four levels. It is open to students from 12 years old. At the 
               end of this cycle, students enter secondary school at the age of 16. They obtain the Baccalaureate at the age of 18 or 
               19, a diploma that opens the doors to university.</note> Improving our approach to teaching the subject is important 
               because in the precolonial period, the Atlantic slave trade had a significant impact on <name>Senegal</name>, and 
               slavery, as an institution, became common in some societies. Further, the legacy of the slave trade and of domestic 
               slavery weighs heavy on Senegalese society today. One cannot understand the present without understand the impact of 
               slavery and the slave trade.
            </p>
            <p>Today the focus of middle cycle schooling is broad and not to a great extent <name>Senegal</name>-specific. Students 
               are taught about the mechanisms and circuits of the slave trade and commerce through the study of ancient African 
               civilizations (such as <name>Egypt</name>, <name>Nubia</name>, and <name>Ethiopia</name>), the empires of medieval 
               <name>Sudan</name> and <name>West Africa</name> (such as <name>Ghana</name>, <name>Mali</name>, <name>Songhai</name>, 
               <name>Sokoto</name>, and <name>Macina</name>), the Mossi kingdoms, the states of the <name>Gulf of Guinea</name> 
               (<name>Yoruba</name> and <name>Benin</name>) and the societies of <name>Senegambia</name> (such as <name>Jolof</name>, 
               <name>Gaabu</name>, <name>Fouladou</name>) <ptr target="#republique2006"/>. Further, under the current middle cycle 
               curriculum, teaching about slavery does not concretely promote the effective application of important pedagogical 
               methods and approaches, such as expository writing and dialogue and task methods,<note>The method of tasks requires the 
               pupil to <quote rend="inline">take the initiative, his activity, his thinking, putting him as much as possible in 
               situations where he will research (search for information, documentary research), surveys, interviews, reports of visits, 
               excursions, group work, case studies, role-playing...</quote>. It is a situation where the student participates in 
               their training through practical activities related to the teaching program of their level of study.</note> which are, 
               after all, essential to learners. It is at this level that the open-source, online dataset derived from the Senegal 
               Registers of Liberation, a unique historical register of the liberations of nearly 30,000 enslaved people in 
               <name>Senegal</name> between 1857 and May 1903, can be useful in pedagogical innovations in teaching about the slave 
               trade and slavery in <name>Africa</name> and <name>Senegal</name>.<note>For more on the Senegal Registers of Liberation, 
               see Roberts and Wall in this special issue.</note> The Registers provide information on ages, genders, categories, and 
               origins of freed enslaved people, their pathways towards liberation, and the evolution and dynamics of the end of 
               slavery in <name>West Africa</name>.
            </p>
            <p>Based on the directives of the National Education Orientation Laws (1991) and the Consolidated History Program (2006), 
               this article demonstrates how, when transcribed and made accessible online in an open-source format, these registers can 
               promote new pedagogical innovations in the teaching of the slave trade and slavery in <name>Senegal</name>. These 
               innovations are centered on the pedagogy of what we call <q>discovery exploitation construction</q> in the digital 
               humanities. Our approach involves the creation of new teaching paradigms that emerge from the online presentation and 
               integration of the registries into middle cycle curricula.
            </p>
            <p>Thus, our reflection will be articulated around four aspects. First, we will review the current teaching of the slave 
               trade and slavery and its limits; second, we will analyze the possible pedagogical and didactic perspectives of the 
               liberation registers; third, we will look at the ethics necessary for the use of digital humanities in the teaching of 
               the history of coercion in Senegalese middle cycle schooling; and finally, we will explore the challenges the liberation 
               registers raise.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>I. Teaching about the Slave Trade and Slavery in <name>Senegal</name>: A Status Report</head>
            <p>After independence from <name>France</name> in 1960, <name>Senegal</name> embarked on a process of curriculum reform to 
               align public schooling with the aspirations of the nation and its newly independent people. Curricular reforms took place 
               in 1965, 1998, and 2006, resulting in a national consolidated curriculum in 2006. In the 2006 Consolidated History 
               Program for the middle cycle curricula, the theme of the slave trade and slavery is addressed through specific and 
               general lessons. The aim of these lessons is: <quote rend="block">to help students acquire the concepts and facts that 
               will enable them to better understand the events, [but also] to develop specific skills in the subject; to encourage them 
               to pose problems and [...] ask questions; to lead them to be autonomous in the development of their own knowledge 
               <ptr target="#republique2006" loc="3"/>.</quote>. The objective is to form <quote rend="inline">autonomous and 
               supportive</quote> citizens, capable of demonstrating <quote rend="inline">mobilizable knowledge</quote> on the history 
               of <name>Senegal</name> and <name>Africa</name>, to be based on the historical approach and methodology, to have an 
               irreversible patriotic and civic posture, and to assume responsibility in any circumstance and situation. This is in 
               accordance with the Orientation Law (1991), which stipulates that National Education must aim to:
                 <list type="unordered">
                   <item><quote rend="inline">Raise the cultural level of the nation</quote> or, in other words, build the nation by 
                     training citizens who are cultured and proud of their Senegalese origins; and
                   </item>
                   <item><quote rend="inline">Train free men and women, capable of creating the conditions for their fulfillment at all 
                     levels, of contributing to the development of science and technology, and of providing effective solutions to the 
                     problems of national development. <ptr target="#republique1991"/></quote>
                   </item>
              </list>
            </p>
            <p>Including instruction on the slave trade and slavery in the curriculum enables learners to become aware of their past, 
               however painful it may be, and to construct a valorizing perception of Black Africans. This historical theme links school 
               education to current issues, which are linked to the problem of identity in an increasingly globalizing world. The goal 
               was therefore to create in young Senegalese a sense of attachment to a community of people who built the Americas 
               through their own sweat and blood and, therefore, to be proud of this community's trajectory and help shape its future. 
               What is really sought is the need to encourage a certain social and patriotic commitment among students, a commitment 
               that would be a useful viaticum to get rid of the colonial negation associated with Black Africans. The idea is, in 
               short, to create in the student a sense of <quote rend="inline">cultural nationalism</quote> and Black pride.
            </p>
            <p>Some twenty lessons and a few consolidation activities are devoted to the issue of the slave trade and slavery in the 
               middle cycle curricula. In most of the lessons, this phenomenon is approached from the angle of the civilizations of the 
               great empires or kingdoms of ancient and medieval <name>Africa</name> (see L6 to L11 in the 6th grade; L6 to L11 and 
               then L14 to L17 in the 5th grade; L10 to L15 in the 4th grade). Aspects of the slave trade that are covered in detail are 
               its origins, mechanisms, evolution, and consequences.
            </p>
            <p>These curricula do not always make it possible for teachers to delve deeply into, among other things, the demographics 
               of the slave trade (e.g., its volume over time and particularly from <name>Senegal</name>, its patterns with regard to 
               the gender and age of enslaved people, and its differential impact on regions in <name>Senegal</name> and across 
               <name>West Africa</name>). In addition, teachers do not have access to materials that make it possible to explore the 
               actors involved — elites who controlled processes of enslavement and, importantly, the enslaved themselves, some of 
               whom were exported into the Atlantic and some of whom remained in bondage in Africa itself. Apart from 
               <name>Toussaint Louverture</name>, no enslaved person is ever named in the lessons on these issues. The teaching of the 
               phenomenon has not changed in the schools; the curriculum approaches generalized populations of enslaved people as 
               products, not as actors. Students are exposed to historical and literary texts on the subject, they visit the Slave House 
               on <name>Gorée Island</name>, and they prepare a dossier on <name>Gorée</name> in the slave trade or on research work to 
               be presented in the form of a lecture. This means that the learners are more involved in storytelling and narration than 
               in the analysis and critical exploration of concrete and primary historical resources. The teachers' background readings 
               of the slave trade in the classroom reflect an embryonic conception of the facts that consists 
               <quote rend="inline">almost exclusively in blaming exogenous factors for the fate of <name>Africa</name> from the 15th 
               century onwards</quote> <ptr target="#seck2009" loc="72"/>.
            </p>
            <p>If we want to comply with one of the recommendations of the Consolidated History Program to instill students with 
               <quote rend="inline">a conception of history that privileges the facts of civilization, economic, [statistical], 
               political, social and cultural data</quote> <ptr target="#republique2006" loc="5"/>, it is imperative that students be 
               exposed to statistical resources when learning about the slave trade and slavery. It is also imperative that we humanize 
               the study of slavery and the slave trade in <name>Senegal</name>, centering named people whose life histories are 
               relatable and understandable. The Senegal Registers of Liberation are, therefore, appropriate for studying and 
               understanding the social history of this era, focusing first on the captives and only then preceding to the political, 
               economic, and institutional history of this phenomenon. This would be a history that allows students to have a panoramic 
               vision of a dark chapter in the evolution of <name>Africa</name>.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>II. Pedagogical and Didactic Perspectives of the Freed Slaves Register</head>
            <p>The Registers of Liberation, an official government record of the liberation of enslaved people in <name>Senegal</name> 
               between 1857 and 1903, which was recorded by French colonial officials after slavery was abolished in 
               <name>Senegal</name>, consists of twenty registers that together contain evidence of 28,930 liberations. 
               They record <quote rend="inline">the date, the identification number assigned to that specific liberation, the name of 
               the enslaved person, place of birth, age, place of liberation in the colony of <name>Senegal</name>, and name and 
               position of the colonial administrator who authorized the liberation</quote> <ptr target="#goodwin_etal2021"/>. A team 
               of Senegalese and American researchers have transcribed the registers into a dataset and are making a searchable and 
               analyzable version available 
               (<ref target="https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/5185180">https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/5185180</ref>). As a 
               compilation of liberations, the registers are a dashboard of freed enslaved people, a kind of tracing of freedoms. They 
               make it possible to analyze the rate and pace of releases and to better understand the geopolitical and economic 
               restructuring in a region like <name>Senegambia</name>. They clearly show that <quote rend="inline">unaccompanied 
               minors accounted for 68% of the total number of unaccompanied women</quote> <ptr target="#goodwin_etal2021"/>. Indeed, 
               the release of young people was more frequent than that of the elderly. The period of release is also an interesting 
               aspect studied by the registers. <name>Goodwin</name> et al. affirm that a <quote rend="inline">majority of releases 
               occurred between the months of March and June (41%), the months of October to January account for only 26% of the total 
               releases between 1894 and 1903</quote> <ptr target="#goodwin_etal2021"/>. The registers are, in short, a document that 
               traces the captives and their social and cultural history. They become, therefore, a pedagogical resource of paramount 
               importance. Their use can allow for a finer analysis of the dynamics of liberation in <name>Senegal</name> in the 
               nineteenth and twentieth centuries by promoting interactive teaching strategies which are at the heart of pedagogical 
               practices. But how?
            </p>
            <p>Registers I, III, V, IX, XI, XIV, and XVII, which detail captives' liberation from August 6, 1857 to April 14, 1903, 
               are a rich and significant pedagogical resource in teaching 4th grade lessons 5 (the economic consequences of the slave 
               trade in <name>Africa</name>), 7 (the slave trade in <name>Senegal</name>), and 8 (the abolitionist movement).<note>See 
               <ref target="https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/5185180">https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/5185180</ref>.</note> 
               In classroom practices and in developing curricula, the teachers can address the following elements:
              <list type="unordered">
                <item>In Lesson 5, they explore how the slave trade and slavery in <name>Africa</name> contributed to the 
                  disorganization of African economies, the depopulation of the continent, the disorganization of society, the 
                  reinforcement of social inequalities and the conflicts between kingdoms;
                </item>
                <item>In Lesson 7, they analyze the origins and evolution of enslavement and slavery in this country and how 
                  enslavement and slavery contributed to its political, social, and demographic consequences by insisting on the 
                  same elements mentioned previously;
                </item>
                <item>In Lesson 8, the focus is on the causes of the suppression of this phenomenon.<note>With the registers, 
                  there is a good chance that the teacher who wishes to remain in these three classic orientations can be even 
                  better equipped to strengthen or improve them.</note>
                </item>
              </list>
            </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure01">
              <head>Administrative document with information related to freed enslaved people, including their civil status and 
                 origin.</head>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="figure02">
              <head>Administrative document with further information related to freed enslaved people, including their date of release, 
                 the names of their parents, those of the declarants, etc.</head>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Moreover, the content of the Registers of Liberation allows us to go beyond these aspects. A rigorous exploitation of 
               this resource helps to see and insert into the lessons the geographic and social origins of the captives, the periods of 
               liberation, and the actions of enslaved people. The registers also allow us to create and teach both demographic 
               histories of generalized populations and life histories of named enslaved individuals. We can at once understand broad 
               patterns and humanize the study of slavery by piecing together shards of information recorded in the primary source to 
               uncover histories of named enslaved people's networks, familial relations, movements, and more. An analysis of the 
               liberations between 1881 and 1885 shows, for example, that the captives freed by the jurisdictions of 
               <name>Saint-Louis</name>, <name>Dakar</name>, <name>Gorée</name>, <name>Dagana</name>, and <name>Get Ndar</name> came 
               from various regions of <name>Senegambia</name>: <name>Sudan</name>, <name>Brouillard</name>, <name>Gambia</name>, 
               <name>Fouta Diallon</name>, <name>Ouassoulou</name>, <name>Ngabou</name>, <name>Cayor</name>, <name>Casamance</name>, 
               <name>Haut-Niger</name>, <name>Guidimakha</name>, <name>Boundou</name>, and others. All age groups were represented, as 
               indicated in the registry: children (1 to 14 years), adolescents (15 to 25 years), adults (27 to 50 years). And within 
               each of those age groups, the registers allow us to dig down to the level of the individual and understand through 
               fragmentary data something about the individual's unique life history.
            </p>
            <p>The registers thus offer a panoply of teaching and learning activities, including:
              <list type="unordered">
                <item>running statistical analysis of data from the registry to identify the distribution and classification of 
                  captives by gender, age, and geographic origin;
                </item>
                <item>computing the number of liberations by time period;
                </item>
                <item>discerning the leading consequences of enslaved people's liberty;
                </item>
                <item>constructing bar, pie, and semicircle diagrams according to the objectives assigned to a lesson;
                </item>
                <item>analyzing data to answer a wide range of issues essential to understanding the slave trade, its consequences, 
                  and its abolition in <name>Senegal</name> and <name>Africa</name>; and
                </item>
                <item>writing life histories of enslaved people from shards of recorded information.
                </item>
              </list>
               These lessons are based on the manipulation of digital data in the Registers of Liberation. Thus, specifically, we could 
               have, among other things, pedagogical interventions related to the registry, such as project-based approaches and 
               cooperative learning.
            </p>
            <p>Project-based approaches promote a rewarding educational experience by making it possible to highlight activities in the 
               classroom that lead to the production of new concrete knowledge on a question. They introduce learners to the processing 
               of <quote rend="inline">different data to give them meaning according to the objectives pursued, defined and decided by 
               the collective in charge of the project</quote> <ptr target="#boutet2016" loc="28"/>. Project-based approaches 
               approaches are therefore a pedagogy of experience that encourages the learner to <quote rend="inline">understand 
               reality</quote>.
            </p>
            <p>Cooperative pedagogy makes it possible to learn from others and strengthens citizenship and critical thinking, thereby 
               promoting positive interdependence. In other words, it is a pedagogy intended to make learners understand that the 
               process of acquiring knowledge and knowledge is based on mutualization and that the percentage of success is also the 
               result of pooling in training. Cooperative learning includes the category of social interaction models. In short, the 
               approaches described above help the teacher to be part of the objective-based pedagogy recommended in teaching-learning.
            </p>
            <p>It is easy to see that the advantage of the registry is that it can promote active and guided methods. In active methods, 
               the teacher places the student at the center of learning, encouraging them to construct their own knowledge by using a 
               variety of teaching resources adapted from the information in the registers. Such active methods, fundamental in 
               historical practice, fulfill the goals of the Consolidated History Program but require an <quote rend="inline">organized 
               and methodical sequence plan</quote> focused on situational and prerequisite (cognitive) preparation, modeling 
               (explanatory phase), guided practice, objectification, regular revisions, and evaluation 
               <ptr target="#couerbe2015"/>. This sequencing aims to motivate students, to inform them, and to encourage them to analyze 
               data, interact with one another, and produce historical analyses. It places learners in the timeframe of the history of 
               the phenomenon studied and its multiple ramifications. Exploring, analyzing, and interpreting digital data with students 
               allows them to become aware, from a comparative pedagogical perspective, of the multicultural and multifaceted nature of 
               the slave trade and slavery, to grasp <quote rend="inline">the identities forged there, and to integrate into the 
               construction of historical knowledge a community of [Black] destiny that concerns the past and the present as well as the 
               future</quote> <ptr target="#heimberg2009" loc="21"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Beyond the <q>active approach</q> that the registers could promote in teaching and learning, their appropriate and 
               practical use argues in favor of three theoretical currents: cognitivism, constructivism, and socioconstructivism. 
               As <name>Cardin</name> writes, <quote rend="inline">These three approaches have in common that they recognize the 
               determining role of the learner in the construction of his or her own knowledge and skills</quote> 
               <ptr target="#cardin2009" loc="34–35"/>. The use of evidence from the Registers of Liberation enables instructors to 
               adapt their teaching of the slave trade to the intelligence and personality of the students. This enables them to 
               examine the socio-cultural statistics of the phenomenon in question through pedagogical testing (activities, tasks, and 
               confrontations). Advocating an <quote rend="inline">ethical use of the document</quote>, in turn, allows students to 
               construct history and to get out of the straitjacket of the standard history of the slave trade and slavery, which is 
               limited to recounting its causes, mechanisms, organization, and consequences.
            </p>
            <p>While we know more and more about the ways in which students appropriate the history taught, and we know that the force 
               of the lecture alone is powerless to fix passive learning and knowledge, the practices of transmitting 
               <quote rend="inline">a closed knowledge to which students must adhere</quote> forcefully question, on the threshold of 
               the twenty-first century, the real stakes of historical training <ptr target="#hery2009" loc="115"/>.
            </p>
            <p>The transition that can be made by the registers is thus a boon for learners in the process of acquiring first-hand 
               historical knowledge. By focusing on the slave trade and slavery from the perspective of African enslaved people who 
               sought their own freedom rather than from the perspective of the capitalist slave traders in <name>Europe</name> and the 
               <name>Americas</name>, the registers provide a new understanding of the past.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>III. Digital Humanities, Ethics, and the Teaching of Slave Trade and Slavery in <name>Senegal</name>: What 
             Postures?</head>
            <p>The Registers of Liberation allow us to explore many cultural and social aspects related to slavery and the slave trade. 
               Who was made captive? From what geographic regions did captives come from? From what societies and cultures? What names 
               and surnames did enslaved people have? Such sensitive information in a conservative society like <name>Senegal</name>'s, 
               where discussions of people's enslaved descent are discouraged, raises ethical questions about the use of the registries 
               in the classroom. In the collective imagination, enslaved people were inferior, and descendants of enslaved people 
               continue to carry that stigma today. Thus, a kind of self-censorship around discussions of slavery has been created to 
               avoid conflicts and divisions that could undermine national cohesion. It is attested that even in the humanistic studies 
               the issue of slavery in Senegambian societies has been almost silenced for a long time by African historians. For 
               <name>Ibrahima Thioub</name>: <quote rend="block">the relative scarcity of studies devoted to domestic slavery by 
               African historians contrasts sharply with the importance of the phenomenon, its generalization across the continent, its 
               variable scope from one era to another, the role and functions of slaves in all areas of activity, and the diversity of 
               their social status. <ptr target="#thioub2009" loc="17"/></quote> How, then, can we reconcile the public-facing and 
               accessible nature of the digital humanities with the ethics of teaching this phenomenon, which in some societies is 
               considered dehumanizing, to young college students?
            </p>
            <p>These questions, though not an exhaustive list of considerations, identify some of the critical issues to address 
               prior to using digital resources like the Registers of Liberation. <name>Marc Bloch</name> calls for an appropriation 
               of the modern tools of science in history, tools which do not make a clean sweep of the past but instead represent part 
               of a transdisciplinary approach that allows for the forging of new formal models to achieve the objectives of teaching 
               and learning. Far from being only a virtual library, the humanities are spaces for the construction of scientific 
               knowledge that can be used in class and exploited in accordance with current pedagogical recommendations.
            </p>
            <p>Without ethics and responsibility in their use and transmission, the application of digital humanities to the teaching 
               of slavery in conservative societies such as <name>Senegal</name>'s can be destructive of cohesion and harmony between 
               populations. Descendants of enslaved people may feel dehumanized by stereotypes regarding slavery, which fosters 
               resentment and hatred between descendants and those who claim to hail from enslavers, among others. Ethics in such a 
               case would be part of a patriotic perspective.
            </p>
            <p>As for responsibility, it would lie in the fact that to teach is to choose. To choose is to proceed by useful 
               discrimination: discrimination that would have as its goal the respect of human dignity. This would not mean ignoring 
               historical reality. It is a question of acting with respect, morality, and prudence in the process of transmission.
            </p>
            <p>The use of digital data in history, a strategic and sensitive discipline, especially when it comes to taking an interest 
               in slavery, calls for the data to be appropriated pedagogically, that is to say, bearing in mind that not everything can 
               be transmitted and said as such without subterfuge. Clearly, it is a question of how to bring about the 
               <quote rend="inline">emergence of a digital materialism</quote> based on appropriate methods of training, learning, and 
               information transmission. In this case, the digital historical resource should be used not as a <q>bomb</q> that 
               destroys social cohesion, but as material for reflection, science, didactics, and pedagogy. It then becomes what 
               pedagogues and didacticians would describe as toolboxes for the trainer and the teacher that are part of two levers of 
               performance of the history curriculum: teaching through tools and sources.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>IV. Challenges of Introducing Pedagogical Innovations Using Digital Humanities</head>
            <p>The challenges linked to the use of digital humanities in educational pedagogy are many and varied. The development of 
               technologies in a connected century means that no training or learning process can ignore digital technology. What is 
               at stake is the quality of learning and the performance of students who may feel more at home with the web than with 
               paper; hence the conception of the Learner 2.0. The Learner 2.0 is that learner of the technological and digital age, a 
               learner who is aware of digital innovations, which are part of their experience, activities and daily evolution. This 
               is why introducing pedagogical innovations using digital humanities means connecting Senegalese schools and learners to 
               the world of today and tomorrow. This would also be in line with principles of the New School for 
               <name>Senegal</name>,<note>In January 1981, the General Assembly on Education and Training was convened. Echoing a deep 
               malaise in the Senegalese education system, the participants (government, trade unions, civil society, etc.) concluded 
               the need for a <quote rend="inline">radical overhaul of the education system, with a view to a new school more in line 
               with the deep aspirations of the Senegalese people, to the mastery of the scientific and technical conditions of our 
               integral development, democracy, social justice, peace, human progress</quote> <ptr target="#republique1991"/>. The New 
               School is clearly a school for <name>Senegal</name> and its aspirations.</note> a modern school serving universal 
               needs, where teachers are called upon to incorporate new knowledge and methods in history that are commonly accepted for 
               their relevance, originality, validity, and decisive contribution to learners. Embracing these innovations and their 
               impact on sicence and society reflects and unerstanding that the digital humanities can promote individualization and 
               collaborative work.
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, incorporating digital humanities into teaching practice means introducing both teachers and students to the 
               concept of scripting: <quote rend="inline">entering the digital era of learning head-on</quote> 
               <ptr target="#sauvage2019"/>. The challenge, in fact, is to think of a digital pedagogy of the future applicable to 
               history. It is a question of thinking about teaching history by the click of a mouse, which <quote rend="inline">enables 
               us to move beyond the ancestral and obsolete (albeit etymological) association of work/suffering towards 
               learning/pleasure</quote> <ptr target="#sauvage2019"/>. It is also a question of integrating the teaching of history in 
               <name>Senegal</name> into globalization, with the aim of inscribing it and the learners in the time-world of digital 
               pedagogy, which is mperative in a century of information and communication technologies.
            </p>
            <p>Ultimately, if we consider that tomorrow's world is that of the virtual and of information and communication 
               technologies, if modernity inevitably involves the integration of nations into the digital world, then we are called 
               upon, within the framework of our training curricula, to give a central place to the digital humanities. Digital 
               innovation must be a prime concern and imperative. It will be a question of pedagogical adaptation via digital didactics 
               in history, for the educational dimension of digital humanities is expressed in <quote rend="inline">the transmission of 
               skills within and outside educational institutions, the training of trainers and teachers, democratization and open 
               access to culture</quote> <ptr target="#bourgatte_etal2017" loc="157"/>.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>The treatment of issues related to the slave trade and slavery in Senegalese middle cycle schooling is trapped in a 
               form of academic writing that privileges its mechanisms, consequences, and areas of action. This form of history 
               relegates the captive to a demographic and their individual social and cultural dimensions to the background. Thus, 
               we need to make a sociological history of the captive in the turmoil of the slave trade and slavery more central to the 
               history of <name>Senegal</name>. Teachers have been hindered in this task by the lack of available sources on slavery in 
               <name>Senegal</name>. The open-source, online version of the Senegal Registers of Liberation allows us to fill this 
               historiographic gap. The possible didactic transposition of the data from the registers can promote the renewal of school 
               history on this issue. In addition, it argues in favor of a lively and constructive pedagogy that allows teachers and 
               learners to break with the liturgy and traditional rites of teaching about the slave trade and slavery in class. The 
               implementation of activities and tasks that give a great deal of space to the analysis of figures, to the sociology of 
               the captives and to their geographical and cultural origins, not only makes it possible to avoid dissociating historical 
               culture from the interests of the student, but it also allows us to make the pedagogical space the cradle of historical 
               vocation and of the collective consciousness that is so much sought after in a century of conflicting identities. The 
               use of the registers must however be accompanied by a robust discussion of the ethics and morality of transmission of 
               this history in order for digital humanities not to become a tool of social disarticulations.
            </p>
            <p>On another note, one might well ask how, in a continent marked by the digital divide, should we reconcile the teaching 
               of history and the use of digital technology? Even if the problem has arisen in the recent past, the efforts made to 
               equip certain schools with computer rooms are helping to encourage pedagogical innovations associated with digital 
               technology. The requirement to be part of these innovations has become an imperative that the COVID-19 pandemic has 
               helped to bring to light. From now on, education and training are required to be bimodal for greater effectiveness and 
               efficiency.
            </p>
        </div>
      </body>
      <back>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bloch1974" label="Bloch 1974">Bloch, M. (1974) <title rend="italic">Apologie pour l'histoire ou Métier 
             d'historien</title>. Paris: Armand Colin.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bourgatte_etal2017" label="Bourgatte, Ferloni, and Tessier 2017">Bourgatte, M., Ferloni, M., and Tessier, L. 
             (2017) <title rend="quotes">Communiquer en Humanités numériques: de la non-conférence aux non-actes</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Les Cahiers de la SFSIC</title>, 13, pp. 155-162.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="boutet2016" label="Boutet 2016">Boutet, M. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Expérience et projet: la pensée de Dewey 
             traduite en action pédagogique</title>, <title rend="italic">Phronesis</title>, 5(2), pp. 23-34. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.7202/1038137ar">https://doi.org/10.7202/1038137ar</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="brochier1965" label="Brochier 1965">Brochier, J. (1965) <title rend="quotes">J. Suret-Canale, Contexte et 
             conséquences sociales de la traite africaine, en Présence Africaine</title>, <title rend="italic">Revue Tiers 
             Monde</title>, 6(21), pp. 314. 
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cardin2009" label="Cardin 2009">Cardin, J.-F. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Identité nationale et histoire 
             scolaire: la controverse récente autour du nouveau programme d'istoire nationale au Québec</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Raison, comparaisons, éducation: La revue française d’éducation comparée</title>, 4 January, 
             pp. 33-52.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="couerbe2015" label="Couerbe 2015">Couerbe, V. (2015) <title rend="italic">Enseigner la traite négrière et 
             l'esclavage, ou comment élaborer un récit historique sans choquer en CM1</title>. PhD dissertation. 
             École supérieure du professorat et de l’éducation de l’académie de Paris.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="goodwin_etal2021" label="Goodwin, Ivans, Roberts, and Wall 2021">Goodwin, J., Ivans E., Roberts R., 
             and Wall R (2021) <title rend="quotes">The registers of slave liberation in colonial Senegal: Preliminary analysis of 
             the evidence from 1894 to 1903</title>, <title rend="italic">Esclavages &amp; Post-esclavages</title>, 5. Available 
             at: 
             <ref target="https://journals.openedition.org/slaveries/5495">https://journals.openedition.org/slaveries/5495</ref> 
             (accessed: 28 September 2022).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="heimberg2009" label="Heimberg 2009">Heimberg, C. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Quelques questions posées à 
             l'histoire scolaire et leur écho en Suisse romande. Raison, comparaisons, éducation</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">La revue française d’éducation comparée</title>, 4 January, pp. 19-31.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hery2009" label="Hery 2009">Hery, E. (2009) <title rend="quotes">L'Histoire et les pédagogies de 
             l'apprentissage dans l'enseignement secondaire du XXe siècle</title>, <title rend="italic">Les Sciences de l'éducation 
             - Pour l’Ère nouvelle</title>, 42(2) pp. 101-117.
          </bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="republique2006" label="Republique du Senegal 2006">Republique du Senegal (2006) 
              <title rend="italic">Programme consolidé d'histoire d'octobre 2006.</title> Dakar, Senegal: 
              Ministère de l'Éducation nationale du Sénégal.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="republique1991" label="Republique du Senegal 1991">Republique du Senegal (1991) <title rend="italic">Loi 
             d'orientation n° 91-22 de l'éducation nationale du 16 février 1991</title>. Dakar, Senegal: Ministère de l'Éducation 
             nationale du Sénégal. 
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="sauvage2019" label="Sauvage 2019">Sauvage, J. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Humanités numériques et formation 
             innovante en didactique du FLE</title>, <title rend="italic">Recherches en didactique des langues et des cultures</title>, 
             16(2). Available at: 
             <ref target="http://journals.openedition.org/rdlc/7051">http://journals.openedition.org/rdlc/7051</ref> 
             (accessed: 25 June 2023).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="seck2009" label="Seck 2009">Seck, I. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Esclavage et traite des esclaves dans les 
             manuels de l'enseignement secondaire du Sénégal: des programmes de domestication coloniale aux programmes dits 
             d'enracinement et d'ouverture</title>, <title rend="italic">Historiens et géographes du Sénégal</title>, 8 September, 
             pp. 69-78. 
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="thioub2009" label="Thioub 2009">Thioub, I. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Regard critique sur les lectures 
             africaines de l'esclavage et de la traite atlantique</title>, <title rend="italic">Historiens et géographes du 
             Sénégal</title>, 8 September, pp. 15-28. 
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
