<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Reading the <title rend="italic">Quan Tang
                        shi</title>: Literary History, Topic Modeling, Divergence Measures</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Peter <dhq:family>Broadwell</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Center for Interdisciplinary Research, Stanford University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>broadwell@stanford.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Peter Broadwell is a Digital Scholarship Research Developer in the Center
                            for Interdisciplinary Digital Research at Stanford University, where he
                            contributes to research projects in the digital humanities and
                            computational social sciences. He studied computer science at UC
                            Berkeley and received his PhD in Musicology from UCLA in 2010.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Jack W. <dhq:family>Chen</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Virginia</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>jwc8v@virginia.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Jack W. Chen is Associate Professor of Chinese Literature at the
                            University of Virginia. He is the author of <title rend="italic">The
                                Poetics of Sovereignty: On Emperor Taizong of the Tang
                                Dynasty</title> (Harvard University Asia Center, 2010) and co-editor
                            of <title rend="italic">Idle Talk: Gossip and Anecdote in Traditional
                                Chinese Literature</title> (University of California Press, 2013. He
                            is co-director of the Humanities Informatics Lab at UVA.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>David <dhq:family>Shepard</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Scholarly Innovation Lab, UCLA</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>dave@humnet.ucla.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>David Shepard is the Research Projects Developer at UCLA’s Scholarly
                            Innovation Lab. He received his PhD in English from UCLA in 2012. He is
                            a coauthor of <title rend="italic">HyperCities: Thick Mapping in the Digital Humanities</title>.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000434</idno>
                <idno type="volume">013</idno>
                <idno type="issue">4</idno>
                <date when="2019-12-14">14 December 2019</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2019-11-18" who="murelj">added final metadata set by authors via
                email</change>
            <change when="2019-10-12" who="murelj">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>The present paper addresses the problem of literary history as a problem of data
                    comprehensiveness and selection, seeking not to resolve the impossibility of
                    literary historical narrative, but to reframe it through a computational
                    perspective. Our focus is on the <title rend="italic" xml:lang="zh">Quan Tang
                        shi</title>
                    全唐詩 (Complete Tang poetry), the
                    massive comprehensive anthology of Tang poetry that was produced at the height
                    of the Qing dynasty (1644–1912). The sheer quantity of Tang poetry preserved in
                    the <title rend="italic" xml:lang="zh">Quan Tang shi</title> (over 50,000 poems
                    and poem fragments) exceeds the human-scale perspectives of close reading. To
                    make sense of the corpus as a whole, we will show how two related forms of
                    distant reading — topic modeling and divergence measures — allow us to reframe and
                    rethink these literary historical questions and provide a new perspective on
                    what it means to read Tang poetry.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Examines how topic modeling and divergence measures can be used to examine literary historical questions regarding Tang poetry</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The writing of literary history is perhaps an impossible endeavor. Even beyond
                    the broader problem of justifying what counts as literature, we are faced with
                    the question of how a historical narrative framework can effectively and
                    comprehensively represent a given literary tradition. In many ways, this is a
                    data modeling problem, one that turns on the question of reducing the vast
                    arrays of literary data into a comprehensible narrative. <note><ref
                            target="#rosenthal2017">See Rosenthal 2017</ref> for a discussion of the
                        relationship between narrative and data, though the problem of how the
                        narrative form impacts the data model is not raised. On the topic of data
                        modeling, <ref target="#flanders2016">see Flanders and Jannidis 2016</ref>,
                        though, conversely, there is no consideration of narrative as a data
                        model.</note> That is, even if one lowers one’s sights to consider only a
                    particular genre within a specific literary tradition — say, poetry written
                    during the Tang dynasty (618–907) — there is still too much writing to account
                    for and to fit into a coherent narrative. The problem is further complicated by
                    the lack of a clear standard for what should be selected and what omitted, and
                    how the selected portion could justifiably represent the whole of the data. As a
                    result, literary histories tend to recycle the same small sample of
                    super-canonical works and authors, unless the literary history is specifically
                    aimed at broadening the canon or focused on a previously marginalized
                    tradition.</p>
                <p>The present paper addresses the problem of literary history precisely as a
                    problem of data comprehensiveness and selection, seeking not to solve the
                    impossibility of literary historical narrative, but to reframe it through a
                    computational perspective. We take as our critical object the <title
                        rend="italic" xml:lang="zh">Quan Tang shi</title>
                    全唐詩 (Complete Tang poetry; hereafter
                        <title rend="italic">QTS</title>), the massive comprehensive anthology of
                    Tang poetry that was commissioned by imperial decree in 1705, at the height of
                    the Qing dynasty (1644–1912). Because the poetry of the Tang had become the
                    standard for poetic composition over the intervening dynasties, the compilation
                    of the <title rend="italic">QTS</title> thus may be said to represent the
                    culmination of some 800 years of literary canonization. This work is
                        <emph>the</emph> major source for extant Tang poetry, and moreover,
                    constitutes a literary historical perspective on the development of Tang poetry
                    in its complex and multidimensional classificatory scheme (more on this below).
                    However, the sheer quantity of Tang poetry that is preserved in the <title
                        rend="italic">QTS</title> — over 50,000 poems and poem fragments — simply
                    exceeds the human-scale perspectives of close reading. Yet without reading the
                    entirety of the <title rend="italic">QTS</title>, there can be no comprehensive
                    understanding of what Tang poetry is, let alone a literary historical account of
                    Tang poetry that can make use of the entire range of evidence and itself remain
                    intelligible. To this end, what is required is access to a different scale of
                    reading, one that has been characterized as <cit><quote rend="inline">distant
                            reading</quote>
                        <ptr target="#moretti2000a"/><ptr target="#underwood2017"/></cit>, but might
                    be more accurately thought of as machinic reading or as computational
                    criticism.</p>
                <p>Two points should be noted. First, on the question of distant reading versus
                    close reading, we are mindful of Andrew Piper’s caution against the
                    oft-brandished either/or dichotomy between the two scalar approaches. He writes,
                            <cit><quote rend="block" source="#piper2015">I want us to see how
                            impossible it is not to move between these poles when trying to
                            construct literary arguments that operate at a certain level of scale
                            (although when this shift occurs remains unclear). In particular, I want
                            us to see the necessary integration of qualitative and quantitative
                            reasoning, which, as I will try to show, has a fundamentally circular
                            and therefore hermeneutic nature.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#piper2015" loc="69"/></cit></p>
                <p>We fully agree with the necessity of a both/and approach that allows for
                    recursively circular processes of insights between scales of reading, though the
                    question remains of what it means to mediate between machinic and human
                    understandings of text and the equally important question of how a machinic
                    vision of reading might transform how we as humans understand hermeneutics.
                    Second, there has been relatively little work on distant reading methodologies
                    with regard to East Asian corpora, not only because of technical issues such as
                    character encoding and tokenization, but also because of the higher degree of
                    linguistic difficulty in mastering East Asian languages and textual traditions.
                    This said, in recent years there has been work on topic modeling and classical
                    Chinese text corpora <ptr target="#nichols2018"
                    />, focusing on particular issues in early thought. Mention should also be made
                    of an endeavor to apply topic modeling to a very large classical Chinese corpus,
                    though its results are more general and preliminary, and there are some basic
                    issues with document selection and preparation <ptr target="#allen2019"/>.
                    There have also been some studies of East Asian literary history using
                    computational methods that take up questions of genre and style as related to
                    problems of scalar reading <ptr target="#vierthaler2016"/><ptr
                        target="#long2016"/>, and along similar lines more specifically for Tang
                    poetry <ptr target="#liu2018"/>.</p>
                <p>This essay begins with a discussion of literary history and how it has framed
                    problems of data selection and completeness, before turning to an overview of
                    the <title rend="italic">QTS</title>. To make sense of the corpus as a whole, we
                    will then show how two related forms of distant reading — topic modeling and
                    divergence measures — allow us both to reframe and rethink these literary
                    historical questions and to access a new perspective on the practice of literary
                    history.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>I. What Do We Do When We Write Literary History?</head>
                    <p>Literary history, as a subfield within literary scholarship, has occupied an
                        ambivalent place, one that has seen a decline in terms of institutional or
                        disciplinary training, even while new literary histories are still being
                        written. The purpose of literary history can be defined in various ways,
                        including the emergence and development of a genre or genres, the rise of a
                        national literature, or the situation of literary writing within particular
                        historical and cultural contexts. Yet, however literary history is defined,
                        it is complicated by a number of factors, among which are the restrictions
                        that both the individual critic and the narrative form impose on what
                        authors and texts can be included, and what it means to include certain
                        authors or texts and not others, not to mention the broader problems of
                        working with historical context. David Perkins, in his now–seminal study,
                            <title rend="italic">Is Literary History Possible?</title>, writes:
                            <quote rend="block" source="#perkins1992">Whatever else they have also
                            hoped to accomplish, all literary historians have sought to represent
                            the past and to explain it. To represent it is to tell how it was and to
                            explain it is to state why — why literary works acquired the character
                            they have and why the literary series evolved as it did. … Of course
                            representation and explanation can never be complete, as literary
                            historians and theorists have always recognized. Even if a historian
                            knew all the relevant facts and answers, he could not crowd them into a
                            book. The only complete literary history would be the past itself, but
                            this would not be a history, because it would not be interpretive and
                            explanatory.</quote> Perkins goes on to ask <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#perkins 1992">how much incompleteness is acceptable</quote> and
                        to note how the fact that <quote rend="inline" source="#perkins1992">a
                            literary history must be written from a point of view</quote> — the
                        limited perspective of the critic—inflects the explanatory argument of the
                        narrative <ptr target="#perkins1992" loc="13"/>. These are problems that
                        underlie all narrative historiography, since the nature of narrative
                        historical argument involves simplification by means of representationality.
                        That is, certain data are selected to serve as representative of the whole,
                        and such choices are always informed by value judgments and critical
                        interventions.</p>
                    <p>To speak of data selection entails a need for evidentiary standards by which
                        the selection is made, but how standards are determined is not always clear
                        in literary historical writing. Data are not agnostic, because what gets
                        chosen as data always already implies value judgments <ptr
                            target="#drucker2011"/>
                        <ptr target="#rosenberg2013"/>. Decades earlier, René Wellek and Austin
                        Warren had already noted this exact point: <cit><quote rend="block"
                                source="#wellek1956">There are simply no data in literary history
                                which are completely neutral <q>facts</q>. Value judgements are
                                implied in the very choice of materials: in the simple preliminary
                                distinction between books and literature, in the mere allocation of
                                space to this or that author. Even if we grant that there are facts
                                comparatively neutral, facts such as dates, titles, biographical
                                events, we merely grant the possibility of compiling the annals of
                                literature. But any question a little more advanced, even a question
                                of textual criticism or of sources and influences, requires constant
                                acts of judgement.</quote>
                            <ptr target="#wellek1956" loc="40"/></cit> Neither Wellek and Warren nor
                        Perkins are arguing against historiographic simplification, since literary
                        histories, much like maps, provide us with signposts by which to navigate
                        the practically boundless territories of literary data. Indeed, one might go
                        even further: We rely on literary history to tell us what to read, to tell
                        us what counts as literature — in short, to demarcate the very boundaries of
                        the vast and otherwise amorphous realm of textuality. The map is not and
                        should not be the territory if the map is to be of any use. That said, there
                        is still a problem of <emph>how</emph> one makes the initial selections. To
                        allocate space in the historical narrative to a particular author means that
                        other authors must be neglected, or simply reduced to passing mention; at
                        some point the linearity of the narrative will require that data be excluded
                        or discussed in aggregate; and this refracts the data in ways that can be
                        obscured through the graceful telling of literary history. <note>It is worth
                            noting that Wellek and Warren’s first edition of <title rend="italic"
                                >Theory of Literature</title> was published in 1948, the same year
                            that Claude Shannon published his <title rend="quotes">A Mathematical
                                Theory of Information</title>, the essay that is often cited as
                            ushering in the Information Age. Wellek and Warren, of course, do not
                            make reference to the kinds of engineering problems with which Shannon
                            was concerned, but they are conscious of how the vast possible
                            quantities of literary facts impact the writing of literary history.
                            Some work has been done on intersection between the history of
                            information science and the history of literary studies, though there is
                            more that can be done <ptr target="#geoghegan2011"/>
                            <ptr target="#liu2010" loc="153–200"/>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>While one reduction of data takes place at the point of the historical
                        narrative’s composition, another reduction takes place over the history of
                        readership. Margaret Cohen speaks of the <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#cohen1999">Great Unread</quote>, the unquantified mass of
                        writings that have been lost through readerly neglect <ptr
                            target="#cohen1999" loc="23"/>. This same idea is expressed rather more
                        colorfully by Franco Moretti, who speaks of the <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#moretti2000b">slaughter of literature</quote> and <cit><quote
                                rend="inline" source="#moretti2000b">the butchers–readers: who read
                                novel A (but not B, C, D, E, F, G, H…) and so keep A <q>alive</q>
                                into the following one, and so on until eventually A becomes
                                canonized</quote>
                            <ptr target="#moretti2000b" loc="209"/>.</cit> Moretti’s model has its
                        flaws, both because it assumes <quote rend="inline">the shape of the past
                            from that of the present</quote>, effectively rediscovering the canon it
                        claims to question <ptr target="#bode2017" loc="90"/>, and because it treats
                        each hypothetical novel as a stable and discrete entity. The fact that
                        Novels B, C, or D are not chosen does not necessarily mean that their traits
                        go untransmitted to later generations. Novel A, whose traits are passed on,
                        may also have traits similar to Novels B, C, and D, etc., and indeed, most
                        novels within a particular genre that are produced around the same time are
                        likely to be more similar to one another than not. If Moretti’s model does
                        not quite hold, we may at least say that readership plays some kind of role
                        in the selection process of literary history, a process that is largely
                        unsupervised and distributed, in the sense that there is no single
                        intelligence that dictates which literary works will be canonized and which
                        will not.</p>
                    <p>Yet, although Moretti views the composition of literary history as largely an
                        afterthought, a rubber stamp of approval as he says, with the real work done
                        by the decentered agency of readership, the writing of literary history is
                        never simply reflective of reading histories, just as literary
                        historiography is never the sole constitutive authority of what is read. The
                        literary historian stands at the end of a lengthy process of selection,
                        charged with representing the history of the successfully transmitted
                        genetic material of literary data, but she also provides a critical
                        intervention into the history of readership, one that potentially
                        renegotiates the terms of readerly histories. That is to say, literary
                        historiography both articulates unarticulated processes of canonization and
                        consciously makes further selections of material both from within the
                        readerly canon and from without.</p>
                    <p>However the immense accumulations of literary data are pruned and managed
                        before they reach us, we might consider such reductions of data to be
                        blessings, since to paraphrase Ann Blair, there is simply too much to read
                            <ptr target="#blair2011"/>. Nevertheless, with the advent of massive
                        text digitization projects and the development of quantitative, rather than
                        qualitative, reading methodologies, we might begin to explore what a
                        literary history of a whole corpus (defined in terms of genre, period,
                        author, or even on greater scales, such as tradition) would look like. We
                        are mindful that qualitative perspectives will not be supplanted by
                        quantitative methods, and that quantitative perspectives will not simply
                        serve to confirm (or disprove) qualitative judgments. At the same time, the
                        impact of computational methodologies has not yet been fully assessed; how
                        one reads across multiple scales is not yet integrated into literary and
                        cultural studies. This essay is a first step toward articulating a set of
                        epistemological methodologies for a computational understanding of literary
                        history.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>II. What Is the <title rend="italic">QTS</title>?</head>
                    <p>To explore this problem of literary history, we will take as our object of
                        analysis the <title rend="italic">Quan Tang shi</title>, a comprehensive
                        anthology of (almost) all Tang dynasty (618–907) poetry <ptr
                            target="#qts1960"/> that was compiled between 1705 and 1707 under the
                        nominal editorship of the prominent official and imperial confidant Cao Yin
                        曹寅 (1658–1712) and a team of scholars led by Peng Dingqiu 彭定求 (1645–1719)
                            <ptr target="#spence1966" loc="156–65"/>. <note>Unsurprisingly, not all
                            Tang poems are collected in the <title rend="italic">QTS</title>. For an
                            anthology of uncollected Tang poems, see Chen 1992. Poetry recovered
                            from Dunhuang would not have been included in the <title rend="italic"
                                >QTS</title> because the Dunhuang Library Cave was not discovered
                            until 1900 <ptr target="#ren2014"/>.</note> Despite oft-voiced
                        complaints about textual errors, misattributions, and duplicate or omitted
                        poems, this is an extraordinary work of scholarship that has preserved
                        almost all poetry composed between the seventh and tenth centuries that
                        might otherwise have been lost. And because the <title rend="italic"
                            >QTS</title> corpus is a historically defined and comprehensive
                        collection of extant Tang verse, the flaws inherent to Matthew L. Jockers’s
                        macroanalytic approach to English literature, namely that his corpus is,
                        despite his grander claims, “incomplete, interrupted, haphazard,” are not
                        relevant here <ptr target="#jockers2013" loc="172"/>
                        <ptr target="#bode2017" loc="83"/>.</p>
                    <p>The structure of the <title rend="italic">QTS</title> is itself remarkable,
                        representing an ingenious attempt during its time to manage a vast array of
                        literary data and allow for efficient retrieval of documents within a
                        complex system. It consists of nine hundred chapters (<term xml:lang="zh"
                            >juan</term>
                        卷), with 49,403 poems (<term xml:lang="zh"
                            >shou</term>
                        首), as well as 1,055 poem fragments and couplets
                            (<term xml:lang="zh">ju</term>
                        句) <ptr target="#tong1998" loc="17"/>. This work
                        was based on two earlier anthologies of Tang poetry: first, the <title
                            rend="italic">Tangyin tongqian</title>
                        唐音統籤 (Assembled documents of Tang
                        tones), which was compiled by the Ming scholar Hu Zhenheng 胡震亨 (1569–ca.
                        1644) <ptr target="#hu2003"/>; and an earlier project, also entitled <title
                            rend="italic">Quan Tang shi</title>, that was begun by the Ming-Qing
                        transition poet Qian Qianyi 錢謙益 (1582–1664) and continued by Ji Zhenyi 季振宜
                        (b. 1630), now referred to as the <title rend="italic">Quan Tang shi
                            gaoben</title>
                        全唐詩稿本 (Draft version of the
                        complete Tang poems) <ptr target="#qian1979"/>. The <title rend="italic"
                            >QTS</title> is organized for the most part in a chronological fashion
                        with certain significant exceptions. The contents of the work are identified
                        as follows:</p>
                    <table>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell role="label">Chapters</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Contents</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">1–9</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems by emperors, empresses and imperial
                                members</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">10–16</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems relating to rituals and sacrifices</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">17–29</cell>
                            <cell role="data"><term>Music Bureau</term> poetry</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">30–731</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems by individual poets of the Tang dynasty</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">732–733</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems by dynastic villains and rebels</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">734–766</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems by individual poets of the Five Dynasties
                                Period</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">767–784</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems by poets with partial biographical
                                information</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">785–787</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems without authorial attribution</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">788–794</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Linked verse poems (<term xml:lang="zh">lianju</term>
                                聯句)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">795</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Incomplete poems and lines by poets not listed
                                above</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">796</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Incomplete poems and lines without authorial
                                attribution</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">797–805</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems by women </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">806–851</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems by Buddhist figures</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">852–859</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems by Daoist figures</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">860–862</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems by (male) immortals (<term xml:lang="zh"
                                    >xian</term>
                                仙)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">863</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems by female immortals (<term xml:lang="zh"
                                    >nüxian</term>
                                女仙)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">864</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems by spirits (<term xml:lang="zh">shen</term>
                                神)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">865–866</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems by ghosts (<term xml:lang="zh">gui</term>
                                鬼)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">867</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems by anomalies (<term xml:lang="zh">guai</term>
                                怪)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">868</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems sent in dreams (<term xml:lang="zh">meng</term>
                                夢) </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">869–872</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Jest and insult poems (<term xml:lang="zh"
                                    >xienüe</term>
                                諧謔) </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">873</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems inscribed on walls (<term xml:lang="zh"
                                    >tiyu</term>
                                提語) and judgments (<term xml:lang="zh"
                                    >pan</term>
                                判)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">874</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Songs (<term xml:lang="zh">ge</term>
                                歌) sung by groups or local
                                communities</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">875</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Prophetic verse (<term xml:lang="zh">chenji</term>
                                讖記)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">876</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Sayings in verse form (<term xml:lang="zh">yu</term>
                                語)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">877</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Proverbs and enigmatic verse (<term xml:lang="zh"
                                    >yanmi</term>
                                諺謎)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">878</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Prescient popular ditties (<term xml:lang="zh"
                                    >yao</term>
                                謠)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">879</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Drinking songs (<term xml:lang="zh">jiuling</term>
                                酒令)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">880</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Divination songs (<term xml:lang="zh">zhanci</term>
                                占辭)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">881</cell>
                            <cell role="data">The <term xml:lang="zh">Mengqiu</term>
                                蒙求 primer by Li Han 李瀚</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">882–888</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Poems left out of previous sections (<term
                                    xml:lang="zh">buyi</term>
                                補遺)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">889–900</cell>
                            <cell role="data">Song-lyrics (<term xml:lang="zh">ci</term> 詞) </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>The first nine chapters are devoted to poems by members of the Tang imperial
                        household, while chapters 10 to 29 cover ritual-related poetic texts and
                            <term xml:lang="zh">yuefu</term> 樂府 poetry (poetry that relates to the
                        Han dynasty Music Bureau or were composed under titles related to this
                        office) <ptr target="#allen1992"/>
                        <ptr target="#owen2006b" loc="301–307"/>. However, the bulk of the
                        anthology’s contents (chs. 30–731) follow an approximate chronological order
                        of the lives of the individual poets included within. The anthology breaks
                        from historical chronology to include poems by dynastic villains such as the
                        eunuch Gao Lishi 高力士 (684–762) and the rebel Huang Chao 黃巢 (d. 884) (chs.
                        732–33) before the historical chronology resumes with poets of the Five
                        Dynasties (chs. 734–66). However, following this, one finds poets with
                        increasingly less biographical information, beginning with poets for whom
                        full names and rank or geographic association are known, but who have no
                        verified dates, then taking up poets who lack names but have some kind of
                        other association that can be used to refer to them (i.e., <quote
                            rend="inline">Traveler at Mount Li</quote>
                        麗山遊人), and ending with poems that
                        no longer have attributed authors (chs. 767–87). This is followed by linked
                        verse (poems composed collaboratively, with each poet contributing
                        alternating lines or couplets), incomplete poems (lines, couplets, stanzas)
                        by poets without otherwise extant complete poems, and incomplete poems
                        without any attribution (chs. 788–96).</p>
                    <p>Excepting the sections for poems written by imperial household members and
                        dynastic villains, the anthology is, up to this point, organized according
                        to a literary historical logic, one that seeks to order the poems by
                        chronological precedence according to the authors’ biographical information,
                        and then places those poems that lack such information afterwards in
                        descending order of how much information is available. Pauline Yu, writing
                        on Tang poetic anthologies, has called attention to the essential
                        relationship between anthologies and literary history. She points out how
                        poems in traditional Chinese anthologies <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#yu1990">were generally arranged in chronological order, if
                            known, within an individual poet’s corpus, and then from author to
                            author as well.</quote> As Yu goes on to note, this practice was
                        distinct from Japanese anthologies, <cit><quote rend="inline"
                                source="#yu1990">whose topical, associative, or thematically
                                sequential organizational schemes suggest principles that are
                                distinctly non-historical</quote>
                            <ptr target="#yu1990" loc="170"/></cit> (also see <ptr target="#yu1994"
                        />). This latter form of anthology is based on the <term xml:lang="zh"
                            >leishu</term>
                        類書 (categorized writings), which
                        were most commonly organized by a hierarchical system of topics, from the
                        cosmic (heaven and earth) to the miniscule (insects) <ptr
                            target="#drège2007"/>. <term xml:lang="zh">Leishu</term> are comparable
                        to encyclopedias insofar as they were intended as comprehensive repositories
                        of textual information, though there are significant differences from the
                        Western concept of the encyclopedia <ptr target="#tian2017"/>. </p>
                    <p>We see a different organizational logic beginning with chapter 797, where the
                            <title rend="italic">QTS</title> departs from a literary historical mode
                        and follows something that is much closer to the topical categories
                        associated with Japanese-style anthologies. This next section (chs. 797–805)
                        is concerned with female poets, from <quote rend="inline">famous
                            beauties</quote> (<term xml:lang="zh">mingyuan</term>
                        名媛) and professional female performers (<term
                            xml:lang="zh">jinü</term>
                        妓女) to well-known named authors such as Xue Tao
                        薛濤 (d. 832), Yu Xuanji 魚玄機 (ca. 844–68), and Li Ye 李冶 (d. 784). Following
                        this are sections on Buddhist and Daoist poets (chs. 806–59), and then
                        sections on immortals (<term xml:lang="zh">xian</term>
                        仙), spirits (<term xml:lang="zh">shen</term>
                        神), ghosts (<term xml:lang="zh">gui</term>
                        鬼), and anomalies (<term xml:lang="zh"
                            >guai</term>
                        怪) (chs. 860–66). The last chapters of the
                        anthology are truly miscellaneous, including examples of divination verse
                            (<term xml:lang="zh">zhanci</term>
                        占辭), proverbs and enigmatic verse (<term
                            xml:lang="zh">yanmi</term>
                        諺謎), prescient popular ditties (<term
                            xml:lang="zh">yao</term>
                        謠), poems from dreams (<term xml:lang="zh"
                            >meng</term>
                        夢), and poems inscribed on walls (<term
                            xml:lang="zh">tiyu</term>
                        提語). Wherever possible, these chapters begin with
                        figures related to the imperial house (emperors, palace women) and then
                        proceed in chronological order.</p>
                    <p>The organizational logic of the <title rend="italic">QTS</title> is worth a
                        brief comment as it combines two earlier organizational schemes for literary
                        anthologies: the categorical scheme associated with the encyclopedic <term
                            xml:lang="zh">leishu</term> and the comprehensive chronological scheme
                        that became prominent with Ming dynasty literary anthologies. Both forms of
                        organization express a critical intelligence that orders documents in a way
                        that makes theoretically possible the search and retrieval of particular
                        documents. Yet because the <title rend="italic">QTS</title> is constructed
                        on a larger scale than what an individual reader can productively manage,
                        the anthology functions in many ways more like an archive or a database than
                        a work intended for personal perusal.</p>
                    <p>One might contrast the <title rend="italic">QTS</title> to other smaller Tang
                        poetic anthologies that were clearly meant for individual readers, such as
                        the slightly later Qing anthology, <title rend="italic" xml:lang="zh">Tang
                            shi sanbaishou</title>
                        唐詩三百首 (The three hundred poems of
                        the Tang). Compiled by Sun Zhu 孫誅 (1722–78), this extremely popular
                        selection of approximately three hundred poems has served as an elementary
                        poetry primer for generations through to the present day <ptr
                            target="#qian2000" loc="364"/>. To frame this within broader issues of
                        literary history, while the <title rend="italic">QTS</title> has served as
                        the imperially sanctioned and culturally canonical edition of Tang poetry
                        since its compilation, it was the <title rend="italic">Tang shi
                            sanbaishou</title> (and similar anthologies) that provided convenient
                        and familiar access and thus actually shaped the idea of Tang poetry for
                        most readers. In this way, the <title rend="italic">Tang shi
                            sanbaishou</title> served as a primary training dataset for literary
                        historical knowledge, curating the popular experience of Tang poetry
                        throughout society, and thus constructing standards of taste and readerly
                        expectation for what a Tang poem should be.</p>
                    <p>While literary histories of the Tang are not usually based on elementary
                        anthologies like the <title rend="italic" xml:lang="zh">Tang shi
                            sanbaishou</title>, they are nevertheless shaped by other cultural
                        datasets, whether these are more scholarly anthologies, critical studies, or
                        university curricula. If this is the case, then what might a history of Tang
                        poetry look like if the dataset were comprehensive, or at least more robust?
                        That is to say, how might <emph>reading</emph> the <title rend="italic"
                            >QTS</title> alter our view of Tang poetic history? To be sure, both the
                        act of reading the <title rend="italic">QTS</title> and any critical
                        representation of this knowledge would certainly depart from the usual
                        narrative forms associated with conventional literary history. Indeed, while
                        the <title rend="italic">QTS</title> has often been mined as a resource for
                        histories of Tang poetry (in English, see <ref target="#owen1977">Owen
                            1977</ref>, <ref target="#owen1981">Owen 1981</ref>, <ref
                            target="#owen2006a">Owen 2006a</ref>; in Chinese, see <ref
                            target="#xu1994">Xu 1994</ref>, <ref target="#yang1996">Yang
                        1996</ref>), it is rarely considered in its own right. After all, how many
                        poets and poems, representing the literary accumulation of nearly three
                        hundred years, can be fruitfully discussed within a single narrative
                        framework? And even if such a narrative framework were possible, what
                        examples of poetry should be selected and what omitted? How should the
                        oeuvre of an individual poet be represented? How does the unit of analysis,
                        whether it be the individual poet, a poetic style, or a literary theme,
                        shape and inflect the literary historical account? If we are to understand
                        Tang poetry not in terms of the limited dataset of authors and texts, but in
                        terms of the whole of transmitted literary data, then we will need to take a
                        macroscopic perspective, one that initially forgoes the granularity of close
                        reading for something that takes place at a more stratospheric level.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>III. On Topic Modeling as Literary Methodology</head>
                    <p>In an age in which massive text digitization projects have been carried out
                        by research centers, universities, government agencies, and individuals,
                        literary historical claims need not rely solely upon microscale reading. The
                        problem of close reading is that it is only possible at the scale of the
                        individual text, which then necessitates an exemplary approach to the
                        selection and analysis of the critic’s dataset <ptr target="#hickman2012"
                            /><ptr target="#north2013"/>. To avail oneself of distant reading
                        methods, however, is to adopt a somewhat different understanding of what it
                        is to read a text, one that does not rely upon the anecdotal, limited nature
                        of individual data-gathering. Here it is the machine that transforms the
                        interpretative process, providing the scalar shift and quantitative capacity
                        that makes reading large corpora possible. Computational analysis is not
                        necessary for the individual poem, but when confronted by thousands of poems
                        (or more), then the computer makes it possible to extract meaningful
                        information on a macroscopic level from the aggregated texts. N. Katherine
                        Hayles has written on this point, noting that we are entering an age of
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#hayles2010">machine reading</quote>, which
                        is to say, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#hayles2010">computer
                                algorithms used to analyze patterns in large textual corpora where
                                size makes human reading of the entirety impossible</quote>
                            <ptr target="#hayles2010" loc="72"/></cit>. And Stephen Ramsay writes:
                                <cit><quote rend="block" source="#ramsay2011">It is one thing to
                                notice patterns of vocabulary, variations in line length, or images
                                of darkness and light; it is another thing to employ a machine that
                                can unerringly discover every instance of such features across a
                                massive corpus of literary texts and then present those features in
                                a visual format entirely foreign to the original organization in
                                which these features appear. Or rather, it is the same thing at a
                                different scale and with expanded powers of observation. It is in
                                such results that the critic seeks not facts, but patterns. And from
                                pattern the critic may move to the grander rhetorical formations
                                that constitute critical reading.</quote>
                            <ptr target="#ramsay2011" loc="17"/></cit> It is important to note that
                        Ramsay also argues (elsewhere in his work) that computer-aided reading,
                        which he calls <quote source="#ramsay2011" rend="inline">algorithmic
                            criticism</quote>, is not a radical break from traditional modes of
                        literary reading, since the human critic’s acts of interpretation can also
                        be said to depend on rule-based processes — which is to say, upon algorithms
                        — even though the critic’s manipulations and deformations of text may not be
                        as explicit or programmatic as those of the computer. And to return to
                        Hayles’ point, the major difference that can be realized through the
                        computer’s algorithmic reading is simply that of the object of study, which
                        is no longer confined to the single text or a succession of single texts,
                        but a macroscalar aggregation of texts.</p>
                    <p>More recent work such as Andrew Piper’s <title rend="italic"
                            >Enumerations</title> follows essentially the same guiding principles:
                        Piper uses statistical methods to approximate the judgements of a human
                        reader at a macroscopic scale. Piper arrives at some impressive conclusions,
                        including that characters within novels are more different from each other
                        than they are from characters in other novels, and that heroes in
                        twentieth-century science fiction are just as introspective as the heroines
                        of nineteenth-century women’s fiction. While critics’ chosen statistical
                        methods have become more sophisticated, the basic approach of using
                        statistics to approximate the human reader’s critical judgments at scale
                        persists.</p>
                    <p>Topic modeling, as a form of text mining, is one method of reading a large
                        corpus, and while it is becoming increasingly familiar to practitioners of
                        literary analysis, we will provide a quick summary here, one that is
                        intended to set the terms for the following section. There are various
                        introductions and overviews for those seeking more detailed summaries <ptr
                            target="#meeks2012"/>; <ptr target="#underwood2012"/>; <ptr
                            target="#riddell2012"/>). In brief, topic modeling deploys a set of
                        probabilistic algorithms to identify latent semantic patterns within a set
                        of documents. This is how David Blei, co-author of the most widely used
                        probabilistic model — <term>latent Dirichlet allocation</term> or LDA <ref
                            target="#blei2003">(see Blei, Ng, and Jordan 2003)</ref> — describes it:
                            <quote rend="block" source="#blei2012">…the goal of topic modeling is to
                            automatically discover the topics from a collection of documents. The
                            documents themselves are observed, while the topic structure — the
                            topics, per-document topic distributions, and the per-document per-word
                            topic assignments — is <term>hidden structure</term>. The central
                            computational problem for topic modeling is to use the observed
                            documents to infer the hidden topic structure. This can be thought of as
                                <q>reversing</q> the generative process — what is the hidden structure
                            that likely generated the observed collection?</quote>
                        <ptr loc="79" target="#blei2012"/></p>
                    <p>There are a number of terms and concepts that need to be explained. First of
                        all, there is the issue of <term>latency</term>, which Blei refers to as the
                            <quote source="#blei2012" rend="inline">hidden structure</quote> of the
                        corpus. Topic modeling posits that there is a latent semantic structure
                        beneath the observable corpus, and that there is a difference between what
                        we can read in the everyday sense of the word and what only the computer can
                        discern. This hidden structure is what topic modeling seeks to recover as
                        the corpus’s <term>generative model</term>, or the matrix of thematically
                        significant word clusters that make up the corpus as it presently exists.
                        These thematic word clusters are the <term>topics</term> that the algorithm
                        seeks to model, composed of words that have a high rate of co-occurrence
                        within documents (understood here as any significant unit of text). The
                        topics are probabilistically significant distributions of words that
                        comprise the corpus’s documents, and each of the documents is understood as
                        a mixture of topics. Document word order is not important, as the topic
                        model treats the corpus simply as a <q>bag of words,</q> drawing out each
                        word and assigning it to a topic based on the frequency of its co-occurrence
                        with other frequently co-occurring words.</p>
                    <p>How can this model claim to reflect the process of composing literature, let
                        alone literary history? The answer is that it does not, but it approximates
                        it. As readers, we may assume the poetic process for a poet — or a group of
                        poets — as something like: first, a poet sets out to express an idea, which
                        is composed of one or more themes, like <q>love</q> and <q>beauty</q>. Next,
                        the poet chooses concrete images to express these themes and ideas, such as
                            <q>love</q> and <q>roses</q>. From this, the poet puts the ideas into
                        words, e.g., <q>My love is like a red, red rose</q>. A human reader, reading
                        the poem, works in reverse: she encounters the poet’s actual words and
                        transforms them into a set of images and thoughts, ultimately seeking to get
                        a sense of <q>what the poet is actually writing about</q> — in other words,
                        the themes he is trying to express. The specific layers described above
                        perhaps do not matter so much: there may be more to the processes of
                        composition or reading. Our point is that what we experience as the richness
                        of human reading are the different levels of experience that a poem inspires
                        in a reader: visualized images, emotional experiences, resonances with other
                        words, historical context, and the like. The processes of producing or
                        consuming literature is a process of either expressing or discovering these
                        layers.</p>
                    <p>LDA follows a similar process: it starts from the poet’s word choice and
                        assumes that some latent variables (images or themes) drive the poet’s word
                        choices (the observed variables). It models the latent variables from the
                        observed variables. While LDA is an approximate model, with far less
                        sophistication than a human reader, it scales better. LDA approximates what
                        a human being does with less sophistication: it has only two layers of
                        meaning (observed and latent variables) versus the reader’s potentially many
                        interpretive layers. However, it can work at a much larger scale, and with
                        much greater accuracy because it is not subject to the failures of human
                        memory. A human critic using LDA works off of this approximation: she
                        assumes that the latent variables match some of the things that a human
                        reader will discover using their own interpretive apparatus, and interprets
                        LDA’s topics as patterns of imagery, themes, or ideas. She must negotiate
                        between the rich meanings that a reader can extract from the few texts that
                        a human reader can read, and the far less rich latent patterns that the LDA
                        model can discover.</p>
                    <p>From this negotiation, we are able to derive a different model for doing
                        literary history, one that scales to a larger set of texts. If one conceives
                        of literary history as an epistemological process of discovery, one that
                        seeks to understand the parameters for how the literary past is constructed,
                        then this perspective has the potential to reconceptualize our received
                        evidentiary standards. What follows may not resemble literary historical
                        work, and indeed, may read more like laboratory reports than critical
                        analysis, but this is necessary: we are proposing that a macroanalytic
                        literary history will require different methodologies, ones that negotiate
                        between human and machine visions of textuality. To highlight the
                        applications of such a computationally enhanced methodology to poetic
                        studies and perhaps more broadly, we illustrate how judicious examination of
                        a topic model of the <title rend="italic">QTS</title> calls out poems whose
                        authors and genres have not received the blessing of concerted attention
                        from scholars, yet upon close inspection present exemplary literary and
                        historical insights. Moreover, the identification of these poems and their
                        revelatory topical similarities (and divergences) follows from what is
                        arguably the key analytical contribution of LDA topic modeling: its ability
                        to infer semantically alloyed relationships between sets of words that may
                        appear together in the same document infrequently or even not at all, and to
                        do this at a corpus-wide scale that is inaccessible to the minds of even the
                        most well-read scholars. The discussion also emphasizes the importance of
                        keeping the human <q>in the loop</q> throughout such computer-aided
                        analyses, as computational measures of significance do not always correspond
                        to humanistic notions of meaning.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>IV. The <title rend="italic">QTS</title> and Topic Modeling</head>
                    <p>On the most basic level: the topic modeling program that we used is <title
                            rend="italic">MALLET (MAchine Learning for LanguagE Toolkit)</title>
                        <ptr target="#mccallum2002"/>. For the <title rend="italic">QTS</title>
                        corpus, we excluded all poetic fragments (generally orphan couplets and
                        lines) from the topic model, as the shortness of these documents
                        statistically skews the output, though we retained sections of significant
                        length, such as Chapter 881, which is comprised solely of the poetic primer
                            <term xml:lang="zh">Mengqiu</term>, as it was feasible to divide these
                        into poem-length subsections. We did not use a stop-word list, as many
                        classical Chinese grammatical particles have other, non-particle meanings
                        depending on the context. We specified that <title rend="italic"
                            >MALLET</title> should generate 150 topics, which was the number of
                        topics (following an iterative trial-and-error process) that provided the
                        most informational complexity while minimizing interpretive
                            perplexity.<note>Note that the problem of optimizing the ideal number of
                                topics for LDA is still unresolved. This is discussed, with relevant technical sources, in <ref target="#tangherlini2013"
                                loc="731">Tangherlini and Leonard 2013, 731</ref>.</note> From this, we
                        received three reports: a topic-keys report (TKR), a topic-phrase report
                        (TPR), and a document-topics report (DTR) — all of which will be discussed
                        in turn. While these reports may be familiar to those who have experience
                        with topic modeling, discussing these reports in detail is important for our
                        argument, as we will demonstrate.</p>
                    <p>The first output file, the topic-keys report, is a non-ranked list of topics
                        that shows the twenty strongest correlated words in each topic in ranked
                        order (note that these are only the top twenty correlated words for a given
                        topic, as this is the default number in <title rend="italic"
                        >MALLET</title>). Here are the first eleven topics from the TKR: <list
                            type="ordered">
                            <item>馬 車 騎 行 塵 出 長 鞭 門 走 白 嘶 金 蹄 道 鞍 青 黃 馳
                                    驅</item>

                            <item>酒 醉 杯 飲 一 客 酌 醒 勸 滿 尊 傾 對 笑 壺 歡 酣 送 倒
                                    且</item>

                            <item>不 人 能 知 誰 生 自 有 無 來 豈 得 在 與 作 但 令 可 古
                                    解</item>

                            <item>相 年 家 見 弟 同 兄 來 逢 長 少 還 自 許 多 喜 說 親 作
                                    時</item>

                            <item>江 海 迢 潮 帆 吳 越 楚 孤 滄 客 去 洲 波 歸 遠 湖 浪 遞
                                    南</item>

                            <item>寂 遙 寥 空 落 寞 朝 風 獨 見 中 思 林 月 清 在 寒 逍 想
                                    招</item>

                            <item>夜 月 明 燈 曉 殘 漏 星 聲 更 照 暗 寒 宿 燭 火 半 光 露
                                    鐘</item>

                            <item>我 不 為 此 言 爾 者 何 有 亦 如 生 人 與 得 苦 無 所 願
                                    令</item>

                            <item>水 東 流 西 山 日 去 雲 空 落 歸 中 路 陵 白 復 見 長 暮
                                    盡</item>

                            <item>金 玉 珠 銀 紫 錦 重 寶 黃 光 刀 環 裁 佩 衣 雙 盤 珊 龍
                                    垂</item>

                            <item>蕭 風 雨 秋 暮 條 寒 雲 吹 起 獨 颯 晚 上 日 樹 葉 空 向
                                    索</item>
                        </list> The first column is the topic ID number, assigned by <title
                            rend="italic">MALLET</title> without rank significance. The second is
                        the set of the words assigned to the topics in ranked order of correlation
                        strength.</p>
                    <p>As the topics simply consist of ranked lists of words, to understand what the
                        topics signify requires that labels be added to the topic-keys report. These
                        labels are necessarily acts of interpretation, though useful ones for
                        translating the machine perspective on the corpus into human terms. Here
                        again are the first eleven topics, now with our provisional labels:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>馬 車 騎 行 塵 出 長 鞭 門 走 白 嘶 金 蹄 道 鞍 青 黃 馳
                                驅 horses, traveling </item>
                        <item>酒 醉 杯 飲 一 客 酌 醒 勸 滿 尊 傾 對 笑 壺 歡 酣 送 倒
                                且 drinking ale </item>
                        <item>不 人 能 知 誰 生 自 有 無 來 豈 得 在 與 作 但 令 可 古
                                解 particles, common verbs </item>
                        <item>相 年 家 見 弟 同 兄 來 逢 長 少 還 自 許 多 喜 說 親 作
                                時 families, home </item>
                        <item>江 海 迢 潮 帆 吳 越 楚 孤 滄 客 去 洲 波 歸 遠 湖 浪 遞
                                南 southern waterscapes </item>
                        <item>寂 遙 寥 空 落 寞 朝 風 獨 見 中 思 林 月 清 在 寒 逍 想
                                招 remoteness and longing </item>
                        <item>夜 月 明 燈 曉 殘 漏 星 聲 更 照 暗 寒 宿 燭 火 半 光 露
                                鐘 night: moon and lamp </item>
                        <item>我 不 為 此 言 爾 者 何 有 亦 如 生 人 與 得 苦 無 所 願
                                令 particles, pronouns </item>
                        <item>水 東 流 西 山 日 去 雲 空 落 歸 中 路 陵 白 復 見 長 暮
                                盡 landscape: traveler </item>
                        <item>金 玉 珠 銀 紫 錦 重 寶 黃 光 刀 環 裁 佩 衣 雙 盤 珊 龍
                                垂 precious materials </item>
                        <item>蕭 風 雨 秋 暮 條 寒 雲 吹 起 獨 颯 晚 上 日 樹 葉 空 向
                                索 autumn evening scene </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Taking a closer look at Topic 1, to which we have attached the label
                            <term>traveling with horses</term>, we may further gloss the listed
                        terms as follows: 馬 (horse), 車 (carriage or wagon),
                            騎 (rider or to
                        ride), 行 (to travel), 塵 (dust), 出
                            (to depart, set forth), 長
                            (long), 鞭 (whip),
                            門 (gate), 走 (to run), 白
                            (white), 嘶 (to
                            neigh), 金 (gold, metal), 蹄 (hoof),
                            道 (road), 鞍 (saddle), 青
                            (green-blue), 黃
                            (yellow, brown), 馳
                            (to gallop, to rush), and 驅 (to drive forward, to urge forth).
                        All of these words are either thematically related to horses and traveling
                        or illustrate what the linguist Shuanfan Huang calls syntactic contiguity,
                        such as the three color terms <ptr target="#huang2013" loc="55–80"/>.</p>
                    <p>More difficult to label is a result such as Topic 4, which consists of many
                        commonly used words, including the particle 相
                            (mutually, or an adverbial particle replacing a direct
                        object), 年 (year), 家 (family, home), 見 (to see, to meet),
                            弟 (younger brother), etc., which
                        might relate to a number of poetic themes involving home and family or
                        perhaps something broader. There are a number of such topics, where the
                        meanings of the terms are clear but how they relate semantically remains
                        more or less ambiguous, inviting the human interpreter to fill in the gaps
                        and to imagine possible poems that might be constructed with these terms.
                        Here, the problem becomes one of projecting meaning where meaning is
                        indeterminate, or perhaps, not determined in ways that accord with our
                        (human) cultural categories.</p>
                    <p>Turning back to the <title rend="italic">MALLET</title> output files, the
                        same results are available in a more detailed list with weights for each
                        word and for frequently occurring phrases. This is provided in the second
                        output file, the topic-phrase report. This report first begins with a
                        listing of frequently occurring phrases (combinations of tokens) in the
                        topic and then provides a ranked list of the first nineteen words in the
                        topic, followed by a ranked list of the 21 most common phrases. As the TPR
                        is an even lengthier report than the TKR, here is the section just for Topic
                        0, reformatted as two separate tables. The first table lists each word in
                        ranked order with word weights and token counts:</p>
                    <table>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell role="label">Word</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Word Weight</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Count</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">馬</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.16849291492169124</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2937</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">車</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.049968447019677585</cell>
                            <cell role="data">871</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">騎</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.03568355229189375</cell>
                            <cell role="data">622</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">行</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.031897194653204064</cell>
                            <cell role="data">556</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">塵</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.03172508748780908</cell>
                            <cell role="data">553</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">出</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.030577706385175835</cell>
                            <cell role="data">533</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">長</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.027594515518329414</cell>
                            <cell role="data">481</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">鞭</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.02702082496701279</cell>
                            <cell role="data">471</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">門</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.025299753313062934</cell>
                            <cell role="data">441</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">走</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.020595490792266653</cell>
                            <cell role="data">359</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">白</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.018358097642131834</cell>
                            <cell role="data">320</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">嘶</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.016694395043313638</cell>
                            <cell role="data">291</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">金</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.016120704491997016</cell>
                            <cell role="data">281</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">蹄</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.014973323389363778</cell>
                            <cell role="data">261</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">道</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.014629109058573805</cell>
                            <cell role="data">255</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">鞍</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.01359646606620389</cell>
                            <cell role="data">237</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">青</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.013424358900808904</cell>
                            <cell role="data">234</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">黃</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.012047501577649016</cell>
                            <cell role="data">210</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">馳</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.011990132522517355</cell>
                            <cell role="data">209</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">驅</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.01187539441225403</cell>
                            <cell role="data">207</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>The second table lists frequently occurring phrases, with phrase weights and
                        counts:</p>
                    <table>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell role="label">Phrase</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Phrase Weight</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Count</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">車 馬</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.0615748963883955</cell>
                            <cell role="data">104</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">馬 蹄</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.04262877442273535</cell>
                            <cell role="data">72</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">走 馬</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.04085257548845471</cell>
                            <cell role="data">69</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">馬 嘶</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.04026050917702783</cell>
                            <cell role="data">68</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">驄 馬</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.03197158081705151</cell>
                            <cell role="data">54</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">騎 馬</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.028419182948490232</cell>
                            <cell role="data">48</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">鞍 馬</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.02427471876850207</cell>
                            <cell role="data">41</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">駟 馬</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.020130254588513915</cell>
                            <cell role="data">34</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">匹 馬</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.018354055654233273</cell>
                            <cell role="data">31</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">駿 馬</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.017761989342806393</cell>
                            <cell role="data">30</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">駑 駘</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.017169923031379514</cell>
                            <cell role="data">29</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">躞 蹀</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.013025458851391355</cell>
                            <cell role="data">22</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">匆 匆</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.012433392539964476</cell>
                            <cell role="data">21</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">驅 馬</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.011841326228537596</cell>
                            <cell role="data">20</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">騏 驥</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.010657193605683837</cell>
                            <cell role="data">18</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">羸 馬</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.010065127294256957</cell>
                            <cell role="data">17</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">車 騎</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.009473060982830076</cell>
                            <cell role="data">16</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">馬 鞭</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.0076968620485494375</cell>
                            <cell role="data">13</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">騏 驎</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.0076968620485494375</cell>
                            <cell role="data">13</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">白 馬</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.0076968620485494375</cell>
                            <cell role="data">13</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">嘶 馬</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.007104795737122558</cell>
                            <cell role="data">12</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>As can be seen, the TPR provides a clearer breakdown of the strength of each
                        word’s correlation to the topic. Each word is assigned a value that denotes
                        its topic weight, or the number of times that the word appears within
                        documents identified with this particular topic. For example, the
                        first–ranked character for Topic 0 is 馬
                            (horse), which is represented in the TPR as having a weighting of
                        0.1685 (rounded up) and a count of 2937, which means that it represents
                        16.85% of the 17,431 word occurrences assigned to topic 0 in the corpus
                        (this count is also provided in the TPR). In other words, in the entire
                        corpus, 馬 appears more than 2937 times, but
                        for 2937 of the instances in which it occurs, it is assigned to topic 0.
                        Most words will have a weighting value of &lt;0.001 in the TPR for a
                        specific topic, reflecting the default prior probability that any word in
                        the corpus vocabulary will appear in a topic at some infinitesimal level.
                        Words with this value in the topic–phrase report are considered to have
                        negligible weight within the modeled topic but are nevertheless still
                        represented. For some topics there may be a more even distribution of
                        strongly correlated words, while for others there may be a marked
                        differential between the first word and the next–strongest words.</p>
                    <p>The final <title rend="italic">MALLET</title> output file is the
                        document–topics report, which shows the strength of each topic within every
                        document. This is an extremely long report, consisting of the percentage
                        breakdowns of each of the 150 topics for every poem in the <title
                            rend="italic">QTS</title>. Rather than present the entire report, we
                        have excerpted part of the report for Poem 30_1 in the corpus, which is to
                        say, the first poem from Chapter 30, titled <title rend="quotes">On Han
                            Gaozu</title>
                        詠漢高祖. This is not an arbitrary
                        selection, as this is the point in the anthology where it begins to be
                        organized by individual poets in roughly chronological order, taking on a
                        literary historical logic. Moreover, this poem was composed by the late
                        Sui-early Tang figure Wang Gui 王珪 (570–639), who served under Tang Emperor
                        Taizong 唐太宗 (r. 626–49) and is not particularly remembered for his poetic
                        ability. As such, this poem represents an example of the <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#cohen1999">Great Unread</quote>, a literary work
                        that should have been forgotten except for its inclusion in the <title
                            rend="italic">QTS</title>.</p>
                    <p>Before turning to the report, it might be useful to be able to read the text
                        of the poem, which we have translated in full as follows:</p>
                    <lg>
                        <l>漢祖起豐沛， Han Gaozu arose from Feng Town in
                            Pei County,<note>Han Gaozu 漢高祖 (r. 202–195 BCE), born Liu Bang 劉邦
                                (256–195 BCE), was the founding emperor of the Han dynasty (202
                                BCE–220 CE).</note></l>
                        <l>乘運以躍鱗。 Riding fortune’s course with
                            high-leaping scales.<note>This same image is used in the first poem in
                                the <title rend="quotes" xml:lang="zh">Gufeng</title> 古風 (<title
                                    rend="quotes">Ancient Airs</title>) series by Li Bo 李白: <quote
                                    rend="inline">The gathered talents entrust themselves to [the
                                    Sage’s] peerless brilliance, / Riding fortune’s course, all are
                                    leaping scales</quote>
                                群才屬休明，乘運共躍鱗. See <ref
                                    target="#qu1980">Qu and Zhu 1980, 2.91</ref>; and <ref
                                    target="#qts1960"><title rend="italic">QTS</title> 1960,
                                    161.1670</ref>.</note></l>
                        <l>手奮三尺劍， In his hand he brandished a
                            three-foot sword,</l>
                        <l>西滅無道秦。 And to the west he destroyed the
                            lawless Qin.</l>
                        <l>十月五星聚， In the tenth month, the five
                            planets clustered,<note>This is an auspicious celestial event, the
                                appearance of the first five planets, each identified with one of
                                the Five Phase elements (water, metal, earth, fire, and wood), all
                                in one region of the sky.</note></l>
                        <l>七年四海賓。 In seven years, all in the four
                            seas were his guests.<note>That is to say, the people of the world all
                                become Han Gaozu’s subjects.</note></l>
                        <l>高抗威宇宙， Lofty and unyielding, he awed the
                            universe,</l>
                        <l>貴有天下人。 Exalted, he took charge of all
                            the world’s people.</l>
                        <l>憶昔與項王， I think back on how he
                            accompanied Xiang Yu,<note>Xiang Yu 項羽 (232–202 BCE) was a nobleman of
                                Chu who led the rebellion against the Qin dynasty (221–206 BCE) and
                                triumphed, in 207 BCE, with the support of Liu Bang. Xiang Yu then
                                founded the Western Chu, declaring himself king, and warred with Liu
                                Bang over the empire. Liu Bang would eventually triumph in the
                                battle at Gaixia, after which Xiang Yu committe suicide.</note></l>
                        <l>契闊時未伸。 Now long separated, that age
                            cannot be reached.</l>
                        <l>鴻門既薄蝕， Both at the Hongmen Feast he was
                            treated poorly,</l>
                        <l>滎陽亦蒙塵。 And at Xingyang, where he fled,
                            covered in dust. <note>This couplet refers to Xiang Yu’s plot to kill
                                Liu Bang, the future Han Gaozu, at a feast at Hongmen and later at
                                Xingyang. At Hongmen, Xiang Yu’s cousin Xiang Zhuang 項莊 was to
                                perform a sword dance and stab Gaozu, but Gaozu was protected by
                                Xiang Chan 項纏, uncle of Xiang Yu and Xiang Zhuang, who joined the
                                dance and blocked each attack. Afterwards, Gaozu’s forces were
                                surrounded at Xingyang (in modern-day Henan), and so he dressed up
                                women in armor, sending them out to surrender, while he himself fled
                                with a handful of men <ptr target="#sima1993" loc="30–33, 38–40"
                                />.</note></l>
                        <l>蟣虱生介胄， Lice are born in armor and
                            helmets,</l>
                        <l>將卒多苦辛。 Generals and soldiers endure much
                            suffering.</l>
                        <l>爪牙驅信越， As his claws and teeth: Han Xin
                            and Peng Yue forged ahead,</l>
                        <l>腹心謀張陳。 As his belly and heart: Zhang
                            Liang and Chen Ping laid plots.<note>Han Xin 韓信 (d. 196) and Peng Yue 彭越
                                (d. 196 BCE) were both military commanders under Liu Bang. Zhang
                                Liang 張良 (d. 186 BCE) and Chen Ping 陳平 (d. 178) were strategists who
                                served under Liu Bang.</note></l>
                        <l>赫赫西楚國， How glorious was Western Chu’s
                            kingdom,</l>
                        <l>化爲丘與榛。 Transformed now into mounds and
                                underbrush.<note> Western Chu (206–202 BCE) was the name of the
                                kingdom founded by Xiang Yu after the conquest of Qin.</note></l>
                    </lg>
                    <p>This is a fairly standard example of a <q>poem on history</q> (<term
                            xml:lang="zh">yongshi shi</term>
                        詠史詩), one that focuses on the founding emperor of
                        the Han dynasty. One might trace out the progression of the poem from its
                        broad-stroke portrait of the ruler’s rise to power to its focus on his war
                        with his great rival Xiang Yu and the eventual ruin of Xiang Yu’s Western
                        Chu. The poem evokes a lost age of heroes, of glorious victories, fabled
                        escapes, and tragic falls, bookending the triumphant founding of the Han
                        dynasty with the barren fate of the Western Chu.</p>
                    <p> However, a different approach to analyzing this poem can be found in <title
                            rend="italic">MALLET</title>’s document-topics report. We have quoted
                        only a portion of the lengthy report, stopping at the point where the
                        percentage falls below 1%:</p>
                    <p><quote rend="inline">1969 30_1, 30 0.10952380952380952 16 0.05952380952380953
                            139 0.05238095238095238 7 0.03809523809523809 135 0.03095238095238095
                            110 0.03095238095238095 32 0.03095238095238095 15 0.03095238095238095 49
                            0.02380952380952381 42 0.02380952380952381 125 0.016666666666666666 124
                            0.016666666666666666 122 0.016666666666666666 115 0.016666666666666666
                            109 0.016666666666666666 98 0.016666666666666666 92 0.016666666666666666
                            87 0.016666666666666666 83 0.016666666666666666 66 0.016666666666666666
                            36 0.016666666666666666 </quote></p>
                    <p>Following the two poem IDs (<q>1969</q>, meaning the 1969th poem of the
                        corpus; and <q>30_1</q>, referring to the document’s chapter number and its
                        poem number within the chapter), <title rend="italic">MALLET</title>
                        provides two pieces of information: the topic ID number and the percentage
                        of that topic within the poem. Included in the whole of the report are all
                        150 topics in descending order of strength (again, <title rend="italic"
                            >MALLET</title> assumes that all topics are represented in each
                        document, even if in statistically insignificant percentages). We can see
                        that, for this document, it is Topic 30 that ranks most highly, constituting
                        approximately 10.95% of the poem. Only the top twenty-one topics (topics
                        with values &gt;1%) are actually meaningful in this case, as most topics
                        belong to the long tail of statistical insignificance. Here are the top
                        topics (values are rounded up) in descending order of significance and with
                        our preliminary labels for the topics:</p>
                    <table>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell role="label">TopicID </cell>
                            <cell role="label">Percentage</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Topic (first 20 terms in rank order)</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Topic Label</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">30</cell>
                            <cell role="data">10.952%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">天 大 皇 四 帝 海 萬 太 功 夷 方 王 三 命 元 聖
                                    乾 業 宗 武
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">empire and sovereign power</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">16</cell>
                            <cell role="data">5.952%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">不 如 食 生 足 骨 口 死 飢 肉 眼 齒 腹 為 土 耳
                                    力 飲 可 破
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">mortality, eating and drinking</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">139</cell>
                            <cell role="data">5.238%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">塵 人 春 新 身 親 勤 鄰 殷 頻 津 為 巾 輪 濱 四
                                    辰 辛 貧 巡
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">tsyen 真 <term>rhyme category</term></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">7</cell>
                            <cell role="data">3.81%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">我 不 為 此 言 爾 者 何 有 亦 如 生 人 與 得 苦
                                    無 所 願 令
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">pronouns and particles</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">135</cell>
                            <cell role="data">3.095%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">將 軍 兵 戰 旗 馬 旌 功 劍 弓 戎 營 騎 鼓 戈 羽
                                    角 虜 射 箭
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">military, armies</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">110</cell>
                            <cell role="data">3.095%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">未 自 慚 知 豈 雖 薄 終 非 已 顧 愧 負 辭 寧 猶
                                    難 甘 心 敢
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">shame, regret</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">32</cell>
                            <cell role="data">3.095%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">十 三 年 二 五 四 六 七 一 八 百 千 九 月 今 歲
                                    前 載 老 第
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">numbers, calendrical time</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">15</cell>
                            <cell role="data">3.095%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">王 漢 秦 國 宮 吳 陵 帝 楚 武 臺 陽 長 子 安 亡
                                    苑 作 蘇 梁
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">Han and pre-Han kingdoms</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">49</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2.381%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">南 北 東 西 山 風 望 國 城 日 向 斗 河 闕 起 海
                                    長 直 復 從
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">territorial space, cardinal directions</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">42</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2.381%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">庭 中 滿 洞 月 山 風 樹 裏 長 高 入 空 雲 水 煙
                                    起 日 上 陽
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">courtyard / landscape scene?</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">125</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.667%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">門 深 開 日 閉 高 戶 滿 入 客 出 堂 朱 外 巷 院
                                    掩 牆 庭 靜
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">gates, halls, and built spaces</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">124</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.667%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">所 言 子 豈 道 志 異 為 良 非 懷 自 徒 昔 貞 乃
                                    可 賢 常 義
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">particles / will and righteousness?</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">122</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.667%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">魚 水 釣 下 垂 鳥 池 上 時 小 鱗 竿 驚 得 網 有
                                    無 欲 避 坐
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">fisherman, fishing</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">115</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.667%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">劍 士 氣 生 平 感 侯 壯 橫 長 縱 交 雄 將 子 英
                                    安 報 燕 節
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">heroes, men of valor</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">109</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.667%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">江 湘 南 楚 水 客 舟 遠 雲 孤 秋 山 瀟 雁 陽 浦
                                    湖 去 渚 夢
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">southern (Chu) riverscapes</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">98</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.667%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">神 禮 德 惟 肅 樂 靈 降 薦 既 誠 載 以 明 昭 永
                                    斯 福 陳 備
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">ritual and ceremony</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">92</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.667%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">龍 雷 騰 神 虎 如 驚 蛟 若 蛇 電 橫 當 鼓 倒 大
                                    氣 怪 勢 天
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">dragons, tigers, images of divine power</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">87</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.667%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">然 化 物 無 浩 天 心 異 造 有 形 方 道 可 忽 中
                                    變 至 窮 言
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">divine creation and transformation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">83</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.667%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">古 草 荒 人 空 在 野 木 平 跡 遺 地 舊 原 猶 城
                                    餘 有 無 蕪
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">desolate wilderness</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">66</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.667%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">遊 留 休 頭 秋 侯 州 收 憂 求 愁 不 丘 浮 酬 裘
                                    子 諸 牛 羞
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">ghou 尤 <term>rhyme category</term></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">36</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.667%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">天 下 太 地 子 中 一 上 海 出 道 入 平 黃 九 四
                                    守 白 大 成
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">empire and territory</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>From this, we might say that <title rend="quotes">On Han Gaozu</title> is a
                        document constructed out of assorted topics that might be labeled
                            <q>empire and sovereign power</q>, <q>mortality, eating and
                            drinking</q>,
                        <q>tsyen
                        真 <term>rhyme category</term></q>,<note>Classical Chinese rhymes
                            were codified as rhyme-books (sometimes spelled as <q>rimebooks</q>) in
                            the medieval period, with rhyming words categorized under header-words
                            that represented the entire rhyme category. We have used David Prager
                            Branner’s reconstructed medieval Chinese transcription in representing
                            the rhyme category header-words <ptr target="#branner1999"/> and made
                            use of his online rhyme database Yintong 音通, which can be accessed
                                here: <ref target="http://yintong.info/yintong/public/index.php"
                                >http://yintong.info/yintong/public/index.php</ref>.</note>
                        <q>pronouns and particles</q>, <q>military, armies</q>,
                            <q>shame, regret</q>, <q>numbers, calendrical time</q>,
                            <q>Han and pre-Han kingdoms</q>, <q>territorial space, cardinal
                            directions</q>, and the ambiguous <q>courtyard / landscape
                            scene</q>. Some of these are topics with a strong semantic identity
                        (for example, both <q>empire</q> topics), though some are topics that
                        represent syntactic and grammatical functions (<q>pronouns and
                            particles</q>) and formal characteristics of the poem (<q>tsyen
                        真 <term>rhyme category</term></q>). We also find the presence of
                        topics that are not easy to label, such as the unclear Topic 42
                            (<q>courtyard / landscape scene?</q>), and topics that are
                        inexplicably present, such as Topic 66 (<q>ghou
                        尤 <term>rhyme category</term></q>), which is a second rhyme
                        category topic not otherwise evidenced in the poem. It is important to keep
                        in mind that our interpretive perplexity is the result of differences
                        between how humans and how <title rend="italic">MALLET</title> reads the
                        corpus, and that <title rend="italic">MALLET</title>’s identification of
                        topics for documents are not based on semantic reasoning but on the
                        distribution of vocabularies. At times human and machine readings might
                        converge, leading to deeper insight into the corpus, but at other times, we
                        are reminded of our methodological — and ontological — differences.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>V. Using Topics to Think through Literary History</head>
                    <p>Up until his point, the application of topic modeling to the <title
                            rend="italic">QTS</title> has largely been to reframe the question of
                        representing and accessing the poetic corpus, and where we have provided an
                        analytical perspective, it has focused on understanding what a topic model
                        represents in relation to the poetic documents. Here, we propose that topic
                        modeling may help us to think through the problem of selection criteria in
                        constructing a literary historical account, enabling one to navigate the
                        vast unread of Tang poetry, selecting poems that do not reflect the
                        individual critic’s own biases and preferences, or those preferences
                        predetermined by anthological training sets and other unknowable selection
                        processes over the course of history. The resulting literary historical
                        narrative would be semi-supervised, more strongly dependent upon human
                        reading and interpretation at certain points in the process, and more
                        strongly dependent upon machine reading at others. This would not be the
                        utopian fantasy of posthuman reading, where machine objectivity replaces
                        human subjectivity, but a shifting balance between a machine-assisted
                        perspective and a traditional <q>analog</q> perspective. Part of this
                        approach, however, is a serious attempt to engage the machine’s perspective,
                        to try to understand how the machine sees the collection of documents, and
                        to translate this into human terms. To this end, we rely on the
                        Jensen-Shannon divergence measure <ptr target="#lin1991"/>, which quantifies
                        the difference between any (finite) number of probability
                            distributions.<note>This measure takes its name from Jensen’s inequality
                            (devised by Johan L. W. V. Jensen; <ref target="#jensen1906">see Jensen
                                1906</ref>, and <ref target="#needham1993">Needham 1993</ref>) and
                            the Shannon entropy (formulated by Claude E Shannon; <ref
                                target="#shannon1948">see Shannon 1948</ref>, and <ref
                                target="#shannon1949">Shannon and Weaver 1949</ref>).</note> In our
                        case, these distributions are the probabilities of topics constituting
                        documents, as in <title rend="italic">MALLET</title>’s document-topics
                        report described above. Although this measure is formulated in terms of
                            <q>divergence</q>, it allows us to explore document similarity, much
                        like vector similarity measures, and to perform unsupervised information
                        retrieval within a large textual corpus.<note>There are other ways to
                            calculate document similarity, including vector similarity measures such
                            as cosine similarity <ref target="#salton1983" loc="201–204">(cf. Salton
                                and McGill 1983, 201–4)</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Although the supervised selection of <title rend="quotes">On Han
                            Gaozu</title> (Poem 30_1) as a starting point may have been somewhat
                        arbitrary, chosen because of its position as the first poem in the main
                        section of the <title rend="italic">QTS</title> (the chronological-by-author
                        section that runs from Chapter 30 to 731), its literary obscurity makes it a
                        useful example of Tang poetry’s Great Unread. We could imagine, however,
                        that we have arrived at this poem after navigating a topic-based index of
                        the corpus and now seek to find topically similar poems. Using <title
                            rend="quotes">On Han Gaozu</title> as our target document, the top five
                        most similar documents according to the Jensen-Shannon divergences of their
                        topic distributions are identified as follows:</p>
                    <table>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell role="label">Document ID</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Poem Title and Author</cell>
                            <cell role="label">English Translation</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Similarity Score</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">1969 (30_1)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">《詠漢高祖》王珪</cell>
                            <cell role="data"><title rend="quotes">On Han Gaozu</title> by Wang
                                Gui</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">573 (13_68)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">《享太廟樂章。象德舞》 段文昌 </cell>
                            <cell role="data"><title rend="quotes">Hymns for the Offering to the
                                    Ancestral Temple: Dance for Manifesting Virtue</title> by Duan
                                Wenchang </cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.8822478125653975</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">38884 (767_29)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">《苻堅投棰》 孫元晏 </cell>
                            <cell role="data"><title rend="quotes">Fu Jian Casts His Whip</title> by
                                Sun Yuan’an</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.8787439416072281</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">2751 (52_30)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">《過函谷關》 宋之問 </cell>
                            <cell role="data"><title rend="quotes">Visiting Hangu Pass</title> by
                                Song Zhiwen</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.877820744700559</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">37314 (729_66)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">《二廢帝》 周曇 </cell>
                            <cell role="data"><title rend="quotes">On the Two Deposed
                                    Emperors</title> by Zhou Tan</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.8722429641594189</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">2009 (31_26)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">《梁郊祀樂章。慶休》 ?</cell>
                            <cell role="data"><title rend="quotes">Hymns for the Liang Suburban
                                    Sacrifice: Jubilation</title> by unknown author</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.872006203906182</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>The table is mostly self-explanatory, but it is worth quickly pointing out
                        that because <title rend="quotes">On Han Gaozu</title> is the benchmark for
                        the similarity measure scores, it has a score of 1.0, meaning that it is
                        identical with itself, and that the more similar a document is to <title
                            rend="quotes">On Han Gaozu</title>, the higher its fractional similarity
                        score.</p>
                    <p> One striking aspect of the divergence measure is how <title rend="quotes">On
                            Han Gaozu</title>, traditionally understood as a poem on
                            history, correlates strongly to poems originating from ritual and
                        sacrificial occasions. The top document retrieved in this manner is Poem
                        13_68, <title rend="quotes">Hymns for the Offering to the Ancestral Temple:
                            Dance for Manifesting Virtue</title>
                        享太廟樂章：象德舞, by the mid-/late Tang
                        poet and official Duan Wenchang 段文昌 (773–835):</p>
                    <cit><quote rend="block" source="#qts1960">
                            <lg>
                                <l>肅肅清廟 How magnificent and solemn,
                                    the ancestral temple,</l>
                                <l>登顯至德 Radiating forth its
                                    perfected virtue!</l>
                                <l>澤周八荒 Your grace covered the
                                    eight expanses,</l>
                                <l>兵定四極 Your armies settled the
                                    four directions.</l>
                                <l>生物咸遂 Living creatures all
                                    followed suit,</l>
                                <l>群盜滅息 All thieving ceased and
                                    came to an end.</l>
                                <l>明聖欽承 The Enlightened Sage
                                    reverently has inherited this,</l>
                                <l>子孫千億 Transmitting it to
                                    descendants for countless generations.</l>
                            </lg></quote>
                        <ptr target="#qts1960" loc="13.133"/></cit>
                    <p>This hymn belongs to the family of ritual songs categorized as <title
                            rend="quotes">Lyrics for the Suburban Altars and Ancestral
                            Temple</title>
                        郊廟歌辭, and according to the <title
                            rend="italic" xml:lang="zh">Jiu Tang shu</title>
                        舊唐書 (Old history of the Tang
                        dynasty), it was performed at the tomb of Tang Emperor Xianzong 唐憲宗 (r.
                        805–20) <ptr target="#liu1986" loc="31.1140"/>
                        (for background on this form, see <ref target="#jensen2012">Kevin Jensen
                            2012</ref>). The hymn uses the archaizing tetrasyllabic form, rather
                        than the pentasyllabic (or heptasyllabic) form used throughout most Tang
                        verse; this is common in other poems composed for ritual or formal court
                            occasions.<note>Tetrasyllabic verse is generally associated with the
                                <title rend="italic">Classic of Poetry</title> (<title rend="italic"
                                xml:lang="zh">Shijing</title> 詩經), the oldest extant collection of
                            poetry in China and one of the Confucian Classics. Although poets
                            continued to compose in tetrasyllabic form throughout the Han dynasty
                            and the Period of Division (220–589 CE), by the Tang dynasty, most poets
                            would compose in pentasyllabic or heptasyllabic meter, reserving the
                            tetrasyllabic form mainly for ritual genres, archaizing modes, and
                            certain formal occasions <ptr target="#raft2007"/>.</note> The lyrics
                        themselves are fairly straightforward and do not contain much of aesthetic
                        interest, mainly serving to translate the ritual moment into linguistic
                        expression.</p>
                    <p> On the face of it, Duan Wenchang’s poem would seem to share little in common
                        with Wang Gui’s poem, given the differences in poetic subgenre and occasion.
                        However, the DTR (document-topics report) for <title rend="quotes">Hymns for
                            the Offering to the Ancestral Temple: Dance for Manifesting
                            Virtue</title> reveals a similar topical mixture:</p>
                    <table>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell role="label">TopicID</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Percentage</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Topic (first 20 terms in rank order)</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Topic Label</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">30</cell>
                            <cell role="data">10.163%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">天 大 皇 四 帝 海 萬 太 功 夷 方 王 三 命 元 聖
                                    乾 業 宗 武
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">empire and sovereign power</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">87</cell>
                            <cell role="data">5.285%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">然 化 物 無 浩 天 心 異 造 有 形 方 道 可 忽 中
                                    變 至 窮 言
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">divine creation and transformation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">98</cell>
                            <cell role="data">4.065%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">神 禮 德 惟 肅 樂 靈 降 薦 既 誠 載 以 明 昭 永
                                    斯 福 陳 備
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">ritual and ceremony</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">32</cell>
                            <cell role="data">2.846%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">十 三 年 二 五 四 六 七 一 八 百 千 九 月 今 歲
                                    前 載 老 第
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">numbers, calendrical time</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">149</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.626%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">忘 隱 清 心 閒 興 林 靜 勝 自 外 幽 景 愛 機 塵
                                    坐 情 對 境
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">reclusion</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">131</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.626%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">朝 恩 主 重 詔 拜 承 明 從 臣 榮 紫 賜 門 闕 寵
                                    官 命 列 禁
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">imperial court</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">126</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.626%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">多 過 更 深 遠 近 宜 入 偏 地 好 和 處 隨 經 移
                                    數 重 客 高
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">visiting someone</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">113</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.626%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">惡 死 禍 者 敢 罪 危 狼 殺 受 非 防 虎 力 反 利
                                    失 亂 命 傷
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">disaster</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">111</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.626%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">應 出 隨 朝 從 還 臨 先 行 分 迎 暫 逐 近 節 遠
                                    待 將 旌 方
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">welcoming / serving?</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">109</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.626%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">江 湘 南 楚 水 客 舟 遠 雲 孤 秋 山 瀟 雁 陽 浦
                                    湖 去 渚 夢
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">southern (Chu) riverscapes</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">108</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.626%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">復 念 歲 已 懷 所 窮 忽 歎 何 良 憂 未 當 豈 夕
                                    役 終 思 歡
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">remembering, mourning</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">83</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.626%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">古 草 荒 人 空 在 野 木 平 跡 遺 地 舊 原 猶 城
                                    餘 有 無 蕪
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">desolate wilderness</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">72</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.626%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">山 石 松 巖 溪 泉 林 幽 雲 鳥 谷 蘿 深 澗 隱 青
                                    徑 野 下 竹
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">mountain scene</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">40</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.626%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">天 人 地 上 不 生 下 此 長 一 道 得 日 為 間 何
                                    高 意 擾 白
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">Heaven and Earth</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">36</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.626%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">天 下 太 地 子 中 一 上 海 出 道 入 平 黃 九 四
                                    守 白 大 成
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">empire and territory</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">15</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1.626%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">王 漢 秦 國 宮 吳 陵 帝 楚 武 臺 陽 長 子 安 亡
                                    苑 作 蘇 梁
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="data">Han and pre-Han kingdoms</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>The fact that <title rend="quotes">On Han Gaozu</title> and <title
                            rend="quotes">Hymns for the Offering to the Ancestral Temple: Dance for
                            Manifesting Virtue</title> share Topic 30 (<q>empire and sovereign
                            power</q>) as their highest ranking topic is a large factor in the high
                        similarity score between the two documents. However, equally important is
                        how the two documents rank Topics 32 (<q>numbers, calendrical time</q>), 98
                            (<q>ritual and ceremony</q>), 87 (<q>divine creation and
                            transformation</q>), 109 (<q>southern [Chu] riverscapes</q>), 15 (<q>Han
                            and pre-Han kingdoms</q>), 83 (<q>desolate wilderness</q>), and 36
                            (<q>empire and territory</q>). There are clear thematic similarities
                        here, given that both poems treat the foundings of empire, though no
                        traditional literary history would correlate these two poems, as they would
                        be classified differently based on their metrical forms and subgenres: one a
                        pentasyllabic poem on history and the other a tetrasyllabic
                            ritual poem.</p>
                    <p>Moreover, we can see how a comparison of document topic rankings may help us
                        to understand what similarity and divergence means on a cultural and
                        semantic level. If <title rend="quotes">On Han Gaozu</title> and <title
                            rend="quotes">Hymns for the Offering to the Ancestral Temple</title>
                        both rank Topic 30 (<q>empire and sovereign power</q>) first in terms of
                        topic percentage, they diverge in their second highest ranked topic, which
                        is Topic 16 (<q>mortality, eating and drinking</q>) for <title rend="quotes"
                            >On Han Gaozu</title> and Topic 87 (<q>divine creation and
                            transformation</q>) for <title rend="quotes">Hymns for the Offering to
                            the Ancestral Temple</title>. This suggests that where a poem on history
                        diverges from a ritual poem that also treats historical events is in the
                        combination of secondary vocabularies. The topic we have labeled
                            <q>mortality, eating and drinking</q> evokes subjective experience in a
                        way that connects the lament on historical memory to the individual poet,
                        and this would not be fitting for a ritual poem that is articulated at the
                        higher register of <q>divine creation and transformation</q>.</p>
                    <p>Finally, related to this, we can also address the problem of topics that
                            <title rend="italic">MALLET</title> identifies in a particular document
                        but that are not clearly evident to the human reader. For example, consider
                        Topic 122 (<q>fishermen, fishing</q>), which ranks highly in <title
                            rend="quotes">On Han Gaozu</title> and the presence of Topic 149
                            (<q>reclusion</q>), which ranks highly in <title rend="quotes">Hymns for
                            the Offering to the Ancestral Temple</title>. The two documents diverge
                        on these topics (among others, of course), but what is interesting is that
                        neither topic is particularly evident in the documents in which they are
                        highly ranked. The question becomes, why does <title rend="italic"
                            >MALLET</title> consider these <q>ghost topics</q> important for their
                        respective documents when their vocabularies are not clearly invoked by
                        their documents? We hypothesize that ghost topics are identified by the
                        machine reader because they are contiguous to topics that are clearly
                        evidenced in the documents, and that such identifications speak to latent
                        semantic networks to which these documents can be connected.<note>This also
                            provides a justification for overshooting the value of n in the initial
                            assignment of the number of topics for <title rend="italic"
                                >MALLET</title>. If one sets the number of topics so high that
                                <title rend="italic">MALLET</title> begins finding topics that are
                            not noticeably present in specific documents, these extra topics may
                            still be meaningful as semantic ghosts of the topics that are more
                            evident in the corpus. Lowering the value of n most likely would
                            eventually banish these ghosts.</note> That is to say, if <title
                            rend="quotes">On Han Gaozu</title> says nothing about fishermen or
                        fishing (a common trope for the wisdom of humble folk), it nevertheless is
                        comprised of a number of vocabulary sets that are adjacent to the topic of
                        fishermen in some way, from the <q>southern (Chu) riverscapes</q> of Topic
                        122 to the <q>heroes, men of valor</q> of Topic 115, implying that
                            <q>fishermen, fishing</q> should be located within the semantic networks
                        of these probabilistic distributions. Likewise, there is nothing about
                            <q>reclusion</q> in <title rend="quotes">Hymns for the Offering to the
                            Ancestral Temple</title>, though the highly ranked cluster of topics
                        that emphasize imperial court ritual, such as Topic 87 (<q>divine creation
                            and transformation</q>), Topic 98 (<q>ritual and ceremony</q>), and
                        Topic 131 (<q>imperial court</q>), create a space for the recluse, who is
                        often figured in diametric opposition to the courtier, as the obverse face
                        of the same sociopolitical coin.</p>
                    <p>To conclude: if we think about poetry not in terms of subgenres or standard
                        metrical forms, but rather in terms of constitutive vocabularies, it becomes
                        clear that there is a shared set of terms that crosses different poetic
                        modes, creating hidden textual communities that would not usually be noticed
                        when reading along traditional throughlines. The detection of hidden or
                        unremarked communities of poems is not in itself literary history, but it
                        lays a new evidentiary foundation for how literary history might be
                        imagined. Instead of narrating the development of poetic style or genre
                        based upon the chronological progression of authors, one might take a
                        radically agnostic thematic approach, one that treats literary compositions
                        as <q>bags of words</q> and seeks out the commonalities of vocabulary across
                        these bags, using topics to dictate the selection of documents for argument
                        and analysis. Such an approach might not answer the impossible question of
                        map and territory — of data completeness and selectivity — that haunts
                        narrative historical representation, but it would allow pathways into the
                        true unconscious of literary history, the Great Unread that contemporary
                        databases of digitized corpora are beginning to resurrect and make
                        legible.</p>
                    <p>Here, we reaffirm that human reading on its own cannot make sense of this
                        quantity of data, and machinic reading lacks the capacity to translate
                        patterns into meaningful arguments. It is only a conjoining and interweaving
                        of machinic and human perspectives that make it possible to read a
                        collection on the scale of the <title rend="italic">QTS</title>; it is only
                        through reading the collection as a whole that one may arrive at a
                        comprehensive model of its contents; and it is by engaging with a
                        comprehensive model that literary history may find its standards for the
                        necessary reductions of data that make its narratives possible.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgements">
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>We would like to thank Timothy R. Tangherlini for his
                advice throughout, as well as Evan Nicoll-Johnson, Yunshuang Zhang, and Ruichuan Wu
                for their support during the data preparation phase of the project. We are also
                grateful to the former UCLA Center for Digital Humanities (now HumTech) for
                providing a meeting space and resources.</p></div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="allen2019" label="Allen et al. 2019">Allen, Colin, Hongliang Luo,
                    Jaimie Murdock, Jianghuai Pu, Xiaohong Wang, Yanjie Zhai, and Kun Zhao. 2017.
                        <title rend="quotes">Topic Modeling the Hàn diǎn Ancient Classics</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Journal of Cultural Analytics</title> (2017). <ref
                        target="http://culturalanalytics.org/2017/10/topic-modeling-the-han-dian-ancient-classics-%E6%B1%89%E5%85%B8%E5%8F%A4%E7%B1%8D/"
                        >http://doi.org/10.22148/16.016</ref>. Accessed September 5, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="allen1992" label="Allen 1992">Allen, Joseph R. <title rend="italic">In
                        the Voice of Others: Chinese Music Bureau Poetry</title>. Ann Arbor: Center
                    for Chinese Studies, The University of Michigan (1992).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blair2011" label="Blair 2011">Blair, Ann. <title rend="italic">Too
                        Much to Know: Managing Scholarly Information before the Modern Age</title>.
                    New Haven: Yale University Press (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blei2012" label="Blei 2012">Blei, David. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Probabilistic Topic Models</title>. <title rend="italic">Communications of
                        the ACM</title> 55.4 (2012): 77–84.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blei2003" label="Blei et al. 2003">Blei, David, Andrew Y. Ng, and
                    Michael I. Jordan. <title rend="quotes">Latent Dirichlet Allocation</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Journal of Machine Learning Research</title> 3 (2003):
                    993–1022.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bode2017" label="Bode 2017">Bode, Katherine. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Equivalence of <term>Close</term> and <term>Distant</term> Reading, or,
                        Toward a New Object for Data-Rich Literary History</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Modern Language Notes</title> 78.1 (2017): 77–106.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="branner1999" label="Branner 1999">Branner, David Prager. <title
                        rend="quotes">A Neutral Transcription System for Teaching Medieval
                        Chinese</title>. <title rend="italic">T’ang Studies</title> 17 (1999):
                    1–169.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="branner2004" label="Branner and Weng 2004">Branner, David Prager and
                    Yi Weng. <title rend="italic">Yintong: Chinese Phonological Database</title>
                    音通：聲韻學數據庫. 2004-9.<ref
                        target="http://yintong.info/yintong/public/index.php"
                        >http://yintong.info/yintong/public/index.php</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chen1992" label="Chen 1992">Chen, Shangjun 陳尚君, ed. <title
                        rend="italic">Quan Tang shi bubian</title>
                    全唐詩補編 (Supplement to the <title
                        rend="italic">Complete Tang Poems</title>). 3 vols. Beijing: Zhonghua shuju
                    (1992).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cohen1999" label="Cohen 1999">Cohen, Margaret. <title rend="italic"
                        >The Sentimental Education of the Novel</title>. Princeton: Princeton
                    University Press (1999).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drège2007" label="Drège 2007">Drège, Jean-Pierre. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Des ouvrages classés par catégories: les encyclopédies chinoises</title>.
                    In <title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Qu’était-ce qu’écrire une encyclopédie en
                        Chine? / What Did It Mean to Write an Encyclopedia in China?</title>, edited
                    by Florence Establet-Bretelle and Karine Chemla, 19–38. <title rend="italic"
                        xml:lang="fr">Extrême-Orient, Extrême-Occident</title>, hors série
                    (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2011" label="Drucker 2011">Drucker, Johanna. <title
                        rend="quotes">Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 5.1 (2011). <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html</ref>.
                    Accessed September 10, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="flanders2016" label="Flanders and Jannidis 2016">Flanders, Julia and
                    Fotis Jannidis. <title rend="quotes">Data Modeling</title>. In <title
                        rend="italic">A New Companion to the Digital Humanities</title>, edited by
                    Susan Scriebman, Ray Siemens, and John Unsworth, 229–37. Chichester, UK: John
                    Wiley &amp; Sons (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="geoghegan2011" label="Geoghegan 2011">Geoghegan, Bernard Dionysius.
                        <title rend="quotes">From Information Theory to French Theory: Jakobson,
                        Lévi-Strauss, and the Cybernetic Apparatus</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Critical Inquiry</title> 38 (2011): 96–126.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hayles2010" label="Hayles 2010">Hayles, N. Katherine. <title
                        rend="quotes">How We Read: Close, Hyper, Machine</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">ADE Bulletin</title> 150 (2010): 62–79.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hickman2012" label="Hickman and McIntyre 2012">Hickman, Miranda B. and
                    John D. McIntyre, eds. <title rend="italic">Rereading the New Criticism</title>.
                    Columbus: Ohio University Press (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hu2003" label="Hu 2003">Hu, Zhenheng 胡震亨 (1569–ca. 1644), <title
                        rend="italic" xml:lang="zh">Tangyin tongqian</title>
                    唐音統籤 (Assembled documents of Tang
                    tones). 9 vols. Shanghai: Shanghai guji chubanshe (2003).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="huang2013" label="Huang 2013">Huang, Shuanfan Huang. <title
                        rend="italic">Chinese Grammar at Work</title>. Amsterdam: John Benjamins
                    Publishing Company (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jensen1906" label="Jensen 1906">Jensen, J. L. W. V. <title
                        rend="quotes" xml:lang="fr">Sur les fonctions convexes et les inégalités
                        entres les valeurs moyennes</title>. <title rend="italic">Acta
                        Mathematica</title> 30 (1906): 175–93.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jensen2012" label="Jensen 2012">Jensen, Kevin A. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Wei-Jin Sacrificial Ballets: Reform versus Conservation</title>. Ph.D.
                    diss., University of Washington (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jockers2013" label="Jockers 2013">Jockers, Matthew L. <title
                        rend="italic">Macroanalysis: Digital Methods &amp; Literary History</title>.
                    Urbana: University of Illinois Press (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lin1991" label="Lin 1991">Lin, Jianhua. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Divergence Measures Based on the Shannon Entropy</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title> 37.1 (1991):
                    145–51.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2018" label="Liu et al. 2018">Liu, Chao-Lin, Thomas J. Mazanec, and
                    Jeffrey R. Tharsen.. <title rend="quotes">Exploring Chinese Poetry with Digital
                        Assistance: Examples from Linguistic, Literary, and Historical
                        Viewpoints</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Chinese Literature and
                        Culture</title> 5.2 (2018): 276–321.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2010" label="Liu 2010">Liu, Lydia. <title rend="italic">The
                        Freudian Robot: Digital Media and the Future of the Unconscious</title>.
                    Chicago: University of Chicago Press (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu1986" label="Liu 1986">Liu, Xu 劉煦 (887–947), <title rend="italic"
                        xml:lang="zh">Jiu Tang shu</title>
                    舊唐書 (Old history of the Tang). 16
                    vols. Beijing: Zhonghua shuju (1986).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="long2016" label="Long So 2016">Long, Hoyt and Richard Jean So. <title
                        rend="quotes">Literary Pattern Recognition: Modernism between Close Reading
                        and Machine Learning</title>. <title rend="italic">Critical Inquiry</title>
                    42 (2016): 235–67.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mccallum2002" label="McCallum 2002">McCallum, Andrew Kachites. <title
                        rend="italic"><title rend="italic">MALLET</title>: A Machine Learning for
                        Language Toolkit</title>. 2002. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://mallet.cs.umass.edu/index.php"
                        >http://mallet.cs.umass.edu/index.php</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="meeks2012" label="Meeks 2012">Meeks, Elijah and Scott B. Weingart,
                    eds. Special issue, <title rend="quotes">The Digital Humanities Contribution to
                        Topic Modeling</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital
                        Humanities</title> 2.1 (2012). Available at: <ref
                        target="http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-1/dh-contribution-to-topic-modeling/"
                        >http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-1/dh-contribution-to-topic-modeling/</ref>.
                    Accessed January 9, 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moretti2000a" label="Moretti 2000a">Moretti, Franco. <title
                        rend="quotes">Conjectures on World Literature</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >New Left Review</title> 1 (2000a): 54–68.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moretti2000b" label="Moretti 2000b"> — . <title rend="quotes">The
                        Slaughterhouse of Literature</title>. <title rend="italic">MLQ: Modern
                        Language Quarterly</title> 61, no. 1 (2000b): 207–27.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="needham1993" label="Needham 1993">Needham, Tristan. <title
                        rend="quotes">A Visual Explanation of Jensen’s Inequality</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">The American Mathematical Quarterly</title> 100.8 (1993):
                    768–71.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nichols2018" label="Nichols et al. 2018">Nichols, Ryan, Edward
                    Slingerland, Kristoffer Nielbo, and Uffe Bergeton. <title rend="quotes">Modeling
                        the Contested Relationship between Analects, Mencius, and Xunzi: Preliminary
                        Evidence from a Machine-Learning Approach</title>. <title rend="italic">The
                        Journal of Asian Studies</title> 77.1 (2018): 19–57. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0021911817000973"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1017/S0021911817000973</ref>. Accessed September 5,
                    2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="north2013" label="North 2013">North, Joseph. <title rend="quotes"
                        >What’s <term>New Critical</term> about <term>Close Reading</term>? I.A.
                        Richards and His New Critical Reception</title>. <title rend="italic">New
                        Literary History</title> 44, no. 1 (2013): 141–57.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="owen1977" label="Owen 1977">Owen, Stephen. <title rend="italic">The
                        Poetry of the Early T’ang</title>. New Haven: Yale University (1977).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="owen1981" label="Owen 1981"> — . <title rend="italic">The Great Age of
                        Chinese Poetry: The High T’ang</title>. New Haven: Yale University
                    (1981).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="owen2006a" label="Owen 2006a"> — . <title rend="italic">The Late Tang:
                        Chinese Poetry of the Mid-Ninth Century (827–860)</title>. Cambridge:
                    Harvard University Asia Center (2006a).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="owen2006b" label="Owen 2006b"> — . <title rend="italic">The Making of
                        Early Chinese Classical Poetry</title>. Cambridge: Harvard University Asia
                    Center (2006b).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="perkins1992" label="Perkins 1992">Perkins, David. <title rend="italic"
                        >Is Literary History Possible?</title> Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins
                    University Press (1992).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piper2015" label="Piper 2015">Piper, Andrew. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Novel Devotions: Conversional Reading, Computational Modeling, and the
                        Modern Novel</title>. <title rend="italic">New Literary History</title> 46
                    (2015): 63–98.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piper2018" label="Piper 2018"> — . <title rend="italic">Enumerations:
                        Data and Literary Study</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press
                    (2018).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="qian1979" label="Qian and Ji 1979">Qian, Qianyi 錢謙益 (1582–1664)
                    and Ji Zhenyi 季振宜 (b. 1630), comps. <title rend="italic" xml:lang="zh">Quan Tang
                        shi gaoben</title>
                    全唐詩稿本 (Draft edition of the complete
                    Tang poems). Edited by Qu Wanli 屈萬里 and Liu Zhaoyou 劉兆祐. 71 vols. Taipei:
                    Lianjing chuban shiye gongsi (1979).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="qian2000" label="Qian 2000">Qian, Zhonglian 錢仲聯, gen. ed., et al.
                        <title rend="italic" xml:lang="zh">Zhongguo wenxue dacidian</title>
                    中國文學大辭典 (Great dictionary of Chinese
                    literature). 2 vols. Shanghai: Shanghai guji chubanshe (2000).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="qu1980" label="Qu and Jincheng 1980">Qu, Tuiyuan 瞿蛻圓 and Zhu Jincheng
                    朱金城, eds. <title rend="italic" xml:lang="zh">Li Bai ji jiaozhu</title>
                    李白集校注 (Annotated edition of Li Bai’s
                    literary collection). 4 vols. Shanghai: Shanghai guji chubanshe (1980).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="qts1960" label="QTS 1960"><title rend="italic">Quan Tang shi</title>
                    全唐詩 (Complete Tang poems). 25 vols.
                    Beijing: Zhonghua shuju (1960).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="raft2007" label="Raft 2007">Raft, Zebulon David. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Four-syllable Verse in Medieval China</title>. Ph.D. diss., Harvard
                    University (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay2011" label="Ramsay 2011">Ramsay, Stephen. <title rend="italic"
                        >Reading Machines: Toward an Algorithmic Criticism</title>. Urbana:
                    University of Illinois Press (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ren2014" label="Ren 2014">Ren, Zhongmin 任中敏, ed. <title rend="italic"
                        xml:lang="zh">Dunhuang geci zongpian</title>
                    敦煌歌辭總編 (Complete edition of Dunhuang
                    songs and lyrics). 3 vols. Nanjing: Fenghuang chubanshe (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="riddell2012" label="Riddell 2012">Riddell, Allen B. <title
                        rend="quotes">A Simple Topic Model (Mixture of Unigrams)</title>. July 22,
                    2012. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.ariddell.org/simple-topic-model.html"
                        >https://www.ariddell.org/simple-topic-model.html</ref>. Accessed January 9,
                    2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rosenberg2013" label="Rosenberg 2013">Rosenberg, Daniel. <title
                        rend="quotes">Data before the Fact</title>. In <title rend="italic">“Raw
                        Data” Is an Oxymoron</title>, edited by Lisa Gitelman, 15–40. Cambridge: MIT
                    Press (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rosenthal2017" label="Rosenthal 2017">Rosenthal, Jesse. <title
                        rend="quotes">Introduction: Narrative against Data</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Genre</title> 50.1 (2017): 1–18.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="salton1983" label="Salton and McGill 1983">Salton, Gerard and Michael
                    J. McGill. <title rend="italic">Introduction to Modern Information
                        Retrieval</title>. New York: McGraw-Hill Book Company (1983).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shannon1948" label="Shannon 1948">Shannon, Claude E. <title
                        rend="quotes">A Mathematical Theory of Communication</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Bell Systems Technical Journal</title> 27 (July, October
                    1948): 379–423, 623–56.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shannon1949" label="Shannon and Weaver 1949">Shannon, Claude E. and
                    Warren Weaver. <title rend="italic">The Mathematical Theory of
                        Communication</title> Urbana: The University of Illinois Press
                    (1949).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sima1993" label="Sima 1993">Sima Qian. <title rend="italic">Records of
                        the Grand Historian: Han Dynasty I</title>. Trans. Burton Watson. Rev. ed.
                    Hong Kong and New York: The Research Centre for Translation, Chinese University
                    of Hong Kong and Columbia University Press (1993).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="spence1966" label="Spence 1966">Spence, Jonathan D. <title
                        rend="italic">Ts’ao Yin and the K’ang-hsi Emperor</title>. New Haven: Yale
                    University Press (1966).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tangherlini2013" label="Tangherlini and Leonard 2013">Tangherlini,
                    Timothy R. and Peter Leonard. <title rend="quotes">Trawling the Sea of the Great
                        Unread: Sub-corpus Topic Modeling and Humanities Research</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Poetics</title> 41: 725–49.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tian2017" label="Tian 2017">Tian, Xiaofei. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Literary Learning: Encyclopedias and Epitomes</title>. In <title
                        rend="italic">Oxford Handbook of Classical Chinese Literature (1000 BCE–900
                        CE)</title>, edited by Wiebke Denecke, Wai-Yee Li, and Xiaofei Tian, 132–46.
                    New York: Oxford University Press (2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tong1998" label="Tong 1998">Tong Peiji 佟培基. <title rend="quotes"
                        xml:lang="zh">Jin sanbai nian <title rend="italic">Quan Tang shi</title> de
                        zhengli yu yanjiu</title>
                    近三百年《全唐詩》的整理與研究
                    (Corrections and research on the <title rend="italic">Complete Tang
                        poems</title> over the last three hundred years), <title rend="italic"
                        >Wenxian</title> 文獻 (Textual evidence) 59.3 (1998): 17–28.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="underwood2012" label="Underwood 2012">Underwood, Ted. <title
                        rend="quotes">What Kind of <q>Topics</q> Does Topic Modeling Actually
                        Produce?</title> April 1, 2012. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://tedunderwood.com/2012/04/01/what-kinds-of-topics-does-topic-modeling-actually-produce/"
                        >https://tedunderwood.com/2012/04/01/what-kinds-of-topics-does-topic-modeling-actually-produce/</ref>.
                    Accessed January 9, 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="underwood2017" label="Underwood 2017"> — . <title rend="quotes">A
                        Genealogy of Distant Reading</title>. <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital
                        Humanities Quarterly</title> 11.2 (2017). Available at: <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/2/000317/000317.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/2/000317/000317.html</ref>.
                    Accessed September 11, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vierthaler2016" label="Vierthaler 2016">Vierthaler, Paul. <title
                        rend="quotes">Fiction and History: Polarity and Stylistic Gradience in Late
                        Imperial Chinese Literature</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of
                        Cultural Analytics</title> (2016). DOI: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.31235/osf.io/t9b7v">10.31235/osf.io/t9b7v</ref>.
                    Accessed August 20, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wellek1956" label="Wellek and Warren 1956">Wellek, René and Austin
                    Warren. <title rend="italic">Theory of Literature</title>. 3rd ed. New York:
                    Harcourt, Brace &amp; World (1956).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="xu1994" label="Xu 1994">Xu, Zong 許總. <title rend="italic"
                        xml:lang="zh">Tang shi shi</title>
                    唐詩史 (A history of Tang poetry).
                    Nanjing: Jiangsu jiaoyu chubanshe (1994).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="yang1996" label="Yang 1996">Yang, Shiming 楊世明. <title rend="italic"
                        xml:lang="zh">Tang shi shi</title>
                    唐詩史 (A history of Tang poetry).
                    Chongqing: Chongqing chubanshe (1996).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="yu1990" label="Yu 1990">Yu, Pauline. <title rend="quotes">Poems in
                        Their Place: Collections and Canons in Early Chinese Literature</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Harvard Journal of Asiatic Studies</title> 50.1 (1990):
                    163–96.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="yu1994" label="Yu 1994"> — . <title rend="quotes">The Chinese Poetic
                        Canon and Its Boundaries</title>. In <title rend="italic">Boundaries in
                        China</title>, edited by John Hay, 105–23. London: Reaktion Books
                    (1994).</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
