<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Categorising Legal
               Records – Deductive, Pragmatic, and Computational Strategies</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Marlene <dhq:family>Ernst</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0097-2267</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Passau, Department of Digital
                  Humanities</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>marlene.ernst@uni-passau.de</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Sebastian <dhq:family>Gassner</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Passau, Department of Digital
                  Humanities</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>sebastian.gassner@uni-passau.de</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Markus <dhq:family>Gerstmeier</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4283-6434</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Passau, Department of Digital
                  Humanities</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>markus.gerstmeier@uni-passau.de</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Malte <dhq:family>Rehbein</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3252-0604</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Passau, Department of Digital
                  Humanities</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>malte.rehbein@uni-passau.de</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000708</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->017</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->3</idno>
            <date/>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000708/000708.xml"
               >GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>Reprocessing printed source material and facilitating large-scale qualitative as well
               as quantitative analyses with digital methods poses many challenges. A case study on
               approximately 10,000 inventory entries for legal cases from the Special Court Munich
               (1933–1945) highlights those and offers a glimpse into a digitisation workflow that
               allows for in-depth computer-aided analysis. For this paper, different methods and
               procedures for developing categorisation systems for legal charges are discussed.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>Three different approaches to categorising semi-structured information concerning
               legal history</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Remarks on Categorisation – Theoretical Considerations</head>
            <p>Many printed historical sources still await systematic reprocessing, or
                  <q>upcycling”</q>
               <ptr target="#donig_rehbein2022"/> in order to facilitate large-scale qualitative and
               quantitative analyses by digital means. In this instance, we are dealing with
               approximately 10,000 legal cases from the Special Court Munich throughout the entire
               period of the National Socialist regime in Germany (1933–1945) which were thoroughly
               documented in a printed format as <title rend="quotes">Archive Inventory</title> in
               the 1970s <ptr target="#baystmuk19751977"/>. While the original court files are
               heterogeneous in their structure and comprise all kinds of documents, from
               handwritten notes to typewritten forms, and therefore are not predestined for a
               systematic and automated approach in extrapolating the content, the documentation
               done in the 1970s, the <title rend="quotes">Archive Inventory</title>, presents us
               with a semi-structured repository of knowledge that can be analysed by digital
               methods. First steps towards such were set about recently <ptr
                  target="#gerstmeier2022"/>. For further analyses, we have to pre-process the
               semi-structured data from the <title rend="quotes">Archive Inventory</title> – i.e.,
               categorisation in the form of organising the information contained within the source
               material.</p>
            <p>The ultimate goal of the future work is a large-scale study of the sentencing
               practices of the Special Courts. In this study, for example, correlations between
               social status, accusation, and sentencing level are to be sought as well as general
               patterns. Overall, this serves the objective of describing the legal norm (or
                  <q>average</q> practice) and at the same time uncovering anomalies (cf.
               Schlumbohm, 1998, p. 28). We are discussing the following six theoretical
               considerations:</p>
            <list type="ordered">
               <item>Categorisation moves between macro- and microhistorical approaches. Such a path
                  to a comprehensive macrohistorical study contrasts with smaller-scale
                  microhistory, for which studies based on few samples of single records already
                  exist. For computer-assisted macrohistorical research, corresponding digital tools
                  are being developed under the metaphor of <quote rend="inline">macroscopy</quote>
                  (Graham, Milligan, and Weingart, 2016). However, this research approach generally
                  still awaits a theoretical foundation. When Jürgen Schlumbohm (1998, p. 29)
                  discussed whether micro- and macrohistory are to be understood as complementary or
                  incommensurable, he concluded with regard to the aggregation of data following
                  categorisation that <quote rend="inline">a kind of <q>theory of
                     aggregation</q></quote> does not yet exist for historical science. This still
                  seems to be true, and the resulting desideratum needs to be addressed. This is not
                  only the case because of the increase of data-driven research also in
                     <q>traditional</q> Humanities disciplines such as History, but especially
                  because a sharp division (in the understanding of a counterpart) between macro and
                  micro studies seems to be as outdated as the rigid adherence to disciplinary
                  boundaries. However, just as there might be no interdisciplinarity without
                  disciplines, the interchange between macro and micro studies should not lead to
                  the abandonment of the cores of the respective research paradigm, but rather form
                  a smooth transition. It is here that categorisation or general modelling forms an
                  important bridge between the study of the particular at the micro level and that
                  of the general at the macro level — from the close-up view to the distant view and
                  back again. Such bridge-building, however, must be purposeful as well as
                  systematic and shall not result in eclectic bricolage and thus
                  arbitrariness.</item>
               <item>Categorisation is data modelling. All categorisation is modelling and the
                  models we create help <quote rend="inline">understanding the world by means of
                     patterns and principles</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bod2018" loc="p. 78"/> in the sense of the macrohistory we seek.
                  Hence, general model theory applies to categorisation. Among other things, this
                  means that categorisations are reasoned (and subjective) selection processes. This
                  is of considerable methodological importance for any data-driven work, especially
                  in the Digital Humanities, but is apparently too often neglected, which
                  significantly diminishes the value of the results. Categorisations are conscious
                  typifications or exemplifications and must be demarcated not only from
                  arbitrariness but also from unconscious formation of stereotypes (cf. <ptr
                     target="#ginzburg_poni1991"/>).</item>
               <item>Categorisation is complexity reduction. This, too, forms an area of tension
                  between micro- and macrohistory. In the context of methodological approaches of
                  the Digital Humanities, reference could be made here to procedures of close and
                  distant reading. In close reading, the human researcher processes significantly
                  more information from each source but fewer sources, whereas, in distant reading,
                  significantly more sources are condensed into less information. In our case, for
                  example, microhistory corresponds to the close reading of complete, more
                  substantial, but only few sample records, while the macrohistorical approach
                  corresponds to the distant reading of aggregated data. In such a reduction of
                  complexity, it has to be weighed up how much of the source content has to be taken
                  over 1:1 and how much may be typified. The higher the degree of abstraction, the
                  greater the danger of losing relevant content without achieving any more
                  selectivity. This is a problem we have encountered especially in the pragmatic
                  approach below. In the case of the Special Courts, reducing potentially
                  substantial sources (<q><foreign xml:lang="de">Akte</foreign></q>/file) to a few
                  data (<q><foreign xml:lang="de">Aktenregest</foreign></q>/record), which are then
                  additionally aggregated into categories, could be considered typical for
                  macro-historical questions based on secondary data from <q>upcycling</q>
                  processes.</item>
               <item>Categorisation of historical data means dealing with time. The period of
                  validity of categories is often limited, which becomes especially evident over the
                  transition from pre-modern to modern times (<q><foreign xml:lang="de"
                        >Sattelzeit</foreign></q>) but should be seen as a fundamental challenge of
                  historical macro studies in general. Here we usually have two levels to consider:
                  first, the present time from which we write history, and second, the past about
                  which we write, whose sources we use, and whose terminology we rely on. In the
                  case discussed here, there is even a third temporal level, namely the indexing of
                  the files carried out in the 1970s and the vocabulary used there to produce the
                     <title rend="quotes">Archive Inventories</title>. This results in the challenge
                  to do justice – as far as possible – to the conceptuality and the vocabulary of
                  the source while at the same time creating a valid categorisation over different
                  temporal levels and evaluating it critically (cf. Seiffert, 2006, p. 205; Wehler,
                  1972, p. 20).</item>
               <item>Categorisation is hermeneutical and ontological. It has already been described
                  in the literature that there is a tense but also distinctly appealing relationship
                  between source vocabulary and modern typology. In addition, in our case it is
                  especially important not to fall for the Nazi ideology and the language they used
                  (cf. Klemperer, 1947/2020), which often stands in contrast to actually valid law
                  (of the Weimar Republic), to a modern understanding of law, and to human rights,
                  which are considered universal today. The question of universals alluded to here
                  is also of fundamental importance for categorisation. Seiffert (2006, p. 159)
                  distinguishes between <quote rend="inline">source terms</quote>, <quote
                     rend="inline">modern terms</quote>, and <quote rend="inline">supra-temporal
                     terms</quote>. Certain terms, he claims are <quote rend="inline"
                     >timeless</quote>, such as the category <quote rend="inline">human
                     being,</quote> and thus <quote rend="inline">so general and formal that we can
                     unhesitatingly apply them to any historical epoch without fear of doing
                     violence to the historical fact</quote>. It is essential to keep this
                  ontological dimension in mind when categorising. In the three approaches we have
                  followed, especially the inductive-computational (automated) one attempts a
                  clustering via the source terms (of the secondary source). It takes the finding of
                  the source terms without further interpretation as its basis of categorisation,
                  while the first two approaches interpretively process a priori or inductive
                  theoretical presuppositions. But here, too, the question remains: is this
                  interpretation present-tense, is it situated within the hermeneutically
                  understanding of the past under investigation, or can it be supra-temporal?</item>
               <item>Categorisation has a normative function. Directly linked to these
                  considerations is the question of whether a categorisation is descriptive or
                  normative: does it describe (ontologically: <q>A is an X</q>) or does it norm
                     (<q>shall A be an X</q>, <q>shall A be understood as an X</q>)? A source
                  approach is arguably more descriptive, while the use of modern terms tends toward
                  a normative view. Thus, categorisation, like any kind of norm-setting, runs the
                  risk of having a domination or even ruling function inherent in it (cf. Richter,
                  2021, p. 53 with reference to <ptr target="#durkheim_mauss1901"/>). This is
                  particularly relevant in data-based research: Whoever prescribes the data
                  categories sets norms. Therefore, given categories must always be critically
                  questioned, which is especially important when <q>upcycling</q> older data. This
                  also applies to primary data (take Census data, for example: here the exercise of
                  domination is particularly conspicuous, which admittedly was also practised under
                  Nazi rule, but not only there, see e.g., race laws). Such categorisations can then
                  have an impact on the formation of society/ies.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The following pages present a case study on three different approaches towards the
               categorisation of legal sources from the Nazi era taking three different points of
               view into account: a) a deductive one, which operates on the basis of
               legal-philosophical and legal-historical theory; b) a pragmatic-explorative one,
               operating with secondary source texts, but using contemporary understandings for
               category formation; and c) an inductive-computational approach. They highlight the
               varying spectrum and different views one can take on the past while simultaneously
               showcasing the interplay between the theoretical considerations described above.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction to the Source Material</head>
            <p>Although not an entirely new phenomenon in NS Germany, the Special Courts were
               distinctive in the sense that they combine regular criminal law and charges of the
               form of non-conformity according to Nazi ideology under one jurisdiction. Not least
               because of this, the contents of the cases are particularly diverse and hard to grasp
               in modern legal terms. The corresponding case files are just as complex and
               heterogenous in their content and structure – from typewritten forms to handwritten
               notes. The compilatory work done in the 1970s helps to get a better grasp on the
               content of the original files by putting the information in a model of a more concise
               and structured nature.</p>
            <p>The inventory, which was compiled by a team from the Bavarian State Archives between
               1975 and 1977, is in itself remarkable in several respects. It was printed in a
               limited quantity of copies, self-published in off-set technology, bound off-site and
               not distributed on the book market, but given away to libraries and archives. The
               resulting volumes are thus rather to be understood as <q>grey literature</q>, as
               auxiliary means for the internal use of authorities and for scientific purposes. They
               are not only a finding aid but a possible answer to the challenge of indexing mass
               sources and a source in themselves, reflecting editorial decision-making processes of
               that time. In the example of entry number 165, we get a glimpse of the overall
               structure of an inventory record with the main content description by the authors in
               English added in blue: </p>
            <figure>
               <head>Example of inventory record number 165 with added content description in
                  blue.</head>
               <figDesc>Written record of court proceedings for a specific case</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Instead of highlighting individual fates and putting emphasis on particular
               information of the respective procedure reflected in the file and its transmission
               process, the editors decided to define a standardised set of general characteristics
               to be collected for each case. That this standardisation changed over the
               long-stretched process of compilation is only natural, e.g., for cases from 1939
               onwards, the underlying relevant legal paragraphs have been added. Thus, additionally
               complicating the computation process of today. As researchers of digital history,
               this circumstance confronts us with several challenges at once, especially in the
               context of categorisation.</p>
            <p>Nonetheless, analysis of a more comprehensive nature is made possible through the
               digital transformation. Because the corresponding primary sources, i.e., case files,
               have been analysed only partly, the inventory still retains great relevance for
               research today. The main aim lies in digitally upcycling the inventory in order to
               make the records available and pre-process the data for quantitative analyses, e. g.,
               correspondence analysis for which well-designed categorisation is essential. After
               digitisation and pre-processing, information extraction from the machine-readable
               text is possible through its formalised structure. The compilatory work done in the
               1970s has been meticulous and offers access to the content on a systematic level.
               Nonetheless, close reading raises questions about how the editors structured their
               approach. There also seems to be some inconsistency in how the information was
               processed (e.g., the wording of the charges laid against the defendants). Those
               inconsistencies pose a challenge for the digital upcycling in the sense of automated
               processes taking, for example, the extraction of accusation categories: For further
               large-scale analysis, cases on derogatory or critical remarks – by far the largest
               group of charges – belong in the same category, whether they may refer to the
               spreading of rumours (on Hitler or otherwise) or rants about the regime in general.
               Those cases are to be differentiated from crimes still liable to prosecution today,
               like rape or theft.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Workflow – From Paper to Dataset </head>
            <p>Automatic recognition of typewritten text (OCR) is a comparatively established field
               that already has a number of standardised procedures. Permissively licensed OCR
               engines such as Tesseract (Smith 2007) or Calamari (Wick, Reul, and Puppe, 2018) are
               not inferior in quality to proprietary solutions (Reul et al., 2018). The workflows
               associated with these solutions can be better shared and adapted for similar usage
               contexts. As part of the project, we therefore implemented and incrementally improved
               numerous pipelines.</p>
            <p>Initially, the books have been scanned using an overhead book scanner.
               Unsurprisingly, the resulting digitised pages showed warping and skew. Several
               attempts of performing optical character recognition after automatic de-warping and
               de-skewing did not lead to satisfying results. The overall error in the OCR results
               introduced by distorted pages, combined with deteriorated and contaminated typeface
               could not be reduced to an acceptable level, after the fact, by software alone. Page
               warping is due to the pages being bound into books. By unbinding the books and
               digitising single pages using a document feeder scanner, page warping and page skew
               could be eliminated almost completely. Deterioration and contamination of the
               typeface were still present, but the overall error rate was significantly
               reduced.</p>
            <p>In the next step, we employed Tesseract for OCR on all pages, specifying a German
               dictionary and the calligraphy hand <title rend="quotes">Fraktur</title> and
               outputting one file per digitised page, in hOCR format <ptr target="#baierer2020"/>.
               Compared to plain text, hOCR has the added advantage of preserving layout
               information. Each page contained several inventory records, with entries sometimes
               spanning two pages, when starting close to the bottom of a page. We continued
               processing the text programmatically by undoing the physical boundaries at page-level
               and, instead, splitting the text at logical boundaries, namely at the inventory
               record level. Out of 9,955 inventory records, 8,531 or 86 % could be extracted
               successfully [2]. With separate inventory records in plain text format, our algorithm
               continued to parse and translate each entry into JSON format [3]. Each JSON record
               captures meta information, such as page number and name of the hOCR file containing
               the record, and the content of the inventory record itself in separate fields, as
               detailed in Figure 1. It should be noted that we also retain the underlying plain
               text within each JSON record, to maintain the opportunity to make (manual)
               corrections or to retrace decisions later. </p>
            <p>In a final step, we selected relevant information from a subset of JSON fields and
               created a CSV file, serving as the baseline for the different categorisation
               approaches described throughout the rest of this article. Each row in the CSV file
               contained a unique identifier, the inventory record, the <q>law</q> or legal basis /
                     <q><foreign xml:lang="de">Gesetzesgrundlage</foreign></q>, respectively, and
               the duration of the case, as well as normalised versions of the inventory record and
               duration. The normalised inventory records retained only the accusation / <q><foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Anklagegrund</foreign></q>, stripping off the result of the
               proceedings and lemmatizing all words. The normalised duration contains the starting
               date only, standardised as YYYY-MM-DD. After this pre-processing, the information is
               principally available for computer-aided analysis but additional strategies for
               systematically approaching the data had to be developed. </p>
            <p>Different approaches may be taken in processing, categorising and engineering an
               in-depth analysis of the 10,000 cases. After the initial digitisation and information
               extraction – processes which were formalised with regard to reusability and a
               proof-of-concept workflow for source digitisation in mind –, challenges are posed by
               different categorisation models that may be applied to the corpus. The different
               methods, from an intuitive approach based on keywords to automated processes
               utilising natural language processing and clustering the results, exemplify how
               varying methods can influence our view on the past. In this paper, these different
               perspectives and their interconnections will be discussed in order to open up a new
               scholarly approach to the inventories. They are especially important for subsequent
               statistical analyses.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Categorisation Methodologies</head>
            <p>Even though positive law was seen critically or even derogatory within the
               ideologically affected legal system of the <q>Third Reich</q>, NS judiciary somehow
               cleverly understood to use the benefits of a traditionally grown and reliably
               functioning judicial machinery like in modern Germany for its own ideological means
               of arbitrariness and terror throughout all changes of 20th century political systems
               (Lahusen, 2022). The other way around, the extent to which the German judiciary more
               or less voluntarily made itself a <quote rend="inline">stooge</quote> (Weber and
               Piazolo, 1998, pp. 13–14; Gruchmann, 2001) of the Nazi regime is exemplarily proofed
               by the Special Courts, while their specific legal bases, which were enacted from 1933
               onwards without any parliamentary participation, exemplify the dissolution of the
               legislature in the <q>Third Reich</q>. </p>
            <p>Simultaneously, the ancient Greek etymology of the term <q>category</q> comprises
               primarily nothing else than a legal significance – <q><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                     >κατηγορεῖν</foreign></q> means <quote rend="inline">to accuse</quote>, <quote
                  rend="inline">to charge</quote> (<ptr target="#gemoll2006" loc="p. 453"/>; TLL
               III, 1906–1912, col. 602). As we focus on a court, a categorisation along its
               authoritative working base regards a deepened consideration of applicable laws, legal
               regulations, ordinances, decrees, or even – depending on the granularity depth of
               data modelling – the specific legal paragraphs that were valid at the time. And
               indeed, each decision of a court in the modern sense refers to a concrete legal
               basis: Even in the <q><foreign xml:lang="de">Unrechtsstaat</foreign></q> of NS
               dictatorship judges could not simply render judgements at their own discretion,
               according to the legal principle <quote rend="inline"><foreign xml:lang="la">nulla
                     poena sine lege</foreign></quote>
               <ptr target="#feuerbach1801" loc="p. 20"/>. This formal aspect of Special Courts was
               dedicatedly criticised by ideologically convinced Nazis in German Judiciary and
               Faculties of Law (<ptr target="#garbe1999" loc="pp. 141–142"/>; <ptr
                  target="#froelich1983" loc="p. 210"/>). So, purely theoretically, such a deductive
               approach might be the most reasonable.</p>
            <div>
               <head>a) Deductive-(Legal-)Philosophical and (Legal-)Historical Approach </head>
               <p>Our first approach of categorisation can be classified as <emph>deductive</emph>.
                  There is a certain degree of legal-philosophical background behind the historical
                  phenomenon investigated, but more prominently we are offered references to
                  specific legal sources – at least for part of the case files. </p>
               <p>Deduction is considered a most distinguished philosophical method of
                  categorisation (Kant, 1787/1904, pp. 104–130, §§14–27). The most paradigmatic
                  modern contribution to the conceptualisation of deduction as a philosophical
                  method relates to law <ptr target="#fichte1966"/>. Concerning the NS Special
                  Courts, a categorisation alongside the legal bases is particularly interesting as
                  their qualities are remarkably diverse. First of all, we chose a legal theoretical
                  distinction between the positive law (Kelsen, 1934/2017) and laws and legal
                  regulations, respectively, in the sense of Carl Schmitt’s (1922/2002) and other NS
                  legal thinkers’ theory of law and society. It marks the peculiarity of NS Special
                  Courts within the contemporary judicial system of the Reich that in the same way
                  of their institutionalisation beyond the regular courts, the NS regime began with
                  its legislation of special penal regulations besides the regular criminal laws
                  that had been systematically codified in the German Nation State since 1871
                  (RStGB, 1871/1935). The proceedings before the Special Courts concerned first of
                  all exclusively such <q>crimes</q>, or – to be more semantically neutral – actions
                  that only had been criminalised by a certain kind of NS special penal regulations.
                  A closer look on the complex process of the Nazi Seizure of Power shows that the
                  NS regime relaunched special penal legislation even before relaunching the
                  Weimar-invented Special Courts (<q><foreign xml:lang="de"
                  >Verordnung</foreign></q>, 1933), at first by means of the <title rend="quotes"
                     >Reichstag Fire Decree</title> (1933). The scientific estimation of this
                  ordinance as <quote rend="inline">the fundamental exceptional law on which the
                     National Socialist dictatorship was primarily based until its collapse</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bracher1960" loc="p. 82"/> shows the principal significance of this
                  kind of repression for the establishment of NS dictatorship. </p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">D-1:</title> The most important and in over twelve years of
                  NS special penal judiciary most often applied special legal regulation
                  (Hüttenberger, 1981) became the so-called <title rend="quotes"><foreign
                        xml:lang="de">Heimtückegesetz</foreign></title> (1934). Thereby, the term
                        <q><foreign xml:lang="de">Heimtücke</foreign></q>, i.e.,
                     <q>insidiousness</q>, must be understood as a typical NS dysphemism. This law
                  criminalised every kind of verbal or written critical comment on the NS regime or
                  on certain Nazi politicians – whereas in regular German criminal law,
                     <q>insidiousness</q> is actually an essential characteristic of murder (RStGB,
                  1871, §211,2). We define the early NS special penal law regulations as our
                     <term>category D-1</term>. </p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">D-2:</title> As another facet of their peculiar role within
                  the NS system of persecution and repression, Special Courts were increasingly used
                  for <q>regular crimes</q>. The longer the NS regime lasted, the more frequent such
                  cases were brought before it. This phenomenon is well known by existing research
                  literature (e.g., <ptr target="#doerner1998" loc="pp. 36–39"/>; Wogersien, 2007).
                  Apart from a few exceptions (e.g., Graczyk 2021, pp. 250–330), concrete numbers or
                  data on this topic have not been presented yet. The Mannheim Special Court shows,
                  for example: In 1933 18.6 % of <q>regular</q> first instance judgements (like
                  theft or murder) were tried before it, but in 1943 this percentage would increase
                  up to 43.9 % (Oehler, 1997, pp. 36–37). Precise statistical analyses on the
                  question of how often in 1933 still valid laws (RStGB, 1871/1934) were applied
                  represent a desideratum. By the example of Special Court Munich, this can be
                  approached through our computer-based investigation of its archive inventory from
                  the 1970s (cf. section below). Besides the codified law, Munich Special Court even
                  applied rather marginal regulations and decrees of regular penal law for its
                  judgements, up to the late Weimar <title rend="quotes">Animal Protection
                     Act</title>
                  <ptr target="#apa1930"/> or exclusive Bavarian state laws – what surprises in the
                  face of anti-federal Nazi system –, like the <title rend="quotes">Slaughter Tax
                     Act</title> (1930).</p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">D-3:</title> Research so far has also thematised that the
                  beginning of World War II meant a significant incision in the history of NS
                  special judiciary. Already since 1938, a veritable boost of new specific NS
                  special penal law regulations began to unfold. This ‘second wave’ of NS special
                  criminal law-making is correlating with the sheer increase in the number of cases
                  brought to trial before, e.g., the Munich Special Court since 1939: Between 1933
                  and 1938, 3,123 proceedings were carried out, but in the years 1939–1945 they
                  reached 6,823. This tremendously increasing repression no longer exclusively
                  referred to the regime’s <q>own</q> German <q><foreign xml:lang="de"
                        >Volksgemeinschaft</foreign></q> but to foreigners (mostly forced labourers
                  and prisoners of war), too, since the annexations of 1938 and 1939 and
                  particularly since Germany’s war of aggression. This justifies the formation of
                  another deductive-legal-historical category, especially since these new products
                  of NS special penal law regulation [4] – in contrast to the more generally
                  applicable <q><foreign xml:lang="de">Heimtückegesetz</foreign></q>– are concerned
                  with more or less specific war-related deviance or resistance, or with the racial
                  or ethnic affiliation of prosecuted people itself, respectively:</p>
               <list type="unordered">
                  <item>The most universally formulated regulation of D-3 is the <title
                        rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="de"
                        >Volksschädlingsverordnung/VVO</foreign></title> (1939). With its typical
                     dysphemic Nazi-language title (Klemperer, 1947/2020, pp. 291, 403) and enacted
                     four days after the beginning of World War II, Munich Special Court would apply
                     it 1,074 times until 1945, often under the imposition of the death penalty,
                     which VVO §1 provides, e.g., in the case of looting. The <title rend="quotes"
                           ><foreign xml:lang="de">Wehrkraftverordnung</foreign></title> (1939)
                     criminalised actions that, in the eyes of the NS regime, undermined the defence
                     force. By 1945, Munich Special Court had applied it 779 times.</item>
                  <item>Beyond these, the NS regime enacted at the very beginning of World War II
                     special penal regulations concerning specific kinds of resistance in the
                     context of everyday life during the war, too, such as listening to hostile
                     radio programs [5] (cf. Hensle, 2005; <ptr target="#christians2020"
                        loc="pp. 265–276"/>) as well as a whole range of ordinances dealing with
                     individual misbehaviour to the harm of war economy (<ptr
                        target="#christians2020" loc="pp. 217–227"/>; Hackl, 2022), e.g., the <title
                        rend="quotes">Ordinance on War Economy</title> (1939), applied 599 times by
                     Munich Special Court.</item>
                  <item>NS special penal law regulations and judgment routine of the Special Courts
                     were over time even involved in the ideological and racist war of determination
                     and the Shoah, which is manifested especially by the <title rend="quotes">Penal
                        Ordinance against Polish and Jews</title> (1941).</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">D-4:</title> Finally, in the context of <q>total war</q>, the
                  judicial practice of NS Special Courts reached out even to the legal basis of
                  another non-regular jurisdiction instance, namely to the proprietary penal law of
                  the German <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="de"
                  >Wehrmacht</foreign></title>. The Military Penal Code (MStGB, 1943), originally
                  launched by early <foreign xml:lang="de">Kaiserreich</foreign>, would be the legal
                  basis for three judgments of the Munich Special Court in 1944/45.</p>
               <p>For an understanding of the historical phenomenon of NS Special Courts and their –
                  since 1939 once again changed – role within the Nazi repression system, a
                  deductive categorisation along the concrete legal bases of proceedings may provide
                  a substantial epistemological profit. It might even go to the core of the complex
                  relationship between National Socialism and law as well as justice, respectively,
                  in a diachronic perspective. As far as the legal bases of the Munich Special Court
                  during World War II are concerned, we are dealing with a simultaneous set of legal
                  sources that arose at different times and, according to legal theory, are to be
                  evaluated differently. This multimodality of legal bases, some of which are
                  applied simultaneously in proceedings, is to be modelled in categories D-5, D-6,
                  and D-7 (concrete numbers cf. below, <title rend="quotes">Comparison</title> and
                  Figure 5). Especially since 1939, Munich Special Court often would apply D-2 legal
                  bases – above all paragraphs of the RStGB (1871) – in addition to the D-3 NS
                  special penal law regulations whenever possible. Also, the <title rend="quotes"
                        ><foreign xml:lang="de">Heimtückegesetz</foreign></title> (1934) of D-1
                  would still be applied extensively in addition to the new special penal law
                  regulations from 1938 onwards; even the <title rend="quotes">Reichstag Fire
                     Decree</title> (1933), still kept being applied by the Munich Special Court,
                  even in times of <q>total war</q> (17 times, remarkably in most cases against
                  Jehovah’s Witnesses).</p>
               <p>Ideally, deductive categorisation seems to be the most rational method of
                  understanding the actual nature of this historical phenomenon. In our present
                  research, however, it indeed proves to be only partially purposeful. Formally, the
                  façade of a rationally acting judiciary was maintained even under the conditions
                  of <q>total war</q> (Lahusen, 2022, pp. 141–185, illustrated with the example of
                  Aachen Special Court), although the Munich NS Special Court was undoubtedly part
                  of a state of injustice. The problem lies rather in the fact that in our research
                  we do not work primarily on the basis of the court records themselves but with the
                  help of secondary records prepared in the 1970s (cf. above, introduction to the
                  source material). As is the case with many digital humanities projects today, the
                  editors of the <q>pre-digital</q> database of the BayStMUK-<title rend="quotes"
                     >Archive Inventory</title> changed their metadata scheme in the course of data
                  entry. Thus, it happens that the laws/ordinances/legal paragraphs that had been
                  applied by the NS Special Court were only recorded in the inventory records from
                  the beginning of Part 3 (1939) onwards during the scientific retrospective of the
                  1970s <ptr target="#baystmuk19751977" loc="1976, p. 619; 1977, p. 2349"/>. In the
                  records on the trials and discontinued proceedings of the years 1933–1938, no
                  legal basis is given in the records of the <title rend="quotes">Archive
                     Inventory</title> at all and for the phase from 1938 to 1945 are also some
                  instances where such explicit information is missing (specifically in 473 cases).
                  Nonetheless, even for the proceedings where the record entries offer no paragraph
                  in the <title rend="quotes">Archive Inventory</title>, the offence recorded in
                  each case can always be used to draw conclusions about an unambiguous criminal
                  offence and the applied written law (cf. below, comparison). For the research
                  design of our project, this means that a categorisation along the legal basis of
                  the special court proceedings actually only makes sense for the period from the
                  beginning of 1939 onwards, even though 6,830 of the entire 9,954 cases captured by
                  the <title rend="quotes">Archive Inventory</title> took place after the beginning
                  of 1939.</p>
               <p>For our research and the formation of meaningful and, above all, useful categories
                  for the quantitative historical analysis of the (secondary) source corpus, this
                  lack of data and missing information means that we have to find a more pragmatic
                  methodology in order to focus on the actual object of investigation – i.e., the
                  Munich NS Special Court and its repressive practice or the <quote rend="inline"
                     >everyday</quote> resistance and deviance of the wider population in the <title
                     rend="quotes">Third Reich</title> and the <quote rend="inline">wartime
                     society</quote> (Wildt, 2007; Wildt 2019, pp. 302–325) that manifested itself
                  before this court.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>b) Pragmatic-Explorative Approach </head>
               <p>Through a random sample of cases for close reading and the intensive study of the
                  source material in the context of the digitisation and data modelling process, we
                  could gain an overview of the content. This insight allowed us to think of several
                  topics relevant to categorising the charges by applying an intuitive system. In
                  some cases, the demarcation was relatively easy: A huge part of the charges
                  concern negative remarks against the regime (e.g., the claim that the Reichstag
                  was set on fire by National Socialists) and leading figures thereof (e.g., the
                  allegation that Hitler and Göring are gay). Another very clear category deals with
                  social interactions with prisoners of war. Non-war-related inventory records
                  contain crimes from bodily harm, e.g., in the form of murder, to theft. Evaluating
                  the charge content showed that the wording used to describe the individual
                  accusations is in many cases standardised. This offered the possibility of sorting
                  the whole corpus with a few selected keywords per category – so our hypothesis. </p>
               <p>A first trial run of the approach – by defining eight categories, by analysing a
                  sample of 90 randomly chosen cases and looking for similarities in their content
                  for classification (1-bodily harm, 2-fraud, 3-economic crimes, like theft,
                  4-war-related economic crimes, like illicit butchering, 5-interactions with
                  prisoners of war, 6-sophisticated regime critique, written and oral resistance,
                  7-conspiracy, like pamphlet distribution, 8-negative remarks) – revealed a
                  disproportional surplus with over 40 % of cases concerning negative remarks. To
                  cater for deeper statistical analysis in the future, differentiating within this
                  main part of accusations became relevant in order to gain better insights into the
                  relationship between accusations, results, and socio-political backgrounds of the
                  accused. So, through a review and quality control loop, we decided to refine
                  categories, what they each comprise as well as which keywords to use. Thereby,
                  comparing the success and failure of predicted results from single keywords places
                  induction in a pragmatic context (cf. Holland et al., 1986).</p>
               <p>The query or category allocation was carried out on the basis of the normalised
                  charge text. The number of keywords necessary per category varies. Through a
                  review loop for each, the most efficient and concise word variations were sought
                  and found. Working with a spreadsheet, the course of action was to test keyword
                  variations on the column with the normalised charge text before incorporating the
                  best version into a nested formula, i.e., the most efficient one in terms of the
                  number of cases that could be allocated without compromising the results for other
                  categories. In some cases, only parts of words and phrases were used in order to
                  incorporate as many different word and verb forms as possible without compromising
                  the results by accidentally returning cases dealing with wholly different content.
                  This process led to the following categories with the different topics included in
                  each. </p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">E-1</title> bodily harm and morality: The primary aim was to
                  separate cases of murder, manslaughter and other bodily injury offences from those
                  that were purely regime-related. A review loop revealed that many charges deal
                  with people accused of talking about how Hitler and other NS functionaries should
                  be murdered or otherwise harmed, but where no actual deed was done. Additionally,
                  the review process revealed that there were also many instances of morality
                  (indecent behaviour) and rape brought before the Special Court. Though many
                  different accusations are part of this category and almost 20 keywords were
                  necessary for allocating them into this category (the highest number from all out
                  of the categorisation process), overall, only 264 instances are dealing with cases
                  that are still (mostly) relevant under criminal law today. </p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">E-2</title> fraud: 308 cases are related to fraudulent
                  behaviour. Only five keywords sufficed in order to collect all relevant instances.
                        <q><foreign xml:lang="de">Betrug</foreign></q>/fraud was commonly used in
                  the inventory in this case but also forgery (e.g., of documents) gets mentioned. </p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">E-3</title> theft and bribery: This category comprises not
                  only economic crimes still punishable by law today, like theft of goods, burglary,
                  or tax evasion but also instances where begging or embezzlement are concerned. In
                  the end, 909 cases are sorted into this category. </p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">E-4</title> war-related economic crimes: Cases in this
                  category are differentiated from the former by their relation to war. They mostly
                  concern food supply whereby black-market dealings, illegal slaughtering of
                  livestock, and illicit dealings with ration coupons are meant. Additionally,
                  foreign exchange crimes are also put in the same category which, in the end,
                  comprises 644 cases. </p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">E-5</title> prisoners of war-related crimes: This is another
                  instance, similar to the second category, where sorting was relatively easy and a
                  small number of keywords sufficed to cover 661 cases. The wording, for the most
                  part, stays the same throughout all inventory records for the cases where – mostly
                  (young) women – helped or socially interacted with prisoners of war. Additionally,
                  escape aid was also put in this category. </p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">E-6</title> regime criticism including religious and
                  political persecution: Differentiating between categories 6 and 7 involved the
                  toughest decisions in the process. In the end, mainly due to the extensive review
                  and quality control process, it seemed most prudent to aggregate political and
                  religious persecution (like members of the Communist Party and Jehovah’s
                  Witnesses) with instances where politically or religiously motivated active
                  resistance in the form of written statements or preaching against the regime
                  during Sunday service are concerned. Initially, cases involving the unauthorized
                  ownership and/or wearing of NS-uniforms or badges were also put here. But the main
                  motivation behind this pretence of being part of or supporting the regime was
                  self-preservation, thus not being on the same resistance level as the other
                  entries within the category. Those keywords were therefore relegated to category
                  E-7 and also resulted in decimating the number of relevant cases by approximately
                  200 till only 238 remained in category E-6. </p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">E-7</title> conspiracy and protest: Through the additional
                  cases moved from the former one, 528 instances could be found where active
                  resistance in the form of protest or consummation of illegal media but also active
                  actions for self-preservation are concerned. This also comprises the distribution
                  of leaflets as well as listening to foreign radio channels. </p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">E-8</title> negative remarks and hearsay: Although the review
                  and quality control process helped in distinguishing more properly between the
                  different categories, the by far most extensive category remains the one related
                  to negative remarks. 3,005 instances can still be ascribed to people commenting on
                  different aspects of the regime in different settings – from people repeating
                  hearsay about deaths in concentration camps to others insulting the government
                  during a session at the local inn. </p>
               <p>
                  <title rend="italic">E-9</title> person-related remarks: As the first trial run of
                  this approach showed, disproportionately many cases deal with accusations based on
                  negative remarks and/or hearsay. In order to differentiate those a little bit
                  more, cases where Hitler/the <q><foreign xml:lang="de">Führer</foreign></q> or
                  other leading figures of the regime, like Goebbels or Himmler, are part of the
                  claim are separated from the rest, resulting in 1,523 cases.</p>
               <p>Due to varying phrasing of the editors from the 1970s for the charges within the
                  inventory records (e.g., for negative remarks we have <quote rend="inline"
                        ><foreign xml:lang="de">schimpfen</foreign></quote>/ranting, <quote
                     rend="inline"><foreign xml:lang="de">negativ, abfällig
                  äußern</foreign></quote>/speaking derogatorily, <quote rend="inline"><foreign
                        xml:lang="de">kritisch äußern</foreign></quote>/critical remarks etc.),
                  partly due to the long process of collecting data and creating the inventory and
                  partly due to the fact, that different persons worked on them as well as still
                  remaining OCR-errors, it helped to keep the single category keywords as short as
                  possible. Thus, we encapsulated varying spellings and verb forms as well as common
                  OCR-errors like <q>a</q> instead of <q>ä</q> within one query. As the search for
                  the keywords is operated via the normalised and shortened text, which is sometimes
                  very individual in its wording concerning the charges, additional approximately
                  100 cases, which otherwise would result in being relegated to the group of
                  uncategorised records, can be allocated to the group of <q>negative remarks and
                     hearsay</q> by querying for <q><foreign xml:lang="de">gesagt haben
                        soll</foreign></q> (reported to have said) in the full text at the end. In
                  the end, 451 records remain uncategorised (<title rend="italic">E-0</title>) due
                  to poor quality of the OCR-text or because an accusation related to certain
                  allegations is mentioned only once, e.g., there is one accusation of poisoning
                  wells, a trope used against Jews since the Middle Ages.</p>
               <p>The resulting formula of nested if-then queries [6] is quite intricate but also
                  streamlined concerning efficiency. Nonetheless, one has to keep in mind that the
                  sequence within the query influences the result. If we, for example, retrieve
                  cases by filtering for charges of the category <quote rend="inline">bodily harm
                     and morality</quote>, like fornication/<q><foreign xml:lang="de"
                        >Unzucht</foreign></q> or murder, first, we would also put cases in the same
                  category where hearsay in relation to such crimes is concerned. The assigning of
                  the cases to single crime categories by particularly chosen keywords is subject to
                  individual biases as some – like the unauthorised wearing of badges and uniforms
                  (ultimately put into <title rend="italic">E-7</title>) – could be placed in
                  different categories depending on where we as editors choose to put them.
                  Therefore, we also developed a more <q>objective</q> inductive-computational
                  approach.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>c) Inductive-Computational Approach </head>
               <p>The inductive-computational approach aims at producing a categorisation with
                  little manual intervention by applying algorithms from natural language processing
                  (NLP), machine learning, and clustering. Most algorithms used must be
                  parameterised which requires expert knowledge, structured exploration of the
                  parameter space and experimentation. </p>
               <p>Starting from the baseline CSV file (cf. <title rend="quotes">Workflow</title>
                  above), we first trained a doc2vec model (Le, 2014) using the gensim library for
                  Python 3 (Rehurek, 2010). The algorithm defines an ample set of parameters, some
                  of which have a strong influence on the quality of the document embeddings
                  produced. Our goal was to cluster similar inventory records close together and far
                  apart from non-similar ones. Finding the right set of parameters requires trial
                  and error: define a parameter configuration, train a doc2vec model, obtain
                  embeddings for all documents, and evaluate the results visually. At this point, we
                  would like to note that we added a manual intervention: doc2vec does not solve a
                  classification task (there is no ground truth) but, instead, generates document
                  embeddings. Thus, no metric exists to assess the quality formally and
                  automatically in terms of classification accuracy of the embeddings produced.
                  Therefore, we selected a doc2vec model manually: we first computed embeddings for
                  all documents and plotted them in 2D space separately for each model; we then used
                  visual inspection to select a model that would generate a non-homogeneous
                  distribution of documents with clear clusters. Figure 2 exemplifies how we
                  explored the parameter space to select a model: each subplot represents a model
                  trained with a distinct set of parameters and shows the document embeddings
                  generated by the model projected into 2D space.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Exploring the parameter space to select a model: each subplot represents one
                     model trained with a distinct set of parameters and shows embeddings for all
                     documents after projection into 2D space. For example, the models 9–12 show a
                     homogeneous distribution of documents, without pronounced clusters; other
                     models, such as model 3, are better for our purpose because they result in more
                     structured alignments of document embeddings.</head>
                  <figDesc>Sixteen scatter plots</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Even a small set of parameters result in a huge space to explore: for example,
                  five parameters with three possible values each would require 35 = 243 models to
                  be trained and assessed. To limit the number of parameter configurations and,
                  thus, the number of models to be trained, we relied on our expertise and followed
                  the advice given by Lau (2016) on recommendations for optimal doc2vec
                  hyper-parameter settings. We then systematically explored the parameter space, by
                  first defining for each parameter a range of allowed values and then iterating
                  each possible combination of all parameters. For example, when allowing a = {1, 2,
                  3} and b = {4, 5, 6}, we would obtain nine possible combinations of a and b,
                  namely {1, 4}, {1, 5}, … {3, 5}, {3, 6}. After training only a small number of
                  doc2vec models and inspecting the results visually, we were able to identify some
                  parameter values which would always produce insufficient results, independently of
                  all other parameters. For example, disabling negative sampling or switching on
                  hierarchical softmax would always produce a homogeneous distribution of documents,
                  without distinct clusters, which is undesirable for our purpose. We excluded these
                  parameters from the exploration by setting a fixed value and shrinking the
                  parameter space to explore by orders of magnitude.</p>
               <p>Besides exploring doc2vec parameters configurations, the selection of a training
                  corpus has a significant impact on the quality of the models produced. Initially,
                  we trained our model on our own inventory records and used the same set of
                  documents to obtain document embeddings. Our corpus consisted of 8,532 valid
                  inventory records with an average length of 5.3 words. We were able to improve our
                  models to show more pronounced clusters by using a different corpus during
                  training, containing 1,454 legal documents from between 1933 and 1945 with an
                  average length of 444 words [7].</p>
               <p>After training and manually selecting a doc2vec model through visual inspection
                  [8], we were ready for the final step: clustering. First, we inferred a
                  high-dimensional embedding for each inventory record and then projected each
                  300-dimensional vector into 2D space by applying t-SNE (van der Maaten, 2008). We
                  then transformed our data into quantiles [9] before clustering by applying DBSCAN
                     <ptr target="#esteretal1996"/>. We used pandas (McKinney, 2010), numpy (Harris,
                  2020), and sklearn (Pedregosa et al., 2011) to implement all steps. The image
                  below shows a clustering of document embeddings representing our inventory
                  records.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Document embeddings, clusters, and categories from the
                     inductive-computational approach.</head>
                  <figDesc>Scatterplot with dots in several differnt colors where same-color dots
                     are clustered together.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpeg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Each dot represents a doc2vec embedding which corresponds to a single inventory
                  record. Similar documents are located close together and form clusters. Each
                  cluster corresponds to one category. Outliers are not part of any cluster. Note
                  that the image shows results from a particular choice of parameters used for
                  training the doc2vec model and for clustering document embeddings. We manually
                  chose a set of parameters. Different parameters would produce a significantly
                  different output.</p>
               <p>The number of clusters/categories in this approach was much higher than in the
                  other two approaches. This was because documents were grouped solely based on
                  contextual information found in the texts, whereas the other approaches grouped
                  legally related documents together, even if they were appearing in completely
                  unrelated contexts. For example, category E-5 (prisoner of war-related,
                  pragmatic-explorative approach) collects all accusations concerning contact with
                  prisoners of war, whereas the three categories C-35, C-37, C-38 are produced in
                  the inductive-computational approach, seemingly distinguishing between the
                  nationality of the prisoners.</p>
               <p>The following table (Figure 4) shows statistics for all 46 clusters sorted by the
                  number of documents within each cluster. The third column shows the relative
                  number of documents contained within each cluster. The right-most column shows the
                  top three most frequent words occurring within the cluster. Almost 16 % of all
                  documents belong to C-00 which collects outliers and corresponds to the
                     <q>uncategorised</q> category in the other two approaches. The clusters are
                  unevenly sized. The eight largest clusters (17 % of all clusters, not including
                  C-00) contain 50 % of all categorised documents. Out of these eight clusters, five
                  contain the word <q><foreign xml:lang="de">Äußerung</foreign></q> (remark) within
                  the top three cluster words which correspond to 35 % of all documents. This
                  clearly shows that a large proportion of all accusations concerned remarks about
                  the regime, leaders, the war etc.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Overview of cluster results of the inductive-computational approach with top
                     three keywords for each.</head>
                  <figDesc>Table showing keywords for each cluster from Figure 3</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
               </figure>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Comparison of the Different Approaches and Conclusion </head>
            <p>As described, the different categorisation approaches offer various and specialised
               views on the source material. The comparison of the individual case numbers per
               category (cf. Figure 5 as well as compared to Figure 4) already makes that clear. </p>
            <figure>
               <head>Figure 5. Case numbers per category for the first two approaches.</head>
               <figDesc>Tables comparing different categorization results for each
                  appraoch</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>Figure 5. Case numbers per category for the first two approaches. Figure 6.
                  Document embeddings and clusters of the inductive-computational approach with
                  colours/categories from the pragmatic-explorative approach.</head>
               <figDesc>Scatterplot with dots in several differnt colors where same-color dots are
                  clustered together</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.jpeg"/>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>Figure 6. Document embeddings and clusters of the inductive-computational
                  approach with colours/categories from the pragmatic-explorative approach. Figure
                  7. Document embeddings and clusters of the inductive-computational approach with
                  colours/categories from the deductive-(legal-)philosophical approach.</head>
               <figDesc>Scatterplot with dots in several differnt colors where clusters contain dots
                  of multiple colors</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.jpeg"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Nevertheless, some degree of overlap can be identified as well (cf. Figures 6 and 7).
               For several of the categories formed in the pragmatic-explorative approach, for
               example, it can be said that the offences subsumed under each category were
               criminalised in the first place by a very specific Nazi special criminal law
               ordinance:</p>
            <p>The simplest compatibility of one of the pragmatic-explorative categories is in
               category E-5 prisoners of war-related crimes. An indictment or conviction in this
               case always took place under §4 of the <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Wehrkraftverordnung</foreign></title> and is therefore also part of the
               deductive category D-3 (as can also be seen in the overlaps and distinctive colouring
               of clusters in the top-left quadrant in Figures 6 and 7). As already mentioned, C-35,
               C-37, and C-38 combined show a similar composition of cases. Conformity in this
               instance is predominantly owed to the wording used by the editors in the 1970s and
               the clearly defined legal basis for prisoners of war-related crimes.</p>
            <p>Three of these pragmatic-explorative categories even refer to a single Nazi special
               criminal law ordinance, namely the <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Heimtückegesetz</foreign></title>, or to be even more precise, to three
               concrete paragraphs of the <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Heimtückegesetz</foreign></title> (§§1, 2, and 4), namely E-8 negative remarks
               and hearsay and E-9 person-related remarks. Offences subsumed in E-6 regime criticism
               including religious and political persecution, however, were also based on the <title
                  rend="quotes">Reichstag Fire Decree</title> in some clearly identifiable cases –
               always against Jehovah’s Witnesses (known and listed in the records as <title
                  rend="italic">Ernste Bibelforscher</title>). This shows the qualitatively, but
               also quantitatively extremely large role that the <title rend="quotes"><foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Heimtückegesetz</foreign></title> had for the juridical practice
               of the Nazi special courts. Through the inductive-computational approach, we find
               that this distinction is made even more clear in the category C-28.</p>
            <p>For <q>regular</q> offences where prosecution by the special court was primarily
               based on very specific paragraphs of regular codified criminal law, similar
               correspondences between the categorisation approaches can be determined. Overall, for
               the diachronic analysis of the 1970s <title rend="quotes">Archive Inventory</title>
               regarding the various legal sources used as a basis for the NS Special Court
               proceedings, this at least partial factual correspondence of the
               pragmatic-explorative categorisation carried out along semantic terms with certain
               laws, ordinances, or even certain legal paragraphs helps to gain a better
               understanding for the source material as well as for a more thorough reflection on
               what the categories represent. This enables us to choose the most suitable approach
               for different questions and also to better take into account the necessary
               theoretical background (cf. above, remarks on categorisation). </p>
            <p>Through the different categorisation approaches, all of which took into account the
               various theoretical considerations of categorisation as initially stated in this
               paper, we now have templates for processing those inquiries. Next steps also include
               a refinement of the extracted information from the hOCR files in order to maximise
               the number of valid cases that can be incorporated in the analysis as well as to get
               a more accurate picture of categorising them. Successful categorisation – not only of
               charges but of other relevant information such as results of the proceedings – also
               provides the basis for more far-reaching analyses. For example, it is planned to
               conduct correspondence analyses on different aspects, like (in-)dependencies between
               socio-demographic markers and charges as well as results. The workflow initially
               adopted the terminology used in the 1970s which is essentially based on the source
               terms and not yet on a controlled and reduced vocabulary. Since
               statistical/quantitative in-depth analyses are not very fruitful when based on a
               large number of source terms as they tend to be less significant and more confusing
               in the (visual) representation, data has to be aggregated employing different kinds
               of categories, for instance on questions of social status or professions. For this
               paper, we focused on accusations. Yet, our considerations apply analogously to other
               categories to be formed. The presented deliberations on categorisation are to be
               understood in preparation for the upcoming historical investigation of the data with
               the help of this kind of statistical method.</p>
            <p>Notes</p>
            <p>[1] Authors are listed in alphabetical order. </p>
            <p>[2] Before unstitching the books and using an overhead book scanner instead of a
               document feeder scanner, we were able to extract only 7,778 out of 9,955 inventory
               records. Eliminating page warping and skew in the digitised images allowed us to
               extract an additional 753 inventory records and improve our result by 8 %.</p>
            <p>[3] We would like to thank Andreas Einwiller for programming a Python script
               extracting JSON records from hOCR-files.</p>
            <p>[4] A detailed overview of all National Socialist special penal regulations enacted
               in the years 1933–1944 can be found in: BayStMUK Part 7: Register 1, 1977, pp.
               2338–2346 <ptr target="#baystmuk19751977"/>.</p>
            <p>[5] <title rend="italic">Verordnung über außerordentliche Rundfunkmaßnahmen</title>,
               enacted on 1 September 1939; RGBl I 1939, Nr. 169, p. 1681.</p>
            <p>[6] As an example, the query part for E-1 presents itself as follows:
               WENN(ODER(ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("sittlich";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("Notzucht";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("Unzucht";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("züchtig";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("Abtreibung";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("Rauf";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("Mord";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("Raub";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("Kind";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("Totschlag";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("Tötung";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("Angriff";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("Körper";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("Drohung";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("Brand";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("erpress";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("vergew";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("Nötigung";[@[text_normalized]]));ISTZAHL(SUCHEN("spreng";[@[text_normalized]])));"1
               - bodily harm and morality"; [if part/subquery for next category follows]). </p>
            <p>[7] We would like to thank the <title rend="quotes">Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin ‒
                  Preußischer Kulturbesitz</title> for providing us with a larger corpus of similar
               language, namely the <title rend="italic">Entscheidungen des Reichsgerichts in
                  Zivilsachen</title> (RGZ, 1880–1945) and the <title rend="italic">Entscheidungen
                  des Reichsgerichts in Strafsachen</title> (RGSt, 1880–1945). Available at:
               https://staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/emedien-meldungen/rgz-rgst (Accessed: 02 December
               2022).</p>
            <p>[8] We selected a model trained on the RGZ/RGSt corpus using gensim’s Doc2Vec class
               supplying the following parameters: vector size=300, epochs=200, dm=1, hs=0,
               mincount=2, negative=5, sample=1e-4, window=2.</p>
            <p>[9] Clustering is sensitive to the distribution of data. Without knowing the
               distribution of data, the quality of clustering can be improved by normalising data
               using quantiles. Available at:
               https://developers.google.com/machine-learning/clustering/prepare-data (Accessed: 02
               December 2022).</p>

         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="apa1930" label="Animal Protection Act 1930"> Animal Protection Act. (1930)
                  <title rend="quotes"><q>Tierschutzgesetz</q> vom 24. November 1933</title> in
                  <title rend="italic">RGBl I 1933</title>, Nr. 132, pp. 987–989.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baierer2020" label="Baierer 2020">Baierer, Konstantin. (2020) hOCR – OCR
               Workflow and Output embedded in HTML. Available at: <ref
                  target="http://kba.github.io/hocr-spec/1.2/"
                  >http://kba.github.io/hocr-spec/1.2/</ref> (Accessed: 22 November 2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baystmuk19751977" label="BayStMUK 1975–1977">BayStMUK. (1975–1977)
               Widerstand und Verfolgung in Bayern 1933–1945. Hilfsmittel, im Auftrag des
               Bayerischen Staatsministeriums für Unterricht und Kultus (BayStMUK), herausgegeben
               von der Generaldirektion der Staatlichen Archive Bayerns. Archivinventare, Bd. 3:
               Sondergericht München, 7 Teile. München: Eigendruck des Staatsarchivs München /
               Buchbindung Schmidkonz Regensburg.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bod2018" label="Bod 2018">Bod, Rens. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Modelling
                  in the Humanities: Linking Patterns to Principles</title> in Ciula, Arianna et al.
               (ed.) <title rend="italic">Models and Modelling between Digital and Humanities – A
                  Multidisciplinary Perspective</title>. <title rend="italic">Historical Social
                  Research Supplement</title>, 31, pp. 78–95.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bracher1960" label="Bracher 1960">Bracher, Karl Dietrich. (1960) <title
                  rend="quotes">Stufen der Machtergreifung</title> in Bracher, Karl Dietrich, Sauer,
               Wolfgang, and Schulz, Gerhard (ed.) <title rend="italic">Die nationalsozialistische
                  Machtergreifung. Studien zur Errichtung des totalitären Herrschaftssystems in
                  Deutschland 1933/34</title>. Köln: Westdeutscher Verlag, pp. 31–368.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="christians2020" label="Christians 2020">Christians, Annemone. (2020)
                  <title rend="italic">Das Private vor Gericht. Verhandlungen des Eigenen in der
                  nationalsozialistischen Rechtspraxis</title>. Göttingen: Wallstein Verlag.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="donig_rehbein2022" label="Donig and Rehbein 2022">Donig, Simon and
               Rehbein, Malte. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Für eine <q>gemeinsame digitale
                     Zukunft</q>. Eine kritische Verortung der Digital History</title> in <title
                  rend="italic">Geschichte in Wissenschaft und Unterricht</title>, 9/10, pp.
               527–545.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="doerner1998" label="Dörner 1998">Dörner, Bernward. (1998) <title
                  rend="italic"><q>Heimtücke</q>: Das Gesetz als Waffe. Kontrolle, Abschreckung und
                  Verfolgung in Deutschland 1933–1945</title>, Paderborn / München / Wien / Zürich:
               Ferdinand Schöningh.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="durkheim_mauss1901" label="Durkheim and Mauss 1901">Durkheim, Emile and
               Mauss, Marcel. (1901) <title rend="quotes">DE QUELQUES FORMES PRIMITIVES DE
                  CLASSIFICATION. CONTRIBUTION A L’ÉTUDE DES REPRÉSENTATIONS COLLECTIVES</title> in
                  <title rend="italic">L’Année sociologique</title>, 6, pp. 1–72.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="esteretal1996" label="Ester et al. 1996">Ester, Martin, Kriegel,
               Hans-Peter, Sander, Jörg, and Xu, Xiaowei. (1996) <title rend="quotes">A
                  density-based algorithm for discovering clusters in large spatial databases with
                  noise</title> in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Second International
                  Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining</title> (KDD'96), pp.
               226–231.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="feuerbach1801" label="Feuerbach 1801">Feuerbach, Paul Johann Anselm [von].
               (1801) <title rend="italic">Lehrbuch des gemeinen in Deutſchland geltenden Peinlichen
                  Rechts</title>. Gießen: Georg Friedrich Heyer.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fichte1966" label="Fichte 1966/70">Fichte, Johann Gottlieb. (1966/70)
                  <title rend="quotes">Grundlage des Naturrechts nach Prinzipien der
                  Wissenschaftslehre</title> [first edition 1796] in Jacob, Hans and Lauth, Reinhard
               (ed.) <title rend="italic">J. G. Fichte-Gesamtausgabe der Bayerischen Akademie der
                  Wissenschaften</title>. Stuttgart-Bad Canstatt: Friedrich Frommann Verlag (Günther
               Holzboog), Werke, Vol. 3: pp. 291–460, Vol. 4: pp. 1–166.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="froelich1983" label="Fröhlich 1983">Fröhlich, Elke. (1983) <title
                  rend="italic">Die Herausforderung des Einzelnen. Geschichten über Widerstand und
                  Verfolgung</title> (= Bayern in der NS Zeit. Herausgegeben von Martin Broszat und
               Elke Fröhlich, VI). München / Wien: R. Oldenbourg Verlag.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="garbe1999" label="Garbe 1999">Garbe, Detlef. (1999) <title rend="italic"
                  >Zwischen Widerstand und Martyrium. Die Zeugen Jehovas im <q>Dritten
                  Reich</q></title> (= Studien zur Zeitgeschichte, 42), 4th edition. München: R.
               Oldenbourg Verlag.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gemoll2006" label="Gemoll 2006">Gemoll. (2006) <title rend="italic"
                  >Griechisch-deutsches Schul- und Handwörterbuch von W. Gemoll und K.
                  Vretska</title>, 10th edition. München / Düsseldorf / Stuttgart: Oldenbourg
               Schulbuchverlag GmbH.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gerstmeier2022" label="Gerstmeier et al. 2022">Gerstmeier, Markus, Donig,
               Simon, Gassner, Sebastian, and Rehbein, Malte. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Die
                  Archivinventare zum Sondergericht München (1933–1945) digital. Quellenwert –
                  Verdatung – Erkenntnisperspektiven</title> in <title rend="italic">Archivalische
                  Zeitschrift</title>, 99 (1), pp. 215–251.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ginzburg_poni1991" label="Ginzburg and Poni 1991">Ginzburg, Carlo and
               Poni, Carlo. (1991) <title rend="quotes">The Name and the Game. Unequal Exchange and
                  the Historiographic Marketplace</title> in Muir, Edward Wallace and Ruggiero,
               Guido (ed.) <title rend="italic">Microhistory and the Lost Peoples of Europe</title>.
               Selections from Quaderni storici. Baltimore: MD, pp. 1–10. Available at: <ref
                  target="http://opac.regesta-imperii.de/id/2114403"
                  >http://opac.regesta-imperii.de/id/2114403</ref> (Accessed: 22 November
               2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="graczyk2021" label="Graczyk 2021">Graczyk, Konrad. (2021) <title
                  rend="italic">Ein anderes Gericht in Oberschlesien. Sondergericht Kattowitz
                  1939–1945</title> (= Beiträge zur Rechtsgeschichte des 20. Jahrhunderts, 119).
               Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="graham_milligan_weingart2016" label="Graham, Milligan, and Weingart 2016"
               >Graham, Shawn, Milligan, Ian, and Weingart, Scott B. (2016) <title rend="italic"
                  >Exploring big historical data. The historian's macroscope</title>. London:
               Imperial College Press. Available at: <ref target="http://www.themacroscope.org/2.0/"
                  >http://www.themacroscope.org/2.0/</ref> (Accessed: 22 November 2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gruchmann2001" label="Gruchmann 2001">Gruchmann, Lothar. (2001) <title
                  rend="italic">Justiz im Dritten Reich 1933–1940. Anpassung und Unterwerfung in der
                  Ära Gürtner</title> (= Quellen und Darstellungen zur Zeitgeschichte, 28), 3rd
               edition. München: R. Oldenbourg Verlag.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hackl2022" label="Hackl 2022">Hackl, Gabriele. (2022) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Über das Mögliche urteilen. Urteilsfindung in Kriegswirtschaftsverfahren vor dem
                  Sondergericht Wien</title> in Ruby, Sigrid and Krause, Anja (ed.) <title
                  rend="italic">Sicherheit und Differenz in historischer Perspektive / Security and
                  Difference in Historical Perspective</title>. Baden-Baden: Nomos Verlag, pp.
               241–259.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="harris2020" label="Harris 2020">Harris, Charles R. et al. (2020) <title
                  rend="quotes">Array programming with NumPy</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Nature</title>, 585(7825), pp. 357–362. Available at <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2649-2"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2649-2</ref> (Accessed: 03 December
               2020).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="heimtueckgesetz1934" label="Heimtückegesetz 1934">Heimtückegesetz. (1934)
                  <title rend="quotes">Gesetz gegen heimtückische Angriffe auf Staat und Partei und
                  zum Schutz der Parteiuniformen, 29 December 1934</title> in <title rend="italic"
                  >RGBl I 1933</title>, Nr. 137, pp. 1269–1271, preceeded by the <title
                  rend="quotes">Verordnung des Reichspräsidenten zur Abwehr heimtückischer Angriffe
                  gegen die Regierung der nationalen Erhebung, 21 March 1933</title> in <title
                  rend="italic">RGBl I 1933</title>, Nr. 24, p. 135.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hensle2005" label="Hensle 2005">Hensle, Michael. (2005) <title
                  rend="italic"><q>Rundfunkverbrechen</q> vor nationalsozialistischen
                  Sondergerichten. Eine vergleichende Untersuchung der Urteilspraxis in der
                  Reichshauptstadt Berlin und der südbadischen Provinz</title>. Von der Fakultät I
               Geisteswissenschaften der Technischen Universität Berlin genehmigte Dissertation zur
               Erlangung des akademischen Grades Doktor der Philosophie (2001). Available at: DOI
               10.14279/depositonce-1208 (Accessed: 22 November 2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hollandetal1986" label="Holland et al. 1986">Holland, John H., Holyoak,
               Keith J., Nisbett, Richard E., and Thagard, Paul R. (1986) <title rend="italic"
                  >Induction: Processes of Inference, Learning, and Discovery</title>. Cambridge,
               Massachusetts: MIT Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="huettenberger1981" label="Hüttenberger 1981">Hüttenberger, Peter. (1981)
                  <title rend="quotes">Heimtückefälle vor dem Sondergericht München
                  1933–1939</title> in Broszat, Martin, Fröhlich, Elke, and Grossmann, Anton (ed.)
                  <title rend="italic">Bayern in der NS-Zeit IV: Herrschaft und Gesellschaft im
                  Konflikt, Teil C</title>. München / Wien: R. Oldenbourg Verlag, pp.
               435–526.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kant1904" label="Kant 1787/1904">Kant, Immanuel. (1787/1904) <title
                  rend="quotes">Kritik der reinen Vernunft. Zweite, hin und wieder verbeſſerte
                  Auflage</title> in Preußische Akademie der Wissenschaften (ed.) <title
                  rend="italic">Kant‘s gesammelte Schriften, Band III</title>. Berlin:
               Reimer.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kelsen2017" label="Kelsen 2017">Kelsen, Hans. (2017) <title rend="italic"
                  >Reine Rechtslehre</title> [first edition: Leipzig / Wien 1934]. Mit einem Anhang:
               Das Problem der Gerechtigkeit. Studienausgabe der 2. Auflage 1960, ed. by Matthias
               Jestaedt. Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="klemperer1947" label="Klemperer 1947/2020">Klemperer, Victor. (1947/2020)
                  <title rend="italic">LTI. Tagebuch eines Philologen. Herausgegeben von Elke
                  Fröhlich</title>. Stuttgart: Philipp Reclam Jun. [first edition: Berlin:
               Aufbau-Verlag]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lahusen2022" label="Lahusen 2022">Lahusen, Benjamin. (2022) <title
                  rend="italic">Der Dienstbetrieb ist nicht gestört. Die Deutschen und ihre Justiz
                  1943–1948</title>. München: C. H. Beck.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lau_baldwin2016" label="Lau and Baldwin 2016">Lau, Jey Han and Baldwin,
               Timothy. (2016) <title rend="quotes">An Empirical Evaluation of doc2vec with
                  Practical Insights into Document Embedding Generation</title>. arXiv. Available
               at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.1607.05368"
                  >https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.1607.05368</ref> (Accessed: 02 December
               2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="le_mikolov2014" label="Le and Mikolov 2014">Le, Quoc V. and Mikolov,
               Tomas. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Distributed Representations of Sentences and
                  Documents</title>. arXiv. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://arxiv.org/abs/1405.4053v2">https://arxiv.org/abs/1405.4053v2</ref>
               (Accessed: 02 December 2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mckinney2010" label="McKinney 2010">McKinney, Wes. (2010) <title
                  rend="quotes">Data Structures for Statistical Computing in Python</title> in
                  <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 9th Python in Science Conference</title>,
               pp. 56–61. Available at: DOI 10.25080/Majora-92bf1922-00a (Accessed: 02 December
               2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mstgb1943" label="MStGB 1943">MStGB. (1943) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Strafrecht der deutschen Wehrmacht: Militärstrafgesetzbuch,
                  Kriegssonderstrafrechtsverordnung, Kriegsstrafverfahrensordnung,
                  Wehrmachtdisziplinarstrafordnung, Beschwerdeordnung, Sondergerichtsbarkeit für
                  Angehörige der SS und Polizeiverbände, Reichsstrafgesetzbuch und zahlreiche andere
                  Bestimmungen</title>. München: C. H. Beck.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oehler1997" label="Oehler 1997">Oehler, Christiane. (1997) <title
                  rend="italic">Die Rechtsprechung des Sondergerichts Mannheim 1933–1945</title> (=
               Freiburger Rechtsgeschichtliche Abhandlungen. Neue Folge, 25). Berlin: Duncker and
               Humblot.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ordinance1939" label="Ordinance on War Economy 1939">Ordinance on War
               Economy. (1939) <title rend="quotes"><q>Kriegswirtschaftsverordnung</q> vom 4.
                  September 1939</title> in <title rend="italic">RGBl I 1939</title>, Nr. 163, pp.
               1609–1613 and 1700.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pedregosaetal2011" label="Pedregosa 2011">Pedregosa, F. et al. (2011)
                  <title rend="quotes">Scikit-learn: Machine Learning in Python</title> in <title
                  rend="italic">Journal of Machine Learning Research</title>, 12, pp.
               2825–2830.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="penal1941" label="Penal Ordinance against Polish and Jews 1941">Penal
               Ordinance against Polish and Jews. (1941) <title rend="quotes"><title rend="quotes"
                     >Verordnung über die Strafrechtspflege gegen Polen und Juden in den
                     eingegliederten Ostgebieten</title> vom 4. Dezember 1941</title> in <title
                  rend="italic">RGBl I 1941</title>, Nr. 140, pp. 759–761.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rehurek_petr2010" label="Rehurek and Petr 2010">Rehurek, Radim and Sojka
               Petr. (2010) <title rend="quotes">Software Framework for Topic Modelling with Large
                  Corpora</title> in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the LREC 2010 Workshop on
                  New Challenges for NLP Frameworks</title>. Valletta: ELRA, pp. 45–50. Available
               at: <ref target="https://radimrehurek.com/gensim/index.html"
                  >https://radimrehurek.com/gensim/index.html</ref> (Accessed: 02 December
               2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="reichstagfire1933" label="Reichstag Fire Decree 1933">Reichstag Fire
               Decree. (1933) <title rend="quotes"><title rend="quotes">Verordnung des
                     Reichspräsidenten zum Schutz von Volk und Staat</title> vom 28. Februar
                  1933</title> in <title rend="italic">RGBl I 1933</title>, p. 83.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="reuletal2018" label="Reul et al. 2018">Reul, Christian et al. (2018)
                  <title rend="quotes">State of the Art Optical Character Recognition of 19th
                  Century Fraktur Scripts using Open Source Engines</title>. arXiv. Available at:
                  <ref target="http://arxiv.org/abs/1810.03436"
                  >http://arxiv.org/abs/1810.03436</ref> (Accessed: 15 November 2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rgbli1922" label="RGBl I 1922–1945">RGBl I. (1922–1945) <title
                  rend="italic">Deutsches Reichsgesetzblatt, Teil I, herausgegeben vom
                  Reichsministerium des Innern</title>. Berlin: Reichsverlagsamt.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rgst1880" label="RGSt 1880–1945">RGSt. (1880–1945) <title rend="italic"
                  >Entscheidungen des Reichsgerichts in Strafsachen. Herausgegeben von den
                  Mitgliedern des Gerichtshofes und der Reichsanwaltschaft</title>, 77 Volumes.
               Berlin – Leipzig: Verlag Veit und Comp. (Vol. 78, concerning 1945’s decisions, was
               published in 2007: Berlin – Boston: Verlag Walter de Gruyter). Available at: <ref
                  target="https://rgst-1staatsbibliothek-2berlin-1de-10099dfd10212.erf.sbb.spk-berlin.de/"
                  >https://rgst-1staatsbibliothek-2berlin-1de-10099dfd10212.erf.sbb.spk-berlin.de/</ref>
               (Accessed: 02 December 2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rgz1880" label="RGZ 1880–1945">RGZ. (1880–1945) <title rend="italic"
                  >Entscheidungen des Reichsgerichts in Zivilsachen 1880 bis 1945. Herausgegeben von
                  den Mitgliedern des Gerichtshofes und der Reichsanwaltschaft</title>, 173 Volumes.
               Berlin – Leipzig: Verlag Veit und Comp. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://rgz-1staatsbibliothek-2berlin-1de-10099dfd10212.erf.sbb.spk-berlin.de/"
                  >https://rgz-1staatsbibliothek-2berlin-1de-10099dfd10212.erf.sbb.spk-berlin.de/</ref>
               (Accessed: 02 December 2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="richter2021" label="Richter 2021">Richter, Hedwig. (2021) <title
                  rend="italic">Demokratie. Eine deutsche Affäre. Vom 18. Jahrhundert bis zur
                  Gegenwart</title>. Bonn: Bundeszentrale für politische Bildung.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rstgb1871" label="RStGB 1871, 1935">RStGB. (1871, 1935) <title
                  rend="italic">Strafgesetzbuch für das Deutsche Reich vom 15. Mai 1871</title> –
               appeared until 1945 in different editions, e. g. 1935: Strafgesetzbuch für das
               Deutsche Reich. Mit Erläuterungen und einem Anhang, enthaltend strafrechtliche
               Nebengesetze und Notverordnungen. Begründet von Julius von Staudinger. Neubearbeitet
               von Hermann Schmitt, 20th edition. München / Berlin: C. H. Beck.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schlumbohm_gribaudi1998" label="Schlumbohm and Gribaudi 1998">Schlumbohm,
               Jürgen and Gribaudi, Maurizio. (ed.) (1998) <title rend="italic">Mikrogeschichte –
                  Makrogeschichte. Komplementär oder inkommensurabel? Göttinger Gespräch zur
                  Geschichtswissenschaft</title> (= Göttinger Gespräche zur Geschichtswissenschaft,
               7). Göttingen: Wallstein-Verl.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schmitt1922" label="Schmitt 1922/2021">Schmitt, Carl. (1922/2021) <title
                  rend="italic">Politische Theologie. Vier Kapitel zur Lehre von der
                  Souveränität</title> [first edition 1922]. 11th edition. Berlin: Duncker und
               Humblot.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="seiffert2006" label="Seiffert 2006">Seiffert, Helmut. (2006) <title
                  rend="italic">Einführung in die Wissenschaftstheorie. Zweiter Band:
                  Geisteswissenschaftliche Methoden: Phänomenologie – Hermeneutik und historische
                  Methode – Dialektik</title>. 11th edition. München: C. H. Beck.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="slaughter1930" label="Slaughter Tax Act 1930">Slaughter Tax Act. (1930)
                  <title rend="quotes"><title rend="quotes">Gesetz zur Abgleichung des ordentlichen
                     Staatshaushalts (Nr. 48110)</title> vom 31. Oktober 1930</title> in <title
                  rend="italic">Gesetz- und Verordnungs-Blatt für den Freistaat Bayern</title>, Nr.
               34, München, 3. November 1930, pp. 327–332.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="smith2007" label="Smith 2007">Smith, Ray. (2007) <title rend="quotes">An
                  Overview of the Tesseract OCR Engine</title> in <title rend="italic">Ninth
                  International Conference on Document Analysis and Recognition (ICDAR
               2007)</title>, 2. Curitiba, Parana, Brazil: IEEE, pp. 629–633. Available at: <ref
                  target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/4376991/"
                  >http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/4376991/</ref> (Accessed: 15 November
               2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tll1906" label="TLL 1906–1912">TLL. (1906–1912) <title rend="italic"
                  >Thesavrvs lingvae Latinae, Vol. III: C – Comvs, ed. avctoritate et consilio
                  academiarvm qvinqve Germanicarvm: Berolinensis, Gottingensis, Lipsiensis,
                  Monacensis, Vindobonensis</title>. Lipsiae: In aedibvs B. G. Tevbneri.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vandermaaten_hinton2008" label="van der Maaten and Hinton 2008">van der
               Maaten, L. J. P. and Hinton, G. E. (2008) <title rend="quotes">Visualizing
                  High-Dimensional Data Using t-SNE</title> in <title rend="italic">Journal of
                  Machine Learning Research</title>, 9, pp. 2579–2605.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="verordnung1933" label="Verordnung 1933">Verordnung. (1933) <title
                  rend="quotes"><title rend="quotes">Verordnung der Reichsregierung über die Bildung
                     von Sondergerichten</title> vom 21. März 1933</title> in <title rend="italic"
                  >RGBl I 1933</title>, Nr. 24, pp. 136–138.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="volksschaedlingsverordnung1939" label="Volksschädlingsverordnung 1939"
               >Volksschädlingsverordnung. (1939) <title rend="quotes"><title rend="quotes"
                     >Verordnung gegen Volksschädlinge</title> vom 5. September 1939</title> in
                  <title rend="italic">RGBl 1939 I</title>, Nr. 168, p. 1679.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="weber_piazolo1998" label="Weber and Piazolo 1998">Weber, Jürgen and
               Piazolo, Michael. (1998) <title rend="quotes">Parteisoldaten in Richterrobe</title>
               in Weber, Jürgen and Piazolo, Michael (ed.) <title rend="italic">Justiz im Zwielicht.
                  Ihre Rolle in Diktaturen und die Antwort des Rechtsstaates</title>. München:
               Olzog, pp. 11–22.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wehler1972" label="Wehler 1972">Wehler, Hans-Ulrich. (ed.) (1972) <title
                  rend="italic">Geschichte und Soziologie</title>. Köln: Kiepenheuer und
               Witsch.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wehrkraftverordnung1939" label="Wehrkraftverordnung 1939"
               >Wehrkraftverordnung. (1939) <title rend="quotes"><title rend="quotes">Verordnung zur
                     Ergänzung der Strafvorschriften zum Schutze der Wehrkraft des Deutschen
                     Volkes</title> vom 25. November 1939</title> in <title rend="italic">RGBl I
                  1939</title>, Nr. 238, p. 3219.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wick_reul_puppe2018" label="Wick, Reul, and Puppe 2018">Wick, Christoph,
               Reul, Christian, and Puppe, Frank. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Calamari. A
                  High-Performance Tensorflow-based Deep Learning Package for Optical Character
                  Recognition</title>. arXiv. Available at: <ref
                  target="http://arxiv.org/abs/1807.02004">http://arxiv.org/abs/1807.02004</ref>
               (Accessed: 15 November 2022).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wildt2007" label="Wildt 2007">Wildt, Michael. (2007) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Das <q>Bayern-Projekt</q>, die Alltagsforschung und die
                  <q>Volksgemeinschaft</q></title> in Frei, Norbert (ed.) <title rend="italic"
                  >Martin Broszat, der <q>Staat Hitlers</q> und die Historisierung des
                  Nationalsozialismus</title>, Göttingen: Wallstein Verlag, pp. 119–129.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wildt2019" label="Wildt 2019">Wildt, Michael. (2019) <title rend="italic"
                  >Die Ambivalenz des Volkes. Der Nationalsozialismus als
                  Gesellschaftsgeschichte</title>, 2nd edition. Berlin: Suhrkamp.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wogersien2007" label="Wogersien 2007">Wogersien, Maik. (2007) <title
                  rend="quotes">Allgemeines <q>unpolitisches Strafrecht</q> als Kriegsstrafrecht vor
                  den Sondergerichten</title> in Daubach, Helia-Verena (ed.) <title rend="italic"
                     ><q>… eifrigster Diener und Schützer des Rechts, des nationalsozialistischen
                     Rechts …</q>. Nationalsozialistische Sondergerichtsbarkeit. Ein
                  Tagungsband</title> (= Juristische Zeitgeschichte Nordrhein-Westfalen, 15).
               Düsseldorf: Eigenverlag des Justizministeriums des Landes Nordrhein-Westfalen, pp.
               63–72.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
