<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">

  <!-- BEGIN TEI HEADER ELEMENTS -->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Another Type of Human Narrative: Visualizing Movement
          Histories Through Motion Capture Data and Virtual Reality</title>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Eugenia S. <dhq:family>Kim</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>The Hong Kong Academy for Performing Arts</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>eugeniakim@hkapa.edu</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Eugenia S. Kim is a Lecturer of Performing Arts Research at the Hong Kong Academy for
              Performing Arts. She received her PhD from the School of Creative Media, City
              University of Hong Kong where she created the movement history <title rend="italic"
                >Lithium Hindsight 360</title> by making use of Virtual Reality and Motion Capture
              technologies. Eugenia takes an interdisciplinary practice-based approach to her
              research which includes digital curation for dance and new media art.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
        <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
        <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000514</idno>
        <idno type="volume">015</idno>
        <idno type="issue">1</idno>
        <date when="2021-03-05">05 March 2021</date>
        <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
        <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
          <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
          <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at<ref
              target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
              >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
          <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2020-09-18" who="Taylor Arnold">Created file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <!-- END TEI HEADER ELEMENTS -->

  <!-- BEGIN TEXT -->
  <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
    <!-- FRONT TEXT -->
    <front>
      <dhq:abstract>
        <p>In this article I propose that motion capture (mocap) and virtual reality (VR) technology
          can be used to record and visualize movement histories as a supplement to oral histories
          or for when a memory is based in a embodied experience. One specific example would be the
          presentation of illness narratives. To illustrate this situation, I examine the concept of
          illness narratives, particularly those created by dance artists, and use my movement
          history, <emph>Lithium Hindsight 360</emph>, as a case study. This analysis comes from the
          perspective of a hybrid movement artist, VR creator, archivist and digital humanist, with
          first-hand experience of the challenges encountered when creating a movement history. The
          challenges are presented within the context of mocap recording, data curation, digital
          preservation and sustainability issues. I end this article by providing some basic
          practical strategies and recommendations for researchers who are new to documenting
          movement histories. </p>
      </dhq:abstract>
      <dhq:teaser>
        <p>In this article I propose that motion capture (mocap) and virtual reality (VR) technology
          can be used to record and visualize movement histories as a supplement to oral histories
          or for when a memory is based in a embodied experience.</p>
      </dhq:teaser>
    </front>

    <!-- BODY TEXT -->
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>Human narratives are one of the most compelling and versatile information sources. One
          specific category, oral histories, "play a unique role in to documenting cultural heritage
          and in preserving memories of historical and everyday events" <ptr target="#tebeau2013"/>.
          These verbal narratives have traditionally been recorded in audio, video and as written
          transcriptions. Based on the importance of how an oral history is performed <ptr
            target="#abrams2010"/> and of how much information physical gestures and facial
          expressions can convey <ptr target="#ritchie2003"/>, a question arises about whether the
          media formats listed above sufficiently capture all the nuances of non-verbal information.
          By extension, there is also a question of whether all memories can be verbalized and if
          other means of expression are better suited for communicating the content of those
          memories.</p>
        <p>The issue of performance and non-verbal information within an oral history poses a
          complex translation problem. Video recordings or "videohistory" helps capture physical
          movement and nuances that audio recordings and transcripts cannot <ptr
            target="#williams2011"/>. Furthermore, certain kinds of cultural experiences cannot be
          fully described using only words. A concrete example of this are descriptions of symbolic
          poses and gestures used for complicated rituals. Similarly, physical interactions between
          individuals and their reactions to situations also lose their nuance when described
          verbally or through controlled cinematography. From an ethical standpoint, voice and
          photographic images can be potentially compromising even if censored or modified. This may
          be important if a memory includes some form of physical trauma, distress or injury. Based
          on the notion that an oral history is the verbal recounting of an experience, then it
          could be posited that a movement history is a kinesthetic rendering of lived human
          experiences where identifying voice and visuals could be obscured if needed.</p>
        <p>With these factors in mind, I propose that the concept of a "movement history" be
          considered for memories that are based in physical embodied experiences which can be
          difficult to describe with only words or depict using photographs and video. This
          definition reflects Albert Lichtblau's statement that "physically active remembering also
          influences the narration, especially when psychology and mentality can be brought into
          contact with the past <ptr target="#lichtblau2011"/>. Additionally, I recommend that
          movement histories be captured and presented in a way which enables a viewer to see all
          angles and details of the movement rather than be restricted to a single angle or framing.
          It is currently easiest to achieve this effect by combining mocap and VR technology with
          the understanding that other technologies may be used in the future.</p>
        <p>I begin my exploration of this concept by reviewing how the evolution of oral history
          practices can lead to the creation of movement histories. For this article, I will focus
          on illness narratives expressed through somatic movement practices with my own movement
          history, <emph>Lithium Hindsight 360</emph> as a case study. Following that I offer some
          practical insights from my own experience as a motion capture (mocap) and virtual reality
          (VR) researcher to offer practical tips and relatively affordable technology solutions.
          One key issue will be the dissemination and accessibility of the mocap data as there is
          still a usability barrier in the form of technological devices. Additional resources
          tailored to content creators helping to maintain the movement dataset and accompanying
          visualization interfaces are also suggested.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Background</head>
        <p>The roots of this article started in my previous research on digital dance preservation.
          As a choreographer and digital archivist, I was intent on finding a practical way to
          preserve human movement as accurately as possible. At first I believed very strongly in
          all the existing preservation practices, whether it was collecting good metadata, using
          high quality video for documentation or ensuring that a repository followed the Open
          Archival Information System [OAIS] model. These practices worked well in the archives and
          libraries where I worked, but were not so feasible as an independent artist working alone.
          From an archivist's perspective it meant processing haphazardly maintained content. From a
          choreographer's perspective, it was frustrating to be unable to see and analyze all the
          nuances of how a dance work was performed.</p>
        <p>In 2013, I started to become more invested in the Boston dance community and its history
          since the 1950s. In an effort to fill gaps in the existing documentation, I was inspired
          by The Dance Oral History Project created by the New York Public Library <ptr
            target="#new2020"/>.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure01">
          <head>"Bebe Miller Interview, Excerpt." Source credit: New York Public Library. <ref
              target="https://www.nypl.org/audiovideo/bebe-miller-interview-excerpt"
              >https://www.nypl.org/audiovideo/bebe-miller-interview-excerpt</ref>.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>By luck, dance scholar Jeffrey Friedman happened to be teaching an oral history workshop
          in Boston around this time. Hearing him talk about dance-specific examples was very useful
          as I prepared to conduct my own interviews. Very quickly, however, I encountered the same
          problem that had plagued me for documenting dance: how does one verbally describe
          movements that defy words?</p>
        <p>This problem eventually formed the basis for my practice-based research on creating
          movement-based pathographies. My original motivation for using mocap and VR was to give
          patients and viewers alike a sense of privacy. After constructing my initial prototype,
          however, I realized another benefit. By using mocap data to create an animation viewable
          in VR, viewers could have complete freedom to examine the movement from any angle or
          distance. In some ways this meant a more unbiased form of moving image documentation in
          that the framing of the content had not been decided for the viewer.</p>
        <p>I also began to notice some similarities between illness narratives and pathographies
          with oral history which I address later in this article. The most obvious commonality is
          the autobiographical narrative based on an individual's memory. This common trait thus
          made me start to wonder about the possibility of movement-based equivalent to oral history
          – that is, a movement history.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Oral History into Movement History: Mutable Memories</head>
        <p>Oral history was originally considered the domain of historians and has since been
          adopted by a variety of disciplines such as ethnology, anthropology and sociology as well
          as used for social work and community-led projects <ptr target="#abrams2010"/>. For
          example, a local historical society may conduct oral histories to help a community learn
          about its past <ptr target="#baum1978"/>. Guidelines and instruction courses for how to
          conduct an oral history are available but there is technically no single correct way to
          engage in oral history <ptr target="#ritchie2003"/>. In terms of specific activities, Lynn
          Abrams describes oral history as consisting of three main components: 1) an interview
          process and product of interview, 2) research methodology and result of research process
          and 3) an act of recording and final record <ptr target="#abrams2010"/>.</p>
        <p>At the core of any oral history is a human memory. These memories usually reflect
          recollection of and/or commentary on significant events, although they may also be
          centered on daily life or more private events. The fact that these memories are not always
          precise <ptr target="#matusiak2017"/> can be seen as problematic or beneficial in that it
          can affect the accuracy and presentation of content. To avoid frustration, interviewers
          are encouraged to think of oral history as a shared responsibility with those whom they
          are interviewing <ptr target="#ritchie2003"/>. To that end, the extent to which an oral
          historian must gain the trust of their subjects is no small matter. When this trust is
          well-placed, a potential platform for communicating information through narratives is
          created. This platform can be useful for bringing awareness to marginalized communities
          and hidden histories <ptr target="#abrams2010"/>.</p>
        <p>Although visual content may help supplement verbal descriptions, the perspectives are
          often limited or curated by the documenter. Sometimes a lack of aural clarity or a need to
          adhere to "filmic language" can also interfere with accurately capturing all the
          information provided <ptr target="#williams2011"/>. Given the rapid developments in 21st
          century audio/video technology, it is increasingly easier to supplement oral histories
          with additional information or options for interaction. An example of this would be the
          University of Southern California Shoah Foundation's Dimensions in Testimony exhibition
          which combines holographic projections, voice recognition and natural-language processing
            <ptr target="#usc2020"/>. This immersive way of viewing and interacting with a subject
          speaking their oral history could generate a deeper understanding as it would allow users
          to change distance, angle and relationship to the subject. At the same time, the use of
          multimedia technology must make logical sense given the costs, logistics and ethics
          involved <ptr target="#hughes2015"/>.</p>
        <p>To address the issues of providing an enhanced viewing experience without being
          extravagant in one's technology choices, it may be useful to look to the field of dance
          for performance strategies that can help add nuance. The connection between dance and oral
          histories is that dances are a part of oral tradition that can be intangible and ephemeral
          in such a way that challenges the act of documentation itself <ptr target="#whatley2017a"
          />. Furthermore, "Dance also challenges other experts to think about devising imaginative
          methods or scoring, notating, annotating, and archiving a processual, somatic, and
          multisensory practice" <ptr target="#whatley2017a"/>. Since a movement history is still
          based on a personal memory, it would be logical to look at how somatic dance forms that
          embrace the unique attributes of an individual body for strategies on how to recall,
          express and perform embodied experiences in a physical manner.</p>
        <p>Somatic movement practices often require practitioners to explore the idiosyncrasies of
          their bodies and their relationship to other bodies in a way that generates a sort of
          autobiography. These movement practices can also be used to literally illustrate life
          events which leads to a form of double-layered autobiography. Improvisational methods may
          incorporate internal and/or external questioning which then becomes reminiscent of an oral
          history interview. The range of somatic movement practices range from the Asian
          disciplines of yoga and tai chi to more recent systems such as Feldenkrais and Body Mind
          Centering. Within that spectrum lie somatic dance forms that have become increasingly used
          for artistic expression: Authentic Movement, Contact Improvisation and Skinner Releasing
          Technique amongst others. Steve Paxton, founder of Contact Improvisation, was known for
          his Small Dance ritual which guides the individual to examine their own body. This
          self-examination was later part of Paxton's documentation about his process which
          essentially served a sort of autobiography of his body <ptr target="#corin2017"/>.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Bill T. Jones, who also used Contact Improvisation, created several solos
          based on both his own life events and his body's mechanics. Jones helped pioneer the
          combining of somatic movement practices with motion capture technology. The particular
          nature of Jones' works yielded what could be considered a type of movement history. An
          early example would be the 1999 Bill T. Jones collaboration with the Open Ended Group,
            <emph>Ghostcatching</emph>. Originally intended to challenge the boundaries of the human
          body <ptr target="#open2019"/>, <emph>Ghostcatching</emph> was not intentionally
          autobiographical but in the end took on autobiographical elements specific to Jones <ptr
            target="#open2019"/>.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure03">
          <head>"After Ghostcatching HD excerpts." Source credit: The OpenEndedGroup.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/26407428"/>
        </figure>
        <p>Similarly, the motion capture samples performed by Steve Paxton as part of his research
          on contact improvisation that started in 1986 and were released on DVD-ROM in 2008 were
          not necessarily autobiographical <ptr target="#corin2017"/>.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure04">
          <head>"STEVE PAXTON : MATERIAL FOR THE SPINE - DVDrom TRAILER." Source credit:
            Contredanse.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8CntWmA1YTw"/>
        </figure>
        <p>More recently, somatic movement experts such as Ruth Gibson are more consciously adapting
          their technique to the limitations of mocap systems <ptr target="#whatley2012"/> and
          taking a phenomenological approach to mocap recording for VR environments <ptr
            target="#kozel2018"/>.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure05">
          <head>"MAN A VR." Source credit: Ruth Gibson and Bruno Martelli.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/150828741"/>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>An Overview of Motion Capture, VR and Somatic Movement Practices</head>
        <p>The integration of new technologies into oral history practice is not unusual. Digital
          technology in particular can be integrated across all aspects of the process, whether it
          is in recording, archiving or disseminating content <ptr target="#boyd2011"/>. It is
          therefore reasonable to assume that oral history can evolve to the next level of
          incorporating virtuality. This is already present in projects such as the previously
          mentioned Dimensions in Testimony exhibition. Virtuality can be used for various purposes
          whether it is to increase access, create a sense of immersion, generate a sense of
          embodiment or any other number of reasons. For movement histories, the goal is to allow
          viewers to examine physical memories without being invasive to the source. To that end,
          mocap and VR can help create a safer way to view and interact with such content.</p>
        <p>Mocap data is extremely versatile in that it can be used for everything from scientific
          motion analysis to mainstream entertainment. Conceptually mocap has its roots in Eadweard
          Muybridge's animation experiments and Max Fleischer's rotoscope device <ptr
            target="#boucher2011"/>. Technologically, the systems used at the time of writing
          descend from motion tracking systems developed in the 1970s and 1980s. One such example
          are the point light displays developed by Gunnar Johansson <ptr target="#jensenius2013"/>.
          Since then a variety of systems have been released such as sensor-based systems that rely
          on accelerometers and camera-based optical systems using infrared markers. The latter type
          of system allows for reliable tracking and orientation of joints <ptr
            target="#jensenius2013"/> and accurate capture that enables a variety of data
          interpretation and facings <ptr target="#mccormick2020"/>.</p>
        <p>The visualization of this mocap data can also help with human movement analysis <ptr
            target="#whatley2017a"/>. Although mocap data can be visualized in both 2D and 3D
          spaces, the latter option allows viewers full rein over perspective within a 6DOF (degrees
          of freedom) interactive context. The term "6DOF" refers to the three directions in which
          the head can move (3DOF) combined with the three directions in which the body can move
          through space <ptr target="#cisneros2019b"/> An added benefit of VR is that it is fully
          immersive and therefore visual distractions can be eliminated. Untethered headsets such as
          the <emph>Oculus Quest</emph> provide additional freedom in movement. This adds to a sense
          of immersion which can be a useful element for supporting a narrative. Previous concerns
          about motion sickness and ergonomic issues <ptr target="#cobb1999"/> are being addressed
          through improved headset design, increased graphics computing power and a generally better
          understanding of VR design principles. Researchers such as Michael Madary and Thomas K.
          Metzinger have released recommendations for more ethical design <ptr target="#madary2016"
          /> and constant updates in software platforms and standards also contribute to an improved
          experience. Another benefit of using an immersive environment is the ability with which it
          is possible to blend both visual and aural media with sound playing as vital a role to
          immersion as visuals. This balance between types of media may help address Mark Tebeau's
          concerns about overemphasizing visual representations of oral histories and the need for
          novel ways of data visualization <ptr target="#tebeau2013"/>.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Illness Narratives in Oral History and Somatic Movement Practices</head>
        <p>The concept of phenomenology or "the experience of" is very relevant to memories. A
          specific type of memory rooted in phenomenology is the illness narrative. The purpose of
          an illness narrative is to share a patient's perspective on experiencing symptoms,
          treatment, stigma and other aspects of an illness <ptr target="#frank1995"/>. This
          perspective may agree or contrast with a medical professional's. Like oral histories,
          illness narratives can focus on specific incidents, lifelong stories or become part of a
          collection of multiple narratives. More importantly, certain types of patients such as the
          chronically ill can be categorized as part of a marginalized and/or silenced group who are
          able to regain their voice through sharing their stories <ptr target="#hawkins1999"/>.
          Abrams states that "Oral history was intended to give a voice to the voiceless, a
          narrative to the story-less and power to the marginalized" <ptr target="#abrams2010"/>.
          From this perspective, the collective experiences of patients can potentially reflect
          hidden truths about society.</p>
        <p>Within the history of medicine, the use of oral history has evolved significantly over
          time. Oral histories were initially conducted for male figures of influence in medicine
          before taking on a social history role in the 1970s and a supporting evidence role in the
          1990s <ptr target="#winslow2011"/>. It was the course of this evolution that the question
          of how to provide a patient's history as opposed to that of a doctor's came into
          existence. Scholars such as Arthur W. Frank and Arthur Kleinman would start to collect and
          analyze the narratives of patients while G.Thomas Couser would start to bring the term
          "pathography" forward into the 20th century.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure06">
          <head>"Narrating Disability Inside and Outside the Clinic: Beyond Empathy." Source credit:
            Centre for Culture and Disability Studies.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4w1fU-dr1qM"/>
        </figure>
        <p>Some debate would be spurred by Anne Hawkins' very specific definition of pathography in
          that it is limited to a written account of physical illness <ptr target="#hawkins1999"/>.
          Her approach would later be challenged by performing arts scholars such as Alex Mermikides
          and Gianna Bouchard who identified theatrical performance as a type of "embodied
          pathography" <ptr target="#mermikides2016"/>.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure07">
          <head>"Bloodlines: Dana Centre Performance 2013." Source credit: The Chimera
            Network.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mmQRrs3UsS4"/>
          <!--
          <dhq:passThroughCode><iframe width="560" height="315"
              src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mmQRrs3UsS4" frameborder="0"
              allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
            /></dhq:passThroughCode>
            -->
        </figure>
        <p>Kay Jamison's autobiography as a patient with bipolar disorder <ptr target="#jamison1996"
          /> and Kerry Davies' collection of mental patient narratives would also challenge the
          focus on physical illness <ptr target="#davies2001"/>. Most importantly, the recognition
          of the invisibility of patients <ptr target="#winslow2011"/> and how narratives can help
          with self-awareness and regaining personal agency <ptr target="#davies2001"/> elevates the
          importance of enabling patients to communicate their stories.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure08">
          <head>"Bipolar and me | Kay Redfield Jamison." Source credit: Wellcome Collection.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mhPAXpW6KhI"/>
          <!--
          <dhq:passThroughCode><iframe width="560" height="315"
              src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mhPAXpW6KhI" frameborder="0"
              allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
            /></dhq:passThroughCode>
            -->
        </figure>
        <p>Several traditional oral history collections currently exist, including several on mental
          health. They include the oral histories of disability and personal and mental health
          collections at the British Library <ptr target="#british2020"/>, the Australian
          Generations Oral History Project <ptr target="#monash2015"/> and the Schizophrenia Oral
          History Project <ptr target="#schizophrenia2020"/>. There also exist dance and other
          movement-based works which are based on a patient experiences. As an art form, illness
          narratives have been created and shared by professional dancers for centuries with classic
          examples being the madness scene in <emph>Giselle</emph> and a deathbed duet in
            <emph>Manon</emph>.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure09">
          <head>"Marianela Nuñez performs the Mad Scene in Giselle (The Royal Ballet)." Source
            credit: Royal Opera House.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ySHiD3-zDi0"/>
          <!--
          <dhq:passThroughCode><iframe width="560" height="315"
              src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ySHiD3-zDi0" frameborder="0"
              allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
            /></dhq:passThroughCode>
            -->
        </figure>
        <figure xml:id="figure10">
          <head>"Manon – Act III pas de deux (Sarah Lamb, Vadim Muntagirov; The Royal Ballet)."
            Source credit: Royal Opera House.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PSF7OPuJIGA"/>
          <!-- 
          <dhq:passThroughCode><iframe width="560" height="315"
              src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PSF7OPuJIGA" frameborder="0"
              allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
            /></dhq:passThroughCode>
            -->
        </figure>
        <p>As a non-dramatized account performed by a patient, however, illness narratives become
          subject to moral and ethical complications. In some cases, an illness is accompanied by
          feelings of helplessness, shame and/or stigma as expressed by Havi Carel in her account of
          struggling with lymphangioleiomyomatosis <ptr target="#carel2013"/>.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure11">
          <head>"Prof Havi Carel." Source credit: Royal College of Physicians.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SdY55718slU"/>
          <!--
          <dhq:passThroughCode><iframe width="560" height="315"
              src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SdY55718slU" frameborder="0"
              allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
            /></dhq:passThroughCode>
            -->
        </figure>
        <p>For attendees of Depression and Bipolar Support Alliance patient support meetings, the
          confidentiality requirement is a reminder that sharing identifying information about a
          patient may have negative consequences <ptr target="#dbsa2019"/>. The outcome is
          reminiscent of other marginalized or endangered communities where survival is dependent on
          obscuring identity. In a positive light, sharing an illness narrative can lead to greater
          understanding and advocacy for improvements in social infrastructure for patients.</p>
        <p>One of the pioneers in this area would be Anna Halprin. Although her solo works such as
            <emph>Portrait</emph>
          <ptr target="#halprin1977"/> were more intended to heal her own cancer rather than simply
          depict the experience of cancer, she would later proceed to create works about the
          experiences of others. One such work, <emph>Intensive Care: Reflections on Death and
            Dying</emph>
          <ptr target="#halprin2000"/>, is based on her husband's hospitalization. Similarly, Bill
          T. Jones' 1994 <emph>Still/Here</emph> is based on the stories of actual patients with
          life-threatening conditions <ptr target="#new2019"/>.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure12">
          <head>"ANNA HALPRIN: Intensive Care - Sea Ranch Dance Collective." Source credit: John
            Veltri and Marguerite Lorimer.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rSwOLWEK4Sk"/>
          <!--
          <dhq:passThroughCode><iframe width="560" height="315"
              src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rSwOLWEK4Sk" frameborder="0"
              allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
            /></dhq:passThroughCode>
            -->
        </figure>
        <figure xml:id="figure13">
          <head>"Still/Here." Please see video <ref
              target="https://www.numeridanse.tv/en/dance-videotheque/stillhere">here</ref>. Source
            credit: Numeridanse.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure12.jpg"/>
        </figure>
        <p>The contrast between <emph>Intensive Care</emph> and <emph>Still/Here</emph> lies in the
          ethical complications surrounding both pieces. In Halprin's case, she performs in a piece
          about someone with whom she had a close relationship with. <emph>Still/Here</emph>, on the
          other hand, is Jones' interpretation of stories that he collected from others before
          presenting it on the bodies of professional dancers. This question of whether such a
          deeply personal story should be depicted by an outsider calls to mind Susan Kozel's
          challenging of Daniel Dennett's notion of the heterophenomenologist <ptr
            target="#kozel2007"/>. While heterophenomenology is not inherently unethical, the value
          of such a practice becomes more questionable when the experiences of traditionally
          silenced and/or vulnerable populations are being presented through the lens of an external
          neutral observer.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Case study: Movement-based Pathography</head>
        <p>The concept of phenomenology is the central driver for illness narratives as evidenced by
          the research of aforementioned medical humanists Frank and Carel as well as S. Kay Toombs
          and others. Within narrative medicine, phenomenology refers to the experience of having an
          illness, whether referring to the sensation of symptoms, daily living and/or contextual
          experiences <ptr target="#carel2013"/>. It therefore makes sense to extend the narrative
          medicine approach to movement-based illness narratives regardless of documentation method.
          For my own work <emph>Lithium Hindsight 360,</emph> a set of somatic movement-based
          illness narratives about bipolar disorder, I referenced the VR ballet
            <emph>[pain]Byte</emph> developed by Genevieve Smith-Nunes <ptr target="#smith2018"/>.
          Both <emph>Lithium Hindsight 360</emph> and <emph>[pain]Byte</emph> are based on the lived
          experiences of their respective creators with an emphasis on community engagement.
          Anonymizing the identities of the mocap performers for ethical purposes was another common
          factor.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure14">
          <head>"pain[byte] VR on Vimeo." Source credit: Genevieve Smith-Nunes.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/241495760"/>
        </figure>
        <figure xml:id="figure15">
          <head>"Lithium Hindsight 360 Video Capture July 2019." Source credit: Eugenia S.
            Kim.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/350437712"/>
        </figure>
        <p>In order to generate the movement histories presented in <emph>Lithium Hindsight
            360</emph>, I combined several somatic movement practices to translate the experience,
          structure the movement and perform the memory. I chose this approach because I noticed
          that universally relatable physical gestures and movements being expressed by mental
          health patients while sharing their experiences in a group setting. Examples might include
          hand tremors, moving slowly due to exhaustion or agitated rapid gesticulation with the
          arms. For translating and structuring memories into movement, I adapted the Life Art
          Process to help me identify key positions and gestures with specific experiences. To do
          this, I first compiled a list of commonly known adolescent bipolar disorder symptoms, read
          the individual testimonials in medical reports and then tried to translate what I had
          read. Based on that experience, I decided that it was more appropriate to use my own
          bodily experience as a patient with bipolar disorder. This decision lead to the creation
          of two different scenes, "Symptoms" and "Maintenance".</p>
        <p>In "Symptoms", individual symptoms are depicted by a group of mannequins that resemble
          each other. They are anchored by a mannequin attempting to ask for help but unable to
          articulate its needs. Presenting the physical movements without an explanation of the
          symptom can make a viewer pause and rethink their previous understanding of what a mental
          health condition looks or feels like. For "Maintenance" viewers are taken through a
          standard day of waking up, taking medicine, anxiety over interacting with others,
          exhaustion from feigning good health and then the return to bed. This scene has a more
          traditional dance sequence as I used to dance to relieve anxiety and stress. The majority
          of the movement is more pedestrian to the point of almost looking like pantomime. Since
          the predominant physical feeling was the sensation of constantly falling apart, the avatar
          is also constantly shifting and appearing to disintegrate before stabilizing again.</p>
        <p>To perform and generate all of the movement, I used various forms of improvisation
          methods including Contact Improvisation and Authentic Movement to sequence the positions
          and gestures into a narrative. At this level, I was not thinking about using specific
          vocabulary from a technique. Instead I was adapting concepts such as initiating movement
          from an internal point or using a video camera as my "witness" rather than a person.
          Taking this approach helped me avoid "performing" or overdramatizing my movements.
          Finally, my own movement style or "voice" is influenced by martial arts forms such as tai
          chi. This results in movement that is alternatively fluid and percussive.</p>
        <p>Initially I had thought it would be better to translate the experiences of other patients
          with bipolar disorder as presented in medical reports similar to what Jones had done with
          his choreography. When I realized that this type of heterophenomenology exacerbates issues
          raised by Susan Kozel about agency and representation that could lead to silencing <ptr
            target="#kozel2007"/>, I made the decision to use my own movement history of being a
          patient. If this type of heterophenomenology is done in conjunction with patients then it
          may be ethically possible and accurate for a third party to portray the experiences of
          another even without a close personal relationship.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Practical Strategies and Considerations</head>
        <p>Two of the first assumptions that might come to mind when beginning a mocap and VR
          project is that it is very expensive or technically difficult to generate. In the earlier
          days of mocap and VR this would have been accurate given the experimental nature and
          limited access to technologies. As of 2020, there is a constantly growing range of
          consumer-level hardware and software tools that are still capable of producing high
          quality results. The simplification of user interfaces and procedures enables creators and
          researchers to think more holistically about their approach rather than having to become
          expert programmers and technicians. In this section I offer tips generated from
          discussions with some of the experts referenced in this article as well as my own personal
          experiences with multiple hardware systems and recording scenarios. For further details on
          tasks such as selecting a mocap system, data clean-up, preservation and getting started
          with a project, please see the Appendix.</p>
        <p>In terms of performance, the most important factor is to remember that there is a
          difference between documenting, performing and performing for documentation purposes.
          Subjects may need to exaggerate their movements slightly to avoid occlusion issues. This
          too depends on the type of system and the level of subtlety being captured. For example, a
          motion sensor like the Kinect can capture full-body, facial and finger data with a single
          device.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure16">
          <head>"Turning the Kinect into a motion-capture device." Source credit: Engadget.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_POTSkgARHc"/>
          <!--
          <dhq:passThroughCode><iframe width="560" height="315"
              src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_POTSkgARHc" frameborder="0"
              allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
            /></dhq:passThroughCode>
            -->
        </figure>
        <p>Using a marker-based system, however, allows for more detail refinement later in the
          visualization stage. Extra set-up time and warm up takes are also recommended as it allows
          the subject to become accustomed to the direct or indirect impact of a mocap system on
          their body. This is similar to the process of an interviewer engaging with their subject
          before conducting an oral history interview.</p>
        <p>Other useful strategies can be found in the work of dance movement researchers. In her
          overview of mocap dance, Kim Vincs reminds readers that concepts such as gravity, race,
          and gender can all be manipulated in post-production <ptr target="#vincs2015"/>. This
          manipulation eases the pressure for a "perfect" performance and provides the option of
          hiding certain physical traits. More technical factors such as pre-acceleration of the
          body and thinking in terms of motion trails rather than shapes may help with recording
          cleaner data. Movement artist-researcher Steph Hutchison conscientiously adapted her
          practice to the requirements of a mocap system to yield better results <ptr
            target="#hutchison2013"/>. One practical modification was in thinking of the markers on
          her body as "partners" to work with rather than struggle with.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure17">
          <head>"Recognition Steph Agent Avatars Blobs Tryptic Emergence." Source credit: Steph
            Hutchison.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure17.jpg"/>
        </figure>
        <p>At the time of writing, it is generally recommended to conduct shorter takes of a
          movement history for several technical reasons. The first is that a system can glitch out
          which would then affect the system calibration and therefore render the rest of the mocap
          data unusable. This glitching can happen regardless of whether an inertial, optical or
          other system is used. Another reason is that most human bodies have a limit for how long
          they can continuously move. A trained body may be able to move continuously for a long
          time whereas a less active person may be fatigued after several minutes. Finally a long
          take will lead to a larger file that may be harder for an animation software to process
          and visualize. The mocap recording process will usually yield several files per session,
          so a consistent file naming scheme and stable storage system is essential. This may seem
          like a routine course of action but these steps can easily be forgotten when caught up in
          the moment or pressed for time. Finally, if a transcription and analysis of the movement
          is necessary, it may be useful to use systems such as Labanotation and Laban Movement
          Analysis. Both Labanotation and Laban Movement Analysis (LMA) were based on the work of
          modern dance pioneer Rudolf Laban <ptr target="#eddy2009"/>. Labanotation is a graphical
          method of notating movement while LMA is a method for describing the quality and
          motivation of movement. The two systems can be used together or separately.</p>
        <p>When recording, it is important to avoid simply documenting the memories through
          recording them and to remember that access, storage and preservation are part of this
          process as well <ptr target="#sant2017"/>. Although this fact may seem normal to any
          archivist, librarian or other information professional, it is not always obvious to
          laypersons. A significant difference between movement histories and artistic works using
          mocap is that a history focuses on authentically presenting what has been practiced or
          lived whereas artistic works typically strive to create a certain aesthetic or explore the
          differences between each performance of said work. Therefore the need to preserve multiple
          iterations of a history or striving for a technically perfect performance is
          eliminated.</p>
        <p>On a technical level, there are some challenges specific to the preservation of mocap
          data and VR projects. In 2006 it was already noted that the quantity of mocap data
          produced from a session could be quite large and was not easily searchable <ptr
            target="#hachimura2006"/>. <emph>WhoLoDancE</emph> repository tools have optimized
          searchability of movement to a certain degree <ptr target="#cisneros2019a"/> but a
          mainstream non-textual search engine has still yet to emerge in any discipline.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure18">
          <head>"WhoLoDancE: an overview." Source credit: WhoLoDancE.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="http://www.wholodance.eu/Videos/#lg=1&amp;slide=0"/>
        </figure>
        <p>From a VR perspective, one must decide whether to use an existing game engine such as
          Unity or engineer a bespoke solution. Further objects such as 3D models, texture maps,
          supplementary audio and video may also need to be taken into consideration. Fundamentally,
          the digital curation of movement histories comprised of mocap data and VR projects is the
          same as for any other set of digital objects in that standardized file formats (i.e. fbx,
          bvh) used across multiple industries are typically used for the source objects. If
          anything, the most challenges lie in the lack of a standard file format for gaming engines
          such as Unity and Unreal. Constant changes in both hardware and software also make it
          difficult to pinpoint a single ideal long-term (&gt;25 years) file format for any of the
          objects contained within a VR project.</p>
        <p>Given the rapid evolution of mocap and related technologies, the practical solution would
          be to focus on maintaining and migrating mocap data with the expectation that the
          visualization of that data will change over time. This is not to belittle the work that
          goes into creating VR environments. Instead, by focusing on movement as the primary source
          of information, the content can be made more accessible since it could be visualized in
          multiple ways. In an ideal setting, digital preservation practices such as using
          repositories built on the OAIS (Open Archival Information System) reference model and
          metadata standards would be expected. Implementing such practices, however, also comes
          with a significant cost <ptr target="#matusiak2017"/>. To help relieve the burden on data
          stewards, it may be useful for movement history creators to reference the strategies of
          existing artists' toolkits <ptr target="#skinner2015"/> and habits of new media artists
            <ptr target="#post2017"/>. Furthermore, the previously theoretical concept of networked
          digital archives <ptr target="#macdevitt2012"/> has already materialized in the form of
          widespread cloud computing services. The need for large and flexible storage space is
          better served by these services than traditional servers.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Conclusion and Future Evolutions</head>
        <p>In the past, the recording of mocap and its subsequent visualization was technically
          complicated and costly. The process of mocap is still not as simple as making an audio
          recording, but evolutions in digital technology certainly make it easier. Similar things
          could be said about VR as new tutorials, hardware sets and software solutions continue to
          be released. For the immediate future, the most frequent use of movement histories might
          be as a complementary pairing with oral histories. Examples include a voiceover
          accompanying an illness narrative using mocap or a written account of a traumatic event
          accompanied by movement illustrating key moments. A future concern for this type of
          visualization is that of enabling accessibility for the visually impaired <ptr
            target="#hughes2015"/>. In the future, haptics might be able to help resolve vision
          impairment or reliance on text by conveying a different type of a sensory information. The
          initial work conducted at Deakin Motion Lab and the Institute for Intelligent Systems
          Research and Innovation (IISRI) that integrates social haptics with dance to create an
          embodied experience through kinesthesia <ptr target="#mccormick2020"/> may well lead to
          being able to completely experiencing the physical memory of another individual.</p>
        <p>On a more personal level, I had two major revelations while constructing my own movement
          history. The first discovery was that the reactions to my LH360 experience often reflected
          more about a viewer's previous perceptions about mental health and the communities they
          came from than any truth or understanding about the experience being shown to them. In
          other words, it was possible to induce reflexivity and intersubjectivity through
          presenting abstracted movement in an immersive environment. Patients would express relief
          and motivation that someone else was sharing an experience similar to theirs. Non-patients
          would question their previous perceptions of mental health patients. As I had never
          encountered this kind of reaction when similar movement was presented as a live
          performance, I was extremely surprised by this result. Presenting the VR experience and
          the publications about it have also brought me into contact with a wide range of artists
          and researchers working on similar projects.</p>
        <p>These kinds of connections and discoveries are why I became an interdisciplinary
          practice-based researcher in the arts rather than an artist, archivist or other type of
          humanities researcher. Traditionally, artistic practice is supposed to speak for itself
          through the artistic work itself and academic research should be presentable through
          textual publications. Yet there are still forms of human-generated content that are too
          multi-faceted to be presented using only one kind of media or without contextual
          information. The <emph>LH360</emph> development process relied on methodologies such as
          autoethnography, reflective practice and user experience design as well as an
          understanding of various artistic technique. Furthermore, I received comments that viewing
          the VR experience enhanced an understanding of its associated publications and vice versa.
          Based on my experience with creating <emph>LH360</emph>, I believe that forms of artistic
          expression can be utilized for purposes other than creating pure works of art or
          entertainment. The concept of an artistic practice-based researcher has been acknowledged
          in academic circles since the 1980s <ptr target="#candy2006"/>
          <ptr target="#nelson2013"/> which means that there are pioneers to look up to, a current
          peer community, and most likely an increase in this type of researcher. Regardless of
          whether one comes from an academic, artistic or hybrid approach, increasing developments
          in visual, aural, and haptic technologies should make it more feasible to reproduce
          non-verbal content that addresses all the senses. Over time, these innovations may lead to
          more multi-dimensional presentations of individual memories, historical events and entire
          cultures.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Appendix: Choosing Hardware and Software Options</head>
        <p>The first thing that researchers should consider is their choice of mocap system. Ideally
          the system should be chosen based on the type of movement recorded, frequently used body
          part(s), portability and need for anonymity. It may be tempting to choose a system for its
          cost, convenience or availability but this can later create problems. A comparison of
          several systems is provided below to illustrate how the attributes of a system could be
          problematic or simply not useful for a researcher. The information is a combination of
          general knowledge and my personal experience using the listed system. It is by no means an
          extensive listing of all systems currently available on the market. For a more detailed
          look into mocap systems, I recommend reading the white paper released by Epic Games in May
          2020.</p>
        <table xml:id="table01">
          <head/>
          <row>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">System</hi></cell>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Type/Description</hi></cell>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Unique Attributes</hi></cell>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Benefits</hi></cell>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Limitations</hi></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Microsoft Kinect</cell>
            <cell>Depth camera/Motion sensor device</cell>
            <cell>Originally a gaming device</cell>
            <cell>Excellent for point cloud effects. Very cheap to buy and easy to setup.</cell>
            <cell>May need multiple devices. Combining multiple data sources may require a custom
              software solution.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>HTC Vive Tracker</cell>
            <cell>Inertial/Repurposed trackers</cell>
            <cell>Repurposes part of the HTC Vive virtual reality headset package</cell>
            <cell>Very portable set-up. Can be used with third party software.</cell>
            <cell>The weight of the sensors affected ease of movement</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Notch Pioneer</cell>
            <cell>Inertial/Motion sensors strapped to body</cell>
            <cell>Individual sensors are attached to adjustable straps</cell>
            <cell>Easy to put on and customize location of sensors. Reasonably priced and
              expandable.</cell>
            <cell>Need smartphone or tablet for recording</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Perception Neuron</cell>
            <cell>Inertial/Wearable sensors in a suit</cell>
            <cell>Sensors are attached to a "suit" of straps.</cell>
            <cell>Fairly easy to put on and lightweight. Includes a comprehensive software
              platform.</cell>
            <cell>May require frequent calibration. Weight of the battery pack can affect movement.
              Requires wireless router setup.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Rokoko Smartsuit</cell>
            <cell>Inertial/Wearable sensors in a suit</cell>
            <cell>Can be used almost anywhere.</cell>
            <cell>Suit is comfortable and well-constructed. Price is about the same as a high-end
              laptop. Can be combined with face and hand mocap devices.</cell>
            <cell>Separate suits need to be purchased for each person/size. Same battery pack and
              wireless router issue as Neuron. Cannot accurately measure changes in levels.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Optitrack Prime</cell>
            <cell>Optical/Passive markers (reflective)</cell>
            <cell>Comes in multiple configuration options.</cell>
            <cell>Very good software and easy calibration. Can do almost any kind of motion with
              ease. Easy to use data clean-up tool.</cell>
            <cell>The most expensive option. Requires a lot of resources (i.e. computing,
              electricity, space). Good technician with knowledge of marker setups, calibration,
              etc. is essential.</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <p>Another aspect to consider about choosing a hardware system is the software platform that
          accompanies it as well as the external software platforms that the hardware can interface
          with. Software can affect how cleanly motion is captured, provide easier ways to clean up
          and manipulate the data, or even enable faster sharing. In some situations, the hardware
          may not be the most robust, but the software makes the rest of the process easier. Most
          systems will come with their own proprietary software or require use of a licensed
          program. Ultimately the final decision should take into consideration whether one is
          recording full body large movements or smaller subtle movements, whether identity is an
          issue, if factual accuracy is required or if emotional expressiveness is the main
          priority.</p>
        <p>Just like with any other data set, mocap data clean-up is extremely time consuming. The
          clean-up process usually consists of manipulating coordinates using either a linear graph
          editor or actual points in 3D space. While there are tools to help automate the process it
          is useful for researchers to review the raw capture and the cleaned-up version to ensure
          that vital details are not accidentally erased. By contrast, mapping the data to a 3D
          model to generate an animation can be relatively quick so long as the skeleton has been
          properly mapped.</p>
        <p>Based on existing practices from commercial industry as balanced by financial
          limitations, I would recommend the following hardware, software, digital object and
          project planning starting points for researchers engaging in mocap and VR for the first
          time. Factors include cost of renting or purchasing a mocap system, personnel time and
          compensation and whether the project is being worked on a full or part-time basis.</p>
        <table xml:id="table02">
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="bold">Ideal Expensive Setup</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="bold">Moderate Investment Setup</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="bold">Basic Setup</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <list>
                <item>Marker-based/optical system with knowledgeable technician (Optitrack is
                  good)</item>
                <item>Programmer with knowledge of Unity or other visualization software</item>
                <item>3D modeler for custom figure and environment</item>
                <item>At least 2 sessions at 2 hours each for a short recording</item>
                <item>3 months of dedicated time for visualization</item>
              </list>
            </cell>
            <cell>
              <list>
                <item>Portable sensor suit system</item>
                <item>Unity or software template</item>
                <item>A way to customize a stock 3D figure and environment</item>
                <item>At least 2 hours for the recording session</item>
                <item>3 months of partial time for visualization</item>
              </list>
            </cell>
            <cell>
              <list>
                <item>Notch, Vive or Kinect type system</item>
                <item>WebVR template using frameworks such as A-frame</item>
                <item>Stock 3D figure for free and mapped photos</item>
                <item>Keep interview very short and shoot as best as possible</item>
                <item>No deadline for completion of visualization</item>
              </list>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div>
    </body>

    <!-- BACK TEXT -->
    <back>
      <listBibl>
        <bibl xml:id="abrams2010" label="Abrams 2010">Abrams, L., <title rend="italic">Oral History
            Theory</title>. Milton Park and New York (2010).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="baum1978" label="Baum 1978">Baum, W.K., <title rend="italic">Oral History for
            the Local Historical Society,</title> Third Edition Revised. Nashville (1978).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="boucher2011" label="Boucher 2011">Boucher, M. ,<title rend="quotes">Virtual
            Dance and Motion-Capture</title>
          <title rend="italic">Contemporary Aesthetics,</title> 9. Available at: <ref
            target="https://contempaesthetics.org/newvolume/pages/article.php?articleID=614"
            >https://contempaesthetics.org/newvolume/pages/article.php?articleID=614</ref> [Accessed
          10 November 2019].</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="boyd2011" label="Boyd 2011">Boyd, D., <title rend="quotes">Achieving the
            Promise of Oral History in a Digital Age</title>,In Ritchie, D. (ed.), <title
            rend="italic">The Oxford Handbook of Oral History</title>, New York (2011), pp.
          285-302.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="british2020" label="British 2020">. The British Library. <title rend="quotes"
            >Oral Histories of Disability and Personal and Mental Health</title> Available at: <ref
            target="https://www.bl.uk/collection-guides/oral-histories-of-personal-and-mental-health-and-disability"
            >https://www.bl.uk/collection-guides/oral-histories-of-personal-and-mental-health-and-disability</ref>
          [Accessed 01 May 2020].</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="candy2006" label="Candy 2006">Candy, L. <title rend="quotes">Practice Based
            Research: A Guide. CCS Report: 2006-V1.0 November.</title>Available at: <ref
            target="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/257944497"
            >https://www.researchgate.net/publication/257944497</ref> [Accessed 27 February
          2020].</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="carel2013" label="Carel 2013">Carel, H., Illness: <title rend="italic">The Cry
            of the Flesh (The art of living),</title> New York (2013).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="cisneros2019a" label="Cisneros et al. 2019a">Cisneros, R.E., Stamp, K.,
          Whatley, S. and Wood, K. <title rend="quotes">WhoLoDancE: Digital tools and the dance
            learning environment</title>
          <title rend="italic">Research in Dance Education</title>, 20<title rend="italic"
          >.</title>1 (2019): 54-72.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="cisneros2019b" label="Cisneros et al. 2019b">Cisneros, R.E., Wood, K.,
          Whatley, S., Buccoli, M., Zanoni, M. and Sarti, A. <title rend="quotes">Virtual Reality
            and Choreographic Practice: The Potential for New Creative Methods</title>
          <title rend="italic">Body, Space and Technology</title>, 18.1 (2019): 1-32.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="cobb1999" label="Cobb 1999">. Cobb, S. V. G., Nichols, S., Ramsey, A. and
          Wilson, J. R. <title rend="quotes">Virtual reality-induced symptoms and effects
            (VRISE)</title>
          <title rend="italic">Presence</title>, 8.2 (1999):169–186.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="corin2017" label="Corin 2017">Corin, F. <title rend="quotes">Steve Paxton's
            Material for the Spine: The Experience of a Sensorial Edition.</title>In M. Bleeker
          (ed.), <title rend="italic">Transmission in Motion: The Technologizing of Dance</title>,
          London and New York (2017), pp. 32-40.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="davies2001" label="Davies 2001">. Davies, K. <title rend="quotes">Silent and
            Censured Travellers"? Patients' Narratives and Patients' Voices: Perspectives on the
            History of Mental Illness since 1948</title>
          <title rend="italic">Social History of Medicine</title>, 14.2 (2001): 267-92.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="dbsa2019" label="DBSA 2019">Depression and Bipolar Support Alliance: DBSA.
            <title rend="quotes">DBSA SUPPORT GROUPS: An Important Step on the Road to
            Wellness</title> Available at: <ref
            target="https://www.dbsalliance.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/DBSA_SUPPORT_GROUPS.pdf"
            >https://www.dbsalliance.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/DBSA_SUPPORT_GROUPS.pdf</ref>
          [Accessed 13 May 2020].</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="eddy2009" label="Eddy 2009">Eddy, M. <title rend="quotes">A brief history of
            somatic practices and dance: historical development of the field of somatic education
            and its relationship to dance</title>
          <title rend="italic">Journal of Dance and Somatic Practices</title>, 1.1(2009):
          5-27.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="frank1995" label="Frank 1995">Frank, A. W. <title rend="italic">The Wounded
            Storyteller: Body, Illness, and Ethics</title>. Chicago (1995).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="hachimura2006" label="Hachimura 2006">Hachimura, K. <title rend="quotes"
            >Digital Archiving of Dancing</title>
          <title rend="italic">Review of the National Center for Digitization</title>, 8 (2006):
          51-66.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="halprin1977" label="Halprin 1977">Halprin, A. <title rend="quotes"
            >Portrait.</title>Available at: <ref
            target="https://digitalcollections.nypl.org/items/65a512d0-aa03-0133-bcae-60f81dd2b63c"
            >https://digitalcollections.nypl.org/items/65a512d0-aa03-0133-bcae-60f81dd2b63c</ref>
          [Accessed 22 November 2019].</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="halprin2000" label="Halprin 2000">Halprin, A. <title rend="quotes">Intensive
            Care, Reflections on Death and Dying.</title>Available at: <ref
            target="https://digitalcollections.nypl.org/items/3bcc1450-342a-0131-a70d-685b35830967"
            >https://digitalcollections.nypl.org/items/3bcc1450-342a-0131-a70d-685b35830967</ref>
          [Accessed 22 November 2019].</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="hawkins1999" label="Hawkins 1999">Hawkins, A. H. <title rend="italic"
            >Reconstructing Illness: Studies in Pathography</title> , 2nd edition, West Lafayette
          (1999).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="hibbitts2020" label="Hibbitts 2020">Hibbitts, D. "Choosing a real-time
          performance capture system." Available from: <ref
            target="https://cdn2.unrealengine.com/Unreal+Engine/performance-capture-whitepaper/LPC_Whitepaper_final-7f4163190d9926a15142eafcca15e8da5f4d0701.pdf"
            >https://cdn2.unrealengine.com/Unreal+Engine/performance-capture-whitepaper/LPC_Whitepaper_final-7f4163190d9926a15142eafcca15e8da5f4d0701.pdf</ref>
          [Accessed on May 29, 2020].</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="hughes2015" label="Hughes 2015">Hughes, J., <title rend="quotes">Taking the
            Leap: Including Video in Audio Oral Histories</title>
          <title rend="italic">Oral History Australia Journal</title>, 37 (2015): 63-71.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="hutchison2013" label="Hutchison and Vincs 2013">Hutchison S. and Vincs, K.
            <title rend="quotes">Dancing in Suits: A Performer's Perspective on The Collaborative
            Exchange Between Self, Body, Motion Capture, Animation and Audience</title> in Leland,
          K., Fisher, L. and Harley, R. (eds.), <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 19th
            International Symposium of Electronic Art</title>, ISEA2013, Sydney (2013), pp.
          1-4.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="jamison1996" label="Jamison 1996">Jamison, K. R. <title rend="italic">An
            Unquiet Mind.</title> New York (1996).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="jensenius2013" label="Jensenius 2013">Jensenius, A. R. <title rend="quotes"
            >Some Video Abstraction Techniques for Displaying Body Movement in Analysis and
            Performance</title>
          <title rend="italic">LEONARDO</title>, 46.1 (2013): 53-60.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="kozel2007" label="Kozel 2007">Kozel, S. Closer: <title rend="italic"
            >Performance, Technologies, Phenomenology</title>. Cambridge (2007).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="kozel2018" label="Kozel et al. 2018">Kozel, S., Gibson, R., and Martelli, B.
            <title rend="quotes">The Weird Giggle: Attending to Affect in Virtual Reality</title>
          <title rend="italic">Transformations</title>, 31 (2018): 1-24.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="lichtblau2011" label="Lichtblau 2011">Lichtblau, A. <title rend="quotes">Case
            Study: Opening Up Memory Space: The Challenges of Audiovisual History.</title>In
          Ritchie, D. (ed.), <title rend="italic">The Oxford Handbook of Oral History</title>, New
          York (2011), pp. 277-284.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="macdevitt2012" label="MacDevitt 2012">MacDevitt, J. <title rend="quotes">The
            User-Archivist and Collective (In)Voluntary Memory: Read/Writing the Networked Digital
            Archive.</title>In Gardiner, H. and Bailey, C. (eds.), <title rend="italic"
            >Revisualising Visual Culture</title>, London (2012), pp. 109-124.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="madary2016" label="Madary and Metzinger 2016">Madary, M. and Metzinger, T. K.
            <title rend="quotes">Real virtuality: A code of ethical conduct; Recommendations for
            good scientific practice and the consumers of VR-technology</title>
          <title rend="italic">Frontiers in Robotics and AI</title>, 3.3 (2016): 1–23.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="matusiak2017" label="Matusiak et al. 2017">Matusiak, K. K., Taylor, A.,
          Newton, C., and Polepeddi, P. <title rend="quotes">Finding access and digital preservation
            solutions for a digitized oral history project: A case study</title>
          <title rend="italic">Digital Library Perspectives</title>, 33.2 (2017): 88-99.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="mccormick2020" label="McCormick et al. 2020">McCormick, J., Hossny, M.,
          Fielding, M., Mullins, J., Vincent, J.B., Hossny, M., Vincs, K., Mohamed, S., Nahavandi,
          S., Creighton, D. and Hutchison, S. <title rend="quotes">Feels Like Dancing: Motion
            Capture–Driven Haptic Interface as an Added Sensory Experience for Dance Viewing</title>
          <title rend="italic">LEONARDO</title>, 53.1 (2020): 45-49.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="mermikides2016" label="Mermikides and Bouchard 2016">Mermikides, A. and
          Bouchard, G. (Eds.). <title rend="italic">Performance and the Medical Body.</title> London
          (2016).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="monash2015" label="Monash 2015">Monash University, School of Philosophical,
          Historical and International Studies. <title rend="quotes">Australian Generations Oral
            History Project</title> Available at: <ref
            target="https://www.monash.edu/arts/philosophical-historical-international-studies/australian-generations"
            >https://www.monash.edu/arts/philosophical-historical-international-studies/australian-generations</ref>
          [Accessed 01 May 2020].</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="nelson2013" label="Nelson 2013">Nelson, R. <title rend="italic">Practice as
            Research in the Arts: Principles, Protocols, Pedagogies, Resistances</title>.
          Houndsmill, Pelgrave (2013).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="new2019" label="New York Live Arts 2019">New York Live Arts. <title
            rend="quotes">Still/Here | New York Live Arts</title> Available at: <ref
            target="https://newyorklivearts.org/repertory/stillhere/"
            >https://newyorklivearts.org/repertory/stillhere/</ref> [Accessed 24 November
          2019].</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="new2020" label="New York Public Library 2020">New York Public Library. <title
            rend="quotes">Dance Oral History Project</title> Available at: <ref
            target="https://www.nypl.org/oral-history-project-dance"
            >https://www.nypl.org/oral-history-project-dance</ref> [Accessed 24 April 2020].</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="open2019" label="Open Ended Group 2019">Open Ended Group. <title rend="quotes"
            >Ghostcatching</title> Available at: <ref
            target="http://openendedgroup.com/artworks/gc.html"
            >http://openendedgroup.com/artworks/gc.html</ref> [Accessed 24 November 2019].</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="post2017" label="Post 2017">Post, C. <title rend="quotes">Preservation
            Practices of New Media Artists: Challenges, Strategies, and Attitudes in the Personal
            Management of Artworks</title>
          <title rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title>, 73.4 (2017): 716-732.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="ritchie2003" label="Ritchie 2003">Ritchie, D.A. <title rend="italic">Doing
            Oral History: A practical guide</title>. Second Edition. New York, (2003).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="sant2017" label="Sant 2017">Sant, T. (ed) <title rend="italic">Documenting
            Performance : The Context and Processes of Digital Curation and Archiving</title>.
          London and New York (2017).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="schizophrenia2020" label="Schizophrenia Oral History Project 2020">The
          Schizophrenia Oral History Project. Available at: <ref
            target="https://schizophreniaoralhistories.com/"
            >https://schizophreniaoralhistories.com/</ref> [Accessed on 01 May 2020].</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="skinner2015" label="Skinner 2015">Skinner, C., Tyas, P., and Street, A. <title
            rend="italic">Artists in the archives toolkit: A toolkit for best practice</title>.
          Wiltshire (2015). Available at: <ref
            target="https://theartsinwiltshire.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/artist-archive-doc-final.pdf"
            >https://theartsinwiltshire.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/artist-archive-doc-final.pdf</ref>.
          [Accessed 1 October 2019].</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="smith2018" label="Smith 2018">Smith-Nunes, G., Shaw, A., and Neale, C. <title
            rend="quotes">PainByte: Chronic Pain and Biomedical Engineering Through the Lens of
            Classical Ballet &amp; Virtual Reality</title><title rend="italic">Proceedings of the
            Twelfth International Conference on Tangible, Embedded, and Embodied
          Interaction</title>, Stockholm, Sweden (March 2018).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="tebeau2012a" label="Tebeau 2012a">Tebeau, M. <title rend="quotes">Visualizing
            oral history - Oral history in the digital age - Case study: Visualizing oral
            history.</title>Lansing, 2012. Available at: <ref
            target="http://ohda.matrix.msu.edu/2012/06/visualizing-oral-history/"
            >http://ohda.matrix.msu.edu/2012/06/visualizing-oral-history/</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="tebeau2012b" label="Tebeau 2012b">Tebeau, M. <title rend="quotes">Case study:
            visualizing oral history</title>. In D. Boyd, S. Cohen, B. Rakerd, &amp; D.
            Rehberger (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Oral history in the digital
          age.</title> Institute of Library and Museum Services.Available at: <ref
            target="http://ohda.matrix.msu.edu/2012/06/visualizing-oral-history/"
            >http://ohda.matrix.msu.edu/2012/06/visualizing-oral-history/</ref> [Accessed 1 October
          2019]  </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="tebeau2013" label="Tebeau 2013">. Tebeau, M. <title rend="quotes">Listening to
            the city: Oral history and place in the digital era</title>
          <title rend="italic">Oral History Review</title>, 40.1 (2013): 25-35.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="usc2020" label="USC 2020">USC Shoah Foundation. <title rend="quotes"
            >Dimensions in Testimony</title> Available at: <ref target="https://sfi.usc.edu/dit"
            >https://sfi.usc.edu/dit</ref> [Accessed 24 April 2020].</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="vincs2015" label="Vincs 2015">Vincs, K. <title rend="quotes">Virtualizing
            Dance.</title>In Rosenberg, D. (ed.), <title rend="italic">The Oxford Handbook of
            Screendance Studies</title>, New York (2016), pp. 263-282.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="whatley2012" label="Whatley 2012">Whatley, S. <title rend="quotes">The Poetics
            of Motion Capture and Visualisation Techniques: The Differences between Watching Real
            and Virtual Dancing Bodies.</title>In Reynolds, D. and Reason, M. (eds.), <title
            rend="italic">Kinesthetic Empathy in Creative and Cultural Practices</title>, London
          (2012), pp. 264-279.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="whatley2017a" label="Whatley 2017a">Whatley, S. <title rend="quotes"
            >Documenting Dance: Tools, Frameworks and Digital Transformation.</title>In Sant, T.
          (ed.), <title rend="italic">Documenting Performance : The Context and Processes of Digital
            Curation and Archiving</title>, London and New York (2017a), pp. 283-304.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="whatley2017b" label="Whatley 2017b">Whatley, S. <title rend="quotes"
            >Transmitting, Transforming, and Documenting Dance in the Digital Environment</title>
          <title rend="italic">TDR: The Drama Review</title>, 61.4 (2017): 78-95.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="williams2011" label="Williams 2011">Williams, B.R. <title rend="quotes">Doing
            Video Oral History.</title>In Ritchie, D. (ed.), <title rend="italic">The Oxford
            Handbook of Oral History,</title> New York (2011), pp. 267-276.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="winslow2011" label="Winslow and Smith 2011">Winslow, M. and Smith, G. <title
            rend="quotes">Medical Ethics and Oral History.</title>In Ritchie, D. (ed.), <title
            rend="italic">The Oxford Handbook of Oral History</title>, New York (2011), pp.
          372-392.</bibl>
      </listBibl>
    </back>
  </text>
  <!-- END TEXT -->

</TEI>
