<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Medieval manuscript descriptions and the
                    Semantic Web: analysing the impact of <title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> on
                    Italian codicological-paleographical data</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Anna <dhq:family>Bellotto</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Vienna</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>anna.bellotto@univie.ac.at</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Anna Bellotto holds a MA degree in Italian Philology from University of
                            Padova (Italy) and a MA degree in Digital Humanities from King’s College
                            London (UK). In 2018 she joined the team of <title rend="italic">Phaidra</title>, University of
                            Vienna’s digital repository. With a strong interest in modelling and
                            standardization of metadata, her current work focuses on data models and
                            controlled vocabularies in a Linked Open Data environment.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000449</idno>
                <idno type="volume">014</idno>
                <idno type="issue">01</idno>
                <date/>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>Semantic Web technologies provide the ability to more effectively connect and
                    integrate structured data by disclosing their intended meaning and therefore
                    making explicit their description, context and provenance. Thanks to their
                    nature, Semantic Web technologies have produced insights into the challenges
                    associated with standardizing metadata for manuscripts. Scholars depend on
                    highly specific catalogue records in order to understand a manuscript and raise
                    research questions which take into account either its physicality or its nature
                    of <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#burrows2011">evidence for all aspects of
                            life in the medieval period</quote><ptr target="#burrows2011"/></cit>.
                    However, the heterogeneity of codicological-paleographical records in terms of
                    metadata and terminology is weakening the integration and interoperability
                    within the community. Ontologies in particular have been evaluated as a clever
                    approach towards a better communication.</p>
                <p>The employment of knowledge representation in the field of medieval manuscript
                    descriptions is still narrow, though. Against the state of the art, this paper
                    attempts to add some evidence: it analyses the impact of a top-level ontology
                    designed for modelling cultural objects, namely <title rend="italic">CIDOC
                        Conceptual Reference Model</title>, on a set of fifteen Italian manuscript
                    descriptions encoded in <title rend="italic">TEI</title> standard using the
                    online platform <title rend="italic">ManusOnLine</title>. In this case study,
                    the semantics underlying the selected <title rend="italic">TEI
                    XML</title>-encoded manuscript descriptions were visually explored according to
                    a subset of <title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title>’s classes and properties. In
                    doing so, the process of the creation of a manuscript was split and analysed in
                    its internal phases in accordance with the <title rend="italic">CIDOC
                        CRM</title> event-modelling principle. Within the dataset, tags as
                    &lt;date&gt; and &lt;name&gt; are used sporadically to encode factual
                    information; however, this case study shows that events and relations can be
                    generally deduced from the <title rend="italic">XML</title> structure of a
                    manuscript description, although they are not expressively identified. Overall,
                    the analysis demonstrates that <title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> can
                    represent a valuable aid to overcome manuscripts-related issues — i.e.
                    granularity, contradictory knowledge and terminology — and potentially create an
                    interlinked data platform which could greatly enhance the study of human
                    culture.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>How can the <title rend="italic">CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model</title> help
                    address issues in the representation of manuscripts?</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head/>
            <div>
                <head>1. Introduction</head>
                <p>European medieval manuscripts represent one of the most significant treasures of
                    human culture and society, revealing rich information about the past that is
                    invaluable to historical research. History, art history, literature and
                    philology, codicology and palaeography, all rely on the analysis of manuscripts,
                    and scholars in these disciplines engage with these objects in unique ways.
                    However, whether the main focus may be the handwritten document in its
                    physicality or the textual content of the manuscript, <cit><quote rend="inline"
                            source="#pierazzo2010">‘the first level of enquiry always is (or should
                            be) the document, the physical support that lies in front of the
                            scholar’s eyes’</quote><ptr target="#pierazzo2010" source="398"/></cit>.
                    The physical — i.e. codicological and palaeographical — details of a manuscript
                    play a pivotal role not only in the identification and study of the handwritten
                    source, but also enable the scholar to reconstruct a particular social and
                    cultural context. Research related to handwritten primary sources is thus
                    dependent on the descriptions of manuscripts. These descriptions aim to provide
                    a faithful reconstruction of a manuscript by expressing its formal structure in
                    a technical language also made of abbreviations and <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >formulae</foreign>
                    <ptr target="#petrucci1984" loc="10"/>. According to Italian cataloguing
                    practice, after a first outline of the external <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >facies</foreign> each description should delineate the history of the
                    codex, the texts contained within it and finally the bibliography for research
                    on the manuscript <ptr target="#petrucci1984" loc="76–86"/>. </p>
                <p>Today, XML-encoded analytic descriptions of the physical and intellectual nature
                    of manuscripts work as digital surrogates of these artifacts while enabling the
                    knowledge contained in these descriptions to be interrelated and thus
                    potentially compared by users. Indeed, as stressed by Stinson <ptr
                        target="#stinson2009"/>, the purpose of the cataloguing itself has slightly
                    changed with its translation to the digital environment. In a setting where
                    facsimile images can be often accessed to visualise the original artifacts,
                    descriptions have gained a new level of usefulness: they serve as <cit><quote
                            rend="inline" source="#stinson2009">a means for sorting, classifying,
                            and comparing collections of manuscripts</quote><ptr
                            target="#stinson2009" loc="40"/></cit> because, even when digital images
                    are available to scholars, <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#fabian2016"
                            >without metadata, there is no access and no meaning</quote><ptr
                            target="#fabian2016"/></cit>. The result of the online descriptive
                    records is that hypertext information is now searchable, potentially linked,
                    making comparisons among manuscripts easier. However, the interrelation of
                    intellectual objects <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#pitti2004">requires
                            creating explicit machine-readable data that allow automated correlation
                            or collocation of related resources</quote><ptr target="#pitti2004"
                        /></cit>. European cultural heritage institutions recognise the need to
                    create metadata; nevertheless, the lack of automated correlation is a major
                    challenge to the creation of timely and granular metadata for medieval
                    manuscript descriptions. Specifically, the heterogeneity of
                    codicological-paleographical records in terms of metadata and terminology is
                    weakening the integration and interoperability within the community. </p>
                <p>This paper<note>Drawn from the same author's MA Dissertation <ptr
                            target="#bellotto2017"/>.</note> focuses on one approach that has been
                    proposed against this unstandardised setting: the Semantic Web addresses
                    metadata automation because of its potential to leverage ontologies as means to
                    more effectively connect medieval manuscript data according to its semantics. At
                    present, although the valuable role of computational ontologies is getting
                    interest in the broader Humanities, the employment of these recent developments
                    in knowledge representation is still narrow in the field of medieval manuscript
                    descriptions, which always require an <soCalled>ad hoc</soCalled> consideration
                    due to the peculiar data they examine <ptr target="#barbero2013"/>. Against this
                    scenario, this paper concentrates on primary sources coming from the Middle
                    Ages, and it explores the impact of a top-level ontology designed for modelling
                    cultural objects, namely <title rend="italic">CIDOC Conceptual Reference
                        Model</title>, on a specific set of Italian manuscript descriptions. Though
                    limited in the extent of its examination, this case study attempts to add
                    evidence and potentially further the analysis and implementation of ontologies
                    on codicological-paleographical catalogue records. </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section2">
                <head>2. Medieval manuscript descriptions: an unstandardised setting</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Metadata standards</head>
                    <p>Medieval manuscripts can be described within general databases, such as a
                        library’s collection database, or specific manuscript databases. In the
                        former context, records about a collection of manuscripts might be encoded
                        in bibliographic technical and structural standards, as – for example –
                            <title rend="italic">MARC 21 Format for Bibliographic Data</title> or
                            <title rend="italic">UNIMARC</title>. In contrast, most of the
                        significant European catalogues use the <title rend="italic">Text Encoding
                            Initiative</title> (<title rend="italic">TEI P5</title>) standard to
                        encode metadata about their medieval manuscripts. Specifically, the <title
                            rend="italic">TEI Manuscript Description</title> element (<hi
                            rend="italic">&lt;msDesc&gt;</hi>) arose to meet the needs of the
                        European manuscript cataloguing tradition in terms of both the logical
                        macrostructure of the records and the content of each field. Nevertheless,
                        despite the functionalities in <title rend="italic">TEI</title>, a unique
                        standard has not been universally established and a variety of metadata
                        schemas can thus be encountered when studying this domain.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Granularity of the records</head>
                    <p>The semantic and syntactical nature of XML provides many opportunities for
                        encoding granular and extensible records, which offers many unique
                        opportunities for data about medieval manuscripts. Moreover, the <title
                            rend="italic">TEI</title>
                        <hi rend="italic">&lt;msDesc&gt;</hi> module documentation, which proposes
                        general guidelines rather than precise rules, also accommodates flexibility
                        on the amount of information to be included. In the context of networking
                        and interoperability this <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#uhlir2009"
                                >different levels/depth of manuscript descriptions</quote><ptr
                                target="#uhlir2009" loc="74"/></cit> is one of the main challenges
                        towards the metadata crosswalk.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Terminology</head>
                    <p><title rend="italic">TEI</title> is a complex schema, which means, to analyse
                            <title rend="italic">TEI</title> records, we need a clear understanding
                        of elements and terminology. A first level of inconsistency depends on the
                        variety of data schemas that can be adopted in this domain: some <title
                            rend="italic">TEI</title> elements could be similar to those of a
                        customized data structure or the <title rend="italic">MARC 21</title>
                        standard, but they may not use the exact same terms. Taking into account how
                        multilingualism complicates this framework on a further level <ptr
                            target="#burrows2011"/>
                        <ptr target="#humphrey2007" loc="23–26"/>
                        <ptr target="#kummer2011"/>. The language of manuscript catalogues varies
                        from country to country; furthermore, expert palaeographers tend to make
                        terminological choices according to their sub-domains and contexts <ptr
                            target="#hassner2012" loc="25"/>
                        <ptr target="#petrucci1984" loc="59"/>, consequently causing an
                        heterogeneous and unstandardised vocabulary in terms of handwriting. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Encoding methods in <title rend="italic">TEI</title> standard</head>
                    <p>Barbero and Trasselli <ptr target="#barbero2014"/> highlighted critical
                        aspects about the encoding of some codicological data in <title
                            rend="italic">TEI</title> format. According to their analysis, when
                        creating records for manuscripts material, the number of folios and size of
                        leaves are particularly exposed to differences in description. Furthermore,
                        they emphasized that a single procedure about how to structure each
                        information is not provided by the <title rend="italic">TEI
                            Guidelines</title> and this factor represents an obstacle towards the
                        desirable data sharing. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3. Current proposals: Semantic Web and ontologies</head>
                <p> Research on Semantic Web technologies has produced insights into the challenges
                    associated with standardizing metadata for manuscripts. In particular, the
                    application of ontologies in the domain of codicological and paleographical data
                    has been evaluated as a clever approach towards better communication within the
                    community. A clarification about what ontology means in this context, and its
                    relation with the Semantic Web and Linked Data, constitutes a preliminary step
                    in understanding which benefits ontologies can offer to the complex framework
                    outlined in <ref target="#section2">Section 2</ref>.</p>
                <p>The word <q>ontology</q> in a computational sense is derived from a long
                    established tradition in the philosophical field, namely the concept -
                    introduced by Aristotle - of <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#guarino1998">a
                            particular system of categories accounting for a certain vision of the
                            world</quote><ptr target="#guarino1998"/></cit>. Though preserving a
                    close link to its source, the computer science community has adapted the term to
                    the digital environment to describe an engineering artifact which can be defined
                    as a <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#studer1998">formal, explicit
                            specification of a shared conceptualisation</quote><ptr
                            target="#studer1998" loc="184"/></cit>. Conceptualisation is the
                    backbone of an ontology <ptr target="#guarino2009" loc="2–3"/>: consisting of an
                    abstract model of the state of affairs of a certain area of interest, an
                    ontology takes the objects, concepts and other relevant entities of this area
                    and it explicitly defines them and the relationships among them<note> Using the
                        technical terminology, concepts are defined as <q>classes</q> and concrete
                        examples of these concepts within a domain are called <q>instances</q>;
                        relationships are named <q>properties</q>
                        <ptr target="#subhascini2011"/>.</note>. In order to be called
                        <q>ontology</q>, the model needs to reflect <cit><quote rend="inline"
                            source="#studer1998">‘a certain rate of consensus about the knowledge in
                            that domain’</quote><ptr target="#studer1998" loc="184"/></cit>, and
                    therefore to express a view accepted by that specific community rather than by
                    an individual. Finally, the ontology has to be given in a formal language, that
                    is in a machine-readable format. The overall result is a set of logical axioms
                    usually based on the so-called Description Logics, a formal language for the
                    knowledge representation that gives the capability of deducing new information
                    from an explicated group of data <ptr target="#biagetti2016" loc="49–50"/>. As a
                    consequence of the aforementioned logical foundations, information integration
                    and exchange are the main valuable tasks that ontologies can perform. They
                    capture and model a shared understanding of a domain, making explicit the
                    inherent semantics and thus avoiding ambiguous meanings. In doing so, they act
                    as a medium for knowledge sharing and communication not only among resources of
                    an area but also over different systems.</p>
                <p>Thanks to their nature, ontologies have played a fundamental role in the
                    development of the Semantic Web. The concept of the Semantic Web, or <title
                        rend="quotes">Web of Data</title>
                    <ptr target="#W3Cb2015"/>, was publicly conceived in the early 2000s as an
                    extension of the World Wide Web able to automatically read and process data and
                    information without human intervention <ptr target="#berners-lee2001"/>. From
                    the very first, the essential requirement for this task was that the meaning —
                    i.e. the semantics — of Web data should have been explicated in a
                    machine-readable format in order to allow computers to discover, manipulate and
                    link information from heterogeneous sources <ptr target="#hitzler2010"
                        loc="11–12"/>. Ontologies thus became a basic component of the Semantic Web,
                    since they provide meaningful identifications of concepts and relationships and
                    help data to be powerfully searched, integrated and exchanged <ptr
                        target="#taye2010" loc="182–188"/>. The achievement of such a framework
                    needed a set of established standards and technologies to create relationships
                    among different datasets and thus formally explain computers how to access and
                    associate the information <ptr target="#W3Ca2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#yoose2013"/>. The term <q>Linked Data</q> refers to this technical
                    set. </p>
                <p>The role of the ontologies of sharing a common knowledge representation and
                    rendering <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#noy2001">domain assumptions
                            explicit</quote><ptr target="#noy2001" loc="1"/></cit> has been assessed
                    by Burrows <ptr target="#burrows2011"/> and Kummer <ptr target="#kummer2011"/> a
                    significant opportunity to enhance the interoperability and connection in the
                    body of knowledge of medieval manuscripts. Albeit referring to a broader range
                    than the single manuscript descriptions, in Burrow’s opinion the coexistence of
                    different data structure standards could be overcome by making explicit the
                    semantic categories (as names, concepts, events) embedded in resources about
                    manuscripts. Unique identifiers for each of these entities could allow an
                    interlinked environment where data within heterogeneous resources point to them.
                    Envisioning which contribution the Semantic Web could bring to codicology,
                    Kummer has discussed a similar approach. He has considered how the application
                    of a specific ontology designed within the cultural heritage, the <title
                        rend="italic">CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model</title> (<title rend="italic"
                        >CIDOC CRM</title>), could integrate data and <cit><quote rend="inline"
                            source="#kummer2011">support communication processes</quote><ptr
                            target="#kummer2011" source="140"/></cit>. The fact that <title
                        rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> concentrates <cit><quote rend="inline"
                            source="#kummer2011">on contextualization of objects</quote><ptr
                            target="#kummer2011" loc="133"/></cit> and allows different opinions and
                    uncertain information to be encoded together, has been argued to fit well with
                    the codicological framework. In regard to the first aspect, the core of this
                    ontology is indeed represented by the events, a basic concept which allows to
                    integrate facts, objects, actors, places <ptr target="#doerr2003" loc="85"/>. </p>
                <p>In the same way, the terminological aspect which challenges the medieval
                    manuscripts area has found in the Semantic Web techniques a possible resolution.
                    Whether considering the perspective of multiple national languages or
                    recognising that an established palaeographical vocabulary still misses,
                    scholars seem to agree that an ontology could represent a valuable answer
                    because it could be able to align different vocabularies in a conceptual map
                        <ptr target="#burrows2011" loc="125"/>
                    <ptr target="#hassner2012" loc="27–29"/>
                    <ptr target="#kummer2011" loc="144–145"/>
                    <ptr target="#uhlir2009" loc="75–76"/>. In two cases the <title rend="italic"
                        >SKOS</title> standard has been suggested as the appropriate format for this
                    mapping. </p>
                <p>Although many points of analysis could have been explored in the research area of
                    this paper, Kummer’s proposal of testing the suitability of <title rend="italic"
                        >CIDOC CRM</title> to codicological data was particularly taken into
                    account. Indeed, it was investigated how <title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title>
                    could address some of the challenges that <ref target="#section2">Section
                        2</ref> has outlined. <ref target="#section4">Section 4</ref> illustrates
                    this introductory analysis in more detail. </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section4">
                <head>4. A case study: methodological premises and approach</head>
                <div>
                    <head>4.1. <title rend="italic">ManusOnLine</title> and two <soCalled>special
                            projects</soCalled></head>
                    <p><title rend="italic">ManusOnLine</title> (or <title rend="italic"
                        >MOL</title>) constitutes the outcome of the most significant Italian
                        proposal towards a standardised manuscript cataloguing. Inaugurated in 2007,
                        it is the first Italian online software developed for the encoding of
                        manuscript descriptions <ptr target="#barbero2014" loc="1"/>
                        <ptr target="#marcuccio2010" loc="33"/>
                        <ptr target="#merolla2014" loc="53"/>. To date, 415 cultural heritage
                        institutions use this relational database to create descriptions of their
                        manuscripts and make freely accessible their data on the web, in some cases
                        also providing digital images. In order to provide libraries and research
                        institutions with the same data they have produced, in 2012 <title
                            rend="italic">MOL</title> then developed an application to export
                        manuscript descriptions as <title rend="italic">TEI XML</title> files. </p>
                    <p>Taking into account the more complex and various European settings previously
                        described, it could be properly argued that the focus on a single schema and
                        encoding method challenges the validity of the outcomes of an ontology
                        implementation. It is thus important to stress some considerations. On the
                        one hand, scholars’ judgements on the appropriateness of <title
                            rend="italic">TEI</title> in this domain were considered as an argument
                        in favour of the first aspect. Moreover, as it will be further presented, a
                        special research has been started about the harmonization between <title
                            rend="italic">TEI</title> and <title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title>
                        (see <ref target="#section5.2">Section 5.2</ref>). In view of <title
                            rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> as the ontology selected for this case
                        study, this was viewed as an additional reason. On the other hand, a uniform
                        encoding method was preferred according to the necessity of a homogeneous
                        corpus on where to focus the analysis. A level of variety, although
                        different, was intended to be added by the following characteristic. </p>
                    <p><title rend="italic">MOL</title> provides a further grade of cooperation. It
                        allows specialised research projects to use its software for the cataloguing
                        while consenting them to keep a total autonomy in the management of their
                        records <ptr target="#ICCU2017"/>. Two of these projects which are
                        collaborating with <title rend="italic">MOL</title> are <title rend="italic"
                            >Censimento Internazionale Manoscritti Francescani</title> (<title
                            rend="italic">International Census of Franciscan Manuscripts</title>),
                        and the <title rend="italic">Illuminated Dante Project</title> (or <title
                            rend="italic">IDP</title>). The first one, supervised by the <title
                            rend="italic">International Society of Franciscan Studies of
                            Assisi</title>, aims to gather together the textual tradition of the
                        thirteenth-fourteenth century Franciscan sources belonging to different
                        literary genres and hold in Italian and foreign cultural institutions <ptr
                            target="#ICCU2017"/>. Alternatively, the <title rend="italic"
                            >IDP</title> will create by 2021 the most comprehensive online archive
                        of those manuscripts of Dante’s <title rend="italic">Divine Comedy</title>
                        containing illustrations and dating to the fourteenth-fifteenth centuries.
                        This archive will provide their codicological and iconographic descriptions
                        as well as high-definition images <ptr target="#AIUCD2016"/>
                        <ptr target="#IDP2017"/>.</p>
                    <p>Commonly, the granularity and depth of descriptions is influenced by the
                        decisions made by each project’s cataloguers: the general guiding purpose
                        affects the meticulousness of the cataloguing activity. These two projects
                        can represent two examples: whereas <title rend="italic">IDP</title> is
                        based on thorough and complete first-hand descriptions that have required
                        the supplement of new codicological-paleographical fields in <title
                            rend="italic">MOL</title>
                        <ptr target="#AIUCD2016"/>, the <title rend="italic">International Census of
                            the Franciscan Manuscripts</title> is only focused on the digitisation
                        of existing printed catalogues <ptr target="#ICCU2017"/>, often quite dated.
                        It is also noteworthy to emphasise that, since it is a database for
                        manuscripts in a broad extent, <title rend="italic">MOL</title> itself
                        allows a certain level of flexibility. </p>
                    <p>For the aspects aforementioned, the differences of these two special
                        projects, while being founded on a common ground — i.e. <title rend="italic"
                            >MOL</title> — assessed an interesting material on which to analyse the
                        implementation of an ontology. This approach was led by the intent of
                        collecting an <soCalled>heterogeneous</soCalled> dataset, although in a
                        restricted sense, and disclosing the challenges that could emerge when
                        dealing with singular documents as medieval manuscripts are. More precisely,
                        the study was based on a subcorpus of fifteen manuscript descriptions
                        belonging to both the projects (the list is provided in <ref target="#appendix3">Appendix 3</ref>).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4.2. <title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title></head>
                    <p><title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> is an ontology specifically devoted to
                        the domain of cultural objects. As a result, <title rend="italic">CIDOC
                            CRM</title> presents a modelling design that attempts to address the
                        challenges produced by this kind of object: <cit><quote rend="inline"
                                source="#zollner-weber2008">‘imprecision, vagueness,
                                lacunae’</quote><ptr target="#zollner-weber2008" loc="122"/></cit>
                        as well as context-dependency and multiple interpretations. </p>
                    <p>Firstly, it is a top-level ontology, meaning that it delineates general
                        classes and properties, as events, places, actors, <cit><quote rend="inline"
                                source="#guarino1998">which are independent of a particular problem
                                or domain</quote><ptr target="#guarino1998"/></cit>. However, in
                        order to supply the needs of specific communities and applications, <title
                            rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> has been made potentially extensible. As
                        many new sub-classes or sub-properties as required by each sub-domain can be
                        added to the available classes and properties of the conceptual model <ptr
                            target="#stead2008"/>. This theoretical ground is particularly relevant
                        when explored by the perspective of manuscript descriptions. On the one
                        hand, the core classes and properties which sit at the top of the ontology
                        should be valid for all the records despite their divergence in the
                        granularity. Equally, more detail can later be included in the ontology. On
                        the other hand, as was stressed by Kummer <ptr target="#kummer2011"/>, the
                        possibility to incorporate different views on the same material is helpful
                        for the uncertainty that in some cases affects the
                        codicological-paleographical information, such as multi-interpretable dates
                        or scribal hands. </p>
                    <p>Secondly, at the foundation of <title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> there
                        is the aim of focusing on the semantics of data schemas, in particular the
                        relationships that exist among the inherent concepts, rather than the
                        terminology related to data encoded in these schemas <ptr
                            target="#ICOMCIDOC2017" loc="I"/>. For this reason, classes referring to
                        the terminology (<title rend="italic">E41 Appellation</title>) have been
                        distinguished from the concepts underlying data <ptr target="#stead2008"/>.
                        The fact that medieval manuscript cataloguing often involves a significant
                        diversification in the vocabulary, whether paleographical or simply
                        linguistic, seems to find a support in <title rend="italic">CIDOC
                            CRM</title>’s distinction between top-level semantics and terminology.
                        Where an agreement on the terms to be used still misses, a correspondence
                        between the concepts that sit behind those terms could instead be more
                        easily obtained. </p>
                    <p>The implementation of <title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> sought to
                        disclose to what extent the above articulated theoretical assumptions could
                        be accepted within the constraints of the dataset selected as a case study.
                        Nevertheless, the application and extension of an existing ontology on a
                        specific dataset is a long and time-consuming work requiring great expertise
                        both on the technologies and the domain knowledge of the materials. The
                        approach which was undertaken within this case study should be thus rather
                        viewed as an initial attempt which considered only the first step of this
                        long process. Specifically, the semantics underlying the selected <title
                            rend="italic">TEI XML</title>-encoded manuscript descriptions of the
                            <title rend="italic">International Census of the Franciscan
                            Manuscripts</title> and <title rend="italic">IDP</title> were explored
                        according to a subset of <title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title>. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5. Implementing <title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title></head>
                <div>
                    <head>5.1. Preliminaries</head>
                    <p>The implementation of an ontology should always start from defining
                                <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#noy2005">its domain and
                                scope</quote><ptr target="#noy2001" loc="5"/></cit>. Answering the
                        question <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#hiebel2010">what knowledge do
                                you want to represent</quote><ptr target="#hiebel2010" loc="2"
                            /></cit> thus corresponds to the first primary step that needed to be
                        performed. Within the high-level element <title rend="italic">TEI</title>
                        <hi rend="italic">&lt;msDesc&gt;</hi>, the components <hi rend="italic"
                            >&lt;msIdentifier&gt;</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&lt;msContents&gt;</hi>
                        (with its potential series of <hi rend="italic">&lt;msItem&gt;</hi>
                        elements), <hi rend="italic">&lt;physDesc&gt;</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >&lt;history&gt;</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&lt;additional&gt;</hi><note>
                            This element has been excluded from the proposed mapping process given
                            its closer relation to the bibliographic than
                            codicological-paleographical interest.</note>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >&lt;msPart&gt;</hi>, together with more specialised tags that can occur
                        within them, are used to define detailed descriptive data about a manuscript
                        (see <ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>). Within the framework of
                        potentially highly accurate records as promised by <title rend="italic"
                            >MOL</title>, the approach chosen for this case study was to consider as
                        much detail as possible, i.e. all the codicological, paleographical, textual
                        and historical information encoded in the <title rend="italic">TEI
                            XML</title> descriptions of the specific set of manuscripts.</p>
                    <p> Once the decision about how general the ontology is going to be has been
                        made, the desired information has to be mapped to the <title rend="italic"
                            >CRM</title> classes and properties that best represent it <ptr
                            target="#hiebel2010" loc="2"/>
                        <ptr target="#theodoridou2016"/>. It is at this second stage of the process
                        that the examination of the event-centric principle — on which <title
                            rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> is founded — produced a further
                        consideration. As stressed by Doerr and Kritsotaki <ptr target="#doerr2006"
                        />, the modelling of historical contexts in terms of events and processes
                        can more effectively aggregate and link, through varied kinds of
                        relationships, historical and cultural information. Indeed, history can be
                        seen as a sequence of events <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#doerr2006"
                                >involving participation of people and things</quote><ptr
                                target="#doerr2006"/></cit> and the creation of cultural objects is
                        placed within this process. It can be easily recognised that the same
                        theoretical principle was not applied to the design of the <title
                            rend="italic">TEI</title> structure of a manuscript description. Within
                        a <title rend="italic">TEI XML</title> record, data related to the physical
                        carrier, the intellectual content carried by it and the full historical
                        process that brought a manuscript into existence is encoded separately.
                        However, on the contrary, all this information overall composes a network of
                        relationships: actors, materials, ideas have met in particular space-times
                        and need to be linked in order to capture the historical context of a
                        manuscript. </p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure01">
                        <head>Macrostructure of the <title rend="italic">TEI</title> manuscript
                            description. <ptr target="#barbero2013"/></head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.JPG"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>As a consequence, a conceptual re-arrangement of all the details contained in
                        the manuscript descriptions was considered a pivotal step in order to more
                        easily map the <title rend="italic">TEI</title> metadata to <title
                            rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> ontology. In accordance with the <title
                            rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> event-modelling principle, the whole
                        general sequence of activities which has as its outcome the current
                        historical condition of a manuscript, both in its physical and intellectual
                        nature, was split and analysed in its internal phases. The theoretical
                        implementation of the ontology was performed according to this temporal
                        order. </p>
                    <p>Regarding the practical mapping, <title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> does
                        not provide any guidelines about how to integrate local schemas to the
                        concepts defined in the ontology. The documentation of the standard only
                                <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#nussbaumer2010">defines the model
                                on a purely conceptual level</quote><ptr target="#nussbaumer2010"
                                loc="2"/></cit>. Confronting with this lack, a way of performing the
                        alignment of metadata with the ontology is the creation of <soCalled>mapping
                            chains</soCalled> (or paths), i.e. <cit><quote rend="inline"
                                source="#nussbaumer2010">sequence[s] of semantically associated
                                    [<title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title>] classes and properties,
                                representing a specific concept</quote><ptr target="#nussbaumer2010"
                                loc="8"/></cit>. The binding of a manuscript – for example – can be
                        represented by the following mapping chain: <hi rend="italic">E12
                            Production</hi> - <hi rend="italic">P108 has produced</hi> - <hi
                            rend="italic">E22 Man-Made Object</hi> - <hi rend="italic">P2 has
                            type</hi> - <hi rend="italic">E55 Type</hi>: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Binding</hi>. Within the framework of the analysed set of manuscripts,
                        mapping paths were thus created for each concept occurring in each specific
                        stage of the creation of a manuscript. While the chains are graphically
                        displayed in <ref target="#appendix1">Appendix 1</ref>, the table in <ref target="#appendix2">Appendix 2</ref> schematically presents
                            them<note>It has to be stressed that the graphical representations
                            illustrate in more detail the mapping, due to the complexity and large
                            number of properties among entities.</note>.</p>
                    <p>Finally, as previously delineated, <title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> is
                        a potentially extensible ontology. In order to <cit><quote rend="inline"
                                source="#nussbaumer2007">preserve the original semantics and/or to
                                uniquely identify the metadata information</quote><ptr
                                target="#nussbaumer2007" loc="12"/></cit> it allows – for instance –
                        to sub-class existing classes. This sub-classing can be modelled through two
                        approaches: by creating new sub-classes or by specialising and extending the
                        class <title rend="italic">E55 Type</title><note> This class is used to
                                    <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#ICOMCIDOC2017">characterize
                                    and classify instances of CRM classes</quote><ptr
                                    target="#ICOMCIDOC2017" loc="27"/></cit>.</note> introducing a
                        domain-specific vocabulary. The first method is by all means more elaborate;
                        the latter is ontologically easier and more time-saving. Also bearing in
                        mind the <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#theodoridou2016">[m]inimality
                                modelling principle of <title rend="italic">CIDOC
                                CRM</title></quote><ptr target="#theodoridou2016"/></cit> according
                        to which a new class should be created only if it requires new additional
                        properties, for this case study the second method was evaluated the most
                        appropriate. In particular, the values of the instances of <title
                            rend="italic">E55 Type</title> were drawn from the terminology provided
                        by Muzerelle <ptr target="#muzerelle2002"/>. Although this online resource
                        cannot be strictly considered a controlled vocabulary, it was positively
                        assessed taking into account a possible multilingual integration of
                        manuscript descriptions. </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="section5.2">
                    <head>5.2. Mapping and its evaluation</head>
                    <p>Since 2004, a unit within the <title rend="italic">TEI Ontologies Special
                            Interest Groups (SIGs)</title> has been focused on the relationship
                        between <title rend="italic">TEI</title> and <title rend="italic">CIDOC
                            CRM</title> standards towards a mapping of the elements of the former
                        with classes and properties of the latter <ptr target="#eide2010"/>
                        <ptr target="#eide2014"/>
                        <ptr target="#eide2006"/>
                        <ptr target="#eide2007"/>
                        <ptr target="#ore2009"/>. Specifically, it has been underlined the
                        development from <title rend="italic">TEI P4</title> to <title rend="italic"
                            >TEI P5</title> in including <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#ore2009"
                                >new elements for marking-up real-world information</quote><ptr
                                target="#ore2009" loc="165"/></cit>, as – for instance – <hi
                            rend="italic">&lt;person&gt;</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&lt;place&gt;</hi>,
                            <hi rend="italic">&lt;event&gt;</hi>, <hi rend="italic">
                            &lt;relation&gt;</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&lt;name&gt;</hi>. A comparison
                        of these tags with <title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> conceptual model
                        was then performed, attempting at the same time to propose different ways to
                        interlink the two standards. Nevertheless, a great part of the cited
                        articles are based on the assumption that the <title rend="italic"
                            >TEI</title> documents representing the background of the analysis
                        already contain marked-up real world information. This is actually not a
                        standard characteristic. As underlined by Eide and Ore, it <cit><quote
                                rend="inline" source="#eide2007">is common to most <hi rend="italic"
                                    >TEI</hi> documents</quote><ptr target="#eide2007"/></cit> that
                        – for example – <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#eide2007">events are not
                                tagged</quote><ptr target="#eide2007"/></cit>. </p>
                    <p>However, a manuscript description is a particular type of <title
                            rend="italic">TEI</title> document. It has been designed having in mind
                        the implicit conceptual model at the base of the European cataloguing
                        practice. Consequently, it can be inferred that each specialised <title
                            rend="italic">TEI</title> element has been introduced according to an
                        agreed contextual meaning. Considering the <title rend="italic">XML</title>
                        structure of a manuscript description rather than its textual content, at
                        least events and relations can be generally deduced although they are not
                        expressively identified. The following example can serve as a better
                        explanation. The identification of the copyist and especially the date of
                        writing represent two of the main challenges faced by paleographers and
                        codicologists when studying a manuscript <ptr target="#petrucci1984"
                            loc="49–54"/>. This is due to the fact that, in most of the cases, the
                        transcription of a text was carried out anonymously, without any temporal
                        indication. However, an exception to this status quo is represented by the
                        colophon, i.e. an original date (and name) handwritten by the copyist on the
                        leaves during the stage of the handwriting. For its inherent semantics, the
                        presence of a colophon (<hi rend="italic">E34 Inscription</hi>) means that
                        this final formula was added by a person (<hi rend="italic">E21
                        Person</hi>), i.e. the copyist,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>and it may contain
                        information able to identify (<hi rend="italic">P67 refers to</hi>) the date
                        of writing and the copyist himself, helping the scholar to provide his own
                        hypothesis on the manuscript (<hi rend="italic">P16 was used for - E13
                            Attribute Assignment</hi>) (see <ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref>).
                        Making explicit causal and temporal relationships, the overall mapping of
                        the specific <title rend="italic">TEI</title> records to <title
                            rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> was generally successful because of this
                        aspect. </p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure02">
                        <head>Modelling of a colophon.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The aforesaid reasoning needs further consideration, though. Events require
                        to be placed in specific time frames and linked to identified actors in
                        order to model factual information. If this data is not encoded in tags as
                            <hi rend="italic">&lt;date&gt;</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                            >&lt;name&gt;</hi>, individual histories of handwritten primary sources
                        cannot be retrieved. This was the main drawback affecting the mapping
                        process. In <title rend="italic">MOL</title> records the presence of <hi
                            rend="italic">&lt;name&gt;</hi> was really sporadic and the use of <hi
                            rend="italic">&lt;origDate&gt;</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                            >&lt;date&gt;</hi> was limited – for instance – to the origin of a
                        manuscript, the life of the text’s author and the date of a binding. </p>
                    <p>In reference to some of the aspects against which the choice of <title
                            rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> ontology was made, the described project
                        was finally assessed as positive evidence. Firstly, the dissimilarities
                        between bare and more accurate descriptions did not heavily affect the good
                        outcome of the implementation. As a representative specimen, the conceptual
                        identification of a comprehensive class for any kind of illumination
                        occurring in a manuscript, distinct from its subtypes, allowed to model the
                        different granularity of this category found in the analysed records. During
                        the modelling, it was chosen to firstly sub-type the class <hi rend="italic"
                            >E55 Type</hi> for classifying the physical feature holding the
                        illumination, e.g. initial, leaf, frieze (encoded in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >TEI @type</hi> attribute). Then, the class <hi rend="italic">E41
                            Appellation</hi> was used to specify the conventional terms for
                        describing a particular category (occurring in the <title rend="italic"
                            >TEI</title>
                        <hi rend="italic">@subtype</hi> attribute), whose semantic meaning is
                        explained by the class <hi rend="italic">E36 Visual Item</hi> (see <ref
                            target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref>). </p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure03">
                        <head>Modelling of an illumination.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>An additional level of evaluation pertains the contradictory views. <title
                            rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> ontology enabled to distinguish facts
                        that were asserted by the handwritten sources from those that, although
                        based on these sources, were only <cit><quote rend="inline"
                                source="#eide2008">exhibited in or presupposed</quote><ptr
                                target="#eide2008"/></cit>. An example is provided. Handwritten
                        texts usually do not include titles, which thus need to be deduced through a
                        scholar’s analysis of the content. However, it can happen that titles occur
                        in a specific leaf and thus no interpretation is required. Two mappings of
                        the title of a manuscript (see <ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>) were
                        thus needed in order to make a clear distinction between the factual and
                        interpretative nature of information. </p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure04">
                        <head>Different mappings for the two types of title.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Lastly, the use of the class <hi rend="italic">E55 Type</hi> for representing
                        the concepts of a codicological thesauri and the use of <hi rend="italic"
                            >E41 Appellation</hi> for naming instances of classes <cit><quote
                                rend="inline" source="#ICOMCIDOC2017">by convention, tradition, or
                                agreement</quote><ptr target="#ICOMCIDOC2017" source="21–22"/></cit>
                        showed that the distinction between concepts and terminology is actually
                        possible. According to this principle, in the context of an heterogeneous
                        vocabulary for handwriting scripts, it was possible to keep separate the
                        concept of the style of script (<hi rend="italic">E55 Type)</hi> from – for
                        example – the conventional name <q>littera textualis</q> (<hi rend="italic"
                            >E41 Appellation)</hi> (see <ref target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref>). </p>
                    <p>
                        <figure xml:id="figure05">
                            <head>Part of the modelling of the handwriting of the texts.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>6. In the <soCalled>real world</soCalled>: broader considerations</head>
                <p>The analysis presented in this paper was not performed on a comprehensive range
                    of medieval manuscript descriptions encoded in different metadata schemas,
                    neither did it involve the implementation of an ontology in all its required
                    stages. If so, these choices would have let results have a more authoritative
                    voice, highlighting at the same time a major level of complexity that the
                        <soCalled>real world</soCalled> necessarily involves. The following
                    paragraphs aim to introduce this broader context, stressing a potential affinity
                    with other areas facing similar challenges.</p>
                <p>Just considering <title rend="italic">TEI</title> standard, individual
                    customisations of the <title rend="italic">TEI P5</title> manuscript description
                    module would be the first hurdle to deal with during the investigation of
                    heterogeneous manuscripts data. The proposal by Page et al. <ptr
                        target="#page2019"/> of an intermediate, simplified and more rigid XML file,
                    i.e. a selected list of metadata fields coming from an overall analysis of the
                    source records, could be assessed as a feasible approach, representing a form of
                    standardization where to focus the mapping to the ontology. Nevertheless,
                    whatever workflow is chosen, the engagement of experts in expressing the
                    processes and methods they used for encoding their data remains pivotal.
                    Institutions who <quote rend="inline" source="#nussbaumer2010">precisely know
                        the semantic definitions</quote> of their schemas <ptr
                        target="#nussbaumer2010" loc="8"/>
                    <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#oldman2016">‘must be involved in encoding the
                            meaning of their own information’</quote><ptr target="#oldman2016"
                            loc="265"/></cit>. Equally, corporate bodies’ commitment to provide
                    Linked Data versions of manuscript data should take into account the <cit><quote
                            rend="inline" source="#zeng2019">semantic enrichment</quote><ptr
                            target="#zeng2019" loc="30"/></cit> of their datasets values by linking
                    their data to external authority files and controlled vocabularies. A web
                    platform as the one developed by the <title rend="italic">symogih.org</title>
                    project <ptr target="#beretta2017"/> might be seen as the most straightforward
                    path to this envisioned framework. In this user-friendly environment, data
                    providers would be allowed to annotate their descriptions as well as to
                    represent the embedded knowledge of their data structures <cit><quote
                            rend="inline" source="#beretta2017">encoding knowledge units directly
                            into texts</quote><ptr target="#beretta2017"/></cit> — i.e. linking
                        <title rend="italic">TEI</title> tags to classes and properties of a <title
                        rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title>-based ontology. On top of this platform a
                    portal should then be implemented for exploring, searching and discovering the
                    harmonized datasets and records. Nonetheless, all these infrastructural
                    components would require noticeable long-term and large-scale efforts. As
                    emphasized by Burrows, much more work on Linked Open Data has been made in the
                    fields of Classics, Ancient History and LAM community, bringing into existence
                    significant collaborative annotation platforms as <title rend="italic"
                        >Pelagios</title> or <title rend="italic">Perseus Digital Library</title>,
                    whereas <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#burrows2018">this kind of framework
                            for linking disparate resources is lacking for medieval and Renaissance
                            studies</quote><ptr target="#burrows2018" loc="14"/></cit>. </p>
                <p>Despite the above-mentioned considerations, the challenges in terms of
                    infrastructure as well as human and economic resources should not overcome the
                    potential benefits that such an implementation could involve. The introductory
                    paragraphs of this article have underlined how <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#burrows2018">manuscripts form a crucial evidence base for the
                        humanities, and research into their histories has important benefits for a
                        wide range of disciplines</quote>
                    <ptr target="#burrows2018" loc="2"/>, from social science to art history. The
                    recognition of different scribal hands in the same manuscript – for instance –
                    can help the understanding of its genesis and transmission, telling insightful
                    knowledge about the monastery in which it was firstly written, its spheres of
                    influence and its links. On the other hand, a valuable binding and a large
                    presence of illuminated letters can reveal something about the social status of
                    the family by whom the codex was commissioned. The possibility of searching
                    across disparate databases on a single platform – thanks to semantic
                    relationships such as those defined by <hi rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</hi> – would
                    enhance the quality, in terms of both discovery and analysis, of a great variety
                    of large-scale qualitative investigations which researchers could be focused
                    on.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>7. Conclusions</head>
                <p>Semantic Web technologies provide the ability to more effectively connect and
                    integrate structured data by disclosing their intended meaning and therefore
                    making explicit their description, context and provenance. While allowing
                    integration and interoperability across heterogeneous resources, one great
                    benefit of the Semantic Web is that the local meaning of each of these resources
                    is never lost and the source systems are not demanded for large changes:
                            <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#oldman2016">semantics can be embedded
                            (rather than described separately) within exactly the same
                            structure</quote><ptr target="#oldman2016" loc="254"/></cit>. Within the
                    context of medieval manuscript descriptions, the implementation of ontologies
                    can represent a valuable enhancement of manuscript research. A growing number of
                    semantically interlinked and automatically discoverable descriptions, though
                    encoded by different institutions in a variety of standards and vocabularies,
                    could firstly enable researchers to extend their query and thus their range of
                    observation. At the same time, the unlimited retrieval of information could make
                    scholars face unplanned discussions and questions.</p>
                <p>The case study presented in this paper has been focused on one specific instance
                    of medieval manuscript data lacking explicit semantics: the
                    paleographical-codicological descriptions belonging to two different collections
                    within the Italian catalogue <title rend="italic">ManusOnLine</title>. The
                    disclosing of relationships and concepts embedded in the tags of the analysed
                        <title rend="italic">TEI</title> records revealed that a deep
                    domain-specific knowledge, i.e. the process of the creation of a manuscript and
                    its involved terminology, is essential towards an effective mapping of this data
                    to an ontology. Along with this, bringing under scrutiny the <title
                        rend="italic">TEI</title> encoding of data and the context of this
                    information led to discerning, in an epistemological process, factual from
                    categorical data. It has been also emphasized how abstract entities and
                    properties of the suggested <title rend="italic">CIDOC CRM</title> ontology
                    allow individual interpretations. </p>
                <p>Taking into account the limitations of this case study and its challenges, this
                    initial theoretical attempt towards the proposed solution of the Semantic Web
                    technologies to integrate an heterogeneous framework, as that of medieval
                    manuscript descriptions, can be positively evaluated. However, there are still
                    many problems that need to be addressed if considering a real-world
                    implementation. But despite current and potential questions that demand to be
                    investigated, tools are now available to achieve the promising outcome
                    illustrated in the first paragraph of this conclusion. It remains to invest in
                    Digital Humanities research and the cultural community in terms of interest,
                    skills and collaborative work. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix1">
                <head>Appendix 1</head>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/Appendix1.pdf"/>
                    <figDesc>Appendix 1 Image File</figDesc>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix2">
                <head>Appendix 2</head>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/Appendix2.pdf"/>
                    <figDesc>Appendix 2 Image File</figDesc>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix3">
                <head>Appendix 3</head>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/Appendix3.pdf"/>
                    <figDesc>Appendix 3 Image File</figDesc>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgements">
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>A pivotal thank you to Dr Kristen Schuster for the great encouragement and
                    enthusiastic support in writing this article.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="AIUCD2016" label="AIUCD 2016"><title rend="italic">Illuminated Dante
                        Project (IDP): Una startup per la digitalizzazione e l’analisi della più
                        antica iconografia dantesca (secc. XIV-XV)</title>. Venezia (2016). &lt;<ref
                        target="http://www.iccu.sbn.it/opencms/export/sites/iccu/documenti/2016/V_CONVEGNO_ANNUALE_DELLxAIUCD_Panel_IDP.pdf"
                        >http://www.iccu.sbn.it/opencms/export/sites/iccu/documenti/2016/V_CONVEGNO_ANNUALE_DELLxAIUCD_Panel_IDP.pdf</ref>&gt;.
                    Accessed 1 July 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barbero2013" label="Barbero 2013">Barbero, G. (2013). Manoscritti e
                    standard. <title rend="italic">DigItalia</title>. &lt;<ref
                        target="http://digitalia.sbn.it/article/view/824"
                        >http://digitalia.sbn.it/article/view/824</ref>&gt;. Accessed 1 July 2018. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barbero2014" label="Barbero and Trasselli 2014-2015">Barbero, G. and
                    Trasselli, F. (2014-2015). Manus OnLine and the Text Encoding Initiative Schema,
                        <title rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>.
                        &lt;<ref target="https://jtei.revues.org/1054"
                        >https://jtei.revues.org/1054</ref>&gt;. Accessed 1 July 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bellotto2017" label="Bellotto 2017">Bellotto, A. (2017). <title
                        rend="italic">Towards the implementation of CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model
                        on medieval manuscript descriptions - Modelling ManusOnLine records</title>.
                    MA Dissertation in Digital Humanities, Faculty of Arts &amp; Humanities, King’s
                    College London. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="beretta2017" label="Beretta 2017">Beretta, F. (2017). <title
                        rend="italic">Collaboratively Producing Interoperable Ontologies and
                        Semantically Annotated Corpora: the symogih.org project</title>. Third
                    International Workshop on Semantic Web for Scientific Heritage, May 2017,
                    Portoroz, Slovenia. &lt;halshs-01539489&gt;. Accessed 20 April 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berners-lee2001" label="Berners-Lee et al. 2001">Berners-Lee, T.,
                    Hendler, J. and Lassila, O. (2001). The Semantic Web. <title rend="italic"
                        >Scientific American</title>, May Issue. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="biagetti2016" label="Biagetti 2016">Biagetti, M. T. (2016). Un modello
                    ontologico per l’integrazione delle informazioni del patrimonio culturale:
                    CIDOC-CRM, <title rend="italic">JLIS.it</title>, 7 (3). &lt;<ref
                        target="https://www.jlis.it/article/view/11930"
                        >https://www.jlis.it/article/view/11930</ref>&gt;. Accessed 1 July
                    2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burrows2011" label="Burrows 2011">Burrows, T. (2011). Applying
                    Semantic Web Technologies to Medieval Manuscript Research. In: Fischer, F.,
                    Fritze, C., Vogeler, C., 2011. <title rend="italic">Kodicologie und Paläographie
                        im digitalen Zeitalter 2 (Codicology and palaeography in the digital age
                        2)</title>, Schriften des Instituts für Dokumentologie und Editorik. Books
                    on Demand (BoD), Norderstedt, pp.117-131. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burrows2018" label="Burrows 2018">Burrows, T. (2018). Connecting
                    Medieval and Renaissance Manuscript Collections. <title rend="italic">Open
                        Library of Humanities</title>, 4(2), p.32. &lt;<ref
                        target="http://doi.org/10.16995/olh.269"
                        >http://doi.org/10.16995/olh.269</ref>&gt;. Accessed 20 April 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="doerr2003" label="Doerr 2003">Doerr, M. (2003). The CIDOC Conceptual
                    Reference Module: An Ontological Approach to Semantic Interoperability of
                    Metadata, <title rend="italic">AI Magazine</title>, 24 (3). &lt;<ref
                        target="https://aaai.org/ojs/index.php/aimagazine/article/view/1720/1618"
                        >https://aaai.org/ojs/index.php/aimagazine/article/view/1720/1618</ref>&gt;.
                    Accessed 1 July 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="doerr2006" label="Doerr and Kritsotaki 2006">Doerr, M. and Kritsotaki,
                    A. (2006). Documenting Events in Metadata. &lt;<ref
                        target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org/sites/default/files/Documenting%20Events%20in%20Metadata.pdf"
                        >http://www.cidoc-crm.org/sites/default/files/Documenting%20Events%20in%20Metadata.pdf</ref>&gt;.
                    Accessed 1 July 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eide2008" label="Eide 2008">Eide, O. (2008). The Exhibition Problem. A
                    Real-life Example with a Suggested Solution. <title rend="italic">Literary and
                        Linguistic Computing</title>, 23 (1), pp.27-37.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eide2010" label="Eide 2010">Eide, O. (2010). <title rend="italic"
                        >Guidelines for the creation of TEI documents that will map well to
                        ontologies such as the CIDOC-CRM. – Draft</title>. &lt;<ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/SIG/Ontologies/guidelines/guidelinesTeiMappableCrm.html"
                        >http://www.tei-c.org/SIG/Ontologies/guidelines/guidelinesTeiMappableCrm.html</ref>&gt;.
                    Accessed 1 July 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eide2014" label="Eide 2014-2015">Eide, O. (2014-2015). Ontologies,
                    Data Modeling, and TEI. <title rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding
                        Initiative.</title> &lt;<ref target="https://jtei.revues.org/119"
                        >https://jtei.revues.org/119</ref>1&gt;. Accessed 1 July 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eide2006" label="Eide and Ore 2006">Eide, O. and Ore, C.-E. (2006).
                    TEI, CIDOC-CRM and a Possible Interface Between the Two. In: ACH and ALLC,
                        <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2006</title>. Sorbonne, Paris,
                    France, 5-9 July 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eide2007" label="Eide and Ore 2007">Eide, O. and Ore, C.-E. (2007).
                        <title rend="italic">From TEI to a CIDOC-CRM Conforming Model: Towards a
                        Better Integration Between Text Collections and Other Sources of Cultural
                        Historical Documentation.</title> &lt;<ref
                        target="http://www.edd.uio.no/artiklar/tekstkoding/poster_156_eide.html"
                        >http://www.edd.uio.no/artiklar/tekstkoding/poster_156_eide.html</ref>&gt;.
                    Accessed 1 July 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fabian2016" label="Fabian 2016">Fabian, C. (2016). RDA as a New
                    Starting Point for International Cooperation: Retrospective National
                    Bibliographies and Medieval Manuscripts. <title rend="italic">Cataloguing &amp;
                        Classification Quarterly</title>, 54 (5-6), pp.338-349.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="guarino1998" label="Guarino 1998">Guarino, N. (1998). Formal Ontology
                    and Information Systems. In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of FOIS’98, Trento,
                        Italy, 6-8 June 1998</title>, amended version. Amsterdam: IOS Press,
                    pp.3-15. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="guarino2009" label="Guarino et al. 2009">Guarino, N., Oberle, D., and
                    Staab, S. (2009). What Is an Ontology?. In: S. Staab and R. Studer, eds. 2009.
                        <title rend="italic">Handbook on Ontologies</title>. Berlin, Heidelberg:
                    Springer Berlin Heidelberg, pp.1-17.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hassner2012" label="Hassner et al. 2012">Hassner, T., Rehbein, M.,
                    Stokes, P. A. and Wolf, L. (2012). Computation and Palaeography: Potentials and
                    Limits. <title rend="italic">Dagstuhl Manifestos</title>, 2 (1),
                    pp.14-35.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hiebel2010" label="Hiebel et al. 2010">Hiebel, G., Hanke, K. and
                    Hayek, I. (2010). Methodology for CIDOC CRM based data integration with spatial
                    data. In: CAA’ 2010 Fusion of Cultures, <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                        38</title><hi rend="superscript">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> Conference on
                        Computer Applications and Quantitative Methods in Archaeology</hi>. Granada,
                    Spain April 2010. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hitzler2010" label="Hitzler et al. 2010">Hitzler, P., Krötzsch, M.,
                    Rudolph, S. (2010). The Quest for Semantics. In: P. Hitzler, M. Krötzsch and S.
                    Rudolph, eds. 2010. <title rend="italic">Foundation of Semantic Web
                        Technologies</title>. Boca Raton: Chapman &amp; Hall/CRC, pp.1-16.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="humphrey2007" label="Humphrey 2007">Humphrey, J. (2007). Manuscripts
                    and Metadata: Descriptive Metadata in Three Manuscript Catalogs: DigCIM,
                    MALVINE, and Digital Scriptorium. <title rend="italic">Cataloging &amp;
                        Classification Quarterly</title>, 45 (2), pp.19-39.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ICCU2017" label="ICCU 2017">ICCU. (2017). <title rend="italic">Manus
                        OnLine</title>. &lt;<ref target="http://manus.iccu.sbn.it/index.php?lang=en"
                        >http://manus.iccu.sbn.it/index.php?lang=en</ref>&gt;. Accessed 1 July
                    2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ICOMCIDOC2017" label="ICOM/CIDOC CRM Special Interest Group 2017"
                    >ICOM/CIDOC CRM Special Interest Group. (2017). <title rend="italic">Definition
                        of the CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model</title>. Version 6.2.2. &lt;<ref
                        target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org/sites/default/files/2017-09-30%23CIDOC%20CRM_v6.2.2_esIP.pdf"
                        >http://www.cidoc-crm.org/sites/default/files/2017-09-30%23CIDOC%20CRM_v6.2.2_esIP.pdf</ref>&gt;.
                    Accessed 1 July 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="IDP2017" label="IDP 2017">IDP. (2017). <title rend="italic"
                        >Illuminated Dante Project</title>. &lt;<ref
                        target="http://www.dante.unina.it/public/frontend/index/language/en"
                        >http://www.dante.unina.it/public/frontend/index/language/en</ref>&gt;.
                    Accessed 1 July 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kummer2011" label="Kummer 2011">Kummer, R. (2011). Semantic
                    Technologies for Manuscript Descriptions – Concepts and Visions. In: Fischer,
                    F., Fritze, C., Vogeler, C., 2011. <title rend="italic">Kodicologie und
                        Paläographie im digitalen Zeitalter (Codicology and palaeography in the
                        digital age)</title>, Schriften des Instituts für Dokumentologie und
                    Editorik. Books on Demand (BoD), Norderstedt, pp.133-156.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="marcuccio2010" label="Marcuccio 2010">Marcuccio, R. (2010). <title
                        rend="italic">Catalogare e fare ricerca con Manus Online</title>. <hi
                        rend="italic">&lt;</hi><ref
                        target="manus.iccu.sbn.it/upload/BibliotecheOggi_Marcuccio2010.pdf"
                        >manus.iccu.sbn.it/upload/BibliotecheOggi_Marcuccio2010.pdf</ref><hi
                        rend="italic">&gt;</hi>. Accessed 1 July 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="merolla2014" label="Merolla and Negrini 2014">Merolla, L. and Negrini,
                    L. (2014). <title rend="italic">Guida a ManusOnLine (MOL) - Standard per la
                        catalogazione dei manoscritti delle biblioteche italiane</title>. &lt;<ref
                        target="www.iccu.sbn.it/opencms/export/sites/iccu/documenti/2014/GUIDA_MOLsettembre_2014.pdf"
                        >www.iccu.sbn.it/opencms/export/sites/iccu/documenti/2014/GUIDA_MOLsettembre_2014.pdf</ref>&gt;.
                    Accessed 1 July 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="muzerelle2002" label="Muzerelle 2002">Muzerelle, D. (2002). <title
                        rend="italic">Vocabulaire codicologique : répertoire méthodique des termes
                        français relatifs aux manuscrits</title>. &lt;<ref
                        target="http://vocabulaire.irht.cnrs.fr/pages/vocab2.htm"
                        >http://vocabulaire.irht.cnrs.fr/pages/vocab2.htm</ref>&gt;. Accessed 1 July
                    2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="noy2001" label="Noy and McGuinness 2001">Noy, N. F. and <ref
                        target="http://www.ksl.stanford.edu/people/dlm">McGuinness</ref>, D. L.
                    (2001). <title rend="italic">Ontology Development 101: A Guide to Creating Your
                        First Ontology</title>. &lt;<ref
                        target="https://protege.stanford.edu/publications/ontology_development/ontology101.pdf"
                        >https://protege.stanford.edu/publications/ontology_development/ontology101.pdf</ref>&gt;.
                    Accessed 1 July 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nussbaumer2007" label="Nussbaumer and Haslhofer 2007">Nussbaumer, P.
                    and Haslhofer, B. (2007). <title rend="italic">Putting the CIDOC CRM into
                        Practice - Experiences and Challenges</title>. &lt;<ref
                        target="https://eprints.cs.univie.ac.at/404/"
                        >https://eprints.cs.univie.ac.at/404/</ref>&gt;. Accessed 1 July
                    2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nussbaumer2010" label="Nussbaumer et al. 2010">Nussbaumer, P.,
                    Haslhofer, B. and Klas, W. (2010). <title rend="italic">Towards Model
                        Implementation Guidelines for the CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model</title>.
                        &lt;<ref target="eprints.cs.univie.ac.at/58/1/nussbaumer10_cidoc_crm.pdf"
                        >eprints.cs.univie.ac.at/58/1/nussbaumer10_cidoc_crm.pdf</ref>&gt;. Accessed
                    1 July 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="oldman2016" label="Oldman et al. 2016">Oldman, D., Doerr, M. and
                    Gradmann, S. (2016). Zen and the Art of Linked Data: New Strategies for a
                    Semantic Web of Humanist Knowledge. In: S. Schreibman, R. Siemens and J.
                    Unsworth, eds. 2016. <title rend="italic">A New Companion to Digital
                        Humanities</title>. John Wiley &amp; Sons, pp.251-273.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ore2009" label="Ore and Eide 2009">Ore, C.-E. and Eide, O. (2009). TEI
                    and cultural heritage ontologies: Exchange of information? <title rend="italic"
                        >Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 24 (2), pp.161-172.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="page2019" label="Page et al. 2019">Page, K., Burrows, T., Hankinson,
                    A., Holford, M., Morrison, A., Lewis, D. and Velios, A. (2019). <title
                        rend="italic">A Layered Digital Library for Cataloguing and Research:
                        Practical Experiences with Medieval Manuscripts, from TEI to Linked
                        Data</title>. In: Digital Humanities Conference 2019, 9 - 12 July 2019,
                    Utrecht, the Netherlands. &lt;<ref
                        target="http://ualresearchonline.arts.ac.uk/14433/"
                        >http://ualresearchonline.arts.ac.uk/14433/</ref>&gt;. Accessed 13 September
                    2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="petrucci1984" label="Petrucci 1984">Petrucci, A. (1984). <title
                        rend="italic">La descrizione del manoscritto. Storia, problemi,
                        modelli</title>. 1st ed. Urbino: La Nuova Italia Scientifica.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pierazzo2010" label="Pierazzo and Stokes 2010">Pierazzo, E., and
                    Stokes, P. (2010). Putting the Text back into Context: A Codicological Approach
                    to Manuscript Transcription. In: Fischer, F., Fritze, C., Vogeler, C., 2011.
                        <title rend="italic">Kodicologie und Paläographie im digitalen Zeitalter 2
                        (Codicology and palaeography in the digital age 2)</title>, Schriften des
                    Instituts für Dokumentologie und Editorik. Books on Demand (BoD), Norderstedt,
                    pp.397-429. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pitti2004" label="Pitti 2004">Pitti, D. V. (2004). Designing
                    Sustainable Projects and Publications. In: S. Schreibman, R. Siemens and J.
                    Unsworth, eds. 2004. <title rend="italic">A Companion to Digital
                        Humanities</title>. Oxford: Blackwell. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stead2008" label="Stead 2008">Stead, S. (2008). <title rend="italic"
                        >The CIDOC CRM, a Standard for the Integration of Cultural
                        Information</title>. &lt;<ref
                        target="http://old.cidoc-crm.org/cidoc_tutorial/index.html"
                        >http://old.cidoc-crm.org/cidoc_tutorial/index.html</ref>&gt;. Accessed 1
                    July 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stinson2009" label="Stinson 2009">Stinson, T. (2009). Codicological
                    Description in the Digital Age. In: Assmann, B., Rehbein, M., 2009. <title
                        rend="italic">Kodicologie und Paläographie im digitalen Zeitalter
                        (Codicology and palaeography in the digital age)</title>, Schriften des
                    Instituts für Dokumentologie und Editorik. Books on Demand (BoD), Norderstedt,
                    pp.309-338.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="studer1998" label="Studer et al. 1998">Studer, R., Benjamins, V. R.
                    and Fensel, D. (1998). Knowledge Engineering: Principles and methods, <title
                        rend="italic">Data &amp; Knowledge Engineering</title>. &lt;<ref
                        target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0169023X97000566"
                        >http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0169023X97000566</ref>&gt;.
                    Accessed 1 July 2018. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="subhascini2011" label="Subhascini and Akilandeswari 2011">Subhashini,
                    R. and Akilandeswari, J. (2011). A survey on ontology construction
                    methodologies, <title rend="italic">International Journal of Enterprise
                        Computing and Business Systems</title>. &lt;<ref
                        target="http://www.ijecbs.com/January2011/N5Jan2011.pdf"
                        >http://www.ijecbs.com/January2011/N5Jan2011.pdf</ref>&gt;. Accessed 1 July
                    2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taye2010" label="Taye 2010">Taye, A. A. (2010). Understanding Semantic
                    Web and Ontologies: Theory and Applications. <title rend="italic">Journal of
                        Computing</title>, 2 (6), pp.182-192.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="theodoridou2016" label="Theodoridou et al. 2016">Theodoridou, M.,
                    Bruseker, G., Daskalaki, M. and Doerr, M. (2016). <title rend="italic"
                        >Methodological tips for mappings to CIDOC CRM</title>. &lt;<ref
                        target="www.cidoc-crm.org/sites/default/files/CAA2016MethodologicalTipsForMappingsToCIDOC-CRM-v4.pptx"
                        >www.cidoc-crm.org/sites/default/files/CAA2016MethodologicalTipsForMappingsToCIDOC-CRM-v4.pptx</ref>&gt;.
                    Accessed 1 July 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="uhlir2009" label="Uhlíř and Knoll 2009">Uhlíř, Z. and Knoll, A.
                    (2009). Manuscriptorium Digital Library and ENRICH Project: Means for Dealing
                    with Digital Codicology and Palaeography. In: Assmann, B., Rehbein, M., 2009.
                        <title rend="italic">Kodicologie und Paläographie im digitalen Zeitalter
                        (Codicology and palaeography in the digital age)</title>, Schriften des
                    Instituts für Dokumentologie und Editorik. Books on Demand (BoD), Norderstedt,
                    pp.67-78.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="W3Ca2015" label="W3Ca 2015">W3Ca (2015). <title rend="italic">Linked
                        Data</title>. [web page] &lt;<ref
                        target="https://www.w3.org/standards/semanticweb/data"
                        >https://www.w3.org/standards/semanticweb/data</ref>&gt;. Accessed 1 July
                    2018. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="W3Cb2015" label="W3Cb 2015">W3Cb (2015). <title rend="italic">Semantic
                        Web</title>. [web page] &lt;<ref
                        target="https://www.w3.org/standards/semanticweb/"
                        >https://www.w3.org/standards/semanticweb/</ref>&gt; Accessed 1 July 2018. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="yoose2013" label="Yoose and Perkins 2013">Yoose, B., and Perkins, J.
                    (2013). The Linked Open Data Landscape in Libraries and Beyond. <title
                        rend="italic">Journal of Library Metadata</title>, 13 (2-3), pp.
                    197-211.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zeng2019" label="Zeng 2019">Zeng, M. L. (2019). <title rend="italic"
                        >Semantic enrichment for enhancing LAM data and supporting digital
                        humanities</title>. &lt;<ref
                        target="https://recyt.fecyt.es/index.php/EPI/article/view/epi.2019.ene.03/42134"
                        >https://recyt.fecyt.es/index.php/EPI/article/view/epi.2019.ene.03/42134</ref>&gt;.
                    Accessed 29 April 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zollner-weber2008" label="Zöllner-Weber and Apollon 2008"
                    >Zöllner-Weber, A. and Apollon, D. (2008). The challenge of modelling
                    information and data in the humanities. In: T. Hug, <title rend="italic">Media,
                        Knowledge &amp; Education – Exploring new Spaces, Relations and Dynamics in
                        Digital Media Ecologies</title>. Innsbruck, Austria 25-26 June 2007.
                    Innsbruck: Innsbruck University Press. </bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
