<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Unveiling the Editing Process of Japanese Demons Picture Scrolls:
                How Digital Humanities Played a Role in Developing a New Theory in Art History</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Shoji <dhq:family>Yamada</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4940-5231</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>International Research Center for Japanese Studies</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>shoji@nichibun.ac.jp</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                      <p>Shoji Yamada has been a professor at International Research Center for Japanese Studies (Nichibunken) since 2011. After acquiring a B.A. and a M. Med. Sci. 
                         at Tsukuba University, he worked for four years for IBM-Japan, then took a position as research assistant in the Department of Computer Science at Tsukuba 
                         College of Technology. He joined Nichibunken as an assistant professor in 1996 and earned a doctorate from Kyoto University in 1998. He has been working on 
                         the history of cultural exchange, copyright and culture, and digital humanities. His writings include <title rend="italic">Tokyo Boogie-woogie and 
                         D.T. Suzuki</title> (2022) from the University of Michigan Press (<ref target="https://doi.org/10.3998/mpub.12268621">https://doi.org/10.3998/mpub.12268621</ref>);  
                         <title rend="quotes">Who moved my masterpeice? Digital reproduction, replacement, and the vanishing cultural heritage of Kyoto</title> (2017) in the 
                         <title rend="italic">International Journal of Cultural Properties</title>, 24(3), pp. 295–320 
                         (<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0940739117000145">https://doi.org/10.1017/S0940739117000145</ref>); and <title rend="italic">Shots in the dark: Japan, 
                         zen, and the West</title> (2009) from the University of Chicago Press.
                      </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000717</idno>
                <idno type="volume"><!-- volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date></date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            	<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
            		<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
            	</taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <term corresp="#data_analytics"/>
                    <term corresp="#visual_art"/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                  <list type="simple">
                    <item>edit distance</item>
                    <item>Japanese art history</item>
                    <item>lineage tree</item>
                    <item>hand scroll</item>
                    <item>yokai</item>
                  </list>
                </keywords>
            	<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
            		<list type="simple">
            			<item></item>
            		</list>
            	</keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
        	<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000717/000717.xml">GitHub</ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>This paper examined seventy-one <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Hyakki Yagyō Emaki</foreign></title> 
                   (<title rend="quotes">Night Parade of One Hundred Demons</title> Picture Scroll; Demons Scroll) and estimated the artistic editing 
                   process using a digital humanities approach. The edit distance was used to illustrate the lineage trees 
                   of Demons Scrolls, focusing on the arrangement of the demons in the procession. The author concluded that 
                   a type of scroll depicted the demon arrangement closest to the prototype of the renowned Shinjuan lineage 
                   scrolls. By numbering the demons in the procession, the author contributed quantitative evidence to the 
                   ongoing iconographical interpretation debate. The paper ends with a discussion of new questions 
                   regarding Demons Scrolls that have arisen as a result of this research. By applying similar methods to other 
                   materials, the scope of digital humanities can be expanded.
                </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
              <p>A seminal study employs digital humanities to decode the pictorial evolution and lineage of Japan's enigmatic <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Hyakki Yagyō 
                 Emaki</foreign></title> (<title rend="quotes">Night Parade of One Hundred Demons</title> Picture Scroll), offering a fresh perspective on artistic iconography.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
<body>
    <div>
      <head>1. Introduction</head>
      <p>Digital humanities have promoted the digitization, sharing, and visualization of humanities resources. However, as Flanders, Piez 
         and Terras stated in the first issue of <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, digital humanities 
         <quote rend="inline">is by its nature a hybrid domain, crossing disciplinary boundaries and also traditional barriers between theory 
           and practice, technological implementation and scholarly reflection</quote> <ptr target="#flanders2007" loc="par. 3"/>. 
        </p>
        <p>Digital humanities is an ongoing effort to facilitate interaction between traditional humanities and digital/computational methods. 
           However, continuing this effort is somewhat challenging. The main obstacles are difficulties in understanding each other's languages 
           and methodologies. To promote interaction with humanities scholars, the digital humanities side should demonstrate how their methods 
           can contribute to specific humanities research topics. Similarly, humanities scholars should expand their knowledge of digital/computational 
           approaches. What is needed is not sophisticated tools or presentations but concrete results that address unsolved questions.
        </p>
        <p>Flanders argues that humanities computing does not primarily concern itself with either the discovery of new knowledge or the 
           validation of existing information. Instead, she suggests that its core function lies in the modeling of that knowledge, and in certain 
           instances, the modeling of the modeling process itself. According to her, humanities computing is a method of exploring our modes of 
           knowledge acquisition and the presentation of that knowledge for personal study <ptr target="#flanders2009" loc="par. 10"/>. Going beyond 
           Flanders's argument, this paper aims to model how we comprehend a type of artwork using a mixed quantitative and qualitative methodology, 
           and furthermore discover new knowledge in the field of Japanese art history from a digital humanities perspective.
        </p>
        <p>New discoveries through digital humanities approaches are still forthcoming. Regarding the knowledge discovery in art history by computer 
           vision technology, Lang and Ommer discussed effective use cases of digital technology, which include a classification and visualization 
           of age and social status of models in painted portraits. They conveyed the idea that it is not enough to just convert analog methods into 
           digital ones, as this approach does not capture the unique attributes and potential of digital data. They emphasized that the generation 
           of new knowledge only becomes possible when we devise new computational methods for handling digital data. This level of knowledge production, 
           they argue, could not be achieved with analog data and its corresponding methods. The impact of this shift, they stressed, extends beyond 
           art historians to also touch earlier generations of academics, particularly students <ptr target="#lang2021" loc="par. 26"/>.
        </p>
        <p>The use of digital methods, nonetheless, should be judiciously applied to facilitate seamless communication between scholars in humanities 
           and digital humanities. An effective stragegy is to pursue a study on a topic that is not overly specialized, thereby eliciting broader 
           interest and utilizing a language mutually comprehensible to each other. In order to meet these criteria, this paper undertakes an examination 
           of well-known artworks in Japan, utilizing digital methods that are not excessively complex.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>2. Mysteries Surrounding the <title rend="quotes">Night Parade of One Hundred Demons</title> Picture Scrolls</head>
        <p><title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Hyakki Yagyō (Yakō) Emaki</foreign></title><note><title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Hyakki 
           Yagyō Emaki</foreign></title> are a genre of handscroll paintings that illustrate a nocturnal parade of demons and spirits. These scrolls depict 
           a variety of supernatural figures associated with musical instruments, Buddhist ritual objects, household implements, and other mundane objects 
           awakening and marching under the cover of night. The significance of these motifs remains enigmatic, and art historians have debated how to 
           interpret these works. This type of picture scroll was frequently reproduced during the premodern period and widely disseminated. Since Japanese 
           kanji characters do not have fixed pronunciations, the romanization cannot always be determined. In the majority of instances, historians and 
           cultural anthropologists read the characters as <q><foreign xml:lang="ja">Hyakki Yagyō</foreign></q>, whereas literature scholars prefer 
           <q><foreign xml:lang="ja">Hyakki Yakō</foreign></q>.</note> (<title rend="quotes">Night Parade of One Hundred Demons</title> Picture Scroll; 
           henceforth, Demons Scroll), which depicts <foreign xml:lang="ja">yōkai</foreign> (Japanese specters) marching at midnight, have been popular in 
           Japan due to the enigmatic and humorous depictions of demons.<note>For further information on Japanese <foreign xml:lang="ja">yōkai</foreign> 
           culture, see <ptr target="#foster2009"/>, <ptr target="#foster2015"/>, and <ptr target="#komatsu2018"/>.</note> It is believed that numerous 
           Japanese painters replicated this subject between the sixteenth and nineteenth centuries, resulting in the formation of several lineages of 
           <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Hyakki Yagyō</foreign></title> scrolls.<note>In many cases of premodern artworks in Japan, one work 
           is copied by another artist, and that work is then copied by another. The same practice can be observed in the Demons Scrolls. In this paper, 
           a <q>lineage</q> refers to this kind of linear connection of copied works.</note>  The creation of multiple copies of these scrolls is indicative 
           of a significant <q>copy culture</q> in premodern Japanese art.<note>For a discussion of the copy culture in Japan, see <ptr target="#cox2007"/>.</note>
        </p>
        <p>Shinjuan, a sub-temple of Daitokuji temple in Kyoto, owns the most famous version of the Demons Scroll, attributed to Tosa Mitsunobu<note>Japanese 
           names are rendered according to the traditional order (last name comes first).</note> (1434–1525) and designated as an important cultural 
           property of Japan (Figure 1). The majority of research on Demons Scrolls has referenced this Shinjuan copy. Since the Shinjuan scroll is 
           believed to be the oldest of the known Demons Scrolls, it is only natural that scholars have focused their attention on it. However, 
           previous research has overlooked an important fact: although many copies depict the same demons as the Shinjuan painting, few scrolls have 
           the same compositional arrangement.<note>Prior studies include <ptr target="#komatsu1979a"/>, <ptr target="#komatsu1979b"/>, 
           <ptr target="#komine1997"/>, <ptr target="#kobayashi1997"/>, <ptr target="#kawaguchi2002"/>, <ptr target="#koga2006"/>, <ptr target="#tokeshi2007"/>, 
           <ptr target="#tsuji2012"/>, <ptr target="#nagura2020"/>, and <ptr target="#yanagisawa2020"/>.</note> If the Shinjuan scroll is the oldest Demons Scroll, 
           then many more copies with the exact same arrangement should be preserved. The demon arrangement in the Shinjuan scroll is likely one of many 
           variants of the Shinjuan lineage of Demons Scrolls. It is also possible that the configuration of demons in the Shinjuan scroll's 
           prototype differed from the extant copy.
        </p>
          <figure>
            <head>Detail of the Shinjuan scroll (viewed from right to left). The size of the entire scroll is 33x735 cm <ptr target="#tanaka1999"/>.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/Fig01.png"/>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
        <p>Researchers of the Demons Scrolls have noted the need to reevaluate the Shinjuan scroll's significance. Tanaka Takako, a scholar of 
           Japanese medieval literature, stated, <quote rend="inline">The Shinjuan copy was likely not the prototype of the Demons Scroll, but 
           rather a unique case. In other words, among the numerous Demons Scrolls that circulated between the sixteenth and nineteenth centuries, 
           I believe the Shinjuan lineage was fortuitously propagated</quote> <ptr target="#tanaka2002" loc="220"/>. Yumoto Kōichi, a collector 
           and researcher of materials pertaining to Japanese specters, wrote, <quote rend="inline">If the Shinjuan lineage is the standard, 
           other copies omitted certain demons and added new ones. To position the Shinjuan version, its relationship with other types of Demons 
           Scrolls must be clarified</quote> <ptr target="#yumoto2005" loc="53"/>. In response to these studies, the Japanese expert on specter 
           culture Komatsu Kazuhiko stated, <quote rend="inline">When considering the lineage of Demons Scrolls, we must set the Shinjuan copy 
           aside</quote> <ptr target="#komatsu2008" loc="164"/>. Based on their perceptions, this paper will present a new theory regarding the 
           Shinjuan scroll.
        </p>
        <p>In addition to the Shinjuan lineage, there are several other variants with different demons and what appears to be a mixture of two 
           lineages. Tanaka centered her attention on a copy known as the <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Tōhaku mohon</foreign></title> 
           (in this paper, the Tōhaku-A scroll). The Tōhaku-A scroll contains all of the demons depicted in the Shinjuan scroll, as well as a 
           large number of additional demons. Tanaka presumed that the original Tōhaku-A lineage predates the Shinjuan lineage and that the latter 
           is an idiosyncratic copy of the Tōhaku-A lineage created by extracting demons from it.
        </p>
        <p>In 2007, the <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Hyakki no zu</foreign></title> (<title rend="quotes">Picture of One Hundred 
           Demons</title>) picture scroll acquired by the International Research Center for Japanese Studies 
           (<title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Nichibunken</foreign></title>; in this paper, Nichibunken-A scroll) was discovered to be 
           composed of demons from the Tōhaku-A lineage minus those from the Shinjuan scroll. Komatsu's investigation of the Nichibunken-A scroll led 
           him to conclude that its prototype dates to the sixteenth century, the same era during which the Shinjuan version is believed to have been 
           painted. Komatsu argued that, contrary to Tanaka's theory, the original Tōhaku-A was a combination of the Shinjuan and Nichibunken-A 
           compositions. Moreover, Komatsu asserted that Demons Scrolls can be classified into four distinct lineages that do not overlap, and that 
           these lineages were sometimes combined to produce a variety of copies. The four lineages are represented by the Shinjuan, Nichibunken-A, 
           Kyoto City University of the Arts (KCUA), and Hyogo Prefecture Museum of History (Hyogo-A) scrolls <ptr target="#komatsu2008" loc="233"/>.
        </p>
        <p>The study by Komatsu was the first to investigate and classify sixty-four known Demons Scrolls, including those preserved in the United 
           States and Europe. By examining a diversity of scrolls, Komatsu was able to clarify that there are combined copies of Shinjuan and 
           Nichibunken-A; Shinjuan and KCUA; Shinjuan and Hyogo-A; and Nichibunken-A and KCUA. If we were to accept Tanaka's theory that the Shinjuan 
           scroll is an idiosyncratic copy, we would have to recognize that demons in Tōhaku-A were neatly separated to form the Shinjuan and 
           Nichibunken-A lineages, with no overlap. However, this is unlikely. In contrast to Tanaka's theory, Komatsu's <q>mixture theory</q> 
           seems more plausible. The author agrees with the mixture theory positing that there are four distinct lineages of Demons Scrolls: 
           Shinjuan, Nichibunken-A, KCUA, and Hyogo-A, and that these were intermixed to produce the Tōhaku-A scroll and other combined copies. 
           However, previous studies, including those by Komatsu, have focused on the differences and interpretations of the images while ignoring 
           the arrangement of the demons. Using the digitized photographs of scrolls that Komatsu collected and others that have recently been made 
           available on the internet, it is possible to estimate the process by which Demons Scrolls were drawn and edited by successive generations 
           of painters.
        </p>
        <p>Utilizing a computational method, this paper will explore new approaches to this research topic. The author will not employ aesthetic 
           criteria, such as line quality. Deliberately disregarding minor differences in depiction, the author 
           will identify the demons based on the parade's sequential order. Similar to a DNA test, we will calculate the proximity between two 
           scrolls and try to determine the genealogy of Demons Scrolls.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>3. Estimation Model for the Picture Scroll Editing Process</head>
        <p>Several previous studies have examined the editorial process of Japanese cultural artifacts. Yano Tamaki has conducted research on the 
          genealogy of esoteric texts on the tea ceremony (<foreign xml:lang="ja">chadō</foreign>) <ptr target="#yano1999"/> <ptr target="#yano2022"/>, 
          as well as the <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Sanjūrokkasen Emaki</foreign></title> (<title rend="quotes">Picture Scroll of 
          Thirty-Six Master Poets</title>) <ptr target="#yano2006" loc="36–42"/>, using tools such as SpritsTree<note>Available at: 
          <ref target="https://uni-tuebingen.de/en/fakultaeten/mathematisch-naturwissenschaftliche-fakultaet/fachbereiche/informatik/lehrstuehle/algorithms-in-bioinformatics/software/splitstree/">https://uni-tuebingen.de/en/fakultaeten/mathematisch-naturwissenschaftliche-fakultaet/fachbereiche/informatik/lehrstuehle/algorithms-in-bioinformatics/software/splitstree/</ref>.</note> 
          and Hayashi's Quantification Theory Family III.<note>Hayashi's Quantification Theory was developed by Hayashi Chikio during late 1940s 
          to 50s and widely used in Japan. Its <q>Family III</q> is mathematically equivalent to Correspondence Analysis.</note> Nevertheless, these 
          studies rely on textual arrangement, including those that focus on illustrated scrolls. There is a conspicuous lack of previous research that 
          examines the genealogy of picture scrolls based on their visual representations.
        </p>
        <p>To ascertain the picture scroll editing process, we propose the following estimation model: the fewer the differences between scrolls, 
           the shorter the number of edits between them, and the closer they are to each other in the chain of copying. For instance, if one block 
           differs between scrolls A and B, and between B and C, and two blocks differ between scrolls A and C, the most likely conclusion is that 
           B was created by editing A, and C was created by editing B (or vice versa). Obviously, one cannot rule out the possibility that C was 
           created by editing A without mediating B, but this is probably not the case.
        </p>
        <p>This paper utilizes the concept of edit distance in order to quantify the differences between scrolls. Edit distance is a standard method 
           for determining text similarity <ptr target="#nerbonne2005"/>.<note>The edit distance is a metric for evaluating the dissimilarity between 
           two strings. It quantifies the number of operations (e.g. insertions, deletions, and substitutions) necessary to convert one string into 
           another. This metric is widely utilized in computer science and linguistics to assess the similarity of two strings.</note> In recent years, 
           the field of linguistic computing has developed a variety of applications for edit distance, such as historical name normalization 
           <ptr target="#hamalainen2018"/> <ptr target="#benito-santos2019"/>, text comparison <ptr target="#bernholz2011"/> <ptr target="#hyytiainen2022"/>, 
           and analysis of library catalog transmission <ptr target="#baker2022"/>. Its application to visual arts, however, is somewhat challenging 
           because edit distance is rarely applied to non-textual data.
        </p>
        <p>Typically, edit distance is calculated based on the number of edit operations per symbol, but to accommodate this application to Demons 
           Scrolls, we will use symbol blocks (chunks of symbols) as the unit and count the numbers of swap, insertion, and deletion operations 
           on the blocks. This estimation model differs from Levenshtein distance (including insertion, deletion, and substitution) and 
           Damelau-Levenshtein distance (Levenshtein plus transposition of two adjacent characters). We will assume that the differences between 
           the symbol arrays <q>123456789</q> (sequence-A), <q>145678239</q> (sequence-B), and <q>167845239</q> (sequence-C) are due to editing 
           operations. The estimated editing procedure is described in Figure 2. The symbol block <q>23</q> in sequence-A first swaps with 
           <q>45678</q>, then it turns into sequence-B. Next, the symbol block <q>45</q> in sequence-B swaps with <q>678</q>, then it becomes 
           sequence-C. The edit distance between A and B (and also between B and C) is one, while the edit distance between A and C is two. In this 
           example, it is plausible that the sequence-A is edited into sequence-B, which is then edited into sequence-C (or vice versa). This 
           estimation model is incapable of determining a single conclusion; it can only indicate what are the plausible processes. Therefore, 
           it is essential to confirm the estimation's accuracy by employing additional qualitative methods.
        </p>
          <figure>
            <head>Estimation model of editing process using edit distance of symbol sequences.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/Fig02.png"/>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
        <p>This estimation model posits that picture scrolls can be segmented and encoded. By identifying the individual demons depicted in a Demons 
           Scroll, it is possible to create symbol blocks and segment the scroll. However, this estimation model is challenging to apply when parts of 
           a scroll are missing or if the consecutively joined sheets of paper have become disordered.<note>Japanese picture scrolls are comprised of 
           several sheets of paper which are joined together to form a continuous horizontal format. The individual sheets are detachable and can be 
           easily rejoined, so disorder may occur after the series of sheets are separated.</note>
        </p>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>4. Works for Discussion</head>
        <p>This paper will analyze seventy-one Demons Scrolls, which include the sixty-four works catalogued by Komatsu 
           <ptr target="#komatsu2008" loc="249–254"/>. We excluded works that were evidently copied after the mid-nineteenth century, and limited 
           our study to the previously mentioned four lineages, as well as works constituting mixed editions of them. Komatsu classified the lineages 
           as follows: class-A (Shinjuan lineage), class-B (Nichibunken-A lineage), class-C (KCUA lineage), and class-D (Hyogo-A lineage).<note>There 
           are numerous scrolls with <q><foreign xml:lang="ja">Hyakki Yagyō</foreign></q> or similar terms in their titles, but we omitted them if the 
           majority of demons depicted are not from these four lineages.</note> In addition, he discovered four types of mixed copies, including 
           class-AB (Shinjuan+Nichibunken-A), class-AC (Shinjuan+KCUA), class-AD (Shinjuan+Hyogo-A), and class-BC (Nichibunken-A+KCUA). However, a closer 
           look at these scrolls reveals that Komatsu's class-AB can be divided further into two classes: class-AB (the Shinjuan scroll demons come first, 
           followed by the Nichibunken-A parade of demons) and class-BA (the demons in the Nichibunken-A scroll come first, followed by those in the 
           Shinjuan scroll). Class-AD can also be divided into AD and DA. Our revised list of works is presented in the Appendix in light of these findings.
        </p>
        <p>As stated at the end of section 2, we identified the demons by focusing on their relative positions in the parade sequence as opposed to 
           minute differences in their depictions. Similar demons appearing in a similar sequence in two scrolls are deemed identical, and the two 
           arrangements are thought to be the same (Figure 3). This method is not applicable to picture scrolls with a strong suspicion of missing or 
           disordered sheets of paper, or to folding screens and hanging scrolls. Therefore, such materials were excluded from the analysis. The target 
           works are consequently limited, as shown in the Appendix. We should note that one of the target works (Kyōgaen in class-AC) is a woodblock-printed 
           book and not a painted scroll. We decided to include it because the demons in the book are depicted in sequential order and it contains useful 
           information such as the date of publication. 
        </p>
          <figure>
            <head>A case where two arrangements are regarded as identical, considering the adjacent demons (upper: Nichibunken-A, lower: Geidai-A).</head>
                <graphic url="resources/Fig03.png"/>
                <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>5.1 Genealogy of the Shinjuan Lineage</head>
        <p>Based on the arrangement of demons, we will first attempt to estimate the editing process of the Shinjuan (class-A) lineage, the most 
           popular lineage of Demons Scrolls. As depicted in Figure 4, we identified all the demons in the Shinjuan scroll and assigned numbers to them. 
           Using these numbers, eight other class-A scrolls were converted into symbol sequences. The Shinjuan (No. 1 in Appendix), Itō (No. 7), Iwate (No. 9), 
           NDL-A (No. 12), Nichibunken-B (No. 14), Nichibunken-C (No. 15), Rekihaku-A (No. 18), Rikkyo (No. 21), and Spencer-B (No. 23) are the nine scrolls 
           examined here that show almost the same numbers of demons in comparison to the Shinjuan scroll (Figure 5). In the case of the Shinjuan and 
           Rekihaku-A scrolls, for instance, if we swap two blocks of demons in Shinjuan, (No. 04−07 with 08−30, and No. 20−30 with 31−43 in Figure 4) the 
           demons transform into the arrangement in Rekihaku-A. The edit distance between the two scrolls is therefore two (See Figure 6).
        </p>
          <figure>
            <head>Numbering the demons in the Shinjuan scroll. The scroll is viewed from upper-right to lower-left <ptr target="#tanaka1999"/>.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/Fig04.png"/>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <head>Demons in the Shinjuan scroll are sequentially numbered from the beginning (right edge of the scroll) to the end (left edge). 
                  The hyphenated numbers are the common blocks in eight scrolls excepting Rikkyo. The numbers that are underlined or in square 
                  brackets indicate the duplication and the omission of a demon, respectively. The Rikkyo scroll is separated from the discussion 
                  because of its unique arrangement.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/Fig05.png"/>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <head>Edit distance between two scrolls. The scrolls are viewed from right to left.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/Fig06.png"/>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
        <p>Of these nine scrolls, we omitted the Rikkyo scroll because of its evidently unique arrangement. It has an unusual layout compared to 
           other scrolls and can be considered an atypical copy. The edit distances between eight of the scrolls are shown in Table 1. Among them, 
           the arrangement of Nichibunken-B is particularly notable (Yumoto-A [No. 26 in the Appendix] has the same arrangement).<note>The 
           Yumoto-A scroll is in fact a more detailed copy than Nichibunken-B. Nevertheless, we chose the latter because it is undeniably an older scroll.
           The NDL-B (No. 12 in the Appendix) and Spencer-B scrolls both contain written accounts of each scene that are identical. The Tōhaku-B (No. 71) 
           and Spencer-B scrolls are rare cases where the names of demons are included.</note> This copy is connected to five scrolls (Shinjuan, Itō, NDL-A, 
           Nichibunken-C, and Rekihaku-A) via an edit distance of one.
        </p>
          <table>
            <head>Edit distance between eight Shinjuan (class-A) lineage scrolls. The lower left section of the table is omitted because the numbers are 
                  identical to those in the upper right section.</head>
            <row role="label">
              <cell></cell>
              <cell role="label">Shinjuan</cell>
              <cell role="label">Itō</cell>
              <cell role="label">Iwate</cell>
              <cell role="label">NDL-A</cell>
              <cell role="label">Nichibunken-B</cell>
              <cell role="label">Nichibunken-C</cell>
              <cell role="label">Rekihaku-A</cell>
              <cell role="label">Spencer-B</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell role="label">Shinjuan</cell>
              <cell>0</cell>
              <cell>2</cell>
              <cell>3</cell>
              <cell>2</cell>
              <cell>1</cell>
              <cell>2</cell>
              <cell>2</cell>
              <cell>2</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell role="label">Itō</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>0</cell>
              <cell>3</cell>
              <cell>2</cell>
              <cell>1</cell>
              <cell>2</cell>
              <cell>2</cell>
              <cell>4</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell role="label">Iwate</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>0</cell>
              <cell>3</cell>
              <cell>2</cell>
              <cell>3</cell>
              <cell>3</cell>
              <cell>5</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell role="label">NDL-A</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>0</cell>
              <cell>1</cell>
              <cell>2</cell>
              <cell>2</cell>
              <cell>4</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell role="label">Nichibunken-B</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>0</cell>
              <cell>1</cell>
              <cell>1</cell>
              <cell>3</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell role="label">Nichibunken-C</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>0</cell>
              <cell>1</cell>
              <cell>4</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell role="label">Rekihaku-A</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>0</cell>
              <cell>4</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell role="label">Spencer-B</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>0</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
        <p>Based on the matrix of edit distance, multiple possible lineage trees can be drawn. The simplest tree is a structure where the 
           sum of the distances is minimized, or the <q>minimum spanning tree</q>, as depicted in Figure 7. Nichibunken-B (Yumoto-A), which 
           is located at the <q>root</q> and has the shortest distance to other scrolls, is connected to the Itō, NDL-A, Nichibunken-C, 
           Rekihaku-A, and Shinjuan scrolls at a distance of one, and to the Iwate scroll at a distance of two. Spencer-B is connected at two 
           to the Shinjuan scroll, while Rikkyo is isolated. If the class-A lineage shares a common ancestor, this tree indicates that the 
           Nichibunken-B scroll's demon arrangement is the closest to it. In other words, it is possible that the Shinjuan scroll is a rearranged 
           version of Nichibunken-B's prototype.
        </p>
          <figure>
            <head>The minimum spanning tree of class-A scrolls.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/Fig07.png"/>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
        <p>This lineage tree is supported by a comparison of iconographic details. For example, let us investigate whether or not a handle is 
           depicted on the pot lid of the <q>demon wearing a pot lid</q> that appears in the latter half of class-A lineage scrolls (Figure 8). 
           Japanese art historian Komatsu Shigemi observed that the handle depicted in the Tōhaku-A (No. 49 in the Appendix) scroll was missing 
           in the Shinjuan scroll. He stated that <quote rend="inline">such detailed copying strongly suggests that the Shinjuan scroll was painted 
           based on a prototype</quote> and that the Shinjuan scroll had another prototype <ptr target="#komatsu1979b" loc="132"/>. If we apply the 
           presence or absence of the <q>pot lid handle</q> to the lineage tree depicted in Figure 7, we find that the <q>handle</q> is depicted in 
           Nichibunken-B (Yumoto-A), which is at the <q>root</q>, and in the Iwate version, but not in other scrolls. This indicates that the 
           presence of the <q>handle</q> was clearly distinguished on the lineage tree. While Nichibunken-B (Yumoto-A) retains the demon arrangement 
           of the ancestorial copy relatively well, the Shinjuan and other six scrolls are copies of versions in which the <q>pot lid handle</q> was 
           omitted.
        </p>
          <figure>
            <head>With and without <q>pot lid handle</q> (left: Nichibunken-B scroll, right: Shinjuan scroll).</head>
              <graphic url="resources/Fig08.png"/>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
        <p>In what ways do the demon configurations of the Nichibunken-B and Shinjuan scrolls differ? As illustrated in Figure 9, the two can be 
           transformed by a single block swap. It is remarkable that some of the movable demon blocks in the Shinjuan scroll can be separated 
           at the paper joins. Five joins in this scroll do not overlap the figures, and three of them are the boundaries where the demons are 
           arranged differently than in Nichibunken-B. In contrast, only one join at the beginning of the Nichibunken-B scroll does not overlap the 
           figure. In other words, the arrangement of the demons in the Shinjuan scroll can be transformed to that of Nichibunken-B by simply 
           detaching the paper joins and rearranging the sheets. If the arrangement of Nichibunken-B is closer to the Shinjuan scroll's prototype, 
           we can conclude that the order of paper sheets became disordered during a remounting and resulted in the current arrangement in the 
           Shinjuan scroll. This new theory regarding Demons Scrolls emerged from the field of digital humanities. Close inspection reveals that the 
           Shinjuan scroll's joined sheets of paper are stained along their edges. This indicates that the sheets of papers were separated and 
           preserved for a certain period of time, and is evidence supporting our conclusion that the sheets were incorrectly arranged when the 
           scroll was reassembled.
        </p>
          <figure>
            <head>Differences in the arrangement of demons in the Nichibunken-B and Shinjuan scrolls (viewed right to left). Up arrows indicate 
                  the places where the paper sheets are joined and the figures do not overlap.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/Fig09.png"/>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>5.2 Iconographical Interpretation Through Numbering</head>
        <p>Because the majority of Demons Scrolls lack the names and descriptions of each demon, it is difficult to comprehend their iconographic 
           meanings. Nonetheless, by numbering the demons, we are able to see how the individual demons collectively form meaningful units. If a 
           block of demons appears in multiple copies, it indicates that it was recognized as a <q>unit</q> by multiple painters. 
        </p>
        <p>Researchers of Demons Scrolls have debated the iconography of No. 31 (running fox lady) in Figure 10: whether she is <q>running 
           toward</q> the group of ugly women with black teeth<note>Tooth blackening (<foreign xml:lang="ja">ohaguro</foreign>) was a Japanese 
           cosmetic treatment used primarily by married women to darken their teeth.</note> in front of her (No. 24−30) <ptr target="#komatsu1979a" loc="81"/> 
           <ptr target="#yumoto2005" loc="40"/>, or <q>escaping</q> from the cloud of demons that follows (No. 32−) <ptr target="#yasumura1987" loc="43"/> 
           <ptr target="#komatsu2008" loc="39"/>. An examination of Figure 5 reveals that six scrolls (Itō, Iwate, NDL-A, Nichibunken-B, Nichibunken-C, 
           and Rekihaku-A) contain the common separation of the block between No. 30 and 31. While it is impossible to determine the intentions of the 
           original painter of the class-A lineage, this separation suggests that many painters who copied the scroll may have interpreted the 
           <q>running fox lady</q> as <q>escaping</q> from the <q>cloud of demons</q>. This is another new theory developed through digital 
           humanities. As previously discussed, misordering of the sheets of paper is suspected between section No. 30 and 31 in the Shinjuan scroll. 
           In other words, the original compositional arrangement would also have intended the <q>fox lady</q> to be <q>escaping</q>.
        </p>
          <figure>
            <head>One of the common separated blocks of demon sequences in the class-A lineage annotated on the Shinjuan scroll 
                  <ptr target="#tanaka1999"/>.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/Fig10.png"/>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>5.3 Genealogy of the Class-AB/BA Lineage</head>
        <p>Next, we will examine the ancestry of the class-AB/BA lineages. Class-AB comprises the combined scrolls that begin with Shinjuan demons 
           followed by Nichibunken-A demons, and class-BA is the opposite. In terms of the arrangement of demons, class-AB/BA scrolls share a common 
           characteristic. Near the end of the scrolls, there is a section where three demons from the class-B lineage are interwoven among class-A 
           demons (Figure 11). Such shared characteristics would not exist if the prototypes for class-AB and class-BA scrolls were created independently 
           by different painters at different times. Instead, it would be more natural to assume that class-AB/BA scrolls share a common ancestor and 
           later copies followed this sequence as it appears in their ancestor scroll. The characteristics of class-AB/BA scrolls are summarized in 
           Table 2.
        </p>
          <figure>
            <head>Shared sequence of class-AB/BA lineage scrolls (Tōhaku-A).</head>
              <graphic url="resources/Fig11.png"/>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <table>
            <head>Characteristics of class-AB/BA scrolls.</head>
              <row role="label">
                <cell role="label">Class</cell>
                <cell role="label">No.</cell>
                <cell role="label">Scroll</cell>
                <cell role="label">class-A Part</cell>
                <cell role="label">class-B Part</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>AB</cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell>35</cell>
                <cell>Beatty</cell>
                <cell>Identical to Shinjuan (the first demon omitted)</cell>
                <cell>Many swaps and omissions</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell>36</cell>
                <cell>Kunaichō-A</cell>
                <cell>Many swaps and omissions</cell>
                <cell>Many swaps, deformations, and omissions</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell>37</cell>
                <cell>Rekihaku-C</cell>
                <cell>Identical to Shinjuan</cell>
                <cell>Most demons omitted leaving three</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>BA</cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell>40</cell>
                <cell>Geidai-A</cell>
                <cell>Identical to Shinjuan</cell>
                <cell>Many swaps and omissions</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell>45</cell>
                <cell>OHRM</cell>
                <cell>Partially swapped from Shinjuan</cell>
                <cell>Many swaps, deformations, and omissions</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell>47</cell>
                <cell>Rekihaku-B</cell>
                <cell>Identical to Tōhaku-A</cell>
                <cell>Many swaps, deformations, and omissions</cell>
              </row> 
              <row>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell>49</cell>
                <cell>Tōhaku-A</cell>
                <cell>Partially swapped from Shinjuan</cell>
                <cell>Many swaps, deformations, and omissions</cell>
              </row>
          </table>
        <p>At first glance, it is evident that the majority of demon configurations of the class-A part of the picture scroll are nearly 
           identical to those of the Shinjuan scroll. In contrast, the demons in the class-B part contain more swaps, deformations, and 
           omissions from the Nichibunken-A scroll. In the Kunaichō-A, OHRM, Rekihaku-B, and Tōhaku-A scrolls, a deformation refers to the change 
           from <q>demon with spear and hat</q> to <q>octopus head demon</q> (Figure 12). 
        </p>
          <figure>
            <head><q>Demon with spear and hat</q> and <q>Octopus head demon</q> (left: Nichibunken-A scroll; right: Tōhaku-A scroll).</head>
              <graphic url="resources/Fig12.png"/>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
        <p>Among the class-AB scrolls, the only scroll discussed in this paper is the Beatty scroll, which retains the arrangement of 
           demons relatively well. On another front, this method make it possible to trace the genealogy of class-BA. Based on the edit 
           distance among the class-BA scrolls (Table 3), the minimum spanning tree is depicted as a linear connection: Geidai-A to OHRM to 
           Tōhaku-A to Rekihaku-B (or vice versa) with distances of two, two, and one, respectively. As in the case of class-A scrolls, this lineage 
           tree must be evaluated based on qualitative characteristics. The four class-BA scrolls contain four peculiar depictions: a demon with 
           a <q>pot lid handle</q> attached or not, a fleeing monkey wearing a hat or not, a spear-carrying demon with an octopus head or not, 
           and a demon holding two leaves depicted or not (Table 4). Using these binary categorical data, Figure 13 is generated as a dendrogram.
        </p>
          <table>
            <head>Edit distance between class-BA scrolls.</head>
              <row role="label">
                <cell role="label"></cell>
                <cell role="label">Geidai-A</cell>
                <cell role="label">OHRM</cell>
                <cell role="label">Rekihaku-B</cell>
                <cell role="label">Tōhaku-A</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell role="label">Geidai-A</cell>
                <cell>0</cell>
                <cell>2</cell>
                <cell>5</cell>
                <cell>4</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell role="label">OHRM</cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell>0</cell>
                <cell>3</cell>
                <cell>2</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell role="label">Rekihaku-B</cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell>0</cell>
                <cell>1</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell role="label">Tōhaku-A</cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell>0</cell>
              </row>
          </table>
          <table>
            <head>The qualitative characteristics in class-AB (Beaty) and BA (others) scrolls.</head>
              <row role="label">
                <cell role="label">Scroll</cell>
                <cell role="label">Pot Lid Handle</cell>
                <cell role="label">Monkey with Hat</cell>
                <cell role="label">Octopus Head</cell>
                <cell role="label">Two Leaves</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Beatty</cell>
                <cell>✓</cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell>✓</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Geidai-A</cell>
                <cell>✓</cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell>✓</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>OHRM</cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell></cell>
                <cell>✓</cell>
                <cell></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Tōhaku-A</cell>
                <cell>✓</cell>
                <cell>✓</cell>
                <cell>✓</cell>
                <cell></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Rekihaku-B</cell>
                <cell>✓</cell>
                <cell>✓</cell>
                <cell>✓</cell>
                <cell></cell>
              </row>
          </table>
          <figure>
            <head>Dendrogram of four class-BA scrolls employing four characteristics of demon depiction (average linkage clustering and Euclid 
                  distance). The Tōhaku-A and Rekihaku-B scrolls share the same characteristics.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/Fig13.png"/>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
        <p>This dendrogram supports the premise that the root of the lineage tree is traceable to Geidai-A. As a result, the most straightforward 
           iconographic transmission started from Geidai-A, which was inherited by OHRM, Tōhaku-A, and Rekihaku-B (Figure 14). First, the 
           <q>demon with two leaves</q> motif was omitted from Geidai-A, creating a nested image for OHRM. The <q>demon with a spear and hat</q> 
           appearing at the beginning of the scroll was transformed into a <q>demon with an octopus head</q> at this time.<note>Similar transformation 
           is indicated in Figure 12.</note> When the ancestor of the OHRM scroll was swapped by two blocks, the arrangement of Tōhaku-A was produced. 
           A further one-block swap resulted in the Rekihaku-B arrangement. In addition to OHRM, the Tōhaku-A and Rekihaku-B scrolls also exclude 
           the <q>demon with two leaves</q> motif and transform the <q>demon with a spear and hat</q> into an <q>octopus head demon</q>.
        </p>
          <figure>
            <head>From Geidai-A to OHRM, Tōhaku-A, Rekihaku-B scrolls. The last parts of the scrolls have been abbreviated.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/Fig14.png"/>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
        <p>Based on the preceding, Figure 15 depicts the results of estimating the editing process of the class-AB/BA lineages. Initially, 
           these classes were created relying upon prototypes of the Shinjuan and Nichibunken-A scrolls, but at some point the <q>demon in a white 
           robe</q> motif was omitted. The Geidai-A scroll is the closest to the class-BA prototype. The OHRM scroll was created using Geidai-A's 
           ancestor as a template. In the process, the <q>demon with a spear and a hat</q> became an <q>octopus head demon</q>, and the 
           <q>demon with two leaves</q> motif was omitted. The ancestors of Tōhaku-A and Rekihaku-B were born from the OHRM prototype.
        </p>
          <figure>
            <head>Estimation of the editing process of the class-AB/BA lineage. Each scroll name does not always refer to the scroll itself but also 
                  may indicate its prototype.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/Fig15.png"/>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
        <p>Let us apply two qualitative characteristics of the iconographic specifics to the results of this estimate. The first characteristic is 
           the presence or absence of a <q>pot lid handle</q> in the previously mentioned class-A lineage, and the second is whether or not the 
           <q>fleeing monkey</q> in the latter half of the class-B lineage is wearing a hat. As seen in the Nichibunken-B scroll, it can be 
           assumed that the <q>pot lid handle</q> was originally a part of the class-A lineage, but that it was eliminated in the Shinjuan scroll. 
           As in the Nichibunken-A scroll, the <q>fleeing monkey</q> would have been depicted without a hat in the class-B prototype. These two 
           characteristics were passed along to the Beatty and Geidai-A scrolls. In contrast, a <q>pot lid handle</q> was added after the Geidai-A 
           scroll was created, and the <q>fleeing monkey</q> was covered with a hat after the OHRM. These characteristics are shared by the Tōhaku-A 
           and Rekihaku-B scrolls.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>Estimating the Editing Process of Demons Scrolls</head>
        <p>The editing processes of the class-AC and AD/DA lineages remain to be estimated. As for class-AC, Kyōgaen (No. 55 in the Appendix), 
           Sendai (No. 56), Tōdai (No. 58), and Yumoto-F (No. 59) will be considered. It is difficult to determine the edit distance between these 
           works, however, due to the numerous additions, deletions, and swaps of demons from the prototype. The arrangement of demons in the 
           class-A lineage appears to be based not on the Shinjuan scroll but on Nichibunken-B in all of these materials. Consequently, the 
           <q>pot lid handle</q> is depicted in all the class-AC scrolls that have survived. It was combined with the ancestor of KCUA to form 
           the class-AC prototype, from which the draft of Kyōgaen (dated 1775) was created.
        </p>
        <p>As for class-AD/DA scrolls, the characteristics are indicated in Table 5. Similar to class-AC, AD shares many characteristics with 
           Nichibunken-B instead of the Shinjuan scroll. Rekisaikan-B and Spencer-C, which retain the arrangement of Nichibunken-B, appear to be 
           the closest to the class-AD prototype.
        </p>
          <table>
            <head>Characteristics of class-AD/DA scrolls.</head>
              <row role="label">
                <cell role="label">Class</cell>
                <cell role="label">No.</cell>
                <cell role="label">Scroll</cell>
                <cell role="label">class-A Part</cell>
                <cell role="label">class-D Part</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>AD</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>60</cell>
              <cell>Ehime</cell>
              <cell>Unique arrangement</cell>
              <cell>Many additions, swaps, and omissions</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>64</cell>
              <cell>Rekisaikan-B</cell>
              <cell>Identical to Nichibunken-B</cell>
              <cell>Many additions, swaps, and omissions</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>65</cell>
              <cell>Rekihaku-D</cell>
              <cell>A part of Nichibunken-B</cell>
              <cell>Resembles Spencer-C</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>66</cell>
              <cell>Spencer-C</cell>
              <cell>Identical to Shinjuan (the first to the third demons omitted)</cell>
              <cell>One demon swapped from Rekisaikan-B</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>DA</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>69</cell>
              <cell>Yamauchi</cell>
              <cell>Unique arrangement</cell>
              <cell>Identical to Spencer-C</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>70</cell>
              <cell>Waseda-B</cell>
              <cell>Identical to NDL-A</cell>
              <cell>Identical to Spencer-C</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
        <p>As an example, we will describe how the demons in Rekisaikan-B are arranged. Although the sequence is split and copied, the demons are 
           identical to those in the Nichibunken-B scroll; however, the editing of the demons from Hyogo-A is more complicated. Moreover, the 
           class-D part of the Rekisaikan-B scroll contains two demons that are absent from Hyogo-A. This suggests that the demons within the Hyogo-A 
           scroll may have been repeatedly swapped and eliminated during the copying process from the class-D prototype.
        </p>
        <p>On the basis of the preceding argument, the class-AD/DA editing process can be estimated as follows: First, the class-A component of AD/DA 
           scrolls is based on the prototype of Nichibunken-B. The initial class-AD/DA scrolls were created from this and the ancestor of Hyogo-A. 
           However, after the creation of the prototypes, it is difficult to ascertain the genealogies of this lineage. The <q>pot lid handle</q> 
           is not depicted in existing class-AD/DA scrolls. Since the prototype of class-A appears to have possessed the <q>pot lid handle</q> motif 
           as exemplified in Nichibunken-B, it was likely eliminated around the time the ancestors of these scrolls were painted. If this is the case, 
           class-AD/DA scrolls which include the <q>pot lid handles</q> could be the missing link in this lineage.
        </p>
        <p>Finally, let us summarize the estimation of the editing processes of Demons Scroll lineages (Figure 16). The most important point is that 
           among the various scrolls in the class-A lineage, the compositional arrangement of demons in Nichibunken-B is older than that of the 
           most famous Shinjuan scroll. In addition, the author argues that the arrangement of demons in the present-day Shinjuan scroll was created 
           through the misordering of its paper sheets. In class-AB/BA scrolls, the arrangement seen in Nichibunken-A was combined with that of the 
           current Shinjuan scroll, whereas class-AC and AD/DA scrolls are assumed to have combined motifs from the ancestor of Nichibunken-B, instead 
           of the Shinjuan scroll. Since Kyōgaen, a class-AC printed book, has a colophon dated 1775, the original class-AC lineage must have been 
           established prior to that year.
        </p>
          <figure>
            <head>Estimation of the editing process of Demons Scroll lineages.</head>
              <graphic url="resources/Fig16.png"/>
              <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
        <p>The other datable artifact is Tōhaku-B, a scroll of class-BC that was not examined in detail for this paper. Tōhaku-B contains demons 
           from the KCUA scroll mixed with those from Nichibunken-A (the majority of which are inverted), as well as demons not found in either 
           scroll. It is dated 1617, so it is likely that both the Nichibunken-A and KCUA scrolls were painted prior to that year. Based on the 
           clothing and customs depicted in the scrolls, some scholars believe that their prototypes were painted in the sixteenth century. Since 
           the Shinjuan scroll is also said to have been created in the sixteenth century, the prototype for Nichibunken-B must have been made around 
           or prior to that time. On the other hand, since it is believed that the original Hyogo-A scroll was created during the Edo period (1603–1868), 
           it can be assumed that the class-AD/DA lineages evolved during the same time frame or later.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>6. Conclusion</head>
        <p>The above-mentioned estimates are the result of using a digital humanities approach to study Demons Scrolls, focusing on the configuration 
           of demons. The fact that we were able to deduce and reconstruct the rational editing process from the surviving scrolls provides additional 
           support for the mixture theory of Demons Scrolls. However, there is one flaw in this paper's methodology. If the differences in arrangement 
           are the result of changes in the order of the paper sheets occurring in later periods, the conclusion may be affected. Although scrolls 
           with a high probability of misordered paper sheets were excluded from this study in advance, if a disorder is discovered in other scrolls, 
           it will be necessary to reconsider our findings. However, if we consider this kind of disorder to be the result of editing by someone other 
           than the painter, it may not be necessary to exclude all disordered scrolls.
        </p>
        <p>To further strengthen the mixture theory of Demons Scrolls, two additional riddles must be solved. First, if there are four distinct 
           lineages, why are the surviving non-class-A scrolls so few in number? There are at least twenty-seven copies in the class-A lineage, but 
           only two in class-B and class-D, and three in the class-C lineages. Second, why are all the demons in the combined scrolls from the class-A 
           lineage? If there were four distinct lineages, one would expect to find a greater number of combined scrolls from lineages other than class-A. 
           The only exception to this rule is Tōhaku-B (class-BC, No. 71 in the Appendix); the absence of class-BD and CD scrolls is also a mystery. 
           This may be due to the preferences of the group of painters who replicated the Demons Scroll and/or their patrons. We defer clarification 
           of this point to future art historical research.
        </p>
        <p>This digital humanities research methodology is applicable to other types of undated materials in which the separable unit in the content 
           is ordered sequentially and there are multiple versions in which the unit is swapped, omitted, or a new unit is inserted. To name a few 
           examples: handwritten catalogs of Japanese martial arts, other picture scrolls of which multiple copies were produced, and even drafts of 
           novels. To broaden the potential application of this method, mutual understanding and increased collaborations between the digital humanities 
           and other disciplines are essential.
        </p>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>Acknowledgements</head>
        <p>This paper is based on an article originally published in Japanese <ptr target="#yamada2009"/>. The author added new data, corrected errors, 
           updated the discussion, and edited the manuscript for an Anglophone audience. This research utilized digital images collected by the 
           Database Project for Cultural Materials on Monsters and Specters directed by Komatsu Kazuhiko at the International Research Center for 
           Japanese Studies (Nichibunken).
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="appendix">
      <head>Appendix</head>
      <table>
            <row role="label">
              <cell role="label">Class</cell>
              <cell role="label">No.</cell>
              <cell role="label">Name (tentative)</cell>
              <cell role="label">Owner</cell>
              <cell role="label">Format</cell>
              <cell role="label">Official Resource</cell>
              <cell role="label">Target</cell>
              <cell role="label">Note</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A (Shinjuan lineage)</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>1</cell>
              <cell>Sinjuan</cell>
              <cell>Shinjuan sub-temple, Daitokuji temple</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>2</cell>
              <cell>Appendix for <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Kaidan meisakush ū</foreign></title></cell>
              <cell>Unknown</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Identical to Rekisaikan-A</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>3</cell>
              <cell>Boston</cell>
              <cell>Museum of Fine Arts, USA</cell>
              <cell>Hanging scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Hanging scroll format</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>4</cell>
              <cell>Gakushuin</cell>
              <cell>Gakushuin University</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>One demon dropped; almost identical to Nichibunken-B</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>5</cell>
              <cell>Guimet</cell>
              <cell>Guimet Museum, France</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>First half missing; identical to Itō and Nichibunken-B</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>6</cell>
              <cell>Gunma</cell>
              <cell>Gunma University</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Whole picture is unknown</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>7</cell>
              <cell>Itō</cell>
              <cell>Itō Mitsunori</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell>Attributed to Kanō Morifusa, ca. 1688–1707</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>8</cell>
              <cell>Iwase</cell>
              <cell>Iwase Bunko Library</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Unique arrangement; demons added from <title rend="quotes">Bakemono zukushi</title></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>9</cell>
              <cell>Iwate</cell>
              <cell>Iwate Prefectural Museum</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>10</cell>
              <cell>Kōdaiji</cell>
              <cell>Kōdaiji temple</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>First half missing; identical to Itō and Nichibunken-B</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>11</cell>
              <cell>Krakow</cell>
              <cell>Museum of Japanese Art and Technology, Poland</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Second half missing</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>12</cell>
              <cell>NDL-A</cell>
              <cell>National Diet Library</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://dl.ndl.go.jp/info:ndljp/pid/2541003">https://dl.ndl.go.jp/info:ndljp/pid/2541003</ref></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>13</cell>
              <cell>NDL-B</cell>
              <cell>National Diet Library</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://dl.ndl.go.jp/info:ndljp/pid/2540972">https://dl.ndl.go.jp/info:ndljp/pid/2540972</ref></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>With description, demons significantly omitted and swapped; dated 1316 but dubious</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>14</cell>
              <cell>Nichibunken-B</cell>
              <cell>International Research Center for Japanese Studies (Nichibunken)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://toshonin.nichibun.ac.jp/webopac/TW92059016">https://toshonin.nichibun.ac.jp/webopac/TW92059016</ref></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>15</cell>
              <cell>Nichibunken-C</cell>
              <cell>International Research Center for Japanese Studies (Nichibunken)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://toshonin.nichibun.ac.jp/webopac/BB10030852">https://toshonin.nichibun.ac.jp/webopac/BB10030852</ref></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>16</cell>
              <cell>OCM</cell>
              <cell>Osaka City Museum of Fine Arts</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Disorder suspected</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>17</cell>
              <cell>Okura-A</cell>
              <cell>Okura Museum of Art</cell>
              <cell>Screen</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Screen format</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>18</cell>
              <cell>Rekihaku-A</cell>
              <cell>National Museum of Japanese History (Rekihaku)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://www.rekihaku.ac.jp/database/syuz/F-320-3">https://www.rekihaku.ac.jp/database/syuz/F-320-3</ref></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>19</cell>
              <cell>Rekihaku-E</cell>
              <cell>National Museum of Japanese History (Rekihaku)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://www.rekihaku.ac.jp/database/syuz/F-320-705">https://www.rekihaku.ac.jp/database/syuz/F-320-705</ref></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Identical to Iwase; dated 1684</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>20</cell>
              <cell>Rekisaikan-A</cell>
              <cell>Kyoto Institute, Library and Archives (Rekisaikan)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="http://www.archives.kyoto.jp/websearchpe/detail?cls=152_old_books_catalog&amp;pkey=0000000115">http://www.archives.kyoto.jp/websearchpe/detail?cls=152_old_books_catalog&amp;pkey=0000000115</ref></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Identical to NDL-A</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>21</cell>
              <cell>Rikkyo</cell>
              <cell>Rikkyo University</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>22</cell>
              <cell>Saiku</cell>
              <cell>Saiku Historical Museum</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Identical to Shinjuan</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>23</cell>
              <cell>Spencer-B</cell>
              <cell>New York Public Library, USA</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell>With description, two demons are duplicated</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>24</cell>
              <cell>Tōhaku-C</cell>
              <cell>Tokyo National Museum (Tōhaku)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://colbase.nich.go.jp/collection_items/tnm/A-3169?locale=ja">https://colbase.nich.go.jp/collection_items/tnm/A-3169?locale=ja</ref></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Identical to Nichibunken-B</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>25</cell>
              <cell>Waseda-A</cell>
              <cell>Waseda University</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://archive.wul.waseda.ac.jp/kosho/wa03/wa03_03645/wa03_03645_0404/">https://archive.wul.waseda.ac.jp/kosho/wa03/wa03_03645/wa03_03645_0404/</ref></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>First demon omitted from Shinjuan</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>26</cell>
              <cell>Yumoto-A</cell>
              <cell>Yumoto Kōichi</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Identical to Nichibunken-B</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>27</cell>
              <cell>Yumoto-B</cell>
              <cell>Yumoto Kōichi</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Identical to Iwase</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>B (Nichibuken-A lineage)</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>28</cell>
              <cell>Nichibunken-A</cell>
              <cell>International Research Center for Japanese Studies (Nichibunken)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://toshonin.nichibun.ac.jp/webopac/BB10030851">https://toshonin.nichibun.ac.jp/webopac/BB10030851</ref></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>29</cell>
              <cell>Yumoto-C</cell>
              <cell>Yumoto Kōichi</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>A part of Nichibunken-A</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>C (KCUA lineage)</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>30</cell>
              <cell>KCUA</cell>
              <cell>Kyoto City University of Arts</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>31</cell>
              <cell>Okura-B</cell>
              <cell>Okura Museum of Art</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Demons significantly omitted; one demon added</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>32</cell>
              <cell>Tokushima</cell>
              <cell>Tokushima Prefectural Museum</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Demons omitted and added</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>D (Hyogo lineage)</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>33</cell>
              <cell>Hyogo-A</cell>
              <cell>Hyogo Prefectural Museum of History</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://rekihaku.pref.hyogo.lg.jp/en/digital_museum/ebanashi/sakuhin/ka0014/">https://rekihaku.pref.hyogo.lg.jp/en/digital_museum/ebanashi/sakuhin/ka0014/</ref></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>34</cell>
              <cell>Illustration in <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Kaidan meisakush ū</foreign></title></cell>
              <cell>Unknown</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Whole picture is unknown</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>AB (Shinjuan + Nichibuken-A)</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>35</cell>
              <cell>Beatty</cell>
              <cell>Chester Beatty Library, Ireland</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>36</cell>
              <cell>Kunaichō-A</cell>
              <cell>Imperial Household Agency (Kunaich ō)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>37</cell>
              <cell>Rekihaku-C</cell>
              <cell>National Museum of Japanese History (Rekihaku)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://www.rekihaku.ac.jp/database/syuz/F-320-4-93">https://www.rekihaku.ac.jp/database/syuz/F-320-4-93</ref></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell>Dated 1822</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>38</cell>
              <cell>Yuishōji</cell>
              <cell>Yuishōji temple</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Whole picture is unknown</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>39</cell>
              <cell>Yumoto-E</cell>
              <cell>Yumoto Kōichi</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Whole picture is unknown</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>BA (Nichibunken-A + Shinjuan)</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>40</cell>
              <cell>Geidai-A</cell>
              <cell>Tokyo University of the Arts (Geidai)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="http://jmapps.ne.jp/geidai/det.html?data_id=19506">http://jmapps.ne.jp/geidai/det.html?data_id=19506</ref></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>41</cell>
              <cell>Hyogo-B</cell>
              <cell>Hyogo Prefectural Museum of History</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://rekihaku.pref.hyogo.lg.jp/en/digital_museum/ebanashi/sakuhin/ka0014/">https://rekihaku.pref.hyogo.lg.jp/en/digital_museum/ebanashi/sakuhin/ka0014/</ref></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Identical to Tōhaku-A</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>42</cell>
              <cell>Kousanji</cell>
              <cell>Kousanji Museum</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Demons significantly mirrored and swapped</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>43</cell>
              <cell>Kumon</cell>
              <cell>Kumon Institute of Education</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Identical to Tōhaku-A</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>44</cell>
              <cell>Kunaichō-B</cell>
              <cell>Imperial Household Agency (Kunaich ō)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Whole picture is unknown</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>45</cell>
              <cell>OHRM</cell>
              <cell>Osaka Human Rights Museum</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>46</cell>
              <cell>Pushkin</cell>
              <cell>Pushkin State Museum of Fine Arts, Russia</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Whole picture is unknown; identical to Geidai-A</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>47</cell>
              <cell>Rekihaku-B</cell>
              <cell>National Museum of Japanese History (Rekihaku)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://www.rekihaku.ac.jp/database/syuz/F-320-213">https://www.rekihaku.ac.jp/database/syuz/F-320-213</ref></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>48</cell>
              <cell>Sanada</cell>
              <cell>The Sanada Treasures Museum</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="http://jmapps.ne.jp/sndhmt/det.html?data_id=5718">http://jmapps.ne.jp/sndhmt/det.html?data_id=5718</ref></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Identical to Tōhaku-copy</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>49</cell>
              <cell>Tōhaku-A</cell>
              <cell>Tokyo National Museum (Tōhaku)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://webarchives.tnm.jp/imgsearch/show/C0056370">https://webarchives.tnm.jp/imgsearch/show/C0056370</ref></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>50</cell>
              <cell>Tohoku</cell>
              <cell>Tohoku University</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://www.i-repository.net/il/meta_pub/G0000398tuldc_1100016310">https://www.i-repository.net/il/meta_pub/G0000398tuldc_1100016310</ref></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Identical to Tōhaku-A</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>51</cell>
              <cell>Yumoto-D</cell>
              <cell>Yumoto Kōichi</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Demons significantly omitted</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>AC (Shinjuan + KCUA)</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>52</cell>
              <cell>Burke</cell>
              <cell>The Burke Foundation, USA</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Identical to <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Kyōgaen</foreign></title></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>53</cell>
              <cell>Konpira-A</cell>
              <cell>Kotohiragū shrine</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Identical to <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Kyōgaen</foreign></title></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>54</cell>
              <cell>Konpira-B</cell>
              <cell>Kotohiragū shrine</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Identical to <title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Kyōgaen</foreign></title></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>55</cell>
              <cell><title rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Kyōgaen</foreign></title></cell>
              <cell>Kawasaki City Museum etc.</cell>
              <cell>Printed book</cell>
              <cell><ref target="http://kawasaki.iri-project.org/content/?doi=0447544/01800000GK">http://kawasaki.iri-project.org/content/?doi=0447544/01800000GK</ref></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell>Dated 1775</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>56</cell>
              <cell>Sendai</cell>
              <cell>Sendai City Museum</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>57</cell>
              <cell>Spencer-A</cell>
              <cell>New York Public Library, USA</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Disorder suspected</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>58</cell>
              <cell>Tōdai</cell>
              <cell>Tokyo University (Tōdai)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://da.dl.itc.u-tokyo.ac.jp/portal/assets/fbd0479b-dbb4-4eaa-95b8-f27e1c423e4b">https://da.dl.itc.u-tokyo.ac.jp/portal/assets/fbd0479b-dbb4-4eaa-95b8-f27e1c423e4b</ref></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>59</cell>
              <cell>Yumoto-F</cell>
              <cell>Yumoto Kōichi</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>AD (Shinjuan + Hyoga-A)</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>60</cell>
              <cell>Ehime</cell>
              <cell>Museum of Ehime History and Culture</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://ehime-archive.iri-project.org/detail/ps-0011">https://ehime-archive.iri-project.org/detail/ps-0011</ref></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>61</cell>
              <cell>Geidai-B</cell>
              <cell>Tokyo University of the Arts (Geidai)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="http://jmapps.ne.jp/geidai/det.html?data_id=32299">http://jmapps.ne.jp/geidai/det.html?data_id=32299</ref></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Identical to Rekisaikan-B</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>62</cell>
              <cell>Kyōgoku</cell>
              <cell>Kyōgoku Natsuhiko</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Whole picture is unknown</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>63</cell>
              <cell>Nichibunken-D</cell>
              <cell>International Research Center for Japanese Studies (Nichibunken)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://toshonin.nichibun.ac.jp/webopac/BB10059786">https://toshonin.nichibun.ac.jp/webopac/BB10059786</ref></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Demons significantly swapped</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>64</cell>
              <cell>Rekisaikan-B</cell>
              <cell>Kyoto Institute, Library and Archives (Rekisaikan) / The Museum of Kyoto</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>65</cell>
              <cell>Rekihaku-D</cell>
              <cell>National Museum of Japanese History (Rekihaku)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://www.rekihaku.ac.jp/database/syuz/F-320-532">https://www.rekihaku.ac.jp/database/syuz/F-320-532</ref></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>66</cell>
              <cell>Spencer-C</cell>
              <cell>New York Public Library, USA</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>67</cell>
              <cell>Yumoto-G</cell>
              <cell>Yumoto Kōichi</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Whole picture is unknown</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>DA (Hyoga-A + Shinjuan)</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>68</cell>
              <cell>Mononobe</cell>
              <cell>Mononobe jinja shrine</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Demons significantly swapped</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>69</cell>
              <cell>Yamauchi</cell>
              <cell>Tosa Yamauchi Family Treasury and Archives</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>70</cell>
              <cell>Waseda-B</cell>
              <cell>Waseda University</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://archive.wul.waseda.ac.jp/kosho/chi04/chi04_01059/">https://archive.wul.waseda.ac.jp/kosho/chi04/chi04_01059/</ref></cell>
              <cell>✓</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>BC (Nichibuken-A + KCUA + ɑ)</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>71</cell>
              <cell>Tōhaku-B</cell>
              <cell>Tokyo National Museum (Tōhaku)</cell>
              <cell>Hand scroll</cell>
              <cell><ref target="https://webarchives.tnm.jp/imgsearch/show/C0043198">https://webarchives.tnm.jp/imgsearch/show/C0043198</ref></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>Demons significantly omitted and inverted; dated 1617</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
    </div>
</body>
    <back>
      <listBibl>
        <bibl xml:id="baker2022" label="Baker, Salway and Roman 2022">Baker, J., Salway, A. and Roman, C. (2022) 
          <title rend="quotes">Detecting and characterising transmission from legacy collection catalogues</title>, 
          <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 16(2). <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/16/2/000615/000615.html">
          http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/16/2/000615/000615.html</ref>.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="benito-santos2019" label="Benito-Santos, Díaz and Sánchez 2019">Benito-Santos, A., Díaz, A. R. and Sánchez, R. T. (2019)
          <title rend="quotes">Exposing uncertainty on the historical name normalization task</title>,
          <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Seventh International Conference on Technological Ecosystem for Enhancing Multiculturality</title>, 
          pp. 795–803. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1145/3362789.3362920">https://doi.org/10.1145/3362789.3362920</ref>.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="bernholz2011" label="Bernholz and Zillig 2011">Bernholz, C. D. and Zillig, B. L. P. (2011)
          <title rend="quotes">Comparing nearly identical treaty texts: A note on the <title rend="italic">Treaty of Fort Laramie with Sioux, etc., 1851</title> 
          and Levenshtein's edit distance metric</title>, <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 26(1), pp. 5–16.
          <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqq016">https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqq016</ref>.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="cox2007" label="Cox 2007"> Cox, R. (ed.) (2007) <title rend="italic">The culture of copying in Japan: Critical and 
          historical perspectives</title>. London: Routledge.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="flanders2007" label="Flanders, Piez and Terras 2007">Flanders, J., Piez, W. and Terras, M. (2007) 
          <title rend="quotes">Welcome to <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title></title>, 
          <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 1(1). <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/1/1/000007/000007.html">
          http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/1/1/000007/000007.html</ref>.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="flanders2009" label="Flanders 2009">Flanders, J. (2009) <title rend="quotes">The productive unease of 21st-century digital
          scholarship</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 3(2). 
          <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/3/000055/000055.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/3/000055/000055.html</ref>.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="foster2009" label="Foster 2009">Foster, M. D. (2009) <title rend="italic">Pandemonium and parade: Japanese 
          monsters and the culture of yōkai</title>. Oakland: University of California Press.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="foster2015" label="Foster 2015">Foster, M. D. (2015) <title rend="italic">The book of yōkai: Mysterious creatures of
          Japanese folklore</title>. Oakland: University of California Press.
        </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hamalainen2018" label="Hämäläinen, M. et al 2018">Hämääinen, M. et al (2018) <title rend="quotes">Normalizing early English
          letters to present-day English spelling</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Second Joint SIGHUM Workshop on Computational
          Linguistics for Cultural Heritage, Social Sciences, Humanities and Literature</title>, pp. 87–96. 
          Available at: <ref target="https://aclanthology.org/W18-4510">https://aclanthology.org/W18-4510</ref>
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="hyytiainen2022" label="Hyytiäinen 2022">Hyytiäinen, P. (2022) <title rend="quotes">A new method in establishing
          quantitative relationships between manuscripts of the <title rend="italic">New testament</title></title>, 
          <title>Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 38(1), pp. 151–166. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqac030">
          https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqac030</ref>
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="kawaguchi2002" label="Kawaguchi 2002">Kawaguchi, E. (2002) <title rend="quotes">Hyakki yakō emaki o yomu</title>,
          <title>Fuji jyoshi daigaku kokoubungaku zasshi</title>, 67, pp. 77–92.
        </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kobayashi1997" label="Kobayashi 1997">Kobayashi, N. (1997) <title rend="quotes">Morifusa hitsu hyakki yagyō emaki</title>,
          <title rend="italic">Dearute</title>, 13, pp. 18–41.
        </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="koga2006" label="Koga 2006">Koga, H. (2006) <title rend="quotes">Kokuritsu kokkai toshokan zō <title rend="italic">Hyakki 
          yakō emaki</title> (kotobagaki tsuki) ni tsuite</title>, <title rend="italic">Buken tankyū</title>, 44, pp. 1–12.
          <ref target="https://doi.org/10.15017/8950">https://doi.org/10.15017/8950</ref>
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="komatsu1979a" label="Komatsu 1979a">Komatsu, S. (1979) <title rend="quotes">Zuhan hyakki yagyō emaki</title>, in
          Komatsu, S. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Nihon emaki taisei 25: Nōe hōshi ekotoba; Fukutomi zōshi; Hyakki yagyō emaki</title>.
          Tokyo: Chokoronsha, pp. 69–91.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="komatsu1979b" label="Komatsu 1979b">Komatsu, S. (1979) <title rend="quotes"><title rend="quotes">Hyakki yagyō emaki</title> 
          no nazo</title>, in Komatsu, S. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Nihon emaki taisei 25: Nōe hōshi ekotoba; Fukutomi zōshi; Hyakki yagyō emaki</title>.
          Tokyo: Chokoronsha, pp. 126–141.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="komatsu2008" label="Komatsu 2008">Komatsu, K. (2008) <title rend="italic">Hyakki yagyō emaki no nazo</title>. Tokyo: Shuisha Shinsho.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="komatsu2018" label="Komatsu 2018">Komatsu, K. (2018) <title rend="italic">Introduction to yōkai culture: Monsters, ghosts, 
          and outsiders in Japanese history</title>. Tokyo: Shuppan Bunka Shinkō Zaidan.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="komine1997" label="Komine 1997">Komine, K. (1997) <title rend="quotes">Supensā-bon <title rend="quotes">Hyakki yakō emaki</title> 
          ni tsuite: Kotobagaki o Chūshin ni</title>, <title>Chūsei Bugaku Kenkyū</title>, 23, pp. 69–79.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="lang2021" label="Lang and Ommer 2021">Lang, S. and Ommer, B. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Transforming information into
          knowledge: How computational methods reshape art history</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 15(3). 
          <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/3/000560/000560.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/3/000560/000560.html</ref>.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="nagura2020" label="Nagura 2020">Nagura, S. (2020) <title rend="italic">Shinjuan-bon <title rend="italic">Hyakki yagyō 
          emaki</title> kenkyū: Bukkyō o matou yō</title>. PhD thesis. Aichi Prefectural University. Available at:
          <ref target="http://doi.org/10.15088/00004335">http://doi.org/10.15088/00004335</ref>.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="nerbonne2005" label="Nerbonne 2005">Nerbonne, J. (2005) <title rend="quotes">Computing contributions to the humanities</title>,
          <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 20(1), pp. 25–40. 
          <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqh041">https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqh041</ref>.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="nishiyama2016" label="Nishiyama 2016">Nishiyama, M. (2016) <title rend="quotes"><title rend="quotes">Yōbutsue</title> no Tanjyō: 
          <title rend="quotes">Hyakki yagyō emaki</title> towa nanika</title>. <title rend="italic">Kwansei gakuin shigaku</title>, 43, pp. 97–122.
          Available at: <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/10236/00025742">http://hdl.handle.net/10236/00025742</ref>.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="tanaka1999" label="Tanaka 1999">Tanaka, T. (1999) <title rend="italic">Zusetsu hyakki yakō emaki o yomu.</title>
          Tokyo: Kawadeshobō Shinsha.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="tanaka2002" label="Tanaka 2002">Tanaka, T. (2002) <title rend="italic">Hyakki yakō no mieru toshi</title>. Tokyo: Chikuma Gakugei Bunko.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="tokeshi2007" label="Tokeshi 2007">Tokeshi, N. (2007) <title rend="italic"><title rend="quotes">Hyakki yakō emaki</title>
          (Shinjyuan-bon) wa nani o arawashite irunoka</title>, <title rend="italic">Sōsui</title>, 8, pp. 23–43.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="tsuji2012" label="Tsuji 2012">Tsuji, E. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Supensā korekushon shozō <title rend="quotes">Hyakki yakō
          emaki</title> ni tsuite</title>, <title>Nihon bungaku ronkyū</title>, 71, pp. 22–31.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="yanagisawa2020" label="Yanagisawa 2020">Yanagisawa, E. (2020)<title rend="quotes">Hitachi-koku shimodate-han karō maki-ke kyūzō 
          no <title rend="quotes">Hyakki yagyō emaki</title> ni tsuite</title>, <title rend="italic">Gakushuin daigaku shiryōkan kiyō</title>, 26, pp. 1–7.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="yamada2009" label="Yamada 2009">Yamado, S. (2009)<title rend="quotes"><title rend="quotes">Hyakko yagyō emaki</title> henshū 
          no keifu: Jōhōgaku kara no kaimei</title>, <title rend="italic">Nihon Kenkyū</title>, 40, pp. 103–128.
          <ref target="http://doi.org/10.15055/00000512">http://doi.org/10.15055/00000512</ref>
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="yano1999" label="Yano 1999">Yano, T. (1999)<title rend="italic">Kundaikansōchōki no sōgō kenkyū</title>. Tokyo: Bensei Shuppan.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="yano2006" label="Yano 2006">Yano, T. (2006) <title rend="quotes">Buka keitōgaku: Rekishi o fukugensuru</title>, in
          Murakammi, M. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Bunka jōhōgaku nyūmon</title>. Tokyo: Bensei Shuppan, pp. 36-48.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="yano2022" label="Yano 2022">Yano, T. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Rikū hyakkaiki no naiyō to Keitōgakuteki kentō</title>,
          <title rend="italic">Chasho Kenkyū</title>, 11, pp. 88–100.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="yasumura1987" label="Yasumura 1987">Yasumura, T. (1987) <title rend="quotes"> Egakareta yōkai: Hyakki yagyō emaki</title>,
          in Yasumura, T. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Bessatsu taiyō 57: Nihon no yōkai</title>. Tokyo: Heibonsha, pp. 39–49.
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="yumoto2005" label="Yumoto 2005">Yumoto, K. (2005) <title rend="italic">Hyakki yagyō emaki: Yōkaitachi ga sawagidasu</title>.
          Tokyo: Shogakukan.
        </bibl>
      </listBibl>           
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
