<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">The Form of the Content: The Digital Archive
               Nahuatl/Nawat in Central America</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Laura <dhq:family>Matthew</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Marquette University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email/>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Michael <dhq:family>Bannister</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Independent Programmer Analyst</dhq:affiliation>
               <email/>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000491</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date/>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2020-08-27" who="jmurel">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>The digital archive <title rend="quotes">Nahuatl/Nawat in Central America</title>
               (NECA) assembles and makes publicly available a growing corpus of Nahuan-language
               documents produced in Spanish Central America. Many are fragments within larger
               Spanish-language documents and difficult to locate in the archive. NECA has succeeded
               in bringing attention to this understudied corpus but has so far failed to attract
               users to its transcription and translation tool. We consider the reasons for this
               creative failure based on user data, and suggest that the specialized skills and
               distinct academic communities needed to move this project forward require other
               workspaces, including the non-digital, in advance of online collaboration.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>Some thirty years ago, in <title rend="italic">The Content of the Form</title>, Hayden
            White reminded his fellow historians of the extent to which history's content is
            dictated by the form of its presentation. Annals, chronicles, biographies, narrative,
            and discursive analyses all entail "ontological and epistemic choices with distinct
            ideological and even specifically political implications" [White 1987, ix]. Here, we
            adapt White's title to make a similar point about the digital archive <title
               rend="italic">El Náhuatl/Náhuat en Centroamérica</title> or in English, <title
               rend="italic">Nahuatl/Nawat in Central America</title> (NECA; <ref
               target="http://nahuatl-nawat.org/">http://nahuatl-nawat.org</ref>).<note>The terms
                  <q>Náhuatl</q> and <q>Náhuat</q> in Spanish, <q>Nahuatl</q> and <q>Nawat</q> in
               English, are currently the most conventional ways of referencing these related but
               distinct languages. As Hansen 2016 explains, the orthographic conventions of Nahuan
               languages are fluid and we do not intend any definitive statement by selecting these
               particular ones. On the politics of orthography and revitalization see also Olko and
               Sullivan 2013 esp. pp. 201-11, and van Zantwijk 2011.</note> Whereas White focused on
            how content may be influenced by its form independent of the creator's intent, here we
            examine the curatorial decisions we made regarding NECA's form in order to intentionally
            impact the reception, use, and utility of its content.</p>
         <p> NECA assembles a corpus of handwritten, colonial-era texts produced in Central America
            in variations of the related Mesoamerican languages Nahuatl and Nawat, from eight
            repositories in Guatemala, Mexico, Spain, and the United States. It emphasizes the fact
            that these oft-ignored documents exist, and encourages their collaborative study across
            national, scholarly, community, and disciplinary lines. Neither goal is neutral or
            apolitical, although the significance of studying these texts may vary depending on
            whether the user is an indigenous rights activist from Mexico City or Los Angeles, a
            linguist in Mayan languages from Guatemala, a native speaker from Guerrero, a primary
            school teacher from El Salvador, or a doctoral candidate from Europe, etc. In this essay
            we explain our rationale for creating a digital archive of Nahuatl texts from Central
            America in the first place, arguing that NECA's content should be studied not only by
            individuals analyzing particular texts for the purposes of geographically or
            disciplinarily bounded research and revitalization projects, but also collaboratively
            and more experimentally as a standalone corpus. We then review the ontological and
            epistemic as well as technical choices we made in the project's design to encourage this
            outcome. NECA's form attempts to prod users towards a variety of actions both within and
            outside the digital archive. The success or failure of the affordances we created to
            increase the usefulness and usability of the site, and thus to direct the user toward
            specific activities, can be measured in the site's analytics. These indicate not just
            where the digital environment we created is working well or can be improved, but also
            where it may not be the best workspace available — or at least, not yet. The Content:
            Why Nahuatl in Central America?</p>
         <p> Nahuatl, best known as the language of the Aztec empire, was spoken by tens of millions
            of people in the early sixteenth century. It is not a single language but a range of
            mutually intelligible "Nahuan" variants ranging from northern Mexico to Nicaragua since
            at least the second half of the first millennium A.D. &lt;see Figures 1 and 2&gt;. Many
            Nahuan languages have died out, especially in the last 150 years. Others persist but are
            threatened by continued and increasing contact with and preference for European
            languages such as Spanish and English. Today, there are approximately 1.5 million native
            speakers of Nahuatl variants in Mexico and the United States disapora, and around 200
            native speakers of the related language Nawat in the Izalcos and Santo Domingo de Guzmán
            areas of Sonsonate and in Tacuba, Ahuachapán, both in western El Salvador &lt;<ref
               target="http://www.unesco.org/languages-atlas/index.php"
               >http://www.unesco.org/languages-atlas/index.php</ref>&gt;.<note> In the colonial
               period Nawat was called "Pipil" or "mexicana corrupta" by the Spanish. Both "Nawat"
               and "Pipil" are common terms for the same language spoken in El Salvador today. To
               avoid confusion, in this article we refer only to "Nawat."</note> Nahuan languages in
            Guatemala, Belize, Honduras, and Nicaragua have largely ceased to exist.</p>
         <p> &lt;Figure 1 - Classification of Nahuan languages&gt;</p>
         <figure/>
         <p>&lt;Figure 2 - Approximate distribution of major Mesoamerican language families at the
            time of Eurasian contact. Given the extent of migration, trade, and diplomacy as well as
            the reach of the Aztec empire, this map is an oversimplification and leaves out many
            other languages such as Totonacan, Xinka, and non-Nahuan languages of the Uto-Aztecan
            branch.&gt;</p>
         <p> When the Spanish arrived in 1519, central Mexico was the most urbanized, politically
            powerful, and densely populated part of Mesoamerica. The Spanish made the defeated Aztec
            capital of Tenochtitlan the bureaucratic heart of their own nascent empire, and engaged
            Indigenous intellectuals in a remarkable, sometimes violent merging of Mesoamerican and
            European writing systems [McDonough 2014, Townsend 2016]. This produced a significant
            amount and variety of Nahuatl written in Roman script that has been studied extensively,
            for centuries in Mexico and more recently in the United States and Europe.</p>
         <p> This large corpus of Nahuatl documentation from central Mexico has spawned a number of
            digital projects with a variety of aims, such as increasing access to lesser-known texts
            and making databases of glyphic and linguistic information searchable online for
            comparative study. For instance, the <hi rend="italic">Compendio Enciclopédico
               Náhuatl</hi> &lt;<ref target="http://cen.iib.unam.mx/"
            >http://cen.iib.unam.mx/</ref>&gt; links linguistic data from approximately twenty
            historical and modern Nahuatl dictionaries with separate databases of information from
            pictorial and alphabetic texts. The <hi rend="italic">Nahuatl Dictionary </hi>of the
            Wired Humanities Project at the University of Oregon &lt;<ref
               target="https://nahuatl.uoregon.edu/">https://nahuatl.uoregon.edu</ref>/&gt; allows
            users to search for attestations, headwords, and themes associated with any string of
            letters in English, Spanish, or Nahuatl, in order to compare usages in early modern
            Nahuatl from central Mexico as well as contemporary Nahuatl from the Huasteca, Veracruz.
            Also from Oregon, the <hi rend="italic">Early Nahuatl Library</hi> and the <hi
               rend="italic">Mapas Project </hi>&lt;<ref target="https://enl.uoregon.edu/"
               >https://enl.uoregon.edu</ref>/&gt; make available images, transcriptions, and
            English translations of around 100 Nahuatl texts with annotations from a variety of
            archival and published sources. <hi rend="italic">Axolotl</hi> &lt;<ref
               target="https://axolotl-corpus.mx/">https://axolotl-corpus.mx</ref>/&gt; similarly
            depends on the published and unpublished work of established scholars to cross-reference
            approximately 30 colonial-era books in Spanish-Nahuatl translation.</p>
         <p> Significant colonial-era Nahuan language documentation also exists from outlying
            regions of the former Aztec empire. Like the Aztecs, the Spanish used central Mexican
            Nahuatl as an imperial <hi rend="italic">lingua franca</hi> [Dakin and Lutz 1996,
            Herrera 2003, Gasco 2017, Herranz 2001]. <hi rend="italic">Nahuatlatos</hi> — native and
            non-native speakers of Nahuatl who acted as translators and scribes — constituted a
            crucial link in the chain of translation from other Mesoamerican languages to Nahuatl to
            Spanish or Latin and vice versa, making them key actors in diplomacy, Catholic
            evangelization, and the application of Spanish law. Aztec outposts administered by
            central Mexican Nahuatl speakers at the edges of unconquered territory lay the
            groundwork for Nahua-Spanish invasion and colonization of independent regions such as
            Michoacán, Oaxaca, the Yucatán, and Central America [Carrasco 1999, Navarrete 1996,
            Voorhies and Gasco 2004]. In the United States in the 1990s, a historical methodology
            called the New Philology began to analyze records of Spanish bureaucracy written in
            Nahuatl not only in central Mexico, but also in regions where it acted as a second
            language of translation [Restall 1997, 2003, Terraciano 2001, Christensen 2013]. </p>
         <p> In Central America, Nahuatl's usefulness as a tool of empire was augmented by its
            mutual intelligibility with Nawat and other Eastern Peripheral Nahuan languages natively
            spoken in what today is Chiapas (Mexico), southwestern Guatemala, and El Salvador [Aráuz
            1960, Rivas 1969, Campbell 1985, Fowler 1989, Reyes 1961, Navarrete 1975, Knab 1980,
            Gasco 2016]. Comparatively little attention, however, has been paid to Central American
            documents written in colonial-era Nahuan languages. This is partially due to an apparent
            lack of material. Such appearances, however, are deceiving. The largest repositories of
            colonial-era documents from Central America outside of Spain are located in Chiapas and
            Guatemala, both of which have significant Maya populations. Mayan language documents
            from these regions are therefore highly valued, highlighted in archival catalogs, and
            may even be removed from their original context to become standalone documents.<note>
               For instance, documents of only a few pages each in many different indigenous
               languages and genres — cofradía documents, letters, tribute records, etc., — are
               archived together as standalone documents, removed from their original documentary
               context with no paper trail, within the folder A1 legajo 6074 in the Archivo General
               de Centro América in Guatemala City. Similarly, see Quiroa 2017 on the recent
               decision by the Newberry Library in Chicago to physically separate the <hi
                  rend="italic">Popol Wuj</hi> from the rest of the clerical text by Dominican Fr.
               Francisco Ximenez to which it once belonged, while preserving a record of its
               provenance and the state in which it arrived at the Newberry. The removal of texts
               from their place of origin by antiquarian collectors and scholars, with permission or
               not, represents yet another kind of decontextualization.</note> By contrast,
            documents in Nahuan languages are fragmentary, rarely noted as such, and often remain
            hidden inside bundles of Spanish-language legal papers. Historians of Spanish Guatemala
            typically rely on scribal Spanish translations of Nahuan language text, while Maya
            linguists and language revitalization activists tend to view historical writing in
            Nahuan languages as a colonial-era imposition that has little to offer their project of
            fortifying Mayan languages for future generations and recovering Mayan historical and
            sacred texts. </p>
         <p> In neighboring El Salvador, by contrast, Nawat — the only surviving natively-spoken
            Nahuan language in Central America — is simultaneously valorized as part of the national
            patrimony and discriminated against in everyday life. In 1932, Salvadoran state forces
            massacred tens of thousands of peasants, most of them Nawat speakers, in response to an
            uprising against coffee plantations. Fearful of further repression, survivors avoided
            speaking Nawat in public or teaching it to their children [Lindo Fuentes et al, 2007,
            Gould and Lauria Santiago, 2008]. This generational trauma, combined with deep-seated
            social and economic prejudices against indigeneity and a heavy emphasis on Spanish in
            the education system, has brought Nawat in El Salvador to a critical point of
            endangerment in the twenty-first century. Research on historical Nawat has therefore
            taken a back seat to the urgent task of recording and teaching modern Nawat [Lemus 2004,
            2018, Lara Martínez 2015]. In Nicaragua and Honduras, where Nahuan languages are no
            longer spoken, Nahua heritage is also nationalistically valorized but historically
            hazier and thus far, not well documented [Bonta 2009, Lara Martínez and McCallister
            2014, Brinton 1883, McCafferty 2015]. </p>
         <p> For all these diverse and contradictory reasons, few Central Americans have studied
            historical documents in Nahuan languages from their own region (although this is
            beginning to change; see Romero 2017, Cossich 2012). Indeed, it has long been assumed
            that hardly any such documentation existed. The most basic goal of NECA is to correct
            this false impression. Our central claim, however, is not merely that these documents
            exist, but that they are worth studying.</p>
         <p> Linguistically, Central American documents in Nahuan languages bring an entirely new
            data set to debates about the historical evolution of Nahuan languages, especially in
            areas beyond the imperial center. Linguists generally agree on the basic dialectal
            features of two main branches of Nahuatl, Eastern and Western, as well as the urban,
            imperial Nahuatl developed in fifteenth- and sixteenth-century Mexico-Tenochtitlan
            [Dakin and Canger 1985, Canger 1988, Canger 2011, Hansen 2014].<note> But see the
               cautionary example provided by Madajczak and Hansen 2016, who show that even the
               characteristics assigned to these generally accepted linguistic labels may be
               combined or modified and fail to precisely identify the language of any given
               document. </note> How Nahuan languages from Central America fit into these typologies
            is less settled. Lyle Campbell [1985] viewed the central Mexican characteristics of
            Nahuan-language colonial-era documents from Guatemala as the product of contact with the
            central Mexican allies of the Spanish. Karen Dakin's broader analysis of 20 letters in
            Nahuatl from sixteenth-century Santiago de Guatemala [Dakin and Lutz 1996] and 14 other
            documents mostly from Chiapas [Dakin 2009, 2010a] led her to posit an "archaic" Nahuan
            language that predated and continued to be used in Central America alongside the
            Aztec/Spanish <hi rend="italic">koine. </hi>Dakin considers this a unique southern
            Postclassic <hi rend="italic">lingua franca</hi> quite distinct from the Aztec <hi
               rend="italic">koine</hi>, linking it to pan-Mesoamerican Zuyuan ideology [López
            Austin and López Luján 2000] and possibly earlier Nahua-Maya interactions [Dakin 2010b].
            Sergio Romero [2014] sees the same texts as evidence of local, precolumbian Nahuan
            vernaculars. NECA makes possible significant advances in these linguistic debates, by
            more than doubling the number of identified sources and making high quality images of
            them accessible online. NECA is also notable for its range of dates and genres:
            catechisms, wills, letters to Spanish officials, town council memos, bills of sale,
            community annals, tributary rolls, judicial testimony and denunciations, land titles,
            musical manuscripts, and confraternity books from the mid-sixteenth to the early
            eighteenth century. Religious texts in Indigenous languages are a foundational genre in
            Mesoamerican studies, and have been analyzed for the cadences of Mesoamerican ceremonial
            speech as well as the intense and sometimes antagonistic back-and-forth between European
            and Indigenous intellectuals [Burkhart 2011, Sell et al. 2008, Sparks 2017, Doesburg and
            Swanton 2008].<note> The literature on this process is of linguistic, religious, and
               intellectual exchange is vast and varied, resting on the shoulders of scholars such
               as Angel María Garibay, Fernando Horcasitas, and Miguel León-Portilla in Mexico, and
               Dennis Tedlock, James Lockhart, Louise Burkhart, and Judith Maxwell in the United
               States. </note> Grammars, vocabularies, catechisms, and other Mesoamerican language
            texts produced by Catholic friars also provide valuable linguistic information,
            sometimes unwittingly. The clerical author of the late seventeenth-century Guatemalan
            sermon <hi rend="italic">Teotamachilizti in yiuliliz auh in ymiquiliz Tutemaquizticatzim
               Iesu Christo</hi> now held at the John Carter Library at Brown University in the
            United States, for instance, noted the existence of a vehicular or "vulgar" Nahuatl used
            alongside Nawat and the central Mexican <hi rend="italic">koine </hi>in Guatemala. The
            cleric aspired to write his sermon in the "vulgar" dialect but frequently slipped back
            into the central Mexican variety with which he was more familiar [Madajczak and Hansen
            2016, Romero 2014]. Bureaucratic documentation generated mostly by Indigenous <hi
               rend="italic">nahuatlatos</hi>, conversely, tends to imitate the prestigious central
            Mexican <hi rend="italic">koine</hi> and to adopt Spanish legal formulae, but also
            employs less standardized orthography that reflects local speech patterns and the
            decreasing influence over time of the Catholic church on translation norms [von Mentz
            2009, Lockhart 1991, Pizzigoni 2007, Olko and Sullivan 2013]. Historians have used such
            bureaucratic and legal documentation to track political, sociocultural and linguistic
            changes in Mesoamerica as a result of European colonialism, and to uncover regional and
            subregional variations of the language. They have done so by systematically assembling,
            transcribing, translating, cataloguing the characteristics of, and comparatively
            analyzing various corpora of Nahuatl documents. This methodology holds great promise for
            NECA. With transcriptions and translations — to date, an aspirational goal — we would be
            able to create a database of dialectal and other linguistic features, locations, genres,
            scribes' names, year of creation, etc., which would surely yield new insights into the
            history of Nahuatl's diffusion, scribal and ecclesiastical networks, relationship to
            geography, and other avenues of future research. Beyond philology, translations and
            transcriptions of the documents assembled by NECA would enrich the social history of the
            region. The vast majority of lives revealed are of non-native speakers of Nahuan
            languages: African urbanites, Oaxacan plantation workers, Maya choirmasters and cofradía
            officials, French merchants, and innumerous indigenous political leaders: Mam, K'iche',
            Tzeltal, Tojolabal, Jakalteko, Kaqchikel, etc. Contact points between friars, Spanish
            administrators, and local authorities are also plentiful in these documents. Family
            relations simmer underneath accusations of adultery, bigamy, and incest. Inventories and
            wills track the material culture of everyday life and the globalization of Mesoamerican
            commerce. Witchcraft, land and inheritance disputes, and the forced labor of women all
            make an appearance. The input of scholars and community members who may not have Nahuan
            language skills but who bring deep expertise in Mayan and Central American history,
            anthropology, archaeology, geography, and art history is crucial for contextualizing
            such information and incorporating it into larger narratives.<note> A short list might
               include Arroyo 2004 (especially Popenoe de Hatch, Akkeren, and Chinchilla) on
               precolumbian Nahuas on the Guatemalan Pacific coast; Fowler 1989, Escalante Arce
               2001, and Sampeck 2015 on Nahua peoples in 'Pipil' territory; Luján-Muñoz 1988 and
               Herrera 2003 on Spanish Guatemala; Stevenson 1964, Borg 1985, and Morales 2015 on
               musical traditions; Lutz 1994 and Lokken 2000 on Afro-descendents in Guatemala; and
               Viqueira Albán 2002 on Chiapas. </note>
         </p>
         <p> To our assertion of NECA's potential for advancing Nahuan linguistics and Central
            American history, we add the possibility of supporting Nawat revitalization efforts in
            El Salvador. Diverse and overlapping intercultural and intergenerational campaigns have
            been underway in that country since the early 2000s, including a "language nest" primary
            school immersion program [Lemus 2018], university classes in Nawat as a second language
               &lt;<ref target="http://www.uca.edu.sv/escuela-de-idiomas/cursos-nahuat"
               >http://www.uca.edu.sv/escuela-de-idiomas/cursos-nahuat</ref>/&gt;, regional
            initiatives such as <hi rend="italic">Tushik</hi> &lt;http://tushik.org/&gt; and the
            Colectivo Tzunhejekat &lt;<ref target="https://www.facebook.com/Tzunhejekat"
               >https://www.facebook.com/Tzunhejekat</ref>/&gt;, and social media hubs &lt;<ref
               target="https://www.facebook.com/groups/33974937500"
               >https://www.facebook.com/groups/33974937500/&gt;.</ref> Increasing native speakers'
            access to historical documents written in Indigenous languages has proven valuable in
            other revitalization and decolonization efforts, from the workshop-and-publication model
            in the Polish-Mexican project <hi rend="italic">Revitalizing Indigenous Languages
            </hi>[Olko and Sullivan 2014] to the <hi rend="italic">Ticha</hi> digital archive of
            historical Zapotec documents from Oaxaca discussed by Broadwell et al. in this special
            issue &lt;<ref target="https://ticha.haverford.edu/en"
               >https://ticha.haverford.edu/en</ref>/&gt;. Preliminary discussions with Salvadorans
            involved in Nawat revitalization indicate that while there may be a place for NECA in
            the future, for now the urgency of recording and promoting modern Nawat overshadows
            interest in historical documents. How NECA might contribute to Nawat revitalization is
            uncertain, in part, because the linguistic identification of so many of our documents
            remains unclear and the majority are from Guatemala, where Nawat was historically spoken
            but is no longer. Again, further study via transcriptions and translations is needed in
            order to clarify how the NECA corpus may speak to the case of Salvadoran Nawat. In the
            meantime, we hope that NECA's expression of international scholarly interest in Central
            American Nahuan languages, free access to downloadable, high-quality images of
            colonial-era documents for anyone with an internet connection, and public witness to the
            long history of Nawat in El Salvador stands as a one more "symbol of cultural identity
            and pride ... [the] first step in any language revitalization process" [Lemus 2008,
            8].</p>
         <p> The Form: Going Digital</p>
         <p> NECA began with a list of over 40 documents compiled by Sergio Romero (University of
            Texas at Austin) and Laura Matthew (Marquette University), in collaboration with a dozen
            other colleagues, for an encyclopedia project that never materialized. As Romero and
            Matthew sought alternate ways to publish the list, new items continued to surface. It
            became clear that given the number of Nahuan language documents that go unrecorded in
            archive catalogs and the extent to which scholars tend to run across them unexpectedly,
            the list could easily grow longer and a traditional print publication would quickly
            become outdated. Simply posting the list online might stimulate interest, but the need
            to travel to physical archives represented a significant barrier to serious engagement
            since those with the most capacity to read early modern manuscripts in Nahuan languages
            tend not to live or work in Guatemala and Chiapas, where the main repositories of NECA's
            documents are located. Working with programmer Michael Bannister, and with permission
            from the original repositories, Matthew decided in 2015 to create a digital archive of
            high-quality images using Omeka, the popular open-source content management system for
            digital collections from the Roy Rosenzweig Center for History and New Media (CHNM) at
            George Mason University. For the remainder of this essay, "we" refers to Matthew and
            Bannister as the sole creators and curators of NECA. Our first curatorial decision was
            conceptual: to restrict the archive's geographical range to Central America as defined
            by colonial-era administrative boundaries. This meant including documents from Chiapas
            but not from neighboring and similarly multilingual places like Oaxaca, where Nahuatl
            also functioned as a vehicular <hi rend="italic">lingua franca</hi> [Terraciano 2001,
            Swanton 2008]. Segregating Oaxaca from Central America seemed in some ways artificial
            and over-determined by the same national, academic, and disciplinary boundaries NECA
            aspires to overcome. But such boundaries are both real and significant. At a practical
            level, we accumulated items from Chiapas but not Oaxaca by default, because Chiapas’s
            colonial records were sent to the judicial Audiencia of Guatemala while Oaxaca's were
            sent to Mexico. Linguistically speaking, a Central American focus also directed
            attention to the contact points between Mayan and Nahuan languages. We did not want the
            Central American material to be prematurely absorbed into the considerably more
            developed academic literature on Nahuatl in Oaxaca and elsewhere in Mexico, without a
            proper understanding of the local contexts that produced it. We also took seriously
            Justyna Olko's and John Sullivan's assertion that "more research on this topic [of local
            and regional differences and their relation to standardization] is greatly needed;
            especially useful would be a systematic comparison between regions as well as between
            higher and lower-ranking scribes/authors within a given locality" [Olko and Sullivan
            2013, 192]. A distinctly Central American corpus creates the possibility of comparative
            study with data sets from other multilingual, borderland, and outlying regions where
            Nahuatl was and is spoken, such as Oaxaca, Jalisco, Veracruz, and Guerrero [Canger 2017,
            Olko and Sullivan 2014, Guion et al. 2010, Yañez Rosales 2017]. Finally, by drawing a
            line around Central America we hoped to direct attention towards and raise awareness of
            the ongoing, severely underfunded, but multi-pronged efforts to revitalize Nawat in El
            Salvador. As we began to build the site, created and solicited feedback from an advisory
            board, and presented at conferences in the United States, Guatemala, and El Salvador,
            overlapping and mismatched interests in the NECA corpus became increasingly apparent.
            Historians, anthropologists, and archaeologists working in Central America were
            enthusiastic about sharing their archival references and interested in the information
            the documents contained, which they often could not read. Linguists and philologists
            working primarily in Mexico were interested in the dialectal features of the documents
            but were unfamiliar with their Central American context and history. Scholars and
            activists working on Nahuan languages in Central America expressed interest but lacked
            the financial and human resources to engage NECA without diverting valuable attention
            from existing projects, especially those supporting revitalization of Nawat in El
            Salvador. We began to think about how NECA’s structure could more actively facilitate
            communication across these disciplinary, regional, and national borders. Unlocking the
            information inside the documents would be the essential first step for any kind of
            macro-analysis of the entire corpus, computational or otherwise, and for connecting
            scholars with similar interests and complementary skills. Could we help scholars find
            not just the documents, but each other? Could we create an online workspace that
            encouraged scholars to share their expertise and begin to generate data for comparative
            and collaborative analysis? Taking inspiration from crowdsourcing projects such as <hi
               rend="italic">Colored Conventions</hi> (which has since retired this feature)
               &lt;<ref
               target="https://web.archive.org/web/20150322130256/http:/coloredconventions.org"
               >https://web.archive.org/web/20150322130256/http://coloredconventions.org</ref>/&gt;
            and <hi rend="italic">DIY History </hi>&lt;<ref
               target="https://diyhistory.lib.uiowa.edu/"
            >https://diyhistory.lib.uiowa.edu</ref>/&gt;, we added the transcription plugin Scripto,
            and created an "Add a Document" feature using a Simple Contact Form plugin to encourage
            contributions of new documents. A separate, linked Wordpress site &lt;<ref
               target="https://nahuatlnawat.wordpress.com/"
            >https://nahuatlnawat.wordpress.com</ref>/&gt; became the project blog and discussion
            space. The backbone of Omeka is the items list, supported by Dublin Core-based metadata.
            Most metadata elements are obvious: date, title, source, etc. Nevertheless, each element
            reflects a curatorial decision made by us with certain goals in mind. We added new
            metadata elements for the number of "folios" to emphasize the variety and extent of the
            corpus, and for at-a-glance decisions by users about whether or not to transcribe;
            "sample text" to spark the potential transcriber's and/or translator's interest;
            "location" with the modern countries, states, and/or departments in addition to the
            colonial-era information to allow for sub-regional searches and future experiments in
            mapping; "date of creation" of the item itself to keep a record of the corpus's growth;
            and the "contributor" of the document in order to acknowledge her or his research and
            participation. Metadata omissions also reveal the synergy between form, content, and
            curation. A primary goal of NECA is to encourage the linguistic study of a larger corpus
            of Nahuan documents from Central America than usual, and eventually to gather the
            results in a database of linguistic features for comparative analysis. Some of our
            documents conform to a single, clear Nahuan variant. Most, however, present a mix of
            attributes, as one might expect of writing produced by non-native speakers in a context
            of ongoing (or decreasing) standardization, colonial power dynamics, and the adoption by
            indigenous people of foreign writing technologies. This linguistic heterogeneity makes
            the NECA corpus an exceedingly valuable resource for exploring the history of Nahuan
            languages at linguistic borderlands [Madjazeck and Hansen 2016, 239]. We chose not to
            create a metadata element that prematurely assigned the documents a reductive linguistic
            label until we have more data through transcription and analysis. We also wanted to
            avoid a situation in which non-linguists might interpret such labels as more definitive
            than they really are. Decisions about the items themselves predetermine what researchers
            can and cannot do with them. Most of NECA's items are fragments within larger documents
            — sometimes, much larger. On a mostly non-existent budget, we faced issues of server
            space, labor, and funding: photographers require payment, repositories may charge
            publication fees. Additionally, in this first iteration of the project we were focused
            on access and translation. We therefore chose to publish only the Nahuatl portions of
            any given document, for both practical reasons and in order to attract Nahuatl
            translators. This decision has consequences. For better or worse, it denies the user
            access to any Spanish translation that might have appeared in the original document. It
            also separates the fragment from its larger documentary context, digitally replicating
            the same de-contextualization that has been suffered by many Mayan-language documents. A
            fuller understanding of the document's creation and information can only be achieved by
            consulting the original document in relation to its archival context. Data sets of
            people, places, and other kinds of information contained in the digital archive — for
            instance, paying attention to geographical location or scribal networks — will also
            remain incomplete without access to the full original. Researchers will have to return
            to the physical archives in order to get the whole picture, and we run the danger that
            they will not [Putnam 2016]. Finally, anticipating the user experience led to some
            programming alterations. Omeka's automatically generated citations omitted the original
            archive; we changed the code to cite the document's physical repository and archival
            signature first, followed by NECA and the date of access. To guide users towards
            specific activities, we turned Omeka's "featured items" into a "sample transcription"
            and "featured collections" into "document teams." Omeka's built-in internationalization
            combined with the plugin Locale Switcher made the site bilingual, allowing users to
            choose in real time whether to view the site in Spanish or English. Because we had
            significantly altered the standard Omeka framework with new navigation headings,
            metadata categories, etc., Spanish versions had to be added to the internationalization
            code, as did all Spanish translations of all the text within the transcription tool
            Scripto. However, these changes affected only the user interface, not the items'
            metadata. Assuming that most of our users would be competent in Spanish but not
            necessarily in English, we decided to make Spanish the primary language of the site (and
            in doing so, officially baptized it as NECA: in Spanish, <hi rend="italic">El </hi>N<hi
               rend="italic">áhuatl/náhuat</hi> e<hi rend="italic">n</hi> C<hi rend="italic"
               >entro</hi>a<hi rend="italic">mérica</hi>). All metadata is in Spanish regardless of
            the interface language, and simple pages unaffected by the plugin privilege Spanish at
            the top with anchors to an English translation below.<note> CHNS has since released a
               new version Omeka S with a built-in multilingual option, but as of this writing it is
               not compatible with Scripto. Rafael Lara Martínez generously translated all our
               simple pages into Spanish.</note> &lt;see Figure 3&gt;</p>
         <figure/>
         <p>&lt;Figure 3 - Home page of NECA, a simple page with stable Spanish and anchored English
            translation, plus English navigation and sidebar headings that can be changed to Spanish
            with a click of the flag. The metadata of the items, seen here in the right-hand sidebar
            under "Sample Transcription," is always in Spanish. A video on the
            revitalization/language nest program "Cuna Náhuat" from El Salvador is featured at the
            top of the sidebar.&gt; </p>
         <p> At every structural opportunity we emphasized the collaborative, open nature of the
            project and minimized our own gatekeeping. Conversations during beta testing between
            anthropologist Janine Gasco and historians Julia Madajczak and Agnieszka Brylak inspired
            us to create mechanisms for interdisciplinary document teams to work on single items.
            Contributors of new citations are individually added to the "About Us" page as well as
            to their items' metadata. Transcribers and translators are encouraged to register for
            Scripto with their full name so they can be properly identified in the versioning of
            transcriptions and translations and credited in future publications, as we require under
            our Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial 3.0 U.S. license. NECA is not a
            crowdsourcing project, but it does invite researchers to share their documents, modern
               <hi rend="italic">nahuatlatos</hi> to share their translations, and academics and
            community members to share their ideas transnationally and interdisciplinarily. Through
            its design, the website attempts to make the case that this is worth everyone's while.
            The Form of the Content: If We Build It, Will They Come?</p>
         <p> Archival research and the transcription and translation of idiosyncratic documents
            written in difficult handwriting, often in foreign languages, requires patience, time,
            resources, and above all, advanced skills that accrue over the years. Doctoral degrees,
            job offers, tenure, and future funding depend on demonstrating the fruits of this
            individual labor. There is nothing wrong with claiming the privacy to work, and what we
            have labeled "document teams" in NECA can also form via email, conferences, special
            journal issues, and edited volumes. If NECA's first iteration – the digital archive –
            produces a flurry of new publications and dissertations created outside our platform,
            this will be a positive result. NECA nevertheless encourages scholars to go beyond
            individual documents and to work beyond their comfort zones. It identifies common
            research interests across disciplines and national and academic communities, and
            presents the opportunity to share citations, translations, and knowledge in a public
            forum; to compare notes online; and eventually, given transcriptions and translations,
            to create databases, analyze the corpus as a whole, and experiment with different
            digital and computational tools. The NECA corpus is large and geographically varied
            enough to reveal not only the dialectal features of Nahuan languages in Central America,
            but also the documents’ production related to colonial settlement, ecclesiastical
            influence, social and political networks, the economy, and geography. We see great
            future value, especially, in thinking through NECA’s data using spatial analysis and
            mapping tools. Bringing linguists and translators of Nahuatl together with non-<hi
               rend="italic">nahuatlato</hi> scholars of Central America has the potential to
            advance all this research further, faster. We built NECA to nudge people in this
            collaborative direction. The question is, will they come? So far, the answer is yes and
            no. NECA's analytics from Reclaim Hosting show that since the digital archive went
            online in July 2016, it has received the most intensive and consistent use (measured by
            bandwidth used, the ratio of pages to hits, and annual location data) from Mexico, El
            Salvador, and Guatemala, as well as Spain, Germany, Poland, and France in Europe — the
            last three being major centers of Mesoamerican and Nahuatl studies — and the United
            States, Brazil, and Canada in the Americas. Presentations at the University of Texas at
            Austin in March 2017, the Congreso de Estudios Mayas in Guatemala City in July 2017, the
            Asociación Centroamericana de Lingüística annual meeting in San Salvador in August 2017,
            the American Historical Association annual meeting in January 2018, and the Sociedad
            Mexicana de Historiografía Lingüística in Mexico City in October 2018, each produced
            temporary bumps in the number of unique visitors and/or intensity of use, which then
            tapered off. The Austin presentation acted as an official launch of the project with the
            power of social media behind it, resulting in an eighteen-fold increase in unique
            visitors immediately afterwards (March-April 2017). Subsequent presentations in
            Guatemala and El Salvador produced the most remarkable user data in the site's history
            thus far. In the two months following (July-August 2017) — and with no official social
            media push — the number of unique visitors to the site quadrupled. More importantly, the
            bandwidth and pages-to-hits ratio indicated significantly more searching through the
            site's most complex pages, such as those containing document images, than after the
            Austin presentation. The Central Americans' more intensive use is visible in the
            contrast between their relatively low number of unique visitors (yellow) relative to
            pages, hits, and bandwidth (blue and green) &lt;see Figures 4 and 5&gt;:</p>
         <figure/>
         <p>&lt;Figure 4 - Usage data for NECA, 2017. &gt;</p>
         <figure/>
         <p>&lt;Figure 5 - Top user locales for NECA, 2017. &gt;</p>
         <p> From 2016 through 2018, the United States and Ukraine generated most of the site’s
            hundreds of thousands of page views, 75% of which lasted thirty seconds or less.
            Presumably, a large portion of these were bots. The next largest proportions of visits,
            however, lasted for over one hour (around 8%), thirty minutes to an hour (around 6%),
            and fifteen to thirty minutes (around 4%), suggesting that a significant minority of
            users were seriously engaging the site. Notably, when we ceased to actively promote the
            site in 2019 we saw a drop in unique visitors, a consistent narrowing of the
            pages-to-hits ratio indicating shallower exploration of the site, and 88% of visits
            lasting less than thirty seconds. (For the first time, a large number of such visits in
            2019 came from the Netherlands, bumping Ukraine to third place in the "probably a bot"
            category). Nevertheless, in 2019 the most intensive users — those spending thirty
            minutes to over an hour on the site at a time — still constituted our next largest user
            group, or 7% of the total number of visits. As a digital archive, therefore, NECA is
            doing reasonably well even when we do not take advantage of conferences, social media,
            and other means to publicize and promote it. As an online platform for collaborative
            transcription, it has been less successful. A few people have used the "Add a Document"
            feature to provide new citations and high-quality images, but most of the 19 new
            documents added since the site’s inception have come from our own research or direct
            outreach. The same is true of the Discussion area, where invited essays by Janine Gasco
            on Nahuan agricultural terms in the Soconusco and by Adriana Álvarez on Nahuatl
            instruction at the Universidad de San Carlos in Guatemala have generated a handful of
            comments from community members mostly from El Salvador or of Salvadoran descent in the
            United States, but no serious scholarly engagement, without which we cannot move forward
            to better understand why, how, or to whom these documents might be important. The
            document teams and Scripto's transcription tool have attracted no users at all since
            beta testing in March 2017. This may be a design issue. This first iteration of NECA is
            based on a pre-designed Omeka platform and utilizes only the Scripto features made
            available through the plug-in. Certainly we could improve the transcription and
            translation tool to be more appealing and effective, including a simpler user interface,
            better versioning, an improved commenting feature that identifies the user and is always
            visible, side-by-side images and workspace, progress bars, and the ability to toggle
            between transcriptions, translations, and versioning on a single page. The features and
            functionality of the transcription tool at the <hi rend="italic">Codex Aubin</hi>
               project<hi rend="italic">,</hi> hosted on software developer Ben Brumfield's
            transcription platform FromThePage based on Ruby on Rails &lt;<ref
               target="https://fromthepage.com/">https://fromthepage.com</ref>&gt;, are exemplary
               &lt;<ref target="https://fromthepage.ace.fordham.edu/benwbrum/codex-aubin"
               >https://fromthepage.ace.fordham.edu/benwbrum/codex-aubin</ref>&gt;, as is the
            transcription and search tool created for the <hi rend="italic">Freedom on the Move
            </hi>project &lt;<ref target="https://freedomonthemove.org/index.html"
               >https://freedomonthemove.org/index.html</ref>&gt;. Other projects with more
            user-friendly transcription workspaces than NECA include the Newberry Library's <hi
               rend="italic">Newberry Transcribes </hi>&lt;<ref
               target="https://publications.newberry.org/digital/mms-transcribe/index"
               >https://publications.newberry.org/digital/mms-transcribe/index</ref>&gt; and
            Maynooth University's <hi rend="italic">Letters 1916-1923 </hi>&lt;<ref
               target="http://letters1916.maynoothuniversity.ie/learn"
               >http://letters1916.maynoothuniversity.ie/learn</ref>/&gt;, both of which are based
            on Omeka and Scripto. How the digital archive's form can encourage engagement with its
            content is not, however, only a design issue. The most successful transcription projects
            come from outward-facing institutions digitizing items from their physical archives and
            making them available to "citizen humanists" with the clear goal of public engagement —
            for instance (among many other examples), the Smithsonian Institution's <hi
               rend="italic">Digital Volunteers </hi>initiative &lt;<ref
               target="https://transcription.si.edu/">https://transcription.si.edu</ref>/&gt; and
            the Library of Virginia's <hi rend="italic">Making History </hi>project &lt;<ref
               target="http://www.virginiamemory.com/transcribe"
               >http://www.virginiamemory.com/transcribe</ref>/&gt;. Often, featured collections are
            chosen with audience interest and capabilities in mind. The Stanford University Archives
               &lt;<ref target="https://library.stanford.edu/spc/university-archives"
               >https://library.stanford.edu/spc/university-archives</ref>&gt;, for example, invites
            online transcription of manuscripts related to the university's history, in English.
            Broad or targeted appeal of the subject matter, readability of the documents, and
            language accessibility seem equally relevant to the success of the aforementioned <hi
               rend="italic">Freedom on the Move Project, </hi>which crowdsources transcriptions of
            mostly English, printed newspaper announcements of rewards for runaway African-American
            slaves; <hi rend="italic">Newberry Transcribes</hi>, which presents mostly
            English-language diaries and letters about family life in the Midwest; and the narrower
            but commemorative <hi rend="italic">Letters 1916-1923, </hi>which invites visitors to
            submit and transcribe their own family's documents for upcoming anniversaries of the
            Easter Rising, World War I, and the Irish War of Independence and Civil War. A search
            through the transcription platform FromThePage's various collections suggests that more
            academic projects often involve fewer participants, especially where handwritten
            manuscripts from earlier time periods with idiosyncratic paleography in languages other
            than English are concerned. Online transcription in these circumstances seems to work
            best as a collaboration tool between professors and students, or between small groups of
            colleagues with similar skills. This is the case of the <hi rend="italic">Codex
               Aubin</hi> and <hi rend="italic">French from Outremer </hi>&lt;<ref
               target="https://fromthepage.ace.fordham.edu/collection/show?collection_id=1"
               >https://fromthepage.ace.fordham.edu/collection/show?collection_id=1</ref>&gt;
            projects from Fordham University, which deal with medieval and early modern manscripts
            in Nahuatl and French requiring highly specialized transcribers. Many digital archives
            of similarly challenging material rely entirely on professional teams and do not make
            collaborative online transcription tools available, for instance the <hi rend="italic"
               >BFM - Base de Français Médiéval</hi> &lt;<ref target="http://txm.bfm-corpus.org/"
               >txm.bfm-corpus.org</ref>&gt;, the <hi rend="italic">1641 Depositions Project
            </hi>from Trinity College, Ireland &lt;<ref target="http://1641.tcd.ie/project.php"
               >http://1641.tcd.ie/project.php</ref>&gt;, and the <hi rend="italic">Native Northeast
               Research Collaborative </hi>&lt;<ref target="https://www.thenativenortheast.org/"
               >https://www.thenativenortheast.org</ref>/&gt;. Comparing these projects, and NECA,
            to the <hi rend="italic">Ticha</hi> project described in this issue by Broadwell et al.
            makes clear that the challenges faced by creators of digital archives are highly
            contingent. As a digital archive and online transcription platform for colonial-era
            texts in Zapotec languages from Oaxaca, <hi rend="italic">Ticha</hi> encountered some of
            the same design limitations as NECA when using software such as Scripto and the
            Fieldworks Language Explorer (FLEx) [Broadwell et al. this issue, Broadwell and
            Lillehaugen 2013]. <hi rend="italic">Ticha</hi> was aided by the fact that the interests
            of Zapotec speakers and scholars, ethnohistorians, and linguists converged on the same
            region and language, as opposed to the criss-crossing and sometimes conflicting
            interests faced by NECA. However, <hi rend="italic">Ticha</hi> is also a powerful
            example of what sustained attention to the human side of digital projects — conferences
            and workshops, acceptance and accommodation of a wide range of user communities, and
            outreach especially to non-academic stakeholders, in this case native speakers of
            Indigenous and minority languages — can achieve. To re-design the weakest link of NECA,
            its transcription tool, would require at minimum a switch from the current pre-designed
            website and/or outsourcing of the tool, and possibly changing from WikiMedia to a
            standalone database. It is not clear that, at this stage of the project, the effort
            would be worth it. While some have expressed interest in using the site as a teaching
            tool for advanced students who are simultaneously learning Nahuatl and paleography,
            there is no way to know whether this is happening. Likewise, if more established
            scholars are working with documents from NECA, they are doing outside the context of the
            site. At a practical level, scholars may find online transcription and translation,
            which requires working within the confines of the program and/or between multiple
            formats, less efficient than traditional methods. They may also appreciate opportunities
            for face-to-face discussion prior to performing their work online. Scholarship is risky
            and takes time. Sturdy, creative collaborations between people who have not
            traditionally worked together — such as the local, national, disciplinary, and academic
            networks that have expressed interest in NECA yet remain siloed from each other — may
            initially develop better in person. Rather than immediately overhauling the site or the
            transcription tool, a better next step for NECA may be more old-fashioned: to convene
            scholars and community members in different combinations and venues, with the goal of
            creating collaborative teams and identifying viable research questions and interests in
            common. Digital humanities promises more than a new marriage between mathematical,
            qualitative, and design methodologies and tools. It also proposes a paradigmatic change
            in how scholars collaborate, flattening research and/or learning communities and
            vaunting an idealized, non-hierarchical community where people willingly share their
            research, promote interdisciplinarity, and work in teams of members with complementary
            skills sets, none of which is seen as more important than another. Despite the ways in
            which this mimics Silicon Valley-ese (rightly criticized for its hypocrisy), there is
            much to hold onto here: the potential of digital humanities to communicate with broader
            publics, to democratize the production of knowledge, to make the fruits of scholarship
            more accessible, and to make us all more flexible thinkers. As NECA argues, digital
            archives also have the potential to push scholarship in certain directions by calling
            attention to understudied texts or problematics and by making the materials for studying
            them available. But the digital humanities’ optimistic, even utopian view of the
            scholarly workplace is tinged with disciplinary, financial, and intergenerational
            anxieties. In the United States, humanities scholars of all stripes fear the devaluation
            of their work in the information age. The younger generation faces an increasingly
            freelance economy and shrinking humanities job market from the peculiar position of
            being simultaneously valued for their digital savvy (writing code, understanding
            algorithms, managing project teams, marketing their work), expected to be innovators and
            jacks-of-all-trades, and suspected of not doing the kinds of specialized research that
            got their professorly elders tenure. Established scholars are suspected of lagging
            behind the digital turn, but have more freedom to experiment with digital tools — or not
            — with far less risk to their future careers. They are also the gatekeepers of the
            academy. It is therefore incumbent upon senior scholars, especially, to ponder the
            lessons of creative failure in digital humanities projects. NECA shows the potential for
            digital archiving to turn a wide range of people's attention towards a particular corpus
            of historical documentation and set of questions. NECA also highlights the difficulty of
            attracting scholars to skills-intensive transcription and translation online in
            collaborative projects without prior commitments, goals, and relationships in common.
            While we maintain the first iteration of the NECA digital archive, our next best step
            for transcription and translation — the necessary building blocks of any future database
            — will involve human, not digital, development: recruiting and funding new team members,
            acquiring grant money to pay for skilled transcriptions and translations, and organizing
            conferences. With data in hand and new ideas on the table, we can start to contemplate
            smaller, more limited digital tools — what Rockwell and Sinclair [2016] call "embeddable
            toys" – for scholars to play with, exploring what value computation might bring to the
            analysis of the entire NECA corpus. To move forward we must forcefully argue for the
            funding of <emph>both</emph> methods of scholarship, digital and traditional, most
            especially for those who will be the generators, guardians, and teachers of Nahuatl and
            Nawat in the future.</p>
         <div type="acknowledgements">
            <p>NECA is a joint effort between the authors that has also depended on the generous
               support of others. We thank Marquette University's College of Arts and Sciences for
               start-up funding, Sergio Romero for helping assemble the core document list and
               translations of sample text, Héctor Concohá Chet for photographing documents in the
               Archivo General de Centroamérica in Guatemala City, Rafael Lara Martínez for Spanish
               translations of the primary pages, and Jorge Lemus for his collaboration in El
               Salvador. Ann Hanlon at the Digital Humanities Lab, University of
               Wisconsin-Milwaukee, Adriana Álvarez, Davíd Dominguez Herbón, and Miriam Peña
               Pimentel of the Red de Humanidades Digitales, Universidad Autónoma de México, Sharon
               Leon at the Roy Rosenzweig Center for History and New Media, George Mason University,
               and David Bodenhamer of the Polis Center, Indiana University-Purdue University were
               invaluable sounding boards, as were advisory board members Michael Swanton, Janine
               Gasco, Matilde Ivic de Monterroso, and Karl Offen. Julia Madajczak and Agnieszka
               Brylak tested the transcription tool, and graduate assistants Ben Nestor and Cory
               Haala explored mapping applications. We especially thank the many contributors of
               documents to the site, listed at <ref target="http://nahuatl-nawat.org/aboutus"
                  >http://nahuatl-nawat.org/aboutus</ref>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="alvarezsanchez2014" label="Álvarez Sánchez 2014">Álvarez Sánchez, A.
                  <title rend="italic">Patronazgo y educación. Los proyectos y la fundación de la
                  Real Universidad de San Carlos de Guatemala. (1619-1687)</title>. FFyL-UNAM,
               Mexico (2014).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="arroyo2014" label="Arroyo 2014">Arroyo, B. <title rend="quotes">Mesa
                  redonda sobre arqueología tardía de la Costa Sur: Discusión</title>. In <title
                  rend="italic">XVIII Simposio de Investigaciones Arqueológicas en
               Guatemala</title>, eds. J. P. LaPorte, B. Arroyo, and H. E. Mejía, No. 99. Museo
               Nacional de Arqueología y Etnología, Guatemala (2014).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="arauz1960" label="Aráuz 1960">Aráuz, P. <title rend="italic">El Pipil de
                  la Región de los Itzalcos</title>. Ministerio de Cultura, San Salvador
               (1960).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bonta2009" label="Bonta 2009">Bonta, M. <title rend="quotes">The dilemma
                  of indigenous identity construction: the case of the newly recognized Nahoa of
                  Olancho, Honduras</title>. In <title rend="italic">Temas de Geografía
                  Latinoamericana: Reunión CLAG-Morelia</title>, eds. P. S. Urquijo Torres and N.
               Barrera-Bassols. Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México-Centro de Investigaciones en
               Geografía Ambiental, Morelia (2009), pp. 49-86.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="borg1985" label="Borg 1985">Borg, P. <title rend="quotes">The polyphonic
                  music in the Guatemalan music manuscripts of the Lilly Library</title>. Ph.D.
               dissertation, Indiana University (1985).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brinton1883" label="Brinton 1883">Brinton, D. G. <title rend="italic">The
                  Güegüence: A comedy ballet in the Nahuatl-Spanish dialect of Nicaragua</title>. D.
               G. Brinton, Philadelphia (1883)</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="broadwell2013" label="Broadwell and Lillehaugen 2013">Broadwell, G. and B.
               D. Lillehaugen. <title rend="quotes">Considerations in the Creation of an Electronic
                  Database for Colonial Valley Zapotec</title>. <title rend="italic">International
                  Journal of LASSO</title> 12, 2 (2013): 77-110</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="campbell1985" label="Campbell 1985">Campbell, L. <title rend="italic">The
                  Pipil Language of El Salvador</title>. De Gruyter, Berlin (1985).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="canger2017" label="Canger 2017">Canger, U. <title rend="quotes">A Nawatl
                  Dialect with a Shallow History</title>. Unpublished paper, <ref
                  target="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/317887931_A_Nawatl_Dialect_with_a_Shallow_History_or_Is_the_Nawatl_dialect_area_known_as_the_Western_Periphery_a_True_Dialect_area_2017"
                  >https://www.researchgate.net/publication/317887931_A_Nawatl_Dialect_with_a_Shallow_History_or_Is_the_Nawatl_dialect_area_known_as_the_Western_Periphery_a_True_Dialect_area_2017</ref>,
               accessed June 15, 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="canger2011" label="Canger 2011">Canger, U. <title rend="quotes">El nauatl
                  urbano de Tlatelolco/Tenochtitlan, resultado de convergencia entre dialectos. Con
                  un esbozo brevísimo de la historia de los dialectos</title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >Estudios de cultura náhuatl</title> 42 (2011): 243-258.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="canger1988" label="Canger 1988">Canger, U. <title rend="quotes">Nahuatl
                  Dialectology: A Survey and Some Suggestions</title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >International Journal of American Linguistics</title> 54 (1988): 28-73.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="carrasco1999" label="Carrasco 1999">Carrasco, P. <title rend="italic">The
                  Tenochca Empire of Ancient Mexico: The Triple Alliance of Tenochtitlan, Tetzcoco,
                  and Tlacopan</title>. University of Oklahoma Press, Norman (1999).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cossich2012" label="Cossich Vielman 2012">Cossich Vielman, M. <title
                  rend="quotes">Escritura logo-silábica en los códices del Centro de México del
                  siglo xvi y su importancia para el desciframiento de la escritura nahua no azteca
                  de Centroamérica</title>. In <title rend="italic">Las edades del libro</title>,
               Gravier, M. G., Russell, I. G., and Godinas, L. eds. UNAM, Mexico (2012).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dakin2009" label="Dakin 2009">Dakin, K. <title rend="quotes">Algunos
                  documentos nahuas del sur de Mesoamérica</title>. In <title rend="italic">Visiones
                  del Encuentro de Dos Mundos en América: Lengua, Cultura, Traducción y
                  Transculturación</title>, Dakin, D., Montes de Oca, M., and Parodi, C., eds.
               Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México-Insituto de Investigaciones
               Filológicas/Universidad de California-Centro de Estudios Coloniales Iberoamericanos,
               México/Los Angeles (2009), pp. 247-270.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dakin2010a" label="Dakin 2010a">Dakin, K. <title rend="quotes">Lenguas
                  francas y lenguas locales en la epoca prehispánica</title>. In <title
                  rend="italic">Historia sociolingüística de México</title>, Barriga Villanueva, R.
               and Butragueño, P. M., eds. El Colegio de México, Mexico (2010), pp. 161-183.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dakin2010b" label="Dakin 2010b">Dakin, K. <title rend="quotes">Linguistic
                  Evidence for Historical Contacts between Nahuas and Northern Lowland Mayan
                  Speakers</title>. In <title rend="italic">Astronomers, Scribes, and Priests:
                  Cultural Interchange between the Northern Maya Lowlands and Highland Mexico in the
                  Late Postclassic Period</title>, Vail, G. and Hernández, C., eds. Dumbarton Oaks,
               Washington DC, pp. 217-40.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dakin1996" label="Dakin and Lutz 1996">Dakin, K. and Lutz, C. <title
                  rend="italic">Nuestro pesar, nuestra aflicción tunetuliniliz, tucucuca: Memorias
                  en lengua Nahuatl enviadas a Felipe II por indígenas del Valle de Guatemala hacia
                  1572</title>. UNAM/Centro de Investigaciones Regionales de Mesoamérica,
               México/Guatemala (1996).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dakin1985" label="Dakin and Canger 1985">Dakin, K. and Canger, U. <title
                  rend="quotes">An Inconspicuous Basic Split in Nahuatl</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">International Journal of American Linguistics</title> 51,4 (Oct
               1985): 358-361.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Doesburg and Swanton 2008] Doesburg, S van. and Swanton, M. W. "La traducción de
               la 'Doctrina Cristiana en Lengua Mixteca de Fray Benito Hernández al chocholteco
               (ngiwa)." In Conferencias sobre lenguas otomanges y oaxaqueños, Vol. 2, López Cruz,
               A. and Swanton, M., eds. Colegio Superior para la Educación Integral Intercultural de
               Oaxaca/Instituto Nacional de Lenguas Indígenas/Universidad Autónoma "Benito Juárez"
               de Oaxaca/Fundación Alfredo Harp Helú Oaxaca, Oaxaca (2008), pp. 81-117.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Escalante Arce 2001] Escalante Arce, P. Los Tlaxcaltecas en Centro América.
               Dirección de Publicaciones e Impresos, San Salvador (2001).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Fowler 1989] Fowler, W. The Cultural Evolution of Ancient Nahua Civilizations.
               University of Oklahoma Press, Norman (1989).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Gasco 2017] Gasco, J. "Cacao and Commerce in Late Postclassic Xoconochco." In
               Rethinking the Aztec Economy<hi rend="italic">,</hi> Nichols, D. and Berdan, F. F.,
               eds. University of Arizona Press, Tucson (2017), pp. 221-247. </bibl>
            <bibl>[Gasco 2016] Gasco, J. "Linguistic Patterns, Material Culture, and Identity in
               Late Postclassic to Postcolonial Soconusco." In Archaeology and Identity on the
               Pacific Coast and Southern Highlands of Mesoamerica, García-DesLauriers, C. and Love,
               M., eds. University of Utah Press, Salt Lake City (2016), pp. 126-141.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Gould and Lauria-Santiago 2008] Gould, J. and Lauria-Santiago, A. To Rise in
               Darkness: Revolution, Repression, and Memory in El Salvador, 1920-1932. Duke
               University Press, Durham (2008).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Guion et al. 2010] Guion, S, Amith, J., Doty, C. and and Shport, I. "Word-level
               prosody in Balsas Nahuatl: The origin, development, and acoustiv correlates of tone
               in a stress accent language." Journal of Phonetics 38 (2010): 137-166.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Hansen 2016] Hansen, M. P. "How to spell Nahuatl? Nawatl? Nauatl?" Nahuatl
               Studies (blog), July 26, 2016
               &lt;http://nahuatlstudies.blogspot.com/2016/07/how-to-spell-nahuatl-nawatl-nauatl.html&gt;,
               accessed June 15, 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Hansen 2014] "The East-West split in Nahuan Dialectology: Reviewing the Evidence
               and Consolidating the Grouping." Friends of Uto-Aztecan Workshop, Universidad
               Autónoma de Nayarit. 20 June 2014.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Herranz 2001] Herranz, A. Estado, sociedad, y lenguaje: La política lingüística
               en Honduras. Editorial Guaymuras, Tegucigalpa (2001).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Herrera 2003] Herrera, R. Natives, Europeans, and Africans in Sixteenth-Century
               Santiago de Guatemala. University of Texas Press, Austin (2003).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Knab 1980] Knab, T. "Lenguas del Soconusco, pipil y náhuatl de Huehuetán."
               Estudios de cultura náhuatl 14 (1980): 375-378.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Lara Martínez 2015] Lara Martínez, R. Artes de la lengua náhuat-pipil (Estudios
               lingüísticos). Universidad Don Bosco, San Salvador (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Lara Martínez and Maccallister 2014] Lara Martínez, R.l and Maccallister, R.
               Glosario cultural Pipil-Nicarao, El Güegüense y Mitos en la lengua materna. Editorial
               Universidad Don Bosco, San Salvador (2014). [Lemus 2004] Lemus, J. "El pueblo pipil y
               su lengua." <hi rend="italic">Científica</hi> 4,5 (Junio 2004): 7-28.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Lemus 2008] Lemus, J. "Un modelo de revitalización lingüística: el caso de
               náhuat/pipil de El Salvador." In Identità delle Comunità Indigene del Centro America,
               Messico e Caraibi, Palmisano, A. L., ed. Istituto Italo-Americano, Trieste (2008),
               pp. 127-149.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Lindo-Fuentes et al. 2007] Lindo-Fuentes, H., Ching, E., and Lara Martínez, R.
               Remembering a Massacre in El Salvador: The Insurrection of 1932, Roque Dalton, and
               the Politics of Historical Memory. University of New Mexico Press, Albuquerque
               (2007).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Lockhart 1991] Lockhart, J. The Nahuas After the Conquest: A Social and Cultural
               History of the Indians of Central Mexico<hi rend="italic">, </hi>Sixteenth Through
               Eighteenth Centuries. Stanford University Press, Stanford (1991).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Lokken 2000] Lokken, P. “From Black to Ladino: People of African Descent,
               Mestizaje, and Racial Hierarchy in Rural Colonial Guatemala, 1600–1730.” Ph.D.
               thesis., University of Florida (2000). </bibl>
            <bibl>[López Austin and López Luján 2000] López Austin, A. and López Luján, L. “The
               Myth and Reality of Zuyuá: The Feathered Serpent and Mesoamerican Transformations
               from the Classic to the Postclassic.” In Carrasco, D., Jones, L. and Sessions, S.,
               eds., Mesoamerica’s Classic Heritage: From Teotihuacan to the Aztecs. University
               Press of Colorado, Boulder (2000), pp. 21-84.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Lújan Muñoz 1988] Luján Muñoz, J. Agricultura, mercado, y sociedad en el
               corregimiento del Valle de Guatemala, 1670–80. Universidad de San Carlos Cuadernos de
               Investigación, Guatemala (1988).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Lutz 1994] Lutz, C. Santiago de Guatemala, 1541–1773: City, Caste, and the
               Colonial Experience. University of Oklahoma Press, Norman (1994).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Madajczak and Hansen 2016] Madajczak, J. and Hansen, M. P. "Teotamachilizti: An
               analysis of the language in a Nahua sermon from colonial Guatemala." Colonial Latin
               American Review 25, 22 (2016): 220-244.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Matthew 2012] Matthew, L. Memories of Conquest: Becoming Mexicano in Colonial
                  Guatemala<hi rend="italic">.</hi> University of North Carolina Press, Chapel Hill
               (2012).</bibl>
            <bibl> [Matthew and Romero 2012] Matthew, L. and Romero, S. "Nahuatl and Pipil in
               Colonial Guatemala: A Central American Counterpoint." Ethnohistory 59,4 (2012):
               765-783.</bibl>
            <bibl>[McCafferty 2015] McCafferty, G. "The Mexican Legacy in Nicaragua, or Problems
               when Data Behave Badly." Archaeological Papers of the American Anthropological
               Association, 25 (2015): 110-118.</bibl>
            <bibl>[McDonough 2014] McDonough, K. S. The Learned Ones: Nahua Intellectuals in
               Postconquest Mexico. University of Arizona Press, Tucson (2014).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Mentz 2009] Mentz, B. von. "Cambio social y cambio lingüísitico: El "náhuatl
               cotidiano", el de "doctrina", y el de "escribanía" en Cuauhnáhuac entre 1540 y 1671."
               In Visiones del Encuentro de Dos Mundos en América: Lengua, Cultura, Traducción y
               Transculturación, Dakin, K., Montes de Oca, M., and Parodi, C., eds.. Universidad
               Nacional Autónoma de México-Insituto de Investigaciones Filológicas/Universidad de
               California-Centro de Estudios Coloniales Iberoamericanos, México/Los Angeles (2009),
               pp. 111-146.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Morales 2015] Morales Abril, O. “A presença de música e músicos portugueses no
               vice-reinado da Nova Espanha e na província de Guatemala, nos séculos XVI-XVII.”
               Revista Portuguesa de Musicologia, 2,1 (2015): 149-72.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Navarrete 1996] Navarrete, C. "Elementos arqueológicos de mexicanización en las
               tierras altas mayas.” In <hi rend="italic">Temas mesoamericanos</hi>, Lombardo, S.
               and Nalda, E., eds.. Instituto Nacional de Antropología e Historia, Mexico (1996),
               pp. 309-356.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Navarrete 1975] Navarrete, C. "Nueva información sobre la lengua náhuatl en
               Chiapas." <hi rend="italic">Anales de Antropología</hi> 12,1 (1975): 273-283.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Olko and Sullivan 2013] Olko, J. and Sullivan, S. "Empire, Colony, and
               Globalization: A Brief History of the Nahuatl Language." In Colloquia humanistica:
               Minor Languages, Minor Literatures, Minor Cultures, Lukaszyk, E. and Chuszczewska,
               K., eds. Institute of Slavic Studies Polish Academy of Sciences, Warsaw (2013), pp.
               181-216.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Olko and Sullivan 2014] Olko, J. and Sullivan, J. "Toward a Comprehensive Model
               for Nahuatl Language Research and Revitalization." In Proceedings of the Fortieth
               Annual Meeting of the Berkeley Linguistic Society, Leung, H. et al., eds. Berkeley
               Linguistic Society, Berkeley (2014), pp. 369-397.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Pizzigoni 2007] Pizzigoni, C. "Region and Subregion in Central Mexican
               Ethnohistory: The Toluca Valley, 1650–1760." Colonial Latin American Review 16,1
               (2007): 71–92.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Putnam 2016] Putnam, L. "The Transnational and the Text-Searchable: Digitized
               Sources and the Shadows They Cast." American Historical Review 121, 2 (2016):
               377-402.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Restall 2003] Restall, M. "A History of the New Philology and the New Philology
               in History." Latin American Research Review 38, 1 (2003): 113-134.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Restall 1997] Restall, M. The Maya World: Yucatec Culture and Society, 1550-1850.
               Stanford University Press, Stanford (1997).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Reyes García 1961] Reyes García, L. “Documentos nahoas sobre el Estado de
               Chiapas,” in Los mayas del sur y sus relaciones con los nahuas meridionales, VIII
               Mesa Redonda de la Sociedad Mexicana de Antropología. Sociedad Mexicana de
               Antropología, Mexico (1961), pp. 67-93.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Rivas 1969] Rivas, P. El Nawat de Cuscatlán: Apuntes para un gramática tentativa.
               Ministero de Educación, San Salvador (1969).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Rockwell 2016] Rockwell, G. and Sinclair, S. Hermeneutica: Computer Assisted
               Interpretation in the Humanities. The MIT Press, Cambridge (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Romero 2017] Romero, S. "Los manuscritos en náhuatl centroamericano y la historia
               cultural de Guatemala." Anales de la Academia de Geografía e Historia de Guatemala
               XCII (2017): 75-104.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Romero 2015] Romero, S. "Language, catechisms and Mesoamerican lords in Highland
               Guatemala: Addressing ‘God’ after the Spanish conquest." Ethnohistory 62, 3 (2015):
               623-650.</bibl>
            <bibl> [Romero 2014] Romero, S. "Grammar, dialectal variation and honorific registers in
               Nahuatl in 17th century Guatemala." Anthropological Linguistics 56, 1 (2014):
               1-24.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Romero and Cossich 2014] Romero, S. and Cossich Vielman, M. "El Título de Santa
               María Ixhuatán: Un texto del siglo xvii en náhuatl centroamericano." In XXVIII
               Simposio de Investigaciones Arqueológicas en Guatemala, Arroyo, B., Méndez Salinas,
               L., and Paiz, L., eds. Museo Nacional de Arqueología y Etnología, Guatemala (2014),
               pp. 1231-1241.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Sampeck 2015] Sampeck, K. "Pipil Writing: An Archaeology of Prototypes and a
               Political Economy of Literacy." Ethnohistory 62, 3 (2015): 469-495.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Sell et al. 2008] Sell, B., Burkhart, L., and Wright, E., eds. Nahuatl Theater
               Vol. 3: Spanish Golden Age Drama in Mexican Translation. University of Oklahoma
               Press, Norman (2008).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Stevenson 1964] Stevenson, R. “European Music in Sixteenth-Century Guatemala.”
               The Musical Quarterly 50,3 (July 1964): 341-352.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Sparks et al. 2017] Sparks, G., Sachse, F., and Romero, S. The Americas' First
               Theologies: Early Sources of Post-Contact Indigenous Religion. Oxford University
               Press, New York (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Swanton 2008] Swanton, M. "Multilingualism in the Tocuij Ñudzavui Region." In
               Mixtec Writing and Society/Escritura de Ñuu Dzaui, Jansen, M. and Broekhoven, L. van,
               eds. Koninklijke Nederlandse, Amsterdam (2008), pp. 347-380.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Terraciano 2001] Terraciano, K. The Mixtecs of Colonial Oaxaca: Ñudzahui
               History, Sixteenth through Eighteenth Centuries. Stanford University Press, Stanford
               (2001).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Townsend 2016] Townsend, C. Annals of Native America: How the Nahuas of Colonial
               Mexico Kept Their History Alive. Oxford University Press, New York (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Quiroa 2017] Quiroa, N. "Friar Francisco Ximénez and the Popol Vuh: From
               Religious Treatise to a Digital Sacred Book."Ethnohistory 64, 2 (2017): 241-270. </bibl>
            <bibl>[Viqueira Albán 2002] Viqueira Albán, J. P. Encrucijadas chiapanecas: Economía,
               religión e identidades<hi rend="italic">.</hi> Tusquets Editores/El Colegio de
               México, Mexico (2002).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Voorhies and Gasco 2004] Voorhies, B. and Gasco, J. Postclassic Soconusco
               Society: The Late Prehistory of the Coast of Chiapas, Mexico. University at
               Albany-Institute for Mesoamerican Studies, Albany (2004). [White 1987] White, H. The
               Content of the Form. Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore (1987).</bibl>
            <bibl>[Yañez Rosales 2017] Yañez Rosales, R. H. "Nahuatl L2 texts from Northern Nueva
               Galicia: Indigenous language contact in the seventeenth century." In Language Contact
               and Change in Mesoamerica and Beyond, eds. Dakin, K., Parodi, C., and Operstein, N.
               John Benjamins Publishing Company, Amsterdam/Philadelphia (2017), pp. 237-262.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Zantwijk 2011] Zantwijk, R. van. "El futuro de la lengua náhuatl
               (náhuatlatolli)." Estudios de cultura náhuatl 42 (2011): 259-65.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
