<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Beyond the Word: Immersion and Art in
                    Environmental and Digital Humanities Prototyping</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>first name(s) <dhq:family>family
                        name</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation/>
                    <email/>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000557</idno>
                <idno type="volume"
                    ><!-- volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date/>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p><title rend="quotes">Beyond the Word</title> explores the entanglements of
                    Digital and Environmental Humanities (D&amp;EH) with the word and textuality —
                    but also <emph>beyond</emph> the word and text — with bodies, art, and digital
                    apparati at its center as narrative, speculative, performative, and immersive
                    instruments. Specifically, this article details efforts to incorporate mixmedia
                    immersive literate, sonic, and visual art as a vehicle for teaching critical,
                    speculative D&amp;EH at a time of global ecological and digital transformations.
                    Using two transdisciplinary humanities initiatives developed at the Norwegian
                    University of Science and Technology as test cases, this text focuses on
                    pedagogical prototyping experiments that encourage nondeterministic uses of, and
                    thinking about, digital tools as vehicles for poetry, transmedia environmental
                    storytelling, critical theory, and immersive archival reimagining. It covers the
                    design process and sample activities incorporated to transform multimodal
                    literature and theory pedagogy into inclusive, immersive commons, and it
                    concludes with a reflection on the ethical ramifications of such D&amp;EH
                    work.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>This article examines the overlapping characteristics of Digital and
                    Environmental Humanities.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head/>
            <div>
                <head/>
                <p>Content goes here!</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ackerman2014" label="Ackerman 2014">Ackerman, A. <title rend="quotes">Getting Plants to Write Poems.</title> <title rend="italic">Poetry Foundation</title>, October 31, 2014, <ref target="https://www.poetryfoundation.org/harriet/2014/10/getting-plants-to-write-poems">https://www.poetryfoundation.org/harriet/2014/10/getting-plants-to-write-poems</ref> (accessed April 26, 2018).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ackerman2017" label="Ackerman and Richert 2017">Ackerman, A. and Richert, D. <title rend="italic">Unknown Giants</title> [installation]. Kunsthall Trondheim (2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="alaimo2010" label="Alaimo 2010">Alaimo, S. <title rend="italic">Bodily Natures: Science, Environment, and the Material Self</title>. Indiana University Press, Bloomington (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="alaimo2007" label="Alaimo and Hekman 2007">Alaimo, S. and Hekman, S. J. (eds). <title rend="italic">Material Feminisms</title>. Indiana University Press, Bloomington (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="algorithmic2020" label="Algorithmic Justice League 2020">Algorithmic Justice League (2020), <ref target="https://www.ajl.org/">https://www.ajl.org/</ref> (accessed September 14, 2020).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="armiero2017" label="Armiero and De Angelis 2017">Armiero, M. and De Angelis, M. <title rend="quotes">Anthropocene: Victims, Narrators, and Revolutionaries.</title> <title rend="italic">South Atlantic Quarterly</title>, 116.2 (2017): 345–62.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bernstein2011" label="Bernstein 2011">Bernstein, R. <title rend="italic">Racial Innocence: Performing American Childhood from Slavery to Civil Rights</title>. NYU Press, New York (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="biesenbach2010" label="Biesenbach 2010">Biesenbach, K. <title rend="italic">Marina Abramović: The Artist Is Present</title>. The Museum of Modern Art, New York (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brennan2016" label="Brennan 2016">Brennan, S. A. <title rend="quotes">Public, First,</title> in Gold and Klein (2016), pp. 384–89.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bonsignore2016a" label="Bonsignore, Hansen, Kraus et al. 2016">Bonsignore, E., Hansen, D., Kraus, K., Visconti, A. and Fraistat, A. <title rend="italic">Roles People Play: Key Roles Designed to Promote Participation and Learning in Alternate Reality Games,</title> in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2016 Annual Symposium on Computer-Human Interaction in Play</title>, October 16, 2016, pp. 78–90.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bonsignore2016b" label="Bonsignore, Hansen, Pellicone et al. 2016">Bonsignore, E., Hansen, D., Pellicone, A., Ahn, J., Kraus, K., Shumway, S., Kaczmarek, K., Parkin, J., Cardon, J., Sheets, J., Holl-Jensen, C. and Koepfler, J. <title rend="quotes">Traversing Transmedia Together: Co-designing an Educational Alternate Reality Game for Teens, with Teens,</title> in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 15th International Conference on Interaction Design and Children</title>, June 21, 2016, pp. 11–24.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burdick2015" label="Burdick 2015">Burdick, A. <title rend="quotes">Meta! Meta! Meta! A Speculative Design Brief for the Digital Humanities,</title> <title rend="italic">Visible Language</title>, 49.3 (2015): 12–33.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burdick2012" label="Burdick et al. 2012">Burdick, A., Drucker, J., Lunenfeld, P., Pressner, T. and Schnapp, J. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities</title>. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="caballero2017" label="Caballero and Ekeberg 2017">Caballero, K. and Ekeberg, F. <title rend="italic">Birding the Future: Lab Series</title> (2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chun2016" label="Chun et al. 2016">Chun, W. H. K., Grusin, R., Jagoda, P. and Raley, R. <title rend="quotes">The Dark Side of the Digital Humanities,</title> in Gold and Klein (2016), pp. 493–509.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="clement2016" label="Clement 2016">Clement, T. E. <title rend="quotes">The Ground Truth of DH Text Mining,</title> in Klein and Gold (2016), pp. 534–35.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cordell2016" label="Cordell 2016">Cordell, R. <title rend="italic">How Not to Teach Digital Humanities,</title> in Klein and Gold (2016), pp. 459–74.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="haraway2017" label="Donna Haraway 2017"><title rend="italic">Donna Haraway: Storytelling for Earthly Survival</title> [film]. Dir. F. Terranova. DVD (2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dunne2013" label="Dunne and Raby 2013">Dunne, A. and Raby, F. <title rend="italic">Speculative Everything: Design, Fiction, and Social Dreaming</title> MIT Press, Cambridge, MA and London (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fiormonte2016" label="Fiormonte 2016">Fiormonte, D. <title rend="quotes">Toward a Cultural Critique of Digital Humanities,</title> in Klein and Gold (2016), pp. 438–58.</bibl>
                [Freire 1993] Freire, P. Pedagogy of the Oppressed. New York: Continuum (1993).
                [Fusco and Dominguez 2003] Fusco, C. and Dominguez, R. “On-Line Simulations / Real-Life Politics: A Discussion with Ricardo Dominguez on Staging Virtual Theatre.” TDR, 47.2 (Summer 2003): 151–62.
                [Gardner 2017] Gardner, L. “Can Design Thinking Redesign Higher Ed?,” Chronicle of Higher Education, 64 (September 10, 2017).
                [Galey and Reuecker 2010] Galey, A. and Ruecker, S. “How a Prototype Argues.” Literary and Linguistic Computing, 25.4 (2010): 405–24.
                [Gil 2015] Gil, A. “The User, the Learner and the Machines We Make” (2015), http://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2015/05/21/user-vs-learner/
                [Giroux 1988] Giroux, H.  Teachers as Intellectuals: Toward a Critical Pedagogy of Learning Praeger (1988).
                [Gold 2012] Gold, M. K. (ed). Debates in the Digital Humanities 2012. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2012).
                [Gold and Klein 2016] Gold, M. K. and Klein, L. F. (eds). Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2016).
                [Gold and Klein 2019] Gold, M. K. and Klein, L. F. Debates in the Digital Humanities 2019. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2019).
                [Haraway 2008] Haraway, D. “Otherworldly Conversation, Terran Topics, Local Terms.” In S. Alaimo and S. J. Hekman (eds), Material Feminisms, Indiana University Press, Bloomington (2008), pp. 157–188.
                [Haraway 2016] Haraway, D. Staying with the Trouble: Making Kin in the Chthulucene. Durham, NC, Duke University Press (2016).
                [Hayles 2012] Hayles, N. K. How We Think: Digital Media and Contemporary Technogenesis. University of Chicago Press, Chicago (2012).
                [Hayles and Pressman 2013] Hayles, N. K. and Pressman, J. (eds). Comparative Textual Media: Transforming the Humanities in the Postprint Era. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2013).
                [Heise 2002] Heise, U. K. “Unnatural Ecologies: The Metaphor of the Environment in Media Theory,” Configurations, 10 (2002): 149–68. http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/con/summary/v010/10.1heise.html.
                [Heise et al. 2017] Heise, U., Christensen, J. and Niemann, M. (eds). The Routledge Companion to the Environmental Humanities. Routledge, London (2017).
                [Heldén and Jonson 2017] Heldén, J. and Jonson, H. Encyclopedia. Exhibited at Kunsthall Trondheim (2017).
                [Holmes 2018] Holmes, B. Affectivist Manifesto: Artistic Critique in the 21st Century (2008), https://brianholmes.wordpress.com/2008/11/16/the-affectivist-manifesto/ (accessed December 10, 2018).
                [Howard and Somerville 2014] Howard, Z. and Somerville, M. M. “A Comparative Study of Two Design Charrettes: Implications for Codesign and Participatory Action Research,” CoDesign, 10 (2014): 46–62.
                [Hunter 2019] Hunter J. “The Digital Humanities and “Critical Theory”:  An Institutional Cautionary Tale,”  in Gold and Klein (2019), pp. 188-194. 
                [Kirksey 2014] Kirksey, E. The Multispecies Salon. Duke University Press, Durham, NC (2014).
                [Kordjak-Piotrowska 2013] Kordjak-Piotrowska, J. (ed). Antonisz: Technology for Me Is a Form of Art. Zacheta National Gallery, Warsaw, Krakow (2013).
                [Kraus 2019] Kraus, K. 2019. “The Care of Enchanted Things,” in Gold and Klein (2019), pp.  –.
                [Laboratory for Aesthetics and Ecology 2019] Laboratory for Aesthetics and Ecology (2019). http://www.labae.org/ (accessed July 20, 2019).
                [Lee 2017] Lee, R. Symbiotic Sound [installation]. Kunsthall Trondheim (2017).
                [Linley 2016] Linley, M. “Ecological Entanglement of DH,” in Gold and Klein (2016), pp. 410–37.
                [Liu 2012] Liu, A. “Where Is Cultural Criticism in the Digital Humanities?,” in Gold and Klein (2012), pp. 490–509.
                [Lowe 2015] Lowe, L. The Intimacies of Four Continents. Duke University Press, Durham, NC (2015).
                [Manning 2007] Manning, E. Politics of Touch: Sense, Movement, Sovereignty. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2007).
                [Manovich 2001] Manovich, L. The Language of New Media. MIT Press, Boston (2001).
                [Mauro-Flude 2014] Mauro-Flude, N. “Occult Computing for Artists: An Introduction.” UnMagazine, 8.2 (2014): 1–12.
                [Mauro-Flude 2016] Mauro-Flude, N. “Divination: A Romantic Mutiny in a Maelstrom of Data [Performance-Lecture]” (2016). https://livestream.com/internetsociety/radnetworks/videos/141149701 (accessed December 20, 2018).
                [Mauro-Flude 2017] Mauro-Flude, N. “Methodologies of Risk and Experimental Prototyping,” in C. C. Baker and K. Sicchio (eds), Intersecting Art and Technology in Practice: Techne/Technique/Technology, Routledge, London (2017), pp. 169–81.
                [Mauro-Flude 2019] Mauro-Flude, N. “Performing the Internet: Post Internet Folklore,” in S. R. Wong, H. Li and M. Chou (eds), Digital Humanities and Scholarly Research Trends in the Asia-Pacific (2019), IGI Global, Hershey, PA, pp. 200–27.
                [McDonough et al. 2010] McDonough, J. P., Olendorf, R., Kirschenbaum, M., Kraus, K., Reside, D., Donahue, R., Phelps, A., Egert, C., Lowood, H. and Rojo, S. Preserving Virtual Worlds Final Report. University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities, Rochester Institute of Technology, Stanford University Libraries, and Library of Congress National Digital Information Infrastructure for Preservation Program. (2010).
                [McPherson 2012] McPherson, T. “Why Are the Digital Humanities So White? or Thinking the Histories of Race and Computation,” in Gold and Klein (2012), http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/29 (accessed March 22, 2016).
                [Mittell 2019] Mittell, J. “Videographic Criticism as a Digital Humanities Method,” in Gold and Klein (2019), pp. 224–42.
                [Musiol 2018] Musiol, H. “Metaphors of Decryption: Designs, Poetics, Collaborations,” in R. S. Restrepo (ed), Decrypting Power, Rowman and Littlefield, London (2018), pp. 157–78.
                [Musiol 2020] Musiol, H. “Toxicity, Speculation, and Rights: Political Imagination in Mixmedia, Literary, and Cinematic Futurescapes,” in S. Pinto and A. Schultheis Moore (eds), Writing Beyond the State: Post-Sovereign Approaches to Human Rights and Literary Studies, Palgrave, London (2020), pp. 330–57.
                [Musiol forthcoming 2021] Musiol, H. “‘Spaces for Other Ways to Learn’: Postcolonial Environmental Fiction, Media, and Pedagogy in the North of the Global North.” Special Issue, MLA Teaching Postcolonial Environmental Literature and Media, C. Iheka (ed) (forthcoming 2021).
                [A New We 2017] A New We / Ett Nytt Vi. Kunsthall Trondheim, Norway (2017), co-curated by Helena Holmberg, Carl Faurby, and Laboratory for Aesthetics and Ecology. https://kunsthalltrondheim.no/en/utstillinger/et-nytt-vi (accessed September 14, 2020).
                [Noble 2019] Noble, S. U. “Toward a Critical Black Digital Humanities,” in Gold and Klein (2019), pp. 27–35.
                [Nowviskie 2015] Nowviskie, B. “Digital Humanities in the Anthropocene.” Digital Scholarship in the Humanities, 30 (2015): 4–15.
                [Nowviskie 2018] Nowviskie, B. “Reconstitute the World: Machine Reading Archives of Mass Extinction” (June 12, 2018). http://nowviskie.org/2018/reconstitute-the-world/ (accessed November 22, 2016).
                [Nowviskie 2019] Nowviskie, B. “Capacity through Care,” in Gold and Klein (2019), pp. 424–26.
                [Posner 2016] Posner, M. “What Is Next: The Radical Unrealized Potential of Digital Humanities,” in Gold and Klein (2016), pp. 32–41.
                [Posner 2019] Posner, M. “Sample | Signal | Strobe: Haunting, Social Media, and Black Digitality |, ” in Gold and Klein (2019), pp. 101-122
                [Ramsay 2011] Ramsay, S. Reading Machines: Toward an Algorithmic Criticism. University of Illinois Press, Urbana (2011).
                [Rappaport 2008] Rappaport, J. “Beyond Participant Observation: Collaborative Ethnography as Theoretical Innovation.” Collaborative Anthropologies, 1 (2008): 1–31.
                [Risam 2016] Risam, R. “Navigating the Global Digital Humanities: Insights from Black Feminism,” in Gold and Klein (2016), pp. 359–67.
                [Risam 2019] Risam, R. New Digital Worlds: Postcolonial Digital Humanities in Theory, Praxis, and Pedagogy. Northwestern University Press, Evanston (2019).
                [Risam et al. 2017] Risam, R., Snow, J. and Edwards, S. “Building an Ethical Digital Humanities Community: Librarian, Faculty, and Student Collaboration.” Library Faculty Publications, 1 (2017), https://digitalcommons.salemstate.edu/library_facpub (accessed September 14, 2020).
                [Ruecker 2015] Ruecker, S. “A Brief Taxonomy of Prototypes for the Digital Humanities.” Scholarly and Research Communication, 6 (2015): 1–11.
                [Sack 2019] Sack, W. The Software Arts. MIT Press, Boston (2019).
                [Sandlin et al. 2010] Sandlin, J. A., Schultz, B. D., Burdick, J. (eds). Handbook of Public Pedagogy: Education and Learning beyond Schooling. Routledge, New York (2010).
                [Simanowski 2011] Simanowski, R. Digital Art and Meaning: Reading Kinetic Poetry, Text Machines, Mapping Art, and Interactive Installations. Electronic Mediations 35. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2011).
                [Smith 2012] Smith, N. D. “Design Charrette: A Vehicle for Consultation or Collaboration?” Paper presented at Participatory Innovation Conference (PIN-C), Melbourne, January 12–14, 2012.
                [Stoler 2010] Stoler, A. L. Along the Archival Grain: Epistemic Anxieties and Colonial Common Sense. Princeton University Press, Princeton, NJ (2010).
                [Swanson et al. 2017] Swanson, H. A., Tsing, A. L., Bubandt, N. O. and Gan, E. “Introduction: Bodies Tumbled into Bodies.” In A. L. Tsing, H. A. Swanson, E. Gan and N. Bubandt (eds), Arts of Living on a Damaged Planet: Ghosts and Monsters of the Anthropocene University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2017), pp. M1–M14.
                [Thurston 2013] Thurston, N. Of the Subcontract: Or Principles of Poetic Right. Information as Material, London (2013).
                [Tsing 2012] Tsing, A. L. “On Nonscalability: The Living World Is Not Amenable to Precision-Nested Scales,” Common Knowledge, 18 (2012): 505–24.
                [Tsing et al. 2017] Tsing, A. L., Swanson, H. A., Gan, E. and Bubandt, N. (eds). Arts of Living on a Damaged Planet: Ghosts and Monsters of the Anthropocene. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2017).
                [Vaidhyanathan 2018] Vaidhyanathan, S. “Techno-Fundamentalism Can’t Save You, Mark Zuckerberg,” New Yorker, April 21, 2018, https://www.newyorker.com/tech/elements/techno-fundamentalism-cant-save-you-mark-zuckerberg (accessed May 2, 2018).
                [Wachter-Boettcher 2017] Wachter-Boettcher, S. Technically Wrong: Sexist Apps, Biased Algorithms, and Other Threats of Toxic Tech. Norton, New York (2017).
                [Ward 2015] Ward, M. “Rapid Prototyping Politics: Design and the De-material Turn.” In W. Jonas, S. Zerwas and K. von Anshelm (eds), Transformation Design: Perspectives on a New Design Attitude, Birkhäuser, Basel, (2015), pp. 227–45.
                [Whyte 2016] Whyte, K. P. “Our Ancestors’ Dystopia Now: Indigenous Conservation and the Anthropocene,” in U. K. Heise, J. Christensen and M. Niemann (eds), The Routledge Companion to the Environmental Humanities, Routledge, New York (2016), pp. 206–15.
                [Underwood 2019] Underwood, T. “Digital Humanities as a Semi- Normal Thing,” in Gold and  Klein (2019), pp. 96-98.
                [Vinsel 2018] Vinsel, L. “Design Thinking Is a Boondoggle. Its Adherents Think It Will Save Higher Ed. They’re Delusional,” Chronicle of Higher Education, May 21, 2018.
                [Zunger 2018] Zunger, Y. “Computer Science Faces an Ethics Crisis. The Cambridge Analytica Scandal Proves It,” Boston Globe, March 22, 2018, https://www.bostonglobe.com/ideas/2018/03/22/computer-science-faces-ethics-crisis-the-cambridge-analytica-scandal-proves/IzaXxl2BsYBtwM4nxezgcP/story.html (accessed June 22, 2018).
                [Zylinska 2020] Zylinska, J. AI Art: Machine Visions and Warped Dreams. Open Humanities Press (2020).
                
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
