<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng"    type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.isosch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"     type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Open Tool Registries! Resolving the Directory
                    Paradox with Wikidata </title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Till <dhq:family>Grallert</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5739-8094</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>till.grallert@hu-berlin.de</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Till Grallert is a social and media historian. He currently heads the
                                <title rend="quotes">Methods Innovation Lab</title> for digital
                            history at Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin as part of the NFDI4memory's
                            effort to foster critical and practical data culture within historical
                            disciplines. His research and teaching focusses on the social,
                            intellectual, and conceptual histories of technologies and
                            infrastructures in the predominantly Arabic-speaking, multilingual and
                            multiscriptorial societies of the Eastern Mediterranean from the late
                            18th century onwards.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>

                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Sophie <dhq:family>Eckenstaler</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8633-0120</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Deutsches Dokumentationszentrum für Kunstgeschichte –
                        Bildarchiv Foto Marburg</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>sophie.eckenstaler@uni-marburg.de</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Sophie Eckenstaler designs and implements research software and digital
                            infrastructures at the intersection of the humanities and computer
                            science, with a focus on research software engineering, research data
                            management, and open science. Her work centers on building sustainable,
                            reusable data infrastructures for the humanities. She currently works as
                            a software developer at the Deutsches Dokumentationszentrum für
                            Kunstgeschichte – Bildarchiv Foto Marburg, where she develops a
                            DSpace-based digital image archive in collaboration with
                            Philipps-Universität Marburg.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Claus-Michael
                        <dhq:family>Schlesinger</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6718-5773</idno>
                    <email>post@esthet1cs.net</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Claus-Michael Schlesinger's research specializes in the history of
                            knowledge, with a focus on the technologies, epistemologies and
                            esthetics of born-digital objects. He has worked as a digital
                            scholarship expert with archives and libraries, planning and
                            implementing strategies for accommodating research activities and
                            research data and providing advanced services for researchers,
                            archivists and librarians. Currently afk.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Nicole <dhq:family>Dresselhaus</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0009-0008-8850-3679</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>nicole.dresselhaus@hu-berlin.de</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Nicole Dresselhaus is a research software engineer at
                            Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin, contributing to NFDI4Memory task area
                            data culture. She holds a Bachelor’s in Cognitive Informatics and a
                            Master’s in Natural Sciences Informatics from Bielefeld University, with
                            a background in machine learning, Haskell-based development, and
                            academic teaching. Her career spans roles as an ML specialist, software
                            architect for startups, and developer of research-oriented tools and
                            documentation practices.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Isabell <dhq:family>Trilling</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0009-0005-7177-0293</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>isabell.trilling.1@hu-berlin.de</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Isabell Trilling received her master's degree in digital history from
                            Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin with a thesis on the semi-automatic
                            detection of natural disasters in medieval city chronicles using large
                            language models. Since 2025, she has works as a doctoral research
                            associate on the TextPloring project. Previously, she was a student
                            research assistant in NFDI4Memory's "Methods Innovation Lab" from 2023
                            to 2025.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <!-- This information should be added when the file is created -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000838</idno>


                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="volume">020</idno>
                <idno type="issue">1</idno>
                <date when="2026-01-30">30 January 2026</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/taxonomy.xml"
                            >https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                            target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/projects.xml"
                            >https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/wiki/DHQ-Topic-Keywords; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->

                    <!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new <term> element for each -->
                    <term corresp="#tools"/>

                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->


                    <term>tool registries</term>
                    <term>tool inventory</term>
                    <term>linked open data</term>
                    <term>Wikidata</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
            <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref type="gitHist"
                    target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000838/000838.xml"
                    >GitHub</ref>.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This paper introduces the conceptual framework for open and community-curated
                    tool registries, posing that such registries provide fundamental value to any
                    field of research by acting as curated knowledge bases about a community’s past
                    and current methodological practices as well as authority files for individual
                    tools. The modular framework of a basic data model, SPARQL queries, bash
                    scripts, and a prototypical web interface builds upon the well-established and
                    open infrastructures of Wikimedia, GitLab, and Zenodo for creating, maintaining,
                    sharing, curating, and archiving linked open data. We demonstrate the
                    feasibility of this framework by introducing our concrete implementation of a
                    tool registry for digital humanities, initially repurposing data from existing
                    silos, such as TAPoR and the SSH Open Marketplace, and retaining the established
                    TaDiRAH classification scheme while being open to communal editing in every
                    aspect.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>PLACEHOLDER</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="introduction">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The digital humanities have a strong culture of discussing their tooling.
                    However, apart from projects documenting their workflows with fine-grained
                    metadata, the wider field has not yet developed widely adopted practices for
                    unambiguously citing and referencing such tools or keeping a record of their use
                    and utility for particular research projects <ptr target="#schindler_2021"/>
                    (alireza, 2022) (henny-krahmer, 2022) (Ruth, 2022) (Irrera, 2023, p. 26:4). If
                    at all, authors mostly deploy URLs to websites or code repositories<note> We
                        ourselves are guilty of this referencing practice, e.g. (schlesinger, 2023)
                        (grallert, 2022).</note>, which — like all URLs — are prone to link rot and
                    do not further contextualise a given software. Tool registries thus address an
                    obvious and concrete need of research communities and individual practitioners
                    for transparency and guidance. They collect basic information on software (e.g.
                    names of developers, licenses, version numbers, dependencies, links to code
                    repositories) and add some classification as to their purpose within the
                    research process. In fields with rapidly evolving and complex technology stacks,
                    such as the digital humanities, registries, done right, could serve as one-stop
                    shops for providing a comprehensive and up-to-date overview of (computational)
                    methods and their implementation in specific software, and thus provde a central
                    service within the knowledge ecology. Ideally, they would form part of the
                    semantic web that might guide researchers to projects, publications, and
                    tutorials, and allow them to evaluate the utility of a particular tool for their
                    own needs.</p>
                <div xml:id="X1b986f19cf5c49e1755d27e98369af78629f7f0">
                    <head>Tool Registries in the Digital Humanities</head>
                    <p> Registries of computational tools have grown into a well-established genre
                        within the digital humanities (see (grant, 202)0 for a history of tool
                        registries in DH): from DiRT (<hi rend="italic">Directory of Research
                            Tools</hi>) to Bamboo and the Canadian <hi rend="italic">Text Analysis
                            Portal for Research</hi> (<ref target="https://tapor.ca/">TAPoR</ref>
                        <ref target="https://tapor.ca/"> 3</ref>), from large EU projects like the
                            <ref target="https://marketplace.sshopencloud.eu/">
                            <hi rend="italic">Social Sciences and Humanities Open Marketplace</hi>
                            (SSHOM)</ref> to DARIAH’s (<hi rend="italic">Digital Research
                            Infrastructure for the Arts and Humanities</hi>) now defunct <hi
                            rend="italic">Tools E-Registry for E-Social science, Arts and
                            Humanities</hi> (<ref target="http://teresah.dariah.eu/">TERESAH</ref>),
                        or, in Germany, multiple independent registries developed as part of the <hi
                            rend="italic">National Research Data Infrastructure</hi> (NFDI) and the
                        Specialized Information Services (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Fachinformationsdienste</hi>, FID) (NFDI4Objects, 2025; <hi
                            rend="italic">Registry - NFDI4Culture</hi>, no date; <hi rend="italic"
                            >Home | nfdi.software</hi>, no date). In practical terms, these tool
                        registries are of a dual nature. On the one hand, they embody a field’s
                        methodological knowledge, the archive of scholarship as <hi rend="italic"
                            >techné</hi>,<note> This is inspired by Derrida’s (1996) call for an <hi
                                rend="italic">archivology</hi> and his genealogy of the archive as
                            grounded in the Latin <hi rend="italic">archivum</hi> from Greek <hi
                                rend="italic">arché</hi> as <hi rend="italic">commencement</hi> and
                                <hi rend="italic">commandment</hi> (derrida, 1996)<hi rend="italic"
                                >,</hi> Foucault’s <hi rend="italic">Archaelogy of Knowledge</hi>
                            (foucault, 2002, esp. 126-131)<hi rend="italic">,</hi> and Heidegger’s
                            writing on technology (heidegger, 2000) (c.f. ihde, 2010, esp. 32-35,
                            62)).</note> connecting information about tools to information about
                        their use and purpose. On the other hand, registries are part of the
                        socio-technical infrastructures of the information age to maintain and
                        access the record of that knowledge. It is evident that, at least in the
                        practical reality of limited resources, their aims must remain aspirational
                        in both their content and their infrastructural implementation.</p>
                    <p>Most tool registries approach knowledge about <hi rend="italic">techné</hi>
                        and the infrastructure needed to maintain this knowledge through an archival
                        framework, with its fundamental hierarchy and power relations between
                        knowledge production and knowledge consumption housed and controlled by
                        institutions largely unaccountable to the <hi rend="italic">démos</hi> and
                        enforced by the <hi rend="italic">archon</hi> (chief magistrate) (c.f.
                        (derrida, 1996) (vismann, 2009) (ebeling, 2009)). This is not to say that
                        the archive is governed by ill will. To the contrary. But academic knowledge
                        ecologies are both inherently conservative and hierarchical. Within such a
                        framework, registries seem a sufficiently familiar task to which we can
                        readily apply our well-established models and practices: pro-bono expert
                        peer-review, grant-funded project cycles, curatorial hierarchies, and
                        tightly controlled vocabularies and technical infrastructures.
                        Unfortunately, these commonly result in proprietary data silos and slowly
                        dying interfaces.</p>
                    <p>Quinn Dombrowski (2021) has coined the term <hi rend="italic">directory
                            paradox</hi> to describe the inevitable failure of such approaches to
                        knowledge curation to answer the scholarly need for always up-to-date
                        information in quickly developing fields. Against the backdrop of their own
                        involvement with DiRT and the <ref target="https://vocabs.dariah.eu/tadirah"
                            >TaDiRAH</ref> classification scheme, Dombrowski argues that despite the
                        considerable resources poured into existing tool registries, they have all
                        failed as infrastructures and part of larger scholarly ecosystems, as long
                        as their content and siloed technical infrastructure depend on unpaid
                        volunteer and grant funding (dombrowski, 2021) (c.f. (bernardou, 2018).
                        However, we do not agree with a view that “such ‘registries’ only have value
                        if the data that underpins them is constantly updated” (hughes, 2015, p.
                        156). Instead, they can, and probably should, be considered snapshots or
                        documentations of a field’s historical practices at given points in time and
                        space (c.f. (grant, 2020)).</p>
                    <p>We argue that the resulting tension between researchers and library patrons
                        seeking up-to-date information to solve an issue at hand and curators, who
                        are painfully aware of any given catalogue entry’s quality as a historical
                        artefact bound up in the contingencies of its making, cannot be resolved.
                        We, therefore, propose to shift our perception and start treating catalogues
                        and registries as the imperfect but living documents they are — digital
                        commons that need communal care and upkeep.</p>
                    <p>Gathering and curating information about a large and ever-growing number of
                        tools requires substantial resources and skilled domain experts in a broad
                        range of fields. The common solution to this problem is to build on existing
                        bodies of knowledge or, in other words, to continuously repackage already
                        existing data in new interfaces. Our libraries’ cataloguing ledgers have
                        been superseded by index cards, which were then scanned into a (Card) Image
                        Public Access Catalogue (CIPAC or IPAC), transcribed into digital texts, and
                        ingested into database systems that power OPACs (Open Public Access
                        Catalogue) (c.f. (oberhauser, 2003)). Today, these data are feeding large
                        commercial aggregators, and they are harvested for training large language
                        models and retrieval-augmented generation systems. </p>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="https://marketplace.sshopencloud.eu/">SSHOM</ref> is an example
                        of such a genealogy of tool knowledge. As part of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >European Open Science Cloud</hi> (EOSC) under the European Commission’s
                            <hi rend="italic">Horizon 2020</hi> programme, SSHOM was built by
                        DARIAH, the <hi rend="italic">Common Language Resources and Technology
                            Infrastructure</hi> (<ref target="https://www.clarin.eu/">CLARIN</ref>),
                        and the <hi rend="italic">Consortium of European Social Science Data
                            Archives</hi> (<ref target="https://www.cessda.eu/">CESSDA</ref>)
                        between 2019–23 and is considered a flagship service for DARIAH. In May
                        2023, SSHOM hosted information on almost 1,700 items. More than 1,200 of
                        these were ingested from TAPoR over a few days in late 2022.<note> This
                            information is transparently provided on the item level through the API
                            (see below). The website is much quieter about this fundamental heritage
                            and only lists TAPoR 3 as one of 15 “trusted sources” (<hi rend="italic"
                                >About the data population</hi>, 2023).</note>
                        <ref target="https://tapor.ca/">TAPoR</ref>, in turn, has a strong focus on
                        textual research. Its current iteration integrated yet another popular tool
                        registry, DiRT, in 2017/18, which itself had originated from earlier tool
                        registries such as Bamboo (rockwell, 2006) (dombrowski, 2014) (dombrowski,
                        2021) (grant, 2020). Our Wikidata-based tool registry, outlined on the
                        following pages, follows this example and integrates SSHOM and TAPoR into a
                        linked-open-data environment.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="Xea8aad3e48bae16f1ee21a6fd053caf1b4f031b">
                    <head>Yet another tool registry?</head>
                    <p>The conceptual and technical approach to building a Wikidata-based, open tool
                        registry is rooted in the multidisciplinary background and diversity of job
                        roles of those involved. As a team, we needed both a means to curate tool
                        boxes for specific research questions and disciplinary assemblages of
                        methods as well as an authority file for unambiguously identifying software
                        in research outputs and lab notes. Neither requirement was satisfied by
                        existing tool registries.</p>
                    <p>The first use case is one we frequently encounter in consulting and service
                        contexts in the library (grallert, 2024). Digital scholarship librarians or,
                        more broadly, digital scholarship experts offering research support
                        services, bring their own expertise regarding specific fields of research,
                        scientific methods, and digital tools. Library teams — including teams of
                        one — integrate consulting services with other formats like workshops. They
                        might even offer basic infrastructure as digital scholarship support and act
                        as technical partners for research projects. Institutionalized teams or
                        larger institutional contexts often work with team-specific toolsets and
                        technological stacks, which need to be documented for further reference,
                        e.g. when documenting use cases or research output. Researchers, in turn,
                        seek information regarding the possibilities for implementing computational
                        workflows adapted to specific research questions and research data along the
                        full data life-cycle from aggregation to publication. In such contexts,
                        curated lists of tools reflect team expertise and recommendations for tools
                        optimized for local target groups. It is essential that contributing to such
                        lists is fairly simple. It ought to be governed by expertise and experiences
                        with particular tools and not tied up in institutional hierarchies.</p>
                    <p>Secondly, we were looking for a publicly-accessible authority file of tools,
                        a single source-of-truth about software, which would allow us to
                        unambiguously identify and reference tools employed in the course of a
                        research project (c.f. (irrera, 2023, p. 26:4)). Such an authority file
                        would also greatly facilitate the ability to quickly and transparently
                        curate the tool lists mentioned in our first use case without a need for
                        manually maintaining and updating redundant information: a catalogue to
                        follow up on methods and tools mentioned in other scholars’ research
                        output.</p>
                    <p>The approach proposed here is designed to address both use cases by providing
                        the basic infrastructure to put together a well-curated data set for local
                        communities and make it possible to store aggregated and enhanced data sets
                        ready for reuse.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="design-goals">
                    <head>Design goals</head>
                    <p>The design goals for our tool registry are tailored towards librarians,
                        researchers, and institutions. All of these groups possess domain-specific
                        knowledge about tools and methods. At the same time, they could make good
                        use of descriptions and documentation provided by peers. Therefore, all
                        components of the system — data, software, documentation — shall be open,
                        re-usable, adaptable, and sustainable without continuous access to labour
                        and funding for specific teams of curators. Data produced through the
                        application of modules or components shall satisfy the FAIR criteria (<hi
                            rend="italic">FAIR Principles</hi>, 2020). Users shall also be able to
                        browse and compare data through workflow descriptions or basic modules,
                        e.g. a web frontend with a search interface and browsing functions.</p>
                    <p>Our approach is rooted in <hi rend="italic">minimal computing</hi> practices
                        (gil, 2016) (risam, 2022) and the <hi rend="italic">Endings Principles for
                            Digital Longevity</hi> (ept, 2023). We acknowledge the resources at hand
                        and the constraints under which we operate. As a small team of humanities
                        scholars on fixed-term contracts in various grant-funded research and
                        infrastructure projects, without access to institutional commitments beyond
                        our own labour time, we learned “how to produce, disseminate, and preserve
                        digital scholarship ourselves, without the help we can’t get, even as we
                        fight to build the infrastructures we need at the intersection of, with, and
                        beyond institutional libraries and schools” (gil, 2016, p. 29). We optimised
                        for sustainability and adaptive reuse by consequently separating data and
                        interfaces into independent components, minimising complexity, and opting
                        for openness on every level. Relying on existing infrastructures with proven
                        track records whenever possible reduces overhead for hardware and software
                        to the bare minimum.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="core-components">
                <head>Core components</head>
                <p>Our tool registry is built around Linked Open Data and Wikidata, which provides
                    the socio-technical infrastructure that sustains our effort. Ultimately, our
                    main contribution is conceptual, designing data models, queries, and workflows
                    that instantiate a catalogue of cultural artefacts on top of Wikidata. In order
                    to demonstrate the feasibility of the conceptual framework, we also contributed
                    major data sets from existing tool registries to Wikidata.</p>
                <div xml:id="X3f7954ed8e4808d0f13fbdb1c7d41d06a69caf2">
                    <head>Wikidata</head>
                    <p>Wikidata is the largest public knowledge graph with hundreds of millions of
                        items published under a public domain license.<note> See <ref
                                target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:Statistics"
                                >https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:Statistics</ref> for
                            up-to-date statistics.</note> Such a graph structures information about
                        real-world entities following the Linked Open Data paradigm in statements,
                        which construct relations between items, such as “This item is called
                        ‘Gephi’.” “Gephi is a piece of software”, “Gephi can be used for social
                        network analysis” etc. Established in 2012 by the Wikimedia Foundation,
                        Wikidata is part of the Wikiverse and the structured sister to Wikipedia.
                        Wikibase, the software it runs on, is maintained as free and open-source
                        software (FOSS) (c.f. (vrandecic, 2023)). Most importantly, Wikidata is also
                        an international community of active and passionate volunteers contributing
                        their time and knowledge to a shared knowledge ecology.</p>
                    <p>Wikidata addresses many of the weaknesses of existing tool registries, as
                        outlined above. Firstly, Wikidata inherently adheres to the FAIR principles
                        by making all data findable, accessible, interoperable, and reusable (fair,
                        2020). Even better, Wikidata provides five-star Linked Open Data (LOD)
                        (berners-lee, 2009):</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Data are available on the web with a public domain licence
                            (CC0);</item>
                        <item>Data are machine-readable structured data;</item>
                        <item>Data are serialised in non-proprietary formats;</item>
                        <item>Data adhere to open standards; and</item>
                        <item>Data link to other people’s data to provide context.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Data can be accessed and linked to through multiple APIs (application
                        programming interfaces), including SPARQL endpoints, with canonical
                        identifiers for all items and properties and permanent, versioned URIs for
                        each edit.<note> In fact Wikidata recommends to always reference the
                            versioned permanent URL instead of the canonical ID; see <ref
                                target="https://www.wikidata.org/w/index.php?title=Special:CiteThisPage&amp;page=Q25212027&amp;id=2313077072&amp;wpFormIdentifier=titleform"
                                >https://www.wikidata.org/w/index.php?title=Special:CiteThisPage&amp;page=Q25212027&amp;id=2313077072&amp;wpFormIdentifier=titleform</ref>
                            for citations of <ref
                                target="https://www.wikidata.org/w/index.php?title=Q25212027&amp;oldid=2313077072"
                                >https://www.wikidata.org/w/index.php?title=Q25212027&amp;oldid=2313077072</ref>.
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Secondly, Wikidata is a well-established, open infrastructure with large
                        communities of users, contributors and maintainers, which far exceeds
                        anything we as scholars could ever achieve on an infrastructural level. As
                        such, it is increasingly adopted as a platform to share authority data by
                        GLAM institutions and research projects (allison-cassin, 2018) (odell, 2022)
                        (sardo, 2022) (zhao, 2022) (fagerving, 2023) (grallert, 2025). Thirdly, the
                        underlying Wikibase software is user-centered, despite Wikidata’s seeming
                        emphasis on data. It provides easy tools and protocols for collaboratively
                        editing and contributing data. The threshold for contributing to a tool
                        registry on Wikidata is thus rather low, compared with solutions that employ
                        technical and organisational gatekeeping mechanisms like login or expert
                        verification.</p>
                    <p>Relying on Wikidata as a data store positions tool data as part of the
                        commons. All data on tools can thus become objects of distributed and
                        collaborative efforts to aggregate, sustain, and develop knowledge on tool
                        usage in digital humanities. Most importantly, we are not limited to this
                        particular field. Linked Open Data and Wikidata allow us to engage and join
                        efforts with other communities working with structured descriptions of
                        software, e.g. due to the growing necessity for process metadata or software
                        preservation purposes (christophersen, 2023).</p>
                    <p>Such openness comes with its own challenges. Libraries and large
                        infrastructure projects, as well as researchers curating information are
                        commonly wary to cease authority over “their” data sets to volunteer-driven,
                        radically open projects. While active misinformation campaigns do not
                        constitute a significant problem on Wikidata, misidentification of items and
                        erroneous edits occur on a daily basis. We strongly believe that the
                        benefits of using Wikidata as a platform and open knowledge graph outweigh
                        the potential imperfection of individual data points by far. We argue that
                        imperfect information is already a major “feature” of tool registries. If at
                        all, Wikidata makes it easier to correct data points and keep information up
                        to date. We also address the fluidity of data by saving weekly, versioned
                        screenshots of the data that constitutes “our” tool registry to
                        publicly-funded research data repositories. </p>
                    <p>It is important to point out that Wikidata does not remove the need for data
                        stewardship. Somebody has to put in the necessary labour. But unlike siloed
                        custom infrastructures, sharing, distributing, and transferring such
                        stewardship for the commons is a central pillar of the Wikiverse.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="data-models">
                    <head>Data models</head>
                    <p>We provide a basic object-oriented data model for tools as objects as a
                        reference model. We consider this reference model as a minimal basic set
                        that can and should be extended with domain specific and research specific
                        elements. This means that while everyone is able to use their own models,
                        all information added to Wikidata will immediately become part of the shared
                        tool registry as long as these models respect the basic reference model.</p>
                    <p>Wikidata follows no strict ontology but instead applies an open, bottom-up
                        approach, which is famously referred to as a <hi rend="italic"
                            >folksonomy</hi> (a term coined by (vanderwal, 2004)), with a very basic
                        and deliberately generic data model of <hi rend="italic">items</hi>
                        (identifiers starting with “Q”) and <hi rend="italic">properties</hi>
                        (identifiers starting with “P”) connecting items to other items or <hi
                            rend="italic">values</hi> of various data types (strings, dates,
                        integers …) through <hi rend="italic">statements</hi>. All statements can
                        carry properties as qualifiers and references to the source for this
                        information. A large part of the statements in Wikidata are properties
                        linking to other platforms and authority files through external identifiers.
                        All properties might come with a set of formal constraints, which, if
                        violated, will result in various warning flags in the Wikidata web
                        interface. All items should carry two special string-value properties for
                        multilingual human-readable labels and descriptions. The only mandatory
                        property is <ref target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Property:P31"
                            >instance of (P31)</ref> linking to one or more items, without which an
                        item would not be connected to the larger knowledge graph. But even this
                        constraint is not strictly enforced on a technical level (c.f.
                        (hosseini-beghaeiraveri, 2023).</p>
                    <p>Such a generic and unconstrained data model makes it hard to query Wikidata
                        with a predictive result, but it provides a flexible system for any
                        conceivable, community-driven data modelling: Data models exist largely
                        through communities of practice adhering to them and providing the necessary
                        SPARQL queries for building sub graphs. To this end, we set up a <ref
                            target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:WikiProject_DH_Tool_Registry"
                            >WikiProject</ref> documenting our approach and data model as a port of
                        entry to build a community of people and institutions wanting to maintain a
                        tool registry (<hi rend="italic">Wikidata:WikiProject DH Tool Registry</hi>,
                        2024). A community-oriented documentation and discussion process through the
                            <ref
                            target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:WikiProject_DH_Tool_Registry"
                            >WikiProject</ref> provides a channel for working on the common
                        reference model and evolving the data model regarding mandatory and optional
                        qualities as well as additional modules developed for specific purposes. As
                        an added bonus, WikiProjects rank highly on search engines.</p>
                    <div xml:id="our-basic-data-model">
                        <head>Our basic data model</head>
                        <p>We differentiate between a number of concepts to model the relation
                            between a tool and its purpose:</p>
                        <list type="ordered">
                            <item>Research tools comprise both methods and concrete software.</item>
                            <item>Methods are informed by theories and have a <hi rend="italic"
                                    >purpose</hi>.</item>
                            <item>Methods are implemented through (multiple) layers of software,
                                which, in turn, require <hi rend="italic">hardware</hi> and
                                infrastructural resources such as electricity, internet connectivity
                                or licences and which interact with data <hi rend="italic"
                                    >formats</hi> and <hi rend="italic">serialisations</hi> (reading
                                and writing).</item>
                            <item>Software is written in programming languages and can be interacted
                                with through <hi rend="italic">interfaces</hi>. Command line
                                interfaces and application programming interfaces require knowledge
                                of programming languages to interact with them.</item>
                            <item>Methods, languages, and formats rely on and implement abstract <hi
                                    rend="italic">concepts.</hi>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The tool registry is concerned with only a subset of this larger
                            ontology: <hi rend="italic">software</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                                >methods</hi>. The basic data model for <hi rend="italic"
                                >software</hi> requires no mandatory information in addition to the
                            Wikidata base model of <hi rend="italic">label</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >description</hi>, and <ref
                                target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Property:P31">instance of
                                (P31)</ref> beyond the <ref
                                target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Property:P366">has use
                                (P366)</ref> property that associates <hi rend="italic"
                                >software</hi> with one or more <hi rend="italic">methods</hi>.</p>
                        <p>The basic data model for <hi rend="italic">methods</hi> is even more
                            rudimentary. Here the only mandatory property is a <ref
                                target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Property:P9309">TaDiRAH ID
                                (P9309)</ref> that proclaims equivalence to a concept within “The
                            Taxonomy of Digital Research Activities in the Humanities” (<ref
                                target="https://vocabs.dariah.eu/tadirah">TaDiRAH</ref>, see below).
                            Fig. 1 shows a schematic of this data model conceptualising “Gephi” as
                            an instance of “Software” that can be used for “network analysis.”
                            Additionally, the source for this claim is identified through a
                            reference to the URI of an entry in the SSHOM.</p>
                        <figure>
                            <head/>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/image1.png"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Figure 1: Schematic of our basic data model, using Gephi (Q5548660) as an
                            example.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="tadirah-mapping">
                        <head>TaDiRAH mapping</head>
                        <p>Like all archives, tool registries depend on classification schemes and
                            taxonomies in order to file, retrieve, and produce knowledge about an
                            item in their collection. Over the course of the last decade “The
                            Taxonomy of Digital Research Activities in the Humanities” (<ref
                                target="https://vocabs.dariah.eu/tadirah">TaDiRAH</ref>) has become
                            the most widely adopted classification scheme in the digital humanities
                            and is used in its current version (&gt;2.0) for author-assigned
                            classifications of conference submissions to the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</hi> (ADHO) and <hi
                                rend="italic">Digital Humanities im deutschsprachigen Raum</hi>
                            (DHd) conferences as well as SSHOM (TAPoR uses the older, incompatible
                            version of TaDiRAH).</p>
                        <p>
                            <ref target="https://vocabs.dariah.eu/tadirah">TaDiRAH</ref> was
                            developed from the mid-2010s onwards in the tradition of John Unsworth’s
                            “scholarly primitives” ((hughes, 2015, pp. 155–157); For the genealogy
                            of TaDiRAH see (borek, 2016)). Members of DARIAH-DE and BambooDiRT
                            developed TaDiRAH on the basis of the <ref
                                target="http://digital.humanities.ox.ac.uk/Methods/ICTmethodology.aspx">
                                <hi rend="italic">ICT Methodology</hi>
                            </ref>, which itself had evolved from the AHDS Taxonomy of Computational
                            Methods (2003–) under the auspices of the Oxford University Digital
                            Humanities Programme. The first version of TaDiRAH (v0.5) was released
                            in 2016 (borek, 2015) (borek, 2016) as a four-level hierarchy of <hi
                                rend="italic">goals</hi>, <hi rend="italic">methods</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">techniques</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">objects</hi>.
                            The current iteration (&gt;v2.0) was released in 2021 (borek, 2021) and
                            has been redesigned from the ground up as a SKOS vocabulary (<ref
                                target="https://www.w3.org/TR/skos-reference/">Simple Knowledge
                                Organization System</ref>). Unlike earlier iterations, it only
                            covers methods and techniques as a single type of entities, which can
                            nest in three hierarchical layers. Therefore, v2.0 is not backwards
                            compatible with earlier versions.</p>
                        <p>The major strengths of TaDiRAH are its wide adoption across the field of
                            digital humanities and its integration into wider Linked Open Data (LOD)
                            infrastructures as part of the <ref target="https://vocabs.dariah.eu/"
                                >DARIAH Vocabs services</ref>, which is maintained by the <hi
                                rend="italic">Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural
                                Heritage</hi> (ACDH-CH) of the <hi rend="italic">Austrian Academy of
                                Sciences</hi>. In addition, a partial mapping between TaDiRAH and
                            Wikidata has been implemented on both sides. The Wikidata property <ref
                                target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Property:P9309">TaDiRAH ID
                                (P9309)</ref> was created in 2015 by Adam Schiff, Principal
                            Cataloger at the University of Washington Libraries in Seattle, to state
                            equivalence between a Wikidata item and a TaDiRAH class.</p>
                        <p>However, TaDiRAH has major flaws rather similar to those of tool
                            registries:</p>
                        <list type="ordered">
                            <item>Development depends on voluntary labour and thus the vocabulary
                                has been dormant for a number of years.</item>
                            <item>The current version and its documentation have been hard to find.
                                Until September 2025, when the team finally updated the <ref
                                    target="https://github.com/dhtaxonomy/TaDiRAH">GitHub
                                    repository</ref> to v2.0, search engines usually returned the
                                incompatible v0.5 (see also (zhao, 2022)).</item>
                            <item>The SPARQL endpoint and API, which would serve the classification
                                scheme as RDF, are frequently down.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Despite of these weaknesses, potential competitors and successors have
                            not been successful. The “NeDiMAH Methods Ontology for the Digital
                            Humanities” (<ref target="http://nemo.dcu.gr/">NeMO</ref>) (hughes,
                            2015, pp. 165–167) (bernardou,2018, pp. 4–5), developed with substantial
                            funding from the European Science Foundation by the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Network for Digital Methods in the Arts and Humanities</hi> (<ref
                                target="http://www.nedimah.eu/">NeDiMAH</ref>) from 2011 to 2015
                            (hughes, 2015) is a CIDOC CRM-compliant ontology and provided a mapping
                            from TaDiRAH but has seen no traceable adoption.<note> The academic
                                knowledge graph OpenAlex finds only <ref
                                    target="https://openalex.org/works?page=1&amp;filter=default.search%3ANeMO%20NeDiMAH"
                                    >9 references</ref>.</note> This might be due to information on
                            NeMO — quite fittingly, given its name — being incredibly hard to come
                            by. The official website is outdated and has not been updated with the
                            project results, and access to the documentation, although officially
                            licensed under “CC BY-NC-SA 4.0”, requires a login on <ref
                                target="http://nemo.dcu.gr/resources/"
                                >http://nemo.dcu.gr/resources/</ref>.</p>
                        <p>Given its wide adoption, including our seeding data set of tools from
                            SSHOM and TAPoR, we have therefore opted to retain TaDiRAH
                            classification as the main organising principle for our tool registry.
                            The system is flexible enough to adopt other classification systems
                            should they emerge, as long as their identifiers are mapped to a
                            Wikidata property.</p>
                        <p>The TaDiRAH classification of items is implemented through the <ref
                                target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Property:P366">has use
                                (P366)</ref> property, linking to other Wikidata items that carry a
                                <ref target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Property:P9309">TaDiRAH
                                ID (P9309)</ref>. To this end, we completed the mapping between
                            Wikidata and TaDiRAH so that all TaDiRAH classes can now be found on
                            Wikidata (see below).</p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="X55654b79113e647989a29dab7b2443594658f6c">
                        <head>Optional parts of the basic data model and curating collections of
                            tools</head>
                        <p>The basic data model leverages the weaknesses of an open-world knowledge
                            graph without a formal ontology to our advantage as it can be easily
                            extended to accommodate additional information on individual items, such
                            as licenses, version numbers, URIs of a source code repository, etc. For
                            this purpose, our basic data model proposes a number of optional
                            statements.</p>
                        <p>A core requirement for our tool registry is the ability for diverse
                            communities to curate their own collections. This can be done through
                            the property <hi rend="italic">collection</hi> (<ref
                                target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Property:P195">P195</ref>)
                            pointing to one or more Wikidata items describing the collection and
                            potentially naming curators and contributors (Figure 2). We have
                            implemented two such collections, <hi rend="italic">SSHOM</hi> (<ref
                                target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q131847864">Q131847864</ref>)
                            and <hi rend="italic">TAPoR</hi> (<ref
                                target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q3979414">Q3979414</ref>), to
                            document existing tool registries that formed the basis of our data set
                            (see below). Note that such collections are not necessarily limited to
                            tools classified with TaDiRAH.</p>
                        <figure>
                            <head/>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/image2.png"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Figure 2: Schematic of the data model for modelling registries as
                            collections, using Gephi (Q5548660) as an example</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Domain-specific extensions</head>
                        <p>This approach also allows us to accommodate the needs of other
                            communities that might want to model additional, domain-specific
                            relations. One such extension has been implemented by some of the
                            authors as part of a survey of the fields of digital humanities and
                            digital history. There, we model the relation between methods
                            (classified with TaDiRAH), research output in the form of publications
                            and conference papers, and their authors. This extension then allows to
                            ask for exemplary applications of a method and the tools (potentially)
                            used by specific scholars (grallert, 2025), which, in turn, allows us to
                            track the popularity of tools over time or to build training curricula
                            based on the relevance of particular tools for specific fields (see for
                            instance <hi rend="italic">method_</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">authors.rq</hi> from (grallert, 2024)).</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="frontends">
                    <head>Frontends</head>
                    <p>Wikidata provides several interfaces: a web frontend, APIs, and a <ref
                            target="https://query.wikidata.org/">SPARQL endpoint</ref>. All of these
                        interfaces come with constrains or a non-trivial amount of complexity that
                        necessitate prior knowledge about data structures, protocols, query
                        languages, or hardware-specific extensions to such standards.</p>
                    <p>Wikidata’s default interface is the <hi rend="italic">Linked Data
                            Interface</hi> (Figure 3). It emphasises the platform’s use as an
                        authority file by focusing on individual items. The <hi rend="italic"
                            >Linke</hi> functions both as a view and as an input mask, enabling
                        rather efficient data processing for a graphic user interface. This is
                        greatly facilitated by the simple presentation of a list of statements
                        currently available for any specific item, including all qualifiers and a
                        summary of existing references. However, this reduced presentation has its
                        own disadvantages. For example, the rather technical design of the
                        interface, which is based on the principles of Linked Open Data (LOD), can
                        be perceived as cumbersome and less intuitive, especially for new users and
                        those unfamiliar with knowledge graphs.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head/>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/image3.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Figure 3: The item Gephi (Q5548660) in Wikidata’s Linked Data Interface.</p>
                    <p>But most importantly, by focusing on individual items, this interface does
                        not provide direct access to the underlying knowledge graph. There is no
                        obvious or simple means for accessing and visualising specific subsets of
                        the knowledge graph — e.g. all tools that can be used for social network
                        analysis. Without such a means to return curated tool lists, Wikidata could
                        solely serve as an authority file.<note> Hosseini Beghaeiraveri <hi
                                rend="italic">et al.</hi> (2023) show that subsetting massive
                            knowledge graphs such as Wikidata has become more relevant in recent
                            years (beghaeiraveri, 2023). However, the selection of approaches and
                            tools evaluated in their study also demonstrate that there is no
                            standardised procedure to be easily applied to the tool registry.</note>
                    </p>
                    <div xml:id="query-tools-with-sparql">
                        <head>Query tools with SPARQL</head>
                        <p>As stated above, the data model is fundamentally instantiated through
                            SPARQL queries linking tools to classifications or collections. We
                            therefore provide a set of modular queries for use in various
                            applications and to ease access to SPARQL for colleagues less
                            comfortable writing their own queries from scratch (grallert, 2024).
                            Each query first asks for all items with a TaDiRAH ID, that is items
                            which our model considers to be <hi rend="italic">methods.</hi> It then
                            queries for all items that point to at least one of those methods
                            through the <ref target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Property:P366"
                                >has use (P366)</ref> property and which are instances of “Software”
                            or its subclasses:</p>
                        <p>SELECT DISTINCT ?tool ?toolLabel # only get Software-ID and
                            Software-NameWHERE { ?method wdt:P9309 ?tadirahID. # Variable method is
                            a tadirah-method ?tool wdt:P366 ?method; # Variable tool 'has method'
                            method (wdt:P31/(wdt:P279*)) wd:Q7397. # and tool is child of "Software"
                            SERVICE wikibase:label { # set wikibase-service to auto-language with
                            fallback english bd:serviceParam wikibase:language "[AUTO_LANGUAGE],en".
                            # get the tool-label (=name) of our tool. ?tool rdfs:label ?toolLabel.
                            }}</p>
                        <p>This query returns the IDs of items and their labels as a potential
                            sanity check for human readers. The ID can then be used in further
                            SPARQL queries, API calls, or the plethora of tools for interacting with
                            Wikidata hosted on <ref
                                target="https://wikitech.wikimedia.org/wiki/Portal:Toolforge"
                                >Toolforge</ref>, ranging from <ref
                                target="https://scholia.toolforge.org/">
                                <hi rend="italic">Scholia</hi>
                            </ref>, a long-running project for querying and visualising
                            scientometrics (nielsen, 2017), to <ref
                                target="https://reasonator.toolforge.org/">
                                <hi rend="italic">Reasonator</hi>
                            </ref>, which displays Wikidata items in a view optimised for their
                            particular item-type and enhanced with some basic reasoning.</p>
                        <p>Another option is to directly query for tools in curated collections,
                            such as SSHOM (<ref target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q131847864"
                                >Q131847864</ref>) and TAPoR (<ref
                                target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q3979414">Q3979414</ref>), as
                            mentioned above.</p>
                        <p>#title:Tools in the SSHOM#defaultView:TablePREFIX collection:
                            &lt;http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q131847864&gt; # a specific
                            collectionSELECT ?tool ?toolLabelWHERE { ?tool wdt:P195 collection: ; #
                            items in the collection wdt:P31/wdt:P279* wd:Q7397. # limit tools to
                            software in the broadest sense SERVICE wikibase:label { bd:serviceParam
                            wikibase:language "[AUTO_LANGUAGE],en". ?tool rdfs:label ?toolLabel.
                            }}LIMIT 3000</p>
                        <p>However, writing and adapting such queries require a profound knowledge
                            of the SPARQL query language, which makes it difficult to use for many,
                            if not most potential users. A number of research teams are testing the
                            application of LLMs or LLM-based systems for interacting with knowledge
                            graphs and SPARQL endpoints in natural language with promising results
                            (rony, 2022) (taffa, 2023) (liu, 2024) (rangel, 2024). All current LLMs
                            are pretty good at generating syntactically correct SPARQL but cannot be
                            relied upon to correctly identify entities and properties of any given
                            knowledge graph. Based on our anecdotal testing, the prototypical <ref
                                target="https://spinach.genie.stanford.edu/">SPINACH</ref> chat bot,
                            which was specifically designed for querying Wikidata with SPARQL,
                            outperforms any general purpose LLM and is a great entry point for those
                            with only cursory knowledge of SPARQL (liu, 2024). As always, one needs
                            to check the suggestions for plausibility and the more specific the
                            natural language instructions, the better will be the results. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="tool-registry-frontend-module">
                        <head>Tool Registry Frontend Module</head>
                        <p>In order to overcome the limitations of the Linked Data Interface and
                            SPARQL, we developed <ref target="https://furesh.github.io/toolfindr/">
                                <hi rend="italic">ToolFindr</hi>
                            </ref>, a prototypical web frontend for the tool registry to be used in
                            the context of the <ref
                                target="https://www.ub.hu-berlin.de/de/forschen-publizieren/kompetenzwerkstatt-digital-humanities"
                                >Kompetenzwerkstatt Digital Humanities</ref> (KDH) at the university
                            library of Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin. The idea of using Wikidata as
                            a database and authority file for web applications has successfully been
                            implemented by multiple other projects. Good examples are the <ref
                                target="https://archivfuehrer-kolonialzeit.de/">
                                <hi rend="italic">Archivführer Kolonialzeit</hi>
                            </ref> and <ref target="https://scholia.toolforge.org/">
                                <hi rend="italic">Scholia</hi>
                            </ref>. The core argument for this architecture is that one can build
                            custom interfaces for specific communities based on standardised and
                            well-documented APIs while retaining all the advantages of Wikidata
                            communities of contributors and its centralised and persistent data
                            storage without being locked into its user interface.</p>
                        <p>ToolFindr offers specialised search and some facetted browsing options
                            for digital humanities tools, as well as a more reader-friendly
                            individual view of the tools compared to Wikidata’s native linked data
                            interface. It also enables the integration of corporate design elements
                            and the provision of additional background information relevant to
                            stakeholders in the library. We took particular care to strictly
                            maintain the separation between data and presentation levels in order to
                            ensure data integrity and reusability.</p>
                        <figure>
                            <head/>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/image4.png"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Figure 4: The front-end application developed in the KDH uses Wikidata as
                            a database and authority file.</p>
                        <p>In order to facilitate installation and operation — and to minimise the
                            hurdles for subsequent use by other projects — the frontend is
                            implemented as a static website and published via <ref
                                target="https://furesh.github.io/toolfindr/">GitHub pages</ref>
                            (eckenstaler, 2025). This decision minimises the maintenance effort and
                            makes it easy to deploy the frontend.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="data-and-workflows">
                <head>Data and Workflows</head>
                <div xml:id="data-sources">
                    <head>Data sources</head>
                    <p>As outlined above, tool registers tend to build upon existing data sets. We
                        followed this well-established practice and populated our tool registry with
                        the existing knowledge about tools within the DH community by integrating
                        and linking the <ref target="https://tapor.ca/">TAPoR</ref> and <ref
                            target="https://marketplace.sshopencloud.eu/">SSHOM</ref> data sets and
                        their classification of tools according to <ref
                            target="https://vocabs.dariah.eu/tadirah">TaDiRAH</ref> into Wikidata.
                        This approach was facilitated by all three platforms providing
                        machine-actionable data through APIs and serialised as JSON.</p>
                    <p>Unfortunately, TAPoR’s APIs are entirely undocumented and we only discovered
                        them through other projects interested in the usage of tools within the DH
                        community, namely the <ref target="https://github.com/lehkost/ToolXtractor"
                            >ToolXtractor</ref> (fischer, 2022) (see also (barbot, 2019a) (barbot,
                        2019b) (fischer, 2020). The TAPoR API provides at least two endpoints. <ref
                            target="https://tapor.ca/api/tools/by_analysis"
                            >https://tapor.ca/api/tools/by_analysis</ref> returns a full list of all
                        tools with minimal information for each entry. Importantly, it links tools
                        to categories of research activities, e.g. <hi rend="italic">OpenRefine</hi>
                        to “Enrichment.” <ref target="https://tapor.ca/api/tools/%7BID%7D"
                            >https://tapor.ca/api/tools/{ID}</ref> then returns detailed information
                        for individual tools, based on the tool ID obtained through the first
                            endpoint.<note> Information includes data on tools such as URLs, source
                            code repositories, email addresses of creators, image URLS, metadata on
                            when the TAPoR entry was last updated and by whom, as well as rating on
                            the platform.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="https://marketplace.sshopencloud.eu/">SSHOM</ref>’s API, on the
                        other hand, is well <ref
                            target="https://marketplace-api.sshopencloud.eu/swagger-ui/index.html?url=/v3/api-docs"
                            >documented</ref>. Again, one has to query for all tools (through <ref
                            target="https://marketplace-api.sshopencloud.eu/api/tools-services?approved=true"
                            >https://marketplace-api.sshopencloud.eu/api/tools-services?approved=true)</ref>
                        in order to retrieve the necessary IDs for individual tools, which then
                        allow to use more specific API endpoints such as <ref
                            target="https://marketplace-api.sshopencloud.eu/api/tools-services/%7BID%7D"
                            >https://marketplace-api.sshopencloud.eu/api/tools-services/{ID}</ref>.
                        In either case, the API returns plenty of data, including links to
                        equivalent concepts on Wikidata and classifications such as TaDiRAH or the
                            <hi rend="italic">Austrian Fields of Science and Technology
                            Classification 2012</hi> on the <ref target="https://vocabs.dariah.eu/"
                            >DARIAH Vocabs services</ref>. The APIs, however, do not allow to query
                        for tools by concepts from these classification schemes. It seems that this
                        is only possible through the web interface and URL query parameters,
                            (i.e. <ref
                            target="https://marketplace.sshopencloud.eu/search?f.activity=%7Bactivity%7D"
                            >https://marketplace.sshopencloud.eu/search?f.activity={activity}</ref>)
                        where the camel case in TaDiRAH concepts is replaced with “+” and all
                        component terms are capitalised, i.e. opticalCharacterRecognition needs to
                        be translated to Optical+Character+Recognition.</p>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="https://vocabs.dariah.eu/tadirah">TaDiRAH</ref> is a SKOS
                        vocabulary currently hosted through the <ref
                            target="https://vocabs.dariah.eu/">DARIAH Vocabs services</ref>. Even
                        though this platform is envisioned as part of the Semantic Web and should
                        provide Linked Open Data, it has a patchy track record of doing so. At the
                        time of writing in 2024, neither the service’s <ref
                            target="https://vocabs-api.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">API</ref> and <ref
                            target="https://vocabs-sparql.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">SPARQL endpoint</ref>
                        nor their documentation can be reached. Fortunately, we were able to
                        download all data as RDF in late 2022.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="data-import">
                    <head>Data import</head>
                    <p>There are generally two main methods for adding and editing Wikidata items in
                        bulk: <ref target="https://quickstatements.toolforge.org/"
                            >QuickStatements</ref> and <ref target="https://openrefine.org/"
                            >OpenRefine</ref>. We chose the latter as we had to reconcile our
                        initial data sets with existing items to avoid creating duplicates. In
                        addition, OpenRefine provides means for extensive data manipulation and a
                        graphical user interface, which some of our team members were already
                        familiar with. Edits on Wikidata are generally non destructive. Wikibase,
                        the software running Wikidata, provides a mature system of user management
                        and version control, which allows to revert to earlier states.<note> There
                            are some tools for editing and reverting batch edits, but at the time of
                            writing in 2024 they had become dysfunctional and were looking for new
                            maintainers.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Reconciliation required a lot of semi-automated data cleaning and manual
                        decision making. The necessary schemas for mapping our input data sets to
                        the data model were created iteratively through the OpenRefine GUI and in
                        tandem with the data model. In total, we have mapped 85 missing TaDiRAH
                        classes (mostly through linking TaDiRAH IDs to existing Wikidata items),
                        added almost 700, and edited more than 1200 tools from the SSHOM and TAPoR
                        data sets.<note> The JSON schemas for uploads from OpenRefine to Wikidata
                            can be found at <ref
                                target="https://scm.cms.hu-berlin.de/methodenlabor/p_publish2wikidata"
                                >https://scm.cms.hu-berlin.de/methodenlabor/p_publish2wikidata</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="adding-and-editing-data">
                    <head>Adding and editing data</head>
                    <p>Wikidata allows anyone with an internet connection to edit and contribute
                        without further ado. Registration is not required, but the platform will log
                        the editor’s public IP address in such cases. With our approach, existing
                        queries will pick up new information as soon as they are added to Wikidata.
                        Tracking changes to “our” data set, we see constant improvements of data
                        through a combination of individual edits through the Wikidata user
                        interface, bulk edits, and bots. The latter, for instance, periodically
                        query linked GitHub repositories for new releases and update items
                        accordingly.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="X4917f1618a6f86d81fc5c0ef36168b17a837cf3">
                    <head>Export and publication of stable data sets</head>
                    <p>One of the primary challenges in working with Wikidata in academic
                        environments lies in its open-editing nature; anyone can modify data
                        entries, which might raise concerns about reliability and accuracy. This
                        characteristic necessitates additional measures to ensure the stability and
                        trustworthiness of the information it contains, especially for academic use
                        where data integrity is paramount for reproducibility.</p>
                    <p>To address this issue, we regularly pull copies of our data set from Wikidata
                        in formats such as RDF (serialised as Turtle, .ttl) or JSON-LD using a
                        combination of SPARQL queries and API calls. We publish these versioned
                        releases on platforms like <ref target="https://gitlab.org/">GitLab</ref> or
                            <ref target="https://github.com/">GitHub</ref> and archive them on
                        public repositories such as Zenodo (dresselhaus, 2024).</p>
                    <p>This approach allows the data sets to be cited with a DOI, ensuring that
                        specific versions can be referenced reliably. Wikidata itself provides
                        persistent identifiers for citing particular versions of data objects, but
                        through the Linked Data Interface the statements of such persistent versions
                        of items still point to the canonical ID of other items. The archived data
                        set therefore includes full copies of first-level objects (tools) and their
                        first-degree neighbours. Adding higher-degree neighbours would exponentially
                        increase the size of the data set. This, we argue, represents a sensible
                        balance between the scholarly urge for comprehensive data sets and the
                        requirement to minimise our footprint on infrastructure maintained by
                        others. Full access to historical perspectives on the full data set would
                        require to archive the entire subgraph with all dependencies, which would
                        yield a great amount of Wikidata itself with billions of triples (c.f.
                        beghaeiraveri, 2023) .</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="discussion-and-outlook">
                <head>Discussion and outlook</head>
                <p>In this paper, we have presented a conceptual framework and concrete
                    implementation of what we believe to be a sustainable approach to the directory
                    paradox as formulated by (dombrowski, 2021). Our conceptual framework and
                    implementation of a Wikidata-based tool registry for digital humanities attends
                    to communities who require a flexible and open authority file of cultural
                    artefacts as well as curated lists of subsets. The Linked Open Data paradigm and
                    the Wikiverse allow anyone to contribute their data, curate their own subsets,
                    or to query the graph for connections beyond the initial scope of a tool
                    registry. We are fully aware that the fundamental flexibility and openness of
                    Wikidata and the absence of hierarchical access control and formal ontologies,
                    such as CIDOC-CRM, might impede adoption among libraries and infrastructure
                    providers. However, the QIDs of tools can simply function as a persistent
                    identifier (PID) to connect otherwise disparate and siloed registries and
                    knowledge graphs.</p>
                <p>While TaDiRAH is currently the only classification scheme for research in the
                    digital humanities employed across multiple venues, it can be superseded or
                    amended by future classification schemes for the digital humanities when they
                    emerge. Equally, other fields could use their own classification schemes without
                    breaking the data model and registry introduced in this paper by adapting and
                    modifying the relevant SPARQL queries.</p>
                <p>We acknowledge that the reliance on SPARQL is a major obstacle to wider adoption.
                    We thus perceive of the modular frontend and a graphical user interface for
                    building queries as the most important venues of future development. We can
                    imagine a frontend with editing functionality based on HTML forms, JSON schemas,
                    and the Wikidata REST API currently under development (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Starting fresh: The Wikibase REST API</hi>, 2023) in order to technically
                    enforce data models.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="acknowledgments">
                <head>Acknowledgments</head>
                <div xml:id="funding">
                    <head>Funding</head>
                    <p>This work was funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG) through a
                        collaboration between the NFDI consortium 4Memory (<ref
                            target="http://www.4memory.de">www.4memory.de</ref>, DFG project no.
                        501609550) and <hi rend="italic">Future e-Research Support in the Humanities
                            II</hi> (FuReSH II, DFG project no. 466522693).</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="author-contributions-credit">
                    <head>Author contributions (CRediT)</head>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Conceptualization: Till Grallert, Sophie Eckenstaler, Claus-Michael
                            Schlesinger</item>
                        <item>Data Curation: Till Grallert, Isabell Trilling</item>
                        <item>Investigation: Till Grallert, Sophie Eckenstaler, Isabell Trilling,
                            Sophie Stark</item>
                        <item>Software: Sophie Eckenstaler (Frontend, SPARQL), Nicole Dresselhaus
                            (Archiving), Till Grallert (SPARQL, R)</item>
                        <item>Writing, original draft: Till Grallert, Claus-Michael Schlesinger,
                            Sophie Eckenstaler, Nicole Dresselhaus</item>
                        <item>Writing, review &amp; editing: Till Grallert, Claus-Michael
                            Schlesinger</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="data-availability">
                    <head>Data availability</head>
                    <p>All data and code is available on Zenodo:</p>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>SPARQL queries: (grallert, 2024).</item>
                        <item>Data model and JSON schemas for use with OpenRefine: <ref
                                target="https://scm.cms.hu-berlin.de/methodenlabor/p_publish2wikidata"
                                >https://scm.cms.hu-berlin.de/methodenlabor/p_publish2wikidata</ref>.</item>
                        <item>Front end: (eckenstaler, 2025).</item>
                        <item>Weekly screenshots of the data set as exported from Wikidata:
                            (Grallert and Dresselhaus, 2024–).</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="about_data_2023" label="About the data population 2023">About the data
                    population (2023). <title rend="italic">Social Sciences &amp; Humanities Open
                        Marketplace</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://marketplace.sshopencloud.eu/about/data-population"
                        >https://marketplace.sshopencloud.eu/about/data-population</ref> (Accessed:
                    June 4, 2024).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="alireza_2022" label="Alireza et al. 2022">Alireza, Z., Seung-Bin, Y.,
                    Fischer, F., Ďurčo, M., and Wieder P. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Measuring the
                        use of tools and software in the digital humanities: A machine-learning
                        approach for extracting software mentions from scholarly articles</title>,
                    DH2023, 28 July. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://dh-abstracts.library.virginia.edu/works/12004"
                        >https://dh-abstracts.library.virginia.edu/works/12004</ref></bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="allison-cassin_2018" label="Allison-Cassin and Scott 2018"
                    >Allison-Cassin, S. and Scott, D. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Wikidata: A
                        platform for your library's Linked Open Data</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >The Code4Lib Journal</title> [Preprint], (40). Available at: <ref
                        target="https://journal.code4lib.org/articles/13424"
                        >https://journal.code4lib.org/articles/13424</ref> (Accessed: April 26,
                    2024).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="barbot_2019a" label="Barbot et al. 2019a">Barbot, L., Fischer, F.
                    Moranville, Y., and Pozdniakov, I. (2019a) <title rend="italic">Tools mentioned
                        in the proceedings of the annual ADHO conferences (2015–2019)</title>.
                    Available at: <ref
                        target="https://lehkost.github.io/tools-dh-proceedings/index.html"
                        >https://lehkost.github.io/tools-dh-proceedings/index.html</ref> (Accessed:
                    July 26, 2022).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="barbot_2019b" label="Barbot et al. 2019b">Barbot, L., Fischer, F.,
                    Moranville, Y., and Pozdniakov, I. (2019b) <title rend="italic">Which DH tools
                        are actually used in research?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">weltliteratur.net: A Black Market for the Digital
                        Humanities</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://weltliteratur.net/dh-tools-used-in-research/"
                        >https://weltliteratur.net/dh-tools-used-in-research/</ref> (Accessed: July
                    26, 2022).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="bernardou_2018" label="Bernardou et al. 2018">Bernardou, A., Champion,
                    A., Dallas, C., and Hughes, L.M. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Introduction: A
                        critique of digital practices and research infrastructures</title>, in A.
                    Bernardou et al. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Cultural Heritage Infrastructures
                        in Digital Humanities</title>. London: Routledge (Digital Research in the
                    Arts and Humanities).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="berners-lee_2009" label="Berners-Lee 2009">Berners-Lee, T. (2009)
                        <title rend="quotes">Linked Data - Design Issues</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">W3: World Wide Web Consortium</title> Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/LinkedData#fivestar"
                        >https://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/LinkedData#fivestar</ref> (Accessed: May
                    23, 2024).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="borek_2015" label="Borek et al. 2015" sortKey="Boreka">Borek, L.,
                    Hastik, C., Khramova, V., and Geiger, J. (2015) <title rend="quotes"
                        >TaDiRAH</title>. Digital Humanities Taxonomy Group. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://github.com/dhtaxonomy/TaDiRAH"
                        >https://github.com/dhtaxonomy/TaDiRAH</ref> (Accessed: May 29,
                    2024).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="borek_2016" label="Borek et al. 2016" sortKey="Borekb">Borek, L.,
                    Dombrowski, Q., Perkins, J., and Schöch, C. al. (2016) <title rend="quotes"
                        >TaDiRAH: A case study in pragmatic classification</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 10(1). Available at:
                        <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/1/000235/000235.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/1/000235/000235.html</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="borek_2021" label="Borek et al. 2021" sortKey="Borekc">Borek, L.,
                    Hastik, C., Khramova, V., Illmayer, K., and Geiger, J.D. (2021) <title
                        rend="quotes">Information organization and access in digital humanities:
                        TaDiRAH revised, Formalized and FAIR</title>, in <title rend="italic"
                        >Information between Data and Knowledge</title>. Glückstadt: Werner
                    Hülsbusch (Schriften zur Informationswissenschaft, 74), pp. 321–332. Available
                    at: <ref target="https://epub.uni-regensburg.de/44951/1/isi_borek_et_al.pdf"
                        >https://epub.uni-regensburg.de/44951/1/isi_borek_et_al.pdf</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="christophersen_2023" label="Christophersen et al. 2023"
                    >Christophersen, A., Colón-Marrero, E., Dietrich, D., Falcao, P., Fox, C., Hanson, K., Kwan, A., and McEniry, M..
                   (2023) <title rend="quotes">Software metadata
                        recommended format guide</title>, <title rend="italic">softwarepreservationnetwork.org</title>Zenodo. Available at: <ref
                            target="https://www.softwarepreservationnetwork.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Software_Metadata_Recommended_Format_Guide_v1.1.0_Oct-2023.pdf"
                        >https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10001787</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="derrida_1996" label="Derrida 1996">Derrida, J. (1996) <title
                        rend="italic">Archive fever: A Freudian impression</title>. Translated by E.
                    Prenowitz. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="dombrowski_2014" label="Dombrowski 2014" sortKey="Dombroskia"
                    >Dombrowski, Q. (2014) <title rend="quotes">What ever happened to Project
                        Bamboo?</title>, <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic
                        Computing</title>, 29(3), pp. 326–339. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqu026"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqu026</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="dombrowski_2021" label="Dombrowski 2021" sortKey="Dombrowskib"
                    >Dombrowski, Q. (2021) <title rend="quotes">The directory paradox</title>, in
                    A.B. McGrail, A.D. Nieves, and S. Senier (eds.) <title rend="italic">People,
                        Practice, Power: Digital Humanities outside the Center</title>. Minneapolis:
                    University of Minnesota Press (Debates in the Digital Humanities). Available at:
                        <ref
                            target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/people-practice-power/section/ca87ec4c-23a0-452d-8595-7cfd7e8d6f0c"
                            >https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/people-practice-power/section/ca87ec4c-23a0-452d-8595-7cfd7e8d6f0c</ref>
                    (Accessed: February 24, 2022).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="dresselhaus_2024" label="Dresselhaus and Grallert 2024">Dresselhaus,
                    N. and Grallert, T. (2024) <title rend="quotes">P_wikidata2gitlab</title>.
                    Berlin: NFDI4Memory, Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://scm.cms.hu-berlin.de/methodenlabor/p_wikidata2gitlab"
                        >https://scm.cms.hu-berlin.de/methodenlabor/p_wikidata2gitlab</ref>
                    (Accessed: November 12, 2024).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="ebeling_2009" label="Ebeling 2009">Ebeling, K. (2009) <title
                        rend="quotes" xml:lang="de">Das Gesetz des Archivs</title>, in M.K. Ebeling, S. Günzel,
                    and A. Assmann (eds.) <title rend="italic" xml:lang="de">Archivologie: Theorien des Archivs in
                        Wissenschaft, Medien und Künsten</title>. Berlin: Kulturverlag Kadmos, pp.
                    61–88.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="eckenstaler_2025" label="Eckenstaler and Schlesinger 2025"
                    >Eckenstaler, S. and Schlesinger, C.-M. (2025) <title rend="quotes"
                        >ToolFindr</title>. Kompetenzwerkstatt Digital Humanities (KDH). Available
                    at: <ref target="https://github.com/FuReSH/toolfindr"
                        >https://github.com/FuReSH/toolfindr</ref> (Accessed: September 24,
                    2025).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="ept_2023" label="Endings Project Team 2023">Endings Project Team
                    (2023) <title rend="quotes">Endings principles for digital longevity</title>.
                    Available at: <ref target="https://endings.uvic.ca/principles.html"
                        >https://endings.uvic.ca/principles.html</ref> (Accessed: May 14,
                    2024).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="fagerving_2023" label="Fagerving 2023">Fagerving, A. (2023) <title
                        rend="quotes">Wikidata for authority control: Sharing museum knowledge with
                        the world</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities in the Nordic and
                        Baltic Countries Publications</title>, 5(1), pp. 222–239. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10/gs56rd">https://doi.org/10/gs56rd</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="fair_2020" label="FAIR Principles 2020">FAIR Principles (2020). <title
                        rend="italic">GO FAIR</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.go-fair.org/fair-principles/"
                        >https://www.go-fair.org/fair-principles/</ref> (Accessed: August 5,
                    2020).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="fischer_2020" label="Fischer and Moranville 2020">Fischer, F. and
                    Moranville, Y. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Tools mentioned in DH2020 abstracts.</title>
                        <title rend="italic">weltliteratur.net: A Black Market for the Digital Humanities</title>.
                    Available at: <ref
                        target="https://weltliteratur.net/tools-mentioned-in-dh2020-abstracts/"
                        >https://weltliteratur.net/tools-mentioned-in-dh2020-abstracts/</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="fischer_2022" label="Fischer, yoannspace, and laureD19 2022">Fischer,
                    F., yoannspace and laureD19 (2022) <title rend="quotes">ToolXtractor</title>.
                    Available at: <ref target="https://github.com/lehkost/ToolXtractor"
                        >https://github.com/lehkost/ToolXtractor</ref> (Accessed: May 28,
                    2024).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="foucault_2002" label="Foucault 2002">Foucault, M. (2002) <title
                        rend="italic">The archaeology of knowledge</title>. Translated by A.M.S.
                    Smith. London: Routledge.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="gil_2016" label="Gil and Ortega 2016">Gil, A. and Ortega, É. (2016)
                        <title rend="quotes">Global outlooks in digital humanities: Multilingual
                        practices and minimal computing</title>, in C. Crompton, R.J. Lane, and R.
                    Siemens (eds.) <title rend="italic">Doing digital humanities: Practice,
                        training, research</title>. Abingdon: Routledge, pp. 22–34.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="grallert_2022" label="Grallert 2022" sortKey="Grallerta">Grallert, T.
                    (2022) <title rend="quotes">Open Arabic periodical editions: A framework for
                        bootstrapped scholarly editions outside the global north</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 16(2). Available at: <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/16/2/000593/000593.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/16/2/000593/000593.html</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="grallert_2024a" label="Grallert et al. 2024" sortKey="Grallertb"
                    >Grallert, T., Eckenstaler, S., Tirtohusodo, S., and Schlesinger, C-M..
                    (2024) <title rend="quotes" xml:lang="de">Ob Werkzeugkoffer, Werkstatt
                        oder Baumarkt: Offene, community-kuratierte Tool Registries mit
                        Wikidata</title>. DHd2024, Zenodo, 29 February. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10698252"
                        >https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10698252</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="grallert_2024b" label="Grallert 2024" sortKey="Grallertc">Grallert, T.
                    (2024) <title rend="quotes">Tool registry: SPARQL queries</title>. Available at:
                        <ref target="https://scm.cms.hu-berlin.de/methodenlabor/tr_sparql"
                        >https://scm.cms.hu-berlin.de/methodenlabor/tr_sparql</ref> (Accessed:
                    January 21, 2025).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="grallert_2025a" label="Grallert 2025" sortKey="Grallertd">Grallert, T.
                    (2025) <title rend="quotes">Adding every Arabic periodical published before 1930
                        to Wikidata: Moving the scholarly crowd-sourcing project Jarāʾid to the
                        digital commons</title>, <title rend="italic">Transformations: A DARIAH
                        Journal</title>, 1: Workflows, pp. 1–39. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.46298/transformations.14749"
                        >https://doi.org/10.46298/transformations.14749</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="grallert_2024c" label="Grallert and Dresselhaus 2024–"
                    sortKey="Grallerte">Grallert, T. and Dresselhaus, N. (2024–) <title
                        rend="quotes">Tool registry for digital humanities</title>. Zenodo.
                    Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14259806"
                        >https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14259806</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="grallert_2025b" label="Grallert, Trilling, and Skibba 2025"
                    sortKey="Grallertf">Grallert, T., Trilling, I. and Skibba, A. (2025) <title
                        rend="italic">Wikidata:WikiProject Field Survey Digital Humanities / Digital
                        History</title>. Wikidata. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.wikidata.org/w/index.php?title=Wikidata:WikiProject_Field_Survey_Digital_Humanities_/_Digital_History&amp;oldid=2296127677"
                        >https://www.wikidata.org/w/index.php?title=Wikidata:WikiProject_Field_Survey_Digital_Humanities_/_Digital_History&amp;oldid=2296127677</ref>
                    (Accessed: November 5, 2024).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="grant_2020" label="Grant et al. 2020">Grant, K. et al. (2020) <title
                        rend="quotes">Absorbing DiRT: Tool directories in the digital age</title>,
                        <title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Digital Studies / Le champ numérique</title>, 10(1).
                    Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.325"
                        >https://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.325</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="heidegger_2000" label="Heidegger 2000">Heidegger, M. (2000) <title
                        rend="quotes" xml:lang="de">Die Frage nach der Technik</title>, in F.-W. von Herrmann
                    (ed.) <title rend="italic" xml:lang="de">Vorträge und Aufsätze</title>. Frankfurt: Klostermann
                    (Gesamtausgabe), pp. 5–36.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="henny-krahmer_2022" label="Henny-Krahmer and Jettka 2022"
                    >Henny-Krahmer, U. and Jettka, D. (2022) <title rend="quotes" xml:lang="de">Softwarezitation
                        als Technik der Wissenschaftskultur - Vom Umgang mit Forschungssoftware in
                        den Digital Humanities</title>. DHd 2022 Kulturen des digitalen
                    Gedächtnisses. 8. Tagung des Verbands "Digital Humanities im deutschsprachigen
                    Raum" (DHd 2022), Zenodo, 7 March. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6328047"
                        >https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6328047</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="home_nfdi" label="Home | nfdi.software">Home | nfdi.software (n.d). Available at: <ref target="https://nfdi.software/"
                        >https://nfdi.software/</ref> (Accessed: October 17, 2025).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="hosseini_2023" label="Hosseini Beghaeiraveri et al. 2023">Hosseini
                    Beghaeiraveri, S.A., Labra-Gayo, J.E., Waagmeester, A., Ammar, A., Gonzalez, C., Slenter, D., Ul-Hasan, S., Willighagen, E., McNeill, F., and Gray, A.J.G. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Wikidata subsetting:
                        Approaches, tools, and evaluation</title>, <title rend="italic">Semantic
                        Web</title>, Preprint, pp. 1–27. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.3233/SW-233491"
                        >https://doi.org/10.3233/SW-233491</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="hughes_2015" label="Hughes, Constantopoulos, and Dallas 2015">Hughes,
                    L., Constantopoulos, P. and Dallas, C. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Digital
                        methods in the humanities: Understanding and describing their use across the
                        disciplines</title>, in S. Schreibman, R. Siemens, and J. Unsworth (eds.)
                        <title rend="italic">A New Companion to Digital Humanities</title>.
                    Chicester: Wiley, pp. 150–170. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118680605.ch11"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118680605.ch11</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="ihde_2010" label="Ihde 2010">Ihde, D. (2010) <title rend="italic"
                        >Heidegger's technologies: Postphenomenological perspectives</title>. New
                    York: Fordham University Press (Perspectives in Continental Philosophy).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="irrera_2023" label="Irrera et al. 2023">Irrera, O., Mannocci, A., Manghi, P., and Silvello, G. (2023)
                        <title rend="quotes">A novel curated scholarly graph connecting textual and
                        data publications</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Data and
                        Information Quality</title>, 15(3), pp. 26:1–26:24. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1145/3597310"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1145/3597310</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="liu_2024" label="Liu et al. 2024">Liu, S.,  Semnani, S.J., Triedman, T., Xu, J., Zhao, I.D., and Lam, M.S. (2024) <title
                        rend="italic">SPINACH: SPARQL-Based Information Navigation for Challenging
                        Real-World Questions</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2407.11417"
                        >https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2407.11417</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="nfdi4objects_2025" label="NFDI4Objects 2025">NFDI4Objects (2025)
                        <title rend="italic" xml:lang="de">Verzeichnis und Evaluation vorhandener Tools, Standards
                        und Daten</title>. NFDI4Objects. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://nfdi4objects.net//portal/trails/directory_and_evaluation_of_existing_tools_standards_and_data/"
                        >https://nfdi4objects.net//portal/trails/directory_and_evaluation_of_existing_tools_standards_and_data/</ref>
                    (Accessed: October 17, 2025).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="nielsen_2017" label="Nielsen, Mietchen, and Willighagen 2017">Nielsen,
                    F.Å., Mietchen, D. and Willighagen, E. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Scholia,
                        scientometrics and Wikidata</title>, in E. Blomqvist et al. (eds.) <title
                        rend="italic">The Semantic Web: ESWC 2017 Satellite Events</title>. Cham:
                    Springer International Publishing (Lecture Notes in Computer Science), pp.
                    237–259. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-70407-4_36"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-70407-4_36</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="oberhauser_2003" label="Oberhauser 2003">Oberhauser, O.C. (2003)
                        <title rend="quotes">Card-image public access catalogues (CIPACs): An
                        international survey</title>, <title rend="italic">Program: Electronic
                        Library and Information Systems</title>, 37(2), pp. 73–84. Available at:
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1108/00330330310472867"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1108/00330330310472867</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="odell_2022" label="Odell, Lemus-Rojas, and Brys 2022">Odell, J.,
                    Lemus-Rojas, M. and Brys, L. (2022) <title rend="italic">Wikidata for Scholarly
                        Communication Librarianship</title>. PUI University Library. Available at:
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.7912/9Z4E-9M13"
                        >https://doi.org/10.7912/9Z4E-9M13</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="rangel_2024" label="Rangel et al. 2024">Rangel, J.C., de Farias, T.M., Sima, A.C., and Kobayashi, N. (2024)
                        <title rend="italic">SPARQL Generation: An analysis on fine-tuning OpenLLaMA
                        for Question Answering over a Life Science Knowledge Graph</title>.
                    Available at: <ref target="http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04627"
                        >http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04627</ref> (Accessed: June 11, 2024).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="registry_nfdi4culture" label="Registry - NFDI4Culture">Registry -
                    NFDI4Culture (no date). Available at: <ref
                        target="https://nfdi4culture.de/de/ressourcen/registry.html"
                        >https://nfdi4culture.de/de/ressourcen/registry.html</ref> (Accessed:
                    October 17, 2025).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="risam_2022" label="Risam and Gil 2022">Risam, R. and Gil, A. (2022)
                        <title rend="quotes">Introduction: The questions of minimal
                        computing</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                    Quarterly</title>, 16(2). Available at: <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/16/2/000646/000646.html"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/16/2/000646/000646.html</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="rockwell_2006" label="Rockwell 2006">Rockwell, G. (2006) <title
                        rend="quotes">TAPoR: Building a portal for text analysis</title>, in R.G.
                    Siemens and D. Moorman (eds.) <title rend="italic">Mind technologies: Humanities
                        computing and the Canadian academic community</title>. Calgary: University
                    of Calgary Press, pp. 285–289. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.deslibris.ca/ID/415538"
                        >https://www.deslibris.ca/ID/415538</ref> (Accessed: June 4, 2024).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="rony_2022" label="Rony et al. 2022">Rony, M.R.A.H., Kumar, U., Teucher, R., Kovriguina, L., and Lehmann, J., (2022)
                        <title rend="quotes">SGPT: A generative approach for SPARQL query generation
                        from natural language questions</title>, <title rend="italic">IEEE
                        Access</title>, 10, pp. 70712–70723. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1109/ACCESS.2022.3188714"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1109/ACCESS.2022.3188714</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="ruth_2022" label="Ruth, Niekler, and Burghardt 2022">Ruth, N., Niekler,
                    A. and Burghardt, M. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Peeking inside the DH toolbox -
                        Detection and classification of software tools in DH publications</title>,
                    in <title rend="italic">Workshop on Computational Humanities Research</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Peeking-Inside-the-DH-Toolbox-Detection-and-of-in-Ruth-Niekler/a9017fcb60338fb23bea1c6519da5f40cabbe839"
                        >https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Peeking-Inside-the-DH-Toolbox-Detection-and-of-in-Ruth-Niekler/a9017fcb60338fb23bea1c6519da5f40cabbe839</ref>
                    (Accessed: March 21, 2024).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="sardo_2022" label="Sardo and Bianchini 2022">Sardo, L. and Bianchini,
                    C. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Wikidata: A new perspective towards universal
                        bibliographic control</title>, <title rend="italic">JLIS : Italian Journal
                        of Library, Archives and Information Science = <foreign xml:lang="it">Rivista italiana di
                        biblioteconomia, archivistica e scienza dell'informazione</foreign></title>, pp.
                    291–311. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10/gn7n2m"
                        >https://doi.org/10/gn7n2m</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="schindler_2021" label="Schindler et al. 2021">Schindler, D., Bensmann, F., Dietze, S., and Krüger, F.
                    (2021) <title rend="quotes">SoMeSci- A 5 star open data gold standard knowledge
                        graph of software mentions in scientific articles</title>, in. New York, NY,
                    USA: Association for Computing Machinery (CIKM '21), pp. 4574–4583. Available
                    at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1145/3459637.3482017"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1145/3459637.3482017</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="schlesinger_2023"
                    label="Schlesinger, Gäckle-Heckelen, and Burkard 2023">Schlesinger, C.-M.,
                    Gäckle-Heckelen, M. and Burkard, F. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Onboarding
                        digital humanities students with a shared working environment for
                        introductory courses: Concept, implementation, and lessons learned</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">IDEAH</title>, 3(4). Available at: <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.21428/f1f23564.4c0566bc"
                        >https://doi.org/10.21428/f1f23564.4c0566bc</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="starting_fresh_2023" label="Starting fresh 2023">Starting fresh: The
                    Wikibase REST API (2023). <title rend="italic">Wikimedia Tech News</title>.
                    Available at: <ref
                        target="https://tech-news.wikimedia.de/2023/09/07/starting-fresh-the-wikibase-rest-api/"
                        >https://tech-news.wikimedia.de/2023/09/07/starting-fresh-the-wikibase-rest-api/</ref>
                    (Accessed: March 20, 2025).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="taffa_2023" label="Taffa and Usbeck 2023">Taffa, T.A. and Usbeck, R.
                    (2023) <title rend="italic">Leveraging LLMs in scholarly knowledge graph
                        Question Answering</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.09841"
                        >http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.09841</ref> (Accessed: July 18, 2024).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="vanderwal_2004" label="VanderWal 2004" sortKey="Vanderwal">VanderWal, T. (2004) <title
                        rend="italic">Feed On This</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.vanderwal.net/random/entrysel.php?blog=1562"
                        >https://www.vanderwal.net/random/entrysel.php?blog=1562</ref> (Accessed:
                    February 6, 2025).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="vismann_2009" label="Vismann 2009">Vismann, C. (2009) <title
                        rend="quotes" xml:lang="de">Arché, Archiv, Gesetzesherrschaft</title>, in M.K. Ebeling, S.
                    Günzel, and A. Assmann (eds.) <title rend="italic" xml:lang="de">Archivologie: Theorien des
                        Archivs in Wissenschaft, Medien und Künsten</title>. Berlin: Kulturverlag
                    Kadmos, pp. 89–103.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="vrandecic_2023" label="Vrandečić, Pintscher, and Krötzsch 2023"
                    sortKey="Vrandecic">Vrandečić, D., Pintscher, L. and Krötzsch, M. (2023) <title
                        rend="quotes">Wikidata: The making of</title>, in <title rend="italic"
                        >Companion Proceedings of the ACM Web Conference 2023</title>. New York, NY,
                    USA: Association for Computing Machinery (WWW '23 Companion), pp. 615–624.
                    Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1145/3543873.3585579"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1145/3543873.3585579</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="wikidata_dh_2024" label="Wikidata:WikiProject DH Tool Registry 2024"
                    >Wikidata:WikiProject DH Tool Registry (2024). <title rend="italic"
                        >Wikidata</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.wikidata.org/w/index.php?title=Wikidata:WikiProject_DH_Tool_Registry&amp;oldid=2277445090"
                        >https://www.wikidata.org/w/index.php?title=Wikidata:WikiProject_DH_Tool_Registry&amp;oldid=2277445090</ref>
                    (Accessed: November 5, 2024).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="zhao_2022" label="Zhao 2022">Zhao, F. (2022) <title rend="quotes">A
                        systematic review of Wikidata in digital humanities projects</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, pp. 1–22.
                    Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqac083"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqac083</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
