<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Infrastructural Sovereignty in the Black Atlantic</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Dhanashree <dhq:family>Thorat</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Mississippi State University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>dt1349@msstate.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                 <p><name>Dhanashree Thorat</name> is an assistant professor of English at <name>Mississippi State University</name>. 
                    Her research is situated at the intersection of postcolonial studies and digital humanities. She is a founding 
                    Executive Council member of the Center for Digital Humanities, Pune, in <name>India</name>. She has published 
                    articles in the <title rend="italic">Journal of Postcolonial Writing</title>, <title rend="italic">South Asian 
                    Review</title>, and <title rend="italic">Feminist Media Studies</title>. Thorat is currently working on a book 
                    project on internet infrastructure in the Global South.
                 </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000762</idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <term corresp="#globalDH"/>
               <term corresp="#infrastructure"/>
               <term corresp="#literary_studies"/>
               <term corresp="#race"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>Black digital humanities</item>
                  <item>postcolonial digital humanities</item>
                  <item>digital divide</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000762/000762.xml">GitHub</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
           <p>This article locates how the violent afterlives of slavery and colonialism manifest in internet infrastructure, 
              specifically focusing on Google's undersea fiber-optic cable named <q>Equiano</q>. This naming calls on <name>Olaudah 
              Equiano</name>, an eighteenth-century Black man who was sold into slavery and later purchased his own freedom. 
              <name>Equiano</name> eventually advocated for the abolitionist movement and published an autobiographical account called 
              <title rend="italic">The Interesting Narrative of the Life of Olaudah Equiano, or Gustavus Vassa, the African</title> 
              (1789). Reading Google's infrastructural initiative against the grain of <name>Equiano</name>'s autobiographical 
              narrative, I pursue the histories, lived experiences, and affective registers of enslavement, colonialism, and Black 
              liberation called into being by the invocation of <name>Equiano</name>'s name. This article highlights the implications 
              of undersea cable projects for infrastructural sovereignty when Western and capitalist corporations drive the 
              development of internet infrastructure in postcolonial nation-states like <name>Nigeria</name>. Furthermore, I forward 
              <name>Equiano</name>'s testimony and his unrestrained desire for freedom as a call to reimagine internet 
              infrastructural politics and data justice. <name>Equiano</name>'s autobiography testifies to the capacity of the Black 
              radical imagination to pursue liberatory pathways that had been declared foreclosed under regimes of racial terror. 
              Methodologically, I build on extant scholarship in literary criticism on <name>Equiano</name>'s narrative as well as 
              Black and postcolonial digital humanities to illuminate historically situated (infra)structural modalities and the 
              racial politics undergirding them.
           </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>In June 2019, Google announced a new undersea fiber-optic cable line connecting <name>Portugal</name> and <name>South 
               Africa</name> and named it <q>Equiano</q> after <name>Olaudah Equiano</name>, an eighteenth-century Black man who was 
               kidnapped from his Igbo village and sold into slavery. This article reads Google's infrastructural initiative against 
               the grain of <name>Equiano</name>'s autobiographical narrative to locate how the violent afterlives of slavery and 
               colonialism manifest in and undergird Internet infrastructure projects today.
            </p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head/>
          <epigraph>
            <quote rend="block">"Plantation slavery … has retained a central place in the historical memories of the black 
              Atlantic."</quote>
              <bibl><name>Paul Gilroy</name>, <title rend="italic">The Black Atlantic: Modernity and Double 
                Consciousness</title></bibl>
          </epigraph>
            <p>In June 2019, Google announced a new undersea fiber-optic cable line connecting <name>Portugal</name> and 
               <name>South Africa</name>. Traveling over ocean beds between continents, undersea fiber optic cables are the material 
               backbone of the global internet network, responsible for almost all internet connectivity. Google now partially owns 
               8.5% of the global undersea cable infrastructure, and this new cable project announced by Google will be the third 
               cable entirely owned and operated by Google <ptr target="#zimmer2018"/>. In the map accompanying the Google news 
               release in June 2019, the cable is marked as a white line stretched across the blue waters of the Atlantic and running 
               the length of West <name>Africa</name> between <name>Lisbon</name>, <name>Portugal</name> and <name>Cape Town</name>, 
               <name>South Africa</name> <ptr target="#francois_etal2019"/>. The cable makes landfall just once in this journey in 
               <name>Lagos</name>, <name>Nigeria</name>.<note>Undersea cables make landfall to connect to a country's domestic 
               internet infrastructure and/or to receive power. Google's news release on this cable line suggests other potential 
               landings in West African countries but does not offer a timeline for these other landings.</note> Drawing on this 
               connection to <name>Nigeria</name>, Google named the cable line <q>Equiano</q> and enmeshed the Transatlantic 
               Slave Trade with the undersea fiber optic network of the internet.
            </p>
            <p>This naming evokes <name>Olaudah Equiano</name>, an African man who was kidnapped and sold into slavery as a young 
               boy in <name>Nigeria</name> and eventually purchased his freedom from a British slave owner in 1766. 
               <name>Equiano</name> lived in <name>London</name> for most of his life after manumission, eventually advocating for the 
               abolitionist movement and publishing an autobiographical account called  <title rend="italic">The Interesting 
               Narrative of the Life of Olaudah Equiano, or Gustavus Vassa, the African</title> (1789). Google's naming choice 
               enmeshes a historical legacy with contemporary infrastructure, threaded through by the iterative logic of racial 
               subjugation. While this naming follows the facile ethos of corporate multiculturalism (purportedly honoring 
               <name>Equiano</name>'s life), I read Google's infrastructure initiative in light of <name>Equiano</name>'s narrative 
               to pursue the histories, lived experiences, and affective registers of enslavement, colonialism, and Black liberation 
               called into being by the invocation of his name. I locate how the violent afterlives of slavery and colonialism and the 
               commodification of Black bodies under racial capitalism manifest in internet infrastructure.
            </p>
            <p>I draw this approach particularly from <name>Jessica Marie Johnson</name> who notes that <quote rend="inline">embodied 
               and data-rich histories of slavery [require]…remixing conceptual, discursive, and archival geographies, with deliberate, 
               pained intimacy, and, likely, some violence</quote> <ptr target="#johnson2018" loc="71"/>. <name>Johnson</name>'s 
               reminder that loss and violence are implicit in the datafication of Black life applies two-fold in the context of 
               Google's project. <name>Olaudah Equiano</name> entered Western modernity as an enslaved subject and commodity under 
               the terms of racial capitalism. Centuries later, Google's abrogation of his name and the symbolic transmutation of his 
               personhood into object form (an undersea cable) recreates the troubling dehumanization of Black subjectivity. The 
               recurring nature of this transmutation points to the colonial and racial ideologies through which Google lays claim 
               on African markets and seeks to quantify Black bodies as data. By bringing <name>Equiano</name>'s narrative to bear 
               on Google's techno-infrastructure, I trace the <quote rend="inline">pained intimacy</quote> of slavery which the press 
               release elicits but ultimately eschews due to its distressing as well as subversive capacity 
               <ptr target="#johnson2018"/>.
            </p>
            <p>I first point out the complex politics of naming and Black personhood in <name>Equiano</name>'s autobiographical 
               account and Google's press release and then racialize the notion of connectivity by intertwining techno-utopian 
               narratives of internet connectivity with kinship bonds in <name>Equiano</name>'s account. I argue that Google's 
               project emblematizes how these internet infrastructural projects reroute colonial ambitions, operating in the oceanic 
               pathways of the slave trade and on the ideologies of racial capitalism now trading in datafied Black bodies. I then 
               turn to <name>Equiano</name>'s narrative to present the subversive potential of <name>Equiano</name>'s desire for 
               freedom as it becomes embedded in this cable project. In the gaps and silences of Google's press release, 
               <name>Equiano</name>'s narrative charts an account of vulnerability and survival and speaks to the struggle for Black 
               liberation against the dehumanizing systems of white supremacy and racial capitalism. Most crucially, 
               <name>Equiano</name>'s testimony and his unrestrained desire for freedom present a call to reimagine infrastructural 
               and data logics of racial subjugation. As much as <name>Equiano</name>'s text speaks to the oceanic currents of trauma 
               and abjection, this narrative also reconfigures the Atlantic as a site of Black liberation and speculative 
               (re)imagining of the future.
            </p>
            <p>In this article, I build on extant scholarship in literary criticism on <name>Equiano</name>'s account as well as 
               Black and postcolonial digital humanities to illuminate historically situated (infra)structural modalities and the 
               racial politics undergirding them. This article began as an inquiry into the impact of internet infrastructures on 
               postcolonial sovereignty located within a genealogy of postcolonial and decolonial thinking in the Global South, 
               drawing on germinal work by <ptr target="#ricaurte2019"/> <ptr target="#orji2018"/> <ptr target="#ajayi2002"/> 
               <ptr target="#anand_etal2018"/> <ptr target="#starosielski2015"/> <ptr target="#umezurike2012"/> 
               <ptr target="#duarte2017"/>. Infrastructural assemblages, denoting <quote rend="inline">technical systems and the 
               social networks</quote> that form around them <ptr target="#anand_etal2018"/>, encompass material presence, 
               bureaucratic logics, and ideological orientations that are likewise invested in the production of racial hierarchies 
               and racialized forms of humanity. I particularly foreground Black subject-formation as inseparable from concerns about 
               internet infrastructure and sovereignty in Google's latest project. In this regard, I draw on <name>Kim Gallon</name>'s 
               assertion that <quote rend="inline">Black digital humanities provides a forum for thinking through the ways that black 
               humanity emerges, submerges, and resurfaces in the digital realm</quote> <ptr target="#gallon2016"/>. It is necessary 
               to center the (re)mediation of Blackness in the techno-modern landscape to attend to the racial projects imbricated in 
               and perpetuated by these undersea cable projects in transnational and postcolonial contexts.
            </p>
            <p>While the internet is often perceived as a deterritorialized space, its infrastructure remains material and embedded 
               in state and international politics. The material infrastructure of the internet, dependent on the global fiber optic 
               cable network, has become a matter of state sovereignty, crucial to the economy and security of modern nation-states. 
               States rely on internet infrastructure to access global financial markets and for all major communications, ranging 
               from matters of state security to citizens' use of the internet. This article, thus, refocuses contemporary discussions 
               of data colonialism on the very material infrastructures which undergird algorithmic violence 
               <ptr target="#couldry_etal2019"/>. Infrastructural modalities should be a critical component in our efforts to 
               challenge data colonialism and data injustices. My analysis of <name>Equiano</name>'s narrative for its subversive 
               potential is undergirded by <name>Ruha Benjamin</name>'s reminder that we can redesign technologies 
               <quote rend="inline">to resist coded inequity, to build solidarity, and to engender liberation</quote>, as well as 
               <name>Shaka McGlotten</name>'s writing on the <quote rend="inline">rogue epistemologies</quote> of Black data that 
               can be tuned into counter-knowledges and forms of resistance.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head><name>Olaudah Equiano</name> &amp; the Transatlantic Slave Trade</head>
            <p>When Google announced the Equiano cable line in June 2019, it had two other existing international cable lines 
               (<q>Curie</q>, between <name>California</name> and <name>Chile</name>, and <q>Dunant</q>, between <name>Virginia</name> 
               and <name>France</name>) that are also privately and solely owned by Google. Most cable lines are built as 
               collaborative projects between multiple partners to offset costs, and sole ownership consolidates management and 
               operation parameters within one corporation. The June 2019 press release announcing the Equiano cable follows the 
               company's logic of naming cable lines to honor <quote rend="inline">historical luminaries</quote> 
               (<name>Marie Curie</name>, <name>Henry Dunant</name>, and now <name>Olaudah Equiano</name>) but does little to grapple 
               with the history of slavery in the Atlantic over which the cable project will be laid materially and symbolically. The 
               barely concealed violence of enslavement is glossed over with technical detail. To explain the new cable's name, the 
               document notes: <quote rend="block">Google's private subsea cables all carry the names of historical luminaries, and 
               <name>Equiano</name> is no different. Named for <name>Olaudah Equiano</name>, a Nigerian-born writer and abolitionist 
               who was enslaved as a boy, the Equiano cable is state-of-the-art infrastructure based on space-division multiplexing 
               (SDM) technology, with approximately 20 times more network capacity than the last cable built to serve this 
               region.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>The press release not only omits substantive attention to the Transatlantic Slave Trade but also to the Black man 
               after whom the cable line is named. A single platitude (<quote rend="inline">historical luminary</quote>) covers for 
               <name>Equiano</name>'s life as an enslaved person, his struggle to purchase his freedom, and his work as an 
               abolitionist. Omitting <name>Equiano</name>'s voice entirely, the press release lacks the emotional charge present in 
               his written account, as well as his critical examination of slavery. Instead of delving into these details and their 
               implications, the press memo immediately transitions into technical details. In the long second sentence, 
               <name>Equiano</name>, a Black abolitionist, is symbolically transmuted into <emph>the</emph> Equiano cable. The yawning 
               chasm between the two sentence phrases, <name>Equiano</name>, the Black man, and Equiano, the cable, is incapable of 
               being bridged by the one comma, which stitches the sentence fragments together to perform this dehumanizing 
               transmutation. The press release avoids the <quote rend="inline">pained intimacy</quote> of Black life under slavery 
               with an overflow of technical detail <ptr target="#johnson2018" loc="71"/>. <name>Johnson</name> suggests that an 
               appropriate approach to the archives of slavery (which are also remediated in digital forms) calls for an attentiveness 
               to the pain, discomfort, and messiness of data that encodes Black subjectivity piecemeal. Engaging with 
               <name>Equiano</name>'s presence substantively would require Google to center <name>Equiano</name>'s voice and seriously 
               consider the fears, wishes, and hopes that he writes about as a Black man and their contemporaneous implications.
            </p>
            <p>As the Black narrative contains that trace of violence and suffering which can haunt the white technocratic 
               imagination, the memo instead rushes the transition from man to cable so that the project named after a Black man can 
               become a celebratory feat of progressive multiculturalism and techno-utopianism. While Google's choice of name may have 
               sought to honor a historical figure's legacy, the naming politics described in <name>Equiano</name>'s narrative 
               complicate this choice. The title of <name>Equiano</name>'s narrative, <title rend="italic">The Interesting Narrative 
               of the Life of Olaudah Equiano, or Gustavus Vassa, the African</title> contains two different names and an 
               appellation (<quote rend="inline">the African</quote>). While <q>Olaudah Equiano</q> was the name given to 
               <name>Equiano</name> as a child in <name>Igbo</name>, he was also called <q>Michael</q> and <q>Jacob</q> as an enslaved 
               boy (by slave-owners) before his last slave owner forced him to accept the name <q>Gustavus Vassa</q> after a 
               sixteenth-century Swedish king <ptr target="#equiano1789a" loc="92"/>. In the narrative, <name>Equiano</name> describes 
               his resistance to this newest arbitrary name by stating that he <quote rend="inline">refused to answer to my new name, 
               which at first I did, [and] it gained me many a cuff, so at length I submitted, and was obliged to bear the present 
               name, by which I have been known ever since</quote> <ptr target="#equiano1789a" loc="96"/>. Denying enslaved Black 
               people the names that tied them to their families, communities, and cultures was another form of control exerted over 
               their lives that sought to remove those kinship connections that are crucial to identity and personhood.
            </p>
            <p>Slave-owners rewriting <name>Equiano</name>'s name sought to erase his past as a free human being and delegitimized 
               the cultural and spiritual traditions from which that name originated. <name>Hortense Spillers</name>, writing about 
               these politics of naming in <name>Equiano</name>'s narrative, observes that the <quote rend="inline">captivating party 
               not only <quote rend="inline">[earned]</quote> the right to dispose of the captive body, as it sees fit, but [gained], 
               consequently, the right to name and <quote rend="inline">name</quote> it</quote> <ptr target="#spillers1987" loc="69"/>. 
               The violent act of renaming enslaved Black people gestured, most importantly, to the power held by white slave-owners 
               in turning free Black people into slaves. The act of naming was intended to fix the position of Black subjects as 
               not-equal-to the white enslavers. The cruel irony of the name <q>Gustavus Vassa</q> was the contradiction between the 
               Swedish king, white, exalted, and commanding his fate, and the Black man, whose freedom was stolen. Despite the young 
               boy's understanding of the unfairness of this naming and the violence through which this name was forced on him, the 
               adult man would eventually retain the name <q>Gustavus Vassa</q>. As this was the same name on his manumission 
               paperwork (reproduced in the narrative for the reader to witness), taking on the name of <q>Gustavus Vassa</q> was 
               necessary for <name>Equiano</name> to protect himself during a time when slavery was still legal. As 
               <name>Lovejoy</name>'s work has traced, this name denoted <name>Equiano</name>'s legal, economic, and religious 
               identity in <name>England</name>, and this was also the name that his wife and children would eventually take 
               <ptr target="#lovejoy2012"/>.
            </p>
            <p>The narrative reintroduces, however, a name (<q>Olaudah Equiano</q>) that had been denied to him and which he did not 
               appear to use in his adult life. The narrative also reclaims <name>Equiano</name>'s African origins as a source of his 
               narrative authority and position himself as a credible speaker on the Middle Passage and the horrors of slavery. 
               <name>Equiano</name>'s abolitionist work later in life was predicated on this credibility that he had successfully 
               cultivated in <name>Britain</name>. The reclamation of his Igbo name and African origin asserted the failure of the 
               white slave-owners in their attempts at cleaving <name>Equiano</name> from his political personhood. Claiming both 
               names was then an expression of <name>Vassa</name>/<name>Equiano</name>'s commitment to the abolitionist movement, 
               demonstrating  the complex frames through which he understood his own identity and experiences. The name 
               <q>Olaudah Equiano</q> allowed the author a complex and plural self-fashioning beyond the restrictive juridical terms 
               under which he existed in <name>London</name> <ptr target="#jaros2012" loc="16"/>. Authoring his narrative under both 
               names subverted the racial hegemony by positioning <name>Vassa</name>/<name>Equiano</name> in a liminal space — 
               simultaneously drawing on the Western definitions of personhood that allowed him to live in <name>England</name> as a 
               free man while also indicating the racialized dimensions of the white juridical frameworks which applied to and 
               excluded Black people.
            </p>
            <p>These complexities and politics of naming show how names/naming in this sociopolitical context are tied to the 
               institution of slavery. Google's memorialization notably removes the dual identities of 
               <name>Vassa</name>/<name>Equiano</name> and selects the Africanist name as worthy of honoring. Complicating the name 
               of this undersea cable line is a starting point to bring into question other fundamental claims underpinning the 
               project, such as those of connectivity (taken up in the next section) and of reenvisioning infrastructural pathways 
               (addressed in the concluding section). As <name>Roopika Risam</name> observes, <quote rend="inline">engaging with the 
               politics of representation and look[ing] beyond representation to develop design practices that lay bare the politics 
               surrounding digital knowledge production</quote> are interconnected postcolonial approaches to digital humanities that 
               are required to disrupt (neo)colonialist dynamics proliferating in digital knowledge pathways 
               <ptr target="#risam2018"/>. Google does not need the Africanist connection for the commercial success of this cable 
               line. Nonetheless, <name>Equiano</name>'s name gives Google a tangible Africanist connection at a time of strategic 
               growth and planned development in the continent (such as new data centers), in a way that <q>Gustavus Vassa</q> 
               (a name of Swedish origin) cannot.
            </p>
            <p>Aside from these complicated politics of naming, the very location of <name>Equiano</name>'s birth itself has also 
               been a matter of public and scholarly scrutiny and cannot be easily assimilated into a corporate narrative. Immediately 
               after the publication of <name>Equiano</name>'s narrative, newspapers called into question the authenticity of his 
               claims to African nativity (specifically in the interior of the Bight of Biafra), and <name>Equiano</name> had to 
               repudiate these attacks as attempts to discredit his testimony <ptr target="#caretta1999" loc="97–98"/>. More recent 
               scholarship however has opened up the question of <name>Equiano</name>'s birthplace again. <name>S.E. Ogunde</name> 
               interprets the narrative as written in the vein of literary travel narratives and thus <quote rend="inline">to a large 
               extent fictional</quote> even when <name>Equiano</name> writes of his childhood before slavery 
               <ptr target="#ogunde1982" loc="31"/>. The authenticity of the work was further challenged by <name>Vincent 
               Caretta</name>'s work with baptismal records, which indicate that <name>Equiano</name> was born in South Carolina 
               <ptr target="#caretta1999" loc="102"/>. The contradictions between <name>Equiano</name>'s written account and this 
               archival evidence have been challenged, however, by <name>Lovejoy</name>, who argues that 
               <quote rend="inline">preponderant evidence derived from culture and context confirms his African birth</quote> and 
               offers a differing interpretation of the baptismal records <ptr target="#lovejoy2006" loc="339"/>.
            </p>
            <p>As this discussion indicates, <name>Equiano</name>'s name as well as birthplace are complicated and unsettled matters, 
               marked as they are by the disrupting force of slavery. In the corporate appropriation of <name>Equiano</name>'s 
               identity, such complications are smoothed out through elision. The irony of this purported honoring of 
               <name>Equiano</name>'s legacy under a capitalist project is further emphasized by the intertwined historical 
               developments of capitalism, colonialism, and slavery in the very time period of <name>Equiano</name>'s life. 
               <name>Olaudah Equiano</name>'s entry into the racial economy of slavery is preconditioned on his quantification as 
               cargo and property and his subjugation to white supremacist systems. And the conditions by which he obtains his 
               freedom and the qualifications placed on his status as a freed Black man reveal the continuing interpellation of Black 
               subjects as commodities in the colonial imagination. In 1765, <name>Robert King</name>, the last slave owner to purchase 
               <name>Equiano</name>, assures him that he will allow <name>Equiano</name> to eventually purchase his freedom if 
               <name>Equiano</name> can furnish him with <quote rend="inline">only the same price he gave for [him]</quote> 
               <ptr target="#equiano1789b" loc="12"/>. When the time comes to make good on his promise, <name>King</name> seems 
               confounded and begins <quote rend="inline">to recoil</quote> <ptr target="#equiano1789b" loc="12"/>. Just when it 
               seems that the slave owner will renege on his promise, the white captain of the ship that <name>Equiano</name> has been 
               sailing on intervenes and exhorts him to make good on his word.
            </p>
            <p>Entirely eliding the exploitative conditions of servitude, the captain frames the situation as such: 
               <quote rend="inline">You [the slaveowner] have laid your money out very well; you have received good interest for it 
               all this time, and here is now the principal at last</quote> <ptr target="#equiano1789b" loc="13"/>. 
               <name>Equiano</name>'s labor, the captain observes, has brought the slaveowner <quote rend="inline">more than a 
               hundred a-year</quote>, and he would continue to work for him as a freeman <ptr target="#equiano1789b" loc="13"/>. The 
               captain's unabashed quantification of <name>Equiano</name>'s worth reflects a premise that <name>Eric Williams</name> 
               forwards in his important 1944 book, <title rend="italic">Capitalism and Slavery</title>, that the triangular slave 
               trade <quote rend="inline">provided one of the main streams of that accumulation of capital in 
               <name>England</name></quote> and enabled the advancement of European empires through mercantile and later industrial 
               capitalism <ptr target="#williams1944" loc="52"/>. <name>Cedric Robinson</name> terms this foundational interlinking 
               of racism and capitalism as <quote rend="inline">racial capitalism</quote>, describing the inevitability of racialism 
               permeating <quote rend="inline">the social structures emergent from capitalism</quote> 
               <ptr target="#robinson1983" loc="2"/>. Slavery would be one of these social structures, and it became necessary for the 
               profits of plantation-owners, ship captains, and the extended British bourgeoisie. Given this history and 
               <name>Equiano</name>'s experiences, whether and how an IT corporation trading in the circuits of transnational 
               capitalism could honor <name>Equiano</name>'s legacy remains an open question and would certainly require more 
               introspection on the contemporary impacts of datafication in the African continent.
            </p>
            <p>Instead, Google's press release quickly delves instead into the technical capabilities of this new project to highlight 
               the techno-utopian bounties it will bring to the region to <quote rend="inline">serve</quote> and connect West African 
               countries to the Global North. In the context of a neoliberal corporation operating a cable project in the Atlantic, 
               the term <term>connectivity</term> holds multiple meanings as network connectivity, kinship bonds, and infrastructural 
               (digital) divides. First, internet connectivity can be framed as a technical and material assemblage encompassing 
               networks, devices, and data policies that enable internet access. Google's press release offers generous technical 
               description in reference to this understanding of connectivity. Yoked to this is the socio-political discourse of 
               <emph>connecting</emph> people in underserved locations to each other and to the developed world. This techno-utopian 
               ideal is often touted as the humanitarian mission of companies like Google and Facebook in the Global South 
               <ptr target="#thorat2020" loc="23"/>. The cable's promise to connect people in the region is fraught not just 
               contemporaneously (as I show later) but also historically, against the scene of the Transatlantic Slave Trade which 
               contextualizes the project. In her work on Black digital culture, <name>Anna Everett</name> begins by noting the 
               emergence of <quote rend="inline">paralinguistic and transnational communicative systems and networks of song, dance, 
               talking drums...</quote> as a means of overcoming the dislocation and fragmentation of ties during slavery and then 
               continues into the exploration of African diasporic consciousness through cyberspace.
            </p>
            <p>The loss of kinship ties, what <name>Hartman</name> calls the <quote rend="inline">negation of kinship</quote>, 
               began with enslaved people being stolen from their families and communities, forced into bondage with strangers, and 
               refused the possibility of a shared language <ptr target="#hartman1997" loc="84"/>. In his autobiography, 
               <name>Equiano</name> writes of his futile attempts to return to his family after being kidnapped but before being 
               forcibly moved to a new region. After he is transported to the Americas, he spends years looking for his sister (with 
               whom he had been kidnapped as a young boy but was separated from soon after). Lamenting his loss, he writes, 
               <quote rend="inline">by the horrors of that trade was I first torn away from all the tender <emph>connections</emph> 
               that were naturally dear to my heart</quote> (emphasis mine) <ptr target="#equiano1789a" loc="iii"/>. And after this 
               initial splintering, <name>Equiano</name> witnesses a second splintering of family bonds when he is finally transported 
               to <name>Barbados</name> and watches <quote rend="inline">parents…lose their children, brothers their sisters, husbands 
               their wives</quote> and decries the forced parting of family members as a <quote rend="inline">new refinement in 
               cruelty [which] adds fresh horror to the wretchedness of slavery</quote> <ptr target="#equiano1789a" loc="88"/>. This 
               exercise of racial discipline was another demonstration of power over Black people, in the intimate matrix of family 
               and community ties.
            </p>
            <p>The <quote rend="inline">tender connections</quote> which <name>Equiano</name> holds could not be acknowledged as such 
               by white slave-owners who perceived Black people in dehumanizing frames of existence <ptr target="#equiano1789a"/>. 
               Regulating kinship ties between enslaved Black people was intended to transform people with unique community and family 
               networks, social identities, and political aspirations into units knowable only in the master-slave dyad. To enable 
               networking raised the possibility of revolution, and allowing kinship ties between Black people undercut the property 
               claims that white slave-owners held over enslaved Black people <ptr target="#spillers1987" loc="75"/>. On a wider 
               geographic scale, the oceanic infrastructures and pathways (sea routes, ships, ports, ocean maps, and so on) which 
               enabled networking and trade for Europeans simultaneously enabled the enslavement of Black people. The capacity to 
               regulate connectivity and, above all, the dissemination of information and knowledge (in print and other media) was 
               also crucial to colonial empires seeking to thwart nascent rebellions and revolutions. Despite invoking 
               <name>Equiano</name>'s name and the promise of connectivity in the African continent, Google cannot address this 
               historical rupture of slavery or its contemporaneous repercussions. (The point, though, is not to ask any tech 
               corporation to redress that historical loss, but rather to pursue infrastructural projects grounded in liberatory 
               praxis — a point I return to in the concluding sections.)
            </p>
            <p>Further implicit in Google's cable project there is a parallel discourse on connectivity and infrastructure in the 
               contemporary postcolonial landscape of <name>Nigeria</name> — focusing not only on the digital divide but also on 
               state sovereignty after independence <ptr target="#chidozie_etal2015"/>. The press memo released by Google implies 
               that the new cable line will benefit African countries (specifically <name>Nigeria</name> and <name>South Africa</name>) 
               by adding to the existing network capacity in the region.<note><name>Lagos</name>, the main cable landing station in 
               <name>Nigeria</name>, has eight submarine cables that make landfall here, six of which are international cable lines 
               (ACE, Glo-1, MainOne, NCSCS, and SAT-3/WASC) connecting <name>Nigeria</name> and other African countries to 
               <name>Portugal</name> and other European capitals.</note> In a separate economic report released by Google, the new 
               cable line was positioned to increase internet speeds, reduce domestic Internet prices, and enable greater internet 
               penetration <ptr target="#africa_practice2021"/>. Economic impact assessments do add credence to these claims, as 
               low-cost internet access can drive economic growth, and the <quote rend="inline">expansion of the digital economy and 
               peripheral sectors</quote> could create new jobs in <name>Nigeria</name>, <name>South Africa</name>, and 
               <name>Namibia</name> <ptr target="#adepetun2022"/>. Since the initial press memo in 2019, the Equiano cable now makes 
               landfall in <name>Togo</name> and <name>Namibia</name> too. Such high expectations have been further fueled by Google's 
               commitment in 2021 to a billion-dollar investment across the African continent in start-ups, connectivity, and other 
               tech initiatives <ptr target="#pichai2021"/>.
            </p>
            <p>The veracity and extent of these claims can only be determined in the unfolding landscape of the tech scene in 
               <name>Nigeria</name> over the next five years. One tangible impact though was reported in August 2023 when the 
               Equiano cable absorbed internet traffic affected by simultaneous cable breaks in the West African Cable System (WACS) 
               and the South Atlantic 3 (SAT-3/WASC) due to undersea rock falls <ptr target="#schutters2023"/>. As undersea cable 
               repairs can take weeks, building redundancy into internet infrastructure (through multiple cable lines) has become an 
               economic and national security imperative. Cable projects are expensive investments and sole ownership may be 
               unaffordable for many postcolonial nations. Thus, the utilitarian advantages of the new cable line to postcolonial 
               nations and their citizens cannot be understated, especially if they enable the myriad material, social, and economic 
               benefits that attend internet access.
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, as <name>Yékú</name> and <name>Ojebode</name> observe, <quote rend="inline">digital subjects in 
               <name>Africa</name> are not mere consumers of digital modernity</quote>, and historical remediation can create 
               opportunities for conversations and knowledge sharing <ptr target="#yeku_etal2021" loc="22"/>. In their analysis of 
               Google's Equiano doodle for the Google search homepage, they trace both <quote rend="inline">a commitment to preserving 
               and circulating history</quote> as well as <quote rend="inline">the capitalist appropriations of historical 
               personalities and legacies from <name>Africa</name> and around the world</quote> <ptr target="#yeku_etal2021" loc="8"/>. 
               As a counterpoint, they focus on the reappropriation of Western tech platforms (for instance, the use of a Facebook 
               group to document, disseminate, and interpret Nigerian history). Such paradigms of resistance and subversion are 
               reminiscent of other forms of counter-use of Western technologies (such as radio and telegraph) during colonialism and 
               the independence period in many postcolonial nations. This was the case too in <name>Nigeria</name> where radio networks 
               and mobile cinemas were introduced under British colonization to advance the <q>modernization</q> of the colonized 
               populace. Yet, as <name>Larkin</name> points out in the Nigerian context, media technologies possess an agentive force, 
               what he terms <quote rend="inline">autonomous power</quote>, by which techno-social and material processes involved 
               in the implementation of technologies can shift their use and meaning beyond the planner's ideologies and intentions 
               <ptr target="#larkin2008" loc="4, 20"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Such socio-economic, historical, and material registers complicate the infrastructural politics of the Equiano cable. 
               The animating issue, though, is how the cable sustains the continued exploitation of African peoples despite its 
               productive or subversive uses and possibilities. Google's apparent humanitarian commitment to building network capacity 
               in the region is belied by the implications of this capacity for Google itself. Pointing out that terms like 
               <quote rend="inline">data mining</quote> and <quote rend="inline">data-rich continent</quote> are common in 
               <name>Africa</name>'s tech scene, <name>Abeha Birhane</name> observes that the techno-social 
               <quote rend="inline">discourse of <quote rend="inline">mining</quote> people for data is reminiscent of the colonizer 
               attitude that declares humans as raw material free for the taking</quote> <ptr target="#birhane2019"/>. By facilitating 
               internet access in postcolonial countries, tech companies create a two-fold opportunity for themselves. First, cable 
               lines create a direct pathway to deliver their content to postcolonial markets without relying on other cable providers 
               or paying transit fees to them. Given the vast reach of Google's digital empire, building their own cable lines to 
               deliver content is preferable to leasing on other cable lines. Second, the cable lines facilitate the datafication of 
               Black and brown people in postcolonial countries, enabling tech companies to harvest data that can be used or sold to 
               other companies <ptr target="#nyabola2018"/>. Thus, <name>Ricaurte</name> notes that <quote rend="inline">digital 
               inclusion under this paradigm (the data harvesting business model) means connecting those who are still outside the 
               scope of the data extraction system</quote> to bring them into the ambit of that system 
               <ptr target="#ricaurte2019" loc="7"/>. The large investments that companies like Google, Facebook, Amazon, and 
               Microsoft are making in undersea cable infrastructure anticipate these two ends.
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, Google's sole ownership of the Equiano cable line represents a compromising of infrastructural sovereignty 
               in the postcolonial nation-state in return for internet connectivity. In other words, the postcolonial nation has to 
               rely on private capital (or public-private partnerships in the case of the other cable lines coming ashore in 
               <name>Lagos</name>) for its citizens to have access to the internet, a service deemed necessary for the expression of 
               human rights and which governments worldwide have been charged with protecting by the United Nations 
               <ptr target="#unga2016"/>. Private ownership of digital infrastructure implies that neither postcolonial countries 
               nor their citizens can entirely determine governing and operating policies for a cable line that will connect them to 
               the internet. The material infrastructure of the internet has become a matter of state sovereignty, crucial to the 
               economy and security of modern nation-states. <name>Saskia Sassen</name>, writing about the internet and state 
               sovereignty, observes that the digital age has witnessed the creation of <quote rend="inline">systems that strengthen 
               the claims of certain actors (corporations and large multinational legal firms) and correspondingly weaken the position 
               of smaller players and states</quote> <ptr target="#sassen2006" loc="555"/>. States rely on internet infrastructure to 
               access global financial markets and for all major communications, ranging from matters of state security to citizens' 
               use of the internet.
            </p>
            <p>While <name>Nigeria</name> does maintain ownership stakes in other cable lines coming ashore in <name>Lagos</name>, and 
               the Equiano line will have to follow licensing codes with <name>Nigeria</name>, this arrangement nonetheless allows a 
               Western corporation use of public land in a postcolonial country to primarily advance its own capitalist interests. 
               <name>Turner</name> and <name>Nzimiro</name> have addressed, in other contexts in <name>Nigeria</name>, how foreign 
               multinational corporations can prioritize profit generation over national interests (economic, social, and political).
            </p>
            <p>Such privatizing of internet infrastructure is certainly not a new phenomenon, as private ownership or public-private 
               partnerships have historically enabled the construction of expensive cable projects. However, this tendency toward 
               privatization follows a distinct colonial pattern in which a Western entity controls infrastructural pathways in a 
               former colony. <name>Nigeria</name> or Nigerian corporations, for example, do not have a reciprocal cable line — one 
               which they solely control and which is connected to any country in the Western world. This notion might even be 
               unfathomable for national security interests by many countries in the Global North. This model of Western ownership 
               of key global and postcolonial infrastructure undermines the long arc of independence struggles which wrested control 
               away from colonial empires so that postcolonial countries could own, govern, distribute, and legislate their resources 
               and means of production.
            </p>
            <p>The history of Nigerian telecommunications illustrates these shifts in ownership and control of communications 
               infrastructure. <name>Orji</name>'s exhaustive work traces the origins of <name>Nigeria</name>'s telecommunication 
               industry to a submarine telegraph line established by Cable and Wireless Ltd, a British company, between 
               <name>Lagos</name> and <name>London</name> in 1886 to <quote rend="inline">link the colonial administration in 
               <name>Lagos</name> with the colonial office in <name>London</name></quote> <ptr target="#orji2018" loc="51"/>. The 
               colonial telegraph networks were a technology of empire developed as dictated by military and bureaucratic imperatives. 
               In 2000, <name>Nigeria</name>'s National Policy on Telecommunications looked back on this early development of 
               telecommunications and noted frankly that early networks were <quote rend="inline">geared towards discharging 
               administrative functions rather than the provision of socio-economic development of the country</quote>. Instead of 
               prioritizing the development of a robust (inter)national telecom network, colonial administration prioritized linking 
               <name>Lagos</name> to <name>London</name>. The decision to connect <name>Lagos</name> to <name>London</name> was also 
               a colonial objective rather than one determined by the Nigerian people or by national interests.
            </p>
            <p>After independence, the Nigerian government planned for rapid growth in telecommunications through a government-owned 
               and -operated telecom entity to redress this colonial approach. The challenges and limitations of such a government 
               monopoly in <name>Nigeria</name>, particularly corruption and mismanagement, have been discussed at length and cannot 
               be elided.<note>In much the same way, <ptr target="#gandy2006"/> and <ptr target="#smith2023"/> have shown how 
               inequalities cultivated in water infrastructures in <name>Nigeria</name> under colonial rule were sustained by the 
               postcolonial government as a way to consolidate state power.</note> A similar model of state-led infrastructural 
               development in the telecommunications sector was instituted in other postcolonial countries where the new government 
               was given the ambitious charge of managing a country recovering from colonial rule. Self-determination remained a 
               guiding principle in these nationalized infrastructures: in 1992, when the Nigerian government commercialized (rather 
               than privatized) its major telecom operator, NITEL, it sought to protect its national network from being owned by 
               external companies. With the reminders of colonialism still fresh in the national imagination, protecting this network 
               was considered tantamount to <quote rend="inline">protecting the country's economic sovereignty and national security 
               interests</quote> <ptr target="#orji2018" loc="58"/>. The major shift to government divestment and liberalization in 
               the telecommunications sector was only undertaken in the late 1990s under pressure by the IMF and World Bank through 
               the Structural Adjustment Programme (SAP), which has been criticized by scholars as undermining democratic processes 
               and creating overdependence on multinational corporations <ptr target="#umezurike2012"/> 
               <ptr target="#chidozie_etal2015"/>. I trace this history to point out that political aspirations of self-determination 
               and sovereignty informed public conversations around ownership and management of public services like telecommunications 
               after Nigerian independence.
            </p>
            <p>The final issue belying Google's claims to connectivity concerns the symbolic implications of naming the cable line 
               after <name>Equiano</name>. <name>Equiano</name>'s failed attempts to return home to his family after being kidnapped 
               or find his sister after being sold are a reminder that some losses of slavery cannot be remedied. When 
               <name>Equiano</name> is transported away from <name>Africa</name> in a ship bound for <name>Barbados</name> and finally 
               realizes that he will not be returning home, his despair at his new life and the conditions on board the ship leads him 
               to <quote rend="inline">[wish] for the last friend, death, to relieve [him]</quote> 
               <ptr target="#equiano1789b" loc="73–74"/>. Although he is fearful of the ocean, he writes that he contemplated death by 
               suicide and admits that <quote rend="inline">could I have got over the nettings, I would have jumped over the 
               side</quote> <ptr target="#equiano1789b" loc="73–74"/>. The young boy also witnesses other captives jumping off the 
               ship during that first voyage. While <name>Equiano</name> eventually pushes aside these thoughts, the Atlantic became 
               the resting ground for other enslaved people who died by suicide as well as those who were thrown overboard by ship 
               captains during the voyage. Later in his life, <name>Equiano</name> again comes close to drowning several times — in 
               the <name>Thames</name> and during turbulent storms in <name>Montserrat</name> — as an enslaved shipmate forced into 
               these travels. Without equating <name>Olaudah Equiano</name> (the Black man) and the Equiano cable line, thus 
               perpetuating his dehumanization, I wish to point out the uncanny recurrences and repetitions that emerge due to the 
               cable's symbolic naming and its resting grounds in the Atlantic.
            </p>
            <p>The Google cable returns <name>Equiano</name> home in the twenty-first century in a macabre mimicry of the fate of many 
               enslaved people who drowned in the <name>Atlantic Ocean</name>. The fiber optic infrastructure of the internet is laid 
               on the ocean floor: cable lines are unspooled and dropped off ships to rest on the ocean bed, only coming ashore at 
               cable landing stations (at <name>Lisbon</name>, <name>Lagos</name>, and <name>Cape Town</name>, in this case). The 
               scene of this ocean bed contains that invisible mark of slavery, the <quote rend="inline">bones heaped on the floor of 
               the Atlantic</quote>, and the Equiano cable will be layered over that grievous sediment in perpetuity 
               <ptr target="#hartman2008" loc="72"/>. <name>Christina Sharpe</name>'s poignant words on the 
               <quote rend="inline">unresolved unfolding</quote> of slavery in the present-day are valuable here, as she suggests that 
               <quote rend="inline">in the wake, the past that is not past reappears, always, to rupture the present</quote> 
               <ptr target="#sharpe2016" loc="14, 7"/>. Challenging the pastness of slavery, <name>Sharpe</name> writes about 
               anti-Black ideologies and projects as ongoing and continuing. The liquid temporality of the undersea cable — its 
               imbrication of slavery in the contemporary internet infrastructure through the scene of the Atlantic — raises that 
               haunting reminder of the scene of racial terror. In the hyper-compressed temporal pathway of the fiber optic cable, 
               where time-zones collapse and data is summoned near instantaneously, the pastness of slavery overlaps our current 
               moment as a doubled image.
            </p>
            <p>The undersea cable follows an iterative logic: the <quote rend="inline">state-of-the-art-technology</quote> assembled 
               by Google which appropriates the name of a Black man and follows on the pathway of racial capitalism constitutes yet 
               another instantiation of racial subjugation. In algorithmic terms, iteration represents an automated sequence of 
               instructions which are repeated in loops. Each end point generates a new loop (and can continue ad infinitum) until 
               an end result has been achieved. While the result of each loop can be different, the repetitive nature of the sequence 
               is enshrined in the very code of the system. The systemic values of white supremacy and racial capitalism, especially 
               the construction and perpetuation of racial hierarchies predicated on power and oppression in all facets of society, 
               remain consistent even as they are channeled in morphed and disparate forms. While not immutable, this system is 
               self-sustaining, and following its established codes is easier than divesting from it.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>The Struggle of Black Liberation Against Racial Capitalism</head>
            <p>Thus far, I have highlighted how <name>Equiano</name>'s life and experiences, evoked by Google's new project, illustrate 
               the extractive politics of racial capitalism that sustain colonialism and inform contemporary data regimes. 
               <name>Equiano</name>'s pursuit of freedom from white slave-owners within the limited scope of legal personhood in Western 
               law raises troubling concerns about the hedged possibility of liberation as long as the systems and operations of racial 
               capitalism continue to exist. In this section, I turn to the desire for freedom and self-determination which animates 
               <name>Equiano</name>'s narrative and the implications of that struggle in the context of infrastructural sovereignty 
               and data regimes. To focus solely on Black abjection and its techno-mediation is ultimately insufficient and follows the 
               limited scripts outlined by white supremacy (in its myriad forms) to curtail re-imagined possibilities for subversion, 
               resistance, and revolution.
            </p>
            <p>As much as the Atlantic is located as a site of racial terror and trauma, this waterway is also configured as a radical 
               wellspring of diasporic kinship and resistant subjectivities. I turn to <name>Olaudah Equiano</name> one last time to 
               uphold the irrepressible desire for freedom and self-determination threaded through his autobiographical account and 
               the relevance of this emancipatory envisioning in the context of data infrastructures. Despite the pervasive and 
               entrenched infrastructure of racial capitalism, envisioning possibilities for resisting and subverting this system are 
               important precisely due to the inequities channeled through it. In his preface to <title rend="italic">Freedom 
               Dreams</title>, Kelley points to Black collective imaginations and freedom dreams as radical forces that have enabled 
               Black intellectuals and activists to envision and pursue alternate futures beyond <quote rend="inline">immediate 
               ordeals</quote> <ptr target="#kelley2003"/>. <name>Equiano</name>'s desire to becomes his <quote rend="inline">own 
               master</quote> and exercise his will independently of white slave-owners allows him to look beyond the everyday 
               oppression of slavery meant to wear him down and stilt his life and imagination. Upon his manumission, 
               <name>Equiano</name> terms his new status as <quote rend="inline">freeman</quote> as the <quote rend="inline">most 
               desirable in the world</quote> <ptr target="#equiano1789b" loc="16"/>. He experiences freedom not only as a legal 
               condition but also as a feeling of <quote rend="inline">tumult, wildness, and delirium</quote> that possesses his soul 
               <ptr target="#equiano1789b" loc="16"/>. And after settling in <name>England</name> as a freed man, <name>Equiano</name> 
               takes up the abolitionist cause, pursuing a political struggle to free other Black people. The radical desires that 
               <name>Equiano</name> holds on to include the possibility of an enslaved Black person acquiring their freedom, to live 
               and thrive despite white supremacy, to resist and subvert white supremacist institutions, and finally to advocate on 
               behalf of other Black people.
            </p>
            <p>The narrative <name>Equiano</name> eventually wrote offers testimony to the nascent possibility of freedom even in the 
               face of entrenched systemic violence and the seemingly insurmountable odds of slavery. The possibilities imagined in 
               this text callback to what <name>Sharpe</name> terms as <quote rend="inline">Black being in the wake as a form of 
               consciousness</quote>. Sharpe places emphasis on the <quote rend="inline">to be</quote> and 
               <quote rend="inline">occupy…the infinitive</quote> in what it means to be in the wake of slavery and exist in its 
               afterlives <ptr target="#sharpe2016" loc="14"/>. After manumission, <name>Equiano</name> reclaims the waterways on 
               which he was forced to sail as a means of expressing his political consciousness and enacting his agency. Although he 
               does often take up seafaring because it offers a livelihood, he also expresses his keen interest in seeing the world. 
               In 1768, he writes about leaving <name>London</name> because he had <quote rend="inline">a very great desire to see 
               <name>Turkey</name>…and [was] determined to gratify it</quote> <ptr target="#equiano1789b" loc="86"/>. Later, in 1771, 
               he notes that <quote rend="inline">being still of a roving disposition, and desirous of seeing as many different parts 
               of the world as I could, I shipped myself soon after</quote> <ptr target="#equiano1789b" loc="96"/>. These instances 
               crafting <name>Equiano</name> as a <emph>desiring</emph> subject and his ensuing pursuit of these desires reveal a 
               radical act of personhood. To express desire and to seek personal fulfillment was to strike against the very subjugation 
               and denigration instituted by racial hierarchies. The words <quote rend="inline"><emph>I</emph> shipped 
               <emph>myself</emph></quote> contain a world of possibility — a subject hailing himself and choosing to enact his 
               agency. <name>Sharpe</name>'s infinitive <quote rend="inline">to be</quote> appears here in Equiano's determination 
               <quote rend="inline"><emph>to gratify</emph> it</quote>, which in turn shows readers a Black man living in the wake 
               of slavery and affirming his wishes, curiosities, and interests in the material, social, and spiritual world.
            </p>
            <p><name>Equiano</name>'s autobiography demands that its writer be seen fully, as <name>Olaudah Equiano</name> and 
               <name>Gustavo Vassa</name>, in the full scope of his subjectivity rather than through the dehumanized frames of 
               slavery. This is an important reminder that datafication, like the archives of slavery, produces Black subjectivity 
               knowable only in abjection. Datafication can only produce, after all, fragmentary evidence by disassembling the human 
               subject into <emph>bits</emph> of information sorted into geotags, shopping patterns, browsing histories, and such. 
               <name>Katherine McKittrick</name>, writing about archival violence, terms this the <quote rend="inline">mathematics 
               of unlivingness</quote>, the epistemic condition in which <quote rend="inline">blackness originates and emerges in 
               violence and death, [and] black futures are foreclosed by the dead and dying</quote> in histories of slavery and 
               colonialism <ptr target="#mckittrick2014" loc="18"/>. Black life in the limiting conditions of archival and 
               computational data becomes legible through suffering and death, bits and bytes, fractured and erased. 
               <name>Equiano</name>'s abolitionist work strived against the abjection of slavery, indicating a form of political 
               subjectivity constituted around kinship with other oppressed people. While Black people remain foremost on 
               <name>Equiano</name>'s mind, he also notes the mistreatment of indigenous communities and other enslaved groups during 
               his travels. After settling in <name>England</name> as a free man, <name>Equiano</name> takes up the abolitionist cause 
               to free other Black people. Notably, he was appointed to lead a government initiative to repatriate free Black people 
               to <name>Sierra Leone</name> in 1787 <ptr target="#equiano1789b" loc="243"/>. His staunch advocacy on behalf of the 
               group eventually leads to his dismissal as he points out the corruption of white agents in the initiative. 
               <name>Equiano</name>'s narrative offers an important reminder that radical anti-racist politics emerge not from 
               technological progress (as techno-utopian ideals might suggest) or from institutions and industries invested in racial 
               capitalism but from Black subjects seeking to fashion their own futures.
            </p>
            <p>While <name>Equiano</name>'s autobiographical account cannot offer a liberatory roadmap for resisting data regimes 
               today, it testifies to the capacity of Black radical imagination to pursue pathways that had been declared foreclosed 
               under the harshest conditions of slavery. In invoking <name>Equiano</name>, Google first entangles slavery and 
               colonialism in the modern internet infrastructure. But this ironic invocation also channels historical subtexts of 
               resistance during slavery and colonialism, acts of transgression and subversion against systemic oppression, and the 
               capacity of the radical Black imagination to look beyond entrenched systemic logics. In the terse constellation of 
               adjectives and verbs referring to <name>Olaudah Equiano</name>, the press memo only notes that Google's undersea 
               cables <emph>carry</emph> the names of historical luminaries. To carry <name>Equiano</name>'s name is to accept a 
               responsibility to transmit his legacy across space and time. Equally importantly, to carry <name>Equiano</name>'s 
               legacy necessitates a commensurate abolitionary praxis of Black liberation to which <name>Equiano</name> himself was 
               dedicated. Radical desires and the tumultuous joy of freedom too are invoked by <name>Olaudah Equiano</name>'s name, 
               representing an animating force that can guide our contemporary explorations for equitable infrastructures.
            </p>
            <p>In closing, I would like to reiterate that the need for robust internet infrastructures is likely to continue 
               increasing in postcolonial countries along with increases in data traffic, AI technologies, and ubiquitous computing 
               worldwide. Despite their appearance as entrenched and pervasive, infrastructures are not totalitarian and are capable 
               of being reshaped and reimagined. To heed the call of <name>Equiano</name>'s echoing voice is to ask what an 
               abolitionist and decolonial praxis towards the digital divide looks like. It is necessary, for a start, for 
               infrastructural projects to be shaped at the ground level, particularly with the leadership of Black, brown, and 
               indigenous peoples whose lives will be impacted by new cable projects in the Global South. <name>Equiano</name>'s quest 
               for freedom was accomplished only through bold action, an unwavering determination, and visionary planning. It is 
               imperative that we divest internet infrastructures from the racial genealogies they emerge from, as we are likely to see 
               a further concentration of infrastructural pathways controlled by Western capital. What would internet infrastructural 
               pathways that support Black liberation and enable Black diasporic connections look like? How would governance models for 
               these internet infrastructures shift if they were truly grounded in notions of kinship and shared futurity rather than 
               capitalist profiteering? How should the material infrastructure of the internet in the Black Atlantic account for the 
               historical sediment it rests upon, while sustaining life-affirming projects for the future? These unanswered questions 
               about possible futures of infrastructural development are brought to the fore by engaging with <name>Equiano</name>'s 
               voice.
            </p>
            <p>This article's focus on <name>Equiano</name>'s historically situated voice and literary approach can be expanded in 
               future research to incorporate archival texts on the development of the undersea cable network in West 
               <name>Africa</name> as well as more current sites and conversations of memory-making related to <name>Equiano</name>. 
               There is an urgent need too for additional research on the socioeconomic impact of the Equiano cable in 
               <name>Nigeria</name> and, more broadly, other new cable projects in the African continent. Facebook has announced its 
               own undersea cable project, and there are various extant internet infrastructure projects (ranging from undersea cables 
               to domestic 5G infrastructure) undertaken within the ambit of China's Belt and Road Initiative. Western capital 
               has certainly played a key role in the development of the undersea cable infrastructure, but other foreign powers now 
               have vested interests in this arena too. Mapping the scope of such infrastructure interventions requires attentiveness 
               to the competing political, economic, and cultural ideologies driving these various projects and how they are 
               received on the ground by state and corporate entities as well as public citizens.
            </p>
        </div>
      </body>
      <back>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="adepetun2022" label="Adepetun 2022">Adepetun, A. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Google's Equiano submarine 
             cable begins operation in Nigeria by December</title>, <title rend="italic">The Guardian</title>, 6 October. 
             Available at: 
             <ref target="https://guardian.ng/technology/googles-equiano-submarine-cable-begins-operation-in-nigeria-by-december/">https://guardian.ng/technology/googles-equiano-submarine-cable-begins-operation-in-nigeria-by-december/</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="anand_etal2018" label="Anand, Gupta, and Appel 2018">Anand, N., Gupta, A., and Appel, H. (eds.) (2018) 
             <title rend="italic">The promise of infrastructure</title>. Durham, NC: Duke University Press. 
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ajayi2002" label="Ajayi 2002">Ajayi G. (2002) <title rend="italic">African response to communication 
             technology revolution</title>. African Technology Policy Studies Network. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://atpsnet.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/special_paper_series_8.pdf">https://atpsnet.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/special_paper_series_8.pdf</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="africa_practice2021" label="Africa Practice 2021">Africa Practice (2021) <title rend="italic">Equiano subsea 
             cable: Regional economic impact assessment</title>, 6 October. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://africapractice.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Equiano-Regional-Economic-Impact-Assessment-6-October-2021.pdf">https://africapractice.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Equiano-Regional-Economic-Impact-Assessment-6-October-2021.pdf</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="benjamin2019" label="Benjamin 2019">Benjamin, R. (2019) <title rend="italic">Race after technology</title>. 
             Cambridge, UK: Polity.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="birhane2019" label="Birhane 2019">Birhane, A. (2019) <title rend="quotes">The algorithmic colonization of 
             Africa</title>, <title rend="italic">Real Life Magazine</title>, 18 July. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://reallifemag.com/the-algorithmic-colonization-of-africa/">https://reallifemag.com/the-algorithmic-colonization-of-africa/</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="caretta1999" label="Caretta 1999">Caretta, V. (1999) <title rend="quotes">Olaudah Equiano or Gustavus Vassa? 
             New light on an eighteenth-century question of identity</title>, <title rend="italic">Slavery and Abolition</title>, 
             20(3), pp. 96-105. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01440399908575287">https://doi.org/10.1080/01440399908575287</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="couldry_etal2019" label="Couldry and Mejias 2019">Couldry, N. and Mejias, U.A. (2019) <title rend="italic">The 
             costs of connection: How data is colonizing human life and appropriating it for capitalism</title>. Stanford, CA: Stanford 
             University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="chidozie_etal2015" label="Chidozie, Odunayo, and Olutosin 2015">Chidozie, F.C., Odunayo, L.P., and Olutosin, 
             A.O. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Deregulation of the Nigerian telecommunication sector: Interrogating the nexus between 
             imperialism and development</title>, <title rend="italic">Academic Journal of Interdisciplinary Studies</title>, 4(1), 
             pp. 173-184. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.richtmann.org/journal/index.php/ajis/article/view/5968">https://www.richtmann.org/journal/index.php/ajis/article/view/5968</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="duarte2017" label="Duarte 2017">Duarte, M. (2017) <title rend="italic">Network sovereignty: Building the 
             internet Across Indian country</title>. Seattle, WA: University of Washington Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="equiano1789a" label="Equiano 1789a">Equiano, O. (1789a) <title rend="italic">The interesting narrative of the 
             life of Olaudah Equiano, or Gustavus Vassa, the African</title>, vol. I. Documenting the American South. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://docsouth.unc.edu/neh/equiano1/equiano1.html">https://docsouth.unc.edu/neh/equiano1/equiano1.html</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="equiano1789b" label="Equiano 1789b">Equiano, O. (1789b) <title rend="italic">The interesting narrative of the 
             life of Olaudah Equiano, or Gustavus Vassa, the African</title>, vol. II. Documenting the American South. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://docsouth.unc.edu/neh/equiano2/menu.html">https://docsouth.unc.edu/neh/equiano2/menu.html</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="everett2009" label="Everett 2009">Everett A. (2009) <title rend="italic">Digital diasporas: A race for 
             cyberspace</title>. New York: SUNY Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="francois_etal2019" label="Francois, Chris, and Stowell 2019">Francois, M., Chris, G., and Stowell, J. 
             (2019) <title rend="quotes">Introducing Equiano, A subsea cable from Portugal to South Africa</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Google Cloud Blog</title>, 28 June. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/infrastructure/introducing-equiano-a-subsea-cable-from-portugal-to-south-africa">https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/infrastructure/introducing-equiano-a-subsea-cable-from-portugal-to-south-africa</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gandy2006" label="Gandy 2006">Gandy, M. (2006) <title rend="quotes">Planning, anti-planning, and the 
             infrastructure crisis facing metropolitan Lagos</title>, <title rend="italic">Urban Studies</title>, 43(2), pp. 371-396. 
             Available at: 
             <ref target="http://doi.org/10.1080/00420980500406751">http://doi.org/10.1080/00420980500406751</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gallon2016" label="Gallon 2016">Gallon, K. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Making a case for the Black digital 
             humanities</title>, in Gold, M.K. and Klein, L.F. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Debates in the digital humanities 
             2016</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled/section/fa10e2e1-0c3d-4519-a958-d823aac989eb#ch04">https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled/section/fa10e2e1-0c3d-4519-a958-d823aac989eb#ch04</ref>.
           </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hartman1997" label="Hartman 1997">Hartman, S. (1997) <title rend="italic">Scenes of subjection</title>. 
             New York: Oxford University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hartman2008" label="Hartman 2008">Hartman, S. (2008) <title rend="italic">Lose your mother</title>. Farrar, 
             NY: Straus and Giroux.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="jaros2012" label="Jaros 2012">Jaros, P. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Good names: Olaudah Equiano or 
             Gustavus Vassa</title>, <title rend="italic">The Eighteenth Century</title>, 54(1), pp. 1-22. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/23365023">https://www.jstor.org/stable/23365023</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="johnson2018" label="Johnson 2018">Johnson, J.M. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Markup bodies: Black [life] 
             studies and slavery [death] studies at the digital crossroads</title>, <title rend="italic">Social Text</title>, 
             36(4), pp. 57-79. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1215/01642472-7145658">https://doi.org/10.1215/01642472-7145658</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kelley2003" label="Kelley 2003">Kelley, R.D.G. (2003) <title rend="italic">Freedom dreams: The Black radical 
             imagination</title>. Boston, MA: Beacon Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="larkin2008" label="Larkin 2008">Larkin, B. (2008) <title rend="italic">Signal and noise: Media, infrastructure, 
             and urban culture in Nigeria</title>. Durham, NC: Duke University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lovejoy2006" label="Lovejoy 2006">Lovejoy, P.E. (2006) <title rend="quotes">Autobiography and memory: 
             Gustavus Vassa, alias Olaudah Equiano, the African</title>, <title rend="italic">Slavery and Abolition</title>, 27(3), 
             pp. 317-347. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01440390601014302">https://doi.org/10.1080/01440390601014302</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lovejoy2012" label="Lovejoy 2012">Lovejoy, P.E. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Olaudah Equiano or Gustavus Vassa: 
             What's in a name?</title>, <title rend="italic">Atlantic Studies: Global Currents</title>, 9(2), pp. 165-184. 
             <ref target="http://doi.org/10.1080/14788810.2012.664957">http://doi.org/10.1080/14788810.2012.664957</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mcglotten2016" label="McGlotten 2016">McGlotten, S. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Black data</title>, in 
             Johnson, P. (ed.) <title rend="italic">No tea, no shade: New writings in Black queer studies</title>. Durham, NC: 
             Duke University Press, pp. 262-286.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mckittrick2014" label="McKittrick 2014">McKittrick, K. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Mathematics Black 
             life</title>, <title rend="italic">The Black Scholar</title>, 44(2), pp. 16-28. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5816/blackscholar.44.2.0016">https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5816/blackscholar.44.2.0016</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="nyabola2018" label="Nyabola 2018">Nyabola, N. (2018) <title rend="italic">Digital democracy, analogue 
             politics: How the internet era is transforming politics in Kenya</title>. London: Zed Books.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="nzimiro1975" label="Nzimiro 1975">Nzimiro, I. (1975) <title rend="quotes">The political and social 
             implications of multinational corporations in Nigeria</title>, in Widstrand, C. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Multinational 
             firms in Africa</title>. Uppsala, Sweden: SIAS.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ogunde1982" label="Ogunde 1982">Ogunde, S.E. (1982) <title rend="quotes">Facts into fiction: Equiano's 
             narrative reconsidered</title>, <title rend="italic">Research in African Literatures</title>, 13(1), pp. 31-43. 
             Available at: <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/4618069">https://www.jstor.org/stable/4618069</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="orji2018" label="Orji 2018">Orji, U.J. (2018) <title rend="italic">Telecommunications law and regulation in 
             Nigeria</title>. Newcastle upon Tyne, UK: Cambridge Scholars Publishing.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pichai2021" label="Pichai 2021">Pichai, S. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Our $1 billion investment in Africa's 
             digital transformation</title>, <title rend="italic">Google Blog</title>, 6 October. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://blog.google/around-the-globe/google-africa/google-for-africa/">https://blog.google/around-the-globe/google-africa/google-for-africa/</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ricaurte2019" label="Ricaurte 2019">Ricaurte, P. (2019) <title rend="quotes">Data epistemologies, coloniality 
             of power, and resistance</title>, <title rend="italic">Television &amp; New Media</title>, 20(4), pp. 350-365. 
             Available at: 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1527476419831640">https://doi.org/10.1177/1527476419831640</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="risam2018" label="Risam 2018">Risam, R. (2018) <title rend="italic">New digital worlds: Postcolonial digital 
             humanities in theory, praxis, and pedagogy</title>. Evanston, IL: Northwestern University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="robinson1983" label="Robinson 1983">Robinson, C. (1983) <title rend="italic">Black Marxism: The making of the 
             Black radical tradition</title>. London: Zed Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="sassen2006" label="Sassen 2006">Sassen, S. (2006) <title rend="quotes">Regulating immigration in a global 
             age: A new policy landscape</title>, <title rend="italic">parallax</title>, 11(1), pp. 35-45. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1049240">https://www.jstor.org/stable/1049240</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="schutters2023" label="Schutters 2023">Schutters, L. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Equiano cable keeps Africa 
             connected during undersea faults</title>, <title rend="italic">Bizcommunity</title>, 9 August. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.bizcommunity.com/Article/196/664/240858.html">https://www.bizcommunity.com/Article/196/664/240858.html</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="sharpe2016" label="Sharpe 2016">Sharpe, C. (2016) <title rend="italic">In the wake: On Blackness and 
             being</title>. Durham, NC: Duke University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="smith2023" label="Smith 2023">Smith, D.J. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Water entrepreneurs, infrastructural 
             citizenship, and stat power in Nigeria</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Business Anthropology</title>, 12(2), 
             pp. 183-201. 
             <ref target="http://doi.org/10.22439/jba.v12i2.7060">http://doi.org/10.22439/jba.v12i2.7060</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="spillers1987" label="Spillers 1987">Spillers, H. (1987) <title rend="quotes">“Mama's baby, papa's maybe: An 
             American grammar book</title>, <title rend="italic">Diacritics</title>, 17(2), pp. 64-81. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/464747">https://www.jstor.org/stable/464747</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="starosielski2015" label="Starosielski 2015">Starosielski, N. (2015) <title rend="italic">The undersea 
             network</title>. Durham, NC: Duke University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="thorat2020" label="Thorat 2020">Thorat, D. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Digital infrastructures and 
             technoutopian fantasies: The colonial roots of technology aid in the Global South</title>, in Dodd, M. and Kalra, N. 
             (eds.) <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities in India</title>. New Delhi, India: Routledge, pp. 17-29.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="turner1976" label="Turner 1976">Turner, T. (1976) <title rend="quotes">Multinational corporations and 
             instability of the Nigerian state</title>, <title rend="italic">Review of African Political Economy</title>, 3(5), pp. 
             63-79. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/03056248108703278">https://doi.org/10.1080/03056248108703278</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="umezurike2012" label="Umezurike 2012">Umezurike, C. (2012) <title rend="italic">Globalization, economic 
             reforms and democracy in Nigeria</title>, <title rend="italic">Africa Development</title>, 37(2), pp. 25-61. 
             Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/afrdevafrdev.37.2.25">https://www.jstor.org/stable/afrdevafrdev.37.2.25</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="unga2016" label="United Nations General Assembly 2016">United Nations General Assembly (2016) 
             <title rend="italic">The promotion, protection and enjoyment of human rights on the internet</title>, 27 June. 
             Available at: 
             <ref target="https://digitallibrary.un.org/record/845728?ln=en">https://digitallibrary.un.org/record/845728?ln=en</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="williams1944" label="Williams 1944">Williams, E. (1944) <title rend="italic">Slavery and capitalism</title>. 
             Chapel Hill, NC: University of North Carolina Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="yeku_etal2021" label="Yékú and Ojebode 2021">Yékú, J. and Ojebode, A. (2021) <title rend="quotes">From 
             Google doodles to Facebook: Nostalgia and visual reconstructions of the past in Nigeria</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">African Studies Review</title>, 64(3), pp. 498-522. 
             <ref target="http://doi.org/10.1017/asr.2020.118">http://doi.org/10.1017/asr.2020.118</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="zimmer2018" label="Zimmer 2018">Zimmer, J. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Google owns 63,605 miles and 8.5% of 
             submarine cables worldwide</title>, <title rend="italic">Broadband Now</title>, 12 September. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://broadbandnow.com/report/google-content-providers-submarine-cable-ownership">https://broadbandnow.com/report/google-content-providers-submarine-cable-ownership</ref>.
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
