<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
        xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
        xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Adapting a Research Tool for
                                        Teaching in a Post-Pandemic World: Textual Communities and
                                        Critical Digital Pedagogy in the Context of a Comprehensive
                                        Liberal Arts Research University </title>
                                <dhq:authorInfo>
                                        <dhq:author_name>Barbara <dhq:family>Bordalejo</dhq:family>
                                        </dhq:author_name>
                                        <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8255-0265 </idno>
                                        <dhq:affiliation>University of Lethbridge</dhq:affiliation>
                                        <email>barbara.bordalejo@uleth.ca</email>
                                        <dhq:bio>
                                                <p>Barbara Bordalejo is a textual scholar, editor,
                                                  and digital humanist whose work spans digital
                                                  editing, manuscript studies, and the politics of
                                                  knowledge production in the humanities. She holds
                                                  PhDs from New York University and De Montfort
                                                  University, and she is Director of the Canterbury
                                                  Tales Project and Publishing Director at Scholarly
                                                  Digital Editions. Currently an Adjunct Professor
                                                  at the University of Lethbridge, she has
                                                  previously held academic appointments in Canada,
                                                  the UK, Belgium, and Italy. Her research interests
                                                  include AI and data ethics in higher education,
                                                  the application of bioinformatics to textual
                                                  criticism, and intersectional feminist approaches
                                                  to scholarly editing. Barbara serves as President
                                                  of the Canadian Society for Digital Humanities and
                                                  sits on the editorial board of Digital Scholarship
                                                  in the Humanities. Her recent publications explore
                                                  AI-assisted writing, digital pedagogy, and
                                                  critical approaches to the unessay.</p>
                                        </dhq:bio>
                                </dhq:authorInfo>
                                <dhq:authorInfo>
                                        <dhq:author_name>Davide <dhq:family>Pafumi</dhq:family>
                                        </dhq:author_name>
                                        <idno type="ORCID"
                                                >https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1113-187X</idno>
                                        <dhq:affiliation>University of Lethbridge</dhq:affiliation>
                                        <email>davide.pafumi@uleth.ca</email>
                                        <dhq:bio>
                                                <p>Davide Pafumi is a doctoral candidate at the
                                                  University of Lethbridge specializing in medieval
                                                  studies and Digital Humanities. His research
                                                  focuses on medieval literature, historical
                                                  linguistics, paleography, and computational
                                                  approaches to address complex Humanities research
                                                  questions. He serves as a research assistant to
                                                  the “Canterbury Tales Project,” where he works on
                                                  the transcription, editing, and encoding of the 88
                                                  pre-modern manuscripts in Chaucer’s Canterbury
                                                  Tales textual tradition. Davide has received
                                                  several prestigious awards in the field of
                                                  medieval studies, including the 2023
                                                  Benton-Mahoney Award from the Medieval Association
                                                  of the Pacific and the 2025 Founders Grant from
                                                  the International Courtly Literature Society
                                                  (North American Branch). In 2021, he graduated
                                                  with Honours from the University of Padua, earning
                                                  MA in English and German Linguistics and
                                                  Literatures.</p>
                                        </dhq:bio>
                                </dhq:authorInfo>
                                <dhq:authorInfo>
                                        <dhq:author_name>Morgan S. <dhq:family>Pearce</dhq:family>
                                        </dhq:author_name>
                                        <idno type="ORCID"
                                                >https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1768-4501</idno>
                                        <dhq:affiliation>University of Lethbridge</dhq:affiliation>
                                        <email>morgan.pearce@uleth.ca</email>
                                        <dhq:bio>
                                                <p>Morgan Slayde Pearce is a master’s student at the
                                                  University of Lethbridge and a member of the
                                                  Humanities Innovation Lab. She is a research
                                                  assistant for the Lethbridge Journal Incubator and
                                                  the “Canterbury Tales Project.” Her thesis
                                                  combines medieval literary studies and game
                                                  studies to look at how non-linear narratives in
                                                  various genres and media are used to convey the
                                                  experience of depression and loss, specifically
                                                  through the use of the symbol of the labyrinth.
                                                  Her research combines studies of the history of
                                                  the book, medieval literature, game studies, and
                                                  digital humanities. Morgan received the Alberta
                                                  Graduate Excellence Scholarship in 2023 and the
                                                  Benton-Mahoney Award from the Medieval Association
                                                  of the Pacific in 2024. She graduated from the
                                                  University of Lethbridge with her BA in English in
                                                  2021 with Great Distinction.</p>
                                        </dhq:bio>
                                </dhq:authorInfo>
                                <dhq:authorInfo>
                                        <dhq:author_name>Daniel Paul
                                                  <dhq:family>O’Donnell</dhq:family>
                                        </dhq:author_name>
                                        <idno type="ORCID"
                                                >https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0127-4893</idno>
                                        <dhq:affiliation>University of Lethbridge</dhq:affiliation>
                                        <email>daniel.odonnell@uleth.ca</email>
                                        <dhq:bio>
                                                <p>Daniel Paul O’Donnell is a Professor of English
                                                  and Department Chair at the University of
                                                  Lethbridge. His research and teaching focuses on
                                                  Digital Humanities, the formation and practice of
                                                  the humanities, Open Science, and early medieval
                                                  philology and textual criticism. He is the author
                                                  of Cædmon’s Hymn, A Multimedia Archive, Edition,
                                                  and Study (Medieval Academy of America/SEENET,
                                                  2005, and a co-author of Reading Peer Review: PLOS
                                                  ONE and Institutional Change in Academia
                                                  (Cambridge University Press, 2020). During the
                                                  pandemic, he was PI on a Sloan-funded project
                                                  examining how Open Science instruction was
                                                  adapting to an online environment.</p>
                                        </dhq:bio>
                                </dhq:authorInfo>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                                <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
                                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000787</idno>
                                <idno type="volume"
                                        >019</idno>
                                <idno type="issue"
                                        >2</idno>
                                <date when="2025-06-04"> 4 June 20225</date>
                                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                                        <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
                                        <cc:License
                                                rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"
                                        />
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <p>This is the source</p>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                                        <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                                                target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                                                >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                                        <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
                                        <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                                                target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                                                >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <langUsage>
                                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                                <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
                        </langUsage>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                                        <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
                                        <!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
                                        <term corresp="#pedagogy"/>
                                        <term corresp="#tools"/>
                                        <term corresp="#transcription"/>
                                        <term corresp="#manuscripts"/>
                                        <term corresp="#infrastructure"/>
                                </keywords>
                                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                                        <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
                                        <list type="simple">
                                                <item/>
                                        </list>
                                </keywords>
                                <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
                                        <list type="simple">
                                                <item/>
                                        </list>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
                                        target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000787/000787.xml"
                                        >GitHub </ref>
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
                <front>
                        <dhq:abstract>
                                <p>This article examines the pedagogical adaptation of Textual
                                        Communities, a digital tool originally developed for
                                        collaborative research in textual scholarship, to teach
                                        paleography at the undergraduate level within a liberal arts
                                        context. Prompted by the exigencies of remote learning
                                        during the COVID-19 pandemic and the broader framework of
                                        critical digital pedagogy, the course-design reimagined the
                                        tool’s primary research-focused function — edition-making —
                                        as a dynamic teaching and learning environment emphasizing
                                        transcription, engagement, and student autonomy. The article
                                        presents a specific example of the use of a digital tool in
                                        teaching paleography, detailing its purpose and impact on
                                        student learning and engagement. The article offers a
                                        concrete case study of hybrid- and flexible-by-design
                                        pedagogy, showing the value of using scholarly digital tools
                                        in undergraduate settings.</p>
                        </dhq:abstract>
                        <dhq:teaser>
                                <p>How can digital tools originally developed for research reshape
                                        undergraduate teaching? The authors adapt the Textual
                                        Communities research-tool for using it in a paleography
                                        class, and reflect on critical digital pedagogy, hybrid
                                        learning environments, and the transformative potential of
                                        scholarly infrastructure in the classroom.</p>
                        </dhq:teaser>
                </front>
                <body>
                        <div>
                                <head>Introduction</head>
                                <p>The changes experienced by the higher education community
                                        following the outbreak of COVID-19 remain unprecedented in
                                        light of its impact on different spheres of collective life.
                                        Paraphrasing Marcel Mauss, the pandemic can be viewed as a
                                                <quote rend="inline">total social fact</quote>
                                        <ptr target="#mauss_1966" loc="76–77"/>, playing a pivotal
                                        role in social change due to its significant <quote
                                                rend="inline">implications throughout
                                                society</quote>
                                        <ptr target="#edgar_and_sedgwick_1999" loc="64"/>. Against
                                        this backdrop, this paper addresses the spheres of teaching
                                        digital humanities, specifically in the aftermath of the
                                        pandemic. </p>
                                <p>In 2023, the departments of English and History at the University
                                        of Lethbridge approved an undergraduate advanced course,
                                        under the leadership of Barbara Bordalejo, for English and
                                        History students on paleography of the British Isles
                                        covering texts in Latin, Old French, Old and Middle English
                                        produced between 800 and 1500. When designing the course,
                                        the authors of this paper implemented Textual Communities
                                                <ptr target="#bordalejo_and_robinson_2016"/>, a
                                        collaborative online research system that allows
                                        participants to work asynchronously, which we adapted for
                                        pedagogical purposes. Because of Bordalejo’s experience
                                        during the Fall of 2021, when a surge of the COVID Delta
                                        variant forced all academic staff to pivot to online
                                        teaching, Textual Communities was as much about its
                                        pedagogical promise as its potential use as a distance
                                        learning tool. In this paper, we draw from our practical
                                        experience with the platform and extrapolate a systematic
                                        discussion of the implications of the adaptation and use of
                                        a research tool for pedagogical purposes. One of these
                                        implications is undoubtedly how the lockdown forced
                                        academics and teachers to repurpose existing tools developed
                                        for different ends, such as Textual Communities, with the
                                        aim of easily switching from in-person to remote if and when
                                        required. The students would have the opportunity to work
                                        from home or anywhere else while continuing to receive
                                        constant feedback on their work from the instructors. But
                                        implication of allowing students access to research tools —
                                        and allowing them some of the flexibility we enjoy as
                                        researchers ourselves — is a form of critical pedagogy.</p>
                                <p>In the wake of COVID, a considerable amount of literature emerged
                                        on implementing digital technology in higher educational
                                        contexts <ptr target="#akbar_2016"/>
                                        <ptr target="#lai_2011"/>. These studies centred around the
                                        consequences of the pandemic on teaching and learning at
                                        different levels, highlighting the drawbacks and
                                        opportunities of remote teaching and learning in this
                                        context (e.g. <ptr target="#murphy_2020"/>; <ptr
                                                target="#hofer_et_al_2021"/>); they also theorized
                                        ways in which to normalize e-Learning Pedagogies for the
                                        near (post-pandemic) future <ptr
                                                target="#barrett-fox_et_al_2020"/>
                                        <ptr target="#careaga-butter_et_al_2020"/>. In this paper,
                                        we propose a third topic: looking at the implications these
                                        techniques and tools have for our understanding of what we
                                        ask our students to do. This study presents our experiences
                                        adapting Textual Communities to become a pedagogical aid in
                                        the paleography classroom. Our work serves as a practical
                                        example of addressing the aftermath of the pandemic. It
                                        provides us with both a sound teaching environment and an
                                        effective way to transition to online teaching quickly,
                                        should the circumstances require it. By using tools in this
                                        flexible manner, we ensure that our students are safeguarded
                                        should extreme circumstances arise, whether personal or
                                        affecting the entire community. We share this experience as
                                        a generalizable example and a reproducible strategy for
                                        teaching paleography and the history of handwriting.
                                        Moreover, the current work presents different perspectives
                                        (those of the instructors, the teaching assistants, and the
                                        students) and experiences to assess the importance of this
                                        course, considering its significance in the post-COVID-19
                                        era. The paper presents an overview of the existing
                                        scholarship on emergency e-learning, provided along with the
                                        most recent developments of the discourse surrounding
                                        digital pedagogy and specifically its particular inflection,
                                        i.e., critical digital pedagogy <ptr target="#kim_2018"/>
                                        <ptr target="#stommel_et_al_2020a"/>, whose principles have
                                        served as a methodology for this work. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                                <head>Methods of teaching paleography</head>
                                <p>Paleography is the study of historical handwriting, traditionally
                                        focused on the medieval period. At institutions with strong
                                        material resources, such as a rare books library with
                                        manuscript collections, this class can be taught in
                                        conjunction with other aspects of manuscript culture.
                                        Students might be asked to identify scripts or read directly
                                        from manuscript materials under the direction of a professor
                                        or teaching assistant. Tests might include reading or
                                        copying from original manuscript materials. The breadth of
                                        the course is, to a degree in such cases, determined by
                                        available materials. Institutions with extensive collections
                                        of manuscripts or that are located near repositories with
                                        large holdings can introduce students to a wide range of
                                        scripts, languages, texts, and codicological forms. </p>
                                <p>Newer institutions and institutions with more limited funding or
                                        holdings can offer a simulacrum of such a course using the
                                        increasingly large number of high-quality facsimiles
                                        available from manuscript libraries and other cultural
                                        institutions. Access to freely available digital images
                                        enables a pedagogical model in which students read from
                                        these images during class, while the instructor clarifies
                                        particularly challenging sections. This approach reflects a
                                        practice that has served many generations of paleographers
                                        well. Whether a university has access to the original
                                        artifacts or facsimiles, however, smaller classes have
                                        traditionally been a sine qua non of successful instruction.
                                        While lectures are common in such courses, a very important
                                        part remains hands-on work with the artifacts or facsimiles
                                        themselves, including plenty of one-on-one feedback from the
                                        instructor.</p>
                                <p>Our approach switches the focus from reading aloud to reading and
                                        recording. We asked the students to transcribe the
                                        manuscript pages in class and on their own time and to
                                        include a very light encoding so the transcription could, in
                                        theory, be processed by computers. This encoding component
                                        is an innovation in reference to more traditional approaches
                                        to paleography. This approach enables students to engage
                                        with texts as dynamic semiotic systems, recognizing
                                        transcription not as a mere substitution but as an act of
                                        translation — from the semiotic system of the manuscript to
                                        that of the digital transcription <ptr
                                                target="#robinson_and_solopova_1993"/>. As Robinson
                                        and Solopova (1993) emphasize, transcriptions are inherently
                                        interpretative and incomplete, akin to all translational
                                        acts, as they navigate between distinct semiotic frameworks
                                        (e.g., the primary source and the digital medium). Moreover,
                                        in the context of the semiotic shift, students often
                                        initiate their own reflexive process regarding
                                                <emph>why</emph> and <emph>how</emph> texts should
                                        be interpreted and transcribed. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                                <head>Institutional context</head>
                                <p>In 2023, Barbara Bordalejo had a class on paleography of the
                                        British Isles approved in the departments of English and
                                        History at the University of Lethbridge with manuscript
                                        selections covering texts in Latin, Old French, Old and
                                        Middle English produced between 700 and 1500. Although her
                                        paleographic training in the late 1990s included some access
                                        to digital photography (which was of very low quality at the
                                        time), she primarily worked with analog materials, including
                                        printed photographs, photocopies, and a few manuscripts.
                                        However, after joining the Canterbury Tales Project,
                                        Bordalejo shifted her paleography work to computer
                                        environments, where she worked with digital images taken
                                        from old microfilm and transcribed texts encoded in SGML
                                        using a custom font called <q>Canterbury.</q> The new
                                        course's design builds on and integrates these text encoding
                                        skills, which are useful for text processing using
                                        computers, and commonly implemented in digital humanities. </p>
                                <p>The University of Lethbridge is a comprehensive academic research
                                        university (CARU) with a liberal arts focus that serves a
                                        primarily undergraduate student body. As such, unlike larger
                                        institutions, the University of Lethbridge has a limited
                                        collection of original materials that might be used for
                                        teaching a general paleography class. Historically, the
                                        English Department was well-staffed, but budgeting
                                        constraints weakened the breadth of the program, reducing
                                        its faculty complement by as much as 50%. Bordalejo arrived
                                        in the Fall of 2021 to teach medieval literature, digital
                                        humanities, and humanities data courses. She proposed three
                                        courses that were approved as new offerings: Digital
                                        Textuality (English), Humanities Data (Interdisciplinary),
                                        and Paleography (English and History). Paleography is
                                        offered as a third-year course in both English and History.
                                        There were no prerequisites, but knowledge of Old or Middle
                                        English or History of the Book was recommended for those
                                        taking the class. The official course syllabus (see <ptr
                                                target="#bordalejo_2024"/>) listed the following
                                        objectives: </p>
                                <list type="ordered">
                                        <item>Identify different scripts</item>
                                        <item>Use correct terminology while referring to different
                                                scripts</item>
                                        <item>Understand the historical context of the studied
                                                works</item>
                                        <item>Read and transcribe scripts of the British
                                                Isles</item>
                                        <item>Formulate research questions regarding paleographic
                                                studies</item>
                                </list>
                                <p>Most students had already taken a course focused on medieval
                                        history or medieval literature. About half of the class had
                                        training in either Old English, Middle English, or the
                                        history of the English language. However, there were also
                                        students without any knowledge of these or similar subjects,
                                        including a few from the natural sciences who had very
                                        little background in the humanities at all. A common
                                        characteristic the vast majority of the students shared was
                                        their lack of familiarity with aspects of technology such as
                                        encoding. Although we are unable to document this, the sense
                                        among the more experienced members of our team is that, at
                                        the turn of the century, it was more common for individuals
                                        to have at least some knowledge of HTML acquired through
                                        practices such as blogging and developing websites in the
                                        days before WYSIWYG (What You See Is What You Get) web
                                        applications and the rise of social media. While there has
                                        been an increase in the access of technology in students’
                                        day-to-day lives this does not necessarily mean there has
                                        been a corresponding increase in their understanding of what
                                        goes on on the back-end: </p>
                                <quote rend="block">While many young people use technology daily,
                                        this does not necessarily mean that they possess high-order
                                        technical skills that will allow them to excel beyond their
                                        superficial use of tech gadgets. <ptr
                                                target="#thomas_and_blackwood_2010" loc="8"
                                        /></quote>
                                <p>In fact, while programming languages, such as HTML, remain
                                        popular among users — as illustrated in a recent survey by
                                                <ptr target="#stack_overflow_2024"/> — this does not
                                        represent a general literacy, as we discovered when we asked
                                        students to practice making a small webpage to help them
                                        understand on a base level how information must be
                                        structured in order to allow the machine to process it.
                                        Amongst both offerings of the course, we found that students
                                        struggled to grasp the fundamental logic of computer
                                        languages even before attempting to encode the
                                        manuscripts.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                                <head>Literature review</head>
                                <p>The emergence of academic literature on the pandemic’s impact on
                                        pedagogy has led to two contradictory attitudes. One
                                        approach focuses more on the short-term implications and
                                        views classroom adjustments as a temporary response to the
                                        pandemic. The other is geared towards predicting the
                                        potential long-term impact on pedagogy by continuing to
                                        implement the new strategies developed during the pandemic.
                                        On the one hand, the first attitude highlights the
                                                <q>risks</q> associated with an increased dependency
                                        and deployment of digital tools and online learning in an
                                        educational setting; on the other hand, the second attitude
                                        suggests that teaching practices should be informed by the
                                        COVID experience to enhance them in the future rather than
                                        discarding them once the pandemic is <q>over</q>.</p>
                                <p>Murphy’s work is situated within the first approach. Murphy
                                        focuses on the consequences of what is defined as <quote
                                                rend="inline">emergency eLearning</quote>
                                        <ptr target="#murphy_2020" loc="1"/> criticizing the fact
                                        that the pandemic has led to a general <quote rend="inline"
                                                >securitization</quote> of higher education’s rising
                                        reliance on surveillance technologies and the adoption of
                                        one-size-fits-all solutions. They also emphasize the <quote
                                                rend="inline">danger of normalizing emergency
                                                eLearning</quote> without falling into the rhetoric
                                        of <quote rend="inline">condemning all forms of online
                                                learning,</quote> but still argue for an <quote
                                                rend="inline">emancipation</quote> from the
                                        securitization associated with eLearning <ptr
                                                target="#murphy_2020" loc="10"/>. In this sense,
                                        Murphy is one of the most critical voices in the scholarly
                                        discussion on the pandemic turn. Still, they focus mainly on
                                        the risks — neglecting to address other issues, such as the
                                        degree to which technology is helpful in post-pandemic
                                        pedagogies and the circumstances from which these changes
                                        have come to be.</p>
                                <p>Hofer, Nistor, and Scheibenzuber have discussed the need to
                                        re-examine the pandemic experience in terms of its benefits
                                        to teaching practices. Consistent with the second stance
                                        discussed previously — looking at the lessons learned from
                                        the pandemic as a positive — they engage with the emergency
                                        aspects taken for granted by Murphy <ptr
                                                target="#hofer_et_al_2021"/>. In their contribution,
                                        the authors begin with the idea that normally transformative
                                        processes may not develop in a gradual, cumulative manner,
                                        such as the implementation of digital tools in teaching <ptr
                                                target="#hofer_et_al_2021" loc="2"/>. They argue
                                        that changes <quote rend="inline">can be suddenly triggered
                                                by unexpected and compelling incidents or accidents
                                                that make up crisis situations,</quote> such as in
                                        the case of the pandemic <ptr target="#hofer_et_al_2021"
                                                loc="2"/>. According to their
                                        view, this happens mainly because <quote rend="inline"
                                                >[c]risis situations emphasize the strengths,
                                                uncover the weaknesses, and lead to progress</quote>
                                        <ptr target="#hofer_et_al_2021" loc="2"/>. </p>
                                <p>In the same vein, Barrett-Fox et al. positively assess this
                                                <quote rend="inline">shift for teaching</quote> in
                                        terms of the acceleration of <quote rend="inline">the use of
                                                digital technology,</quote> whose potential may be
                                        regarded as important <quote rend="inline">for online
                                                learning to bring about new pedagogical
                                                approaches</quote>
                                        <ptr target="#barrett-fox_et_al_2020" loc="154"/> in the
                                        post-pandemic. Barrett-Fox et al. emphasize the importance
                                        of transitioning from a <quote rend="inline"
                                                >restoration</quote> to an all-encompassing <quote
                                                rend="inline">transformation</quote> of teaching
                                        practices. This awareness of new approaches and methods to
                                        engaging students comes from the realization that during the
                                        lockdown, <quote rend="inline">it became painfully obvious
                                                that we could not just do the same thing. Some
                                                assignments were no longer possible. Some
                                                expectations were no longer reasonable. Some
                                                objectives were no longer valuable </quote><ptr
                                                target="#barrett-fox_et_al_2020" loc="161–162"/>.
                                        Thus, they not only discuss the potential benefits of online
                                        learning to foster new pedagogical approaches <ptr
                                                target="#barrett-fox_et_al_2020" loc="183–184"/> but
                                        also how such a shift allows increased access to educational
                                        resources and opportunities for students to engage in deeper
                                        learning. At the same time, they highlight potential
                                        drawbacks, such as the risk that digital technology may
                                        exacerbate existing inequalities and the need for teachers
                                        to acquire new digital skills <ptr
                                                target="#barrett-fox_et_al_2020" loc="185–186"/>.
                                        Their contribution joins those who call for further research
                                        into the implications of the pandemic and foresee a positive
                                        outcome from the wider adoption of online learning and new
                                        pedagogies connected to it. </p>
                                <p>For their part, Lohr et al. carried out qualitative research to
                                                <quote rend="inline">address the lack of systematic
                                                research on digitally supported learning activities
                                                and the institutional and personal factors
                                                associated with their occurrence in higher
                                                education</quote>
                                        <ptr target="#lohr_et_al_2021" loc="2"/>. Their broader aim
                                        was to assess the degree of familiarity of teachers with
                                        technology in higher educational environments, and this
                                        allowed the identification of three distinct teacher roles:
                                                <quote rend="inline">powerpointers</quote>, <quote
                                                rend="inline">clickers</quote>, and <quote
                                                rend="inline">digital pros</quote> — each of which
                                        was shown to be more or less comfortable in the use of
                                        digital technologies for teaching purposes. This
                                        differentiation also suggests that implementation is not a
                                        one-to-one relation and does not necessarily lead to digital
                                        pedagogy, even when there is space for digital pedagogical
                                        innovation. <ptr target="#careaga-butter_et_al_2020"/> considered the
                                        degree to which digital tools and resources that contributed
                                        to online education during the pandemic can continue in the
                                        post-pandemic future. This is possible only if teachers are
                                        willing to adopt and integrate them into their teaching
                                        practices and are prepared to offer students the guidance
                                        and support necessary to ensure their success in their
                                        studies. Together with the need <quote rend="inline">to
                                                collaborate in the construction of [...] a new mixed
                                                educational paradigm that can face the post-pandemic
                                                context and meet the new demands and requirements of
                                                the 21st century,</quote> a good-faith effort to
                                        integrate digital technologies into the classroom is the
                                        only way to achieve a <quote rend="inline">true online
                                                education</quote> in the terms they define <ptr
                                                target="#careaga-butter_et_al_2020" loc="29"/>.</p>
                                <p>COVID-19 was not the sole prompt for using digital tools to teach
                                        and learn. For instance, Torsello, Ackerley, and Castello
                                                <ptr target="#torsello_et_al_2008"/> and Forti <ptr
                                                target="#forti_2023"/> have already proved the
                                        usefulness of integrating corpus management programs
                                        designed for linguistic analysis into teaching linguistics
                                        and translation. Social media platforms such as X (formerly
                                        known as Twitter) have also proven to be beneficial both for
                                        teaching and learning purposes <ptr
                                                target="#gleason_and_manca_2020"/>
                                        <ptr target="#rinaldo_et_al_2011"/>. Notably, the cases
                                        mentioned above are the only examples we found where
                                        advanced tools not primarily intended for pedagogical
                                        purposes have been repurposed for educational use.
                                        Addressing this gap presents an opportunity to expand the
                                        array of available resources for educators, potentially
                                        enhancing the quality of the teaching and learning process;
                                        in our case, it involved the unconventional implementation
                                        of Textual Communities in the university classroom
                                        environment.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                                <head>What is Textual Communities?</head>
                                <p>Textual Communities is an online application designed for the
                                        needs of textual scholars working with texts, mainly found
                                        in manuscripts, in multiple versions. It was first
                                        established as a project at the University of Saskatchewan
                                        with funding from the Canadian Foundation for Innovation
                                        (CFI) and support from the U of S’s Digital Research Centre.
                                        Its purpose, as described by Robinson, Nelson, and Klaassen
                                        is to <quote rend="inline">provide the infrastructure and
                                                tools to allow anyone, anywhere interested in a text
                                                to contribute to its study, and thus to become part
                                                of a community working together</quote>
                                        <ptr target="#robinson_et_al_2012"/>. As such, it integrates
                                        tools for the transcription, collation, regularization, and
                                        publication of scholarly editions using a
                                        social-network-like model. Since Textual Communities is
                                        available online, the system has been ideal for large
                                        collaborative projects where participants work
                                        asynchronously and (potentially) at a physical distance. It
                                        has a component that provides version control by recording
                                        the source, time, and responsibility for changes — although,
                                        unlike Google Docs, Textual Communities is not optimized to
                                        allow real-time simultaneous editing of a single document
                                        (making it more similar to GitHub). Instead, the system
                                        keeps track of different versions of transcriptions and
                                        records times, duration, and responsibility. In addition,
                                        the data created within the communities is made available
                                        for <quote rend="inline">unrestricted commercial as well as
                                                non-commercial use</quote>
                                        <ptr target="#robinson_et_al_2012"/>. </p>
                                <p>What sets Textual Communities apart are two features: its
                                        integrated participant- and document-management systems, and
                                        its mapping of the fundamental structure connecting
                                        documents and texts. These reflect two core principles: that
                                        assembling large corpora is best achieved through
                                        well-managed communities of contributors, both academic and
                                        non-academic; and that the usefulness of the corpus depends
                                        on clearly articulating the relationships between materials.
                                        Textual Communities is designed to organize multiple
                                        participants around shared editorial projects. It supports
                                        relational structures ranging from tightly controlled
                                        editorial teams to loosely organized crowdsourced
                                        communities — making it ideal for both classroom use and
                                        long-term research. The name <title rend="quotes">Textual
                                                Communities</title> therefore highlights the
                                        importance of community aspects in textual editing and
                                        scholarship, which is one reason why the system is easily
                                        adaptable for classroom environments. Since the system’s
                                        inception in the 2010s, various projects have welcomed
                                        collaborators from around the globe. For long-term
                                        enterprises like the Canterbury Tales Project, more than one
                                        hundred and twenty participants have joined Textual
                                        Communities since the implementation of its latest version
                                        in 2014. These collaborators are mostly transcribers who
                                        have been trained in TEI-XML as well as in paleography and
                                        Middle English. The system has been tested, and up to forty
                                        participants have been logged into a single project
                                        simultaneously, but there is no reason to believe that
                                        higher numbers would not work either. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                                <head>How did we adapt Textual Communities to the classroom?</head>
                                <p>Although the goal of a paleography course, traditionally and
                                        primarily, has been to train students in the interpretation
                                        of hand-written documents, there has always been an element
                                        of research apprenticeship involved. Medieval and literary
                                        manuscripts are not objects most individuals encounter
                                        outside of a research context (i.e., by requesting access
                                        for research purposes from academic libraries, museums, and
                                        private collectors), and the conventions used to track
                                        student observations — such as the Leiden transcription
                                        conventions — are those used by researchers (e.g. <ptr
                                                target="#wilcken_1932"/>. </p>
                                <p>Today, digital transcription is the standard for projects
                                        interested in text comparison and analysis, whether their
                                        outputs are released in print or digitally. Although the
                                        study of paleography requires reading handwritten materials
                                        and identifying scripts and scribes, paleographers
                                        increasingly find themselves working within digital
                                        environments that need their own subset of specialized
                                        knowledge. In adapting Textual Communities to the
                                        paleography classroom, we continue this tradition. At the
                                        same time, the more complex needs of a digital environment —
                                        which require coding consistency and controlled markup —
                                        necessitated that we also teach our students some basic
                                        information about computer markup and encoding systems, with
                                        particular emphasis on TEI-XML as the standard used for
                                        digital projects. These classes were led by Daniel Paul
                                        O’Donnell, a former Chair of the TEI consortium. Beyond this
                                        basic computational instruction, a series of additional
                                        decisions were required in order to implement Textual
                                        Communities — which was not designed as a pedagogical tool —
                                        into the classroom. </p>
                                <p>For this particular class, for example, the transcriptions did
                                        not need to be further processed or published, and their
                                        long-term preservation was not required (indeed privacy
                                        regulations at the University require records of student
                                        work to be destroyed at set deadlines after the end of a
                                        class unless additional permissions have been granted). We
                                        thought, therefore, that Textual Communities Sandbox offered
                                        an appropriate environment for the students’ work (indeed,
                                        this is the version we recommend for anyone testing the
                                        software or working on short-term mini-projects). This has
                                        most of the same functionalities as the production version:
                                        There are no limitations on creating communities by any
                                        interested parties, but it does not provide archiving and
                                        publication facilities. Although it would have been possible
                                        to use the production version with the same effect, we chose
                                        to create the course within the experimental space. After
                                        all, the primary purpose of its use was beyond the regular
                                        implementations of Textual Communities but still required a
                                        centralized system that would keep track of work being done
                                        and completed by students, as well as of the hours worked
                                        and every change implemented in the texts. Because of its
                                        versioning capabilities, Textual Communities allowed us to
                                        track in real-time the work being done by the students,
                                        either in the classroom or outside of it. As of March 2025,
                                        the sandbox environment referenced in this study has been
                                        retired. All functionality described in this article is now
                                        available through the platform formerly known as the <title
                                                rend="italic">Textual Communities Production</title>
                                        version. The primary site is is <ref
                                                target="https://textualcommunities.com"
                                                >https://textualcommunities.com</ref>; the address
                                                <ref target="https://textualcommunities.org"
                                                >https://textualcommunities.org</ref> now redirects
                                        to this site</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                                <head>Class structure</head>
                                <p>Lessons were structured in three-hour blocks with a short break.
                                        The first part of each lesson was dedicated to the history
                                        of a particular script, its characteristic features, and the
                                        changes in writing technologies during that period. The
                                        course began with Old English manuscripts but also included
                                        Latin, Old French, Old and Middle English texts. To
                                        accommodate each script, we discussed the evolution and use
                                        of specific characters in each period, as well as
                                        contemporary abbreviations and their meanings. Generally,
                                        each lecture concluded by showing particularities present in
                                        sample pages which students would then transcribe, including
                                        ambiguous signs and extra-textual features (e.g. damage to
                                        the manuscript, scribal corrections, etc.) that might cause
                                        difficulty. </p>
                                <p>The rest of the class was dedicated to practical transcription,
                                        during which time each student worked on their individual
                                        transcriptions. The setup of Textual Communities focuses on
                                        understanding the text as an instance of a work preserved in
                                        individual folia within a manuscript (Work/Manuscript/Folio;
                                        see Figure 1), but this is not practical when one expects
                                        students to work mostly independently of each other.</p>
                                <figure>
                                        <head>Textual Communities screen capture showing the
                                                ontological structure
                                                <q>work/manuscript/folio.</q></head>
                                        <figDesc>Textual Communities screen capture showing the
                                                ontological structure
                                                <q>work/manuscript/folio.</q></figDesc>
                                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                                </figure>
                               
                                <p>In production environments, the point of collaboration within
                                        Textual Communities is that different participants work on
                                        different manuscript passages or, if they work on the same,
                                        that they work on different parts of the workflow (e.g.,
                                        transcribing, checking, etc.; see Figure 2). It is also
                                        assumed, in most cases, that contributors will use their
                                        technology (i.e., computers, operating systems, etc.),
                                        albeit with minimal technological requirements. In a
                                        classroom environment, however, neither of these assumptions
                                        is true. First, the students are all learning the same
                                        skills from the same manuscripts, meaning that the community
                                        works in parallel rather than serial in a production
                                        environment. Second, accommodation and equity concerns
                                        necessitate that the system be adapted to allow students to
                                        use their own technology or utilize university-provided
                                        equipment. </p>
                                <figure>
                                        <head>Illustration of the different workflows for production
                                                (where multiple people work on different parts of a
                                                document) and classroom (where each student
                                                transcribes and is evaluated on the same parts of
                                                the same document).</head>
                                        <figDesc>Illustration of the different workflows for
                                                production (where multiple people work on different
                                                parts of a document) and classroom (where each
                                                student transcribes and is evaluated on the same
                                                parts of the same document).</figDesc>
                                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                                </figure>
                               
                                <p>Our classes were scheduled in a lab equipped with Apple computers
                                        to ensure that students had access to sufficient computer
                                        power, regardless of their personal means. But in many cases
                                        (indeed most) students preferred to work on their laptops or
                                        tablets — in some cases, using special adaptations required
                                        for various accommodations. Before the beginning of the
                                        semester, we registered individual students with Textual
                                        Communities and added them to a community called
                                                <q>Paleography2023.</q> This allowed us to upload
                                        manuscript images from various sources and place them in
                                        separate folders, each corresponding to a particular
                                        student. The images were selected to correspond with the
                                        topics and chronology being followed in class (a list of the
                                        texts used for our lessons can be found in <ptr
                                                target="#bordalejo_2024"/>). Instead of separating
                                        the pages according to manuscripts as would have been done
                                        in a production environment, we created individual folders
                                        for each student and populated them with images of the
                                        different manuscript pages assigned to the class (see
                                        Figures 3 and 4, and cf. Figures 1 and 2). </p>
                                <figure>
                                        <head>Textual Communities screen capture showing the modified structure, <q>course/person.</q></head>
                                        <figDesc>Textual Communities screen capture showing the modified structure, <q>course/person.</q></figDesc>
                                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                                </figure>
                                
                                <p>During the practical portion of the class, we walked around the
                                        classroom, ensuring that students could make sense of the
                                        text and answer questions. Frequently, questions led to
                                        conversations about interpretation and misinterpretation,
                                        opinions, and more advanced discussions about the
                                        implications of different transcription choices. Students
                                        often shared their perspectives on the text and its
                                        interpretation collaboratively. Each student was working on
                                        the assigned pages for the day but was encouraged to work at
                                        their own pace. Although, as an instructor, one might prefer
                                        to keep students working at a similar pace, one of the
                                        significant advantages of working within Textual Communities
                                        is that students can take ownership of their time and choose
                                        when and how to work. This is particularly noticeable
                                        towards the end of the semester, as students have gained
                                        confidence and are less hesitant to make their own
                                        decisions. </p>
                                <figure>
                                        <head>Textual Communities screen capture showing the modified
                                                structure, <q>course/person/folio.</q></head>
                                        <figDesc>Textual Communities screen capture showing the modified
                                                structure, <q>course/person/folio.</q></figDesc>
                                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                                </figure>
                                
                                <p>If particular manuscripts turned out to be challenging, the class
                                        swapped completed transcriptions for peer correction as the
                                        class as a whole read the text together. A few students
                                        wanted to pair up outside of class for peer correction. If
                                        this was requested, the professor or teaching assistants
                                        could assign their peers’ transcriptions to them for review
                                        within Textual Communities. A record of the changes made to
                                        the student’s original transcription would be visible, as
                                        Textual Communities has a version control system that allows
                                        users to revert to previous versions so that changes made
                                        are visible.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                                <head>Checking student work</head>
                                <p>Although it might appear that a system allowing the transcription
                                        of primary sources would be intrinsically geared to
                                        paleography class, there are no mechanisms within Textual
                                        Communities to evaluate the accuracy of the transcription of
                                        individual characters. This required that checking and
                                        evaluation be done independently of the system by the
                                        instructor(s) and teaching assistant(s). </p>
                                <p>From an instructor’s perspective, the biggest drawback of Textual
                                        Communities is that it does not have a feature to correct
                                        the submitted transcriptions automatically. Although we do
                                        not dismiss the desirability for pedagogical purposes of
                                        implementing a correction module within the system, this is
                                        not a requirement for classroom use, as correcting
                                        individual transcriptions is not a particularly onerous
                                        task. Ultimately, we employed three methods of correction:
                                        instructor correction, peer correction, and self-correction.
                                        After all students had submitted their transcriptions, the
                                        instructor read the manuscripts aloud. This enabled students
                                        to self-assess, correct their work, and explore various
                                        transcription options. We also tried transcription exchange,
                                        during which students gave each other access to
                                        transcriptions to evaluate each other’s accuracy. </p>
                                <p>During the semester, as students became more proficient, they
                                        were encouraged to revise their transcriptions to ensure
                                        they were as accurate as possible. At the same time, they
                                        were given different choices: to retain all abbreviations,
                                        to expand them, or to use encoding to reflect both states.
                                        We discussed the advantages and disadvantages of each
                                        approach and why they might choose one over the other. These
                                        techniques not only maintain students’ engagement but also
                                        offer an opportunity to test acquired skills in self-guided
                                        work. We acknowledge that we follow in the footsteps of
                                        proponents of critical digital pedagogy, as discussed below.
                                        So, we aim to emphasize students' roles in their educational
                                        journey. In this light, we strive to foster students’
                                        independent thinking and self-determined work. Although the
                                        initial aim of implementing Textual Communities was to
                                        ensure that the class could easily continue online if
                                        required, we soon realized its enormous potential to
                                        exercise student self-regulation, independence, and
                                        confidence-building. The practical format of the class,
                                        combined with supervised independent work, was well received
                                        because it differed from most classes in our department,
                                        which typically focus on analysis and close reading. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                                <head>Teaching assistant’s perspective </head>
                                <p>To support the instructor in the process of providing
                                        constructive feedback and help students improve their
                                        skills, the role of the teaching assistant (TA) in this
                                        set-up is of great importance. First of all, TAs have to be
                                        aware of the course design and ideally contribute to it by
                                        working alongside the instructor. This collaboration can
                                        yield many benefits not only to their overall professional
                                        development as prospective educators but also to enhance
                                        course delivery. Being liminal figures between students and
                                        instructors, they can leverage a privileged observation
                                        point, which enables TAs to provide insights from both
                                        perspectives — the instructor’s and the students'. TAs must
                                        actively participate in class activities, almost as if they
                                        were enrolled students, to assess progress and identify
                                        issues effectively. This involves transcribing texts before
                                        the start of each class, which allows the TAs to understand
                                        the challenges posed by each transcription. Since each
                                        scribe’s work is unique, being familiar with potential
                                        problems in a text enhances their ability to respond quickly
                                        and effectively. This proactive approach ensures that TAs
                                        are well-prepared to support students and address any
                                        difficulties during the course. While the TAs’ presence
                                        enriches the learning experience for both students and the
                                        TAs themselves, it is essential to avoid the drawback of
                                        students becoming overly dependent on them.</p>
                                <p>Another of the domains where TAs can prove very beneficial to the
                                        course is the evaluation of the difficulty of each task as
                                        well as the weekly workload. As the course progresses, the
                                        TA importance does not diminish but instead changes
                                        according to different factors. When the students begin the
                                        course, their unfamiliarity with both the tools (XML-TEI
                                        encoding and the peculiarities of the Textual Communities
                                        Sandbox, above all) and the scripts (insular minuscule,
                                        caroline, gothic, etc.) makes the TAs fundamental in
                                        providing the early personalized and timely feedback that is
                                        essential for the development of these skills. The students
                                        may also struggle with the discontinuities that characterize
                                        each period. For instance, once the students are well
                                        acquainted with the variations of <term>gothica
                                                textualis</term> they will then have to readjust
                                        themselves to the knowledge of a fairly distinct hand such
                                        as <term>anglicana</term>. This struggle, together
                                        with the fatigue of the semester, usually referred to as
                                        <quote rend="inline">exhaustion</quote> or <quote rend="inline">burnout</quote> in the literature <ptr target="#galbraith_and_merrill_2012"/> <ptr target="#law_2007"/>, often requires diversified types
                                        of additional support to students, especially considering
                                        their different learning styles and eventual needs.</p>
                                <p>This means that generally TAs serve as mentors for students.
                                        Having been involved in transcription projects and having
                                        first-hand experience of the issues the students may
                                        encounter, they provide hands-on guidance, troubleshoot
                                        technical problems, and encourage students to explore the
                                        tools autonomously. This last part is fundamental since the
                                        pedagogical role should always be that of offering ongoing
                                        support while avoiding the risk of creating a situation for
                                        which the students solely depend on the TA. In line with the
                                        self-centred learning strategy adopted by the course, TAs
                                        focused on empowering students to develop their
                                        problem-solving skills and independence rather than
                                        providing solutions too readily. This balance ensured that
                                        students benefited from the support of TAs without
                                        compromising their learning and growth, considering that
                                        students’ learning autonomy should always be at the core of
                                        their activities, helping students develop self-confidence
                                        and the necessary skills to navigate the challenges of
                                        digital transcriptions autonomously. This relates to
                                        fundamental metacognitive skills — the awareness of one’s
                                        own learning processes — and TAs must let students develop
                                        these skills in their own ways. For example, bridging the
                                        gap between theoretical knowledge of a handwriting’s
                                        characteristics and the practical application of that
                                        knowledge to understand the idiosyncrasies of a given
                                        manuscript via the student’s own transcription
                                        decisions.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                                <head>Student’s Perspective</head>
                                <p>In both instances of the course offered (Spring 2023 and 2024),
                                        the introductory class was centred around explaining what
                                        transcription is and its different types (diplomatic, etc.).
                                        Textual Communities was not introduced to students
                                        immediately. Instead, they were presented with an image of a
                                        page of <title rend="quotes">Alice’s Adventures in Wonderland</title> in Lewis
                                        Carroll’s handwriting, with the text meandering and curving
                                        across the page. They were asked to transcribe the page onto
                                        paper by hand. This was an initial challenge to see what
                                        students perceived as essential aspects of transcribing.
                                        Would they keep the shape of the words on the page? Would
                                        they copy the page numbers on the original image's corners?
                                        Would they include the virgules and dashes used? This
                                        practice enabled students to understand how transcribing is
                                        an act of interpretation carried out with regard to a larger
                                        purpose and how multiple transcriptions can exist for a
                                        single text. Indeed we use this method in teaching other
                                        computational skills to students at the University of
                                        Lethbridge: by beginning with an illustration of the problem
                                        a system (such as TEI markup) is intended to address (such
                                        as recording an interpretation of a document) and then
                                        asking students to come with their own approach before
                                        teaching them about existing methods. We believe that this
                                        allows students to understand the canonical systems better
                                        by illustrating the problem they were developed to address. </p>
                                <p>With the problem in mind, students were then introduced to the
                                        Textual Communities platform. While the instructor and TAs
                                        initially guided the students on how to use the website's
                                        basic features — how to access their assigned pages, save
                                        their work, etc. — the students were left to decide how
                                        their transcriptions would look. They had to decide what
                                        they wanted to include in their work. For example, if a line
                                        was crossed out and new text was written above the deleted
                                        text, they had to decide whether to include both parts, one
                                        or the other, or indicate the deleted text. Student
                                        transcriptions often differed significantly from one another
                                        due to the decisions that had to be made throughout their
                                        work. The instructor and TAs emphasized that making
                                        different choices about what to include or not include was
                                        not necessarily right or wrong; it was just a matter of
                                        interpretation. Perhaps the best statement about the student
                                        perspective in our course comes from one of our students
                                        herself, Victoria Simmons, quoted here with permission:</p>
                                <quote rend="block">As the Rural Diary Archive [a project the student was looking at]
                                        suggests, crowdsourcing of transcription can be accomplished
                                        not only on a global or national scale but also on a
                                        smaller, local scale by using a classroom setting. A similar
                                        type of collaborative experience was created in our
                                        classroom when we focused on discussing certain parts of
                                        manuscripts that were comparatively complex to transcribe.
                                        When there was a particular section of our assigned
                                        manuscript that was more difficult — due to multiple
                                        adjacent characters written in minimum for example — the
                                        class would be encouraged to individually express to the
                                        class how they had interpreted the characters when they were
                                        transcribing. In most circumstances, this resulted in many
                                        unique interpretations expressed by classmates as to how
                                        they visually followed the connection of ligatures into what
                                        they believed may have been the scribe’s intended
                                        characters. By listening to multiple people voice their
                                        reasoning behind transcribing the writing in the way that
                                        they had chosen, the entire class was invited to look at a
                                        variety of possible interpretations for each transcription.
                                        The most important result of this experience is that each
                                        individual is challenged to question their own method of
                                        transcription. This technique is beneficial to the field of
                                        paleography because it prevents transcribers from settling
                                        on a single, definitive – and potentially incorrect or
                                        incomplete — perspective of the transcription. The benefit
                                        of this experience is amplified when it comes to global
                                        crowdsourcing projects, such as those mentioned above, which
                                        allow both beginners and experts to provide a greater
                                        variety of original viewpoint. (Simmons, student paper,
                                        2023)</quote>
                                <p>As Simmons notes, <quote rend="inline">many unique interpretations [were] expressed
                                        by classmates … By listening to multiple people voice their
                                        reasoning behind transcribing the writing in the way that
                                        they had chosen, the entire class was invited to look at
                                        various possible interpretations for each transcription. The
                                        most important result of this experience is that each
                                        individual is challenged to question their own method of
                                        transcription</quote> (Simmons, student paper, 2023). Viewing other
                                        students’ pages and their work on Textual Communities also
                                        allowed those who were not present in class to still be a
                                        part of this experience of seeing other people’s
                                        interpretations of the text. </p>
                                <p>Students were also encouraged to work together on transcriptions
                                        and to frequently ask questions as the instructor and TAs
                                        were in the room for the working period. As described by
                                        Simmons, a <quote rend="inline">collaborative experience was created in our
                                        classroom</quote> (2023). This, combined with the previously
                                        established attitude of transcription as interpretation,
                                        established that the classwork was not focused on being
                                        <q>right</q> or <q>wrong.</q> Instead, the priority was to learn
                                        important characteristics and traits of the various hands
                                        taught and try their best to complete the assigned pages.
                                        Some students initially seemed apprehensive about the lack
                                        of a <q>grade</q> they would receive for their transcriptions. As
                                        a result, many of the early transcriptions took students a
                                        long time to complete. To alleviate this concern, the
                                        beginning of later classes was devoted to identifying common
                                        errors among multiple students. In both course iterations
                                        (Spring 2023 and Spring 2024), the instructor and TAs
                                        adjusted the amount of correcting done to transcriptions
                                        depending on how much the students requested feedback for
                                        their work. Textual Communities enables instructors
                                        categorized on the platform to access student pages and edit
                                        or add comments to their transcriptions, allowing students
                                        to view comments about their work outside of class time. </p>
                                <p>Accessing Textual Communities outside of class time from any
                                        computer is one of the significant benefits of the platform,
                                        allowing students to work outside of the set class-time
                                        working periods. They could sign in to their account from
                                        any computer. This, combined with the rule in the course
                                        that the pages only had to be done by the end of the
                                        semester, allowed students the flexibility and freedom to
                                        complete coursework at their own pace. This student-centred
                                        approach was enabled by the flexibility offered by the
                                        Textual Communities platform. The collaborative and
                                        accessible platform allowed students to work together with
                                        classmates and consider the many possible interpretations
                                        that transcription might involve. It also allowed students
                                        to access their work and view corrections or comments made
                                        about it on their own time, which might contribute to easing
                                        students’ worries about periods in the semester that
                                        required more of their attention — they could work on their
                                        pages at any point, as long as all of them were completed by
                                        the end of the semester. In short, using Textual Communities
                                        as a platform encouraged students to collaborate, consider
                                        the interpretative process of transcriptions, not focus too
                                        hard on mistakes they might have considered themselves to
                                        have made, and gave them the freedom to work on assigned
                                        pages at times that worked best for their personalized
                                        schedules. </p>
                        </div>
                                <div><head>Discussion</head>
                                <p>The core innovation in using Textual Communities for teaching is
                                        that students make their own research decisions about what
                                        to transcribe and why, with instructors supporting them in
                                        implementing these decisions. As <ptr target="#odonnell_et_al_2016b"/>
                                        argue, the traditional division between <q>research </q>— i.e.,
                                        what the professor engages in and is protected by academic
                                        freedom — and <q>teaching</q> — i.e., when students are told what
                                        to do and how to do it — misrepresents the nature of
                                        Humanities scholarship and limits student learning by
                                        preventing meaningful engagement in research in a meaningful
                                        way. This practice also reflects what we call the <title rend="quotes">First Law
                                        of Humanities Computing,</title> which refers to the fact that any
                                        application of computation to a humanities problem seems to
                                        require a fundamental examination of the purposes behind the
                                        original activity <ptr target="#odonnell_et_al_2016a"/>. Asking students to
                                        consider why they want to transcribe these manuscripts, what
                                        they hope to achieve by doing so, and how they can match
                                        their methods to their goals, is a way of asking them to
                                        engage in critical reflection on their own learning — both
                                        within the course itself and, of course, more broadly within
                                        their programs. Unlike non-digital work, where intuition and
                                        analogy often can serve as guides, digital work demands
                                        conscious design and algorithmic thinking. By allowing
                                        students to exercise judgment and pursue their own
                                        questions, Textual Communities collapses this gap. It
                                        invites students to engage in the same intellectual freedoms
                                        that define research itself. </p>
                                <p>As we described earlier, this meant that there were numerous
                                        active discussions on the implications of specific choices
                                        during the transcription process. While the lecturing and
                                        grading resembled more traditional class structure and
                                        dynamics, which relates to the intrinsic nature of any
                                        paleography class, the use of Textual Communities provided
                                        students with tools and methods — high-resolution, digital
                                        facsimiles, peer dialogue, collaboration, and meaningful
                                        input into the methods they used to transcribe (scribal
                                        corrections, unclear textual segments, a change in scribal
                                        <q>hands,</q> and letter forms) — that allowed them to set their
                                        own research questions, exercise their viewpoints and
                                        interpretations, and pursue them according to their own
                                        critical judgments. </p>
                                <p>The version control system helps students to track their own
                                        variants of the text and can reconstruct their train of
                                        thought regarding their transcription work (for instance,
                                        where the student might interpret a mark modification from a
                                        scribe or ignore it). In contrast to traditional approaches
                                        to paleography, Textual Communities prompts students to
                                        reflect on their actions as they are taking place in an even
                                        more profound manner. The reason for this is that it compels
                                        the students to face the logic of the machine and its
                                        one-sidedness, which forces fixed choices where human
                                        interpretation would allow ambiguity, requiring students to
                                        decide definitively between possibilities that a manuscript
                                        might leave open. For instance, the XML-TEI markup language
                                        allows for hundreds of ways to encode features within a
                                        single page, with variations such as different forms of
                                        damage to the page (such as water damage, erasure, fire,
                                        animal, scraping, etc.). This level of critical engagement
                                        with the problem — the problem-solving itself — creates a
                                        beneficial dialogue, which involves all the members, from
                                        the experts (teachers and TAs) to the students' peers. Some
                                        of the students within the classroom already have an
                                        intuitive understanding of what is going on, and they have
                                        an opportunity to share this with the class. This peer
                                        collaboration throughout the course allows students to see
                                        how others are interpreting and solving the problems they
                                        see on the pages. For instance, students were asked to
                                        attempt to recognize the material of the page on which the
                                        text appeared (whether parchment or paper). As a result,
                                        interpretative uncertainty in the document can be rendered
                                        into different solutions. One student might interpret a
                                        letter form completely differently from another — for
                                        example, reading pride instead of <hi rend="italic"
                                                >þrid</hi> (a variant spelling of <q>third</q>) based on
                                        the common confusion between thorn and p — or assume a sense
                                        of intentionality from the scribe regarding what another
                                        might view as an error. </p>
                                <p>In the foreword of the collection <title rend="italic">Critical Digital Pedagogy</title> edited by Stommel, Friend, and Morris during the
                                        pandemic <ptr target="#stommel_et_al_2020a"/>, Benjamin argues that
                                        such experience functions as a <quote rend="inline">portal, a gateway between
                                        one world and the next</quote> <ptr target="#benjamin_2020"/> leading to a greater integration of
                                        digital tools not initially developed for teaching purposes
                                        in education — as in the case of Textual Communities. In the
                                        introduction to the same collection, the authors also state
                                        that <quote rend="inline">[n]othing in edtech was built for humans. Thus far,
                                        our edtech machines were taught only to speak to other
                                        machines</quote> <ptr target="#stommel_et_al_2020b"/>. An example of this is
                                        represented by video conferencing tools like Zoom that <quote rend="inline">were
                                        not built to meet the moral challenge of a present moment
                                        like this one</quote> <ptr target="#stommel_et_al_2020b"/>. They have allowed, however, for
                                        synchronous collaborative learning experiences and virtual
                                        classroom discussions without replacing the classroom, which
                                        is and remains <quote rend="inline">unique</quote> and distinct from <quote rend="inline">the architecture
                                                of the Web</quote> <ptr target="#stommel_et_al_2020b"/></p>
                                <p>This concept of the uniqueness of the classroom, <quote rend="inline">with all its
                                        limitations</quote> <ptr target="#hooks_1994" loc="207"/>, makes it a <quote rend="inline">location
                                        of possibility,</quote> that allows for both the empowerment of
                                        social actors and the disruption of traditional forms of
                                        teaching. In hooks’ view, education should be a space for
                                        freedom and ultimately a transformative process. She
                                        advocates for engaged pedagogy, which understands classrooms
                                        as a site for self-guided exploration and mutual
                                        participation. While she extends this approach beyond a
                                        traditional academic setting, our practice of using Textual
                                        Communities has been an attempt to integrate these
                                        suggestions meaningfully. We have kept hooks’ perspective in
                                        mind in constructing this environment for our paleography
                                        class. One of our main objectives was to try and
                                        <quote rend="inline">responsibilize</quote> students in the way defined by <ptr target="#spencer_2018" loc="291"/>. For Spencer,
                                        renegotiating the <quote rend="inline">social contract</quote> between professor and
                                        student within the classroom is one of them. Spencer
                                        introduces this concept at the outset of the article,
                                        highlighting the limited roles each party can ethically
                                        operate <ptr target="#spencer_2018" loc="287"/>. According to this
                                        contract, the relationship between the professor,
                                        responsible for the course content and grading criteria, and
                                        the student, seeking to acquire skills to advance their
                                        future career prospects, resembles in its fundamental
                                        features a customer-provider neoliberal transaction. For
                                        Spencer, precisely this transactional dynamic is utterly
                                        problematic since it creates a power imbalance, where the
                                        professor supervises, and the student works at the pace
                                        dictated by the employer, potentially for the professor’s
                                        benefit <ptr target="#spencer_2018" loc="287–288"/>. Moreover, this power
                                        imbalance makes it difficult for students to raise
                                        objections, and thus a need to acknowledge and
                                        constructively engage with this issue for the benefit of
                                        both students and professors <ptr target="#spencer_2018" loc="288–289"/>.
                                        <ptr target="#fellmayer_2020"/> stresses the significance of
                                        reflexivity in coping with this asymmetry by acknowledging
                                        one's privilege and agency in benefiting from an inequitable
                                        society, which impedes meaningful disruption. Therefore, our
                                        focal point was to create a transformative educational
                                        experience for their students through digital tools in the
                                        framework established in the field of critical digital
                                        pedagogy during the pandemic.</p>
                                <p>Critical digital pedagogy is characterized by a deep engagement
                                        with the use of tools and technologies, while encouraging
                                        students to question and reflect on those same tools and
                                        methods <ptr target="#stommel_et_al_2020b"/>. This approach
                                        represents an expansion of the work of Paulo Freire, a
                                        Brazilian educator who criticized educational institutions
                                        for their tendency to silence or marginalize dissenting
                                        voices in his seminal work <title rend="italic">Pedagogy of the
                                                Oppressed</title> <ptr target="#freire_2000"/> and was exiled for his views,
                                        being deeply committed to rethinking education and
                                        advocating for more inclusive and equitable learning
                                        environments. Critical digital pedagogy seeks to dismantle
                                        impediments to learning. It argues that it is especially
                                        fruitful to probe the ground and identify the gap between
                                        theory and practice, but of course, it does not suggest that
                                        there are easy answers to the challenges of remote learning.
                                        While it can be helpful, it must be employed thoughtfully to
                                        be effective. Stommel, Friend, and Morris state that:</p> 
                                <quote rend="block">The word “pedagogy,” as we use it, defines the work of education
                                        at the intersection of theory and practice — the act of
                                        teaching that derives from reflection and which inspires
                                        reflection again. Pedagogy is both where “critical” and
                                        “digital” terminate, and also the whole terrain of teaching. <ptr target="#stommel_et_al_2020b"/></quote>
                                             
                              
                               <p> The triad <q>critical,</q> <q>digital,</q> and <q>pedagogical</q> must be kept
                                        without privileging <q>digital</q> at the expense of <q>critical</q>
                                        or of <q>pedagogy.</q> Suppose one only emphasizes the critical
                                        aspect of teaching. In that case, there is a risk of
                                        reducing it to a mere instrument, relegating the task of
                                        reflecting on teaching to the humanities and separating
                                        critical thinking from STEM fields, for instance. This
                                        narrow approach not only limits the potential impact of
                                        critical work, but also underestimates the vast array of
                                        teaching and learning activities that require criticality
                                        and a commitment to dismantling institutional or societal
                                        obstacles to learning <ptr target="#stommel_et_al_2020b"/>. However, the ideal
                                        process of dismantling barriers to learning has been further
                                        complicated by the challenges that have arisen during the
                                        pandemic period, which have added new layers of complexity
                                        to a pre-existing multifaceted landscape to let students
                                        take ownership of their learning and promote freedom in the
                                        classroom.</p>
                                <p>Effecting this is not necessarily easy, as Maha Bali argues in
                                        the same collection <ptr target="#bali_2020"/>, suggesting it is too easy to focus on
                                        theory and not enough on praxis. As she claims of her
                                        teaching context at the American University of Cairo:
                                        <quote rend="inline">[C]ritical pedagogy [...] is not about knowing how to do
                                        everything right or getting it right the first time, or
                                        every time. It is about putting faith in our learners to
                                        take control of their learning and teach us, each other, and
                                        themselves in the process</quote> <ptr target="#bali_2020"/>. Essentially, this learning
                                        approach is based on the fact that she does not <quote rend="inline">make
                                        everything <emph>explicit</emph>on the first
                                        day,</quote> stating the importance of <quote rend="inline">learning from each other</quote>
                                        and having <quote rend="inline">flexible and negotiable</quote> syllabi, as well as
                                        <quote rend="inline">the importance of dialogue and talk about respectful
                                        disagreement and the importance of class participation</quote> to
                                        continuing to “explore the dungeon” in an autonomous manner
                                                (<ptr target="#bali_2020"/> emphasis in the original)
                                        Moving by these premises, we think that digital technologies
                                        are an ideal means to promote student autonomy, as they
                                        provide a toolkit for students to navigate the learning
                                        process independently. This idea is further echoed by Cathy
                                        N. Davidson’s suggestion to structure a “student-centered
                                        class” that utilizes technology to the extent desired by the
                                        instructor, which allows the instructor to maintain control
                                        while also empowering students to take an active role in
                                        service of their pedagogical needs at the same time
                                        fostering a dynamic and rewarding learning environment that
                                        is flexible and effective <ptr target="#davidson_2020"/>.</p>
                                <p>Pete Rorabaugh (2020) draws from the idea that teaching is a
                                        moral act with significant implications for educators,
                                        including the ethical dimension, to argue that a critical
                                        approach to pedagogy is consistent with the goals of a
                                        digitally-infused curriculum because digital culture offers
                                        that digital tools have the potential to empower students in
                                        the digital sphere by providing them with new opportunities
                                        for human connectivity and enabling them to refocus on how
                                        power works in the classroom:
                                <quote rend="block">Digital tools offer the opportunity to refocus how power works in
                                        the classroom. In its evolution from passive consumption to
                                        critical production — from the cult of the expert to a
                                        culture of collaboration — the critical and digital
                                        classroom emerges as a site of intellectual and moral
                                        agency. <ptr target="#rorabaugh_2020"/></quote>
                                In Rorabaugh’s view, critical digital pedagogies aim to disrupt
                                        the conventional hierarchical structure of the classroom,
                                        allowing students to take charge of their learning and play
                                        an active role in their education. There is a moral
                                        obligation to engage learners in a democratic discovery of
                                        their own empowerment. By utilizing digital tools, students
                                        are given the opportunity to interact and collaborate with
                                        co-learners across various platforms on the internet.
                                        However, this kind of learning environment requires a
                                        critical pedagogue who is knowledgeable and skilled in
                                        selecting appropriate tools and activities and can blend
                                        them with an interactive learning community.</p>
                                <p>For us, the pandemic served as a catalyst for exploring new
                                        approaches to teaching and learning that prioritize critical
                                        thinking, student-centredness, and the thoughtful use of
                                        digital tools. Through the practical application of these
                                        principles, we have been able to create a new kind of
                                        classroom environment that is responsive to the
                                        post-pandemic needs and realities of our students, and that
                                        fosters engagement, collaboration, and meaningful learning
                                        experiences. As we continue to navigate the ongoing
                                        challenges presented by the pandemic and beyond, these
                                        principles will continue to guide our work as educators and
                                        serve as a foundation for innovative and effective
                                        pedagogical practices.</p></div>
                        <div>
                                <head>Conclusion</head>
                                <p>The implementation of Textual Communities as an environment to
                                        teach paleography proved to be advantageous from various
                                        perspectives. It is true that if we were ever to face a
                                        situation similar to that of March 2020 again, we would be
                                        able to move into online teaching almost effortlessly.
                                        However, using an online environment as a teaching resource
                                        has other advantages. Mainly, this environment enables
                                        students to find their own work rhythm.</p>
                                <p>Because paleography is a skill that improves with practice, it is
                                        not uncommon for beginners to experience significant
                                        difficulty and advance at what might seem a slow pace. As
                                        students practice, they are likely to work more efficiently
                                        and accurately. By using Textual Communities, our students
                                        can manage their time in a way that suits their personal
                                        circumstances. For example, someone might start a
                                        transcription during the allocated class period but not be
                                        able to finish it. At home, they can access the system and
                                        work at convenient times with each change recorded in the
                                        versioning component. As the students became familiar with
                                        Textual Communities, they were able to make arrangements for
                                        collaboration with others and create a system of peer
                                        evaluation and support to help each other become more
                                        accurate and achieve better results. Fostering this
                                        cooperative spirit led to the growth of the parties
                                        involved, not only in the study of paleography but also in
                                        their development as researchers and individuals. </p>
                                <p>It is certainly the case that the pandemic induced an
                                        acceleration in the usage of digital technologies in
                                        teaching and learning. While their initial adoption during
                                        the pandemic may have been driven by necessity, the tools’
                                        effectiveness in enhancing the learning experience can still
                                        be effective in the post-pandemic period, as we have
                                        demonstrated in our paper. The potential for innovation and
                                        renovation implicit in many arguments regarding the digital
                                        turn during the pandemic permeates initiatives such as ours.
                                        In seeing the pandemic as an opportunity to encourage
                                        educators to creatively utilize available resources, we
                                        transformed the challenge into an occasion for reorganizing
                                        the classroom space into a hybrid environment. The
                                        uncertainties of a post-pandemic world have compelled us to
                                        be more imaginative and resourceful, prompting us in ways we
                                        might not have considered before. We have been reminded that
                                        we can adapt successfully and find new ways to engage our
                                        students with our subject while giving them a sense of
                                        independence and freedom. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                                <head>Acknowledgments </head>
                                <p>The authors thank Victoria Simmons for contributing a reflection
                                        on classroom-based transcription practices, which has been
                                        included in this article, which helped shape our
                                        understanding of the students’ perspective. We also thank
                                        the referees and editors at DHQ for their thoughtful
                                        comments and recommendations on an earlier draft of this
                                        article.</p>
                        </div>
                </body>
                <back>
                        <listBibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="akbar_2016" label="Akbar 2016">Akbar, M. (2016) <title
                                                rend="quotes">Digital technology shaping teaching
                                                practices in higher education</title>, <title
                                                rend="italic">Frontiers in ICT</title> 3(1). <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.3389/fict.2016.00001"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.3389/fict.2016.00001</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="bali_2020" label="Bali 2020">Bali, M. (2020) <title
                                                rend="quotes">Critical pedagogy: Intentions and
                                                realities</title>, in Stommel, J., Friend, C., and
                                        Morris, S. M. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Critical digital
                                                pedagogy: A collection.</title> Hybrid Pedagogy Inc.
                                        Available at: <ref
                                                target="https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/chapter/critical-pedagogy-intentions-and-realities/"
                                                >https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/chapter/critical-pedagogy-intentions-and-realities/</ref>
                                        (Accessed: 16 October 2024).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="barrett-fox_et_al_2020"
                                        label="Barrett-Fox et al. 2020">Barrett-Fox, R., et al.
                                        (2020) <title rend="quotes">How the Coronavirus pandemic
                                                will change our future teaching</title>, <title
                                                rend="italic">Religion and American Culture</title>,
                                        30(2), pp.147–86. <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.1017/rac.2020.10"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.1017/rac.2020.10</ref></bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="benjamin_2020" label="Benjamin 2020"> Benjamin, R.
                                        (2020) <title rend="quotes">Foreword</title>, in Stommel,
                                        J., Friend, C., and Morris, S. M. (eds.), <title
                                                rend="italic">Critical digital pedagogy: A
                                                collection</title>. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. Available
                                        at: <ref
                                                target="https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/front-matter/foreword/"
                                                >https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/front-matter/foreword/</ref>
                                        (Accessed 16 October 2024).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="bordalejo_2024" label="Bordalejo 2024"> Bordalejo, B.
                                        (2024) <title rend="italic">ENG 3850/ HIST 3850 Paleography
                                                2023</title>. Zenodo. <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13941931"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13941931</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="bordalejo_and_robinson_2016"
                                        label="Bordalejo and Robinson 2024">Bordalejo, B., and
                                        Robinson, P. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Textual
                                                communities</title>, in <title rend="italic">Digital
                                                Humanities 2016</title>, pp. 876-77. Available at:
                                                <ref
                                                target="https://lirias.kuleuven.be/retrieve/534266"
                                                >https://lirias.kuleuven.be/retrieve/534266</ref>.
                                        (Accessed 25 April 2025).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="careaga-butter_et_al_2020"
                                        label="Careaga-Butter et al. 2020">Careaga-Butter, M.,
                                        Badilla Quintana, M. G., and Fuentes-Henríquez, C. (2020)
                                                <title rend="quotes">Critical and prospective
                                                analysis of online education in pandemic and
                                                post-pandemic contexts</title>, <title rend="italic"
                                                >Aloma: Revista de Psicologia, Ciències de
                                                l’Educació i de l’Esport</title>, 38(2), pp. 23–32.
                                                <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.51698/aloma.2020.38.2.23-32"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.51698/aloma.2020.38.2.23-32</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="davidson_2020" label="Davidson 2020">Davidson, C. N.
                                        (2020) <title rend="quotes">Why start with pedagogy? 4 good
                                                reasons, 4 good solutions</title>, in Stommel, J.,
                                        Friend, C., and Morris, S. M. (eds.), <title rend="italic"
                                                >Critical digital pedagogy: A collection</title>.
                                        Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. Available at: <ref
                                                target="https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/chapter/why-start-with-pedagogy-4-good-reasons-4-good-solutions/"
                                                >https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/chapter/why-start-with-pedagogy-4-good-reasons-4-good-solutions/</ref>.
                                        (Accessed: 16 October 2024).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="edgar_and_sedgwick_1999"
                                        label="Edgar and Sedgwick 1999">Edgar, A., and Sedgwick,
                                        P.R. (eds.) (1999) <title rend="italic">Key concepts in
                                                cultural theory</title>. Key Concepts Series.
                                        London; New York: Routledge.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="fellmayer_2020" label="Fellmayer 2020">Fellmayer, J.
                                        (2020) <title rend="quotes">Disruptive pedagogy and the
                                                practice of freedom</title>, in Stommel, J., Friend,
                                        C., and Morris, S. M. (eds.), <title rend="italic">Critical
                                                digital pedagogy: A collection</title>. Hybrid
                                        Pedagogy Inc. Available at: <ref
                                                target="https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/chapter/disruptive-pedagogy-and-the-practice-of-freedom/"
                                                >https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/chapter/disruptive-pedagogy-and-the-practice-of-freedom/</ref>.
                                        (Accessed: 16 October 2024).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="forti_2023" label="Forti 2023">Forti, L. (2023) <title
                                                rend="italic">Corpus use in Italian language
                                                pedagogy: Exploring the effects of data-driven
                                                learning</title>. 1st edn. Routledge Applied Corpus
                                        Linguistics. Abingdon, Oxon; New York, NY: Routledge.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="galbraith_and_merrill_2012"
                                        label="Galbraith and Merrill 2012">Galbraith, C. S., and
                                        Merrill, G. B. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Academic and
                                                work-related burnout: A longitudinal study of
                                                working undergraduate university business
                                                students</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of
                                                College Student Development</title>, 53(3), pp.
                                        453–63. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1353/csd.2012.0044"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.1353/csd.2012.0044</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="freire_2000" label="Freire 2000"> Freire, P. (2000)
                                        Pedagogy of the oppressed. 30th anniversary edn. New York:
                                        Continuum.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="gleason_and_manca_2020" label="Gleason and Manca 2020"
                                        >Gleason, B., and Manca, S. (2020) <title rend="quotes"
                                                >Curriculum and instruction: Pedagogical approaches
                                                to teaching and learning with Twitter in higher
                                                education</title>, <title rend="italic">On the
                                                Horizon</title>, 28(1), pp.1–8. <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.1108/OTH-03-2019-0014"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.1108/OTH-03-2019-0014</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="hofer_et_al_2021" label="Hofer et al. 2021">Hofer, S.
                                        I., Nistor, N., and Scheibenzuber, C. (2021) <title
                                                rend="quotes">Online teaching and learning in higher
                                                education: Lessons learned in crisis
                                                situations</title>, <title rend="italic">Computers
                                                in Human Behavior</title>, 121,106789. <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2021.106789"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2021.106789</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="hooks_1994" label="hooks 1994">hooks, b. (1994) <title
                                                rend="italic">Teaching to transgress: Education as
                                                the practice of freedom</title>. New York:
                                        Routledge. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="kim_2018" label="Kim 2018">Kim, D. (2018) <title
                                                rend="italic">Disrupting the digital
                                                humanities</title>. 1st edn. Santa Barbara, CA:
                                        Punctum Books.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="lai_2011" label="Lai 2011">Lai, K.-W. (2011) <title
                                                rend="quotes">Digital technology and the culture of
                                                teaching and learning in higher education</title>,
                                                <title rend="italic">Australasian Journal of
                                                Educational Technology</title> 27(8). <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.14742/ajet.892"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.14742/ajet.892</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="law_2007" label="Law 2007">Law, D. W. (2007) <title
                                                rend="quotes">Exhaustion in university students and
                                                the effect of coursework involvement</title>, <title
                                                rend="italic">Journal of American College
                                                Health</title>, 55(4), pp. 239–245. <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.14742/ajet.892"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.3200/JACH.55.4.239-245</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="lohr_et_al_2021" label="Lohr et al. 2021"> Lohr, A.,
                                        et al. (2021) <title rend="quotes">On powerpointers,
                                                clickerers, and digital pros: Investigating the
                                                initiation of digital learning activities by
                                                teachers in higher education</title>, <title
                                                rend="italic">Computers in Human Behavior</title>,
                                        119, 106715. <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2021.106715"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2021.106715</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="mauss_1966" label="Mauss 1966">Mauss, M. (1966) <title
                                                rend="italic">The gift: Forms and functions of
                                                exchange in archaic societies</title>. London: Cohen
                                        and West LTD. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="murphy_2020" label="Murphy 2020"> Murphy, M. P. A.
                                        (2020) <title rend="quotes">COVID-19 and emergency
                                                eLearning: Consequences of the securitization of
                                                higher education for post-pandemic pedagogy</title>,
                                                <title rend="italic">Contemporary Security
                                                Policy</title>, 41(3), pp. 492–505. <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.1080/13523260.2020.1761749"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.1080/13523260.2020.1761749</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="odonnell_et_al_2016a" label="O'Donnell et al. 2016a"
                                        sortKey="Odonnell1">O’Donnell, D. P. (2016a) ‘A first law of
                                        humanities computing.’ Journal of Brief Ideas. Available at:
                                        http://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/2887a2c8127dea5e64e512ae7f6a2407.
                                        (Accessed 25 April 2025).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="odonnell_et_al_2016b" label="O'Donnell et al. 2016b"
                                        sortKey="Odonnell2">O’Donnell, D. P., et al. (2016b). <title
                                                rend="quotes">The third academic freedom</title>,
                                                <title rend="italic">Light on Teaching</title>, pp.
                                        4–9. <ref target="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3596098"
                                                >http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3596098</ref>.
                                        (Accessed 25 April 2025).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="rinaldo_et_al_2011" label="Rinaldo et al. 2011">
                                        Rinaldo, S. B., Tapp, S., and Laverie, A.D. (2011) <title
                                                rend="quotes">Learning by tweeting: Using Twitter as
                                                a pedagogical tool</title>, <title rend="italic"
                                                >Journal of Marketing Education</title>, 33(2), pp.
                                        193–203. <ref
                                                target="https://doi-org.uleth.idm.oclc.org/10.1177/0273475311410852"
                                                >https://doi-org.uleth.idm.oclc.org/10.1177/0273475311410852</ref>.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="rorabaugh_2020" label="Rorabaugh 2020">Rorabaugh, P.
                                        (2020) <title rend="quotes">Occupy the digital: Critical
                                                pedagogy and new media</title>, in Stommel, J.
                                        Friend, C. and Morris, S. M. (eds.), <title rend="italic"
                                                >Critical digital pedagogy: A collection</title>.
                                        Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. Available at: <ref
                                                target="https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/chapter/occupy-the-digital-critical-pedagogy-and-new-media/"
                                                >https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/chapter/occupy-the-digital-critical-pedagogy-and-new-media/</ref>.
                                        (Accessed: 16 October 2024).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="robinson_et_al_2012" label="Robinson et al. 2012">
                                        Robinson, P., Nelson, B., and Klaassen, F. (2012) <title
                                                rend="quotes">The textual communities
                                                project</title>, <title rend="italic"
                                                >Interedition</title>. Available at: <ref
                                                target="https://www.interedition.eu/wp-content/bestanden/2012/03/7_2.pdf"
                                                >https://www.interedition.eu/wp-content/bestanden/2012/03/7_2.pdf</ref>.
                                        (Accessed 25 April 2025).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="robinson_and_solopova_1993"
                                        label="Robinson and Solopova 1993">Robinson, P, and
                                        Solopova, E. (1993) <title rend="quotes">Guidelines for
                                                transcription of the manuscripts of the wife of
                                                bath’s prologue</title>, in: Blake, N.F., Robinson,
                                        P.M.W. (eds.), The Canterbury Tales Project Occasional
                                        Papers, Office for Humanities Communication Publications.
                                        Office for Humanities Communication, Oxford, pp. 19–52. <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.11954055"
                                                >https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.11954055</ref></bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="spencer_2018" label="Spencer 2018">Spencer, D. C. K.
                                        (2018) <title rend="quotes">Disrupting labor in digital
                                                humanities; Or, the classroom is not your
                                                crowd</title>, in D. Kim (ed.), <title rend="italic"
                                                >Disrupting the digital humanities</title>. 1st edn.
                                        Santa Barbara, CA: Punctum Books, pp. 273–94.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="stack_overflow_2024" label="Stack Overflow 2024">Stack
                                        Overflow. (2024) <title rend="quotes">Stackoverflow
                                                developer survey</title>. Available at: <ref
                                                target="https://survey.stackoverflow.co/2024/technology"
                                                >https://survey.stackoverflow.co/2024/technology</ref>.
                                        (Accessed 25 April 2025).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="stommel_et_al_2020a" label="Stommel et al. 2020a"
                                        sortKey="Stommel1">Stommel, J., Friend, C., and Morris, M.
                                        S. (eds.) (2020a)<title rend="italic"> Critical digital
                                                pedagogy: A collection</title>. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc.
                                        Available at: <ref
                                                target="https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/"
                                                >https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/</ref>.
                                        (Accessed 16 October 2024).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="stommel_et_al_2020b" label="Stommel et al. 2020b"
                                        sortKey="Stommel2"> Stommel, J., Friend, C., and Morris, M.
                                        S. (eds.) (2020b) <title rend="quotes">Introduction</title>
                                        in Stommel, J. Friend, C. and Morris, S. M. (eds.), <title
                                                rend="italic">Critical digital pedagogy: A
                                                collection</title>. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. Available
                                        at: <ref
                                                target="https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/front-matter/introduction/"
                                                >https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/front-matter/introduction/</ref>.
                                        (Accessed 16 October 2024).</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="thomas_and_blackwood_2010"
                                        label="Thomas and Blackwood 2010">Thomas, J. D. E., and
                                        Blackwood, M. (2010) <title rend="quotes">Computer literacy
                                                and non-IS majors</title>, <title rend="italic"
                                                >Information Systems Education Journal</title>
                                        8(58). <ref target="https://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ1146785"
                                                >https://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ1146785</ref>. </bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="torsello_et_al_2008" label="Torsello et al. 2008">
                                        Torsello, C. S., Ackerley, K., and Castello, E. (eds.)
                                        (2008) <title rend="italic">Corpora for university language
                                                teachers</title>. 74. Bristol: Peter Lang Group
                                        AG.</bibl>
                                <bibl xml:id="wilcken_1932" label="Wilcken 1932"> Wilcken, U. (1932)
                                                <title rend="quotes">Das Leydener
                                                Klammersystem</title>. <title rend="italic">Archiv
                                                Für Papyrusforschung</title> 10, pp. 211–12.</bibl>

                        </listBibl>
                </back>
        </text>
</TEI>
