<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Coca-Cola: An Icon of the American Way of Life.
                    An Iterative Text Mining Workflow for Analyzing Advertisements in Dutch
                    Twentieth-Century Newspapers<!-- article title in English --></title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Melvin <dhq:family>Wevers</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>DH Group, KNAW HUC, Amsterdam, The
                        Netherlands</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>melvin.wevers@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Melvin Wevers is a postdoctoral researcher at the Digital Humanities
                            Group of the KNAW Humanities Cluster in Amsterdam, the Netherlands. In
                            his research, he combines techniques from text mining and computer
                            vision to study cultural-historical phenomena. His PhD research focused
                            on the representation of the United States in Dutch public discourse on
                            consumer goods.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Jesper <dhq:family>Verhoef</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>TU Delft, Delft, The Netherlands</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>j.verhoef-2@tudelft.nl</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Jesper Verhoef, PhD, is a lecturer at Delft University of Technology. He
                            obtained his PhD in Cultural History at Utrecht University. In his
                            dissertation, entitled ‘Contested modernization. America and Dutch
                            identity in public discourse on media, 1919-1989’, he applied various
                            digital techniques.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000338<!-- including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110 --></idno>
                <idno type="volume">011<!-- volume number, with leading zeroes: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue">4<!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date when="2018-01-08">8 January 2018</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>text analysis</item>
                        <item>cultural history</item>
                        <item>americanization</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="DD" when="2017-10-10">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This article analyses advertisements to shed light on the ways in which the
                    Coca-Cola Company tried to shape the Dutch perception of an American way of
                    life, and by extension provided the discursive building blocks for the
                    construction of a mental map of America. Since the National Library of the
                    Netherlands (KB) digitized its newspaper collection, we could analyze newspapers
                    using both computational and traditional means. The central question this
                    article addresses is: Did Coca-Cola advertisements in Dutch newspapers
                    communicate themes that represented the American way of life? Using two separate
                    workflows, we demonstrate how we combined computational and traditional methods
                    in an iterative and transparent manner. These workflows are systematic
                    descriptions of how we used computational tools to answer this paper’s central
                    research question.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>This article analyses advertisements to shed light on the ways in which the
                    Coca-Cola Company tried to shape the Dutch perception of an American way of life
                    and provided the discursive building blocks for the construction of a mental map
                    of America</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>1. Introduction</head>
                <p>In 1938, the American newspaper editor William Allen White famously described
                    Coca-Cola as the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#pendergrast2000">sublimated essence of all that America stands for — a
                            decent thing, honestly made, universally distributed, conscientiously
                            improved with the years</quote>
                        <ptr target="#pendergrast2000" loc="183"/>
                    </cit>. Ever since, scholars have described Coca-Cola as the quintessential
                    representation of American values, ideas, and practices, or rather as the
                    American way of life. For many European businesses, states, and consumer groups
                    the American way of life was a model they sought to mimic <ptr target="#oldenziel2013" loc="195"/>. This model based on cultural ideas,
                    policies, and practices emerged onto the European market in the twentieth
                    century alongside American businesses and American consumer goods <ptr target="#nolan2012" loc="36"/>. According to Richard Pells, in the eyes of
                    European consumers no other <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#pells1997">export served as a more potent symbol of the American
                            way of life than Coke</quote>
                        <ptr target="#pells1997" loc="199"/>
                    </cit>. Greg Castillo, however, rightly points out that scholars should not
                    approach American products, such as Coca-Cola, as <q>ironclad vehicles of an
                        American way of life.</q> He argues that they need to be studied as
                        <q>indeterminate signifiers</q> within their local context separated from
                    their original U.S. context <ptr target="#castillo2010" loc="xiv"/>. This is
                    precisely what this article sets out to do: to analyze to what extent Coca-Cola
                    functioned as a symbol of an American way of life within the Netherlands. </p>
                <p>The specific interpretation of an iconic brand such as Coca-Cola within a
                    national context can, according to Douglas Holt, reveal the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#holt2004">collective anxieties and desires of a nation</quote>
                        <ptr target="#holt2004" loc="6"/>
                    </cit>. Mark Pendergrast, in other words, underlines that the local
                    interpretation of Coca-Cola has functioned as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#pendergrast2000">the best barometer of the relationship with the
                            US</quote>
                        <ptr target="#pendergrast2000" loc="243"/>
                    </cit>. Hence, Dutch newspaper discourse not only offers a lens on the local
                    framing of Coca-Cola and its symbolic connotations but also on the position of
                    Dutch consumers vis-à-vis the United States.</p>
                <p>The United States had a strong cultural, economic, and political presence in the
                    Netherlands throughout the twentieth century. The Dutch perception of this
                    American presence vacillated between bouts of anti-Americanism and
                    pro-Americanism. In the interwar period (1919-1939), as American cultural
                    products such as movies appeared in the Netherlands, Dutch interest in American
                    culture grew, despite anti-Americanism voiced by intellectuals such as Johan
                    Huizinga <ptr target="#toebes1996"/>
                    <ptr target="#kroes1986"/>
                    <ptr target="#verhoef2015a"/>. After the Second World War, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#roholl1992">the attention of the Dutch population was actively
                            focused on America, the new model country</quote>
                        <ptr target="#roholl1992" loc="152"/>
                    </cit> (see also: <ptr target="#kennedy2009" loc="931–48"/>; <ptr target="#schuyt2004" loc="407–10"/>). Especially when it came to new
                    consumption patterns, scholars point out that the Dutch perceived America as a
                    guiding country <ptr target="#roholl1992"/>
                    <ptr target="#elteren1990"/>
                    <ptr target="#schot1997"/>. The Vietnam War incited a new kind of
                    anti-Americanism in the Netherlands. The U.S. politics of war mustered up fierce
                    protests in the late 1960s and early 70s <ptr target="#hellema2012" loc="63"/>
                    <ptr target="#kroes1986" loc="44–45"/>
                    <ptr target="#rossem1981" loc="26–27"/>. Amid anti-American protests, youth did
                    not <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#nolan2012">reject American mass culture, even as they attacked the
                            excesses of consumerism</quote>
                        <ptr target="#nolan2012" loc="277–78"/>
                    </cit>. This illustrates that Dutch feelings of anti-Americanism were not
                    unequivocal, rather they were marred by ambivalence. Little is known, however,
                    about how American consumer goods, such as Coca-Cola, contributed to the Dutch
                    attitude toward the United States. </p>
                <p>We analyzed advertisements to shed light on the ways in which the Coca-Cola
                    Company shaped the Dutch perception of an American way of life, and by extension
                    provided the discursive building blocks for the construction of a mental map of
                    America <ptr target="#eijnatten2013"/>. Since the National Library of the
                    Netherlands (KB) digitized its newspaper collection, we could analyze newspapers
                    using both computational and traditional means.<note> This archive contains over
                        600,000 digitized newspaper editions between 1890 and 1990. Or 76,201,582
                        documents, which comprise articles, advertisements, personal announcements,
                        and captioned illustrations.</note> Advertisements provide a valuable source
                    of information which <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#trtovac2014">fully reflects the spirit of the past, [as it]
                            indicates development of certain industries, but also covers all aspects
                            of cultural and social life</quote>
                        <ptr target="#trtovac2014" loc="9"/>
                    </cit>. Even though the principal motivation of advertisers was to sell
                    products, as Roland Marchand points out <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#marchand1985">advertisers also communicated broader assumption about
                            social values</quote>
                        <ptr target="#marchand1985" loc="xviii"/>
                    </cit>. One of these social values was <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#sassatelli2007">consumption as a way of life</quote>
                        <ptr target="#sassatelli2007" loc="115"/>
                    </cit>. Scholars describe the ethic of consumption as constitutive of the
                    American way of life <ptr target="#lears1994" loc="235–36"/>
                    <ptr target="#mcgovern2006" loc="262"/>. Therefore, the central question this
                    article addresses is: in what ways did Coca-Cola advertisements in Dutch
                    newspapers communicate themes that represented the American way of life?</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. Computational Tools for Cultural Historians</head>
                <p>The application of computational methods in humanities research has led to fierce
                    debates. These frequently focus on the practice of <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#moretti2013">distant reading</quote>
                        <ptr target="#moretti2013"/>
                    </cit>, which denotes reading <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#nicholson2012">the archive from a distance</quote>
                        <ptr target="#nicholson2012" loc="246"/>
                    </cit> and more specifically <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#kirschenbaum2007">the automated search for patterns</quote>
                        <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2007"/>
                    </cit> in vast corpora of text. In these debates, we identify three groups of
                    scholars. One group heralds the merits or <soCalled>the bright sight</soCalled>
                    of distant reading (e.g. <ptr target="#graham2015"/>; <ptr target="#eijnattenetal2013"/>); whereas another warns against the
                        <soCalled>siren call</soCalled> of such methods (e.g. <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2014"/>; <ptr target="#hitchcock2014"/>). Most
                    scholars, however, offer a more nuanced perspective and contend that we have to
                    move beyond the false dichotomy between traditional and computational methods.
                    They argue that computational methods are an addition to, not a replacement of
                    traditional, humanistic interpretation (e.g. <ptr target="#berry2011"/>; <ptr target="#blaxill2013"/>; <ptr target="#bod2013"/>; <ptr target="#porsdam2013"/>; <ptr target="#ramsay2011"/>; <ptr target="#rieder2012"/>; <ptr target="#ross2014"/>; <ptr target="#underwood2016"/>). This is a view we share. Researchers can achieve
                        <q>synergistic interaction</q> by <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayles2012">‘rapid shuttling’ between quantitative information and
                            hermeneutic close reading</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayles2012" loc="31"/>
                    </cit>. Moreover, we concur with Matthew Kirschenbaum: Digital Humanities is <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#kirschenbaum2014">work (…). So let’s talk about this work, in action,
                            this actually existing work</quote>
                        <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2014" loc="61"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p> Within the field of cultural history, relatively few examples of actual digital
                    historical research have appeared <ptr target="#blaxill2013" loc="318"/>
                    <ptr target="#nicholson2013" loc="63"/>. This is surprising since analyzing
                    texts is among cultural historians’ core business. Using words like
                        <q>potential,</q>
                    <q>promise,</q> and <q>possibilities</q> to address the prospects of digital
                    techniques, Cameron Blevins maintains, historians talk the talk, but rarely walk
                    the walk. Therefore, he urges historians to practice what they preach and start
                        <emph>doing</emph> digital historical research <ptr target="#blevins2015"/>.
                    Others add that they should do so in an explicit manner: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#gibbs2013">the creation of, interaction with, and interpretation
                            of data must become more integral to historical writing</quote>
                        <ptr target="#gibbs2013"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>This article takes these pleas to heart. By means of two separate workflows, we
                    demonstrate how we combined computational and traditional methods in an
                    iterative and transparent manner. These workflows are systematic descriptions of
                    how we used computational tools to answer this paper’s central research
                    question. Workflow A (Figure 1) describes how n-gram analysis and full-text
                    searching are apt methods to construct a sub-corpus from a larger corpus of
                    textual data. Used in combination with close reading of specific documents,
                    these methods guide the construction of a sub-corpus. Subsequently, workflow B
                    (Figure 2) lays out how we explored a sub-corpus using AntConc, a corpus
                    analysis toolkit. Workflow B offers various strands of analytical information
                    derived from distant reading and shows how they directed close reading. In
                    answering the research question, we constantly moved back and forth between
                    these modes of analysis. </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Workflow A: constructing a sub-corpus</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <head>Workflow B: analyzing a sub-corpus</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3. Workflow A: Constructing a Sub-Corpus of Coca-Cola Advertisements</head>
                <p>Before being able to answer whether advertisements linked Coca-Cola to an
                    American way of life, it is necessary to answer the following questions. Did the
                    Coca-Cola Company advertise Coca-Cola in Dutch newspapers? If so, when and how
                    frequently? Answering these kinds of descriptive questions has changed
                    considerably with the advent of n-gram viewers and full-text searching as
                    instruments to query digitized archives. Researchers can now use single or
                    strings of keywords to trace specific words or concepts without having to
                    manually browse through the archive to find them (e.g. <ptr target="#nicholson2013"/>; <ptr target="#bingham2010"/>). </p>
                <p> In our research the use of an n-gram viewers served two principal functions.
                    First, it helped to quickly locate specific words in a corpus, which aided the
                    construction of our sub-corpus. By inputting keywords in an n-gram viewer, the
                    tool produced an instant overview of the frequency of words in the corpus
                    relative to the total number of words in one year within the corpus. The graphs
                    generated by n-gram viewers enabled us to compare and trace n-grams to pinpoint
                    continuities and discontinuities in language. This made the mapping of ideas,
                    practices, and products within digitized sources more comprehensive and
                    rigorous. </p>
                <p>The KB n-gram viewer offered a quick way to establish whether and when Dutch
                    newspapers wrote about Coca-Cola.<note>
                        <ref target="http://politicalmashup.nl/">http://politicalmashup.nl/</ref></note> The visualization produced by the
                    KB n-gram viewer (Figure 3) displays the occurrence of the n-grams
                        <q>Coca-Cola</q>, <q>Coca Cola</q>, and <q>Cola</q>.<note> The N-gram viewer
                        does not represent the complete corpus, for instance, 1-grams that were in
                        the corpus <emph>less </emph>than two times – presumably frequently
                        OCR-errors – are not included. </note> Figure 3 shows that <q>Coca-Cola</q>
                    first appeared in this corpus in 1928.<note> The digitized newspaper corpus does
                        not contain all newspapers, and the digitized newspapers contain frequent
                        OCR errors. Therefore, it is difficult to ascertain within 100% certainty
                        that this is actually the first mention of <q>Coca-Cola</q>. </note>
                    Thereafter, newspapers spent relatively little attention to the caramel-colored
                    beverage. After the Second World War, the number of publications steadily rose,
                    and then remained stable until 1974 after which <q>Coca-Cola</q> decreased and
                        <q>Coca Cola</q> sharply increased. <q>Cola</q> increased in tandem with
                        <q>Coca Cola</q>, which coincided with the growing popularity of soft drinks
                    in the Netherlands. In 1958, soft drink consumption in the Netherlands was ten
                    liters per capita. By 1968, this number had drastically increased up to fifty
                    liters per capita <ptr target="#zwaal1993" loc="20"/>. In short, this graph
                    shows when and how often newspapers wrote about Coca-Cola.</p>
                <p> Secondly, we used the KB n-gram viewer to compare the relative occurrence of
                    different consumer goods, which added context to the prevalence of Coca-Cola
                    (cf. <ptr target="#blaxill2013" loc="319"/>). For example, the visualization
                    (Figure 4) of the n-grams <q><emph>koffie</emph></q> (coffee) and
                            <q><emph>bier</emph></q> (beer) shows that coverage of these consumer
                    goods eclipsed that of Coca-Cola. This suggests that Coca-Cola was not a staple
                    good, whereas beer and coffee were. </p>
                <p> The information gathered from the visualizations produced by the KB n-gram
                    viewer necessitated critical interpretation. First, this particular viewer does
                    not offer the option to distinguish between colonial and non-colonial Dutch
                    newspapers, nor can users discriminate articles from advertisements.<note>
                        Unlike the website <ref target="http://www.delpher.nl">www.delpher.nl</ref>,
                        which does allow users to differentiate between articles and
                        advertisements.</note> Put differently, from this visualization alone, we
                    could not determine whether Coca-Cola appeared in advertisements, articles, or
                    both. Secondly, the KB erroneously digitized numerous newspapers editions twice,
                    most notably the popular Dutch newspaper <title rend="italic">De
                        Telegraaf</title> between 1970 and 1978. This heavily skews the n-gram
                    visualization from the 1970s onwards. To overcome these objections, we turned to
                    full-text searching to further refine our sub-corpus. </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>N-grams <q>Coca-Cola</q>, <q>Coca Cola</q>, and <q>Cola</q>
                        <ref target="http://kbkranten.politicalmashup.nl/#q/coca-cola|coca                         cola|cola">http://kbkranten.politicalmashup.nl/#q/coca-cola|coca
                        cola|cola</ref></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <head>N-gram <q>Coca-Cola</q>, <q>Coca Cola</q>, <q>Koffie</q>, and <q>Bier</q>
                        <ref target="http://kbkranten.politicalmashup.nl/#q/coca-cola|coca                             cola|koffie|bier">http://kbkranten.politicalmashup.nl/#q/coca-cola|coca
                            cola|koffie|bier</ref></head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                </figure>
                <div>
                    <head>3.1 Full-text searching </head>
                    <p>After roughly establishing when and how often newspapers mentioned Coca-Cola,
                        we turned to full-text searching to assemble a sub-corpus of Coca-Cola
                        advertisements. We used the text mining tool Texcavator to query the
                        digitized newspaper corpus. This tool was developed as part of the research
                        project Translantis <ptr target="#eijnattenetal2014"/>
                        <ptr target="#eijnattenetal2013"/>
                        <ptr target="#huijnen2012"/>. Using this tool, we filtered results based on
                        metadata such as article type (advertisement, article, personal
                        announcement, and captioned illustration), newspaper type (regional,
                        colonial, and national), periodization, and newspaper title. Furthermore, we
                        used wildcards, Boolean operators, and fuzzy matching to improve the
                        relevant number of hits associated with a query <ptr target="#blaxill2013" loc="328–30"/>. As such, full-text searching enabled a more extensive
                        and advanced way of mapping the corpus than the n-gram viewer was able to
                            do.<note> Unfortunately, this tool is based on the same faulty corpus as
                            the KB n-gram viewer. For the following steps, we first exported the
                            sub-corpus and removed the duplicate advertisements using a Python
                            script. </note>
                    </p>
                    <p> The first step in locating Coca-Cola advertisements involved determining
                        whether Coca-Cola actually advertised in Dutch national and regional
                        newspapers. Searching for <q>Coca-Cola</q> yielded numerous advertisements.
                        These were not only advertisements for Coca-Cola, but also for the soft
                        drink brands Fanta and Sprite. The Coca-Cola Company also produced these
                        drinks and was therefore mentioned.<note> Moreover, the textual information
                            in advertisement was not always recognized as such during the
                            digitization of the newspapers. As a result, the recall of the querying
                            software is sub-optimal, i.e. instances in which the word Coca-Cola was
                            part of the image were more difficult to find by full-text
                            querying.</note> Since we were only interested in the role of Coca-Cola,
                        we excluded these by altering our search query.<note> Resulting in the
                            following query: +(“coca-cola” “coca cola”) -(“fanta” OR
                            “sprite”).</note> We relied on probes of close reading to improve our
                        search query, which corroborates the interdependence between close and
                        distant reading. </p>
                    <p> The refined search query found 2,905 advertisements in regional and national
                        newspapers published between 1890 and 1990. In the same period, 4,517
                        advertisements contained <q>Cola</q> without mentioning
                            <q>Coca-Cola</q>.<note> +(“cola”) -(“coca-cola” “coca cola” “sprite”
                            “fanta”).</note> This demonstrates that Coca-Cola advertisements formed
                        a large portion (39.1%) of the advertisements for Cola beverages.<note>
                            (2,905 advertisements / 7,422 Cola advertisements) * 100 ≈ 39.1</note>
                        Advertisements for Coca-Cola (n = 2,905) and Cola drinks — both Coca-Cola and
                        other brands — (n = 7,422) formed only a small portion of all the digitized
                        newspaper advertisements (n = 18,645,511); only 0,016% contained
                            <q>Coca-Cola</q> and 0,040% <q>Cola</q>. This shows that Coca-Cola was
                        the most dominant Cola brand, but in relation to the overall advertising
                        corpus the ads for Coca-Cola formed a relatively small portion.</p>
                    <p> The timelines in Figure 5 show the absolute and relative annual frequency of
                        Coca-Cola advertisements.<note> The relative frequency expresses the number
                            of Coca-Cola advertisements per 100,000 advertisements. </note> In order
                        to compare the proportion — and thus significance — of Coca-Cola advertisements
                        between periods, we normalized the absolute frequency of Coca-Cola to the
                        total number of advertisements in the corpus. These timelines show that the
                        first advertisements appeared during the 1928 Olympics in Amsterdam when the
                        Coca-Cola Company launched the beverage in the Netherlands <ptr target="#zwaal1993" loc="72–73"/>.<note> This is the first advertisement
                            in this particular digitized corpus. OCR problems might have obstructed
                            the discovery of possible earlier advertisements. </note> Figure 5 also
                        demonstrates that after 1929 the number of Coca-Cola advertisements
                        dwindled, and started to grow again around 1950. From the 1960s onwards, the
                        relative number of Coca-Cola advertised stayed relatively stable (green
                        line) while the absolute number of advertisements (blue line) mushroomed.
                        These peaks in absolute frequency correlate with a general increase of
                        advertisements in the digitized newspaper corpus, which rose from 163,666 in
                        1960 to 275,585 advertisements in 1980. After normalization, these peaks
                        slimmed down and suggest that the proportion of Coca-Cola advertisements
                        within the total corpus of advertisement did not change substantially. </p>
                    <p>Contextualizing these results by close reading shows that the majority of
                        advertisements in the 1970s consisted of job ads by the Coca-Cola Company or
                        advertisements authored by others, such as supermarket chains.<note> The
                            presence of job ads is indicated by the occurrence of words such as ‘job
                            interview’ (<emph>sollicitatie*, </emph>n = 463), <q>experience</q>
                                (<emph>ervaring, </emph>n = 260), <q>wage</q> (<emph>salaris,
                            </emph>n = 181), and <q>education</q> (<emph>opleiding, </emph>n =
                            170).</note> Even though this is an interesting find, the focus here is
                        on how the Coca-Cola Company advertised Coca-Cola. Close readings of
                        advertisements in the other periods exhibited that the majority of
                        advertisements in the sub-corpus were indeed advertisements by the Coca-Cola
                        Company. For this reason, the following analysis will focus on a sub-corpus
                        of Coca-Cola advertisements published between 1928 and 1970. In the next
                        workflow, we show how we analyzed this sub-corpus of Coca-Cola
                        advertisements. </p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Absolute frequency (blue) and relative frequency (green) of
                                <q>Coca-Cola</q> and <q>Coca Cola</q> in Dutch newspapers</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4. Workflow B: Analyzing Coca-Cola Advertisements </head>
                <p>The analysis underlying this workflow consisted of three steps. First, we set out
                    to establish whether the Coca-Cola Company explicitly linked Coca-Cola to the
                    United States. Next, we used AntConc to discern two central themes in Coca-Cola
                    advertisements. Lastly, we examined to what extent these themes signified an
                    American way of life.</p>
                <div>
                    <head> 4.1 How American was Coca-Cola? </head>
                    <p>We looked at the co-occurrence of references to the United States and
                        Coca-Cola to determine whether the Coca-Cola Company related its leading
                        drink to the United States. When calculating the frequency of these
                        co-occurrences, we used context words and a context horizon — two
                        functionalities offered by AntConc. Context words are words that must appear
                        within a set distance — a context horizon — to the search word. We set this
                        distance to ten words to the right and ten to the left of a search word. In
                        our case the context words included different ways of referring to the
                        United States as expressed by the search query: <q>coca?cola</q>.<note> The
                            context words were <q>ameri?a*</q>, <q>vereenigde staten</q>,
                                <q>verenigde staten</q>, <q>usa</q>, <q>u.s.a.</q>, and <q>united
                                states</q>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>We used context words and a context horizon for two reasons. First, the OCR
                        software did not always correctly compartmentalize the advertisements in the
                        newspaper corpus during digitization. Especially in the case of classified
                        ads, the software grouped multiple ads as one single advertisement <ptr target="#verhoef2015b"/>. There are instances where <q>Coca-Cola</q> and
                            <q>America</q> appeared in the actual newspapers in two separate
                        advertisements, whereas after digitization, they were indexed as one single
                        advertisement. A context horizon required the search word and the context
                        words to be in close proximity, which reduced faulty results produced by
                        composite advertisements in which the search word and context words would
                        often be further apart. </p>
                    <p>Secondly, the co-occurrence of two words does not necessarily indicate a
                        relationship between them; it merely suggests the possibility of a
                        relationship. By setting a context horizon, we only looked for references to
                        America in the proximity of <q>Coca-Cola</q>. The proximity we selected is a
                        good indicator of a semantic relationship between words <ptr target="#togninibonelli2001" loc="101"/>.</p>
                    <p>Using the context words and the context horizon, AntConc yielded not a single
                        document in which Coca-Cola and a reference to the United States
                        co-occurred. As this was an unanticipated result, we established whether
                            <q>coca-cola</q> co-occurred with <q>america</q> in advertisements
                        without being in each other’s proximity. This was the case in fifty-one
                        advertisements. We did a close reading of these advertisements, which
                        corroborated that the Coca-Cola Company did not explicitly advertise
                        Coca-Cola as an American product. It also confirmed that most of the
                        co-occurrences resulted from grouped advertisements, or from advertisements
                        in which the words were unrelated. This verified the advantages of setting a
                        context horizon and using context words. </p>
                    <p>A full-text search for the phrase <soCalled>American Cola</soCalled> in the
                        entire corpus of advertisements produced sixty-six results.<note>
                                +(<q>amerikaanse cola</q>
                            <q>amerikaansche cola</q>
                            <q>american cola</q>
                            <q>cola uit amerika</q>).</note> Close examination of these articles
                        showed that from 1964 onwards, retailers and producers other than the
                        Coca-Cola Company occasionally presented Colas as American cola. For
                        instance, the American brand Royal Crown specifically branded its drinks as
                            <soCalled>real American Cola.</soCalled><note>
                            <title rend="quotes">Royal Crown Cola advertisement,</title>” <title rend="italic">Limburgsch Dagblad</title>, December 20, 1966.</note>
                        This shows that other brands explicitly promoted their Cola as American,
                        while the Coca-Cola Company refused to explicitly present its cola as an
                        American cola.</p>
                    <p>Overall, searching for co-occurrences offered an inkling of possible trends
                        in the corpus, in this case that the Coca-Cola Company did not explicitly
                        associate Coca-Cola with America or the United States. Moreover, these
                        searches also ruled out that advertisers used the phrase <q>the American way
                            of life.</q> If Coca-Cola advertisements depicted an American way of
                        life, or referred to the United States, they did so in implicit terms or
                        through visual content.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4.2 A Symbolic Depiction of an American Way of Life </head>
                    <p>In the next step of the analysis, we examined whether Coca-Cola
                        advertisements included themes that might symbolize an American way of life.
                        For this purpose, we used AntConc’s clustering, concordancing, collocation,
                        and word frequency functionalities. We used clustering to detect common
                        phrases that contain specific keywords. Collocation was used to look for
                        words that co-occurred within a specified context horizon <ptr target="#sinclair2004" loc="10"/>. We looked for collocates within a
                        window span of five words to the left and five to the right, and a minimum
                        collocate frequency of ten. We did not use the MI-score that is able to
                        calculate the strength of the collocation as it is not very useful for
                        analyzing advertisements, since these tend to be relatively short. AntConc’s
                        concordancing option allowed us to quickly determine the context in which
                        the discovered words and phrases appeared. Moreover, we turned to the word
                        frequency functionality for a list of all the words and their frequencies
                        within the corpus. </p>
                    <p> In order to keep track of possible changes within advertising discourse, we
                        divided the sub-corpus of Coca-Cola advertisements into four ten-year
                        periods: 1928-1937 (n = 220), 1938-1947 (n = 53), 1948-1957 (n = 372), and
                        1958-1967 (n = 414). Collocation analysis demonstrated that the relatively
                        small set of advertisements between 1938 and 1947 contained no collocates
                        that were of historical relevance. Therefore, our analysis focused on
                        1928-1937, 1948-1957, and 1958-1967.<note> See Appendix A for a list of the
                            collocates.</note></p>
                    <p> From the list of collocates from all three periods, we discerned two themes:
                        the drink’s international and local connotation of the drink, and
                        Coca-Cola’s refreshing and invigorating taste. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head> 4.3 Coca-Cola: Not an American, but a Glocal Brand </head>
                    <p>The first element in Coca-Cola advertisement was the international character
                        of the drink, as expressed by the following words: <q>world</q>,
                            <q>countries</q>, and <q>international</q>.<note>
                            <q><emph>wereld</emph></q>, <q><emph>landen</emph></q>, and
                                    <q><emph>internationale</emph></q>.</note> Advertisements in the
                        interwar period put more emphasis on this theme, as evinced by the higher
                        relative frequency of these words in this period. Figure 6 shows how the
                        international aspect of Coca-Cola appeared during its introduction in the
                        Netherlands in 1928 and 1929, and then virtually disappeared from
                        advertisements until the 1950s. When the drink re-appeared in the 1950s the
                        international aspect more clearly was part of Coca-Cola’s brand identity. As
                        early as 1929, one advertisement read: <q>Coca-Cola quickly conquered the
                            entire world. In Europe, Coca-Cola is the most beloved drink in all the
                            trendsetting places.</q><note>
                            <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">Het Volk</title>, June 3, 1929. <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">Coca-Cola veroverde spoedig de gehele wereld. In
                                    Europa, is Coca-Cola nu de meest geliefde drank in alle
                                    toonaangevende plaatsen.</foreign></q></note> After 1929, the
                        connotation to the brand’s global popularity seems to have disappeared from
                        advertisements. It is important to keep in mind that the number of
                        advertisements between 1930 and 1950 was relatively low, which explains why
                        references to the drink’s international character might not have been found
                        through querying. In the 1950s — when the corpus also contains a sizeable
                        number of ads — internationalism re-emerged as part of Coca-Cola’s brand
                        identity. Throughout the 1950s advertisements continued to highlight the
                        global character of the drink.<note>
                            <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">Het Vrije Volk</title>, June 7, 1952.</note>
                        Advertisers repeatedly mentioned the number of countries and continents in
                        which the Coca-Cola Company sold the drink.<note>
                            <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">Het Vrije Volk</title>, June 10, 1959. </note> This
                        number increased from seventy-eight in 1929, to more than a hundred
                        countries in 1959.<note>
                            <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">Het Vrije Volk</title>, June 25, 1959.</note> The
                        emphasis in ads on this increase helped to establish the idea with Dutch
                        consumers that the global popularity of Coca-Cola was growing.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Absolute frequency (blue) and relative (green) frequency of the
                            international aspect of Coca-Cola</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In addition to the drink’s global character, advertisers tied the drink to
                        the Netherlands. They did so by mentioning the Dutch bottling companies in
                        advertisements. Words such as <q>bottler,</q>
                        <q>to bottle,</q>
                        <q>Amsterdam,</q>
                        <q>Schiedam,</q>
                        <q>Scheveningen,</q> and <q>local</q> situated Coca-Cola within a local
                                    context.<note><q><emph>bottelaar</emph></q>,
                                    <q><emph>bottelen</emph></q>, <q><emph>Amsterdam</emph></q>,
                                    <q><emph>Schiedam</emph></q>, <q><emph>Scheveningen</emph></q>,
                            and <q><emph>plaatselijke</emph></q>.</note> After the Second World War,
                        the Coca-Cola Company allowed local Dutch bottling plants to import
                        Coca-Cola’s trademarked syrup, which bottlers mixed with local mineral water
                            <ptr target="#zwaal1993" loc="145–49"/>. The names of towns that housed
                        the bottling plants appeared in small print at the bottom of advertisements.
                        The appearance of their names in these ads connected Coca-Cola to particular
                        Dutch places.<note> See for instance: <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola
                                advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">Leeuwarder Courant</title>, July 18, 1929; <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">Het Vrije Volk</title>, July 19, 1963.</note>
                        Advertisers further emphasized the <q>local</q> nature of franchises when
                        they claimed that <q>everywhere bottling and distribution of Coca-Cola is a
                            local enterprise.</q><note>
                            <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">Nieuwsblad van het Noorden</title>, October 16,
                            1954.</note> In 1955, <title rend="italic">De Tijd</title> wrote that
                            <q>the Coke bottle is not only known all over the world, it is also of
                            local importance,</q> which further underlines the entanglement of the
                        global and local.<note>
                            <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">De Tijd</title>, January 15, 1955.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Advertisers not only mentioned the locations of bottling plants, they also
                        linked Coca-Cola to Dutch towns, such as Scheveningen, Amsterdam, and
                        Leeuwarden. In 1928, the regional newspaper <title rend="italic">Leeuwarder
                            Courant</title> wrote that after its global success, Dutch consumers
                        could now also buy a Coke in Leeuwarden.<note>
                            <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">Leeuwarder Courant</title>, July 18, 1929.</note>
                        After opening a new factory in Amsterdam in 1961, an ad in <title rend="italic">De Telegraaf</title> announced that <q>Amsterdam and
                            Coca-Cola belonged together!</q><note>
                            <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">De Telegraaf</title>, April 17, 1961.</note> These
                        ads illustrate how Coca-Cola symbolized the entwinement of the global with
                        the local. The association between the global and the local is what Roland
                        Robertson labels <soCalled>glocalization</soCalled>, the interplay between
                        local developments and currents of globalization <ptr target="#robertson1995"/>. Advertisements presented Coca-Cola as a
                        global, international brand somewhat tailored to the local context. </p>
                    <p>The Coca-Cola Company acquainted many Dutch consumers in the 1950s and 1960s
                        with a product with a <term>glocal</term> brand identity, which made
                            <term>glocalization</term> one of the ideas that traveled alongside with
                        Coca-Cola to the Netherlands. Perhaps the <term>glocalizing</term> ability
                        of American brands, such as Coca-Cola, explains why in the eyes of scholars
                        and consumers Americanization became a code word for globalization <ptr target="#oldenziel2007" loc="84"/>
                        <ptr target="#muthyala2012"/>. The Coca-Cola Company did not explicitly
                        relate Coca-Cola to the United States in advertisements. However, the
                        references to the drink’s <emph>glocal</emph> character can be read as
                        uniquely American. Ruth Oldenziel alludes to this particular feature by
                        describing America as having the <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#oldenziel2007">uncanny ability (…) to be everywhere and nowhere at
                                the same time: omnipresent globally, but territorially
                                deterritorialized</quote>
                            <ptr target="#oldenziel2007" loc="87"/>
                        </cit>. The link to the United States was thus not so much an explicit
                        geographical reference, but rather a more implicit connection to symbolisms
                        and affects associated with the United States. The <term>glocalizing</term>
                        ability of prominent American brands such as Coca-Cola also explains how
                        consumers equated the process of Americanization with globalization.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head> 4.4 A Refreshing and Invigorating Taste for Everybody </head>
                    <p>The second theme that dominated Coca-Cola advertisements was its taste. This
                        became most explicit in advertisements published between 1928-1937 and
                        1958-1967. </p>
                    <p> In the interwar period, advertisements described Coca-Cola’s taste as
                            <q>fine</q>, <q>delicious</q> and <q>distinct</q>.<note> Collocates to
                                <q>taste</q>: <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">fijnen</foreign></q> (n =
                            56), <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">heerlijken</foreign></q> (n = 44), and
                                    <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">aparten</foreign></q> (n = 41).</note>
                        Other frequent characteristics of the drink included: refreshing, bubbling,
                        and invigorating.<note> Word (absolute / relative frequency): <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">verfris</foreign>*</q> (144 / 65,44), <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">fris</foreign>*</q> (16 / 7.27), <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">verkwik</foreign>*</q> (16 / 7.27), <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">sprankel</foreign>*</q> (11 / 5), and <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">parel</foreign>*</q>’ (25 / 11.36).</note> Soft
                        drinks contained bubbles that produced a tactile sensation, which
                        advertisers connected to refreshment. This link was expressed in the
                        following slogans: <q>Coca-Cola bubbles in your glass,</q>
                        <q>Coca-Cola is deliciously refreshing,</q> and <q>Coca-Cola’s fizzes and
                            bubbles.</q><note>
                            <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">Coca-Cola parelt in uw glas</foreign></q> (6),
                                    <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">Coca-cola is heerlijk
                                    verfrisschend</foreign></q> (6), and <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">Coca-cola parelt en bruist</foreign></q> (4).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p> Overall, the description of Coca-Cola’s taste did not seem to change
                        drastically between the two periods. Not surprisingly, in both periods the
                        Coca-Cola Company presented their product as delicious and one of a kind.
                        There was, however, another striking characteristic associated with
                        Coca-Cola’s taste: its ability to refresh and invigorate. In the period
                        1958-1967, <q>invigorating</q> collocated significantly to <q>Coca-Cola</q>
                        and <q>taste</q>.<note> Collocate to <q>taste</q>: <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">verkwikking</foreign></q> (26 / 5.90). Collocate to
                                <q>Coca-Cola</q>: <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">verkwikkende</foreign></q> (10 / 2.7). </note> Furthermore, the
                        relative frequency of words denoting invigoration accrued in this period,
                        which substantiates a discursive shift in the Coca-Cola Company’s branding
                        strategy. The ads linked the drink’s refreshing bubbles to invigoration:
                            <q>how invigorating that tingling sparkle.</q><note>
                            <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">Hoe verkwikkend, die tintelende
                                    sprankeling</foreign></q> in <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola
                                advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">De Telegraaf</title>, August 14, 1959. </note>
                    </p>
                    <p>In addition to the drink’s ability to stimulate the consumer, the Coca-Cola
                        Company claimed the drink could — rather paradoxically — also relax the
                        consumer. In one of the first Coca-Cola advertisements in Dutch newspapers,
                        Coca-Cola was associated with leisure time.<note>
                            <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">Het Volk</title>, July 22, 1929.</note> This theme
                        continued to pop up throughout the years. In 1954, for instance, an advert
                        claimed that the beverage would provide <q>rest, relaxation, and new
                            energy.</q><note>
                            <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">Limburgsch Dagblad</title>, November, 12,
                            1954.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>By focusing on relaxation, the advertisements also highlighted its
                        counterpart: stress. The advertisements chiefly situated stress within the
                        context of people at work in the office or homemakers doing their chores.
                        Figure 7 shows how advertisements instructed consumers to <q>stop rushing
                            for a minute! Your nerves will quiet down and all tension will
                            disappear.</q><note>
                            <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">Het Vrije Volk</title>, July 26, 1957; <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">Het Vrije Volk</title>, July 13, 1956.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Moreover, Coca-Cola advertisements informed Dutch consumers that stress and
                        relaxation were part of a modern lifestyle. The Coca-Cola Company claimed
                        that the drink’s ability to stimulate led to its popularity and turned it
                        into a <q>drink cherished by modern people.</q><note>
                            <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">Het Volk</title>, August 16, 1928.</note> The
                        modern businessman and homemaker drank a refreshing bottle of coke during
                        breaks to alleviate stress. This association between products and an urban
                        and modern lifestyle, Marchand shows, blossomed in the United States in the
                        1930s in cigarette advertisements <ptr target="#marchand1985" loc="337"/>.
                        Our results show that the Coca-Cola Company actively sought to evoke similar
                        depictions of such a lifestyle, in which consumption was an integral to
                        being a modern consumer.</p>
                    <p>Another distinctive element of the modern consumer was that both males and
                        female could drink Coca-Cola whenever and with whomever.<note>
                            <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">De Waarheid</title>, January 14, 1950. </note>
                        Moreover, ads explicitly pointed out that the <q>sparkling refreshment</q>
                        and <q>unchanging quality</q> caused people of all ages and in all settings
                        to consume the drink.<note>
                            <title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">De Tijd</title>, April 19, 1952.</note> Phrases
                        such as <q>during work</q>, <q>during dinner</q>, <q>during sports and
                            play</q>, and <q>drank by young and old</q> demonstrate that the
                        Coca-Cola Company set out to make the drink accessible for everyone.<note>
                            <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">onder het werk</foreign></q>, <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">bij het eten</foreign></q>, <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">bij sport en spel</foreign></q>, and <q><foreign xml:lang="nl">voor jong en oud</foreign></q>.</note> Ads for
                        Coca-Cola presented Dutch consumer with a vision of a modern consumer
                        society in which everybody could imbibe the same consumer goods. </p>
                    <p>This image is what scholars such as Richard Pells, T. Jackson Lears, and
                        Charles McGovern describe as an American way of life. Additionally, Victoria
                        de Grazia argues that many American products available in Europe focused on
                        the democratization of consumer goods <ptr target="#grazia2005" loc="217"/>.
                        Our analysis shows that Coca-Cola advertisements in the Netherlands also
                        emphasized this aspect. </p>
                    <p>By means of advertisements, the Coca-Cola Company injected specific elements
                        into the Dutch public consciousness that shaped how the Dutch viewed the
                        American way of life. These elements also resonated within Dutch advertising
                        discourse for other American products, such as cigarettes <ptr target="#wevers2017"/>. This commonality between different kinds of
                        American consumer goods strengthened Coca-Cola’s function as an icon of the
                        American way of life. Further research into different consumer goods is
                        needed to see how they collaboratively contributed to the Dutch perception
                        of the American way of life, or America in general.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head><title rend="quotes">Coca-Cola advertisement,</title>
                            <title rend="italic">Het Vrije Volk</title>, July 26, 1957</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5. Conclusion</head>
                <p>This article has shown that the Coca-Cola Company advertised Coca-Cola in
                    newspapers between 1928 and 1970, with the majority of advertisements published
                    between 1950 and 1965. In these advertisements, Coca-Cola was not explicitly
                    presented as an American brand. Coca-Cola’s link to the United States was much
                    more implicit. Using corpus analysis tools, we have established that an
                    important feature in Coca-Cola’s brand identity was its taste and its
                    international character. Dutch Coca-Cola advertisements unmistakably linked the
                    taste of Coca-Cola to refreshment and invigoration. Furthermore, instead of
                    presenting itself as an American brand, the Coca-Cola Company accentuated
                    Coca-Cola’s international and local character, a phenomenon described as
                        <term>glocalization</term>. </p>
                <p> While ads for Coca-Cola never explicitly mentioned the American way of life,
                    they exposed Dutch consumers to a lifestyle characterized by consumption; a
                    lifestyle often described as an American way of life. Ads provided Dutch
                    consumers with a more symbolic representation of the lifestyle characterized by
                    consumption. The expression of an American way of life in Coca-Cola
                    advertisements manifested on two different levels. First, the advertisements
                    depicted a modern, urban lifestyle — a simulacrum of the burgeoning American
                    consumer society at the time. The second expression of an American way of life
                    took shape in the way advertisers addressed consumers. Consumers in Coca-Cola
                    advertisements could be either male or female, and they were depicted being
                    engaged in activities of leisure or work. Coca-Cola represented elements of an
                    American way of life while at the same time its global spread disassociated the
                    product from its actual origins. This fits within what Rob Kroes calls a
                    resemanticization of reality in which American life is turned into an <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#kroes2000">imaginary realm to be experienced by those who bought a
                            product</quote>
                        <ptr target="#kroes2000" loc="152"/>
                    </cit>. </p>
                <p> Further analyses of advertisements of other consumer goods can shed light on the
                    ways in which advertising discourse as a whole shaped Dutch perceptions of the
                    United States and the American way of life. Moreover, by incorporating
                    newspapers articles, researchers can examine how advertising discourse
                    corresponded with public debates on consumer goods, consumerism, and the United
                    States. This kind of comparative analysis has become more feasible with the
                    availability of computational tools and the proliferation of digitized archives. </p>
                <p>In addition to answering a cultural-historical research question, this article
                    has demonstrated the practical implications of combining traditional and
                    computational methods. By means of two workflows, we have shown how we first
                    constructed a sub-corpus of Coca-Cola advertisements, which we subsequently
                    analyzed using the corpus linguistic toolkit AntConc. </p>
                <p>The workflows highlighted how working with computational tools is not a linear
                    process but requires going back-and-forth between generating output,
                    interpreting output, and a close reading of the sources. This results in a
                    combination of distant and close reading that contextualizes results as well as
                    checks against corpus inadequacies <ptr target="#weller2013" loc="7"/>
                    <ptr target="#dobson2014"/>. When applied in this manner, employing
                    computational tools leads to the discovery of patterns in the dataset, without
                    missing <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hitchcock2014">the power of the particular</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hitchcock2014"/>
                    </cit>—i.e. an optimal interaction between traditional and computational methods
                        <ptr target="#huijnen2015"/>. Further research has to show what can be
                    gained from adding other computational tools to our workflows, such as
                    distributional semantics for tracing historical concept <ptr target="#kenter2015"/>.<note> For more on distributional semantics to trace
                        historical concepts over time see: <ref target="https://www.esciencecenter.nl/project/mining-shifting-concepts-through-time-shico">https://www.esciencecenter.nl/project/mining-shifting-concepts-through-time-shico</ref>.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Appendix A: Absolute and Relative frequency of collocates to ‘Coca-Cola’ in
                    Coca-Cola advertisements</head>
                <table>
                    <head>1928-1937 (n = 220)</head>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> Absolute Frequency </cell>
                        <cell> Relative Frequency (per 100 ads) </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>smaak</cell>
                        <cell>61</cell>
                        <cell>27.7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>overal</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>18.2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>dagelijks</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>18.2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>heerlijk</cell>
                        <cell>39</cell>
                        <cell>17.7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>aparten</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>12.3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>wereld</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>10.9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>landen</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>9.5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>verrukkelijk</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>8.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>dorst</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>8.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>heerlijke</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>7.7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Leeuwarden</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>7.3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>zeldzaam</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>5.9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>bijzondere</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>5.9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>aparte </cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>5.0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>verfrisschend</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>4.5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>parelt</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>4.5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>internationale</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>4.5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>aroma</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>4.5</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <head>1948-1957 (n = 372)</head>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> Absolute Frequency </cell>
                        <cell> Relative Frequency (per 100 ads) </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>overal</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>11.0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>bottelen</cell>
                        <cell>39</cell>
                        <cell>10.5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>heerlijke</cell>
                        <cell>37</cell>
                        <cell>9.9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>gebotteld</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                        <cell>8.9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>distributie</cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>8.3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>geniet</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>7.3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>landen</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>6.5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>sierlijke</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>6.2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>sprankelende</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>5.9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>plaatselijke</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>5.9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>pauze</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>5.4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>iedereen</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>4.8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>verfrissing</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>4.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>ijskoude</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>4.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>flesjes</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>4.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>heerlijk</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>4.3</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <head>1958-1967 (n = 414)</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> Absolute Frequency </cell>
                        <cell> Relative Frequency (per 100 ads) </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>pauze</cell>
                        <cell>88</cell>
                        <cell>23.7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>verfrist</cell>
                        <cell>66</cell>
                        <cell>17.7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>heerlijke</cell>
                        <cell>47</cell>
                        <cell>12.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>smaak</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>11.3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>sprankelende</cell>
                        <cell>39</cell>
                        <cell>10.5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>lekker</cell>
                        <cell>37</cell>
                        <cell>9.9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>bottelaar</cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>8.3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>gebotteld</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>5.4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>heerlijk</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>5.1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Nederlandse</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>4.8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Schiedam</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>4.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>koele</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>4.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Amsterdam</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>3.8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>ijskoude</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>3.5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>verfrissende</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>3.2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>verfrissend</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>3.0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>verkwikkende</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>2.7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>landen</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>2.7</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berry2011" label="Berry 2011">Berry, David M. 2011. <title rend="quotes">The Computational Turn. Thinking about the Digital
                        Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Culture Machine</title> 12: 1–22.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bingham2010" label="Bingham 2010">Bingham, Adrian. 2010. <title rend="quotes">The Digitization of Newspaper Archives. Opportunities and
                        Challenges for Historians.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Twentieth Century British History</title> 21 (2):
                    225–31.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blaxill2013" label="Blaxill 2013">Blaxill, Luke. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Quantifying the Language of British Politics,
                        1880–1910.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Historical Research</title> 86 (232): 313–41.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blevins2015" label="Blevins 2015">Blevins, Cameron. 2015. <title rend="quotes">The Perpetual Sunrise of Methodology.</title> Accessed January
                    11, 2016. <ref target="http://www.cameronblevins.org/posts/perpetual-sunrise-methodology/">http://www.cameronblevins.org/posts/perpetual-sunrise-methodology/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bod2013" label="Bod 2013">Bod, Rens. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Who’s
                        Afraid of Patterns? The Particular versus the Universal and the Meaning of
                        Humanities 3.0.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">BMGN - Low Countries Historical Review</title> 128 (4):
                    171–80.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="castillo2010" label="Castillo 2010">Castillo, Greg. 2010. <title rend="italic">Cold War on the Home Front: The Soft Power of Midcentury
                        Design</title>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dobson2014" label="Dobson 2014">Dobson. 2014. <title rend="quotes">There Is No Such Thing as the ‘unsupervised’. Machine Learning and
                        Critique.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">HASTAC</title>. Accessed May 20. <ref target="http://www.hastac.org/blogs/jed/2014/05/18/there-no-such-thing-%E2%80%9Cunsupervised%E2%80%9D-machine-learning-and-critique">http://www.hastac.org/blogs/jed/2014/05/18/there-no-such-thing-%E2%80%9Cunsupervised%E2%80%9D-machine-learning-and-critique</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eijnatten2013" label="Eijnatten 2013">Eijnatten, Joris van. 2013.
                        <title rend="quotes">Beyond Diversity. The Steady State of Reference
                        Cultures.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">International Journal for History, Culture and
                        Modernity</title> 3 (3): 1–8.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eijnattenetal2013" label="Eijnatten et al. 2013">Eijnatten, Joris van,
                    Toine Pieters, and Jaap Verheul. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Big Data for Global
                        History. The Transformative Promise of Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">BMGN - Low Countries Historical Review</title> 128 (4):
                    55–77.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eijnattenetal2014" label="Eijnatten et al. 2014">Eijnatten, Joris van,
                    Toine Pieters, and Jaap Verheul. 2014. <title rend="quotes">Using Texcavator to
                        Map Public Discourse.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Tijdschrift voor tijdschriftstudies</title> 35:
                    59–65.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="elteren1990" label="Elteren 1990">Elteren, Mel van. 1990. <title rend="quotes"><foreign xml:lang="nl">‘I’m free and I do what I want.’ Het
                            dubbelzinnige beeld van Amerika.</foreign></title> In <title rend="italic">Nuchterheid en nozems. De opkomst van de jeugdcultuur in de
                        jaren vijftig</title>, edited by G. Tillekens, 165–85. Muiderberg:
                    Coutinho.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gibbs2013" label="Gibbs and Owens 2013">Gibbs, Fred, and Trevor Owens.
                    2013. <title rend="quotes">Hermeneutics of Data and Historical Writing.</title>
                    In <title rend="italic">Writing History in the Digital Age</title>, edited by
                    Jack Dougherty and Kristen Nawrotzki. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press.
                        <ref target="http://quod.lib.umich.edu/d/dh/12230987.0001.001/1:7/--writing-history-in-the-digital-age?g=dculture;rgn=div1;view=fulltext;xc=1#7.3">http://quod.lib.umich.edu/d/dh/12230987.0001.001/1:7/--writing-history-in-the-digital-age?g=dculture;rgn=div1;view=fulltext;xc=1#7.3</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="graham2015" label="Graham et al. 2015">Graham, Shawn, Ian Milligan,
                    and Scott Weingart. 2015. <title rend="italic">Exploring Big Historical Data.
                        The Historian’s Macroscope</title>. Londen: Imperial College Press. <ref target="http://www.themacroscope.org/2.0/">http://www.themacroscope.org/2.0/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="grazia2005" label="Grazia 2005">Grazia, Victoria de. 2005. <title rend="italic">Irresistible Empire. America’s Advance through
                        Twentieth-Century Europe</title>. Cambridge: Belknap Press of Harvard
                    University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hayles2012" label="Hayles 2012">Hayles, Nancy K. 2012. <title rend="italic">How We Think. Digital Media and Contemporary
                        Technogenesis</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hellema2012" label="Hellema 2012">Hellema, Duco. 2012. <title rend="italic">Nederland en de jaren zeventig</title>. Amsterdam:
                    Boom.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hitchcock2014" label="Hitchcock2014">Hitchcock, Tim. 2014. <title rend="quotes">Big Data, Small Data and Meaning.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Historyonics</title>. Accessed November 13. <ref target="http://historyonics.blogspot.co.uk/2014/11/big-data-small-data-and-meaning_9.html">http://historyonics.blogspot.co.uk/2014/11/big-data-small-data-and-meaning_9.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="holt2004" label="Holt 2004">Holt, Douglas B. 2004. <title rend="italic">How Brands Become Icons. The Principles of Cultural
                        Branding</title>. Boston: Harvard Business School Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="huijnen2012" label="Huijnen et al. 2012">Huijnen, Pim, Fons Laan,
                    Maarten de Rijke, and Toine Pieters. 2012. <title rend="quotes">A Digital
                        Humanities Approach to the History of Science. Eugenics Revisited in Hidden
                        Debates by Means of Semantic Text Mining.</title> In <title rend="italic">Social Informatics</title>, edited by Akiyo Nadamoto, Adam Jatowt, Adam
                    Wierzbicki, and Jochen L. Leidner, 71–85. Berlin: Springer.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="huijnen2015" label="Huijnen et al. 2015">Huijnen, Pim, and Melvin
                    Wevers. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Digital reconstruction. The digital turn and
                        the use of news media as sources for historical research.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Officina della Storia</title> 13. <ref target="http://www.officinadellastoria.info/magazine/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=416%3Adigital-deconstruction-the-digital-turn-and-the-use-of-news-media-as-sources-for-historical-research&amp;catid=72&amp;Itemid=1">http://www.officinadellastoria.info/magazine/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=416%3Adigital-deconstruction-the-digital-turn-and-the-use-of-news-media-as-sources-for-historical-research&amp;catid=72&amp;Itemid=1.</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kennedy2009" label="Kennedy 2009">Kennedy, James. 2009. <title rend="quotes">Cultural Developments in the Dutch-American Relationships
                        since 1945.</title> In <title rend="italic">Four Centuries of Dutch-American
                        Relations 1609-2009</title>, edited by Hans Krabbendam, Cornelis A. van
                    Minnen, and Giles Scott-Smith, 931–48. Amsterdam: Boom.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kenter2015" label="Kenter 2013">Kenter, T. et al. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Ad Hoc Monitoring of Vocabulary Shifts over Time</title>, in
                        <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 24th ACM International on Conference
                        on Information and Knowledge Management</title>. 2015 ACM. pp. 1191–1200.
                    [online]. Available from: <ref target="http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2806474">http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2806474</ref> (Accessed 10 February
                    2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2014" label="Kirschenbaum 2014">Kirschenbaum, Matthew.
                    2014. <title rend="quotes">What Is ‘Digital Humanities,’ and Why Are They Saying
                        Such Terrible Things about It?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Differences</title> 25 (1): 46–63.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2007" label="Kirschenbaum 2007">Kirschenbaum, Matthew G.
                    2007. <title rend="quotes">The Remaking of Reading. Data Mining and the Digital
                        Humanities.</title> In <title rend="italic">The National Science Foundation
                        Symposium on next Generation of Data Mining and Cyber-Enabled Discovery for
                        Innovation, Baltimore, 11 Oktober 2007</title>. <ref target="http://www.cs.umbc.edu/~hillol/NGDM07/abstracts/talks/MKirschenbaum.pdf">http://www.cs.umbc.edu/~hillol/NGDM07/abstracts/talks/MKirschenbaum.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kroes1986" label="Kroes 1986">Kroes, Rob. 1986. <title rend="quotes">The Great Satan versus the Evil Empire. Anti-Americanism in the
                        Netherlands.</title> In <title rend="italic">Anti-Americanism in
                        Europe</title>, edited by Rob Kroes, Maarten van Rossem, and Marcus
                    Cunliffe. Amsterdam: VU University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kroes2000" label="Kroes 2000">Kroes, Rob. 2000. <title rend="italic">Them and Us. Questions of Citizenship in a Globalizing World</title>.
                    Urbana: University of Illinois Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lears1994" label="Lears 1994">Lears, T. J. Jackson. 1994. <title rend="italic">Fables of Abundance. A Cultural History of Advertising in
                        America</title>. New York: BasicBooks.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="marchand1985" label="Marchand 1985">Marchand, Roland. 1985. <title rend="italic">Advertising the American Dream. Making Way for Modernity,
                        1920-1940</title>. Berkeley: University of California Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcgovern2006" label="McGovern 2006">McGovern, Charles. 2006. <title rend="italic">Sold American. Consumption and Citizenship, 1890-1945</title>.
                    Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moretti2013" label="Moretti 2013">Moretti, Franco. 2013. <title rend="italic">Distant Reading</title>. Londen: Verso.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="muthyala2012" label="Muthyala 2012">Muthyala, John. 2012. <title rend="italic">Dwelling in American. Dissent, Empire, and
                        Globalization</title>. Hanover: Dartmouth College Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nicholson2012" label="Nicholson 2012">Nicholson, Bob. 2012. <title rend="quotes">Counting; Or, How to Read Victorian Newspapers from a
                        Distance.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Victorian Culture</title> 17 (2): 238–46.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nicholson2013" label="Nicholson 2013">Nicholson, Bob. 2013. <title rend="quotes">The Digital Turn. Exploring the Methodological Possibilities
                        of Digital Newspaper Archives.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Media History</title> 19 (1): 59–73.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nolan2012" label="Nolan 2012">Nolan, Mary. 2012. <title rend="italic">The Transatlantic Century. Europe and America, 1890-2010</title>.
                    Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="oldenziel2007" label="Oldenziel 2007">Oldenziel, Ruth. 2007. <title rend="quotes">Is Globalization a Code Word for Americanization?
                        Contemplating McDonalds, Coca-Cola, and Military Bases.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Tijdschrift voor sociale en economische
                        geschiedenis</title>, no. 3: 84–106.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="oldenziel2013" label="Oldenziel and Hård 2013">Oldenziel, Ruth, and
                    Mikael Hård. 2013. <title rend="italic">Making Europe. Technology and
                        Transformations, 1850-2000. Consumers, Tinkerers, Rebels</title>.
                    Houndmills: Palgrave Macmillan.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pells1997" label="Pells 1997">Pells, Richard. 1997. <title rend="italic">Not like Us. How Europeans Have Loved, Hated, and Transformed
                        American Culture since World War II</title>. New York: Basic books.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pendergrast2000" label="Pendergrast 2000">Pendergrast, Mark. 2000.
                        <title rend="italic">For God, Country and Coca-Cola. The Definitive History
                        of the Great American Soft Drink and the Company That Makes It</title>. New
                    York: Basic Books.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="porsdam2013" label="Porsdam 2013">Porsdam, Helle. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities: On Finding the Proper Balance between
                        Qualitative and Quantitative Ways of Doing Research in the
                        Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 7 (3).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay2011" label="Ramsay 2011">Ramsay, Stephen. 2011. <title rend="italic">Reading Machines. Toward an Algorithmic Criticism</title>.
                    Urbana: University of Illinois Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rieder2012" label="Rieder and Röhle 2012">Rieder, Bernhard, and Theo
                    Röhle. 2012. <title rend="quotes">Digital Methods: Five Challenges.</title> In
                        <title rend="italic">Understanding Digital Humanities</title>, edited by
                    David M. Berry, 67–84. Houndmills: Palgrave Macmillan.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="robertson1995" label="Robertson 1995">Robertson, Roland. 1995. <title rend="quotes">Glocalization. Time-Space and Homogeneity
                        Heterogeneity.</title> In <title rend="italic">Global Modernities</title>,
                    edited by Mike Featherstone, Scott M. Lash, and Roland Robertson, 25–44. London:
                    Sage Publications.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="roholl1992" label="Roholl 1992">Roholl, Marja. 1992. <title rend="quotes">Uncle Sam: An Example for All? The Dutch Orientation towards
                        America in the Social and Cultural Field, 1945-1965.</title> In <title rend="italic">Dutch-American Relations 1945-1969. A Partnership, Illusions
                        and Facts</title>, edited by Hans Loeber, 105–52. Assen: Van Gorcum.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ross2014" label="Ross 2014">Ross, Shawna. 2014. <title rend="quotes">In Praise of Overstating the Case. A Review of Franco Moretti, Distant
                        Reading.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 8 (1): 1–8.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rossem1981" label="Rossem 1981">Rossem, Maarten van. 1981. <title rend="quotes">Le Defi Europeen.</title> In <title rend="italic">Image and
                        Impact. American Influences in the Netherlands since 1945</title>, edited by
                    Rob Kroes, 18–30. Amsterdam: Amerika instituut.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sassatelli2007" label="Sassatelli 2007">Sassatelli, Roberta. 2007.
                        <title rend="italic">Consumer Culture: History, Theory and Politics</title>.
                    Los Angeles: SAGE.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schot1997" label="Schot 1997">Schot, Johan. 1997. <title rend="quotes">Consumeren als het cement van de lange twintigste eeuw.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">De Nieuwste Tijd</title> 9: 27–37.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schuyt2004" label="Schuyt and Taverne 2004">Schuyt, Kees, and Ed
                    Taverne. 2004. <title rend="italic">1950. Prosperity and Welfare</title>.
                    Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sinclair2004" label="Sinclair et al. 2004">Sinclair, John MacHardy,
                    Susan Jones, and Robert Daley. 2004. <title rend="italic">English Collocation
                        Studies. The OSTI Report</title>. London: Continuum.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="toebes1996" label="Toebes 1996">Toebes, Joop. 1996. <title rend="quotes">A Country Too Far Away. Images of the Unites States in the
                        Dutch Illustrated Press in the 1920s.</title> In <title rend="italic">American Culture in the Netherlands</title>, edited by Doeko Bosscher,
                    Marja Roholl, and Mel van Elteren, 24–42. Amsterdam: VU University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="togninibonelli2001" label="Tognini-Bonelli 2001">Tognini-Bonelli,
                    Elena. 2001. <title rend="italic">Corpus Inguistics at Work</title>. Amsterdam:
                    Benjamins.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="trtovac2014" label="Trtovac and Dakic 2014">Trtovac, Aleksandra, and
                    Natasa Dakic. 2014. <title rend="quotes">Bringing Historical Newspaper
                        Advertisement into Research Focus - Europeana Newspapers Project.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Преглед НЦД</title> 25: 2–10.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="underwood2016" label="Underwood 2016">Underwood, Ted. 2016. <title rend="quotes">Interesting Times for Literary Theory.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Stone and the Shell. Using Large Libraries to Advance
                        Literary History</title>. <ref target="http://tedunderwood.com/2013/08/04/interesting-times-for-literary-theory/">http://tedunderwood.com/2013/08/04/interesting-times-for-literary-theory/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="verhoef2015a" label="Verhoef 2015a">Verhoef, Jesper. 2015a. <title rend="quotes">Anti-Modern National Identity Formation. Dutch Depictions of
                        America in Public Debates about Film Fandom, 1919-1939.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Powerlines</title> 3 (1). <ref target="http://amst.umd.edu/powerlines/anti-modern-national-identity-formation-dutch-depictions-of-america-in-public-debates-about-film-fandom-1919-1939/">http://amst.umd.edu/powerlines/anti-modern-national-identity-formation-dutch-depictions-of-america-in-public-debates-about-film-fandom-1919-1939/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="verhoef2015b" label="Verhoef 2015b">Verhoef, Jesper. 2015b. <title rend="quotes">The Cultural-Historical Value of and Problems with Digitized
                        Advertisements. Historical Newspapers and the Portable Radio,
                        1950-1969.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Tijdschrift voor tijdschriftstudies</title> 38:
                    51–60.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weller2013" label="Weller 2013">Weller, Toni, ed. 2013. <title rend="italic">History in the Digital Age</title>. Londen: Routledge.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wevers2017" label="Wevers 2017">Wevers, Melvin. 2017. <title rend="quotes">Consuming America: The United States as a Reference Culture in
                        Dutch Debates on Consumer Goods, 1890-1990.</title> Ph.D. dissertation,
                    Utrecht: Utrecht University.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zwaal1993" label="Zwaal 1993">Zwaal, Peter. 1993. <title rend="italic">Frisdranken in Nederland. Een twintigste eeuwse
                    produktgeschiedenis</title>. Rotterdam: Stichting BBM.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>