<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">New Questions, Next Work</title>

            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Bethany <dhq:family>Nowviskie</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1788-5154 </idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>James Madison University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>nowvisbp@jmu.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Dr. Bethany Nowviskie is Dean of Libraries and Chief Academic Technology
                     Officer at James Madison University. A longtime DH scholar and organizer,
                     Nowviskie’s past roles include president of ACH, executive director of the
                     Digital Library Federation, and founding director of the Scholars’ Lab at the
                     University of Virginia.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000632</idno>
         	<idno type="volume"
         		><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
         	<idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->3</idno>
         	<date when="2022-07-22">22 July 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>Digital humanities</item>
                  <item>Organizing</item>
                  <item>Reform</item>
                  <item>Mutual aid</item>
                  <item>Infrastructure</item>
                  <item>Reflection</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
      	<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target=
      		"https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000632/000632.xml">GitHub
      	</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>This brief, invited “metareflection” identifies the most exciting questions in
               digital humanities and cultural heritage as those opened up by a potential
               redistribution of power and redesign of our social and technological infrastructure
               inspired by Black Studies, arts, and digital practice. What might it mean to shift
               from extractive and controlled modes of digital research and curation to ones that
               are generative, healing, and truly open-ended? What will happen if we succeed in
               empowering and centering individuals, collections, and community concerns that have
               long been marginalized? What might the DH community build next, if we make necessary
               changes in capital, focus, and control — and embrace the shaping role of the choices
               that each of us make within living systems every day?</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>We have pathways forward and tantalizing hints, but can scarcely imagine what it will
               mean to shift from extractive modes of digital research and curation — quantifying,
               fragmenting, pinning, hoarding — to ones that are generative, healing, open-ended,
               and which make us whole.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>The necessary project of <emph>reshaping and reforming our digital humanities and
               cultural heritage infrastructure</emph> — along the more liberatory, generative,
            reparative, equitable, and critically informed lines of what Jessica Marie Johnson calls
               <q>Black digital practice</q> — has barely begun <ptr target="#johnson2018"/>.</p>
         <p>By <emph>infrastructure</emph>, I mean the full suite of social and technological
            systems that converge in DH and the work of memory institutions: platforms and tools,
            certainly; but also systems of selection, arrangement, and description of cultural
            materials deemed worthy of attention — and the practices that shape those decisions at
            scale, distributing or reifying authority, security, and privilege. These latter range
            from our very conception of how funding and resourcing can function in this sphere, to
            our practices of hiring, evaluating scholars for tenure and promotion, and instituting
            organizational habits and patterns that either retain and uplift people of color or harm
            and drive them away. It is tempting to frame this complex and eroded infrastructure — in
            all its overwhelming fullness — as something the present generation of DH scholars,
            librarians, archivists, museum workers, technologists, and administrators has simply
            inherited and must drag along. But that would be to diminish the shaping role of the
            choices we make within living systems, every day.</p>
         <p>There is no longer any excuse for disengagement with what an activist Black or Africana
            studies offers the digital humanities. Black scholarship and organizing on the one hand,
            and human survival and flourishing on the other are deeply interlinked. Professions and
            institutions that persist in old patterns without surcease — despite overwhelming
            evidence that change is needed and a better world is possible — participate in the same
            willfully self-destructive logics that drive environmental degradation, piss-poor
            pandemic response, and emboldened White supremacy.</p>
         <p>I offer here — as an invited <q>meta-reflection</q> — a brief set of concepts and
            concerns that have become most meaningful to me as an academic and administrator, in
            setting my own agendas and the organizational ones I am able to influence.</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item><p>First, thanks to scholars like Johnson, Moya Bailey, Kim Gallon, Marisa Parham,
               and Safiya Noble, we can feel increasingly confident that an unfruitful
               techno-utopianism in DH is well and truly dead. It is now evident that the same tools
               and systems that make generative and counter-cultural Black digital practice possible
               have the potential to be (or already are) technologies of misrepresentation and
               misogynoir, of the continued quantification of BIPOC bodies, and of surveillance and control.</p>
               <p>But that is not to say that more hopeful, technological futures have been
               foreclosed. I hang my hopes on a core tenet of Afrofuturism, as outlined by Kodwo
               Eshun and other artists and thinkers: that <emph>the primary marker of a people’s
                  autonomy lies in their ability to craft and control their own, collective
                  intellectual infrastructure</emph>. I therefore ask: what generational
               imaginations will be liberated, for the benefit of everyone, when cultural heritage
               systems, digital libraries, and techno-social platforms of all kinds are built around
               new philosophies of organization and community ownership — for instance, no longer on
               progress narratives and master-slave or parent-child paradigms, or on
               admin/moderator-based models of control, but on frameworks with roots in
                  <emph>ubuntu</emph>, cooperatively governed, holistically understood, and nurtured
               to new ends?</p> 
               <p>The implications for our digital libraries, archives, museums, and research
               infrastructures are extreme. As just one example — which, inspired by Rasheedah
               Phillips, I have explored in a number of talks and essays — truly supporting Black
               futures will not only require ceding ownership over history and its digital delivery
               mechanisms, but even challenging regulated, linear time.<lb/><lb/></p></item>
            <item><p>Doing this needed design work requires <emph>a fundamental shift, not only in
                  institutional but in personal control</emph>. I believe that the majority-white
               generation of leaders who presently dominate cultural heritage and DH need to make
               this shift possible, by deliberately leveraging our power and privilege to resource
               Black-led projects and to position BIPOC, queer, and other minoritized colleagues as
               voices of authority. Then, most importantly, we need to get out of the way.</p>
               <p>The same systems that have positioned us to do this work will — at a moment when
               “diversity” efforts have become institutionally trendy — reinforce and reward our
               remaining in loci of power past our usefulness in supporting others. Alternately,
               such systems will remove us prematurely when it becomes evident we do not support
                  <emph>them</emph>. Therefore, we must commit to the project, wherever it takes us.
               It is also crucial we recognize and vocally acknowledge that our (perhaps newly) good
               and earnest intent does not wipe away past harms or preclude new ones, nor does it
               substitute for the embodied experiences and deep expertise of scholars and archivists
               of Black culture.<lb/><lb/></p> </item>
            <item>
               <p><emph>Capital, too, can be shifted</emph>, as we have recently seen through the
               altered priorities and patterns of decision-making that have come with changes in
               leadership in our major funding agencies. This shift needs to happen in our
               libraries, digital humanities centers, museums, and archives as well — for budgets
               are moral documents. Resourcing cannot productively proceed along the charity-based
               frameworks that groups like the Shift Collective identify as problematic in funding
               community archives, and which have propped up what <title rend="italic"
                  >INCITE!</title> terms the <q>nonprofit industrial complex</q> <ptr target="#incite2017"/>. Scholars of race,
               class, and labor (whose work reinforces the expressed, lived experiences of presumed
               beneficiaries of such partnerships and gifts) demonstrate compellingly that large
               organizations too often work against their ostensible and noble aims — serving
               instead to extract resources and, in the case of nonprofits, not to elevate dissent,
               but to channel and quell it.</p>
               <p>Instead, robust networks of <emph>mutual aid</emph> — based in equity and
               reciprocity, and meeting actual, core needs of our communities — are as necessary in
               DH and digital libraries as they are in the urban and rural settings of our failing
               state. The daily maintenance and long-term sustainability of digital humanities
               projects (not merely as technical systems but as <emph>human</emph> ones) is an
               unsolved problem in our institutions and town-gown collaborations as currently
               configured. Top-down funding models, well directed, can spark desperately needed,
               momentary change — but may never sustain nor truly serve the goals of a new,
               grassroots Black digital practice.<lb/><lb/></p></item>
            <item>
               <p>Most fundamentally,<emph> we do not know what will happen</emph> if we succeed in
                  empowering and centering people, collections, and community concerns that have
                  long been marginalized. We don’t know <emph>what</emph> true shifts in resources
                  and authority might bring. We don’t know what an Afrofuturist digital discovery
                  and cultural heritage platform might look like — because we have never had one.
                  New scholars and practitioners of the digital humanities in search of research
                  questions may find <emph>these</emph> the most exciting, over-arching ones in our
                  field.</p>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>The intersection of Black studies with DH and digital cultural heritage reminds us to
            think across time and globally, through the Diaspora — understanding that abolition,
            memory, the creation and use of tools, and the political, ecological, and
            interdisciplinary projects of decolonization are on trajectories long and broad. We have
            pathways forward and tantalizing hints, but can scarcely imagine what it will mean to
            shift from extractive modes of digital research and curation — quantifying, fragmenting,
            pinning, hoarding — to ones that are generative, healing, open-ended, and which make us
            whole. What might we build next?</p>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="incite2017" label="Incite! Women of Color Against Violence"> Incite! Women of Color Against Violence. (2017) <title rend="italic">The revolution will not be funded: Beyond the non-profit industrial complex.</title> Duke University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="johnson2018" label="Johnson2018">Johnson, Jessica Marie. (2018). <title
                  rend="quotes">Markup bodies</title>. <title rend="italic">Social Text</title>.
               36:4: 57–79. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1215/01642472-7145658"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1215/01642472-7145658</ref>.</bibl>
            
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
