<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Stitching the
               Fragmented: Feminist Maker Pedagogy and Immersive Technologies for Cultural
               Learning</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Mélanie <dhq:family>Péron</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>mperon@sas.upenn.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Mélanie Péron is a Senior Lecturer in French at the University of Pennsylvania where she teaches advanced-level History and Culture courses. Her research interests include the digital humanities and digital media pedagogy, material culture, and Shoah studies.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Meaghan <dhq:family>Moody</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  >https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2235-4016<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Rochester</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>mmoody@rochester.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Meaghan is the Immersive Technologies Librarian for Digital Scholarship at University of Rochester’s River Campus Libraries. She focuses on the development of Studio X, a program and space for extended reality (XR). She supports teaching, research, and learning surrounding XR tools and methods and works to lower barriers to entry for students and faculty. </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Vickie <dhq:family>Karasic</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>Bryn Mawr College</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>vkarasic@brynmawr.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Vickie Karasic is an Educational Technology Specialist at Bryn Mawr College, where she assists members of the College community to incorporate technology meaningfully into course design, teaching, and learning. Her research interests include the use of digital media in language learning, the digital humanities, and teaching and learning spaces.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000614</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->0016</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->2</idno>
            <date when="2022-05-03">03 May 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2022-08-03" who="BRG">added teaser and ORCID</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>To immerse and engage her learners in the particularly difficult topic of WWII Paris,
               a French instructor, with assistance from the university libraries and digital
               humanities lab, embarked upon distinct yet iterative digital projects that allowed
               students to connect with course material through critical making. Starting with
               digital mapping and moving to 360° virtual reality video projects, instructor,
               librarians, and students stitched together fragments of the past to further their
               collective experience of this historical period via immersive technology. Students’
               work was founded upon feminist maker pedagogy and an ethic of care that allowed them
               to step into others’ perspectives and preserve a cultural memory that future students
               will build upon.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>Critical making at the university level on the topic of WWII Paris.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            
         <head></head>
         <p>What connections can 21st-century students at an American university have to people in
            Paris during World War II? In fact, how can both the instructor and her students from an
            American university understand a past that none of them lived in and that happened far
            away? To teach a course on WWII Paris confronts the educator with challenging
            epistemological and pedagogical questions. Referring to the six facets of understanding
            by <ptr target="#wiggins2011"/>, how can students feel empathy for and gain perspective
            and self-knowledge from subjects so far removed — linguistically, geographically,
            temporally, psychologically — from themselves? How can one find the words to talk about
            the ineffable Shoah? Finally, how can one expect them to imagine the German occupation
            of a city to which some of them have never been?</p>
         <p>To address these questions, the instructor, librarians, and students collaboratively
            developed a series of digital projects to archive and spatially locate the fragmented
            stories of Paris-based Shoah survivors. The instructor, Mélanie Péron, shared strong
            friendships and working relationships with several living survivors, to whom she
            introduced her students. In turn, her students became acquainted with these individuals
            from the fall of 2019 into the spring of 2020 as they worked on their respective
            narratives. The course culminated in a week-long stay in Paris, during which students
            met these individuals in person. Librarians, Vickie Karasic and Meaghan Moody, partnered
            with Mélanie and her students through their development of digital projects founded on
            critical making and feminist pedagogy. Using mapping and immersive technologies,
            students created social artifacts intended to live on well after the course. More
            importantly, they fostered collective experiences that overcame the differences of place
            and time to understand themselves, others, and cultural issues.</p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Theoretical Frameworks</head>
         <p>We draw upon our interpretation of <term>critical making</term> in part as
            <ptr target="#ratto2011a"/> articulates in his foundational article on the subject, defining it as <quote rend="inline">a
            mode of materially productive engagement that is intended to bridge the gap between
            creative physical and conceptual exploration</quote> <ptr target="#ratto2011a" loc="252"/>. Critical making overlaps and
            shares practices with art and design, including critical design <ptr target="#dunne2005"/>, but
            departs in its focus on the process over the product. <ptr target="#ratto2011a"/> further highlights
            that critical making entails the thoughtful and engaged communication between makers,
            the destabilization of power differentials, and the creation of connections between
            theory and practice. Perhaps above all, <ptr target="#ratto2011a"/> articulates as key to critical
            making the investment of self and care in the process to bear a responsibility in the
            project’s enduring existence: <quote rend="inline">Ultimately, critical making is about turning the
            relationship between technology and society from a ‘matter of fact’ into a ‘matter of
            concern.’ I see this as requiring personal investment, a ‘caring for’ that is not
            typically part of either technical or social scholarly education</quote> <ptr target="#ratto2011a" loc="259"/>. For our
            purposes, then, critical making entails both the collaborative production of digital
            cultural artifacts and, more importantly, the fostering of human connections that are
            brought about by, and live through, these technological objects beyond this project. Our
            focus on authentic concern, interconnection, and personal investment also aligns with
            tenets of the feminist ethics of care. </p>
         <p>Because of the intensely personal and poignant nature of the course, it was critical to
            embrace the feminist strategy of an ethics of care as its cornerstone. As <ptr target="#hooks1994"/>
            has argued, <quote rend="inline">To teach in a manner that respects and cares for the souls of our students
            is essential if we are to provide the necessary conditions where learning can most
            deeply and intimately begin</quote> <ptr target="#hooks1994" loc="13"/>. As spots were limited in the course, first-round
            students had to answer essay questions followed by an interview for the second round.
            Through this process, Mélanie and the students got to know one another, and she learned
            about their motivations for participating in the course. She gave priority to
            first-generation and/or low-income students for whom the trip was covered by financial
            aid and the opportunity to travel abroad was the first one and might be the last. On the
            first day of class, an important convention was introduced to the class. The students
            and the instructor were to address each other on a first-name basis. The linguistic
            familiarity translated into the creation of a genuine, fostering, and co-constructive
            community. Students were also given weekly, extensive personalized feedback and support
            throughout the course, as they engaged both with this complex and tragic period of
            history and in direct communication with survivors. </p>
            <p>Credited as the originator of the ethics of care theory, <ptr target="#gilligan1982"/> describes the
               ethics of care as a <quote rend="inline">psychological logic of relationships</quote> <ptr target="#gilligan1982" loc="73"/> that denotes a
            <quote rend="inline">connection between self and others which is articulated by the concept of
               responsibility</quote> <ptr target="#gilligan1982" loc="74"/>. Students were invited as collaborators into the class, and they
            were tasked with creating digital projects that preserved survivors’ histories. We asked
            students to exercise care and empathy for these individuals and worked to cultivate this
            capacity through discussion, activities, and feedback. Elaborating on <ptr target="#hooks1994"/> and
               <ptr target="#macedo2018"/>, <ptr target="#accardi2010"/> writes, <quote rend="inline">And what makes care feminist is that
            it sees students as whole human beings, not vessels to be filled with information and
            knowledge. It sees learners as people with thoughts and feelings that they bring to the
            classroom, and which, in turn, affect how they learn</quote> <ptr target="#accardi2010" loc="44"/>. Students were not merely
            absorbing this history and translating it into digital projects but rather were in
            dialogue with survivors and the instructor while aligning their own understanding and
            experiences to those of the survivors — requiring vulnerability, awareness, and
            emotional work. For example, a creative writing project involved two parts over the
            course of the semester: first, students wrote, weekly, a chapter of a fictional
            character’s memoirs living in Paris during the German Occupation, the testimony of which
            aimed at showing a human facet of history; after this, students wrote under imposed
            constraints inspired by post-memory writers, in particular Georges Perec. The list of
            constraints included writing a text about a chosen number, writing a list of memories
            starting each sentence by <q>I remember,</q> and picking a letter from the alphabet and
            writing a text made of words excluding that letter. The objective here was for students
            to experience the difficulties faced by the survivors to tell their stories and to give
            shape to the voids and the silences left by history. At the end of the semester,
            students were asked to compile their pieces in any order; the ultimate constraint
            involved embedding one final page – a new creation of their choosing – in the very
            middle of the collected work. This new page acted as the cylindrical mirror in an
            anamorphic construction through which scattered and disparate fragments regain a shape
            and therefore a meaning invisible until then. In every single case, the anamorphic page
            revealed to the students that, unbeknownst to them, the story of their fictional
            character was a portal through which they discovered a piece of themselves or
            rediscovered a piece of their own narrative. In other words, the creative writing
            project mirrored what the historical digital projects were meant to achieve.</p>
         <p>We aimed for students to feel connected to these individuals and a shared responsibility
            for their legacies. Building upon the ethics of care, <ptr target="#caswell2016"/>'s work
            describes archivists as <quote rend="inline">caregivers, bound to records, creators, subjects, users, and
               communities through a web of mutual affective responsibility</quote> <ptr target="#caswell2016" loc="24"/>. The digital
            projects would be created through the connections students developed with their
            survivors, the instructor, librarians, and with one another. In the classroom, students
            from varied backgrounds bonded over the course discussions and projects, and these bonds
            continued to strengthen while in Paris. The well-traveled students kindly and
            unassumingly helped their classmates ease into the exotic experience. They also
            problem-solved, griped, shared joy and sorrow, and made things together, while
            contributing to the growing body of Shoah archiving taken on by the instructor. </p>
         <p> At the intersection of theory and practice, feminist maker pedagogy extends feminist
            pedagogical modes of inquiry and critique into practice. <ptr target="#cipolla2019"/> writes,
            <quote rend="inline">Introducing ‘making’ as a pedagogical tool into a feminist classroom highlights the
            importance of moving beyond the critique. Feminist makers critique, but they also <emph>engage</emph>, <emph>speculate</emph>, and <emph
               >generate</emph></quote> <ptr target="#cipolla2019" loc="262"/>. Feminist makers contextualize, identify with, and reflect
            on their projects. Making informed by feminist pedagogy encompasses making that is
            rooted explicitly in care and connection: <quote rend="inline">it pays attention to the politics of care and
            vulnerability; and it touches at all points, on the embodied and interconnected
            experience of beings in living systems</quote> <ptr target="#cipolla2019" loc="262"/>. Through feminist maker
            pedagogy, students learn not only how to use tools but also to ask deeper questions
            about those tools and how they are using them. In turn, making prompts students to ask
            new questions and explore a concept through a different modality. Students also grow to
            appreciate troubleshooting, viewing it as a necessary step to better understanding and
            new ideas. </p>
         <p>Feminist maker pedagogy pushes back against prevailing conceptions both of being a <term>Maker</term> and of participation in the <title rend="italic">Maker
               Movement</title>, which are often associated with white, cishet, able-bodied,
            upper-middle-class men and centered on capitalist values and high-technology (e.g.,
            robotics and coding) projects <ptr target="#vossoughi2016"/> <ptr target="#chachra2017"/>. Our project
            embraced this outlook in particular with our reliance on the feminist strategy of
            intuition, which <ptr target="#accardi2010"/> describes as <quote rend="inline">valu[ing] the inner voice, that quiet way
            of knowing, that is contrary to the stereotypical, empirical, androcentric way of
            knowing</quote> <ptr target="#accardi2010" loc="17"/>. Accordingly, the project and the way Mélanie engages with her students
            stem from serendipity, intuition, and instinct — all of which defy simple definition and
            analysis. We must also recognize and acknowledge our positions of privilege here, having
            the affordances of access to technology and resources that have made our project, the
            tools, and travel it has entailed entirely possible. </p></div>
         <div>
          
         <head>Virtual Reality as a Pedagogical Tool </head>
         <p> With our theoretical groundwork laid, we can further expand on the choice of
            technologies for our project; namely, immersive technologies. While the instructor has
            experimented with a variety of digital tools and methods in her courses, this article
            focuses primarily on the creation of 360º recordings that were embedded into a digital
            map and experienced on a virtual reality (VR) head-mounted display (HMD). We selected VR
            as our medium for this project for several reasons. First, VR often provides for more
            engaging learning objects: <quote rend="inline">Virtual reconstructions […] help students understand
            cultures, histories, and artifacts that are physically, temporally, or culturally
            distant. While it may be difficult for American students to visit Notre Dame, extended
            realities can help them experience it in a way that more traditional media cannot</quote>
            <ptr target="#ocallaghan2020"/>.
            While in the HMD, the user is immersed in a 360º simulation in which they can look in
            any direction and visit distant places and times. Not all Mélanie’s classes are able to
            visit Paris, but through VR, they can stand in a park in Paris, view people walking
            around them, become aware of the spatial distance between the various elements
            surrounding them, and listen to fragments of their conversations. VR brings the user
            closer to the real experience than simply reading about it, hearing a description, or
            viewing a video clip. It may not only combine all these modalities but also includes a
            focused environment and a first-person perspective. This capability feels especially
            invaluable in light of the still unfolding COVID-19 pandemic and the uncertainty of safe
            travel. VR also makes private spaces more accessible. Anyone can visit a public park but
            perhaps not a personal residence or a fragile environment. Further, VR and 360º
            recording technology, in particular, can serve as archiving tools to preserve a place at
            a point in time. Imagine being able to revisit your childhood bedroom or your
            grandparent’s house exactly as they looked when you were a child. This was the effect we
            wanted our students to experience.</p>
         <p>With VR technologies, we can also integrate additional data and engagement
            opportunities. For example, <ptr target="#lueck2020"/> describe an XR (extended reality)
            project to illustrate Native Ohlone history at Santa Clara University: <quote rend="inline">Further, the
            technology provided an additional representational layer allowing students not only to
            analyze what is present in the commemorative landscape but also to reveal the histories
            that have been effectively erased from our campus, such as unmarked mission cemeteries</quote> <ref target="#lueck2020">para. 19</ref>
            . In this case, students digitally annotated 360º recordings with critical
            interpretations of their campus’s history, which aren’t represented on the current
            physical sites. In this way, VR technologies enable users to create multimodal learning
            experiences with layered, immersive stories. There is also growing evidence to suggest
            that VR can impact visioning and transcultural understanding. For example, <ptr target="#mills2020"/> created <title rend="italic">La République</title>, an educational VR experience that shares the lives of four
            Parisians living in the same quarter. The experience follows these individuals
            throughout their days at work and at home and in public and private contexts. They found
            that the project <quote rend="inline">led to a clear shift in students’ understanding of Parisian culture</quote>
            <ptr target="#mills2020" loc="756"/>. Of note, they saw that after the VR experiences, students who had not
            previously been to Paris scored similarly to students who had been to Paris before in
            being able to <quote rend="inline">imagine their potential role as active participants in Parisian life</quote> <ptr target="#mills2020" loc="757"/>. The project attempts to enable students to experience feelings of presence, which
            <ptr target="#delapena2010"/> describe as <quote rend="inline">the sense of being in a place</quote> <ptr target="#delapena2010" loc="294"/> and argue
            allow users to understand another’s perspective and thereby empathize with them. </p></div>
         <div>
         <head>VR and Empathy</head>
         <p>Visual artist Chris Milk famously described VR as the <quote rend="inline">ultimate empathy machine</quote>
            during a 2015 TED Talk. Milk created the VR film, <title rend="italic">Clouds Over
               Sidra</title>, about a young girl’s experience in a Syrian refugee camp in Jordan. <ptr target="#milk2015"/> claims the medium enables the viewer to <quote rend="inline">feel her humanity in a deeper way</quote> and
            to <quote rend="inline">empathize with her in a deeper way.</quote> Immersive technologies have become a very
            popular creation tool for consciousness raising and social justice work. For example,
            many projects center issues of race <ptr target="#hyphenlabs"/> <ptr target="#smith"/> <ptr target="#hostileterrain"/>, sexual and gender identity <ptr target="#ayala"/> <ptr target="#helsa2021"/> <ptr target="#ado2021"/>, and other topics. While research has found that VR can promote empathy
            <ptr target="#ahn2013"/> <ptr target="#yee2006"/>, this concept is also
            understandably receiving criticism. Acknowledging that empathy awareness raising
            projects are often well intentioned, <ptr target="#nakamura2020"/> argues that VR <quote rend="inline">is identity tourism
            for the 21st century, but with a difference. This time, the kinds of bodies that are on
            offer are not just exotic, racialized and gendered avatars that users can take on
            recreationally and temporarily</quote> <ptr target="#nakamura2020" loc="54"/> and that VR <quote rend="inline">reproduce[s] racial violence in the
               name of reducing it</quote> <ptr target="#nakamura2020" loc="51"/>. The temporary <soCalled>owning</soCalled> of another’s body and experiences
            is problematic in that you cannot automate real and genuine connection with another
            human being. One cannot really understand what it is to live in a refugee camp by
            wearing a VR HMD for a few minutes. <ptr target="#nakamura2019"/> suggests, <quote rend="inline">If you want to decolonize
            VR, I think we need to look at how to give resources to communities to produce VR that
            don’t have it now.</quote> This could also involve, at a very minimum, collaboration with the
            communities centered by the project. <ptr target="#lueck2020"/> recommend that the
            collaborative process should make room for <quote rend="inline">consultation in an iterative process of
               design and feedback</quote> <ref target="#lueck2020">para. 32</ref>. <ptr target="#caspar2021"/> argues that
            working with communities <quote rend="inline">and in some cases co-writing and co-filming [leads] to better
               storytelling</quote> <ptr target="#caspar2021" loc="137"/>. </p>
         <p>Our project could not have happened without the relationships and trust Mélanie shared
            with the survivors, which she spent years cultivating. The survivors also provided
            guidance throughout the process. In one case, the 360º recording was created in the
            presence of a survivor, Rachel Jedinak, who guided us around key locations. In her
            written memoir, Jedinak echoes what we hope VR can provide the viewers. She explains
            that when she finally found the strength to go back to the neighborhood of her
            childhood, in 1997, <quote rend="inline">[she] reconstructed the places, the streets, the routes, and the
            map now has its shape and lines, wrapped around Duris Street. [Her] past regains its
               geography.</quote><note> <quote rend="inline">Childhoods have their spaces. They stretch out on maps that for a
               long time seem as big as entire cities. As you grow up, you realize that it was only
               four or five streets, a dozen places and the school in the center. My childhood was
               spread out over several maps. I had to find the little girl from the Bellevilloise to
               go back to the one of my early years. The most intimate, probably because it was the
               happiest. All my memories were trapped, like those Christmas ornaments where you can,
               through the glass, watch the snow fall indefinitely. Together we reconstructed the
               places, the streets, the routes, and the map now has its shape and lines, wrapped
               around Duris Street. My past regains its geography</quote> <ptr target="#jedinak2018" loc="23–24"/>. </note> In another case, a survivor’s memoir
            informed how students filmed locations described in the text. The recordings were also
            presented to the survivors, who offered feedback and answered students’ questions. This
            input was then integrated into the final product and proved invaluable because students
            learned from these interactions and subsequently adapted their approaches. Our project
            sought to explore VR’s potential for empathy fostering and perspective sharing.
            Nevertheless, we neither claim that the tool is a replacement for real connections nor
            that it can really make the user understand the violence of life under Occupation or the
            tragedy of the Shoah. We also do not see this project as a means to an end but
            rather as another creative strategy to preserve this history and reach and engage with new
            audiences. </p></div>
         <div>
         <head>VR and Making</head>
         <p>From a making perspective, VR also affords humanities students with unique opportunities
            for critical inquiry, interpretation, and reflection. Neville et al. (<ref target="#neville2020">2020</ref>) write:</p>
         <cit><quote rend="block">The research required for developing culturally sensitive, ethical, and historically
            accurate immersive digital content is both demanding and comprehensive. Compared to
            research methodologies privileging linear subject matter presentations, such as a term
            paper or a video, research for VR projects compels students to consider how elements of
            their chosen topic function together as an interconnected, object-oriented activity
            system</quote> <ref target="#neville2020">para. 4</ref>.</cit>
         <p>Our students engaged with primary and secondary sources to understand what life was like
            for survivors under the Occupation. They used these resources to interpret the ways
            survivors saw, understood, and felt about key locations around Paris and make decisions
            about what information to highlight. They considered how others would engage with their
            360º recording and needed to think about point of view and where and how to position the
            camera. <ptr target="#caspar2021"/> writes: <quote rend="inline">…the most important decision is where to position the
            camera within the environment, in order to provide the viewer with a realistic and clear
            point of view. This point of view is decidedly humanist and comes from an understanding
            of person and place</quote> <ptr target="#caspar2021" loc="139"/>. This aligned with the goals for the course and the need
            to see and articulate these spaces in new ways with the survivors’ memories and point of
            view at the center. </p>
            <p><ptr target="#neville2020"/> continue, <quote rend="inline">Student roles shift from being passive recipients of
            knowledge to co-creators in the learning experience. These shifts allow team members to
            learn from each other as they integrate their own discipline knowledge and methods into
            the project</quote> <ref target="#neville2020">para. 4</ref>. We encouraged students to take ownership of and invest
            personally in the project. These histories and memories required care, and the survivors
            and the instructor trusted the students as collaborators. Their contributions were then
            integrated into the instructor’s digital maps locating the survivors’ childhood geographies; the map is used as an open educational tool for future classes as well as the
            general public. Throughout this creation process, students were also able to see
            knowledge production at work: <quote rend='inline'>Just as the creator of the virtual representation must
            make choices about how ‘real’ to make their visualization (what to include and exclude),
            so the historian makes choices regarding what data to include and how that data is
            represented</quote> <ptr target="#ocallaghan2020"/>. Students came to understand that their recordings were subject to their own
            bias and interpretation and that their directorial decisions really mattered and
            impacted the way others would experience this history. This became especially apparent
            after they shared several meetings with survivors and received feedback on their work.
               <ptr target="#lueck2020"/> write, <quote rend="inline">XR positions students as analysts as well as creators of
            commemorative landscapes, alert to the relations of power and influence that shape these
            constructions, both virtual and physical</quote> <ref target="#lueck2020">para. 29</ref>. Our team’s
            preparation in the classroom, both with immersive technologies and historical and
            cultural coursework, allowed us to embark on what would be a life-changing journey for
            instructor, librarians, students, and survivors alike. </p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Methods</head>
            <div>
         <head>Course Context</head>
         <p>Each year, this course is offered as an advanced French History and Culture course
            through the French and Francophone Studies program. Yet, in fall 2019, a second section
            was opened to non-French speaking students and an eight-day trip to Paris was conducted after the end of the semester. The course description reads:</p>
         <p>In this course, we will explore the dark years of the Vichy Regime's collaboration with
            Nazi Germany. Thus, we will be exploring a past that none of us has experienced
            directly. And not just any past: a past which was repressed, covered, disguised. A past
            full of shadows. A past only spoken of in whispers. A past recalled by memories with
            gaping holes. In short, the myth of the <title rend="italic">Résistance</title> only
            fascinates briefly before the reality of the camps sets in, and one becomes too
            petrified with fear to continue looking back.</p>
         <p>How <emph>can</emph> one talk about what happened? What words <emph>can</emph> one use to tell the story of the missing? These were some of
            the challenges faced by the post-Auschwitz society. This is the challenge of the course
            [...]</p>
         <p><quote rend="inline">I do not <emph>hear</emph> what she says.</quote> The lexical confusion of a student
            whose mother tongue is Spanish was the crucial moment. Translating <emph
               >entender</emph> (to understand) by the French <emph>entendre </emph>(to
            hear) to explain that she did not understand what the author said in her diary written
            in 1942 made sense. The apparent mistake conjured up a series of fundamental questions:
            How to understand a story if you do not hear the voice that tells it? How to make sense
            of words pronounced by voices without context? How to envisage Paris under the German
            Occupation without knowing its space? </p></div>
            <div>
         <head>Mending|Minding Holes with Digital Technology</head>
               <div>
         <head>Digital Map of WWII Paris 1. </head>
            <p>To better answer these questions, Mélanie, in collaboration
            with the Penn Libraries and the Price Lab for the Digital Humanities, first made an
               <ref target="https://pennds.org/melanieperon/neatline/fullscreen/test-exhibit">interactive digital map</ref> of WWII Paris. First, they purchased a vintage 1940 paper map on
            eBay for 5 euros and both scanned and georectified it. Then, they created an Omeka<note>
               Omeka, a free, flexible, open-source web-publishing platform is often a popular
               choice in library- or museum-related projects for displaying digital collections and
               exhibitions. In our case, Omeka provided a platform that would let us interlink
               images, descriptions, and videos while also incorporating the digital map as a main
               feature of the site. </note> site to host the digital map and its ancillary
            documents. Finally, using Neatline,<note> Neatline, an add-on or <q>plugin</q> to Omeka,
               developed by Scholar’s Lab at UVA, allows scholars to tell stories with maps, images,
               and timelines. After testing several digital mapping platforms, Neatline allowed for
               the customization and integrations we wanted our map to display and enabled us to
               have multiple participants working on a project at a given time.</note> Mélanie and
               her student Kyra Schulman geolocated 240 key historical places and identified with a description of the place pre-war, during the war, and post-war. Each pin comes with a picture and,
            when possible, excerpts from selected memoirs, contemporary press articles, and videos
            from the French national archives.</p>
         <p> This stitched-together spatial visualization of history aimed to reduce the historical
            and psychological distance which separates us from then/them. For instance, one could
            tell students in lecture that 13,000 Jews, most of whom lived in East Paris, were
            rounded up on July 16, 1942, and taken to a velodrome located in West Paris before being
            sent to concentration camps. It would not trigger the same understanding of history as
            showing them on the map where the velodrome stood. Once they see how close it was to the
            Eiffel Tower, held as a symbol of modernity and culture, they understand how
            unfathomable the event was at the time and still is. It also enables them to wonder how
            Parisians could say they did not know when many of them must have witnessed the day-long
            procession of buses. These were questions post-war France had to face, too.</p>
         <p>While famous Parisian locations are already known to most students, the map acts as an
            X-ray of the city summoning the untold narratives hidden behind these places. As Patrick
            Modiano, who received the Nobel prize for <quote rend="inline">the art of memory with which he has evoked
            the most ungraspable human destinies and uncovered the life-world of the Occupation,</quote>”
            <ptr target="#nobelmedia2014a"/>, explained in his Oslo speech:</p>
         <cit><quote rend="block">[...] in my youth, to help me write, I tried to find the old Parisian telephone
            directories, especially the ones that listed names by street with building numbers. I
            had the feeling as I turned the pages that I was looking at an X ray of the city – a
            submerged city like Atlantis – and breathing in the scent of time.</quote> <ptr target="#nobelmedia2014b"/></cit>
         <p>Neatline makes the ontological connections between the temporal layers literally
            visible, further supporting Modiano’s palimpsest metaphor. As a matter of fact, upon
            logging into the map, for a few seconds, one can witness different layers overlap, the
            WWII map coming together and eventually laying over the current map of Paris. In this
            specific instance, digital technology reminds the user to read between the lines and
            look beyond the surface, which are elemental inquisitive principles leading to
            understanding. The visualization of the underlying imbricating process also illustrates
            the inherent preservation capacity of digital technology, fixing our artifacts in a
            social collective memory, as opposed to the idea of deletion and obsolescence often
            associated with digital platforms. Finally, by placing the map on the open web, not
            restricted by copyright and hidden behind paywalls, it allows for serendipitous
            discovery. It provides access to a wider audience, not just to those who have access to
            institutional resources or are otherwise connected to scholarly endeavors. </p></div>
               <div>
         <head>Immersive Voices from the Past 2. </head>
            <p>The course material includes the testimonies of
            Arlette Testyler, Francine Christophe, and Rachel Jedinak left with the USC Shoah
            Foundation Visual History Archive (VHA). The three survivors lived in Paris before and
            during part of the war before being interned, deported, or hidden. In July 2019, Rachel
            took the instructor to her childhood neighborhood and walked her through the terrible
            day of July 16, 1942, when the French police arrested her with her mother and sister.
            Unlike their mother, the two young girls were fortunate to escape from the
            Bellevilloise, where Jews were held before being bused to the Vélodrome d’Hiver. Using a
            360° camera, Rachel was filmed walking from where her house stood to the Bellevilloise
            while telling the story of the neighborhood and her family along the way. The makeshift
            ethnographic <ref target="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLIS_ynEbt_u8fmDAB1_kaHruUS3kXybVA">clips</ref> were then added to a digital map dedicated to Rachel. This original
            experience with VR technology enabled the digital cartographic translation to don a
            humanity that speaks to us in a way that we can <emph>hear</emph> today. It
            further inspired the following student-curated digital projects.</p></div></div>
            <div>
         <head>From Learners to Makers</head>
         <p>The digital projects were not introduced as assignments, but rather as lasting
            contributions students were going to make to the course, to the Shoah studies and, more
            importantly, to the people whose stories we were going to transcribe. From the first day
            of class, students knew they were not going to receive concrete grades based on
            prescriptive rubrics. Instead, they had a timeline to help them manage their workflow
            and received personal detailed emails to guide them on their respective works. After
            returning from Paris, they had two weeks to finalize their projects. The final grade
            system was binary: A if the work was completed; B if it was not. The class dynamic was
            built on the honor pledge everyone involved in the projects made to each other and
            themselves — we were going to work and do our best for <emph>them</emph>, the
            people whose stories we wanted to be heard and preserved in a social collective memory. </p>
               <div>
         <head>Mapping Memory 1.</head>
                  <p>On campus, the students were asked to curate <ref target="https://pennds.org/melanieperon/exhibits/show/vha/rachel-jedinak">a webpage</ref> for a survivor
            from the Shoah Foundation VHA. The webpage had to include a biography, pictures, the
            transcription of the testimony and a digital map locating the key places mentioned. In
            groups of four to five, the students from the French section were entrusted with the
            stories of Arlette, Francine, and Rachel. The students from the English section, in
            pairs, had to find VHA testimonies made in English from survivors who, at the time of
            the war, lived in Paris. Two pairs were able to get in touch with their subject — via
            phone conversations for one group and in person for the other group — after conducting
            research on their own. All students received training on how to use Omeka and Neatline
            (Appendix A). The purpose was for their pages to be added to the Omeka course site and
            to subsequently become part of future course material. Students were asked to reflect on
            their roles in shaping these digital histories and to be thoughtful with the design
            aspects of their survivors’ pages and maps. Finally, they learned how to populate a map
            on Neatline using the items they had archived on Omeka. </p>
         <p>One class meeting was also dedicated to teaching students how to use the Parisian public
            transportation system from the hotel they would be staying at to the various places
            connected to their survivor’s story. It was important to create a déjà-vu feeling once
            they arrived in Paris. While in Paris, students were asked to <q>go back</q> to all the
            places they already knew since they had mapped them and gathered corollary documentation
            to be added to their webpage. The group who met their survivor in the U.S. was in daily
            contact <ref target="https://pennds.org/melanieperon/exhibits/show/vha/nathan-spiewak">with him</ref>. They regularly sent him pictures of his former geography to which he
            never failed to respond providing more historical details:</p>
         <cit><quote rend="block">I started to cry looking at the photos. Our apartment was on the left 3rd floor on the
            right side of the stairs. Outside the gate on the left there was a restaurant where my
            mother used to get food and on the right was a store that sold office supplies. The gate
            is different and in the court there was [sic] no plants or anything. I am still crying.
            Please send me the photos that you took of the apartments.</quote> (N. Spiewak, personal communication, January 6, 2020)</cit>
         <p>Thanks to in-person Q&amp;As scheduled with Francine alone and then with Arlette and
            Rachel together, the whole class engaged in an intimate dialogue with history through
            their personal storytelling. The three ladies were amazed and grateful to hear how much
            their young public already knew about their places of memory.</p>
         <p> The mapping project allowed students to physically retrace the steps they had remotely
            taken on the digital platform. Above all, it enabled them to literally walk in the
            survivors’ steps. Despite the changes the streets underwent through time, the students
            were anachronistic reminders of the stories that took place under today’s facades and
            are forgotten by many. They became archiving connectors between then and now, peeling
            off the superimposed layers covering what was once the reality of their survivors.</p></div>
               <div>
         <head>Recording Memory Landscape 2.</head>
           <p> In the second half of the semester, the class read <title
               rend="italic">Sur la Scène Intérieure</title> (<title rend="italic">On the Inner
            Stage</title>) by Marcel Cohen (2013). It tells the story of his family members who never
            came back from deportation. Through his memories as a five-year-old boy and the objects
            that belonged to his loved ones, he takes the reader to the Parisian places and personal
            realms which delineated his childhood. After the text was discussed in class, students
            were divided into four cross-section groups. Each chose one particular place described
            in the book that they wanted to film with a 360° camera in Paris. </p>
         <p>We chose 360° as our medium in part because the consumer-grade cameras (Appendix B)
            proved to be very accessible for new users. Most immersive technologies have a steep
            learning curve and require lengthy periods of time for the creation process. We had only
            a week in Paris and a full program, of which the 360° project was just one part. <ptr target="#lueck2020"/> recommend <quote rend="inline">modest contributions</quote> and a more <quote rend="inline">incremental process</quote> that
            enable <quote rend="inline">more care, more caution, and, ultimately, a more collaborative framework going
               forward</quote> (<ref target="#lueck2020">para. 5</ref>). Our project benefited from this approach as well as it allowed the
            students enough time to grasp the technology, to make and fix mistakes, to get feedback,
            and to edit their projects. </p>
         <p>On campus, students received training using Insta360 One X cameras (Appendix B) and then
            editing the recordings (Appendix C). Once in Paris, over the course of four days,
            students <ref target="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLIS_ynEbt_u-7N2IRHaYp8T5G9EqNCOZQ">filmed</ref> and edited a raw version of their videos. Through the creation of the
            documentaries, students were in dialogue with Cohen’s text, interpreting and capturing
            the space through his words. The use of 360° cameras enabled students to reconstruct
            these spaces — albeit transformed by time — more authentically for viewers, providing
            them with an impression of how these spaces impacted the author. This created a dynamic
            triad of author, students, and viewer in which all have agency. On the one hand, the
            author’s narration accompanied the 360° video and determined filming locations; on the
            other, students interpreted his words through the filming and editing of 360°
            experiences while the viewer in a VR headset chooses how to engage these experiences —
            unhindered by framing boundaries to a degree. </p>
         <p>At the end of each filming day, students edited their footage. They were asked to select
            clips to show the author later that week. The group that filmed the itinerary that
            Marcel Cohen took to visit his mother awaiting deportation in the Rothschild Hospital
            wanted to be creative. They originally shot a clip, in which one of them posed as his
            mother. However, due to its potentially triggering nature, we asked them not to demo
            this clip. When we met the author at his home, he asked Mélanie to read aloud excerpts
            he had selected from his book and other personal documents, explaining he was passing
            his voice onto her. At that moment, Cohen directly invited <emph>us
            </emph>into <emph>his</emph> story and willingly became an active participant in
               <emph>our</emph> project — coming full circle. He then generously answered
            our questions and agreed to put on the Oculus VR headset and watched the first video,
            filmed in the Parc Monceau, one of the places to which he seldom goes back. After an
            initial reaction of wonder, the little-boy-turned-old-man was visibly moved, removed the
            headset, and thanked us. He did not want to see more. This moment was a reminder that
            our use of immersive tools comes with ethical responsibilities. As much as this virtual
            spatial translation can lead to a deeper understanding of the text by the reader, one
            must bear in mind it can also trigger anxiety in the subject/author of the text.
            Following this encounter, the <soCalled>creative group</soCalled> agreed on their own <quote rend="inline">it would not be
            right</quote> to keep their acting scene. This decision-making was an example of how the
            students gained perspective and empathy and grew through the heuristic process. </p>
         <p>Critical making evokes a shared sense of responsibility for work that exists beyond
            itself and its impetus for creation, existing in an interconnected web of relationships.
            This realization became clearer after the poignant meeting with the author, in which the
            group was immersed in his home, his hospitality, and his feedback. Once again, students
            became active collaborators of the course since the recordings were eventually embedded
            on the <ref target="https://pennds.org/melanieperon/neatline/fullscreen/marcelcohen">digital map</ref> dedicated to the author’s life during the war and will be used as
            course material in the future as an alternative reading method of Cohen’s text.</p></div></div></div>
            <div>
         <head>Outcome</head>
         <epigraph><cit><quote rend="block">Transitioning from users to makers helps students understand the deeper issues.</quote>
            <ptr target="#cipolla2019" loc="261"/></cit></epigraph>
               <div>
         <head>Technology Effectiveness</head>
               <p>As <ptr target="#cipolla2019"/> emphasizes, the transition from user to maker is essential for
            students to find meaning through their digital projects. Before learning the making
            technologies utilized in the course — Omeka/Neatline and 360° cameras and software —
            students were asked to assess their own experiences learning technology in the
            classroom, applying technology to their projects and, finally, the overall utility or
            effectiveness of the technology to their project objectives (Appendix D). A survey on
            Google Forms was administered by the instructor to students via email in the fall 2019
            semester as digital projects were underway. Students were informed that survey responses
            would remain anonymous and would in no way impact their individual or project grades. Of
            the 22 students in the class, 18 students responded to the questions in the Technology
            Effectiveness Survey, Part I (Appendix E).</p> 
         
         
               <figure>
                  <head>Results of Technology Effectiveness Survey, Part I</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/image1.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Screenshot of eight pie charts</figDesc>
               </figure>
         
         
           <p> As Figure 1 demonstrates, most students found it easier to create and apply
            digital content to their own projects after having learned the material in a hands-on
            workshop. Unsurprisingly, Neatline proved to be the most challenging of the
            technologies, as students had to navigate both layers — modern-day and 1940s-Paris — of
            the digital map. Most students found Omeka and Neatline effective for telling their
            survivor’s story.</p>
         <p>Surprisingly, many students found making VR recordings even easier than when they were
            learning about them in the workshop. Overwhelmingly, students rated making these videos
            <q>very effective</q> for conveying Marcel Cohen’s story. One student wrote in the survey
            comments, <quote rend="inline">When you put on the VR goggles, it feels as though you are being placed in
            the middle of his story and walking with him through the places of his childhood,</quote>
            harkening back to the core principle of empathy that the instructor intended as a
            pedagogical goal in using this technology to create and then preserve the collective
            memory of this project. </p>
         <p>Although students perceived the technology as effective in carrying out their project
            goals, inevitable and various technical obstacles triggered obvious frustration upon
            use. Upon returning from Paris, students were asked to complete a second survey,
            Technology Effectiveness Survey, Part II, to evaluate the utility of the technologies in
            completing their final projects (Appendix F). The instructor emailed the Google Forms
            survey to the students; they were again informed that results would be kept anonymous
            and that their responses would in no way affect their grades. This survey’s free-form
            responses emphasized that problem-solving processes served as pathways of learning,
            reminding us all how unclarity, unfairness, unanswerable questions are part of life and
            how recognizing it is the first step to <quote rend="inline">build it better</quote> <ptr target="#cipolla2019"/>, as one
            student responded: </p>
         <cit><quote rend="block">The experience of shooting 360° videos allowed me to gain a deeper understanding of the
            places with which Marcel Cohen interacted as a child. While filming the videos was not a
            simple task, and we encountered several challenges along the way, I nonetheless learned
            so much from the entire experience. </quote></cit>
         <p>Because the trip to Paris happened during winter break and ended two days before spring
            semester resumed, students had two weeks to complete their assignments upon returning.
            With their authorization, the instructor proofread and edited the survivors’ webpages
            and maps. The 360° videos were also finalized by the instructor before being embedded
            into a map dedicated to Marcel Cohen. The author declined to record the videos’
            voice-over once more entrusting the instructor to be his voice. All the student-curated
            works will be passed on to the next class as course material. One core agreement is that
            the students will permanently keep their administrative status on Omeka so they may
            remain contributors to the memorial palimpsest we stitched together for as long as they
            choose to. </p></div>
            <div>
         <head>Co-Constructivist Dialogue </head>
         <p>Through these making projects, students experienced first-hand what the instructor had
            experienced through her own projects of the original digital map and Rachel Jedinak’s
            memory walk in 360° in July 2019. The conventional teacher / student binary disappeared
            to give place to a co-constructivist dialogue.</p>
         <p>Students also attained a level of understanding of the texts, and consequently history,
            difficult to achieve had they not been asked to tinker with the matter with their own
            hands. For instance, when they located the main places of their survivors’ childhood,
            they realized how close-knit Arlette’s family was, how Francine Christophe and Marcel
            Cohen must have crossed paths in the Parc Monceau, and how the mothers of Rachel Jedinak
            and Georges Perec (whose work <title rend="italic">W or the childhood memory </title>(1975) is
            studied in class) might have known each other by sight. In response to questions in Part
            II of the survey (Appendix F), one student wrote, <quote rend="inline">Creating the [survivor] testimony and
            page and map was undoubtedly a meaningful experience, and definitely brought me closer
            to my [survivor]’s story and course content. Creating the page and mapp [sic] allowed us
            to delve deeper into our [survivor]’s story and bring to life an aspect of our
            [survivor]’s childhood/story in a creative manner.</quote> </p>
         <p>Filming Marcel Cohen’s memories made them read the text differently. They were, in fact,
            put in situations which led them to read between and behind the lines, as another
            student’s survey response shows: </p>
         <cit><quote rend="block">Walking through the hustle and bustle of Paris from his home to the Cabaret, to the
            brasserie, to the park was physically exhausting, which I feel made me reflect on what
            it might have been like to be a child walking this route. Questions popped into my mind
            like, ‘Was he tired or energetic to get to the park?’ It was only something I would have
            thought of if I didn’t get the experience to shoot the video.</quote></cit>
         <p>Literally walking in the little boy’s shoes triggered a level of empathy, and therefore
            understanding, that would have eluded most ways of reading, as another student
            elaborated in survey comments:</p>
         <cit><quote rend="block">This experience allowed me to a [sic] have a more three-dimensional image/perspective of
            the specific memories Marcel Cohen recounts in his book. While reading the stories in
            the book in itself is a touching/moving experience, tracing Marcel’s footsteps in person
            really helped me to bring to life the passages from the book. Reading the stories is one
            type of experience, but actually seeing the places mentioned in the book and visually
            processing the stories is [a] whole other experience.</quote> </cit>
         <p>The students’ comments to Part II of the survey underline the importance of making an
            abstraction relatable by making one care and that the technology was essential to see
            themselves as part of the narrative.</p></div>
            <div>
         <head>Epistolary and Lasting Exchanges</head>
         <p>One unforeseen, and yet so poetically apropos, outcome of the projects is the epistolary
            exchanges that ensued after our trip to Paris. Upon our return, five students resorted
            to a practice so long forgotten by most of them to express their gratitude to the older
            people we met. Three students also hand-wrote letters to the instructor. This gesture
            recalled <ptr target="#ratto2011b"/>’s  <quote rend="inline">creation of novel understandings by the makers themselves</quote>
            <ref target="#ratto2011b">para. 3</ref> and idea of matter of fact vs. matter of concern: </p>
         <cit><quote rend="block">I had been to Paris a few times before, and it had always been the romantic Paris. A
            city of love, light, intelligence, art, history, and culture. But I now see a new Paris.
            The love and the light are not gone though. They are intermingled with a sort of
            darkness. I had never before noticed any of the plaques on the schools or buildings when
            walking around Paris. I surely have walked past them before, but I was never looking for
            them. And so I never saw them. Now, I have something to look for. I am equipped with
            this knowledge to be able to see both the light and the dark. And it’s not just in
            Paris. I’m sure there is light and dark everywhere in the world. It just takes a little
            extra effort to uncover some of the hidden truths. I hope, as someone who is tasked with
            passing down the stories of the individuals we met, I do a great job at helping others
            to see such things as well. Not only did I discover a new Paris, but it was as though I
            almost discovered a new me. Maybe not a new me, but I was able to see things about
            myself I hadn’t seen before.</quote> (S. Davis, personal communication, January 15, 2020)</cit>
         <cit><quote rend="block">I knew [the course] would be magical but I knew not the extent to which I would be
            forever changed by its teachings. While still processing last week’s trip, I am aware of
            a new sense of gratitude and compassion within me. That’s what this class and journey
            was: opening my eyes to the abundance of humanity that is always and everywhere.</quote> (A. Malinovich, personal communication, January 15, 2020) </cit>
         <p>The gratitude felt by the students was reciprocated by the survivors we met. Within a
            few days after our return, we received emails and letters from each of them. Francine
            Christophe’s husband’s handwritten note, in English, was especially touching: <quote rend="inline">Sad not
            to see you again. If one (or two) of you flies to Paris bear in mind that they have
            friends on the spot [phone number]</quote> (J.-J. Lorch, personal communication, February 3, 2020). The ninety-year-old man recognized the care students put in the projects they
            made and therefore acknowledged them as friends to whom he entrusted his most precious
            possession: his legacy. The learners-turned-makers knocked down walls between
            generations, reduced distances, and built unexpected friendships. The author Marcel
            Cohen echoed Mr. Lorch’s words in a handwritten card he sent in response to a student’s
            letter: </p>
         <cit><quote rend="block">Your visit to Paris, your work, your curiosity are extremely precious if one thinks
            about the future and I don’t doubt you have the ability to make it less dark than the
            past was. Believe in all my gratitude and my deep friendship.</quote> (M. Cohen, personal communication, February 6, 2020)</cit><note> Translated from French by M. Péron</note>
         
         <p>The goal of the projects does not end with the course. Not only do all the participants
            involved in the projects feel a duty to make sure our new old <emph
               >friends</emph>’ voices can continue to be heard, but they are also aware that their
            common experience provides them with reading keys they will be able to apply to future
            situations.</p></div></div>
            <div>
         <head>Further Applications</head>
         <p>Even though the project was first conceived for a foreign language course, it was easily
            adapted to a humanities course taught in English. Since students received technical
            training, it was also listed as an elective toward the institution’s minor in digital
            humanities. While this article describes an iteration of the course with a physical trip
            to Paris, the subsequent iteration did not. Even though it cannot replace the in-situ
            tangible atmospheric feel, the preexisting digital map of WWII Paris combined with the
            embedded 360° videos and Google Map offered a reliable alternative. In the classroom,
            the successive students were able to follow itineraries and walk in the streets as the
            former students had a few months prior. They could also move the slider on the Google
            Map Street View and select a thumbnail to see that same place through time until 2008.
            This is how the mapping project can fulfill its role as a portal through space and time
            from within the classroom. </p>
         <p>One mission of the project is to preserve the fleeting materiality of human stories. We
            have been fortunate to be able to literally record the voices and physically meet
            face-to-face with some of the survivors whose stories we digitally translated. A time
            will come when it won’t be possible anymore. Yet, the materiality of an existence and
            recording voices can take other forms, as Serge Klarsfeld, the author of the now
            searchable <title rend="italic">Memorial to the Jews Deported from France, 1942-1944
            </title>(<ref target="https://www.stevemorse.org/france/">https://www.stevemorse.org/france/</ref>), explains in the preface he wrote to the
            publication of Louise Jacobson’s letters:</p>
         <cit><quote rend="block">But what is a voice? It can be a particularly poignant letter, written before or after
            the arrest, which reveals a personality or the strength of a destiny. It can be a look
            in a photograph that catches your eye and that you will never forget. It can be a simple
            name of a child in a list of deported adults who leaves, alone, isolated, without his or
            her parents, and which you must keep in your memory because you cannot abandon him or
            her too. It can be a drawing that expresses hopes or betrays anguish and sorrow</quote> <ptr target="#jacobson1997" loc="8"/></cit>
           <p><ptr target="#auslander2005"/> also reminds us that <quote rend="inline">most people for most of human history have not
            used written language as their major form of expression. They have created meaning,
            represented the world, and expressed their emotions through textiles, wood, metal,
            dance, and music. Material culture is simply another vital source of historical
            knowledge, supplemental to words for those who have had little access to them</quote> <ptr target="#auslander2005" loc="1018"/>.
            The pedagogic capacity of material culture reassures us that our project not only will
            be able to keep its relevance even after the survivors are not here anymore but also it
            shows that the principle of the project can be adapted to topics without living
            participants. </p>
               <p>One may also think of Princeton’s Shakespeare and Company project 
                  (<ref target="https://shakespeareandco.princeton.edu/">https://shakespeareandco.princeton.edu/</ref>), which catalogs the library cards of Sylvia
            Beach’s Parisian library. On these rectangular sepia cards, the ink, the handwriting,
            the list of books conjure up, in a relatable way, a time long gone and one’s vanished
            existence. Within the same semiotic realm, translating onto a digital platform textiles,
            graffiti, annotations, letters, to list a few examples of traces left behind by a human
            being, can open the same interstice between now and then. When no witness is left or
            when one believes the physical landscape is not legible to us due to substantial
            changes, one should remember Georges Didi-Huberman’s (2018) injunction in his book about
            a visit to Auschwitz-Birkenau:</p>
         <cit><quote rend="block">We can therefore never say, <quote rend="inline">There’s nothing to see, there’s no more to see.</quote> To be able
            to doubt what we see, we must know how to keep looking, how to see in spite of
            everything. Despite the destruction, the erasure, of all things. We must know how to
            look the way an archaeologist looks. And it’s by way of such a gaze – such an
            interrogation – directed toward what we see that things begin to look at us from their
            concealed spaces and bygone time. (...) The destruction of beings does not mean they are
            departed. They’re here, they are indeed here: here in the flowers of the fields, here in
            the birches’ sap, here in this tiny pond where lie the ashes of thousands dead</quote>
            <ptr target="#didihuberman2018" loc="37–38"/></cit>
         <p>​​Nature, materials left behind can still connect <emph>us</emph> to <emph>them </emph>while digital humanities can anchor their existence back in
            time and space, with immersive technology recreating the stories of objects and their
            human voices. </p></div>
            <div>
         <head>Conclusion</head>
         <p>The digital humanities projects presented in this article opened an interstice into the
            fabric of time and space which enables the participants and anyone accessing their
            products to connect with a distant past and a faraway place. Like Medusa, the Shoah
            petrifies and like Perseus, one needs a shield to confront it. The projects became the
            shields the instructor and the students forged in order to approach a frightening part
            of history and draw personal lessons from it. The back-and-forth movement between past
            and present, historical narratives and individual testimonies, national and personal,
            reading and making encouraged them to not only <emph>consider </emph>the time
            period but also to <emph>be considerate</emph> towards those who lived it. It
            enabled them to feel empathy towards people and a time they could not <emph
               >hear</emph> at first. Their endeavors put on the map the unheard stories of invisible
            strangers, stitched together scattered narratives, and weaved an infinite constellation
            connecting that past to our current present. They learned to take into consideration the
            humanity of others, to recognize themselves in others and others in themselves. A
            philanthropic knowledge they can further apply to other invisible, voiceless individuals
            from other places who live around us today.</p>
         <p>As a conclusion, the authors would like to argue that the students who, with nothing but
            care, tinkered with the stories of strangers were all at once curators, cartographers,
            printmakers, videographers and, most importantly, <term>critical
               makers</term>, who benevolently participated in Klarsfeld’s collecting of voices. As <ptr target="#ratto2011a"/> emphasizes that <quote rend="inline">there is an important need for critical makers that can
                  reintegrate technical and social work and thereby innovate both</quote> <ptr target="#ratto2011a" loc="258"/>, we hope that
            enabling students as makers in this course, which is one of praxis, bridging the theory
            and the practice, has prepared them to take such a sociocultural and innovative approach
            to their own future endeavors. </p></div>
         
         <div>
         <head>Appendix</head>
            <div>
         <head>Appendix A: Omeka and Neatline Workshop Outline</head>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>Omeka site introduction<list type="ordered">
               <item>Set up student Omeka accounts</item>
            </list>
            </item>
            <item>Student roles - <hi rend="italic">Shaping Digital Histories</hi>
               <list type="ordered">
                  <item>In small groups (3-4 students), students will create a survivor page that
                     consists of the following: <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Biography</item>
                        <item>Archived collection of items</item>
                        <item>Map of places mentioned by the survivor</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item>Omeka basics <list type="ordered">
               <item>Platform landscape</item>
               <item>Fundamentals <list type="ordered">
                  <item>Items, collections, and exhibits</item>
                  <item>Metadata creation<list type="ordered">
                     <item>Class activity - Describing images with Dublin Core</item>
                  </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>Options for exhibit customization<list type="ordered">
                     <item>Font, color, map icons</item>
                  </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            </item>
            <item>Neatline basics<list type="ordered">
               <item>Add an item to a map</item>
            </list>
            </item>
            <item>Copyright best practices</item>
         </list>
            </div>
            <div>
         <head>Appendix B: 360° Camera Workshop Outline</head>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>Hardware overview<list type="ordered">
               <item>Insta360 One X*<list type="ordered">
                  <item>Lightweight, consumer camera that is beginner-friendly</item>
                  <item>Camera syncs easily with an app available on iOS and Android that
                     serves as a remote for the camera.</item>
                  <item>The FlowState stabilization feature steadies the camera when recording
                     and will help minimize motion sickness. </item>
                  <item>Costs:<list type="ordered">
                     <item>*Insta360 One X2 now available: $429.00</item>
                  </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               </item>
               <item>Related equipment<list type="ordered">
                  <item>USB cord, lens cap, carrier pouch, quick-start guide, lens cleaning
                     cloth, two batteries, one 64 GB SD card, camera tripod</item>
                  <item> Extendable selfie stick</item>
                  <item>Costs*:<list type="ordered">
                     <item>Extra battery: $29.00</item>
                     <item>Lens caps: $5.00</item>
                     <item>SD Card: $15.00</item>
                     <item>Camera tripod: $150.00<list type="ordered">
                        <item>Note: Buy a weighted tripod from a third-party company
                           like Bushman. It’s more expensive than the Insta360 tripod,
                           but it's much sturdier and less likely to be knocked over.
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Extendable selfie stick (3m): $69.00</item>
                     <item>*USB cord, carrier pouch, quick-start guide, lens cloth, one
                        battery come with the camera.</item>
                  </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               </item>
               <item>Camera usage<list type="ordered">
                  <item>Pair camera to smartphone</item>
                  <item>Walk through taking photos and videos</item>
               </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            </item>
            <item>Filming best practices<list type="ordered">
               <item>Explore film locations via Google Maps</item>
               <item>Experiment with the camera<list type="ordered">
                  <item>Example 1 - What’s the best way to record exiting the metro?</item>
                  <item>Example 2 - Is it possible to film from the perspective of a
                     child?</item>
               </list>
               </item>
               <item>Filming living subjects<list type="ordered">
                  <item>Explain to the individual how the camera works</item>
                  <item>Position the camera 4-5 feet away from the individual</item>
                  <item>Try to keep the camera at eye-level</item>
               </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            </item>
            <item>Class activity<list type="ordered">
               <item>Shoot two short videos (&lt;30 seconds)<list type="ordered">
                  <item>Practice shooting from a distance, hidden from the camera</item>
                  <item>Interview a group member </item>
               </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            </item>
            <item>Editing basics <list type="ordered">
               <item>Upload files to Insta360° Studio (free software that only works with
                  Insta360 files)</item>
            </list>
            </item>
            <item>Upload exported .mp4 files to Box<list type="ordered">
               <item>Establish a common file-naming convention and organization system</item>
            </list>
            </item>
            <item>Practice <list type="ordered">
               <item>Use the cameras over the course of the semester to not only learn how to
                  operate the cameras and anticipate any questions or problems but to also
                  understand what it is like to capture contexts familiar and personal.</item>
            </list>
            </item>
         </list>
            </div>
            <div>
         <head>Appendix C: Editing and Uploading 360° Videos in Paris Outline</head>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>Advanced editing options<list type="ordered">
               <item> The Insta360° software does not allow for advanced editing (e.g., multiple
                  clips, add video or audio effects)</item>
               <item>As an alternative, Adobe Premiere Pro allows for advanced editing but may be
                  challenging to use and is not freely available. Students may consider
                  registering for a 7-day trial. <list type="ordered">
                     <item>Northwestern University’s Knight Lab’s “How to Edit 360° Video in
                        Adobe Premiere Pro CC” tutorial (Chiu, n.d.). </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            </item>
            <item>Upload original camera files, edited files, and/or editing instructions to Box
               after each filming day.</item>
         </list>
            </div>
            <div>
         <head>Appendix D: Project Learning Objectives </head>
         <p>The following learning objectives for the two course digital projects were used as the
            basis of the survey questions to assess student learning. </p>
         <p>Project 1: Digital Map (Omeka/Neatline)</p>
         <p>Through completing this project, students will be able to: </p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>create a page on Omeka for a VHA Shoah Foundation survivor, using techniques
               learned and demonstrated in class and through tutorials.</item>
            <item>effectively communicate the survivor’s story through both written (French and
               English) and audio/visual formats. </item>
            <item>create map entries on Neatline for places linked to the survivor’s testimony,
               using techniques learned and demonstrated in class and through tutorials. </item>
         </list>
         <p>Project 2: VR Videos (360° Cameras/Software)</p>
         <p>Through completing this project, students will be able to: </p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>plan out a 360° experience to translate Marcel Cohen’s memoir, including
               storyboarding; blocking; lighting; sound; group roles; camera equipment and settings;
               and video editing.</item>
            <item>produce a 360° video with an Insta360 One X camera and related accessories and
               software that will explore and document the physical locations described in Marcel
               Cohen's memoir.</item>
            <item>situate their 360° video within the growing body of work that already exists on
               the Neatline map and project website, contributing new modes of scholarship to the
               ongoing scholarly conversations. <lb/>
            </item>
         </list>
            </div>
            <div>
         <head>Appendix E: Technology Effectiveness Survey, Part I (administered fall 2019)</head>
         <p>Before departing to Paris, students were asked to rate their perceptions of learning the
            digital mapping and 360° video technology after learning them in the classroom workshops
            and then during the application of these technologies as they completed their projects.
            Then, students were asked to rate the utility, or effectiveness, of the technologies in
            carrying out the objectives of their projects. </p>
               
               <figure><head>Technology
                  Effectiveness Survey, Part I: Google Forms Survey Instrument</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/image2.png"/>
                  <figDesc>screenshot of a Google Form</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
               <div>
         <head>Appendix F: Technology Effectiveness Survey, Part II (administered spring 2020) </head>
         <p>Upon returning from Paris, students were asked to complete a short survey about their
            experiences working with the technologies used throughout the course and how they
            did/did not inform their understanding of course material. Because of the short timeline
            to complete this survey, in addition to delayed IRB approval (March 2020) and the
            evacuation of campus due to the coronavirus pandemic, we did not receive as many
            responses as we would have liked. </p>
         <figure><head>Technology
            Effectiveness Survey, Part II: Google Forms Survey Instrument</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/image3.png"/>
            <figDesc>screenshot of a Google Form</figDesc>
         </figure>
            </div>
         </div>
         
        
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            
            <bibl xml:id="accardi2010" label="Accardi 2010"> Accardi, M. T. (2010). <title rend="italic">Feminist pedagogy for library instruction.</title> Library Juice
               Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ado2021" label="Ado Ato Pictures 2021"> Ado Ato Pictures. (2021). <title rend="italic">Another Dream</title>. <ref
               target="https://www.adoatopictures.com/projects/another-dream"
               >https://www.adoatopictures.com/projects/another-dream </ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ahn2013" label="Ahn 2013"> Ahn, S. J., Le, A., &amp; Bailenson, J. (2013). <title rend="quotes">The effect of embodied experiences on
               self-other merging, attitude, and helping behavior.</title> <title rend="italic">Media Psychology</title>, 16(1), 
               7-38. DOI: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/15213269.2012.755877"
                  >10.1080/15213269.2012.755877</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="auslander2005" label="Auslander 2005"> Auslander, L. (2005). <title rend="quotes">Beyond words.</title> <title rend="italic">American Historical Review</title>, 110(4),
               1015-45. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="auslander2018" label="Auslander and Zahra 2018"> Auslander, L., &amp; Zahra, T. (2018). <title rend="italic">Objects of war: The material culture of conflict
               and displacement</title>. Ithaca: Cornell University Press. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ayala" label="Ayala n.d."> Ayala, J. (n.d.). <title rend="italic">Authentically Us</title>. Jesse Ayala. <ref
               target="https://jesseayala.com/authentically-us"
               >https://jesseayala.com/authentically-us</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="caspar2021" label="Caspar 2021"> Caspar, S. (2021). <title rend="quotes">Insider spaces: Hands-on with XR in the global languages &amp;
               cultures room.</title> <title rend="italic">CALICO Journal, 38</title>(1), 128-150. </bibl>
             <bibl xml:id="caswell2016" label="Caswell and Cifor 2016"> Caswell, M., &amp; Cifor, M. (2016). <title rend="quotes">From human rights to feminist ethics: Radical empathy in
               the archives.</title> <title rend="italic">Archivaria, 81</title>, 23.</bibl>
                
           <bibl xml:id="chachra2017" label="Chachra 2017"> Chachra, D. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Beyond
               making.</title> In J. Sayers (Ed.), <title rend="italic">Making things and drawing boundaries: Experiments in the digital humanities, </title>319-321.
               Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chiu" label="Chiu n.d."> Chiu, S. (n.d.). <title rend="italic">How to edit 360 video in Adobe Premiere Pro CC</title>.
               knight lab. 
               <ref
                  target="https://studio.knightlab.com/results/storytelling-layers-on-360-video/how-to-edit-360-video-in-premiere/"
                  >https://studio.knightlab.com/results/storytelling-layers-on-360-video/how-to-edit-360-video-in-premiere/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="christophe1995" label="Christophe 1995"> Christophe, F. (1995). <title rend="italic">Une petite fille privilégiée. Une enfant dans
               le monde des camps 1942-1945. </title>Paris: L’Harmattan.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="christophe2000" label="Christophe 2000"> Christophe, F. (2000). <title rend="italic">From a world apart: a little girl in the
               concentration camps</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cipolla2019" label="Cipolla 2019"> Cipolla, C. (2019). <title rend="quotes">Build it Better: Tinkering in Feminist Maker Pedagogy.</title> <title rend="italic">Women’s
               Studies</title>, 48(3), 261-282. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/00497878.2019.1593842"
               >https://doi.org/10.1080/00497878.2019.1593842</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cohen2013" label="Cohen 2013"> Cohen, M. (2013). <title rend="italic">Sur la scène intérieure. </title>Paris: Gallimard.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="deardoff2011" label="Deardoff 2011"> Deardoff, D. K. (2011). <title rend="quotes">Assessing intercultural competence.</title> <title rend="italic">New directions
               for institutional research</title>, 149, 65-79. DOI: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1002/ir.381"
               >10.1002/ir.381</ref>
            </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="delapena2010" label="de la Peña et al. 2010"> de la Peña, N., Weil, P., Llobera, J., Giannopoulos, E., Pomés, A., Spanlang, B.,
               Friedman, D., Sanchez-Vives, M., &amp; Slater, M. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Immersive journalism:
               Immersive virtual reality for the first-person experience of news.</title> <title
                  rend="italic">Presence</title>, 19, 291-301. <ref
                     target="https://doi.org/10.1162/PRES_a_00005">10.1162/PRES_a_00005</ref>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="didihuberman2018" label="Didi-Huberman 2018"> Didi-Huberman, G. (2018). <title rend="italic">Bark</title> trans. by Samuel E. Martin.
               Cambridge: MIT Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dunne2005" label="Dunne 2005"> Dunne, A. (2005). <title rend="italic">Hertzian tales: Electronic products, aesthetic
               experience, and critical design.</title> Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="feryok2017" label="Feryok 2017"> Feryok, A. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Sociocultural theory and task-based language teaching: The
               role of praxis.</title> <title rend="italic">TESOL Quarterly</title>, 51(3), 716-727. doi: <ref
               target="https://doi.org/10.1002/tesq.390">10.1002/tesq.390</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="feuerstein1998" label="Feurstein et al. 1998"> Feuerstein, R., Falik, L., &amp; Feuerstein, R. (1998). <title rend="quotes">Feuerstein’s LPAD.</title> In R. Samuda
               (Ed.), <title rend="italic">Advances in cross-cultural assessment</title> (pp. 100–161). Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ganemgutierrez2014" label="Gánem-Gutiérrez 2014"> Gánem-Gutiérrez, G. A. (2014). <title rend="quotes">The third dimension: A sociocultural theory approach to
               the design and evaluation of 3D world virtual tasks.</title> In M. Gonzalez-Lloret &amp; L. Ortega
               (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Technology-mediated TBLT: Researching technology and
                  tasks</title> (pp. 213-237). Amsterdam: John Benjamins Publishing Company. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gilligan1982" label="Gilligan 1982"> Gilligan, C. (1982). <title rend="italic">In a different voice: psychological theory and women's
               development.</title> Cambridge: Harvard University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="helsa2021" label="Helsa 2021"> Helsa. (2021). ​​<title rend="italic">Why increased empathy will revolutionise
               the lives of minorities in the workplace</title>. Helsa Helps. 
               <ref
                  target="https://www.helsahelps.com/article/why-increased-empathy-will-revolutionise-the-lives-of-minorities-in-the-workplace"
                  >https://www.helsahelps.com/article/why-increased-empathy-will-revolutionise-the-lives-of-minorities-in-the-workplace</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hooks1994" label="hooks 1994"> hooks, bell. (1994). <title rend="italic">Teaching to Transgress</title>. New York:
               Routledge.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="hostileterrain" label="Hostile Terrain n.d."> Hostile Terrain (n.d.). <title rend="italic">Pop-up Installation Synopsis</title>.
               Undocumented Migration Project. 
                  <ref target="https://hostileterrain94.wordpress.com/about/"
                     >https://hostileterrain94.wordpress.com/about/</ref></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="hyphenlabs" label="Hyphen-Labs. n.d."> Hyphen-Labs. (n.d.). <title rend="italic">NeuroSpeculative AfroFeminism</title>. <ref
                  target="http://www.hyphen-labs.com/nsaf.html"
                  >http://www.hyphen-labs.com/nsaf.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jacobson1997" label="Jacobson and Kaluski-Jacobson 1997"> Jacobson, L., &amp; Kaluski-Jacobson, N. (1997). <title rend="italic">Les lettres de Louise Jacobson et de
               ses proches: Fresnes, Drancy, 1942-1943.</title> Paris: Laffont.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jedinak2018" label="Jedinak 2018"> Jedinak, R. (2018). <title rend="italic">Nous étions seulement des enfants.</title> Paris: Fayard.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lantolf2009" label="Lantolf and Tracy 2009"> Lantolf, James P., B., Tracy G. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Sociocultural theory and second language
               acquisition: Research Timeline.</title> <title rend="italic">Language Teaching</title>, 42(4), 459-475.
               <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0261444809990048"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1017/S0261444809990048</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lantolf2014" label="Lantolf and Poehner 2014"> Lantolf, J. P., &amp; Poehner, M. E. (2014). <title rend="italic">Sociocultural theory and the pedagogical
               imperative in L2 education: Vygotskian praxis and the research/practice divide.</title> New York: Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lueck2020" label="Lueck and Panich 2020"> Lueck, J. A., &amp; Panich, L.M. (2020). <title rend="quotes">Representing indigenous histories using XR technologies in the classroom.</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of Interactive Technology &amp; Pedagogy</title>,
               17.
               <ref
                  target="https://jitp.commons.gc.cuny.edu/representing-indigenous-histories-using-xr-technologies-in-the-classroom/"
                  >https://jitp.commons.gc.cuny.edu/representing-indigenous-histories-using-xr-technologies-in-the-classroom/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="macedo2018" label="Macedo and Freire 2018"> Macedo, D., &amp; Freire, P. (2018). <title rend="italic">Pedagogy of the oppressed: 50th anniversary edition.</title> New York: Bloomsbury Academic.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="milk2015" label="Milk 2015"> Milk, C. (2015). <title rend="quotes">How virtual reality can create the ultimate empathy machine
               [Video].</title> TED Conferences. <ref
               target="https://www.ted.com/talks/chris_milk_how_virtual_reality_can_create_the_ultimate_empathy_machine?language=en"
               >https://www.ted.com/talks/chris_milk_how_virtual_reality_can_create_the_ultimate_empathy_machine?language=en</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mills2020" label="Mills et al. 2020"> Mills, N., Courtney, M., Dede, C., Dressen, A., &amp; Gant, R. (2020). <title rend="quotes">Culture and
               vision in virtual reality narratives.</title> <title rend="italic">Foreign Language Annals</title>, 53(4), 733-760.
               <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1111/flan.12494"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1111/flan.12494</ref></bibl>
             <bibl xml:id="nakamura2019" label="Nakamura 2019"> Nakamura, L. (2019). <title rend="italic">Lisa Nakamura's presentation at the
                  2019 Digital Democracies Conference</title> [Video]. YouTube. <ref
                  target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E10J7_YgWTI&amp;ab_channel=DigitalDemocraciesGroupSFU"
                  >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E10J7_YgWTI&amp;ab_channel=DigitalDemocraciesGroupSFU</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nakamura2020" label="Nakamura 2020"> Nakamura, L. (2020). <title rend="quotes">Feeling good about feeling bad: virtuous virtual reality and the
               automation of racial empathy.</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of Visual Culture</title>,
               19(1), 47-64.
               <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1470412920906259"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1177/1470412920906259</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="neville2020" label="Neville et al. 2020"> Neville, D., Priest, V., Purcell, S., Kelty-Stephen, D., Arner, T. D., Thomas, J., &amp;
               French, C. (2020). <title rend="quotes">Using virtual reality to expand teaching and research in the liberal arts.</title>
               
                  <title rend="italic">The Journal of Interactive Technology and Pedagogy</title>
               , 17. 
               <ref
                  target="https://jitp.commons.gc.cuny.edu/using-virtual-reality-to-expand-teaching-and-research-in-the-liberal-arts/"
                  >https://jitp.commons.gc.cuny.edu/using-virtual-reality-to-expand-teaching-and-research-in-the-liberal-arts/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nobelmedia2014a" label="Nobel Media AB 2014a"> Nobel Media AB. (2014). <title rend="italic">Prize Announcement. The Nobel Prize.</title>
               <ref target="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/2014/prize-announcement/%20"
                  >https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/2014/prize-announcement/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nobelmedia2014b" label="Nobel Media Ab 2014b"> Nobel Media AB. (2014). <title rend="italic">Patrick Modiano Nobel Lecture.</title> The Nobel Prize. 
               <ref target="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/2014/modiano/lecture/"
                  >https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/2014/modiano/lecture/</ref>
            </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ocallaghan2020" label="O’Callaghan and Harbin 2020"> O’Callaghan, T. F., &amp; Harbin, A. R. (2020). <title rend="quotes">Truly immersive worlds? The pedagogical implications of extended
               reality.</title> <title rend="italic">The Journal of
                  Interactive Technology and Pedagogy</title>, 17. <ref
                     target="https://jitp.commons.gc.cuny.edu/truly-immersive-worlds-the-pedagogical-implications-of-extended-reality/"
                     >https://jitp.commons.gc.cuny.edu/truly-immersive-worlds-the-pedagogical-implications-<lb/>
                     of-extended-reality/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="perec1975" label="Perec 1975"> Perec, G. (1975). <title rend="italic">W ou le souvenir d'enfance</title>. Paris: Denöel.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="perec2002" label="Perec 2002"> Perec, G. (2002). <title rend="italic">W, or the Memory of Childhood</title> trans. by David
               Bellos. Boston: David R. Godine, Publisher.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ratto2011a" label="Ratto 2011a"> Ratto, M. (2011). <title rend="quotes">Critical making: Conceptual and material studies in technology and
               social life.</title> <title rend="italic">The Information Society</title>, 27(4),
               252–260. 
               <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01972243.2011.583819"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/01972243.2011.583819</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ratto2011b" label="Ratto 2011b"> Ratto, M. (2011). <title rend="quotes">Critical Making.</title> In B. van Abel, &amp; R. Klaassen,. &amp; L. Evers,
               &amp; P. Troxler (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Open Design Now</title>. BIS publishers. 
               <ref target="http://opendesignnow.org/index.html%3Fp=434.html"
                  >http://opendesignnow.org/index.html%3Fp=434.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rose2014" label="Rose 2014"> Rose, M. (2014). <title rend="quotes">Making Publics: Documentary as Do-It-with-Others Citizenship.</title> In M.
               Ratto, &amp; M. Boler (Eds.), <title rend="italic">DIY Citizenship: Critical making and social media</title> (pp. 201 -
               212). The MIT Press. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="smith" label="Smith n.d."> Smith, P., Yuxweluptun, L. (n.d.). <title rend="italic">Unceded Territories</title>. Paisley Smith. 
               <ref target="https://www.paisleysmith.com/unceded-territories-vr"
                  >https://www.paisleysmith.com/unceded-territories-vr</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="testyler2010" label="Testyler and Testyler 2010"> Testyler, A., &amp; Testyler, C. (2010). <title rend="italic">Les enfants aussi!</title> Paris: Delattre. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="vossoughi2016" label="Vossoughi et al. 2016"> Vossoughi, S., Hooper, P.K., &amp; Escudé, M. (2016). <title rend="quotes">Making through the lens of culture
               and power: Toward transformative visions for educational equity.</title> <title rend="italic"
                  >Harvard Educational Review, 86</title>(2), 206–232. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.17763/0017-8055.86.2.206"
                  >https://doi.org/10.17763/0017-8055.86.2.206</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wertsch1985" label="Wertsch 1985"> Wertsch, J. V. (1985). <title rend="italic">Vygotsky and the social formation of mind.</title> Cambridge: Harvard University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wiggins2011" label="Wiggins and McTighe 2011"> Wiggins, G., &amp; McTighe, J. (2011). <title rend="italic">The Understanding by Design Guide to Creating
               High Quality Units.</title> Alexandria, VA: ASCD.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="yee2006" label="Yee 2006"> Yee, N., &amp; Bailenson, J.N. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Walk a mile in digital shoes: The
               impact of embodied perspective-taking on the reduction of negative stereotyping in
               immersive virtual environments.</title> <title rend="italic">Proceedings of PRESENCE 2006: The 9th Annual
               International Workshop on Presence</title>, Cleveland, OH. 
               <ref target="https://stanfordvr.com/pubs/2006/walk-a-mile-in-digital-shoes-the-impact-of-embodied-
                  perspective-taking-on-the-reduction-of-negative-stereotyping-in-immersive-virtual-
                  environments/">https://stanfordvr.com/pubs/2006/walk-a-mile-in-digital-shoes-the-impact-of-embodied-
               perspective-taking-on-the-reduction-of-negative-stereotyping-in-immersive-virtual-
               environments/</ref> </bibl>
            
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
