<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
	xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
	xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
				<title type="article" xml:lang="en">Gamer Trouble: A Review</title>
				<!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Himadri <dhq:family>Agarwal</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0009-0000-3328-1230
						<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>University of Maryland</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>hima@umd.edu</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Himadri Agarwal (she/her) is a PhD student in English at the University of Maryland, College Park. She dearly
							loves games — designing them, studying them, and above all, playing them. She is also fascinated by how
							technology and the arts are transformed by one another, and is working towards a certificate in Digital Studies
							in Arts and Humanities. Outside of work, Hima enjoys Bollywood movies, popular science, and bright colors.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
				<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
				<!--This information will be completed at publication-->
				<idno type="DHQarticle-id">000432</idno>
				<idno type="volume">018</idno>
				<idno type="issue">1</idno>
				<date when="2024-03-28">28 March 2024</date>
				<dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
				<availability status="CC-BY-ND">
					<!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
					<cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>This is the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
					<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en" extent="original"/>
				<!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
					<!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
					<!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
					<term corresp="#cultural_criticism"/>
					<term corresp="#games"/>
					<term corresp="#gender"/>
					<term corresp="#race"/>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
					<!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
					<list type="simple">
						<item>gaming</item>
						<item>video games</item>
						<item>gamer trouble</item>
						<item>feminism</item>
						<item>media studies</item>
						<item>new media</item>
						<item>review</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
			<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
					target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000432/000432.xml">GitHub
				</ref>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en" type="original">
		<front>
			<dhq:abstract>
				<!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
				<p>This review of Amanda Phillips’ book <title rend="italic">Gamer Trouble</title> traces the contents of the book,
					notes its resonances with larger scholarly discussions, and considers what it says about gaming and game culture
					overall. It also provides some perspectives on the book’s importance and appeal.</p>
			</dhq:abstract>
			<dhq:teaser>
				<!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
				<p>Reviewing Amanda Phillips' <title rend="italic">Gamer Trouble</title> (2020)</p>
			</dhq:teaser>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div>
				<head>Part I</head>
				<p>Gamers, Amanda Phillips says, have always been in trouble. One could not agree more. In their book, they push the
					boundaries of such trouble; questioning it rather than categorizing it, choosing to <q>run towards the trouble</q>
					rather than against it. <title rend="italic">Gamer Trouble</title> is an exploration of the discomfort, chaos, and
					confusion of video gaming culture, as well as an examination of how structural hierarchies inform, and are often
					reinforced by, the process of game design, creation, and play. The book uses queer and feminist theory, film
					studies, media studies, as well as race theory, to probe into gaming culture. While games have been discussed using
					these concepts before, Phillips’ book is characterized by an important element — chaos. Unlike most other
					scholarship, which tries to taxonomize game theory into neat categories, Phillips not only accepts but encourages
					the chaos inherent in the form; accepting the mutability of gaming rather than attempting to pin it down, leads to
					a nuanced, fertile analysis that does not build boundaries for itself.</p>
				<p>It is oft-discussed that video games perpetuate several forms of discrimination and violence, but rather than
					dismissing games altogether, Phillips chooses to get into the thick of things. Phillips emphasizes the dichotomy
					between the necessity of the simple pleasure of gaming and the frustration that accompanies the recognition of how
					games are contributing to social inequality — in that context, Phillips engages with sexism, homophobia, and racism
					in video gaming, while also being a gamer and a video game fan themself. That is crucial — their double-pronged
					approach of being both an academic and a fan means that they can critique effectively while also being aware of
					more quotidian perspectives, giving the work an edge over several others in the field. Phillips also analyses the
					discipline of game studies as a whole — while occupying a position within the field, they critique the exclusionary
					aspects not just of video games themselves but also the ways of discussing them. Phillips’ concept of
						<term>trouble</term> is also an invocation of the genealogies of conversations about feminism and
					intersectionality, which meet, diverge, and cross each other, creating another chaotic landscape that is used as a
					lens to view game production and content. In addition, trouble also refers to the simultaneous materiality and
					subjectivity of video games — which are hardware, software, story, interactivity, and more. Phillips’
						<term>trouble</term> has several meanings, and the book covers all these implications in some detail.</p>
				<p>
					<title rend="italic">Gamer Trouble</title> goes beyond just the console to think about how video games come to be,
					how they are played, and how they are talked about. The book is both specific and comprehensive — along with some
					detailed close reading of games, the book covers several important aspects of the video game scene. While the
					second chapter goes into the technological aspects of gaming, specifically character creation and the biases
					involved, the third and fourth chapters cover representation in a few case study games: <title rend="italic"
						>Portal</title>, <title rend="italic">Bayonetta,</title> and the <title rend="italic">Mass Effect</title>
					trilogy. The first chapter, meanwhile, discusses discourses about gaming, including sexist campaigns like
					#GamerGate and responses to them.</p>
				<p>The first chapter thinks about the histories of video gaming to come to the crucial conclusion that #GamerGate was
					ordinary rather than extraordinary. It critiques discourses in video game communities, arguing that their
					vitriolic, sexist nature is not new. Phillips frames this using <title rend="italic">Dickwolves</title>, a 2010
					controversy where gamers retaliated to a rape joke featured in a popular comic <title rend="italic">Penny
						Arcade</title>. They discuss the figures of the <q>mean mommy,</q>
					<q>angry feminist,</q>
					<q>based mom,</q> and <q>killjoy,</q> derogatory terms given to feminist gamers, most often people of minoritized
					genders and of colour, for daring to disrupt sexist status quos with their critique. In gaming spaces, such
					critique has often been and continues to be, misrepresented, laughed at, and eventually dismissed due to
					(falsified) reasons of a lack of gaming aptitude. Their statement of the ordinariness of #GamerGate can be mistaken
					as Phillips trivialising it; however, their assertion is not that it was insignificant, but that such practices
					have been occurring for a long time. With the <title rend="italic">Dickwolves</title> example, they demonstrate
					that the issue does not start with #GamerGate, but has origins much farther behind than that, compelling readers to
					look differently at gaming history. It is also important here to take non-academic discourses very seriously —
					through their methodologies, Phillips recognises that video games are not made for studying; they are primarily for
					playing, so conversations had on platforms like forums, social media threads, and stream comments are
					indispensable. Crucially, Phillips’ argument is not limited to gamer discourse itself — they also point to academic
					conversations about games, or the field of game studies itself. Here, they trace how it has, until recently, been
					male-dominated, and analyses the academic writing (or lack thereof) around <title rend="italic">Grand Theft
						Auto</title> to demonstrate how the field has been selective in its scholarship and, as a result, prohibitive for
					marginalized communities.</p>
				<p>In the second chapter, Phillips considers how games are created — examining animation and development processes,
					and how technology reflects sociocultural biases about race and gender. Phillips invokes <term>quantization</term>,
					or the <quote rend="inline">chunking up of a thing like the human face into discrete numbers, in order to explore
						the ways that the numerical fictions about bodies overwrite the complexities of actual identity</quote>
					<ptr target="#phillips2020" loc="22–23"/>. The chapter begins with an exploration of <title rend="italic"
						>Kara,</title> a short film by Quantic Dreams created to demonstrate the animation potential of the company’s new
					game engine. Here, Phillips discusses how that was done through motion capture technology that brought together
					multiple actors of various racial identities, whose differences were erased in favour of homogenous whiteness while
					also reaffirming a unidimensional concept of diversity through Kara’s ability to, say, perform a Japanese lullaby
					with native fluency. Situating such analyses in the racial science of physiognomy, which attempts to read
					personality traits into face features, Phillips goes on to analyse avatar creation, using <title rend="italic"
						>Fallout 3</title> as a case study. As methodologies to understand the workings of the black boxes behind
					interfaces, they consider both deformance, or manipulating interfaces to the extreme to unravel how they work, and
					modding, playing around existing code to explore how much, and in what ways, the game can be remoulded. Phillips
					invokes Gloria Anzaldúa’s <quote rend="inline" xml:lang="es">hacienda caras,</quote> and claims that gamers’
					interactions with avatar creation interfaces are models of navigating oppressive structures through masks (the
					avatar itself) <ptr target="#anzaldua1990"/>; limitations on avatar creation possibilities, therefore, represent a
						<quote rend="inline">wrinkle in the power envelope</quote>
					<ptr target="#phillips2020" loc="23"/> that differentially affects minoritized gamers. Here, Phillips’ technical
					know-how comes into good use: using effective technological methodologies combined with literary theory to generate
					innovative analyses.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Part II</head>
				<p>From analysing the impacts of avatar creation possibilities, Phillips moves on to representations of the
					characters themselves. Here, they use Laura Mulvey’s concept of the <term>male gaze,</term> popularized by film and
					media studies, to look at video game characters, specifically from <title rend="italic">Portal</title> and <title
						rend="italic">Bayonetta</title>. They consider how gaze operates differently in video games, considering the
					presence of user-controlled cameras and of multiple objects which compete for attention. For <title rend="italic"
						>Portal</title>, they analyze GLaDOS, the disembodied female antagonist of the game, juxtaposed with Chell, the
					female avatar players inhabit. Chell is upheld in feminist gamer circles for being brown and wearing a
					full-coverage jumpsuit — which Phillips complicates in discussing her ambiguous brownness, arguing that Chell’s
					character caters to concerns about representation using a least-risk model, intending to maximise market value at
					the expense of specificity. Meanwhile, the sexy titular character of <title rend="italic">Bayonetta,</title> who,
					with her unrealistic proportions and improbable body contortions, was very controversial, is more than an appeal to
					the male gaze — Phillips moves beyond authorial intent to read Bayonetta’s mixed-race heritage, interactions with
					other female characters, as well as movements, to argue that the character defies heteronormativity and challenges
					accepted narratives of gender. Ultimately, the third chapter argues for an updated lens of considering questions of
					race and gender in video gaming, making the case that gendered power dynamics are <quote rend="inline">more
						troubled than they might seem</quote>
					<ptr target="#phillips2020" loc="136"/>.</p>
				<p>The last chapter looks at FemShep, the female version of <title rend="italic">Mass Effect’s</title> customisable
					hero, Commander Shepard. The chapter begins with the question of whether Femshep exists, and ends with the
					assertion that FemShep should not exist. FemShep is known for her sexual interactions with characters of various
					genders, thus being heralded as a depiction of queerness in gaming; however, Phillips studies game animations to
					show that FemShep’s animations, even in sexual contexts, are not very different from BroShep (the male Commander
					Shepard); more than being a queer woman, FemShep runs on the code and motion of a man, simply with the appearances
					of a woman. Phillips also considers how FemShep was not a part of the initial promotions of <title rend="italic"
						>Mass Effect</title>, such decisions later reversed only in favour of a white, redheaded, stereotypically
					attractive FemShep being shown in such promotions. Using Audre Lorde’s concept of <quote rend="inline">house of
						difference,</quote> as well as Kara Keeling’s <quote rend="inline">I=Another,</quote> Phillips moves beyond
					neoliberal notions of diversity and advocates, instead, for difference <ptr target="#lorde1982"/>
					<ptr target="#keeling2011"/>.</p>
				<p>Like the word <q>trouble</q> in its title, <title rend="italic">Gamer Trouble</title> is a book that defies
					categories — it derives its meaning from its muchness, from its difficulty to pin down or confine. It is here,
					there, everywhere, in the best way possible. It looks at video games through feminist history, queer theory, and
					race-related scholarship, asking important questions and creating a landscape that is generative more than
					destructive. The book does not draw rigid boundaries, and neither does Phillips, who is a gamer, researcher,
					writer, and video game fan, all of which are brought to the writing, making it vibrant, dynamic, and colourful.
					Though it is a tad technical, <title rend="italic">Gamer Trouble</title> is fairly accessible too, readable by most
					audiences. The conversations Phillips creates are chaotic; they engage you more than placate you, surprise you more
					than satisfy you, and challenge you more than gratify you. <title rend="italic">Gamer Trouble</title> does not give
					you answers to your questions — it makes you search for them yourself, and embark on a wonderful journey.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<listBibl>
				<bibl xml:id="phillips2020" label="Phillips 2020">Phillips, A. (2020) <title rend="italic">Gamer Trouble: Feminist
						Confrontations in Digital Culture</title>. New York: NYU Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="anzaldua1990" label="Anzaldúa 1990">Anzaldúa, Gloria, ed. (1990) <title rend="italic">Making Face,
						Making Soul / Haciendo Caras: Creative and Critical Perspectives by Women of Color</title>. San Francisco: Aunt
					Lute Foundation.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="keeling2011" label="Keeling 2011">Keeling, Kara. (2011) <title rend="quotes">I = Another: Digital
						Identity Politics</title> in <title rend="italic">Strange Affinities: The Gender and Sexual Politics of
						Comparative Racialization</title>, Grace Kyungwon (ed.) Durham, NC: Duke University Press, pp. 53–75.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="lorde1982" label="Lorde 1982">Lorde, Audre. (1982) <title rend="italic">Zami: A New Spelling of My Name
						— a Biomythography</title>. Trumansburg, NY: Crossing Press.</bibl>
			</listBibl>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
