<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article">From Optical Fiber To Conceptual Cyberinfrastructure</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Patrik <dhq:family>Svensson</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>HUMlab, Umeå University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>patrik.svensson@humlab.umu.se</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p> Patrik Svensson the director of HUMlab at Umeå University and a docent in the
              humanities and information technology. His research concerns digital humanities as a
              field, learning and information technology, cyberinfrastructure for the humanities and
              new media studies.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher><publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000090</idno>
            <idno type="volume">005</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <date when="2011-03-10">10 March 2011</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
          <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
          <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Amy Atticks" when="2011-02-22">entered author changes</change>
         <change who="Amy Atticks" when="2010-10-26">entered bibliographic information</change>
         <change who="Alyssa" when="2010-11-16">checked bibl, began encoding</change>
         <change when="2013-06-20" who="Tassie Gniady">Changed "dhq:caption" to "head."</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>There is currently an infrastructure turn with very real implications for the humanities
          and digital humanities. It comes not only with presumed technology or infrastructure, but
          also with certain assumptions, discursive patterns, and models. This paper analyzes these
          critically and advocates a humanities-based notion of cyberinfrastructure, not necessarily
          built on a science-and-engineering paradigm or exclusively grounded in existing humanities
          infrastructure. It is argued that we need to maintain a critical stance while
          simultaneously engaging in the exploration of research issues and technologies. There is
          often a gap between the material details of infrastructure and underlying, foundational
          ideas, and it is suggested that a model based on conceptual cyberinfrastructure and design
          parameters can be one way of connecting the ideational level with actual implementation.
          HUMlab at Umeå University serves as a case study.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Why the humanities should care about research infrastructure and how humanities
          cyberinfrastructure can be analyzed and built.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>From Optical Fiber To Conceptual Cyberinfrastructure</head>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Whether or not <term>digital humanities</term> is a field can be disputed, but there can be no
          doubt that there is currently a great deal of activity, engagement, investment and
          expressed hope in the intersection of the humanities and the digital. This is the third
          article in a four-part series attempting to explore this very intersection, and it
          examines infrastructure for the humanities in relation to the current discourse of
          research infrastructure (or cyberinfrastructure) and the digital humanities.</p>
            <p>In this article, I argue that the humanities need to consider the multiple opportunities
          associated with cyberinfrastructure, while maintaining epistemic integrity and avoiding
          modeling new infrastructure uncritically after existing models. For example, what is
          humanities cyberinfrastructure? How can we critically engage with the discourse and ideas
          of cyberinfrastructure? What are the infrastructural needs of the humanities? How can new
          infrastructure and digital humanities spaces be designed and implemented? The humanities
          are arguably in a position to co-create and co-construct their own notion of
          cyberinfrastructure, as well as implementing it, even if the discourse and its associated
          implementations do not necessarily conform fully to a science and engineering based model
          or previous layers of scholarly infrastructure. HUMlab, a digital humanities center at
          Umeå University, serves as a case study leading to a more general discussion of design
          principles and conceptual cyberinfrastructure for the humanities. Further, tentative
          advice as to implementing and strategizing humanities cyberinfrastructure is offered.</p>
            <p>The article series, as a whole, traces digital humanities as a project in terms of
          history, epistemic commitments, modes of engagement with the digital, conceptual
          foundations for associated cyberinfrastructure, visions and hope invested, and future
          directions for the field, and necessarily, for the humanities at large.</p>
            <p>In the first article, I examined the discursive transition from humanities computing to
          digital humanities, exploring how this naming is related to shifts in institutional,
          disciplinary, and social organization. I also addressed the epistemic culture and
          commitments of humanities computing, and tensions between this tradition and a broad
          notion of digital humanities.</p>
            <p>In the second article, I explored the broader landscape of the digital humanities through
          a discussion of digital humanities and digital humanists, associated traditions, personal
          encounters and importantly, through a suggested set of paradigmatic modes of engagement
          between the humanities and information technology: information technology as a tool, an
          object of study, an exploratory laboratory, an expressive medium, and as an activist
          venue.</p>
            <p>In the fourth article, I explore the multiple ways in which the digital humanities have
          been envisioned and how the digital humanities can often become a laboratory and vehicle
          for thinking about the state and future of the humanities at large. Some foundational
          issues, including the role of the humanities and changing knowledge production systems,
          are discussed and related to the development of the digital humanities. Furthermore, a
          tentative vision of the digital humanities is presented. This vision is grounded in the
          article series as a whole as well as in the important collaborative possibilities and
          challenges that lie ahead of us.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Outline</head>
            <p>The current article is divided into three parts. The first part discusses the notion and
          discourse of research infrastructure critically, and relates this to the humanities and
          humanities infrastructure. There is a significant gap between the grand visions of the
          discourse of cyberinfrastructure and the actual, implemented infrastructure. It is argued
          that it is essential that the humanities embrace current opportunities and explore
          multiple visions when considering cyberinfrastructure for the humanities, while avoiding
          the dangers of being uncritically modeled after existing humanities infrastructures or
          after technology and science based models. The second part investigates a particular
          example of digital humanities infrastructure in considerable detail. An attempt at
          bridging the gap mentioned above is made through introducing a three-layered model which
          incorporates conceptual cyberinfrastructure (underlying ideas and epistemic grounding),
          design principles (intermediate level articulation of conceptual cyberinfrastructure) and
          actual cyberinfrastructure (implemented infrastructure). Special emphasis is given to
          space, infrastructure and how ideational grounding and physical (as well as digital)
          implementation are negotiated. Finally, the third part of this article reflects on
          packaging, strategizing and implementing cyberinfrastructure for the humanities. This
          discussion draws on the previous parts, as well as experience from building a lab and
          engaging with the digital humanities community.</p>
            <p>It is argued that this expansive approach can help provide a comprehensive picture of
          research infrastructure from visionary discourse to actual implementation, and support a
          sophisticated argument for humanities cyberinfrastructure. However, any analysis of such a
          complex matter as research infrastructure is necessarily partial, and while much of the
          study is fairly general, the case study has provided an important point of canalization.
          This also means that the idea of a physical, digitally inflected laboratory has influenced
          the work, and that some other aspects, including standardization and digital libraries,
          are given limited attention.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Part I: Cyberinfrastructure for the Humanities</head>
            <div>
               <head>Introduction</head>
               <p>Research infrastructure, while traditionally not associated with the humanities, has
            become a topic of conversation on faculty boards and among researchers in the
            humanities. Moreover, there is substantial interest from funding agencies, councils and
            various organizations under rubrics such as cyberinfrastructure and e-science. At this
            point in time, there is a grapple for securing funding, defining key questions and
            aligning the humanities with an epistemic framework bearing a strong science and
            engineering legacy. There is no doubt there are many opportunities, particularly for a
            field such as the digital humanities, but also real risks and important considerations.
            What requires attention is not least the assumed epistemic and ontological neutrality of
            the ‘infrastructure move’ and, correspondingly, its assumed broad applicability for
            everything from geology to cultural studies. In this section, we will consider risks
            associated with modeling humanities cyberinfrastructure on existing infrastructure, or
            on a technology and science driven paradigm. The stakes are high, and the
            cyberinfrastructure movement as a whole – and its articulation as an important strategy
            in the humanities – can be seen as an epistemic power play. It is a power play with very
            real implications for the humanities and the digital humanities.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Research Infrastructure</head>
               <p>In the <title rend="italic">European Roadmap for Research Infrastructures Report
              2006</title>, research infrastructures are defined as follows: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#europeanroadmap2006">In the roadmap, we deal with facilities, resources or services of a
                unique nature that have been identified by pan-European research communities to
                conduct top-level activities in all fields. This definition of Research
                Infrastructures, including the associated human resources, covers major equipment or
                sets of instruments, as well as knowledge‑containing resources such as collections,
                archives and databases. Research Infrastructures may be <term>single-sited,</term>
                        <term>distributed,</term> or <term>virtual</term> (the service being provided electronically).
                They often require structured information systems related to data management,
                enabling information and communication. These include technology-based
                infrastructures such as grid, computing, software and middleware.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#europeanroadmap2006" loc="16"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>This definition is fairly typical, and the full report is typical in the sense of
            providing enumerations of different types of technologies and research infrastructures.
            There is no simple way of defining <term>research infrastructure(s)</term> or
              <term>cyberinfrastructure</term> as the terms are part of a social, institutional and
            political context. Indeed, if we look at the term <term>infrastructure</term> itself, it
            broadly refers to <quote rend="inline" source="#merriam2010">the resources (as personnel, buildings, or
              equipment) required for an activity</quote> as well as <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#merriam2010">the
                underlying foundation or basic framework (of a system or organization)</quote>
                     <ptr target="#merriam2010"/>
                  </cit>. <ptr target="#edwards2009" loc="365"/> state that
            the term often <quote rend="inline" source="#edwards2009">connotes big, durable, well-functioning systems and
              services, from railroads and highways to telephone, electric power, and the
              Internet.</quote>
               </p>
               <p>In practice, the notion of research infrastructure carries with it a number of
            assumptions that are partly linked to funding structures and the idea of infrastructure
            as a resource of national or international interest. Research infrastructure is
            typically taken to be advanced, costly, require national or pan-national funding, be
            associated with leading research and researchers, be part of a system, have use beyond
            single research groups or disciplines, have longevity, and add significant new research
            possibilities.</p>
               <p>In general, much discussion of cyberinfrastructure is technology-driven, data-driven
            and structural-level. This is partly a result of the selling of a new generation of
            research infrastructure (cf. <ptr target="#borgman2007"/>), and partly a result of the
            emphasis on the traditional infrastructural needs of science and technology. Just like
            with <term>digital humanities</term>, the relatively high level of abstraction of a term
            such as <term>cyberinfrastructure</term> allows for descriptions not grounded in
            specific disciplines as much as in a set of high-level epistemic and technological
            commitments:</p>
               <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#nsf2010">OCI supports cyberinfrastructure resources, tools and related
              services such as supercomputers, high-capacity mass-storage systems, system software
              suites and programming environments, scalable interactive visualization tools,
              productivity software libraries and tools, large-scale data repositories and digitized
              secientific data management systems, networks of various reach and granularity and an
              array of software tools and services that hide the complexities and heterogeneity of
              contemporary cyberinfrastructure while seeking to provide ubiquitous access and
              enhanced usability.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#nsf2010"/>
               </cit>
               <p>As Borgman observes, cyberinfrastructure is often defined through example, typically
            emphasizing the <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#borgman2007">integrative, collaborative, and distributed
                nature of new forms of research</quote>
                     <ptr target="#borgman2007" loc="22–23"/>
                  </cit>. In addition, there is frequently an
            assumption of very large and complex data sets. While we do not necessarily need to
            question these assertions, it is important to note that we are concerned with a
            particular type of discourse and epistemic framework. This implies that a possible
            humanities alignment with cyberinfrastructure in this sense is, in fact, also an
            alignment with this discourse and with associated assumptions. For instance,
            distributedness in the sense of optiputers or grid computing is far more likely to be
            seen as cyberinfrastructure than multi-modal communication, data exchange and analysis
            through small-scale qualitative data bases, twitter and on-screen virtual worlds.
            Another assumption is that cyberinfrastructure is quite costly. This is not to say that
            humanities based cyberinfrastructure may not be quite costly, but rather to suggest that
            the structure, epistemics and cost structure of humanities based cyberinfrastructure may
            be different than that of science and engineering based infrastructure. These
            assumptions are real in the sense that they influence the way humanities research
            infrastructure is being imagined and built.</p>
               <p>Research infrastructure seems to easily acquire a status and life beyond <emph>only</emph>
            supporting or facilitating research. Importantly, research infrastructure is not
            research (cf. <ptr target="#rockwell2010a"/>), and it seems appropriate that research
            needs and challenges shape the establishment of new infrastructure. In the case of the
            humanities, we are thus primarily concerned with research challenges and infrastructural
            needs identified by the humanities, and in particular, humanities researchers. A few
            possible examples include: embodiment in digital environments, transformation of urban
            spaces through media technology, tracing narrative structures in computer games, the use
            of map based visualization to find patterns in large sets of archival information, text
            mining technologies for literary and linguistic analysis, and understanding reading
            comprehension with the help of eye tracking equipment.</p>
               <p>However, the nature of infrastructure and funding mechanisms make the process more
            complicated than matching one identified research challenge with an appropriate piece of
            infrastructure. In practice, infrastructure often has to be relatively abstractly framed
            and typically serve more than one specific need in order to qualify as infrastructure.
            Technologies such as visualization and grid computing fulfill this requirement, and they
            often come across as <term>black boxes</term> rather than sites of situated research
            facilitation. Furthermore, funding is much more likely if the infrastructure is
            associated with ‘new’ research and major projected advances. There is also a push for
            interdisciplinary research endeavors. This means that there is a visionary,
            cross-sectional and experimental component to many infrastructural projects.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Research Infrastructure for the Humanities</head>
               <p>The discourse and practice of research infrastructure are strongly situated in science
            and engineering, and typically concerns technology and systems that require national or
            pan-national funding. Examples include high performance computing, grid computing, and
            facilities for synchrotron radiation and biomedical imaging. Also in cases when national
            funding sources in principle are open to all areas of research (including the
            humanities), there is a strong tendency to mainly fund science, engineering and medical
            research. For instance, the Swedish Research Council gave out 40 infrastructural grants
            in 2009 for equipment, running costs for infrastructure and large databases, and none of
            these grants had an obvious humanities focus or humanities based principal investigator,
            although one or two grants were given to quantitative social science projects. Clearly,
            the humanities have not been seen as a significant player in this kind of funding
            schemes apart from in certain areas (e.g. computational linguistics, environmental
            archaeology and digital libraries), which also means that the specifics of humanities
            infrastructures are rarely elaborated on, and there is relatively little discussion of
            what humanities infrastructure in this sense could actually be.</p>
               <p>As was noted above, there is an acknowledgement and push for the importance of better
            and more research infrastructure for the humanities — not least in the digital
            humanities. This process is strongly linked to a realization that material, tools and
            culture are becoming increasingly digitalized, and that academic work is increasingly
            being carried out in a distributed and digitally supported fashion. The background is
            also a relatively recent move towards a <emph>new</emph> generation of research infrastructure
            often called cyberinfrastructure (in the US), e-science (in Europe and Australia) or
            simply research infrastructure (e.g. Canada), which draws on computational resources,
            distributed work and a more inclusive notion of infrastructure. <ptr target="#rockwell2010a"/> describes this movement as an <quote rend="inline" source="#rockwell2010a">infrastructure turn,</quote> while funding agency reports and other sources often
            describe it as a revolution (e.g. <ptr target="#green2007"/>). At least in terms of how
            it is presented, infrastructure in this sense is more likely to include human resources
            and other non-technical aspects than earlier generations of infrastructure.
            Nevertheless, the whole movement is essentially a science and engineering driven
            enterprise: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#atkins2003">The Panel’s overarching finding is that a new age
                has dawned in scientific and engineering research, pushed by continuing progress in
                computing, information, and communication technology; and pulled by the expanding
                complexity, scope, and scale of today’s research challenges.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#atkins2003" loc="31"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>The use of <term>new</term> in this influential National Science Foundation Blue Ribbon
            Report is not accidental; the discourse of cyberinfrastructure is one of <term>new,</term>
                  <term>emerging</term> and <term>expanding.</term>
                  <ptr target="#borgman2007" loc="30"/> states that there are 133 instances of <term>new</term>
            in this report, and most other similar documents show the same trait. The ACLS Report on
            Cyberinfrastructure for the Humanities and Social Sciences <ptr target="#unsworth2006"/>
            reportedly uses 89 instances of <term>new</term> in 64 pages. These figures suggest that
              <soCalled>newness</soCalled> may be a useful prerequisite for (funded) cyberinfrastructure.</p>
               <p>The National Science Foundation Report only mentions the humanities explicitly once (in
            relation to digital libraries), but nevertheless there is clearly an interest in
            engaging with the humanities and social sciences despite the NSF’s focus on science and
            engineering. Similarly, in many accounts of cyberinfrastructure there will be a note
            about the impact on these <emph>non-primary</emph> areas. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#hey2008">Although
                our focus is on e-Science, other research fields such as the social sciences, arts,
                and humanities will also require and benefit from this emerging cyberinfrastructure. </quote>
                     <ptr target="#hey2008" loc="15"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>It may be argued that statements like these are somewhat external to the humanities in
            that they often make outside assumptions about the needs, requirements and priorities of
            the field. In order for the humanities to control our own cyberinfrastructure, we need
            to express humanities-driven needs and engage in constructive dialogue about our current
            and future infrastructure.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Risks and Strategies</head>
               <p>There are risks, however, that need to be addressed in this dialogue. First, existing
            humanities infrastructure may be disregarded as we do not have a tradition of
            science-like infrastructure. Second, the science-based and data-driven model may be
            imposed on the Humanities (sometimes by humanists themselves) without careful discussion
            of the premises and consequences. Third, there is a risk that infrastructural needs or
            agendas compatible with the largely science based model will be the ones most likely to
            be prioritized. Fourth, new humanities infrastructure may be uncritically based on
            existing infrastructure and associated epistemic commitments.</p>
               <p>The position taken in this article is that the current investments and interest in
            cyberinfrastructure and e-science for the humanities present an opportunity to think
            carefully about what the humanities need and may not need in terms of infrastructure
            (broadly interpreted). This cannot be done, however, if we cannot maintain a critical
            stance and advocate a truly humanities based approach to academic infrastructure. At the
            same time, we need to acknowledge that we do not necessarily know what kind of
            infrastructure we need and will need, and that it is important to simultaneously engage
            in the exploration of humanities based research issues and challenges, and in the
            exploration of technology and different kinds of infrastructure (including
            infrastructure that is part of science and engineering cyberinfrastructure).
            Consequently, we must allow for both technology and humanities induced visions and
            implementations in different kinds of combinations.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, we have to be aware of the fact that any investment in cyberinfrastructure
            is likely to be a prioritization and that certain parts of the humanities are more
            likely than others to be good candidates for such investments. It is important, however,
            that this prioritization is not a direct consequence or transfer of a predominantly
            science and engineering model of cyberinfrastructure and that it is not uncritically
            based on existing infrastructural traditions. Importantly, cyberinfrastructure is not
            neutral. In the following, we will look at three models for humanities research
            infrastructure, which exemplify the non-neutrality of cyberinfrastructure: existing
            infrastructure as a model, the humanities having no or little infrastructure, and a
            technology and science driven model.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Existing infrastructure as a model</head>
               <p>The humanities have made use of research infrastructure in scholarly practice from
            early on, and for instance, libraries and archives are often pointed out as essential
            infrastructure to the humanities. Indeed, some writers claim that the humanities
            themselves make up vital infrastructure (e.g. <ptr target="#src2007"/>, 2009-2012), or
            cultural infrastructure can function as trading zones between technological, artistic,
            and humanities practitioners (see <ptr target="#turner2009"/> on Burning Man as a
            cultural infrastructure). A related model is that of network forums as emergent
            structures that blend cultural and infrastructural networks (see <ptr target="#turner2005"/> on the WELL).</p>
               <p>One descriptive model states that there is considerable humanities research
            infrastructure already in place and that this infrastructure is a very good candidate
            for becoming cyberinfrastructure or being digitalized: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#unsworth2006">The
                infrastructure of scholarship was built over centuries. It includes diverse
                collections of primary sources in libraries, archives, and museums; the
                bibliographies, searching aids, citation systems, and concordances that make that
                information retrievable; the standards that are embodied in cataloging and
                classification systems; the journals and university presses that distribute the
                information; and the editors, librarians, archivists, and curators who link the
                operation of this structure to the scholars who use it. All of these elements have
                extensions or analogues in cyberinfrastructure, at least in the cyberinfrastructure
                that is required for humanities and social sciences.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#unsworth2006" loc="6"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>While this is probably a valid description of existing infrastructure (but cf. <ptr target="#rockwell2010a"/>), it largely leaves out infrastructures outside of
            libraries, archives, museums and publication systems. It could be argued that we are
            concerned here with a library and collection based model – admittedly well in line with
            a large part of the humanities. It is important to realize, however, that there is a set
            of epistemic commitments associated with this model – pertaining to structure, delivery,
            material types, retrieval systems, selection procedures, relation between researchers
            and library institution and other issues basic to the humanities – and that any major
            new investment in cyberinfrastructure should not uncritically be based on such, existing
            structures and descriptions. For instance, it would seem that the model presented above
            makes a fairly strong delineation between the collections (institutions, distribution
            systems, professional functions involved, etc.) and the researchers and the research
            community. Drucker addresses such delineations critically: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#drucker2009">The
                design of new environments for performing scholarly work cannot be left to the
                technical staff and to library professionals. The library is a crucial partner in
                planning and envisioning the future of preserving, using, even creating scholarly
                resources. So are the technology professionals. But in an analogy with building
                construction, they are the architect and contractor. The creation of archives,
                analytic tools, statistical analyses of aggregate data in humanities and social
                sciences is work only possible with the combined expertise of technical,
                professional, and scholarly personnel. [...] Modelling scholarship is an
                intellectual challenge, not a technical one. I cannot say this strongly or clearly
                enough.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#drucker2009"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>In contrast to much of the discourse of cyberinfrastructure and digital humanities,
            Drucker focuses on the scholarly challenge and not on the technology or
            technology-induced visions. However, the terms on which this analogy is constructed
            reinforces specific roles, and the term <term>contractors</term> may be seen to mark an
            implicit class distinction and clear institutional positions. A related question is
            whether new institutional roles will develop, and whether these will blur the roles
            described by Drucker and the ACLS report. Along these lines, Blackwell and Crane call
            for institutional change: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#blackwell2009">[…] [W]e need new institutions to
                provide access to the results of our work. Neither the libraries nor the publishers
                of the early twenty-first century serve the needs that emerge in this collection.
                While libraries may survive and indeed flourish as an institution, they will do so
                by subsuming and transforming the functions that we entrusted to publishers in print
                culture.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#blackwell2009"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>The library as a model is hence not static, and as Blackwell and Crane’s example
            illustrates, we need to be careful about not uncritically modeling tomorrow’s research
            infrastructure on past or current infrastructure.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>The Humanities Have no or Little Infrastructure</head>
               <p>There is a sense that traditional humanities have very little need of research
            infrastructure and, at the same time, a partial realization that that the needs may be
            changing. This is an argument sometimes put forward by the digital humanities community:
                <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#bentkowska2007">Despite a slow and uneven uptake of digital technology in
                some areas of the Arts and Humanities research, the discipline is no longer based on
                pen and paper. Specific individual needs of research that relies on the use of
                advanced technologies must be better understood and matched by a level of support
                that is already enjoyed by the scientists.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#bentkowska2007"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>This kind of reasoning to some extent reinforces the sense of <soCalled>basic</soCalled> humanities
            being mainly reliant on technologies such as pen and paper, and it is by no means a new
            argument (see e.g. <ptr target="#roper1991" loc="131"/>). More broadly, however, the
            view of basic humanities as without, or little, significant infrastructure not only
            assumes a science and technology based idea of what makes up infrastructure, but also
            imposes a <soCalled>pen and paper</soCalled> construction of the humanities. Pen and paper, while
            inherently communicative and collaborative, are also linked to the assumption that
            humanities scholarship to a large extent is a solitary endeavor (the individual scholar
            in his or her study): <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#burnette1994">Humanities scholars often work alone
                without collaborators or assistants. In contrast to the cooperative efforts common
                in the sciences and social sciences, humanities scholarship is the result of
                solitary research and thought.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#burnette1994" loc="182"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Obviously most humanities research is not at all solitary (cf. <ptr target="#grafton2009" loc="2–5"/>), even though authorship is often attributed to one
            person. Moreover, there can be no doubt that there is research infrastructure in the
            humanities and that it has a long history. One possible consequence of construing the
            humanities as not having much infrastructure and being a solitary enterprise is a higher
            readiness to adopt science and engineering models of cyberinfrastructure (as if there is
              <soCalled>nothing</soCalled> there to start with).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>A Technology- and Science-driven Model</head>
               <p>When a science and engineering framework is taken to the humanities and social
            sciences, there will often be attempts at aligning specific toolsets and technologies
            with the subject areas in question and here, the starting point will often be the
            technology. A fairly recent example is grid computing (see e.g. <ptr target="#bonnett2008"/>). Questions asked may be: What can grid computing do for the
            humanities? What large humanities data sets are particularly suitable for grid computing
            applications? The gap between high performance computing perspectives on grid computing
            and humanities based research issues and questions can be very large, and in
            facilitating meetings between the two, it is critical to create a common discursive
            space and allow time for dialogue. A good example of deep thinking about this process is
            provided by the report <title rend="quotes">Mind the Gap</title>
                  <ptr target="#rockwell2010b"/>, in which it is argued that currently, the main gap
            between High Performance Computing and research in the humanities relates to research
            culture and support. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#rockwell2010b">On the one hand we have to find ways of
                training and preparing humanities research teams to be able to imagine using
                existing HPC facilties, and on the other we have to develop the ability of HPC
                consortia to be able to reach out and support.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#rockwell2010b"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>One recommendation in the report concerns the necessity of humanists being involved
            early in the process (also in management and decisions). There is a balance between
            discipline and technology driven issues and questions, and finding this common ground is
            not trivial. Importantly, we also need to acknowledge that <soCalled>technological
              competence</soCalled> can be very diverse, research intensive and complex. Indeed, since the
            discourse of cyberinfrastructure has a tendency to take place at an aggregate level in
            relation to complex and internally diverse entities such as the humanities or science
            and engineering, it would seem that real, grounded encounters can be particularly
            valuable.</p>
               <p>On a more abstract level there is a concern with aligning cyberinfrastructure as a
            project with the humanities and social sciences: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#unsworth2006">Humanities
                scholars and social scientists will require similar facilities but, obviously, not
                exactly the same ones: “grids of computational centers” are needed in the humanities
                and social sciences, but they will have to be staffed with different kinds of
                subject-area experts; comprehensive and well-curated libraries of digital objects
                will certainly be needed, but the objects themselves will be different from those
                used in the sciences; software toolkits for projects involving data-mining and
                data-visualization could be shared across the sciences, humanities, and social
                sciences, but only up to the point where the nature of the data begins to shape the
                nature of the tools. Science and engineering have made great strides in using
                information technology to understand and shape the world around us. This report is
                focused on how these same technologies could help advance the study and
                interpretation of the vastly more messy and idiosyncratic realm of human
                experience.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#unsworth2006"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>There is, again, a risk here of adopting a science and engineering based model for
            humanities infrastructure in such a way that it significantly constrains and shapes
            possible research enterprises and directions. The question is also whether it is at all
            possible to discern a point like the one referred to in <q>only up to
              the point where the nature of the data begins to shape the nature of the
            tools</q>. It may be argued that this point occurs very early and that there is more
            at play here than the nature of the data. It could be argued the alignment described in
            the ACLS report is simply not feasible. As Sterne points out, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#sterne2005">disciplines never fully constitute their objects; they fight over them</quote>
                     <ptr target="#sterne2005" loc="251"/>
                  </cit>. He argues that these fights are partly
            what make disciplines maintain their intellectual vibrancy. If the range of data and the
            study objects are in question, it may be difficult to <emph>process</emph> data up to a
            certain point and use generic tools without early involvement from researchers.
            Furthermore, it could be argued any data would already be part of an information and
            knowledge infrastructure that is relevant to knowledge production and creation of tools
            and technology: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#bowker2005">Information infrastructures such as databases
                should be read both discursively and materially; they are a site of political and
                ethical as well as technical work; and that there can be no a priori attribution of
                a given question to the technical or the political realms.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#bowker2005" loc="123"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>Broadly conceived, cyberinfrastructure is intertwined with various institutional,
            social, cultural and historical layers inside and outside the disciplines themselves. As
            research infrastructure often, but not necessarily, supports interdisciplinary work, it
            seems particularly important to situate data structures, standards, technologies,
            knowledge structures and tools in a broad epistemological context. This is even more
            important given that infrastructures have a tendency to become invisible over time and
            that scalability is a commonly assigned property of cyberinfrastructure <ptr target="#bowker1999" loc="33"/>.</p>
               <p>There is a risk that external pressure on the humanities, not least the digital
            humanities, leads us to a positivist, results-driven approach. Here the need to provide
            motivation for funding agencies and university administration unsurprisingly plays an
            important role:</p>
               <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#terras2009">I'd just like to chip in and say this is what the funding councils
              are calling <term>Evidence of Value</term> — and are asking us to show evidence for the
              value of digital humanities research. It's important, as funding cuts in this area
              (such as the withdrawal of funds for the AHDS) are based on the perceived lack of
              evidence of value. Unless we can articulate, as a community, the better/faster/more
              nature of digital, we will struggle even harder for funding in years to come.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#terras2009"/>
               </cit>
               <p>The choice of adjectives here — <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#terras2009">better/faster/more</quote>
                     <ptr target="#terras2009"/>
                  </cit> — suggests a view of
            the digital humanities and associated infrastructure in line with the positivist
            discourse of science and technology driven cyberinfrastructure discussed above. The
            context is a dialogue about <soCalled>making a difference</soCalled> and <soCalled>What
              difference does digital make?</soCalled>
                  <ptr target="#terras2009"/>. While the above excerpt is very short and informal and we
            should not make too much of it, it is nevertheless noteworthy that it does not provide
            arguments that bring in research issues or current disciplinary challenges, which would
            seem indicative of the methodological and technological focus of traditional humanities
            computing.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Implications and Stakes</head>
               <p>At a time when there is both external pressure to specify infrastructural needs for the
            humanities and a growing humanities-internal interest for academic infrastructure and
            for the <term>digital,</term> it is clear that the ways we articulate and implement
            cyberinfrastructure for the humanities have strong implications. What happens if we do
            not explore multiple visions, focus only on digitizing existing infrastructure, or let
            the agenda be set through a technological focus or a model strongly based in the
            sciences?</p>
               <p>Here the question of epistemic commitments (cf. <ptr target="#svensson2009"/>) clearly
            comes into play. A too singular vision of cyberinfrastructure will limit the players and
            participants to those who match the epistemologies embedded in the new infrastructures,
            likewise a narrow focus on extending current infrastructure may result in a kind of
              <term>epistemological conservatism</term> that would foreclose potential new ways of knowing
            and legitimizing knowledge. Equally, a technology and science-inspired model driving the
            agenda could result in a cyberinfrastructure for the humanities without strong grounding
            in the disciplines, knowledge production, and indeed, needs and interests of the
            humanities. Furthermore, there is also the risk of what may be called epistemic
            double-binds (following <ptr target="#ratto2006"/>) where humanities researchers who
            want to make use of the new technologies are caught between the commitments of their
            academic disciplines and those of engineering, computer science and science more
            broadly. Ratto's principal example concerns use of computer-supported visualization and
            modeling in classical archaeology, and how three groups of scholars and scientists — for
            different reasons grounded in different epistemic commitments — rejected a project where
            an immersive 3D environment was used to question traditional understanding of the use of
            terra cotta materials in a particular form of pre-Roman temple. Ratto importantly argues
            that </p>
               <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#ratto2006">[a]cknowledging these commitments can help us develop appropriate
              technologies that help rather than hinder existing research practice, add a layer of
              reflexivity to researchers' choices and decisions, and ultimately, facilitate
              productive cross-disciplinary collaboration</quote>
                  <ptr target="#ratto2006"/>
               </cit>
               <p>Given the cyberinfrastructural push and the considerable interest in establishing new
            initiatives for the digital humanities, there is currently a window of opportunity. This
            window of opportunity needs to be combined with critical engagement to establish good
            practice, explore possible models and have a cyberinfrastructural dialogue across the
            Humanities.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Part II: HUMlab as a Case Study</head>
            <div>
               <head>Introduction</head>
               <p>As we have seen, the discourse on research infrastructure frequently becomes abstract
            and undetailed. At times, it is also positivistic and seemingly unsituated. At close
            quarters, on the other hand, infrastructure is often very concrete and material. The
            step from this material quality, as exemplified by a strand of optical fiber or a
            database server, to the conceptual underpinnings of research infrastructure, e.g. the
            ideas underlying a digital humanities initiative can be very substantial. In the
            following section, it is suggested that it can be helpful to look at the underlying
            ideas and the material qualities as well as intermediate level design principles that
            mediate ideas and infrastructure.</p>
               <p>In order to connect ideational grounding, design principles and actual implemented
            infrastructure, the case study of HUMlab, a digital humanities laboratory in the North
            of Sweden, will be examined in detail, as a particular example of humanities
            cyberinfrastructure. The case study was partly chosen because of the current author’s
            intimate knowledge of it, but also because it serves as a fairly distinct example of
            digital humanities infrastructure. Needless to say, it is only one example of
            infrastructural implementations, and as most infrastructures, highly situated in a
            particular context.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Framing the Case Study</head>
               <p>HUMlab is situated in a comprehensive research university, Umeå University, and as a
            ten-year endeavor, it has just undergone a major expansion supported strongly by the
            university as well as several external funding agencies. HUMlab has a commitment to a
            wide range of different modes of engagement which, naturally, affects infrastructural
            needs and visions. At this particular point in time, the university has taken a decision
            to build a new artistic campus — Umeå Arts Campus — by the river not too far from the
            main campus. Here the Institute of Design, the Academy of Fine Arts, BildMuseet (museum
            for contemporary visual arts) and a new School of Architecture will be situated, in
            addition to the new HUMlab-X. HUMlab will be the only institute or department to have a
            clear presence on both campuses.</p>
               <p>As noted above, there is evidently a considerable gap between the visionary, often
            positivistic and unsituated, discourse on cyberinfrastructure and implemented, and often
            quite material and situated, infrastructure. The connection between the two seems weak
            at times, and as we have seen, the conceptual underpinnings of cyberinfrastructure and
            associated epistemic scope may not be clear or explicated. At the same time, seemingly
            small decisions about technical or constructional details can have a very real impact on
            potential use and research possibilities afforded by the infrastructure. </p>
               <p>Through looking at implemented infrastructure, how it came about, ideational grounding
            and actual use, we can get a better sense of the complexity of the process and hopefully
            suggest a model that makes the concept of cyberinfrastructure richer, at the same time
            as linking to actual infrastructure. In the following, a model which includes conceptual
            cyberinfrastructure, design principles and actual cyberinfrastructure will be explored
            in relation to a particular infrastructural example.</p>
               <p>There are many possible infrastructural needs for a digital humanities lab or any
            digital humanities enterprise. These needs are partly connected to the modes of
            engagement discussed in the second article in this series <ptr target="#svensson2010"/>.
            For example, if the primary mode of engagement is technology as tool, you are likely to
            have rather different needs from an enterprise where the digital as a study object is
            the main focus. Patently, there are a great many different possible implementations for
            any digital humanities related enterprise dependent on factors such as the specific
            context, visions and epistemic scope. </p>
               <p>It is worth stressing the wide range of possible implementations within a single mode
            of engagement such as technology as tool. One example may be a research environment
            interested in experimental work using eye-tracking equipment or phonetic experiments in
            an echo-free room. These various facilities could possibly be manifested in several
            separate (but probably co-localized) rooms. Another example could be an institution
            focused on digital cultural heritage and the use of heavy-duty databases for making
            cultural heritage accessible to researchers around the world. Here the database servers
            would not necessarily have to take up any lab space at all as they would probably be
            housed in a server hall somewhere. Much of the work could then be carried out in
            individual offices or in a small lab space with workstations and space to help
            facilitate collaborative projects. A third example may be found in the tool-building
            phase of a large-scale research project where the digital component was a small part of
            the whole project. Here the facilities and equipment used may be part of that larger
            research project, or there might be some general resources for certain tasks.
            Importantly, all of the above examples require resources beyond the technology proper,
            and high-level competency is often needed. For instance, it does not make much sense to
            invest in high-end eye-tracking equipment if you do not have staff or researchers
            invested in methodology, technical management and maintenance. For more extensive use,
            and higher return on investment (i.e. higher and more <soCalled>efficient</soCalled> use), it is
            unsurprisingly advantageous to have dedicated people and resources connected to the
            infrastructure.</p>
               <p>The installation we will now look at has a more general, multipurpose character beyond
            the needs of single research groups, disciplines or methodological areas. HUMlab is a
            physically grounded studio environment heavily dependent on distributed work,
            international collaboration and reaching out. My knowledge from this institution comes
            from personal engagement and directorship, and while this inside perspective certainly
            calls for methodological concern and care, it also brings long experience from building,
            developing and incorporating a particular institution and its associated
            cyberinfrastructure.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Introducing HUMlab</head>
               <p>HUMlab at Umeå University, Sweden, is a digital humanities center whose main physical
            manifestation is a 500 m<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> (5,500 square feet) studio space
            at the center of the campus below the university library. This location is ideal because
            of its centrality and because it is seen as a neutral space not associated with any
            particular school or department. It is also a space with history and certain, irregular
            physical qualities that seem to help create an engaging and attractive environment.</p>
               <p>The basic idea behind HUMlab, as articulated early on, is to facilitate the meeting
            between humanities, culture and information technology, or put differently, to be a
            meeting place for the humanities, culture and information technology. Being a
            collaborative and intersectional <emph>place</emph> is critical to the operation. This
            fairly simple idea makes up a strong ideational basis, which is evident in the lab’s
            documentation from the very beginning up to this point. At the same time, it is not very
            concrete in the sense of detailing out implementations and constraints. This has allowed
            a fairly dynamic development and a relative openness to ideas and initiatives.</p>
               <p>The roots of this fairly independent role can partly be found in the lab’s origins.
            HUMlab was established in the late 1990s as a result of a discussion at the humanities
            faculty that started around 1994-95. The earliest incitement was the fact that the
            analogue language laboratory (mainly for teaching language pronunciation and
            proficiency) was gradually breaking down, and an early response was to try to devise
            some kind of multimedia lab. The resultant application for external funding was not
            successful, but had it been, the new lab would probably have been fairly traditional and
            instrumental. The failed attempt to secure funding led to the faculty seeking help
            elsewhere, resulting in a multiple-year process and ultimately to a very different
            concept. This concept, the meeting place mentioned above, partly came from outside the
            faculty and through working with a senior and creative officer at the university-wide IT
            function, the faculty secured technological validity, administrative know-how and an
            outside perspective on the humanities.</p>
               <p>The resultant project application rendered some early external funding for equipment in
            1998, and a decision was taken to support the lab at a faculty board meeting in November
            1998. It is noteworthy that the faculty board, despite the secured external funding for
            equipment and a fairly long internal process, was quite divided. The decision was
            positive but it took the decisive vote of the chair of the board to settle the matter.
            This hesitancy is possibly unsurprising, giving the <soCalled>newness</soCalled> of the enterprise and
            that any decision of funding is implicitly or explicitly a matter of prioritization.
            Also, investments in infrastructure or continuously paying for maintaining an
            infrastructure outside the traditional commitment of a faculty brings up important
            questions about long-term costs and the extent of financial and institutional
            commitments.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>The Space</head>
               <p>The idea of having a lab or studio space was part of the concept from very early on.
            Indeed, as we noted above, it all started as a concern with an old language laboratory
            and a possible multimedia replacement, the spatial need and having a lab could be seen
            as part of the original epistemic setup. It was taken further, though, in the subsequent
            discussions of HUMlab. There is a significant difference between a more moderate lab
            space and the large space that was envisioned and later allocated for HUMlab. This may
            partly have been a consequence of the focus on HUMlab as a meeting place and a diverse
            studio space with many different technologies and approaches. Moreover, HUMlab was
            described at an early stage as a <term>playground</term> - a place for exploring, testing
            ideas, connecting with outside initiatives and materials, and playing with technology -
            and this may have added to the sense of needing substantial space.</p>
               <p>The characteristics of the available space played an important role. After some
            negotiation, HUMlab was offered an old space below the university library. For many
            years, the long-term goal, supported by the university management, was to secure another
            space (newly built), but it has gradually become more and more obvious how well the
            existing space works. The location is critical, and a new, nice space at the periphery
            of the campus would most certainly not work as well as a meeting place. Also, the
            quirkiness, character and history of an old space plays an important role, as
            exemplified by the pillars, the irregularity of the space, the basement position and its
            earlier function as an exam hall. We will return to these elements shortly.</p>
               <p>HUMlab as a physical playground and meeting place is very much grounded in ongoing
            activities, lab life, meetings and technology. This physical presence extends into
            various digital environments and the two spaces of activity are richly interlinked. Most
            of the activities and projects are distributed in one sense or another. For instance,
            one of the first projects in the lab (started in 1999) a three-year student based
            exploration and expression in a virtual world hosted by HUMlab <ptr target="#svensson2003"/>, and since then, there has been lively engagement with a
            range of virtual world platforms. Most of the projects to do with digital cultural
            heritage have a presence in the physical lab, but much of the core operation occurs in
            relation to distributed databases and tools in international teams. Another example of
            merging of physical and digital is a fairly recent interest in physical computing. One
            of the 2008-2009 digital art fellows ran an operation called Ms. Balthazar’s Laboratory,
            a physical computing workshop for artistic uses intended primarily for women, with
            continuous meetings in HUMlab. The collaboration and workshops continue after the
            digital art fellow has left Umeå. Another fellow facilitated a process of community
            creation and curation that led to the exhibition of the Open Source Embroidery Project
            in 2009 in HUMlab and the BildMuseet. This exhibition opened in San Francisco in the
            winter of 2009, and it also reverberates in the lab through new courses and other
            activities.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Organization and Collaboration</head>
               <p>In terms of organization, HUMlab is a unit directly under the Humanities faculty and in
            most respects structurally comparable to a department. HUMlab can employ faculty as well
            as staff, and the director of the lab has roughly the same role as a head of a
            department. There is no formal research discipline associated with HUMlab, which means
            that Ph.D. students are affiliated both with HUMlab and a department. Faculty can be
            employed and tenured (in the European sense) by HUMlab. There are many possible
            organizational models, of course, but in many respects this particular organizational
            position seems advantageous. For one thing, there is little risk that HUMlab becomes too
            much associated with one department. HUMlab works with all humanities departments and
            disciplines (but in different ways and to varying extents). A higher organizational
            position such as a being a university level unit may be useful in some respects, but the
            risk may be that you lose disciplinary anchorage. Furthermore, because of the unit’s
            relative independency and multiple modes of engagement with information technology,
            there is little risk that HUMlab becomes classified as a service unit (a kind of unit
            normally prone to restructuring and financial rationalization; cf. <ptr target="#flanders2002"/>).</p>
               <p>An important part of HUMlab as practice is broad collaboration within and outside the
            humanities faculty. It is vital that HUMlab has had (or taken) a mandate to work
            extensively with other parts of the university, artists, companies and others interested
            in collaboration. Often these collaborations function as a way of creating collaborative
            opportunities for humanities researchers, students and departments. Importantly, HUMlab
            presents itself as being dynamically built on such collaborations rather than as a
            distinct and self-sustained research center. This is probably one of the reasons why
            there is strong support for a new HUMlab on the new Umeå Arts Campus. There was clearly
            an interest in having parties who not only engage in collaboration, but whose main
            function is to facilitate collaboration and interdisciplinary meetings (and in a way are
            dependent on rich collaboration for success).</p>
               <p>It may be argued that a chief difficulty in growing digital humanities is finding modes
            of scholarship that enable young researchers to inhabit the often problematic in-between
            zones. HUMlab attempts to balance interdisciplinarity within a collaborative zone with a
            grounding in departments and disciplines. This allows a range of strategies to grow.
            Further, it provides migration in discourses between interdisciplinary zones and centers
            of traditional academic departments and enables solidarities to arise in communities
            across departments, thus helping structure a field of research, and does not force young
            scholars to compromise between conservative choices for career and their interest in
            speaking to the contemporary moment.</p>
               <p>An early strategic decision that shaped HUMlab and associated cyberinfrastructure is
            that access is not restricted to specific groups and that the lab is open to students,
            faculty and staff as well as outside participants (a consequence of the basic idea of
            meeting place). Hence there is no exclusive focus on research, rather a continuous
            cross-fertilization between education, research and development work. HUMlab was
            designed to allow several simultaneous activities, and normally, a single activity
            cannot monopolize the lab. For instance, this means that a teacher using HUMlab for a
            class cannot ask other people to leave the lab (unless they are obviously disturbing the
            teaching), and that interaction between groups and individuals is encouraged. The
            difference between a regular classroom and HUMlab is quite pronounced, while some
            teachers may initially be uncomfortable with HUMlab as learning environment, most seem
            to appreciate the dynamics and energy of the lab. A common reaction if you enter the lab
            for the first time – not least students – is one of (positive) surprise and some
            bewilderment.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>The Importance of Spatial Configuration and Designing Space</head>
               <p>The interrelation between the space, technology and design is key to the actual
            implementation of a digital humanities environment whether it be physical or digital.
            Space and design cannot be divorced from technology and intellectual milieu (cf. <ptr target="#livingstone2003"/>); they are indeed important parts of what makes up
            cyberinfrastructure.</p>
               <p>The physical lab space of HUMlab was originally an examination hall and is situated in
            the oldest part of the university – below the university library and the central
            rotunda. The basement location gives the lab a certain atmosphere (cf. <ptr target="#williams2008"/>), which is reinforced by approaching the lab though a tunnel
            of protruding pipes, cement walls, sounds from the pipes, echoes in the corridor and
            muted noise from the students above. An interesting contrast is created between this
            subterranean feel, with some of the edginess and rawness associated with the
              <soCalled>underground,</soCalled> and the <soCalled>warm</soCalled> inside design of the lab.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure01">
                  <head>Photo of HUMlab (original lab space)</head>
                  <graphic url="...000090/resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc/>
               </figure>
               <p>The foundational function is further evidenced through 24 pillars and the rotunda,
            whose protruding base forms one of the inner walls. The ceiling height is not the same
            throughout the space and in general, the space is fairly irregular. The original lab
            space is about 280 m<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> (3000 square feet). It contains a
            closeable inner space with large windows and the lab’s computer workstations are mainly
            organized around pillars (as <soCalled>islands</soCalled>). Together with the aforementioned glass
            room, a meeting section behind a bookcase and an area with couches and an aquarium, the
            islands make up an important part of the lab space. There are quite a few screens in the
            space, mostly private workstation screens, but also several display screens. Many of the
            private screens are in fact fairly public as the space has been designed to encourage
            people to relate to each other’s work. In this way, there is a simultaneous production
            of a shared sense of publicness, co-location and semi-private space (cf. <ptr target="#mccarthy2001"/>). Other screens consistently work as portals to projects and
            other physical and digital spaces.</p>
               <p>Although a rather untraditional lab environment, the old part of the space has some
            elements associated with traditional computer lab spaces, including the computer
            workstations described above. When HUMlab was expanded in 2008 with an additional 220
              m<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> (2400 square feet), the new space was designed with
            considerably more flexibility than the old part. In a way, the two parts represent
            fairly different implementations and concepts within a common framework. The function of
            an open meeting place is quite pronounced in the new space. At the center is <soCalled>a room
              in a room</soCalled> defined by wallpapered pillars, a rug and a large central table, and all
            these parts can be removed or reconfigured. The rest of the space is fairly open in its
            basic configuration. An important property of the new lab space is a screenscape that
            includes a number of public screens around the space. There are ten large flat screens
            (57"-70") and one very large, back projected high resolution (4K) screen. The large
            screen has multi-touch functionality and there is a spatial audio system which covers
            the screenscape in its entirety. The basic idea is to afford rich contextualization, and
            partly collaborative and partly distributed work in a fairly large interaction space.
            The arrangement of the screens is quite significant and their placement at the periphery
            of the space in combination with the centrally placed table prevents the screens from
            dominating the space.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure02">
                  <head>Photo of HUMlab (part of the screenscape and the expanded studio
                     space)</head>
                  <graphic url=".../000090/resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc/>
               </figure>
               <p>These public screens are simultaneously individual and part of the screenscape, and
            they structure and break up the space in certain ways. Participants in the space can be
            situated in relation to individual screens or in the context of the full screenscape, as
            well in ongoing activities or conversations. <ptr target="#mccarthy2001"/> discusses
            some of these complexities in relation to multiple overhead monitors: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#mccarthy2001">Serial spectacles on overhead screens both symbolically join spaces
                together in long-distance communication and fragment the social atmosphere of their
                immediate environments. The connotations of public address that come with the
                convention of overhead screen placement suture the conversing spectator into (at
                least) two places at once. </quote>
                     <ptr target="#mccarthy2001" loc="124"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>While the screens in the HUMlab screenscape are not placed in an overhead position (but
            rather mid-level), they certainly both fragment and join the space together. The space
            and technical setup encourage experimentation with different configuration and uses.</p>
               <p>Behind the screen perimeter there are a number of workplaces and workstations for
            different research areas and for visiting scholars. Here the large screens mounted on
            pillars help separate the screenscape from the more private area behind the pillars,
            while maintaining a sense of communication in between the more public and the more
            private zones. One of the sections behind the pillars has a combined whiteboard and
            projection screen that is not part of the screenscape and which allows a small research
            group to collaboratively and semi-privately use the screen and associated
            technology.</p>
               <p>There can be no doubt that the ways cyberinfrastructure is constructed and implemented
            have direct bearing on knowledge production and the epistemic scope of such
            infrastructures, and that space, physical and digital, is often a carrier of
            cyberinfrastructure. There is rich meaning to how space and infrastructure are
            configured, juxtaposed and used far beyond the purely functional or technical properties
            of the infrastructure. The following set of quotes illustrates this point in relation to
            a traditional humanities infrastructure - the library. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#hass2001">
                        <p>I'm
                  surprised to realize how much my identity as a humanist at MIT is tied to Building
                  14, how strong its symbolic importance as a space for humanities books and
                  humanities teachers.</p>
                        <p>I think that a Humanities Library should be a kind of intellectual hub for
                  humanities scholars and students. It should house books, of course, but also
                  humanities events, humanities computing resources, etc. Humanists should be able
                  to gather there to exchange ideas. The library is our lab. And our food trucks,
                  minus the food.</p>
                        <p>The best place for writing for me is by the big windows in the Humanities
                  Library, with the network drop nearby. All I ask for is some newer tables, and
                  maybe more ergonomic chairs.</p>
                        <p>The Humanities Library is an oasis in an otherwise inhospitable desert. It
                  provides the Humanities with a dignity that is not accord else on this campus, and
                  therefore sustains me in my sense of intellectual and academic worth on a
                  day-to-day basis.</p>
                     </quote>
                     <ptr target="#hass2001"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>These comments were collected in the beginnings of the 2000s, when there was a
            discussion of the future and location of the humanities library at MIT. The comments
            mainly come from faculty, and here we get a sense of the richness and interconnectedness
            associated with conceptual grounding (the library as idea, meeting place and hub),
            design (e.g. the big windows and the network drop), location, personal engagement with
            the infrastructure, power structures and disciplinary perspectives. </p>
               <p>It is thus important to carefully consider how we design these spaces or
            infrastructures and how they relate to both the technological level of infrastructure
            and conceptual grounding. This may be where we find the kind of articulation and
              <soCalled>packaging</soCalled> required to address the challenge we outlined in Part I of this
            article: the need for humanities based visions of cyberinfrastructure.</p>
               <p>A rich full-length study of the complexities of cyberinfrastructure in relation to
            space and conceptual notions can be found in Reinhold Martin's analysis of corporate
            architecture in the United States after the Second World War <ptr target="#martin2005"/>. He traces how cybernetics and a systems-based theory in architecture come to create
            flexible and modular interiors. In his analysis of IBM and the IBM Rochester's plant -
            designed by architect Eero Saarinen - that opened in September 1958, Martin points to
            how the architecture of modular blue patterns was used to <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#martin2005">displace (or dissimulate) the social hierarchies written into white collars and
                gray flannel, in the name of <soCalled>human relations</soCalled> among mass-produced
                IBMers</quote>
                     <ptr target="#martin2005" loc="170"/>
                  </cit>. One example of this is the visitors'
            entry not being seen as more important or architecturally pronounced than the entries to
            the employees' pavilions. Martin traces the parallels between the design of devices such
            as the IBM 305 Random Access Memory Accounting Machine (RAMAC, released in 1956) and the
            corporate buildings of IBM. He points to the analogy between human nervous systems and
            computer design, and associated neurological terminology made prevalent by John Neumann
            and others, and how this thinking may also become reflected also in the architecture.
                <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#martin2005">While IBM represented itself as a mere maker of business
                machines and <soCalled>calculators,</soCalled> even its building were experimenting with
                  <soCalled>logical controls</soCalled> encoded into a paper-thin skin. Even more than the RAMAC,
                this building's <soCalled>brain</soCalled> was on its surface. In that regard, its image was
                integral to the organizational strategies that kept the company growing and enabled
                it to expand its research into artificial intelligence, pattern recognition, and
                related arenas.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#martin2005" loc="181"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>These arrangements clearly have rich meaning, and it could be argued that such a
            reflective mode and sense of history and ideational grounding also helps us to better
            understand cyberinfrastructure for the humanities.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Conceptual Cyberinfrastructure</head>
               <p>Conceptual cyberinfrastructure can be seen as a set of underlying ideas that provide
            the ideational grounding of a particular instance of research infrastructure. In the
            case of HUMlab, facilitating cross-sectional meetings is such an underlying idea. In the
            model presented here, these basic ideas can be related to design principles. For
            instance, the design principle of translucence (to facilitate both <soCalled>see-through</soCalled>
            and individual space) helps facilitate the idea of HUMlab as a meeting place. These
            principles, in turn, inform the implementation of actual infrastructure (for instance
            making extensive use of glass and not having any fully isolated parts of the lab).</p>
               <p>In practice the flow will be iterative, and for instance, it is rarely the case that
            new space and infrastructure can be built without any constraints imposed from existing
            systems, architecture and research infrastructure, as well as existing funding regimes
            and/or policies at the administrative level. Such constraints (and possibilities) need
            to be presented and negotiated throughout the process.</p>
               <p>While this model may seem ambitious for small installations and for conventionalized
            infrastructure (such as a traditional classroom intended to be used <soCalled>traditionally</soCalled>
            or a standard query system for a research database), it can be quite useful when
            thinking about new kind of learning and research spaces and associated infrastructure.
            It encourages us to be clear about the conceptual underpinnings and epistemic scope,
            think carefully about how these can be translated into design principles and
            operationalized in relation to existing infrastructure and planned cyberinfrastructure.
            If successful, such a process would help us articulate our requirements, visions and
            ideas in a broad, contextualized sense and in relation to conceptual issues, as well as
            physical and digital implementation. Furthermore, it may help us create a meeting point
            for people from the <soCalled>enterprise</soCalled> (department, university administration,
              <soCalled>users</soCalled>) and people involved in the creation of new infrastructure and space
            (architects, hardware and software specialists, contractors, property owners and
            sometimes also funding agencies).</p>
               <p>Importantly, since the digital humanities maximally but not necessarily, incorporates
            many different disciplines, disciplinary pathways, modes of engagement, perspectives and
            outside pressures, it is quite important to be conscious of epistemic traditions and be
            deliberate about the process, vision and implementation. It is also important, however,
            to acknowledge that arriving at a conceptual foundation and implementation often is a
            complex, iterative and exploratory process, and that there are many possible paths.</p>
               <p>In the case of HUMlab, it is quite clear that there has been a set of conceptual
            underpinnings that have shaped the emerging cyberinfrastructure from the beginning,
            although some of these may not have been articulated until quite late in the process.
            Other parts of the conceptual foundation have developed and changed over the years.
            Below, three significant examples are given, one of which is discussed at more length.
            Additionally, individual design principles are detailed in the subsequent section.</p>
               <list type="unordered">
                  <item>
                     <label>Meeting place</label>: The notion of HUMlab as a meeting place is central
              to HUMlab as an idea and space, and clearly articulated in early vision documents as
              well as in actual implementation. This is reflected in the design principles of
              translucence (encouraging contact and having a sense of what other people are working
              on), flexibility (supporting many different kinds of meetings and technological
              platforms) and engagement (a space and endeavor that attracts engagement, intensity
              and interest), and their spatial and technological implementations. In terms of
              facilitating a variety of meetings, HUMlab has plenty of social spaces (also outside
              the lab proper), meeting tables, an <soCalled>outward</soCalled> design that make many computer
              screens visible to others, many large screens, coffee (often free) and a range of
              software, hardware and activities that attract people from different parts of the
              university and from the outside. Also, the lab is available to users 24 hours, all
              year. A well-functioning lab space can help create a platform for managing and
              supporting research infrastructure in that there will always be a range of
              competencies and skill sets available, and at best, a willingness to help and share
              knowledge. The sense of meeting place extends outside the physical lab space, of
              course, and there is a strong dispersed community, ongoing distributed work and shared
              data sets, materials and tool development. </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Multiple modes of engagement</label>: Another conceptual and epistemic
              baseline for HUMlab is the interest in multiple modes of engagement with information
              technology and the digital. This means that the lab has been set up to support work
              with technology as a tool, an object of study, an exploratory laboratory, an
              expressive medium and an activist venue. Although there was no early explicit
              commitment to these particular modes of engagement when HUMlab was started, there was
              an openness and flexibility (both in terms of technology and 'content') that allowed
              for very different kinds of projects and activities. Over the years, cumulative
              practice and reflecting on this practice - also in relation to other international
              initiatives - has resulted in a model of modes of engagement that could be said to be
              part of the conceptual cyberinfrastructure of the lab. This commitment to a range of
              different kinds of engagement has very direct implications for design and
              infrastructure. For example, a multiple-mode focus is not compatible with having a
              traditionally instrumental computer lab setup as the space needs to work for
              activities such as seminars, meetings and relating to various study objects (digital
              and non-digital). These elements are also important in relation to bringing in
              researchers and students from the disciplines - not only because familiar elements may
              be attractive, but also because they perform basic epistemic functions. As we have
              already noted, a commitment to multiple modes of engagement also calls for a varied
              technological setup, and HUMlab offers a wide range of technologies for analytical
              work, visualization, creative work, screenings and physical computing. The downside to
              this may be that it is more difficult to allocate substantial resources to single
              areas (as in a specialized lab environment). More generally, it would seem that the
              humanities often have need for a more diversified and multiplex infrastructure than
              the kind of science and engineering cyberinfrastructure described in policy and vision
              documents (cf. the discussion in Part I and the reflections presented in Part
              III).</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Context and digital visualization and representation</label>: A third
              conceptual foundation draws on the intersection between the humanities as providing
              rich cultural and historical context and technologies of multiplex digital
              visualization and representation. Here the primary associated design principle is
              multiplexity and the most obvious implementation would be the screenscape and
              underlying technological infrastructure. The screen and interaction space has
              different functions in relation to different projects, activities and modes of
              engagement. The actual implemented infrastructure clearly stimulates ideas,
              experiments and uses, and in this sense the infrastructure is just the beginning. Also
              the prototype design presented in various ways (e.g. a 3D model of the design, a fly
              through and as a virtual environment) before the space was implemented provoked ideas,
              but actually having the space makes the process easier, more grounded and multi-level.
              This exemplifies the iterative nature of the process and the fact that new ideas may
              develop as a partial result of having cyberinfrastructure. </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Humanities Representations and Screenscapes in Practice</head>
               <p>In a discussion of the initiative for software studies and associated cultural
            analytics research at UC San Diego, Lev Manovich points to how having access to the
            visualization environment HIperSpace at CALIT2 has made new ideas or directions
            possible: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#franklin2008">HIperSpace is the reason why I am able to think of
                being able to map and analyze global cultural patterns in detail. I would not ever
                think about it if I just worked on my laptop screen.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#franklin2008"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>While facilities such as HIperSpace and HUMlab are very flexible and will generate
            ideas, uses and experiments beyond what could be envisioned at the start, it is also
            true that users and uses are constrained by the way these infrastructures have been
            thought up and set up. This could be said to be part of the conceptual
            cyberinfrastructure. HIperSpace is a very large tiled display made up of many small
            screens - basically a large, rectangular screen with internal mullions (caused by the
            frames of the individual screens). It is seen as a front end to an optiputer and the
            main overarching goal is to <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#defanti2009">examine a <soCalled>future</soCalled> in which
                networking is no longer a bottleneck to local, regional, national and international
                computing</quote>
                     <ptr target="#defanti2009"/>
                  </cit>. The mullions are seen as something that will
            eventually get reduced and maybe disappear altogether visually - thus creating one large
            seamless display. HUMlab, on the other hand, has an investment in both allowing for big
            display walls and for a multitude of separate, visually distinct screens. The frames of
            the screens are thus quite important, as is the positioning of individual screens in the
            space. On a very large screen, such as the HIperSpace installation, you are likely to
            display a number of different materials, sources and windows, and thus the individual
            bits will be framed on the screen, but this framing is screen internal (cf. the notion
            of multiplex frames in <ptr target="#friedberg2006"/>, and the discussion of computer
            windows in <ptr target="#manovich1995"/>) and rather different from having separate
            screens with <term>heavy</term> frames. A somewhat related paradigm for visualization is
            virtual reality (representing an earlier generation of privileged cyberinfrastructure),
            which often tries to remove the frame altogether. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#brooks1999">The visual
                (and aural and haptic) displays that immerse the user in the virtual world and that
                block out contradictory sensory impressions from the real world;</quote>
                     <ptr target="#brooks1999"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>In some ways, the distributed screenscape of HUMlab is the opposite of such virtual
            reality manifestations. In HUMlab, sensory impressions from the <soCalled>real</soCalled> world are
            quite important and the screens are integrated in a lively studio environment. This
            makes the screens less <term>aggressive</term> (to borrow the terminology from <ptr target="#manovich1995"/>) than many other visualization environments. The new part of
            HUMlab borrows elements from visualization spaces, as well as traditional seminar,
            studio and exhibition spaces, and the collaborative affordances (whether in relation to
            technology or not) are quite important. Also, as pointed out above, the screens have
            their own identity and framing. The epistemological stance is thus radically different
            from that of many virtual reality environments where you, as Dan Sandin, co-inventor of
            the CAVE, points out, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#russett2009">in a sense, view things from inside the
                scene</quote>
                     <ptr target="#russett2009" loc="183"/>
                  </cit>. In other words, there is arguably no
            frame. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#bolter2003">There would be no screen between the user and the
                information and no way for the user to step back and contemplate the screen at a
                distance, because she would be wearing the screens as eyepieces that completely
                covered her field of view.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#bolter2003" loc="54"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>HUMlab attempts to bring together multiplex frames (digital screens that contain
            separate elements such as windows) and multiple digital screens in a held-together
            screenscape. Each screen can be run individually in the screenscape, be part of a large
            'computer desktop' or be part of a video-signal level desktop or extended space (which
            can include video, computer and other sources). The screenscape as a whole is part of a
            large studio space with a seminar table in the middle of the room. In this way a range
            of practices and possible uses can be supported, spanning from traditional seminars
            (with no or little technology used), to individual researchers using their workstations
            with one or several screens, to research groups using the large high-resolution touch
            screen collaboratively and in a distributed fashion with remote data sets and
            researchers, to student use of three screens to discuss different solutions to an
            assigned problem, and even to large interactive art installations that use screens,
            different kinds of sensor technology and spatial audio.</p>
               <p>Let us look at a few examples more directly in relation to various humanities based
            uses of the kind of environment that is described above (excluding uses that do not use
            any or little technology). As digitalized material becomes increasingly available, a
            screenscape can help philologists and art historians to display and interact with a
            number of manuscript pages or pictures. Researchers in environmental archeology can pull
            together large data sets, diverse materials and visualized data models in one space, and
            use a large, high-resolution screen to work with the data model (zooming, modifying,
            interrelating the model with data sources) locally or together with remote research
            centers. Site-specific art installations can be created in the space. Students who have
            built virtual exhibitions in Second Life can show their individual or their group’s
            slices of their virtual world on screens. Events such as an indie game evenings can make
            use of all the screens to allow people to interact with a range of games, and in an
            associated presentation, individual games can be moved to the large screen and
            juxtaposed as part of a comparative and analytical process. Other events may bring in
            remote researchers through different types of virtual environments and through
            visualized data sets. Thematic screenings of films can be facilitated in the space. An
            upcoming seminar with an international guest speaker can be contextualized through a
            curated selection of images, video clips, texts and web pages. More generally and
            visionarily, complex scholarly environments for humanistic research can bring together
            analytical tools, distributed materials, representations and ways to tackle central
            research challenges in a studio space such as in the aforementioned descriptions, as
            well as in associated online spaces. </p>
               <p>There is certainly an interesting interrelation between the humanities and technology
            supported visualization and representation, and hopefully the above description shows
            that associated cyberinfrastructure comes with certain epistemic commitments, but also
            that uses grow from the actual implementation and experimentation. Looking at the
            conceptual cyberinfrastructure associated with new part of HUMlab, we have seen that
            multiplexity and framing are critical factors. HUMlab is different from virtual reality
            manifestations where there is ideally no frame (once you are <soCalled>inside</soCalled>) and from
            installations such as the HIperWall which are basically very large multiplex frames.
              <ptr target="#friedberg2006"/> suggests a taxonomy of variables mainly based on a
            cinematic perspective, which includes multiple screens, but her examples are limited to
            cinematic representation (such as Charles and Ray Eames’ Glimpses of the USA exhibition
            at the 1959 Moscow World's Fair). In her discussion of computer screens, Friedberg seems
            to suggest a one-screen (multiplex frame) paradigm: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#friedberg2006">The Windows
                interface is a postcinematic visual system, but the viewer-turned-user remains in
                front of (vorstellen) a perpendicular frame.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#friedberg2006" loc="232"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>This view is challenged by the increased use of many linked but individual screens
            (available on MACs from the late 1980s and on Windows since the mid-nineties).
            Interestingly, <ptr target="#colomina2001"/> shows in her analysis of the Eameses'
            multimedia architecture how separate video screens, although not one screenscape in a
            technical sense, can create a thematic and performative whole. With seven enormous
            screens and seven individual images per screen and one final image, there were a total
            of 50 images in <title rend="italic">Glimpses of the USA</title>. These images were
            presented in thematic bursts in a highly coordinated and very carefully planned
            installation. Although this arrangement does not make the individual frames visually
            multiplex at any given time, frame-internal multiplexity is achieved temporally.</p>
               <p>The HUMlab setup explores the importance of having multiple screens and multiplex
            frames at the same time and how this relates to the essence of the Humanities - rich
            cultural and historical context, heterogeneous qualitative and quantitative materials,
            different modes of representation and presentation, shared presence and multiplex
            perspectives.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Design Principles</head>
               <p>Design principles provide a layer in between the layer of conceptual
            cyberinfrastructure just discussed and the actual implementation. In the case of HUMlab,
            a number of central design principles have emerged in the course of the development of
            the lab. While these principles naturally are situated in a specific context, they also
            have some more general applicability.</p>

               <p>Design principles can be seen as a way of connecting the ideational level with material
            cyberinfrastructure, and as facilitating a means of discussing and articulating
            infrastructural projects without getting caught up only in detailed infrastructure
            and/or the abstract visions typical of the discourse on cyberinfrastructure (cf. Part
            I). The principles are seen as being anchored in both these levels. In the following, I
            will discuss a number of suggested design principles for HUMlab as an infrastructural
            project. The seven principles in question are translucence, flexibility, memory and
            context, multiplexity, non-linearity and messiness, engagement, and adaptability and
            co-evolution. While these are not all-inclusive or unchanging, they suggest an anchored
            and systemic-level foundation for HUMlab as infrastructure.</p>
               <p>In designing the space of HUMlab, an important design principle has been
              <term>translucence</term>. The basic idea is that it is important to see what is going
            on in the lab while not resorting to having one large and totally open space. In optics,
            translucent materials allow light to pass through them diffusely. The constraints and
            affordances are not only visual, of course, and awareness of whether other people can
            hear you or not is, for instance, an important factor. In a studio (or other)
            environment, this translates to having a space which has divisions and separation which
            allow for sub spaces to maintain spatial, auditory and conceptual integrity (to
            different degrees), while also retaining a sense of what is going on in other parts of
            the space. This affects possible interactions in several ways (cf. <ptr target="#erickson2000"/>). On one level, you have access to concurrent activities,
            processes and dialogues. For instance, when the lab or a project is presented to a
            delegation in the inner glass room, there is a good visual sense of activities and
            people outside the room. Similarly, people outside this room have a sense of what goes
            on inside (and will for instance be prepared to act when the delegation prepares to
            leave the inner room). Dourish and Bly’s notion of awareness and their porthole system
            are based on a similar notion, although they emphasize the distributed nature of the
            system: <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#dourish1992">Awareness involves knowing who is <soCalled>around,</soCalled> what
                activities are occurring, who is talking with whom; it provides a view of one
                another in the daily work environments. Awareness may lead to informal interactions,
                spontaneous connections, and the development of shared cultures — all
                important aspects of maintaining working relationships which are denied to groups
                distributed across multiple sites.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#dourish1992" loc="541"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>HUMlab takes as its point of departure the organization of collaborations across
            physical-digital boundaries. For instance, seminars primarily take place in the physical
            space, but they are almost always streamed live, and sometimes there is a secondary
            screen showing remote participants interested in participating in the discussion.
            Earlier this was done through a text-based chat client, and later with video based
            software. The list of remote participants on the screen (which is visible to the
            physical participants) can support a sense of shared presence and increased awareness.
            Similarly, a tweet visualization with local and distant tweets in relation to an ongoing
            seminar helps create a back channel with shared awareness. An important point in
            relation to Dourish and Bly’s article is that designing for awareness and translucence
            is quite important also in physical space, and that many current spaces are
              <term>mixed.</term>
               </p>
               <p>In the physical lab, screens (both public and semi-private ones) play an important role
            in representing ongoing work and in bringing in external worlds and materials
            (portholes). Activities can thus go on in both sub spaces and still retain a sense of
            co-presence and co-location without unnecessarily disturbing each other. Moreover, this
            arrangement opens up space more generally and helps coordinate collaboration. In the
            open part of HUMlab, translucence is supported through many separate, semi-private
            sections as well as through the way screens are positioned to allow a sense of ongoing
            work. The translucent nature of dividers (e.g. half-tall bookcases, hanging absorbents,
            pillars and screens, and an aquarium) allows dialogue, co-presence and some over-hearing
            between sections. </p>

               <p>Another relevant parameter is <term>flexibility</term>. A wider range of activities and
            initiatives can be supported through allowing flexible use of an infrastructural
            resource such as HUMlab. The importance of flexibility is often emphasized in work on
            design of learning and studio environments (<ptr target="#merkel1999"/>, <ptr target="#jamieson2000"/>, and <ptr target="#gonsalvez2000"/>). Simple examples would
            include ease of reconfiguring the space and changing furniture around, allowing many
            different kinds of activities, flexible distribution of media, and a multiplex technical
            implementation. It could be argued that a flexible setup allows more change in
            pedagogical, scholarly and technological practices, whereas a fixed setup has a stronger
            investment in a particular model or framework (cf. <ptr target="#mitchell2003"/>). There
            is a tension, however, between what is flexible and what is fixed, and total flexibility
            is probably not realizable as there will always be decisions that constrain the level of
            flexibility. A totally flexible space would probably have to be a compromise. Also, some
            degree of fixedness can be part of good design practice and deliberate choices to
            encourage certain kinds of use and activities. In the case of HUMlab, and probably many
            other similar environments, there is a rather delicate balance between flexibility and
            fixedness. Some of the fixedness comes from a set of basic underlying ideas about what a
            space is and how it should be used and can be seen as part of the conceptual
            cyberinfrastructure. In some of the virtual spaces associated with HUMlab, similar
            tension can be observed. For instance when an art installation and artist (with
            assumptions of exhibition and controlled space) co-exist in the same Second Life space
            as people who are continuously doing experimental building, and who fly through the
            asserted space of the exhibition with e.g. space ships. Negotiation is often needed in
            order to resolve these clashes.</p>
               <p>One of the things which distinguishes a studio space from a meeting room or most
            classrooms is that there is a strong sense of ongoing work and activities. There is a
            richness to such spaces which partly comes from the <emph>memory and context</emph>
            interwoven into the various modes of expression present and in traces from previous
            projects and people. In a design studio you will often find sketches and prototypes,
            which provide a sense of process and provide points of display and discussion. As a set
            of disciplines, the Humanities are much concerned with rich historical and cultural
            context, which would seem to be well in line with a highly contextual space. If this
            space is also flexible, it may allow for shifting contextual landscapes (e.g. through
            dynamic screens, cf. <ptr target="#manovich1995"/>), as well as a more static or
            semi-static memory and context.</p>
               <p>
                  <term>Multiplexity</term> is a parameter that interrelates with translucence,
            flexibility and rich context. If complex processes and themes are important to the
            humanities as well as collaborative, trans-disciplinary projects, it is relevant to have
            a cyberinfrastructure that supports these multiple perspectives, complex data sets and
            heterogeneous context. In HUMlab, multiplexity in this sense is facilitated in
            particular through the screenscape in the new part of the lab. It allows the
            simultaneous engagement with many types of materials, ideas and perspectives through the
            screens, interaction technology, sensor technology and audio. Furthermore, many screens
            ideally have an empowering function in that there is not only one main screen, which is
            typically controlled by a teacher. Being in control of a single screen is often the same
            thing as having the floor. The screenscape in HUmlab can be controlled by one user, all
            the screens can be used together, or single users can use one or more screens
            individually. In HUMlab, multiplexity is also supported through the many different kinds
            of meeting and work places in the total studio space and through digitally supported
            spaces. In addition, the technology setup is multiplex in that it includes a variety of
            technologies, systems and software. It is quite common that students give this varied
            setup as an important reason for working and studying in HUMlab. Most technology rich
            labs at the university are either generic (basically providing browsing, word processing
            and printing) or program or department specific (often being highly specific and
            restricted as e.g. 3D modelling labs at the computer science department). One underlying
            idea in HUMlab is that a varied technological setup can afford exploration and many
            different types of activities and cross-over effects.</p>
               <p>
                  <term>Non-linearity</term> and <term>messiness</term> is about the importance of having
            spaces that are not too linear, orderly or sterile. Spaces such as university classrooms
            do not normally reflect ongoing work and tend to be fairly non-descript and standard.
            When the class is over, the norm is typically and understandably that the room should be
            left tidy and organized (and hence fairly devoid of rich context). Studio spaces, on the
            other hand, typically reflect ongoing processes and are hence more contextual and
            untidy. <cit>
                     <quote rend="block" source="#fallmann2007">While each and every piece of among the multitude of
                material objects that appear in a progressive design studio seldom by itself has a
                strong or even explicit link to an aspect of the project at hand, they as a
                collection seem to conspire to create the rich environment needed to stimulate
                creativity and create novel ideas.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#fallmann2007" loc="5"/>
                  </cit>
               </p>
               <p>In his discussion of artistic studio spaces, <ptr target="#buren2010" loc="160"/>
            emphasizes how the collection of visible materials viewed at the same time creates a
            sense and understanding of process. </p>
               <p>While lab spaces typically allow more exclusive use of the space than regular
            classrooms they tend not to be as obviously untidy and processual as studio spaces.
            Indeed, <ptr target="#lehmann2009"/> points to connotations of secrecy and specialized
            technological processes associated with laboratories and how media labs may maintain
            some of this sense of <term>black box.</term> There is certainly an element of exclusiveness
            associated with many lab environments, however, it would seem that Lehman underplays the
            difference between <term>laboratory</term> and <term>lab</term> (and <term>media lab</term>). In any case,
            many lab spaces, not least new ones, appear somewhat sterile - in particular if they are
            large, rectangular and fairly mono-functional. Traditional spaces are also often
            horizontal in the sense that floors and ceilings are rarely used beyond their obvious
            core functions – they are not seen as important design elements in a non-linear
            space.</p>
               <p>An important but somewhat illusive parameter is the sense of personal investment,
            energy and attractiveness that may be associated with a space and its people, activities
            and direction. Some spaces seem to lend themselves to <term>engagement</term>, which may
            be manifested in that the space is <soCalled>a place to hang out,</soCalled> through its sense of
              <emph>energy</emph> and that visitors can engage directly with the space and remember it
            afterwards. <ptr target="#mitchell2003"/> talks about the intensity of a space, and it
            might be argued that a high-intensity space encourages engagement, collaboration and
            exploration. It is, of course, impossible to pinpoint exactly what gives a space such
            qualities, but it would seem that non-sterile and heterogeneous spaces are more likely
            to evoke this kind of sentiment, and that a sense of energy can be derived from many
            (different) people sharing the same space, from ongoing creative work, from a sense of
            process and from a culture that supports collaboration, community and dialogue. The flow
            of people gathering for different activities, project meetings and their own work is
            quite important in this context, and the constant influx of new people such as visiting
            postdoctoral fellows and guest speakers adds to that energy as well as integration of
            external materials and distributed presence. Physical elements can clearly play an
            important role here, and examples from HUMlab include the neon sign outside the lab,
            beanbags, inviting couches and tables for meetings and coffee drinking, pictorial mats,
            designer wallpaper, nice-looking whiteboards, plants and a large aquarium. These
            elements can be as critical as computer workstations in supporting a collaborative,
            engaging technology-rich environment, but their meaningfulness is also contextual and
            situational. Thrown-in beanbags and designer couches will not automatically produce an
            attractive studio space.</p>
               <p>Regardless of the time and money invested into planning and designing a learning or lab
            space, and regardless of the amount of flexibility built into the space, a space cannot
            be said to be finished when it has been installed. Beyond any extended installation
            phase or regular long-term maintenance plan, there is a need to think about space as a
            dynamic and evolving entity that is intrinsically linked to users and inhabitants of
            that space as well as any underlying ideational grounding. Actual use of a planned space
            can be predicted and simulated, but use of space is contextual, social and, at least
            sometimes, unpredictable. It may be possible to make a distinction between flexibility
            (basic <emph>designed</emph> flexibility), adaptability (fairly quick responses to apparent
            needs and usage patterns) and co-evolution (long-term changes as a consequence of the
            interplay between the space, users of the space and the conceptual cyberinfrastructure).
            The more long-term processes are thus <term>adaptability</term> and
              <term>co-evolution</term>. In a longer perspective, the life of a building and a site,
            also these processes are fairly short term. Brand distinguishes between different layers
            of shearing from site (eternal) to structure, skin, services and space plan to stuff
              <ptr target="#brand1995" loc="12–13"/>. Most of the processes mentioned here would be
            related to space plan and stuff (furniture, appliances etc.), and sometimes services
            (communications wiring, electrical wiring etc.). </p>
               <p>As indicated above, a basic presumption is that in most cases, it is not possible to
            create a totally flexible space, and that there is a tension between a very high degree
            of flexibility and a grounded, context-specific ideational basis. In HUMlab, an example
            of flexibility (<soCalled>stuff</soCalled>) would be moveable chairs, light-weight tables, portable
            screens and distributed control of audio systems. An example of adaptability (<term>space
              plan</term> and to some extent, <term>services</term>) may be when a table intended for other
            use increasingly started to be used by laptop users and was hence equipped with cabling
            and new light fixtures, or when an underused part of the lab was redesigned with lower
            bookcases (to allow a higher degree of contact through translucence), a new
            laptop-friendly table and a new combined whiteboard and projection screen (see <ref target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref>). </p>
               <figure xml:id="figure03">
                  <head>Photo of HUMlab (redesigned corner)</head>
                  <graphic url="...000090/resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc/>
               </figure>
               <p>After the corner space was redesigned into this more <soCalled>café-like</soCalled> setting, usage
            increased significantly. Given that a space develops over many years, there will be
            on-going co-evolution between the people and activities of that space and how the space
            is continuously reconfigured.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Part III: Strategizing and Implementing Humanities Cyberinfrastructure</head>
            <div>
               <head>Introduction</head>
               <p>As we have seen in this article, research infrastructure for the humanities is diverse,
            multi-level and often distinctly material and highly abstract at the same time. With an
            inclusive definition of research infrastructure, almost anything needed to carry out
            research in the humanities could be included: ranging from paper, pens, books, furniture
            and people to database structures, grid computing facilities, visualization centers and
            libraries. We saw in Part I how cyberinfrastructure can be seen as a science and
            engineering project associated with funding mechanisms, policy making and high-cost
            research equipment of national or international interest. In Part II, a specific
            humanities infrastructure was presented and analyzed, and related to design principles
            and an ideational level, called conceptual cyberinfrastructure. </p>
               <p>If we regard cyberinfrastructure as a system, it could be argued that the humanities
            needs to look at its own existing and future infrastructure in systemic terms. Through
            arguing for a diversified but conceptually unified infrastructure, it may be possible to
            both match the epistemic scope of the humanities and incorporate elements that would be
            difficult to incorporate if the focus is on isolated pieces of equipment. For instance,
            if we see a centrally located seminar table as important to a planned instance of
            humanities infrastructure<note>We have mentioned three examples where such a table
              evidently plays an important role: ACTlab at the University of Texas <ptr target="#svensson2010"/>, Humanities Computing at University of Alberta <ptr target="#svensson2010"/>, and HUMlab (this article).</note>, it should be part of
            our conceptual framing and implementation. A diversified, but amalgated, infrastructure
            is also in line with a broad notion of infrastructure suggested by the ‘infrastructure
            turn’. Part II provided an example of how a specific humanities infrastructure can be
            packaged and unpackaged in this way. We will now look more closely at some aspects of
            packaging and implementing humanities cyberinfrastructure. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Some General Reflections</head>
               <p>In this article, it has been argued that it is vital that the humanities engage in
            conversations about research infrastructure and articulation of possible infrastructural
            needs. It seems reasonable to see the <term>infrastructure turn</term> as an important
            possibility for the humanities, but one laden with assumptions, political context and
            some risks. For instance, we need to be careful not to uncritically buy into a science
            and engineering paradigm or only using existing infrastructure, such as libraries, as a
            default model for new infrastructure. Articulating a humanities-based notion of
            cyberinfrastructure requires reflection and careful consideration, but also strategic
            action and interest in implementation. However, we also need to learn from each other
            and from disciplines and areas that have a strong infrastructural tradition <ptr target="#rockwell2010a"/>. </p>
               <p>It would seem sensible to let the process from idea to actual implementation take time
            given the often high cost of research infrastructure and the relative lack of
            established infrastructural framing for the humanities. Rockwell argues that we should
            support research infrastructure experiments <ptr target="#rockwell2010a"/>. Indeed,
            conceptual sketches, digital models, simulations and different kinds of prototyping are
            important tools in considering, testing, and evaluating suggested infrastructures.
            Mockups, structural diagrams and user trials can help thinking through a digital
            database tool, and a small-size lab installation can generate important knowledge for a
            planned large-scale installation. Moreover, a digital humanities laboratory or center
            can be seen as an experimental space or playground in itself. In the case of HUMlab,
            this has been manifested through having a wide variety of technologies and competencies
            available in the lab, and encouraging exploration and experimentation. </p>
               <p>One common assumption, sometimes even a defining criterion, evident in the discourse on
            cyberinfrastructure is that research infrastructure is distributed. Not just in the
            sense of data or tools being located elsewhere, but in the sense of a shared vision of a
            distributed research space. When discussing virtual organizations, Cummings et al. say
            that through coordinated infrastructure, <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#cummings2008">scientists and
                engineers can work together in environments that allow scientific integration,
                greater access, efficient problem solving, and competitive advantage</quote>
                     <ptr target="#cummings2008" loc="3"/>
                  </cit>. (The main title for their report is
            illustratively <title rend="quotes">Beyond Being There.</title>) Atkins et al. talk
            about distributed <quote rend="inline" source="#atkins2003">laboratories without walls</quote> as a major
            emergent development <ptr target="#atkins2003" loc="13"/>. Typically, work and data are
            not seen as simply distributed, but are said to require high capacity networks and
            distributed computing power. While most digital humanities infrastructures are
            distributed in one sense or another, it might be argued that physical space and local
            context can be quite important infrastructural components, and that we do not
            necessarily need to buy into a <soCalled>placeless,</soCalled> high-capacity and all-distributed sense
            of infrastructure. It could be claimed that the digital humanities operate across a
            spectrum of distributedness. Twitter, Zotero, Flickr and Second Life are all examples of
            distributed platforms that could be integrated in many digital humanities contexts as
            well as complex database systems, online tools, live shared visualizations and grid
            computing. While all of these elements can potentially be integrated in a physical lab
            or studio space, many will not. </p>
               <p>As we have noted, a related assumption is that technology included in
            cyberinfrastructure needs to be high-capacity, top-of-the-line and advanced. Grid
            computing is much more likely to be incorporated in this kind of discourse than, say,
            Zotero and non-massive datasets. The NSF Blue-ribbon report on cyberinfrastructure <ptr target="#atkins2003"/> contains 55 instances of the word <q>advanced</q> and 21
            instances of the collocation <q>advanced cyberinfrastructure.</q> It is
            pointed out that <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#atkins2003">[b]y advanced we mean both the
                highest-performing technology and its use in the most leading-edge
                research</quote>
                     <ptr target="#atkins2003" loc="5"/>
                  </cit> (original emphasis). This
            is an example of how certain expectations in fact define what is and what is not
            research infrastructure. While a platform such as Twitter may not match these
            expectations, it is worth carefully considering Matthew Kirschenbaum’s question:
                <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#kirschenbaum2010">Q: Has Twitter done more as DH cyberinfrastructure than
                any dedicated effort to date?</quote>
                     <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2010"/>
                  </cit>. The
            templates of cyberinfrastructure, however, can be tweaked and reframed if necessary. For
            example, through advocating for a varied and multiplex research infrastructure for the
            humanities, it may be possible to gain enough leverage for it to qualify as
            cyberinfrastructure, while not sacrificing many of the technologies and uses that may
            not qualify as research infrastructure by themselves.</p>
               <p>We will now briefly look at some issues that have been quite important to establishing
            HUMlab as infrastructure, which have more general applicability: the framing of
            cyberinfrastructure, the importance of owning the port, the humanities pushing the
            technological envelope and why we need to speak up.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Framing Humanities Cyberinfrastructure</head>
               <p>Funding is a central concern for most infrastructural projects. Here the humanities
            often find themselves in a position where sources of funding are mainly adapted to other
            areas. At one point, HUMlab attempted to apply for research infrastructure funding of a
            fairly traditional science and engineering kind although this focus was never made fully
            explicit. One problem in this application was matching the funding agency’s expectations
            of infrastructure with the planned implementation. For instance, the call in question
            made it clear that applications should be for functional units and that these units are
            normally quite costly (this category of funding was for expensive equipment). The type
            of infrastructure envisioned had some high-cost parts, but was much more diverse and
            distributed than what was clearly expected in this context – anchored in the idea of a
            fairly broadly conceived humanities and technology lab. The prototypical candidate for
            this kind of call was probably an expensive microscope, spectrometer or high performance
            computing unit; all functional and physical units of considerable cost. The application
            was not successful, but it was a useful exercise in that it made it clear to us that we
            needed to frame the cyberinfrastructure of the lab – not necessarily to conform with the
            expectations of the funding agencies, but rather to make a convincing argument for a
            different type of infrastructural need based on a different epistemic scope. The framing
            that developed from this process emphasized multiplexity (the need for many different
            kinds of perspectives, technology and infrastructure), local and distributed
            collaboration (partly through shared presence and materials), experimentation (the need
            to try infrastructure out together with humanists), openness (the infrastructure would
            attract humanities researchers but also many others) and a high degree of access to the
            infrastructure (24 hours all year).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Owning the Port</head>
               <p>There were some important decisions made at an early stage that shaped HUMlab’s basic
            infrastructure and that were also partly a result of good relations with the
            university-wide computer central. For instance, at the point at which HUMlab was started
            the most logical choice would probably have been to make the network proxy-based like in
            most of the student laboratories. However, this would have made the lab network more
            closed and it would have been difficult to make use of some software requiring specific
            network ports to be open (such as some virtual world software and some systems for
            streaming media). The fact that HUMlab was given the kind of network connection used in
            faculty and staff offices was important and allowed experimentation that would not have
            been possible, or at least difficult, otherwise. This particular issue would probably
            not be very relevant in relation to present-day installations, but there are many other
            choices and considerations that may similarly create obstacles or possibilities (some of
            which are so-called <soCalled>last mile</soCalled> problems). Some of them may seem like purely
            technical low-level considerations without any obvious <emph>content</emph> repercussions, but
            if possible, it is important to be involved in such decisions, and have people on board
            with a good sense of technical infrastructure as well as with an engagement in the
            humanities and the interface between the humanities and technology. </p>
               <p>Another low-level technology example concerns a rather inconspicuous metallic box
            mounted on one of the HUMlab walls. The box contains six pairs of optical fiber
            connected to the university computer central and the virtual reality lab. Without good
            support from the central university administration this installation would not have
            happened, and one general experience is that it is important to get as much done as
            possible at the point of installation. The box has never actually been used, although
            there were some fairly feeble attempts to connect HUMlab to the virtual reality
            laboratory at one point. Thus, this is clearly a failed investment on one level. The
            original rationale was for connecting high-level visualization facilities, and for
            future (largely undefined) use. Even though the connection has not been used in the 10
            years since it was installed, it might be argued that it has provided high-level
            bandwidth and connective possibilities (although unrealized). Of course this non-use is
            not optimal, but it can also be seen as part of providing a good base level
            infrastructure. There is also often a window of opportunity when initial investments and
            construction work are being done. Certain installations can often be done fairly easily
            done as part of a larger construction project. And when looking at future expansion
            plans and creating portals between HUMlab and HUMlab-X, and between HUMlab and several
            international digital humanities centers there has indeed been renewed interest in the
            dedicated optical fiber connection.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Conceptual Cyberinfrastructure and Humanities-based Technological Innovation</head>
               <p>Most digital humanities cyberinfrastructures are likely to incorporate technology to at
            least some, but often considerable, extent, and going from idea and concept to actual
            implementation is not always a simple or fast process. If all it takes is a number of
            standard workstations, or a standard database server, there will most likely not be a
            problem, but larger and non-standard installations are often complex. This is true
            generally speaking, and it is important to have a clear vision and to be able to
            communicate with technology experts in a dialogic and informed fashion. In the case of
            humanities infrastructures, which may be built on different epistemics, there may be
            problems that stem from the differentness of the envisioned installation. In such
            situations, it is quite important to be knowledgeable and communicative enough to be
            able to work the planning and implementation processes.</p>
               <p>Returning to the screenscape in HUMlab, this installation did not fit the template in
            several ways. For instance, the standard multiple screen scenario combines screens to
            create larger, seamless displays. Having screens spread out at the periphery of a large
            space is less common. Several participants in the design process argued in favor of one
            large screenscape which connected the screens seamlessly (rather than having them
            separate). Installing the 11 large screens was not a major technical problem, however,
            rather the complexity lay with how they are controlled and made accessible. Also, the
            screenscape included a 4K projector with very high resolution, which added an additional
            layer of complexity. The basic idea of rich contextualization, humanities-based
            representation and flexibility was implemented through a complex system where the total
            screenscape can be run through dedicated computers (one computer per screen), from one
            computer with an 11-screen desktop or through a video signal level system (where 24
            sources irrespective of type can be placed in the screenscape). This is obviously not an
            off-the-shelf system, and it is critical to be able to not lose track of epistemic
            grounding and the basic idea while discussing implementation with researchers, experts
            and others, and when carrying out the implementation. HUMlab’s screenscape is an example
            of a humanities infrastructural installation pushing the technical boundaries - and this
            is a recurring experience. When the head of one of the computer functions at the
            university described HUMlab at one point he said that it is the most interesting
            technology space on campus. The point here is that it is quite possible for the
            humanities to create a functional and highly visible platform, and that epistemic
            commitments of the humanities disciplines can make for interesting technological
            challenges that will often attract students and experts from the fields of technology
            and engineering.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Speaking Up</head>
               <p>Implementing large, and also often smaller, infrastructural projects in a university
            context is typically a fairly complicated processes with many people, competencies,
            sub-processes and different levels of decision and policy making involved. The degree of
            control and expected involvement depends on many different factors, but in any case,
            anyone involved in this kind of process as a main agent will have to take part in any
            number of meetings, negotiations and concerns about low-level technical and
            constructional details. Speaking up is important. Here design principles can be useful
            as a kind of intermediate language and, in the case of HUMlab, working with a 3D model
            of the planned new part of the lab turned out to be very useful. Partly because the
            model allowed the exploration of different possibilities, but also because the
            "finished" model served very well when planning the actual implementation with
            international experts, contractors, the property owner and university
            administration.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure04">
                  <head>Rendering of HUMlab from 2006 (based on a 3D model)</head>
                  <graphic url="...000090/resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc/>
               </figure>
               <p>In Figure 4, the right hand side of the visualization represents the existing part of
            the lab (as of the beginning of 2006) and left hand side represents the planned
            addition. The end result did not turn out quite as planned, but the basic conceptual
            grounding and the layout are very clear in the actual implementation. Apart from still
            visualizations, associated animations were also created, and these proved quite useful
            in general presentations of HUMlab and when discussing the project with funding
            agencies. </p>

               <p>As has been noted, seemingly small decisions can have significant impact. It is often
            useful to follow the implementation process quite closely and to talk to the people
            involved in the actual implementation (construction workers, engineer, programmers etc.)
            continuously. This allows you to ensure everyone has a sense of what the installation is
            about, learn from each other, and react if there are any misunderstandings. Sometimes
            there might be very different views on the impact of certain decisions. On one occasion
            in the planning of the new part of HUMlab, there was a meeting with most of the
            contractors, university administration and the property owner, where one point of
            disagreement was the new cooling and ventilation system for both parts of the lab. As
            mentioned previously, upgrades of existing infrastructure are often easier when you are
            doing new installations. </p>

               <p>The plan that had been decided on included partially lowering the ceiling in the old
            part of the lab. Even if this may seem like a fairly significant change, it had not been
            communicated verbally, and even if HUMlab had had access to the relevant drawings, they
            would have been difficult to decipher for laymen. The point here is that to the
            contractors this was not a major change. They needed to fit large pipes above the
            ceiling and the most reasonable way to do this would be to lower the ceiling – a matter
            of implementation. At this point, only the HUMlab representative (among 15 people) spoke
            up and articulated the importance of the varying ceiling heights of the lab, and how it
            would be very unfortunate to implement this change. The argument was not functional in a
            strict sense but rather aesthetic and about the energy and sense of the space. Through
            support from the university administration the contractors were asked to see if there
            were any alternative solutions (although it had been said earlier that there was only
            that one possibility). When the rationale had been communicated the contractors found an
            alternative solution, and eventually a way was found to keep the ceiling intact. Also,
            the intricacies of the ceiling scape (above the visible ceiling) became much clearer to
            the HUMlab representative.</p>

               <p>Another interesting point of negotiation concerned wallpapering four pillars with a
            green, leafy pattern in order to help create a sense of a room without the walls, where
            the proposal (partly a result of working with interior decorators) was deemed impossible
            or not suitable no less than three times. This may partly have been a gendered
            experience as the two interior decorators were women proposing an atypical use of
            wallpaper to a totally male dominated work and management group. The issue was resolved
            after HUMlab made it quite clear that the wallpaper was very important to the whole
            expansion. It turned out that one rationale for the initial unwillingness to wallpaper
            the pillars (for the workers) was that it would not be possible to do high-quality
            wallpapering on the round but multi-faceted pillars. Afterwards, everyone involved
            agreed on the success of the wallpapered pillars as concept and implementation. A
            general finding here is that intense collaboration and talking are critical, and that
            there is real value to clearly articulating what we, as part of the core operation of
            the university (research and teaching), need in order to carry out or work.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>Speaking up must be done on many levels. At a workshop on humanities cyberinfrastructure
          at UC Irvine in 2006, there was an appeal (or maybe request) from Dan Atkins, then head of
          the NSF Office of Cyberinfrastructure, that the humanities and social sciences step up and
          show leadership in relation to the issue of future cyberinfrastructure. This article can
          partly be seen as a response to this request in the sense of suggesting a model grounded
          in core humanities challenges, the conceptual cyberinfrastructure to tackle those
          challenges (if any), as well as in design principles and as exemplified in implemented
          cyberinfrastructure. We need to reflect critically on cyberinfrastructure, explore
          ideational and technological visions, and think about the future of the humanities. The
          call is arguably ours.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>I draw on dialogue and collaboration with a great many people, and I would like to
          particularly acknowledge extensive and valuable feedback from Matthew Ratto, Erica Robles,
          Jenna Ng and two anonymous DHQ reviewers. Stephanie Hendrick checked the text and
          argumentation carefully, and Emma Ewadotter assisted me with practical research issues.
          The article also benefited from feedback given after a talk at UCLA, Nov 10, 2009, hosted
          by Johanna Drucker and the Department of Information Studies.</p>

         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="atkins2003" label="Atkins et al. 2003" key="atkins2003">Aktins, Daniel E. et al. <title rend="italic">Revolutionizing Science and Engineering Through Cyberinfrastructure:
            Report of the National Science Foundation Blue-Ribbon Advisory Panel on
            Cyberinfrastructure</title>. National Science Foundation. <ref target="http://www.nsf.gov/od/oci/reports/atkins.pdf">http://www.nsf.gov/od/oci/reports/atkins.pdf</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bentkowska2007" label="Bentkowska-Kafel 2007" key="bentkowska2007">Bentkowska-Kafel, Anna. <title rend="quotes">Needs of the 3D Visualisation Community</title>, 3DVisA Report 2007 <ref target="http://3dvisa.cch.kcl.ac.uk/needs/3DVisA%20Report_Needs.pdf">http://3dvisa.cch.kcl.ac.uk/needs/3DVisA%20Report_Needs.pdf.</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="blackwell2009" label="Blackwell &amp; Crane 2009" key="blackwell2009b">Blackwell, Christopher
          and Gregory Crane. <title rend="quotes">Conclusion: Cyberinfrastructure, the Scaife
            Digital Library and Classics in a Digital age</title>. <title rend="italic"> Digital
            Humanities Quarterly</title> 3.1. <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/1/000035/000035.html">
            http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/1/000035/000035.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bolter2003" label="Bolter and Gromala 2003" key="bolter2003a">Bolter, Jay David and Diane
          Gromala. <title rend="italic">Windows and Mirrors: Interaction design, digital art, and
            the myth of transparency</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2003.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bonnett2008" label="Bonnett, Rockwell and Kuchmey 2008" key="bonnett2008">Bonnett, John,
          Rockwell, Geoffrey and Kyle Kuchmey. <title rend="quotes">High Performance Computing in
            the Arts and Humanities</title>. <ref target="http://www.sharcnet.ca/Documents/HHPC/hpcdh.html">
            http://www.sharcnet.ca/Documents/HHPC/hpcdh.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="borgman2007" label="Borgman 2007" key="borgman2007">Borgman, Christine L. <title rend="italic">Scholarship in the Digital Age: Information, Infrastructure and the Internet</title>.
          Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bowker2005" label="Bowker 2005" key="bowker2005">Bowker, Geoffrey C. <title rend="italic">Memory Practices in the Sciences</title> Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bowker1999" label="Bowker &amp; Leigh Star 1999" key="bowker1999">Bowker, Geoffrey C. and
          Susan Leigh Star. <title rend="italic">Sorting Things Out: Classification and its
            consequences</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1999.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brand1995" label="Brand 1995" key="brand1995">Brand, Stewart. <title rend="italic">How
            Buildings Learn: What happens after they're built</title>. New York: Penguin Books,
          1995. Originally published in 1994.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brooks1999" label="Brooks 1999" key="brooks1999">Brooks, Fredrick B. Jr. <title rend="quotes">What's Real About Virtual Reality?</title>
               <title rend="italic">IEEE Computer, Graphics and Applications, Special Report</title>.
          16-27. November/December 1999. <ref target="http://www.cs.unc.edu/~brooks/WhatsReal.pdf">
            http://www.cs.unc.edu/~brooks/WhatsReal.pdf.</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="buren2010" label="Buren 2010" key="buren2010">Buren, Daniel. <title rend="quotes">The Function
            of the Studio</title>, <title rend="italic">The Studio Reader: On the Space of
            Artists</title>. ed. Jacob, Mary Jane and Michelle Grabner, 156-162. Chicago: University
          of Chicago Press, 2010.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="burnette1994" label="Burnette et al. 1994" key="burnette1994">Burnette, Michaelyn, Gillis,
          Christina M. and Myrtis Cochran. <title rend="quotes">The Humanist and The Library:
            Promoting New Scholarship Through Collaborative Interaction Between Humanists and
            Librarians</title>. ed. Judy Reynolds, 181-191. <title rend="italic">Reference Services
            in the Humanities</title> New York: The Hayworth Press, 1994.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="colomina2001" label="Colomina 2001" key="colomina2001">Colomina, Beatriz. <title rend="quotes">Enclosed by images: The Easmeses' multimedia architecture</title>. <title rend="italic"> Grey Room</title>, 6-29. Volume 02 2001.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cummings2008" label="Cummings et al. 2008" key="cummings2008">Cummings, Jonathan, Finholt,
          Thomas, Foster, Ian, Kesselman, Carl and Katherine A. Lawrence. <title rend="quotes">Beyond Being There: A blueprint for advancing the design, development and evaluation of
            virtual organizations</title>. <title rend="italic">NSF Workshop to Identify Research,
            Infrastructure and Organizational Needs to Accelerate Collaboration in Science and
            Engineering.</title> Office of Cyberinfrastructure, National Science Foundation,
          2008.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="defanti2009" label="Defanti et al. 2009" key="defanti2009">Defanti, Thomas A. et al. <title rend="quotes">The OptIPortal, a scalable visualization, storage, and computing interface
            device for the OptiPuter</title>. <title rend="italic"> Future Generation Computer
            Systems</title>, 114-123. 25, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dourish1992" label="Dourish &amp; Bly 1992." key="dourish1992">Dourish, Paul and Sara Bly.
            <title rend="quotes">Portholes: Supporting Awareness in a Distributed Work
          Group</title>, <title rend="italic">SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing
            Systems</title>. 541-547. Monterey, CA, 1992.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2009" label="Drucker 2009" key="drucker2009b">Drucker, Johanna. <title rend="quotes">Blind Spots: Humanists must plan their digital future</title>, <title rend="italic">
            The Chronicle of Higher Education</title>. 3 April 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="edwards2009" label="Edwards et al. 2009" key="edwards2009">Edwards, Paul. N, Geoffrey C. Bowker,
          Steven J. Jackson, and Robin Williams. <title rend="quotes">Introduction: An Agenda for
            Infrastructure Studies</title>, <title rend="italic"> Journal of the Association for
            Information Systems</title>. 364-374. 10:5, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="erickson2000" label="Erickson &amp; Kellogg 2000" key="erickson2000">Erickson, Thomas and
          Wendy A. Kellogg. <title rend="quotes">Social translucence: an approach to designing
            systems that support social processes</title>, <title rend="italic">ACM Transactions on
            Computer-Human Interaction</title>. 50-83. 7:1, 2000.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="europeanroadmap2006" label="European Roadmap 2006" key="europeanroadmap2006">
               <title rend="quotes">Reports European Roadmap for Research Infrastructures Report 2006</title>. <title rend="italic">European Strategy Forum on Research Infrastructures</title>. Office for
          Official Publications of the European Communities: Luxembourg, 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="flanders2002" label="Flanders &amp; Unsworth 2002" key="flanders2002">Flanders, Julia and
          John Unsworth. <title rend="quotes">The Evolution of Humanities Computing Centers</title>.
            <title rend="italic"> Computers and the Humanities</title>. 379-380. 36, 2002.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="franklin2008" label="Franklin &amp; Rodriguez'G 2008" key="franklin2008">Franklin, Kevin and
          Karen Rodriguez'G. <title rend="quotes">The Next Big Thing in Humanities, Arts and Social
            Science Computing: Cultural Analytics</title>,<title rend="italic">HPCwire</title> 2008.
            <ref target="http://www.hpcwire.com/features/The_Next_Big_Thing_in_Humanities_Arts_and_Social_Science_Computing_Cultural_Analytics.html?page=4">
            http://www.hpcwire.com/features/The_Next_Big_Thing_in_Humanities_Arts_and_Social_Science_Computing_Cultural_Analytics.html?page=4</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="friedberg2006" label="Friedburg 2006" key="friedberg2006">Friedberg, Anne. <title rend="italic">The Virtual Window: From Alberti to Microsoft</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press,
          2006.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fallmann2007" label="Fällman 2007" key="fallmann2007">Fällman, Daniel. <title rend="quotes">Supporting Studio Culture in Design Research</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings
            of IASDR 2007, International Association of Societies of Design Research</title>. The
          Hong Kong Polytechnic University School of Design, Nov 12-15, 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gonsalvez2000" label="Gonsalvez &amp; Atchison 2000" key="gonsalvez2000">Gonsalvez, Christabel
          and Martin Atchison. <title rend="quotes">Implementing Studios for Experimental
            Learning</title>. <title rend="italic"> Proceedings of the Australasian conference on
            Computing Science Education</title>, 116-123. Vol 8, 2000.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="grafton2009" label="Grafton 2009" key="grafton2009">Grafton, Anthony. <title rend="italic">Worlds made by Words: Scholarship and Community in the Modern West</title>. Cambridge,
          MA: Harvard University Press, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="green2007" label="Green 2007" key="green2007">Green, David. <title rend="quotes">Cyberinfrastructure for Us All: An Introduction to Cyberinfrastructure and the Liberal
            Arts</title>. <title rend="italic"> Academic Commons.</title>
               <ref target="http://www.academiccommons.org/commons/essay/cyberinfrastructure-introduction">
            http://www.academiccommons.org/commons/essay/cyberinfrastructure-introduction.</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hass2001" label="HASS 2001" key="hass2001">HASS 2001. <title rend="quotes">HASS Committee on
            the Humanities Library, Final Report</title>. <title rend="italic"> Humanities Library
            Report</title>. MIT, 2001. <ref target="http://libraries.mit.edu/humlib/">
            http://libraries.mit.edu/humlib/.</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hey2008" label="Hey &amp; Trefethen 2008" key="hey2008">Hey, Tony and Trefethen, Anne.
            <title rend="quotes">E-Science, Cyberinfrastructure, and Scholarly
          Communication</title>, <title rend="italic">Scientific Collaboration on the
            Internet</title>, ed. Olsen, Gary, Zimmerman, Ann and Nathan Bos, 15-30. Cambridge, MA:
          MIT Press, 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="humlabblog2006" label="HUMLab Blog 2006" key="humlabblog2006">HUMLab Blog. <title rend="quotes">Matt Ratto seminar</title>. Blog entry, 12 December 2006. Accessed 8 September 2010.
            <ref target="http://blog.humlab.umu.se/?p=426">http://blog.humlab.umu.se/?p=426</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jamieson2000" label="Jamieson et al. 2000" key="jamieson2000"> Jamieson, P., Fisher, K. Gilding,
          T., Taylor, P., and Trevitt, A.C.F. <title>Place and space in the design of new learning
            environments</title>. <title rend="italic">Higher Education Research &amp;
            Development</title>, 221-236. 19(2), 2000.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2010" label="Kirschenbaum 2010" key="kirschenbaum2010b">Kirschenbaum, Matthew. <title rend="quotes">Q: Has Twitter done more as DH cyberinfrastructure than any dedicated
            effort to date?</title>. Twitter Post, 3 July 2010. <ref target="http://twitter.com/mkirschenbaum/status/17659459594">http://twitter.com/mkirschenbaum/status/17659459594</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lehmann2009" label="Lehmann 2009" key="lehmann2009">Lehmann, Ann-Sophie. <title rend="quotes">Invisible work: The representation of artistic practice in digital visual
            culture.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Visual Culture: Theory and
            Practice.</title> ed. Bentkowska-Kafel, Anna, Cashen, Trish and Hazel Gardiner, 33-45.
          Intellect Books: Bristol, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="livingstone2003" label="Livingstone 2003" key="livingstone2003">Livingstone, David. <title rend="italic">Putting Science in Its Place: Geographies of Scientific Knowledge</title>.
          Chicago University Press: Chicago, 2003.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="manovich1995" label="Manovich 1995" key="manovich1995">Manovich, Lev. <title rend="quotes">An
            Archeology of a Computer Screen</title>, <title rend="italic"> NewMedia Topia.</title>
          Soros Center for the Contemporary Art, Moscow, 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="martin2005" label="Martin 2005" key="martin2005">Martin, Reinhold. <title rend="italic">The
            Organizational Complex: Architecture, Media and Corporate Space</title>. Cambridge, MA:
          MIT Press, 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mccarthy2001" label="McCarthy 2001" key="mccarthy2001">McCarthy, Anna. <title rend="italic">Ambient Television: Visual Culture and Public Space</title>. Durham, NC: Duke
          University Press, 1999.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="merkel1999" label="Merkel 1999" key="merkel1999">Merkel, Cecilia. <title rend="quotes">Folkloristics of Educational Spaces: Material Lore in Classrooms with and without
            Walls</title>, <title rend="italic">Library Trends</title>, 417-438. Vol. 47, No. 3,
          1999.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="merriam2010" label="Merriam-Webster 2010" key="merriam2010">Merriam-Webster. <title rend="quotes">Infrastructure</title>, Accessed 14 May 2010.<ref target="http://mw4.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/infrastructure">
            http://mw4.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/infrastructure</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mitchell2003" label="Mitchell 2003" key="mitchell2003a">Mitchell, William. <title rend="quotes">Places for Learning: New Functions and New Forms</title>. Lecture at MIT, 2003.<ref target=" http://mitworld.mit.edu/video/69">
          http://mitworld.mit.edu/video/69.</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nsf2010" label="NSF2010" key="nsf2010">NSF 2010. <title rend="quotes">About Office of
            Cyberinfrastructure</title>. <title rend="quotes">About</title>, <title rend="italic">National Science Foundation: Office of Cyberinfrastructure (OCI)</title>. Accessed 8
          September 2010. <ref target="http://www.nsf.gov/od/oci/about.jsp">http://www.nsf.gov/od/oci/about.jsp</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ratto2006" label="Ratto 2006" key="ratto2006">Ratto, Matthew. <title rend="quotes">Epistemic
            commitments and archaeological representation</title>. <title rend="italic">XV Congrès
            de l’Union Internationale des Sciences Préhistoriques et Protohistoriques, J. Livre des
            Résumés Raposo</title>. ed. Oosterbeek L, p. 60. vol 1, 2006. <ref target="http://www.uispp.ipt.pt/UISPPprogfin/Livro2.pdf">
            http://www.uispp.ipt.pt/UISPPprogfin/Livro2.pdf</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rockwell2010a" label="Rockwell 2010" key="rockwell2010a">Rockwell, Geoffrey. <title rend="quotes">As Transparent as Infrastructure: On the research of cyberinfrastructure in the
            humanities</title>, ed. McGann, Jerome. <title rend="italic">Online Humanities
            Scholarship: The Shape of Things to Come</title>. Rice University Press. <ref target="http://rup.rice.edu/cnx_content/shape/m34315.html">
            http://rup.rice.edu/cnx_content/shape/m34315.html. </ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rockwell2010b" label="Rockwell &amp; Meredith-Lobay 2010" key="rockwell2010b">Rockwell,
          Geoffrey and Megan Meredith-Lobay. <title rend="quotes">Mind the Gap: A multidisciplinary
            workshop bridging the gap between High Performance Computing and the Humanities</title>,
            <title rend="italic">Draft Report 3.0</title>. Prepared with the help of Jeff Antoniak
          and Jon Johansson. <ref target="https://docs.google.com/View?id=dhbw7427_4hnbkr8cd">
            https://docs.google.com/View?id=dhbw7427_4hnbkr8cd.</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="roper1991" label="Roper 1991" key="roper1991">Roper, John P. G. <title rend="quotes">The New
            Humanities Workstation</title>. <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic
            Computing</title>, 131-133. Vol. 6, No. 2, 1991.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="russett2009" label="Russett 2009" key="russett2009">Russett, Robert. <title rend="italic">Hyperanimation: Digital Images and Virtual Worlds</title>. New Barnet, U.K.: John
          Libbey Publishing, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sterne2005" label="Sterne 2005" key="sterne2005">Sterne, Jonathan. <title rend="quotes">Digital
            Media and Disciplinarity</title>, <title rend="italic">The Information Society</title>,
          249-256. 21.4, 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="svensson2003" label="Svensson 2003" key="svensson2003">Svensson, Patrik. <title rend="quotes">Virtual worlds as arenas for language learning</title>. <title rend="italic">Language
            Learning Online: Towards best practice</title>. ed. Felix Uschi, 123-142. Lisse: Swets
          &amp; Zeitlinger, 2003.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="svensson2009" label="Svensson 2009" key="svensson2009">Svensson, Patrik. <title rend="quotes">Humanities computing as digital humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital
            Humanities Quarterly</title>, 3:3 (2009). <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/3/000065/000065.html.">http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/3/000065/000065.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="svensson2010" label="Svensson 2010" key="svensson2010">Svensson, Patrik. <title rend="quotes">The
            Landscape of Digital Humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
            Quarterly</title>, 4:1 (2010). <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/1/000080/000080.html">http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/4/1/000080/000080.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="src2007" label="Swedish Research Council 2007" key="src2007">Swedish Research Council 2007
            <title rend="quotes">Samhällen och kulturer i förändring. Ämnesrådet för humaniora och
            samhällsvetenskaps underlag till Vetenskapsrådets forskningsstrategi 2009–2012</title>,
            <title rend="italic">The Strategic Plan for the Swedish Research Council 2009-2012:
            Humanities and Social Sciences.</title> Swedish Research Council, 2007. <ref target="http://www.vr.se/download/18.61c03dad1180e26cb878000459/Strategi+HS+2007.pdf">
            http://www.vr.se/download/18.61c03dad1180e26cb878000459/Strategi+HS+2007.pdf.</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="terras2009" label="Terras 2009" key="terras2009a">Terras, Melissa. <title rend="quotes">Making a
            Difference </title>. <title rend="italic">Humanist Discussion Group</title> Humanist
          23.192 (2009). <ref target="http://lists.digitalhumanities.org/pipermail/humanist/2009-July/000622.html">http://lists.digitalhumanities.org/pipermail/humanist/2009-July/000622.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="turner2005" label="Turner 2005" key="turner2005">Turner, Fred. <title rend="quotes">Where the
            Counterculture Met The New Economy: The WELL and the Origins of Virtual
            Community</title>. <title rend="italic"> Technology and Culture</title>, 485-512.
          Vol.46, No.3, July 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="turner2009" label="Turner 2009" key="turner2009">Turner, Fred. <title rend="quotes">Burning Man
            at Google: a cultural infrastructure for new media production</title>, <title rend="italic">New Media &amp; Society</title>, 73-94. 11, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="unsworth2006" label="Unsworth et al. 2006" key="unsworth2006"> Unsworth, John et al. <title rend="quotes">Our Cultural Commonwealth: The report of the American Council of Learned
            Societies Commission on Cyberinfrastructure for the Humanities and Social
            Sciences</title>, <title> The ACLS Report</title>, 2006. <ref target="http://www.acls.org/uploadedFiles/Publications/Programs/Our_Cultural_Commonwealth.pdf">
            http://www.acls.org/uploadedFiles/Publications/Programs/Our_Cultural_Commonwealth.pdf.</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="williams2008" label="Williams 2008" key="williams2008">Williams, Rosalind. <title rend="italic">Notes on the Underground: An Essay on Technology, Society, and the Imagination</title>.
          Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2008.</bibl>

         </listBibl>

      </back>
  </text>
</TEI>