<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Playing with Identities: Queering Digital Narratology and the
                    Exploration of Gender and Sexual Identities</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Calvin <dhq:family>Fung</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Monash University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>calvin.fung@monash.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Calvin Fung is currently pursuing a PhD in Creative Writing. His thesis
                            includes a creative component in the form of a Gothic novel set in Hong
                            Kong and a critical component examining the way in which the cultural
                            specificity of Hong Kong interacts with the Gothic genre to extend the
                            postcolonial Gothic and Asian Gothic spectra. His research interests
                            include interdisciplinary narratology, Gothic literary studies and
                            postcolonial studies.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000331</idno>
                <idno type="volume">011</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2017-09-26">26 September 2017</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>game studies</item>
                        <item>gender studies</item>
                        <item>queer theory</item>
                        <item>narrative studies</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2018-07-03" who="DD">Validation Check</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p> This study builds upon previous research that discusses gender and sexual
                    identities and digital narratives by introducing a queer narratological approach
                    to character creation mechanics. First, Lisa Nakamura’s identity tourism and
                    narratological constructs are applied to formalize the concept of the
                    exploration in digital narratives. Second, exploration of gender and sexual
                    identities is demonstrated through a queer narratological analysis of two
                    digital narratives, <title rend="italic">Always Sometimes Monsters</title>
                    (2014) and <title rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title> (2016). Third, the
                    development of character creation mechanics in <title rend="italic">The
                        Sims</title> (2000-2016) series is examined to reflect the advancement
                    toward progressive game designs. Concerns regarding a sexuality blind approach
                    and the downplaying of homophobia are addressed, and Helene Cixous’s
                    poststructuralist <q>other bisexuality</q> as
                    a transgressive product of the fluidity of identities in digital narratives is
                    emphasized. This study elaborates the often-disregarded workings of queer
                    narratology and theory in digital narratives or game designs.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Introduces a queer narratologial approach to character creation mechanics.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <epigraph>
                    <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#cavendish2004">[A]nd if any should like the
                            world I have made, and be willing to be my subjects, they may imagine
                            themselves such, and they are such, I mean, in their minds, fancies or
                            imaginations; but if they cannot endure to be subjects, they may create
                            worlds of their own, and govern themselves as they please.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#cavendish2004" loc="224–225"/>
                    </cit>
                </epigraph>
                <p>So ends Margaret Cavendish, the Duchess of Newcastle’s <title rend="italic">The
                        Description of a New World, Called The Blazing World</title> first published
                    in 1666 and, as can be seen, the idea of imagining into existence a world of
                    one’s own through narrative is no novel one. In the digital age, however,
                    digital narratives give their readers or players an extra degree of freedom to
                    imagine and explore in narrative worlds with the interactivity that is
                    introduced. This article focuses on how digital narratives allow their players
                    to explore their gender and sexual identities.<note> Research for this project
                        was done with funding from the Australian Government Research Training
                        Program Scholarship.</note></p>
                <p>Previous studies on sexuality and video games often quote Bastal <ptr
                        target="#bastal2011a"/>
                    <ptr target="#bastal2011b"/>, a <title rend="italic">Dragon Age 2</title>
                    <ptr target="#EA2011"/> player who posted on BioWare’s social forum, lamenting
                    vehemently over the video game designer’s choice to make the game so appealing
                    to women and gays, especially when he believes that female and queer gamers
                    occupy less than 10 percent of the entire gaming population. In less than 12
                    hours, his first thread received 420 replies. The criticism of the inclusive
                    game design in the <title rend="italic">Dragon Age</title> series continued,
                    however. Three years later, in June 2014, five months before the sequel, <title
                        rend="italic">Dragon Age: Inquisition</title>
                    <ptr target="#EA2014a"/>, was released, another thread regarding the proposed
                    romance dynamics in the upcoming game and its frightful marginalizing
                    homosexuality was created by a player under the name of <q>Duncaaaaaan</q>:<cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#duncaaaaan2014">I am white, straight, and male.
                            Are you upset by this, bioware? [sic] Am I wrong for being white and
                            straight and male? No, of course not, I didn't ask to be born this way
                            and to insult somebody for their race, gender and orientation is
                            extremely bigoted. … It looks to me that bioware [sic] is trying to
                            marginalize core gamers (men in their late teens and beyond) in favour
                            of getting the support of the LGBT community and women, in regards to
                            the character design and story.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#duncaaaaan2014"/>
                    </cit> In less than three hours, the thread received 121 replies. The continued
                    criticism of major video game companies and their inclusion of
                    non-heteronormative practices reflect a resistance toward game designs that
                    challenge traditional gender roles and beliefs and attitudes toward sexual
                    orientations. This article examines the character creation designs of digital
                    narratives from a queer narratological perspective to propose that character
                    creation mechanics can situate the player in an environment where
                    heteronormativity is marginalized in favor of a poststructuralist understanding
                    of gender and sexuality, where players are given the freedom to explore their
                    gender and sexual identities.</p>
                <p>In digital narratives, the ability to play as multiple gender or sexual
                    identities has been seen as the liberation from an essentialist sexed body <ptr
                        target="#nguyen2003"/>, evidence of inclusion by video game companies <ptr
                        target="#condis2015"/> or even an instance of sexuality blindness <ptr
                        target="#greer2013"/>. But the narrative techniques and narratological
                    ideologies that underpin the relationship between sexuality and digital
                    narratives have rarely been studied. To study how digital narratives allow for
                    the exploration of the player’s gender and sexual identities, what exploration
                    is in cyberspace is first established. This is achieved by a review of how
                    identity tourism as a cybercultural construct has been discussed and can be
                    adapted to an understanding of exploration. The requirements for exploration to
                    occur in digital narratives are explicated. Then, the character creation
                    mechanics of two digital narratives in the form of a role-playing game (RPG),
                        <title rend="italic">Always Sometimes Monsters</title>
                    <ptr target="#VagabondDog2014"/>, and visual novel, <title rend="italic">Hustle
                        Cat</title>
                    <ptr target="#DateNighto2016"/> are presented, and an analysis is offered on how
                    their designs allow for an exploration of gender identities and confront players
                    with multiple, conflicting sexual identities through the emergent non-linearity
                    and parallelism of plot structures. Subsequently, in light of the recent <title
                        rend="quotes">Gender Customization Options</title> update to <title
                        rend="italic">The Sims 4</title>
                    <ptr target="#EA2014b"/>, the changes in attitudes toward gender as reflected by
                    the modifications of character creation functions throughout the <title
                        rend="italic">Sims</title> franchise are discussed. The transgressive gender
                    and sexuality configurations produced by the designs of the digital narratives
                    are related to Hélène Cixous’s <quote rend="inline" source="#cixous1976">other
                        bisexuality</quote> to defend against claims of sexuality blindness or a
                    downplaying of the experiences of members of the queer community.</p>
                <p>Before proceeding, the specific usage of certain terms in this article — namely
                    sex, gender, gender identity and sexual identity — must first be clarified.
                    Adapted from GLAAD <ptr target="#GLAAD2011"/> and the American Psychological
                    Association <ptr target="#APA2016"/>, briefly, sex is viewed as more
                    biologically determined than gender, gender identity is understood to be an
                    experienced self that may or may not be different from the assigned sex, and
                    sexual identity is regarded as an orientation or sexual preference typically
                    toward a class of sex.<note> There are significant differences between GLAAD’s
                        and the APA’s definition of one’s sexual orientation. GLAAD’s definition is
                        more general in that sexual orientation is seen as any attraction to another
                        person, whereas the APA’s definition specifies that said attraction be
                        toward a sex.</note> Throughout this article, the reader, player and main
                    character of each narrative will be referred to in the third person because at
                    the heart of the argument in this article lies the conviction that within the
                    digital narrative environment, the reader, the player and main characters’
                    genders (and consequently sexualities) are made fluid by narratives that disturb
                    gender binaries.</p>
                <p>Research on on-screen bodies and their reaction with the interactor’s gender and
                    sexual identities has predominantly been involved with multi-user dungeons or
                    MUDs. These are typically text-based virtual worlds, where users engage in
                    synchronous interaction with other users and the virtual environment. Lisa
                    Nakamura <ptr target="#nakamura1995"/> discusses <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#nakamura1995">netsex</quote> practices by white males who use
                    Asian stereotypes in their online fantasies. Gender and MUDs have been studied
                    extensively <ptr target="#fanderclai1996"/>
                    <ptr target="#kendall1996"/>, and the features of MUDs that gave people over the
                    internet a chance to interact with new textual realities have been thoroughly
                    examined. Sherry Turkle’s <ptr target="#turkle1995"/> book-long study and
                    Shannon McRae’s <ptr target="#mcrae1996"/> essay discuss the sexual experiences
                    and thoughts regarding gender and sexuality from interviews with users of MUDs.
                    The detailed qualitative data from both studies suggest that, having explored in
                    the virtual world of the MUD, users found their conceptions about themselves or
                    how sexuality works changed. </p>
                <p>That the complicated depth of the virtual world of MUDs can be an environment
                    where users can explore their identities is not being contested. However,
                    membership in the online MUD community has declined. On 9 September 2017, I
                    visited one of the major MUDs, <title rend="italic">LambdaMOO</title>, and found
                    that there was little activity — there were a total of 56 players, and only 7 of
                    which were marked as recently active. Research on digital media and sexual
                    experimentation and orientation need to now consider forms of more accessible
                    media. Both Turkle <ptr target="#turkle1995"/> and McRae <ptr
                        target="#mcrae1996"/> acknowledge that people who wish to enter an MUD need
                    some basic knowledge of coding or at least a willingness to learn it. That
                    digital narratives in the form of video games are much easier to install, engage
                    with and disseminate realize and amplify their exploratory function as a greater
                    gaming audience is reached. One of the key outcomes of the proliferation and
                    increased consumption of gaming content that encourages exploration is that the
                    needs of the traditional gamer demographic will be revised for the previously
                    marginalized gaming community. This will become even more evident as video game
                    companies begin to recognize that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#shaw2009">even heterosexual, traditionally
                            gendered gamers may want to play with sexuality and gender in video
                            games</quote>
                        <ptr target="#shaw2009" loc="239"/>
                    </cit>. Further, unlike single-player video games, the sexual encounters on MUDs
                    occur between players, and without any other players online to interact with,
                    experimentation would not be possible — which becomes problematic given the
                    declining MUD community. One of the primary differences between MUDs and the
                    video games studied in this article is that MUDs are more reliant on other
                    players than the author-created environment to form a narrative. In the digital
                    narratives discussed here, interaction with other players in-game is either
                    optional or impossible. Experimentation with gender identities and sexuality in
                    video games is studied as a result of the interaction between the player and a
                    more pre-determined narrative structure and environment.</p>
                <p>From Janet Murray’s <ptr target="#murray1998"/> endorsement of a narratological
                    approach to video games to Gonzalo Frasca’s <ptr target="#frasca2003"/>
                    introduction of a ludological approach, there has been debate as to which
                    methodology and conceptual framework would be more appropriate for studying
                    video games.<note> Oliver Laas’s chapter, <title rend="quotes">Narratives in
                            Digital Games: Their Place and Function in the Study of Digital
                            Games,</title> in <title rend="italic">Expanding Practices in
                            Audiovisual Narrative</title> (2014) provides a good summary of the
                        narratological versus ludological debate.</note> This article does not
                    intend to resolve the debate, but introduces yet another lens through which to
                    view video games — a queer narratological approach. Queer narratology was first
                    employed by Susan Lanser <ptr target="#lanser1995"/> in her seminal article,
                        <title rend="quotes">Sexing the Narrative: Propriety, Desire, and the
                        Engendering of Narratology</title>, and responds to the lack of attention
                    given to sexuality and queer identities in the study of narrative. She reads
                    Jeanette Winterson’s novel, <title rend="italic">Written on the Body</title>,
                    and examines the omission of a protagonist’s sex and gender identity as a
                    narrative technique that prompts questions about the relationship between
                    narration and queer representations. The burgeoning discipline has been
                    gradually receiving more attention with Warhol and Lanser's edited collection
                        <ptr target="#warhol2015"/>, but it is still evident that more has to be
                    said about how narrative theory and representations of queerness are
                    inextricably related. Mia Consalvo’s <ptr target="#consalvo2003"/> landmark
                    study talks about how non-heteronormative sexualities are presented in the first
                        <title rend="italic">The Sims</title>
                    <ptr target="#EA2000"/> game. Her findings, which will be discussed later, can
                    demonstrate the great changes that have happened over a decade after her study
                    to the portrayal of sexualities and gender identities in both <title
                        rend="italic">The Sims</title> series and other video games.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Exploration and Identity Tourism</head>
                <p>Lisa Nakamura’s <ptr target="#nakamura1995"/> identity tourism is where the
                    conceptualization of exploration in a digital context comes from. She first used
                    it as a metaphor <quote rend="inline" source="#nakamura2008">to describe the
                        activity of racial identity appropriation, or <q>passing</q> in
                        cyberspace</quote>. Terms such as <q>passing</q> or <q>identity tourism</q>
                    have been used predominantly in discussions of racial identity, and in American
                    history, passing is associated with a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ginsberg1996">discourse of racial difference
                            and especially with the assumption of a fraudulent <q>white</q> identity
                            by an individual culturally and legally defined as <q>Negro</q> or
                            black</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ginsberg1996" loc="3"/>
                    </cit>. Nakamura <ptr target="#nakamura2008" loc="1675"/> notes that identity
                    tourism is often performed by men who seek <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#nakamura2008">netsex</quote> and can be a process by which <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#nakamura2008">users <soCalled>wear</soCalled>
                        racially stereotyped avatars without feeling racist</quote>. If we refer to
                    this as racial identity tourism, gender and sexual identity tourism is the act
                    of wearing different avatars of varying gender identities and sexualities. While
                    racial identity tourism has been understood in a negative light, Mimi Nguyen
                        <ptr target="#nguyen2003" loc="288"/> has adapted the term to sexual
                    identities to show its transgressive capabilities. She argues that sexual
                    identity tourism renders the digital space into a <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#nguyen2003">liberatory space, disrupting the social determinism of
                        the body from the identifications of the self</quote>, where genders and
                    sexualities can be constructed and reconstructed by players at will through, for
                    example, character creation. Nguyen contributes to the already robust discussion
                    of how the digital space achieves poststructuralist philosophies of gender and
                    sexuality, but the exploratory element of identity tourism, ironically, has not
                    received much attention. In a study of users’ experiences on online MUDs,
                    Shannon McRae <ptr target="#mcrae1996" loc="249"/> notes that gender swapping in
                    virtual space can be <quote rend="inline" source="#mcrae1996">motivated by a
                        sense of self-exploration, to see what sex is like from a different point of
                        view</quote>. Through this process, she continues, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mcrae1996">we can experience for ourselves,
                            inside ourselves, the kinds of things that we associate with female or
                            male, and realize that those aspects are not, after all, something Other
                            and outside of us</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mcrae1996" loc="253"/>
                    </cit>. This act of exploring by <quote rend="inline" source="#mcrae1996"
                        >identity touristing</quote> with the possibility of discovering things
                    previously unknown about the self forms the understanding of exploration in this
                    article.</p>
                <p>Nakamura’s metaphor of <quote rend="inline" source="#nakamura2008"
                        >wearing</quote> an avatar is a starting point for discussing how the
                    exploration happens as a product of identity tourism. However, I argue that the
                    metaphor is insufficient to explain exploration because exploration is an
                    introspective process that requires players to go beyond <emph>wearing</emph>
                    other identities to <emph>being</emph> other identities. There must be a
                    temporary adoption of the digital body’s identity (the digital body as the
                    avatar or player-controlled character) by the real body such that the experience
                    of the digital body can be internalized by the real body and thus modify
                    players’ conceptions of themselves. Agency in a digital narrative has been seen
                    as what combines the real body and the digital body on-screen. Katherine Hayles
                        <ptr target="#hayles2008" loc="17"/> offers a description of this agency as
                    the alternation between <quote rend="inline" source="#dovey2006">top-down
                        approach to narrative in which the narrator spins a story, and the bottom-up
                        model of interactivity in which the user chooses how the story will be
                        told</quote>. This alternation forms what Dovey and Kennedy <ptr
                        target="#dovey2006" loc="109"/> would refer to as the <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#dovey2006">cybernetic loop</quote>, that which makes it so that
                    the <quote rend="inline" source="#dovey2006">player and the game are
                        inseparable for the duration of the game</quote> and transforms the real
                    body of the player into a cyborg, <quote rend="inline" source="#dovey2006">a
                        subjectivity that depends precisely on this collapse of boundary between the
                        human and the machine</quote>. However, how it is that players can adopt the
                        <emph>identity</emph> of their character or avatar must also be
                    addressed.</p>
                <p>If a player is to experience a merge between the identities, then the player must
                        <emph>believe</emph> that such a merge can happen. Concepts such as
                    immersion, what Janet Murray <ptr target="#murray1998" loc="98"/> terms the
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#murray1998">sensation of being surrounded
                        by a completely other reality</quote>, Roland Barthes’s <ptr
                        target="#barthes1989"/>
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#barthes1989">the reality effect</quote>, and
                    realism in general are related to whether this belief is possible. The crux of
                    this issue is, however, whether players can believe that they are an Italian
                    plumber called Mario trying to save Princess Peach of Mushroom Kingdom. Despite
                    the sometimes large physical, psychological, or mental differences between the
                    real body and the digital body, the player can comfortably negotiate these
                    distances and assume the identity of a digital persona. Katherine Angel Cross
                        <ptr target="#angelcross2012"/> has cited pretend play, role playing, and
                    imagination as processes that occur when someone takes on a digital identity,
                    but Peter J. Rabinowitz’s <ptr target="#rabinowitz1977" loc="126–134"/> analysis
                    of narratological audiences provides a more structural approach to this
                    phenomenon. Rabinowitz states that there are four audiences: (1) actual audience
                    — the flesh-and-blood person who reads; (2) authorial audience — the
                    hypothetical reader for whom the author writes; (3) narrative audience — the
                    audience that accepts the fictional world in which the story happens; and (4)
                    ideal narrative audience — the audience by which the narrator, not the author,
                    wishes to be read. Only when players are able to become the appropriate
                    narrative audience — those willing to accept a reality in which they are
                    occupants in a digital, fictional world for the duration of the narrative — can
                    their players adopt the identities of their digital bodies. When the digital
                    body or world is so incompatible with the norms of players that they cannot or
                    refuse to believe they can adopt the identity of their digital body, their role
                    is then more like that of a voyeur controlling and observing an on-screen
                    subject. Pretend play, role play or imagination are then processes by which
                    Rabinowitz’s narrative audience is adopted. Unless players come to change their
                    mind about their digital presence or world, exploration cannot occur because
                    then the distance between the player and their avatar or character becomes so
                    great that the player is not <soCalled>being</soCalled> or even
                        <soCalled>wearing</soCalled> any digital identity.</p>
                <p>The ability to create a character in digital narratives cements the relationship
                    between the players and their digital bodies. Catherine Gallagher <ptr
                        target="#gallagher2006" loc="351"/> makes some noteworthy observations about
                    the fictionality of characters in novels and the emotional attachment between
                    the character and the reader. Readers are attached to fictional characters not
                    in spite of their fictionality but precisely because of it — the fictional
                    setting establishes <quote rend="inline" source="#gallagher2006">a protected
                        affective enclosure that [encourages] risk-free emotional
                    investment</quote>. That the personality exists only in the boundaries of the
                    narrative without <quote rend="inline" source="#gallagher2006">extratextual
                        baggage</quote> means that the reader can be immersed in the experience,
                    identifying with and investing in only the presented individuals. A character’s
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#gallagher2006">peculiar affective
                        force</quote>, Gallagher proposes, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#gallagher2006">is generated by the mutual
                            implication of their unreal knowability and their apparent depth, the
                            link between their real nonexistence and the reader’s experience of them
                            as deeply and impossibly familiar</quote>
                        <ptr target="#gallagher2006" loc="356–357"/>
                    </cit>. Gallagher is primarily referring to characters in novels, but the
                    players in creating their characters in digital narratives would seem to
                    strengthen their bonds toward them. First, by creating a character, one is
                    effectively responsible for its existence. In novels, according to Mieke Bal’s
                    character effect, the illusion of an identity is created. This identity is
                    conceivable only on the textual level as represented by the author. In digital
                    narratives, the character created is a product of both the agency of the player
                    and the author’s systems and rules so that the impenetrability of a character in
                    a novel is less applicable to a character in an electronic setting in which
                    players contribute to the presence of <emph>their</emph> on-screen personality.
                    The players personalize their characters in a way that renders them knowable
                    only to the players themselves, and the imaginary status of a character is no
                    longer imaginary because the players are able to identify parts of their
                    characters’ being as originating from themselves. This relationship between the
                    character and its creator helps situate the player within the narrative
                    audience, and the exploration of one’s identity can be seen as a capitalization
                    on the cyborgian inseparability of players and their creations.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Exploring in Queer Worlds: <title rend="italic">Always Sometimes
                        Monsters</title> and <title rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title></head>
                <p><title rend="italic">Always Sometimes Monsters</title> (henceforth <title
                        rend="italic">ASM</title>) was released in May 2014 by Vagabond Dog and has
                    since received over 1,000 reviews on Steam, most of which were <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#ValveCorporation2017a">very positive</quote>, and
                    awards for Best Writing and Best Indie Game from the Canadian Videogame Awards
                    in 2014 <ptr target="#ValveCorporation2017a"/>. The narrative starts with a
                    brief introductory sequence, after which there is a scene at a party where the
                    player selects the characters. Then, the game progresses one year in game time,
                    and the protagonist is shown to be living a life in squalor because of career
                    issues and, most importantly, because they broke up with their partner. The
                    protagonist receives an invitation to a wedding between this partner and someone
                    else, and the main conflict of the narrative and objective of the game is
                    presented — the protagonist must survive and pass through two cities to reach
                    the wedding ceremony to win their lover back with little funds to spare.
                    Depending on the players’ choices, and assuming that their character survives,
                    they are either successful or unsuccessful in stopping the wedding and getting
                    back with their partner.</p>
                <p>Character creation in <title rend="italic">ASM</title> happens in the party
                    scene, where players control the host of the party and talk to the partygoers.
                    Whomever players make the host talk to becomes their avatar. <figure
                        xml:id="figure01">
                        <head>Screenshot of the scene where the player selects a character. Circled
                            in red is the host that is controlled. Taken on May 19, 2016.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
                    </figure> Most of the characters seen in <ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>,
                    besides the host, can be chosen to be the protagonist. After this selection
                    process, the player controls the protagonist and goes out onto the patio where
                    the lover of the protagonist can be selected. <figure xml:id="figure02">
                        <head>Screenshot of the scene where players select the lover of their
                            protagonist. Circled in red is the character that has been taken control
                            of. Taken on May 19, 2016.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
                    </figure> Again, most of the characters in <ref target="#figure02">Figure
                        2</ref> can be selected as the protagonist’s lover, and after this the
                    player gives the protagonist and their lover names. The player is free to select
                    whatever sex the protagonist or the lover is but, at this point, the expressed
                    gender always corresponds to the assigned sex.</p>
                <p>Research on the player’s freedom to choose an avatar’s sex or gender has
                    discussed this as some form of resistance against the privileged, straight white
                    male gamer, or as a step toward a liberal feminist philosophy. Nielsen <ptr
                        target="#nielsen2015" loc="49"/> argues that in some RPGs when the
                    characters’ sex or sexuality <quote rend="inline" source="#nielsen2015">does
                        not directly hinder characters’ abilities in the game world</quote>, the
                    design of the game conforms to a liberal feminist ideology. This understanding
                    of sex and gender presupposes that gender identities are stable. Perhaps this is
                    because, in scholarship on video games, character creation is seen as a gameplay
                    element that occupies typically the starting sequences of a game, and
                    characters’ sex and gender are understood as subsequently fixed throughout the
                    rest of the game. However, each playable character in <title rend="italic"
                        >ASM</title> is a tabula rasa distinguishable only by the appearance of
                    their avatar, and the choices the player makes to modify this character
                    throughout the narrative reminds us that character creation or characterization
                    is a continuous process. It was mentioned that the expressed gender in <title
                        rend="italic">ASM</title> corresponds to the assigned sex; however, in the
                    final sequence of the game, the wedding ceremony scene, the protagonist is able
                    to have a conversation with a transgender character. This character asks the
                    protagonist a question about their views on gender identity, to which the
                    protagonist may respond that they are transgender, their lover is transgender,
                    they <q>find it gross</q> or they
                    are <q>fine with it</q>. The
                    answer to this question does not affect the plot but can affect players’
                    conception of their protagonist’s gender identity both retroactively and for
                    every future read-through of the narrative. The introduction of a transgender
                    identity distinguishes sex from gender identities and provides players with the
                    opportunity to explore the gender identities generated from a permutation of
                    assigned sexes and experienced genders in a digital narrative. Gender identities
                    and characterization in general in digital narratives should be recognized as
                    fluid and continuously shaped by the narrative and the decisions made by players
                    if the full potential of exploration and identity tourism is to be examined.</p>
                <p><title rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title> was released in March 2016 by DateNighto
                    and has garnered 360 reviews on Steam, with an overall rating of <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ValveCorporation2017b">very positive</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ValveCorporation2017b"/>
                    </cit>. Although it is an RPG, classifying it as a visual novel (not to be
                    confused with the graphic novel) would be more accurate. The visual novel
                    originated in Japan <ptr target="#cavallaro2010"/> but the manga/anime art style
                    seen predominantly in this genre has been adapted by Western cultures, as in
                        <title rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title>; though there has been little
                    academic attention to this genre. Lebowitz and Klug <ptr target="#lebowitz2011"
                        loc="193"/> argue that <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#lebowitz2011">only a handful of visual novels have been
                        released outside the country</quote>, but the genre is in fact quickly
                    gaining popularity outside of Japan. On Steam, there are over 700 games with a
                        <q>Visual Novel</q> tag <ptr target="#ValveCorporation2017d"/>. Lebowitz and
                    Klug <ptr target="#lebowitz2011" loc="194"/> state that it is similar to the
                    choose-your-own-adventure style of narrative and that, most importantly, <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#lebowitz2011">they don’t face the length restrictions
                        found in physical books</quote>. The large amount of branches and complex
                    plots in visual novels require large word counts that are more easily achievable
                    with a digital medium. In Marie-Laure Ryan’s <ptr target="#ryan2009"/> terms,
                    the visual novel, would be considered a <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#ryan2009">playable story</quote> rather than a <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#ryan2009">narrative game</quote>, but the visual
                    novel, as a digital product, is composed of more complex non-linear plots,
                    gameplay functions and audio-visual elements. In the visual novel, the reader is
                    told the narrative predominantly through text and there are junctions in the
                    narrative where the player must decide which option to choose (see <ref
                        target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref>). The route and endings change according
                    to the choices. <figure xml:id="figure03">
                        <head>Screenshot of a narrative junction in <title rend="italic">Hustle
                                Cat</title>. Taken on May 19, 2016.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
                    </figure> The protagonist of <title rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title> is Avery
                    Grey, a young adult who takes a job at a cat café. It turns out that the café is
                    cursed by a spell that turns all its employees into cats when they leave the
                    café. How Avery breaks the curse for the employees at the café is the main
                    storyline. If Avery does not die, Avery always ends up with one of the
                    bachelors/bachelorettes at the café. As in many visual novels, experiencing how
                    the romance plays out with each of the bachelors/bachelorettes is one of the
                    main goals a reader has when approaching the narrative.</p>
                <p>Creating a character in <title rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title> is restricted to
                    choosing what gender the character should be referred to as (<ref
                        target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>) and what picture image they have (<ref
                        target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref>). <figure xml:id="figure04">
                        <head>Screenshot of character creation screen in <title rend="italic">Hustle
                                Cat</title>. Taken on May 19, 2016.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="figure05">
                        <head>Screenshots from <title rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title> of possible
                            portraits (below). The images during the main narrative (top) correspond
                            to the circled portraits. Taken on May 19, 2016.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
                    </figure> Although it is not made explicit, the portraits the reader may choose
                    from in <ref target="#figure05">Figure 5</ref> suggest the choice of the
                    character’s sex. Physical features associated with a stereotypically female
                    body, long hair, breasts and skinnier arms, appear in the <q>female</q> version
                    of the character.</p>
                <p>Even though it is ambiguous as to whether the sex of the character can be chosen,
                    it is clear that there is a distinction between physical appearance and
                    expressed gender identity. This is executed more explicitly than it is in <title
                        rend="italic">ASM</title>, and the rare inclusion of the third-person
                    pronouns to refer to the protagonist in a digital narrative establishes the
                    equality of the multiple gender identities. Whereas from a feminist
                    narratological perspective, Ruth E. Page <ptr target="#page2006" loc="29"/>
                    argues that <quote rend="inline" source="#page2006">ambiguous characterization
                        [challenges] the reader’s notion of gender as a stable, defining feature of
                        a character’s identity</quote>, in this case the reverse is true. The
                    unambiguous assignment of a character’s expressed identity, which may or may not
                    differ from their physical appearance, makes it explicit that a notion of stable
                    binary gender identities is incongruous with the design of this digital
                    narrative. The ability to mix and match sexed bodies and gender identities is
                    what allows the reader to explore how each combination elicits a different
                    response toward their own conception of gender identities. Further, upon closer
                    inspection of <ref target="#figure05">Figure 4</ref>, underneath the selection
                    of pronouns, it reads <q>You can change
                        this mid-game if you like</q>. While reading <title rend="italic">Hustle
                        Cat</title>, the reader can open the options menu to change what pronoun
                    they would like their character to be referred to. From a game design point of
                    view, switching pronouns is not difficult because of the text-based nature of
                    the visual novel. However, the effortlessness of changing the character’s
                    expressed gender on the reader’s part makes <title rend="italic">Hustle
                        Cat</title> the epitome of a digital narrative that encourages exploration
                    of gender identities. Even when the reader does not wish to change pronouns, the
                    knowledge that they can always do so throughout the narrative continuously asks
                    readers whether they are comfortable with the gender identity they experience
                    on-screen. Not answering this question is in itself a response that reaffirms
                    one’s current gender identity. It is from this question-and-answer feedback loop
                    that the exploration of gender identities can occur.</p>
                <p>How character creation allows for the exploration of gender identities has been
                    discussed as predominantly the result of readers’ ability to adopt an array of
                    gender identities. When gender identity is not fixed, however, sexual
                    orientation cannot be fixed as well. How character creation mechanics, in
                    creating parallel worlds and influencing the temporality of the plot, confronts
                    the reader with multiple sexual identities is now examined.</p>
                <p>Susan Lanser’s <ptr target="#lanser1995"/> study, <title rend="quotes">Sexing the
                        Narrative</title>, as mentioned earlier, reads Jeanette Winterson’s <title
                        rend="italic">Written on the Body</title> from a queer narratological
                    perspective. Lanser contends that the protagonist of the novel being unsexed and
                    ungendered produces two major outcomes. First, the reader cannot assign a gender
                    to the protagonist so that they are straight because the protagonist has
                    romantic experiences with both men and women, and thus the reader is always
                    confronted with queerness in the novel. Second, narrative tension from the
                    ambiguity of the protagonist’s sex and gender is created, and she uses as an
                    example of this a scene where the protagonist is in a fight with a male. While
                    an analysis of narrative tension would be interesting, in terms of examining the
                    exploration of sexual identities, understanding how the reader is confronted
                    with queerness is more helpful.</p>
                <p>Those who engage with <title rend="italic">ASM</title> and <title rend="italic"
                        >Hustle Cat</title> are confronted with queer identities from the beginning
                    of the character creation process to the end of the narrative. Whether readers
                    choose to create an identity that is queer or not does not matter, but the
                    design of the digital narrative and the resultant ability to play as queer
                    already situates the reader in an environment of fluid sexual identities. An
                    examination of the parallel/possible worlds and temporality of the digital
                    narrative can demonstrate this. Although to summarize her entire description of
                    these theories would take too long, Marie-Laure Ryan <ptr target="#ryan2006"
                        loc="669"/> notes there are two major types of possible worlds, actual or
                    non-actual. She says, <quote rend="inline" source="#ryan2006">In a story with
                        multiple branches, the world shown by the <emph>current</emph> branch is the
                        only actual one; the others are just nonactualized possibilities</quote>
                    (original italics). In other words, the world created by the reader’s active
                    involvement and shown to the reader is the actual world. She further argues that
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ryan2006">the branches not chosen become
                        counterfactual and usually disappear from the readers’ minds until they
                        start all over again … and the branches passed over no longer
                    matter</quote>. It could be argued that in a hypertext novel, those as
                    complicated as Shelley Jackson’s <title rend="quotes">Patchwork Girl</title>, it
                    is extremely cognitively taxing for the reader to keep track of all the choices
                    they could have made, but the branches passed over do, in fact, matter and they
                    can have an effect on the reader’s mind.</p>
                <p>The queer effect of these parallel worlds or universes on a reader is created by
                    the experienced temporality in a digital narrative. Two notions of time in
                    digital narrative are used here. First, <quote rend="inline" source="#zagal2010"
                        >gameworld time</quote>, which is <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#zagal2010">established by the set of events
                            taking place within the represented gameworld</quote>
                        <ptr target="#zagal2010"/>
                    </cit>. Second, Mieke Bal’s <ptr target="#bal1985" loc="39"/> understanding of a
                    duration of time in a narrative as <quote rend="inline" source="#bal1985"
                        >moments of crisis</quote>, moments when <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#bal1985">in a brief instant of time, the life of persons or an
                        entire nation takes a decisive turn</quote>. Though the outcomes of each
                    read-through may be different, each narrative is grounded in the same crisis —
                    winning your lover back in <title rend="italic">ASM</title> and undoing the
                    curse from the cat café in <title rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title> — and the
                    gameworld time becomes bound to the crisis in each read-through. If the lover in
                        <title rend="italic">ASM</title> is getting married to the protagonist’s
                    rival in one read-through, and in another read-through the lover is leaving the
                    rival for the protagonist, because these events take place in the same gameworld
                    time and moment of crisis, the only logical explanation is that these two events
                    are occurring concurrently in two separate possible worlds. Each digital
                    narrative is then a sum of its parallel worlds, all of which conflict with each
                    other but are of equal validity. Thus, even if a player attempts to select or
                    create <q>nonqueer</q> avatars by selecting, for example, a male protagonist and
                    a female lover in <title rend="italic">ASM</title>, these same avatars start off
                    queer. The design of the narrative necessitates that, at the same fictional time
                    of the narrative, the avatars are romantically engaged with avatars of different
                    sexes and genders in other universes. By default, each character must then
                    possess every quality within the limits of the digital narrative so that the
                    player can choose which one to experience in a particular read-through. The
                    player is confronted with the fact that, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mcrae1996">[i]n virtual reality, mind and
                            body, female and male, gay and straight don’t seem to be such natural
                            oppositions anymore, or even natural categories to assign to
                            people</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mcrae1996" loc="249"/>
                    </cit>, and where multiple, fluid sexual identities are the norm becomes the
                    environment in which players explore.</p>
                <p>The conclusion that all of the possible actual or non-actual worlds in <title
                        rend="italic">ASM</title> and <title rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title> do not
                    inhabit protagonists and love interests with heterosexual sexual identities
                    rests on two premises: first, that there is nothing in the narrative that can
                    confirm the heterosexuality of the protagonist;<note> In <title rend="italic"
                            >ASM</title>, the protagonist may be faced with homophobic or
                        stereotypical remarks by side characters if the protagonist is in a same-sex
                        relationship. However, the reader and protagonist can neither confirm nor
                        deny their sexual orientation.</note> and second, that protagonists can be
                    attracted to either sex, and particularly in <title rend="italic">ASM</title>, a
                    transgender character. Without the narrative marker of sexuality that Lanser
                        <ptr target="#lanser1995"/> describes, the multiple sexualities possible in
                    a single character should only exhibit queerness. There is, however, a
                    possibility that the queerness is not fully experienced. If digital narratives
                    might make people imagine <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#angelcross2012">the concept of changing
                            bodies/identities/genders</quote>
                        <ptr target="#angelcross2012" loc="80"/>
                    </cit>, the structured polysemy that Katherine Sender <ptr target="#sender1999"
                    /> describes, that the same message produces different meanings based on one’s
                    social background and beliefs, presents a possibility that straight people
                    imagine strictly straight worlds. To a part of the narrative audience who
                    refuses to accept that queer sexualities are in the narrative, the queer
                    characters in non-actualized worlds remain marginalized or do not exist because
                    the worlds in which queer characters play a role in the narrative are so
                    incongruous with the player’s norms. The power to explore gender and sexual
                    identities becomes hindered. Although this could be an issue in <title
                        rend="italic">ASM</title>, for <title rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title> this
                    is not the case.</p>
                <p>The main objective in <title rend="italic">ASM</title> is to survive and stop the
                    wedding ceremony to get back with the lover, but, as with any novel, digital or
                    otherwise, the goal of <title rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title> is to master the
                    narrative, to finish reading and to understand the whole story. While in a
                    hypertext novel, as Robert Selig <ptr target="#selig2000"/> notes with Stuart
                    Moulthrop’s <title rend="quotes">Victory Garden</title>, to go through every
                    combination of lexias is implausible, the mastery of the text is possible in the
                    more manageable narrative space of a visual novel. In <title rend="italic"
                        >Hustle Cat</title>, there are six major routes the reader can go through,
                    and in each one the protagonist romances one bachelor/bachelorette. However, one
                    of these bachelors, Graves, is unlocked only after all the routes with other
                    characters have been completed. It is in this route that the backstory of the
                    curse is revealed. Thus, if readers are to fully understand the story and master
                    the text, they must go through every route and, in doing so, their protagonist
                    must experience romances with both males and females. Although the reader may
                    choose the sexes and genders that retain the illusion of heterosexuality, some
                    of the characters, such as Graves and Mason (a bachelorette), are revealed as
                    having queer relationships in the past and when readers must be romantically
                    involved with these two characters, they are reminded that no complete reading
                    of <title rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title> can avoid interaction with queer
                    identities. <title rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title> allows readers to explore
                    sexuality in a digital environment where queerness is the only constant, forcing
                    its readers to either adopt queer identities or actively engage with the lives
                    of its queer characters.</p>
                <p>The ability to explore one’s gender and sexuality in these two digital narratives
                    has been shown to be primarily based on the ability for its players and readers
                    to choose both the protagonist and a love interest’s sex and/or gender. This
                    freedom opens up permutations of sexes, genders and sexualities that are
                    unavoidable because in every play-through, regardless of whether a
                    heteronormative configuration of characters is chosen, the temporally parallel
                    structure of all the possible actual and non-actual worlds forces the player to
                    experience the narrative in a game system in which all the player-controlled
                    protagonists in the narrative are of all possible genders and sexual
                    orientations. Each player is thus confronted with the knowledge that the gender
                    and sexual identities of their on-screen presence can never be fully stable. The
                    inclusion of queer characters other than the player-controlled ones in the game
                    environment further force players to engage with non-heteronormative identities
                    in order to progress through the narrative. It is not only indie digital
                    narratives such as <title rend="italic">ASM</title> and <title rend="italic"
                        >Hustle Cat</title> that employ this <q>queer worlds</q> approach to
                    narrative construction and game design. In the following section, progressive
                    character creation designs in <title rend="italic">The Sims</title> series, and
                    especially its latest sequel, <title rend="italic">The Sims 4</title>, are
                    analyzed.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head><title rend="italic">The Sims</title>, One through Four</head>
                <p>Every four to five years, beginning in 2000, Electronic Arts has released a new
                    sequel to its critically acclaimed and often-studied life-simulation series,
                        <title rend="italic">The Sims</title>
                    <ptr target="#EA2000"/>. In 2014, the latest game in the series, <title
                        rend="italic">The Sims 4</title>
                    <ptr target="#EA2014b"/>, was released and was named the most sold game in both
                    2014 and 2015 by the Entertainment Software Association <ptr target="#ESA2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#ESA2016"/>. For many reasons, it has been and still is mentioned
                    in many video game studies. The first game, which became popular soon after its
                    release, drew attention to the simulation genre in video games. Mia Consalvo in
                    2003 <ptr target="#consalvo2003" loc="181"/> called it <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#consalvo2003">perhaps the most progressive game yet released
                        concerning sexuality, making it a good candidate for study</quote>. Not many
                    substantial changes regarding sexuality were made to the series in the years
                    following the first game in the series, but with the newest update in the latest
                    addition, Electronic Arts may have reclaimed the title that Consalvo gave it
                    over a decade ago.</p>
                <p>In the first game of the series, Create-A-Sim (the name of the character creation
                    process in the game) is a simple matter of choosing between a few options. The
                    name, the age, the race, and the appearance of the Sim (the name of a character
                    or <soCalled>person</soCalled> in the game) can be decided by the player. The
                    Sim is either male or female. The player may allocate <q>points</q> to different
                    traits a Sim may have. A created Sim or group of Sims is always referred to as a
                    family; however, as Consalvo <ptr target="#consalvo2003"/> notes, the player is
                    reminded in the game manual, by its illustrations of heterosexual couples and by
                    its statement that only heterosexual couples may have children, that there are
                    certain restrictions to homosexual romance. Marriage is only allowed for
                    heterosexual couples, while sex or <soCalled>playing in bed</soCalled> is
                    permitted to both homosexual and heterosexual couples.<note> Sex, or
                            <soCalled>playing in bed,</soCalled> is not possible without the
                        installation of the expansion pack to the base game, <title rend="italic"
                            >The Sims: Livin’ Large</title>. Heterosexual Sims do not have sex to
                        create a baby if the pack is not installed but do so through a dialogue
                        option.</note> Any family of Sim adults can adopt a baby, and Sims may
                    receive a phone call when adoption is possible, though this happens randomly and
                    is out of the player’s control. From <title rend="italic">The Sims 2</title>
                    <ptr target="#EA2004"/> onward, restrictions on homosexual Sims are lifted.
                    Marriage becomes an option for gay Sims, though it is called a <q>joined
                        union</q> until <title rend="italic">The Sims 3</title>
                    <ptr target="#EA2009"/> where it is then referred to as marriage. Adopting a
                    child is possible from the second game in the series for Sims hetero-, homo- or
                    bisexual, and they can call adoption agencies directly to arrange this. In the
                    third installation, <q>family</q> is no longer used to describe a group of Sims
                    that live on the same lot but <q>household</q> is used. Character creation
                    mechanics remain largely unchanged except that each subsequent game allows for
                    more customization of, for example, hair styles, clothes and make up. The size
                    of a female Sim’s breasts is made modifiable in <title rend="italic">The Sims
                        3</title>.</p>
                <p>When the latest game in the series, <title rend="italic">The Sims 4</title>, was
                    first released, it had character creation options very similar to the previous
                    game. Electronic Arts in their marketing of the game emphasized that Sims now
                    had <soCalled>emotions,</soCalled> which are indicated to the player in terms
                    such as happy, flirty or depressed. On 2 June 2016, however, two years following
                    the initial release of the game, major changes to the customization of sex and
                    gender in the character creation system were introduced. Players now first
                    choose the Sim’s sex, which is either male or female. The following additional
                    four choices are given to the player when creating a Sim. <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Physical frame:<list type="unordered">
                                <item>Masculine</item>
                                <item>Feminine</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Clothing preference:<list type="unordered">
                                <item>Masculine</item>
                                <item>Feminine</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Pregnancy:<list type="unordered">
                                <item>This Sim can become pregnant</item>
                                <item>This Sim can impregnate</item>
                                <item>Neither of the above</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>Toilet options:<list type="unordered">
                                <item>This Sim can use the toilet standing</item>
                                <item>This Sim can only use the toilet sitting down</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list> The physical frame of a Sim refers to aspects of their body, such as
                    their bone structure or muscle tone. Clothing preference is an option more for
                    convenience and decides what clothes are presented to players when selecting
                    their Sim’s attire, so that a Sim who prefers <soCalled>feminine</soCalled>
                    clothing will be shown those clothes and not <soCalled>masculine</soCalled>
                    clothing. <title rend="italic">Sims</title> games previously only allowed
                        <soCalled>masculine</soCalled> clothes to be worn by male-sexed Sims and
                        <soCalled>feminine</soCalled> clothes for female-sexed Sims. Traditionally,
                    Sims of the female sex are the only ones who can be impregnated by having sex,
                    whereas those of the male sex, if they are abducted by aliens, can become
                    pregnant with alien offspring, which is not possible for female-sexed Sims.
                    Male-sexed Sims used to be the only ones who could impregnate. Pregnancy options
                    revamp this design and lift restrictions applied to the biological sexes. Toilet
                    options can be configured so that the animation of a Sim using the toilet
                    reflects the choice the player makes. After the initial Create-A-Sim sequence,
                    players may click on a wardrobe to change these aspects about their Sim again if
                    they wish to do so.</p>
                <p>While the masculine/feminine distinction used to describe the clothing in the
                    game can be seen as problematic, because it still presupposes an essentialist
                    configuration between clothing and sex, it could be argued that if no
                    distinction was made between <q>masculine/feminine</q> fashion, every time a
                    player clicks on clothing options, both types of clothes would appear, which
                    could lead to longer load times and confusion on the player’s part. Placing
                        <q>stereotypically</q> in front of terms could resolve this, but the new
                    options given to the player more than makes up for this little shortcoming.
                    Avoiding the oversimplistic conclusion that the game in offering the player such
                    freedoms is in some way liberatory, the character creation design can be first
                    approached from a feminist software design perspective. Feminist software
                    design, says Justine Cassell <ptr target="#cassell2000" loc="304–305"/>, adheres
                    to the following tenets: <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Transfer design authority to the user</item>
                        <item>Value subjective and experiental [<foreign xml:lang="la"
                            >sic</foreign>] knowledge in the context of computer use</item>
                        <item>Allow use by many different kinds of users in different
                            contexts</item>
                        <item>Give the user a tool to express her voice and the truth of her
                            existence</item>
                        <item>Encourage collaboration among users</item>
                    </list> In the previous section on <title rend="italic">ASM</title> and <title
                        rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title>, the emphasis was on how players’
                    subjective and experiential knowledge of themselves and the truth of their
                    existence are uncovered when design authority is transferred to the user by
                    creating a character. In the later installations of the <title rend="italic"
                        >Sims</title> series, Electronic Arts created collaborative platforms on
                    which a community of <soCalled>Simmers</soCalled> can be formed. For <title
                        rend="italic">The Sims 3</title>, Electronic Arts <ptr target="#EAnd"/>
                    created a site called <title rend="quotes">The Exchange</title> to encourage
                    players to share the Sims and buildings they had created in the game. <title
                        rend="italic">The Sims 4</title> uses a <title rend="quotes">Gallery</title>
                    in-game where players can directly download others’ creations or upload their
                    own. In under a year of the game’s release, over 92 million Sims were created in
                        <title rend="italic">The Sims 4 </title>
                    <ptr target="#franklin2015"/>. The many discussion forum sites both created by
                    Electronic Arts and fans of the game encourage collaboration among and the
                    participation of players. The addition of the new gender customization options
                    allows players to share created Sims whose identities are explicitly queer so
                    that the feminist game design in the previous games is now also a queer game
                    design in that it promotes the explicit expression of the experiences and
                    subjectivities of players of varying gender and sexual identities.</p>
                <p>The queer worlds approach used in the previous section is applicable to <title
                        rend="italic">The Sims 4</title> in that it could be conceived by the player
                    that a Sim is always inherently bisexual because Sims are able to romance a Sim
                    of any sex or gender. However, referring back to Sender’s <ptr
                        target="#sender1999"/> structured polysemy, players can imagine or perceive
                    a heteronormative gameworld very easily because the vast freedom given to
                    players in a <title rend="italic">Sims</title> game makes the narrative produced
                    emergent. Tinsley Galyean <ptr target="#galyean1995" loc="1"/> on emergent
                    narratives says, <quote rend="inline" source="#galyean1995">We all construct
                        narratives out of our daily activities to help us remember, understand,
                        categorize and share experiences. … If any narrative structure (or story)
                        emerges it is a product of our interactions and goals as we navigate the
                        experience</quote>. In a <title rend="italic">Sims</title> game there are no
                    prewritten narratives like there are in <title rend="italic">ASM</title> or
                        <title rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title>. There is no identifiable moment of
                    crisis that can corner the player into recognizing each subsequent play-through
                    of the game as part of a universe of parallel worlds. In this case, it is the
                    sudden overhaul of the game’s character creation mechanics that <q>queer</q> the
                    game. It is the fact that the most popular computer game of 2014 and 2015 has
                    been updated to include transgenderism and a greater range of queer options that
                    demonstrates a recognition of queer gamers by the video gaming industry. The
                    trend in attitudes towards sex and gender in the <title rend="italic"
                        >Sims</title> series that favors progressive and inclusive game designs
                    forces its players to come to terms with the fact that future games in the
                    series will continue developing to recognize queer identities.</p>
                <p>The exploratory element in <title rend="italic">The Sims 4</title> can be seen
                    from the play style that the design of the game encourages. Consalvo <ptr
                        target="#consalvo2003" loc="189"/> argues that in <title rend="italic">The
                        Sims</title>, <quote rend="inline" source="#consalvo2003">the player does
                        not take on the <q>identity</q> of any one character in particular, but is
                        expected to create and manage multiple characters. … In <title rend="italic"
                            >The Sims</title>, players can control any character they desire, by
                        quickly switching among them and by zooming into and out of different
                        houses</quote>. Although in the newer games, the player often controls a few
                    Sims in a household, and although alternating between a few households is still
                    an option, <title rend="italic">The Sims 4</title> encourages a play style in
                    which players attach themselves emotionally to the Sims they create. Major
                    gaming channels on YouTube such as Pewdiepie <ptr target="#pewdiepie2014"/>,
                    Jacksepticeye <ptr target="#Jacksepticeye2014"/>, and DanAndPhilGAMES <ptr
                        target="#DanAndPhilGAMES2014"/> have produced <q>Let’s plays</q> of <title
                        rend="italic">The Sims 4</title> where the video makers have created
                    versions of themselves to play within the game, which demonstrates the more
                    personal approach taken to gameplay as opposed to the <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#consalvo2003">playing god</quote> mode that Consalvo describes. The
                    time and attention a player gives to tweaking their character, which the
                    detailed customization options makes possible, and the goals players hope their
                    Sims can achieve encourage an emotional investment in their characters. The game
                    marketed as that which allows players to play with life lets players explore the
                    world of the Sims through the eyes of the Sims. Richard Walsh <ptr
                        target="#walsh2011"/> contends that the <title rend="italic">Sims</title>
                    series as simulation and thus representation does not offer a reliable portrayal
                    of real human behavior, which seems to repeat Plato’s dictum in <title
                        rend="italic">The Republic</title> of art and representation as at a third
                    remove from reality, but this does not impede the player’s ability to
                    internalize on-screen experiences because of the verisimilitude of the systems
                    in the game. The resemblance of the relationships between Sims and gender and
                    sex systems in the gameworld to the experiential world assists players in taking
                    part as the narrative audience of the game — an audience that accepts a reality
                    where they are occupants of this digital world. The result is that players can
                    explore by experimenting with the combinations of sex and gender and sexual
                    identities of the characters they have created and are attached to. It is the
                    combined effects of the encouraged play style and the ease of choosing from a
                    multitude of queer identities that foreground the <title rend="italic">Sims
                        4</title> as a digital narrative that allows for the exploration of one’s
                    identity.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Being Sexual Blind, Being <q>Other
                        Bisexual</q> and Concluding Remarks</head>
                <p>For Stephen Greer <ptr target="#greer2013" loc="16"/>, in his examination of the
                        <title rend="italic">Fable</title> and <title rend="italic">Dragon
                        Age</title> video game series, the ability to play as different sexualities
                    without any consequences <quote rend="inline" source="#greer2013">presumes an
                        even playfield</quote> and reveals a sexuality blind approach that might
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#greer2013">free creators from the burden of
                        attempting to create an extended range of avatars, characters and narrative
                        variations covering multiple configurations</quote>. Greer quotes T. L.
                    Taylor <ptr target="#taylor2003" loc="35"/>, who says the result is that <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#taylor2003">issues pertaining to gender
                        and race get taken off the table as areas to be articulated, debated, and
                        confronted</quote>. It is possible that the treatment of different
                    sexualities as equal can cause the important issues on this subject to be
                    disregarded, and in a message board on Steam, some players commented on the lack
                    of homophobia in <title rend="italic">ASM</title> as unrealistic <ptr
                        target="#ValveCorporation2017c"/>; and on a popular site that specializes in
                    articles on <title rend="italic">Sims</title> games, SimsVIP <ptr
                        target="#SimsVIP2016"/> comments on the ability for two biologically male
                    Sims to impregnate each other sparked criticism for being anatomically
                    inaccurate. It could even be said that changing a Sim’s sex, gender, or ability
                    to be pregnant mid-game with a click on the wardrobe is unrealistic and does not
                    adequately reflect the psychological and physical challenges a person faces when
                    undergoing operations to change their sex. However, it must be acknowledged that
                    issues relating to sex, gender identity and sexuality, particularly
                    transgenderism, are only beginning to be incorporated into games by major video
                    game companies.</p>
                <p>Further, in response to allegations that some inclusive video game designs,
                    because of the conflation of varying sexualities, foster an environment in which
                    important issues regarding sexual identities are ignored, it should first be
                    noted that even the inclusion of queer options in video games was met with
                    uproar, as Megan Condis <ptr target="#condis2015"/> notes, from the <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#condis2015">straight male gamer</quote>
                    demographic, thus placing issues of gender and sexuality under the spotlight.
                    The academic reportage of forum threads started by conservative personalities
                    such as Bastal and Duncaaaaaan has revealed the on-going debate on these issues
                    that have taken place simply because game designers have so much as accommodated
                    people outside the privileged heteronormative demographic. In place of the
                    sexuality/gender/transgender-blind approach by some scholars toward the design
                    of video games that encourages an equal treatment of individuals, the emergent
                    transgressive poststructuralist ethos, the idea of <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#cixous1976">other bisexuality</quote>, should be considered as
                    well. As described in her seminal essay, <title rend="quotes">The Laugh of the
                        Medusa</title>, Helénè Cixous’s <ptr target="#cixous1976" loc="884"/> other
                    bisexuality is: <quote rend="block" source="#cixous1976">each one’s location
                        in self (<foreign xml:lang="fr">répérage en soi</foreign>) of the presence —
                        variously manifest and insistent according to each person, male or female —
                        of both sexes, non-exclusion either of the difference of one sex, and, from
                        this <q>self-permission,</q> multiplication of the effects of the
                        inscription of desire, over all parts of my body and the other body.</quote>
                    Cixous’s <title rend="quotes">The Laugh of the Medusa</title> argued against
                    Sigmund Freud’s <title rend="quotes">Medusa’s Head</title>, published in 1922.
                    Whereas Freud saw bisexuality as a merge of masculinity and femininity, Cixous’s
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#cixous1976">other bisexuality</quote>
                    resists these binaries. She imagines a sexuality that destabilizes traditional
                    dichotomies of male and female, masculinity and femininity — phallogocentric
                    dichotomies where femininity is formed based on what masculinity is not. What
                    results from other bisexuality is <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#binhammer1991">a future when males and females
                            explore the infinite possibilities of their bisexuality, in this world
                            of elsewhere, <q>woman</q> will no longer hold us captive, and the
                            either/or of essentialism will be worn out</quote>
                        <ptr target="#binhammer1991" loc="77"/>
                    </cit>. <q>Other bisexuality</q> describes desire as flowing infinitely and
                    everywhere, from anyone and to anyone, with no restrictions whatsoever.</p>
                <p>Cixous’s essay was also famous for its coinage of <foreign xml:lang="fr">écriture
                        féminine</foreign>, or <q>feminine writing</q>, which according to her is
                    where other bisexuality can be experienced. However, the spirit of other
                    bisexuality appears in the discussed digital narratives as well. While it is
                    implicit that characters in <title rend="italic">ASM</title> or <title
                        rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title> are sexed as male or female, and it is
                    explicit in the <title rend="italic">Sims</title> series, these digital
                    narratives design characters as bodies of infinitely variable desires not
                    directed exclusively at any gender or sex, where essentialist configurations of
                    gender and sexual identities collapse. Especially in the queer parallel worlds
                    analysis, where a digital narrative is the culmination of playthroughs or
                    readthroughs with protagonists of all possible sexualities, the limitlessness of
                    experimentation with desire encapsulates the transgression of other bisexuality.
                    In such digital narratives, the progressive poststructuralist understanding
                    trumps the heteronormative categories of genders and sexualities and a
                    destabilized essentialism and unstable identities become the only stable
                    understanding of gender and sexuality. Considering the freedom to choose one’s
                    on-screen identity without consequence as embodying the spirit of other
                    bisexuality rather than being sexuality blind appreciates the transgressive
                    potential and power of the digital narrative. It also recognizes progression of
                    the designs of digital narratives in a direction that promotes the inclusion of
                    a previously marginalized gaming demographic. This is not to say that the
                    shortcomings that a sexuality blind approach uncovers should be ignored, but the
                    digital narrative as a platform where unrestrained, multidirectional libidinal
                    economies can be realized and can be experimented with should be considered as
                    well.</p>
                <p>As Jerry Kang <ptr target="#kang2000"/> notes, passing in real life is
                    significantly more difficult than doing so in a digital space — to pass racially
                    in real life, he says, for example, one might need to undergo expensive and
                    dangerous surgery. Digital environments allow for the separation between the
                    experienced self and the expressed self at the click of a button. Sherry Turkle
                        <ptr target="#turkle1995" loc="213"/> contends that when you choose to swap
                    genders virtually, <quote rend="inline" source="#turkle1995">you may discover
                        things about yourself that you never knew before … [and] explore conflicts
                        raised by one’s biological gender</quote>. The ability to play as different
                    sexes and have romantic attachments with either sex appeared as early as at the
                    beginning of the <title rend="italic">Sims</title> series in 2000. However, only
                    recently have digital narrative designs considered that the sex to which one is
                    assigned may differ from the gender identity that one experiences. Even though
                    hypersexualized sex icons continue to appear to cater to the straight male
                    community, as major digital entertainment companies become more aware of the
                    previously marginalized consumers of video games, characters with non-binary
                    gender identities, such as Krem in the widely popular video game, <title
                        rend="italic">Dragon Age: Inquisition</title>
                    <ptr target="#EA2014a"/>, are slowly being introduced.</p>
                <p>The study of the exploration of gender and sexual identities has previously
                    focused on interaction in online MUDs, a digital space that requires its users
                    to have some coding knowledge or the willingness to learn coding, but digital
                    narratives accessible by a greater community, such as <title rend="italic"
                        >Sims</title> games, <title rend="italic">ASM</title>, and <title
                        rend="italic">Hustle Cat</title>, are beginning to realize the same
                    exploratory function as well, in particular by situating readers in an
                    environment where gender and sexuality are never fixed, where boundaries of a
                    structuralist ideology of gender and sexuality are continuously challenged. The
                    movement toward narratives where sexual difference and rigid configurations of
                    sexuality are rigorously being undermined might suggest that Cixous’s visions
                    are not that far behind.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="APA2016" label="American Psychological Association 2016">American
                    Psychological Association, 2016, <title rend="quotes">Guidelines for
                        Psychological Practice with Lesbian, Gay and Bisexual Clients</title>,
                    website (2016).Viewed 18 May 2016, <ref
                        target="http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbt/resources/guidelines.aspx"
                        >http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbt/resources/guidelines.aspx</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="angelcross2012" label="Angel Cross 2012">Angel Cross, K. <title
                        rend="quotes">The New Laboratory of Dreams: Role-playing Games as
                        Resistance</title>, <title rend="italic">Women's Studies Quarterly</title>,
                    40.3–4 (2012), pp. 70–88.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bal1985" label="Bal 1985">Bal, M., 1985, <title rend="italic"
                        >Narratology: Introduction to the Theory of Narrative</title>. University of
                    Toronto Press, Toronto ; Buffalo (1985).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barthes1989" label="Barthes 1989">Barthes, R. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Reality Effect.</title> In: Howard, R. (Tran.), <title rend="italic">The
                        Rustle of Language</title>. University of California Press (1989), pp.
                    141–148.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bastal2011a" label="Bastal 2011a">Bastal <title rend="quotes">Bioware
                        Neglected Their Core Audience: The Straight Male Gamer - General
                        Discussion</title>, forum post (17 March 2011). Viewed 24 May 2016, <ref
                        target="https://forum.bioware.com/topic/192281-bioware-neglected-their-core-audience-the-straight-male-gamer/"
                        >https://forum.bioware.com/topic/192281-bioware-neglected-their-core-audience-the-straight-male-gamer/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bastal2011b" label="Bastal 2011b">Bastal <title rend="quotes">Bioware
                        Neglected Their Core Audience: The Straight Male Gamer - General
                        Discussion</title>, forum post (18 March 2011). Viewed 24 May 2016, <ref
                        target="https://forum.bioware.com/topic/193167-bioware-neglected-their-core-audience-the-straight-male-gamer/"
                        >https://forum.bioware.com/topic/193167-bioware-neglected-their-core-audience-the-straight-male-gamer/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="binhammer1991" label="Binhammer 1991">Binhammer, K. <title
                        rend="quotes">Metaphor or Metonymy? The Questions of Essentialism in
                        Cixous</title>, <title rend="italic">Tessera</title>, 10 (1991), pp.
                    65–79.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cassell2000" label="Cassell 2000">Cassell, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Storytelling as a Nexus of Change in the Relationship between Gender and
                        Technology: A Feminist Approach to Software Design.</title> In: Cassell, J.,
                    Jenkins, H. (Eds.), <hi rend="italic">From Barbie to Mortal Kombat: Gender and
                        Computer Games</hi>. MIT Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts (2000), pp.
                    298–326.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cavallaro2010" label="Cavallaro 2010">Cavallaro, D. <title
                        rend="quotes">Anime and the Visual Novel: Theoretical Approaches.</title>
                    In: <title rend="italic">Anime and the Visual Novel: Narrative Structure, Design
                        and Play at the Crossroads of Animation and Computer Games</title>.
                    McFarland &amp; Co, Jefferson, North Carolina (2010), pp. 7–32.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cavendish2004" label="Cavendish 2004">Cavendish, M. <title
                        rend="italic">The Description of a New World, Called The Blazing
                        World</title>, in: Lilley, K. (Ed.), <title rend="italic">The Blazing World
                        and Other Writings</title>, Penguin Classics. Penguin, London ; New York
                    (2004), pp. 119–225.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cixous1976" label="Cixous 1976">Cixous, H. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Laugh of the Medusa</title>, <title rend="italic">Signs</title>, 1.4 (1976),
                    pp. 875–893.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="condis2015" label="Condis 2015">Condis, M. <title rend="quotes">No
                        homosexuals in Star Wars? BioWare, <soCalled>gamer</soCalled> identity, and
                        the politics of privilege in a convergence culture</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Convergence: The International Journal of Research into New
                        Media Technologies</title>, 21.2 (2015), pp. 198–212.
                    doi:10.1177/1354856514527205</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="consalvo2003" label="Consalvo 2003">Consalvo, M. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Hot Dates and Fairy-Tale Romances: Studying Sexuality in Video
                        Games.</title> In: Perron, B., Wolf, M. J. P. (Eds.), <title rend="italic"
                        >The Video Game Theory Reader</title>. Routledge, New York (2003), pp.
                    171–194.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="DanAndPhilGAMES2014" label="DanAndPhilGAMES 2014">DanAndPhilGAMES
                        <title rend="quotes">MEET 'DIL HOWLTER' - Dan and Phil Play: The Sims 4
                        #1</title>, online video (2014). Viewed 24 May 2016, <ref
                        target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=s_osQvkeNRM&amp;feature=youtu.be"
                        >http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=s_osQvkeNRM&amp;feature=youtu.be</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="DateNighto2016" label="DateNighto 2016">DateNighto Hustle Cat, video
                    game, PC (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dovey2006" label="Dovey 2006">Dovey, J., Kennedy, H. W. <title
                        rend="quotes">Bodies and Machines: Cyborg Subjectivity and Gameplay.</title>
                    In: <title rend="italic">Games Cultures: Computer Games as New Media, Issues in
                        Cultural and Media Studies</title>. Open University Press, Maidenhead
                    (2006), pp. 104–122.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="duncaaaaan2014" label="Duncaaaaan 2014">Duncaaaaaan <title
                        rend="quotes">Touchy Subject: A Critique Regarding Sexuality in this Game,
                        Character Design And Privilege: The Cisquisition? - General Discussion
                        (Spoilers)</title>, forum post (29 June 2014). Viewed 24 May 2016, <ref
                        target="https://forum.bioware.com/topic/508306-touchy-subject-a-critique-regarding-sexuality-in-this-game-character-design-and-privilege-the-cisquisition/"
                        >https://forum.bioware.com/topic/508306-touchy-subject-a-critique-regarding-sexuality-in-this-game-character-design-and-privilege-the-cisquisition/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="EA2000" label="Electronic Arts 2000">Electronic Arts <title
                        rend="italic">The Sims 1</title>, video game, PC (2000).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="EA2004" label="Electronic Arts 2004">Electronic Arts <title
                        rend="italic">The Sims 2</title>, video game, PC (2004).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="EA2009" label="Electronic Arts 2009">Electronic Arts <title
                        rend="italic">The Sims 3</title>, video game, PC (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="EAnd" label="Electronic Arts n.d.">Electronic Arts <title
                        rend="quotes">The Sims 3</title>, website (n.d.). Viewed 8 June 2016, <ref
                        target="http://au.thesims3.com/exchange"
                        >http://au.thesims3.com/exchange</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="EA2014a" label="Electronic Arts 2014a">Electronic Arts <title
                        rend="italic">Dragon Age: Inquisition</title>, video game, PC (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="EA2011" label="Electronic Arts 2011">Electronic Arts <title
                        rend="italic">Dragon Age 2</title>, video game, PC (2011). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="EA2014b" label="Electronic Arts 2014b">Electronic Arts <title
                        rend="italic">The Sims 4</title>, video game, PC (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ESA2015" label="Entertainment Software Association 2015">Entertainment
                    Software Association <title rend="italic">The 2015 Essential Facts About the
                        Computer and Video Game Industry</title>. Entertainment Software
                    Association, Washington (2015). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ESA2016" label="Entertainment Software Association 2016">Entertainment
                    Software Association <title rend="italic">The 2016 Essential Facts About the
                        Computer and Video Game Industry</title>. Entertainment Software
                    Association, Washington (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fanderclai1996" label="Fanderclai 1996">Fanderclai, T. L. <title
                        rend="quotes">Like Magic, Only Real.</title> In: Cherny, L., Weise, E. R.
                    (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Wired Women: Gender and New Realities in
                        Cyberspace</title>. Seal Press ; Distributed to the trade by Publishers
                    Group West, Seattle, Washington ; Emeryville, California (1996), pp.
                    224–241.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="franklin2015" label="Franklin 2015">Franklin, R. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Sims - You’ve Made 92,800,000 Sims in The Sims 4’s First Year! -
                        Official Site</title>, website (2015). Viewed 8 June 2016, <ref
                        target="https://www.thesims.com/en_GB/news/sims4-1st-anniversary?cid=42764&amp;sourceid=sims4-social-global-ic-tw-ts4-1yearblog-080215-tw-prev-site-sust&amp;ts=1441217108407&amp;utm_campaign=sims4-social-global-ic-tw-ts4-1yearblog-080215-tw-prev-site-sust&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_source=twitter"
                        >https://www.thesims.com/en_GB/news/sims4-1st-anniversary?cid=42764&amp;sourceid=sims4-social-global-ic-tw-ts4-1yearblog-080215-tw-prev-site-sust&amp;ts=1441217108407&amp;utm_campaign=sims4-social-global-ic-tw-ts4-1yearblog-080215-tw-prev-site-sust&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_source=twitter</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="frasca2003" label="Frasca 2003">Frasca, G. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Simulation versus Narrative: Introduction to Ludology.</title> In: Perron,
                    B., Wolf, M. J. P. (Eds.), <title rend="italic">The Video Game Theory
                        Reader</title>. Routledge, New York (2003), pp. 221–236.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gallagher2006" label="Gallagher 2006">Gallagher, C. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Rise of Fictionality.</title> In: Moretti, F. (Ed.), <hi
                        rend="italic">The Novel</hi>. Princeton University Press, Princeton (2006),
                    pp. 336–363.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galyean1995" label="Galyean 1995">Galyean, T. A. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Narrative Guidance, in: AAAI Spring Symposium Series</title>, presented at
                    the Symposium on Interactive Story Systems, Stanford University (1995).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ginsberg1996" label="Ginsberg 1996">Ginsberg, E. K. <title
                        rend="italic">Passing and the Fictions of Identity, New
                    Americanists</title>. Duke University Press, Durham, North Carolina
                    (1996).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="GLAAD2011" label="GLAAD 2011">GLAAD <title rend="quotes">GLAAD Media
                        Reference Guide - Transgender Issues</title>, website (2011). Viewed 18 May
                    2016, <ref target="http://www.glaad.org/reference/transgender"
                        >http://www.glaad.org/reference/transgender</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="greer2013" label="Greer 2013">Greer, S. <title rend="quotes">Playing
                        queer: Affordances for sexuality in Fable and Dragon Age</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Journal of Gaming and Virtual Worlds</title>, 5.1 (2013), pp.
                    3–21. doi:10.1386/jgvw.5.1.3_1</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hayles2008" label="Hayles 2008">Hayles, N. K. <title rend="italic"
                        >Electronic Literature: New Horizons for the Literary</title>. University of
                    Notre Dame, Notre Dame, Indiana (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Jacksepticeye2014" label="Jacksepticeye 2014">Jacksepticeye <title
                        rend="quotes">KEEPING UP WITH THE BOSSES | The Sims 4</title>, online video
                    (2014). Viewed 24 May 2016, <ref
                        target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f3BSbcEvtLc"
                        >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f3BSbcEvtLc</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kang2000" label="Kang 2000">Kang, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Cyber-Race</title>, <title rend="italic">Harvard Law Review</title>, 113.5
                    (2000), pp. 1130–1208. doi:10.2307/1342340</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kendall1996" label="Kendall 1996">Kendall, L. <title rend="quotes"
                        >MUDder? I Hardly Know ’Er! Adventures of a Feminist MUDder.</title> In:
                    Cherny, L., Weise, E. R. (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Wired Women: Gender and
                        New Realities in Cyberspace</title>. Seal Press ; Distributed to the trade
                    by Publishers Group West, Seattle, Washington ; Emeryville, California (1996),
                    pp. 207–223.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lebowitz2011" label="Lebowitz 2011">Lebowitz, J., Klug, C. <title
                        rend="italic">Interactive Storytelling for Video Games: A Player-centered
                        Approach to Creating Memorable Characters and Stories</title>. Focal Press,
                    Burlington, Massachusetts (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lanser1995" label="Lanser 1995">Lanser, S. S. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Sexing the Narrative: Propriety, Desire, and the Engendering of
                        Narratology</title>, <title rend="italic">Narrative</title>, 3.1 (1995), pp.
                    85–94.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcrae1996" label="McRae 1996">McRae, S. <title rend="quotes">Coming
                        Apart at the Seams: Sex, Text and the Virtual Body</title>, in: Cherny, L.,
                    Weise, E. R. (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Wired Women: Gender and New Realities
                        in Cyberspace</title>. Seal Press ; Distributed to the trade by Publishers
                    Group West, Seattle, Washington ; Emeryville, California (1996), pp.
                    242–263.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="murray1998" label="Murray 1998">Murray, J. H. <title rend="italic"
                        >Hamlet on the Holodeck: The Future of Narrative in Cyberspace</title>, 1st
                    edition. The MIT Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts (1998).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nakamura1995" label="Nakamura 1995">Nakamura, L. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Race in/for Cyberspace: Identity Tourism and Racial Passing on the
                        Internet</title>, <title rend="italic">Works Days</title>, 13 (1995), pp.
                    181–93.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nakamura2008" label="Nakamura 2008">Nakamura, L. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Cyberrace</title>, <title rend="italic">PMLA</title>, 123.5 (2008), pp.
                    1673–1682.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nguyen2003" label="Nguyen 2003">Nguyen, M. <title rend="quotes">Queer
                        Cyborgs and New Mutants: Race, Sexuality, and Prosthetic Sociality in
                        Digital Space.</title> In: Wong, S. C. (Ed.), <title rend="italic">Asian
                        America.Net: Ethnicity, Nationalism, and Cyberspace</title>. Routledge, New
                    York (2003), pp. 281–305.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nielsen2015" label="Nielsen 2015">Nielsen, D. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Identity Performance in Roleplaying Games</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >Computers and Composition</title>, 38.A (2015), pp. 45–56.
                    doi:10.1016/j.compcom.2015.09.003</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="page2006" label="Page 2006">Page, R. E. <title rend="italic">Literary
                        and Linguistic Approaches to Feminist Narratology</title>. Palgrave
                    Macmillan, Houndmills, Basingstoke, Hampshire ; New York (2006).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pewdiepie2014" label="Pewdiepie 2014">Pewdiepie <title rend="quotes"
                        >Sims 4 - Gameplay - Part 1 - MY NEW CHARACTER!</title>, online video
                    (2014). Viewed 24 May 2016, <ref
                        target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Wl253R_Yri4"
                        >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Wl253R_Yri4</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rabinowitz1977" label="Rabinowitz 1977">Rabinowitz, P. J. <title
                        rend="quotes">Truth in Fiction: A Reexamination of Audiences</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Critical Inquiry</title>, vol. 4, no. 1, pp. 121–141.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ryan2006" label="Ryan 2006">Ryan, M.- L. <title rend="quotes">From
                        Parallel Universes to Possible Worlds: Ontological Pluralism in Physics,
                        Narratology, and Narrative</title>, <title rend="italic">Poetics
                        Today</title>, 27.4 (2006), pp. 633–674.
                    doi:10.1215/03335372-2006-006</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ryan2009" label="Ryan 2009">Ryan, M.- L. <title rend="quotes">From
                        Narrative Games to Playable Stories: Toward a Poetics of Interactive
                        Narrative</title>, <title rend="italic">Storyworlds: A Journal of Narrative
                        Studies</title>, 1 (2009), pp. 43–59.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="selig2000" label="Selig 2000">Selig, R. L. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Endless Reading of Fiction: Stuart Moulthrop’s Hypertext Novel <title
                            rend="quotes">Victory Garden</title></title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >Contemporary Literature</title>, 41.4 (2000), pp. 642–660.
                    doi:10.2307/1209006</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sender1999" label="Sender 1999">Sender, K. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Selling Sexual Subjectivities: Audiences Respond to Gay Window
                        Advertising</title>, <title rend="italic">Critical Studies in Mass
                        Communication</title>, 16.2 (1999), pp. 172–196.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shaw2009" label="Shaw 2009">Shaw, Adrienne. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Putting the Gay in Games: Cultural Production and GLBT Content in Video
                        Games</title>, <title rend="italic">Games and Culture</title>, 4.3 (2009),
                    pp. 228–253.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="SimsVIP2016" label="SimsVIP 2016">SimsVIP <title rend="quotes">The
                        Sims 4: Gender Customization, Same Sex Pregnancy, and Unisex
                        Clothing</title>, website (2016). Viewed 21 December 2016, <ref
                        target="https://simsvip.com/2016/06/03/the-sims-4-gender-identity-same-sex-pregnancy-unisex-clothing/"
                        >https://simsvip.com/2016/06/03/the-sims-4-gender-identity-same-sex-pregnancy-unisex-clothing/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taylor2003" label="Taylor 2003">Taylor, T. L. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Multiple Pleasures Women and Online Gaming</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >Convergence: The International Journal of Research into New Media
                        Technologies</title>, 9.1 (2003), pp. 21–46.
                    doi:10.1177/135485650300900103</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="turkle1995" label="Turkle 1995">Turkle, S. <title rend="italic">Life
                        on the Screen: Identity in the Age of the Internet</title>. Simon &amp;
                    Schuster, New York (1995).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="VagabondDog2014" label="Vagabond Dog 2014">Vagabond Dog <title
                        rend="italic">Always Sometimes Monsters</title>, video game, PC
                    (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ValveCorporation2017a" label="Valve Corporation 2017a">Valve
                    Corporation <title rend="quotes">Always Sometimes Monsters on Steam</title>,
                    website (2017). 7 September 2017, <ref
                        target="http://store.steampowered.com/app/274310/"
                        >http://store.steampowered.com/app/274310/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ValveCorporation2017b" label="Valve Corporation 2017b">Valve
                    Corporation <title rend="quotes">Hustle Cat on Steam</title>, website (2017).
                    Viewed 7 September 2017, <ref target="http://store.steampowered.com/app/453340/"
                        >http://store.steampowered.com/app/453340/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ValveCorporation2017c" label="Valve Corporation 2017c">Valve
                    Corporation <title rend="quotes">Small but Cool Detail :: Always Sometimes
                        Monsters General Discussions</title>, forum (24 May 2014). Viewed 7
                    September 2017, <ref
                        target="http://steamcommunity.com/app/274310/discussions/0/522728268734722170/"
                        >http://steamcommunity.com/app/274310/discussions/0/522728268734722170/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ValveCorporation2017d" label="Valve Corporation 2017d">Valve
                    Corporation <title rend="quotes">Steam Search</title>, website (2017). Viewed 7
                    September 2017, <ref target="http://store.steampowered.com/search/?tags=3799"
                        >http://store.steampowered.com/search/?tags=3799</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="walsh2011" label="Walsh 2011">Walsh, R. <title rend="quotes">Emergent
                        Narrative in Interactive Media</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >Narrative</title>, 19.1 (2011), pp. 72–85. doi:10.1353/nar.2011.0006</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="warhol2015" label="Warhol 2015">Warhol, R., Lanser, S. S. <title
                        rend="italic">Narrative Theory Unbound: Queer and Feminist
                        Interventions</title>. The Ohio State University Press, Ohio (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zagal2010" label="Zagal 2010">Zagal, J. P., Mateas, M. <title
                        rend="quotes">Time in Video Games: A Survey and Analysis</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Simulation &amp; Gaming</title>, 41.6 (2010), pp. 844–868.
                    doi:10.1177/1046878110375594</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
