<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Discourse cohesion in
               Xenophon’s On Horsemanship through Sketch Engine</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Victoria Beatrix <dhq:family>Fendel</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6302-3726<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Oxford</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>victoria.fendel@classics.ox.ac.uk</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Victoria Beatrix Fendel did her Bachelor of Arts (Classical Civilisations) and Master of Arts (Greek, Ancient Near East Studies) at the University of Basel, Switzerland (2009–2015).
                     She moved to the University of Oxford, UK, for her DPhil in Classical Languages and Literature (2015–2018),
                     which is published in the Oxford Classical Monographs Series (<title rend="italic">Coptic Interference in the Syntax of Greek Letters from Egypt</title>, OUP 2022).
                     She completed her MPhil in Theoretical and Applied Linguistics at the University of Cambridge (2018–2019) with a focus on French linguistics.
                     She is currently a Leverhulme Early Career Fellow at the University of Oxford (2020–2023).</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Matthew T.<dhq:family>Ireland</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0336-4419<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Sidney Sussex College, University of Cambridge</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>mti20@cam.ac.uk</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Matthew Ireland is a computer scientist, working primarily on the design and analysis of electronics in high-speed systems. 
                     He is director and CTO of the start-up company AAI Robotics Ltd, and has affiliations at Sidney Sussex College and Churchill College, Cambridge. 
                     Matthew has extended interests in the wider application of computational thinking, including in the automated analysis of music and language.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000683</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date/>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>cohesion</item>
                  <item>coherence</item>
                  <item>Xenophon</item>
                  <item><title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title></item>
                  <item>support-verb construction</item>
                  <item>Sketch Engine</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000683/000683.xml"
               >GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>We build a Sketch Engine corpus for Xenophon’s classical Greek scientific treatise
                  <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title>. Sketch Engine is a web-based
               corpus-analysis tool that allows the user to inspect the lexical makeup of a text
               (cf. keyword lists), explore the surroundings of select items (cf. concordances) and
               identify fixed expressions in a text (cf. n-grams). We make available our
               corpus-preparation tool and our corpus configuration file for Sketch Engine. We use
               the Sketch Engine corpus to detect discontiguous verbal multi-word expressions,
               specifically support-verb constructions (e.g. <title rend="italic">to take a
                  decision</title>). We examine how support-verb constructions – through their
               structural and lexical properties – aid discourse coherence and cohesion throughout
               Xenophon’s treatise. We furthermore examine how the recurring support-verb
               constructions in the treatise reflect the scientific register of the text. The
               article shows how an understudied category of lexico-syntactic device (support-verb
               constructions) in classical Greek majorly aids discourse cohesion, structurally and
               contextually speaking. It also shows how an understudied text in the form of a
               technical treatise (<title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title>) majorly furthers
               insight into scientific literacy of the classical period. Finally, by making
               available our corpus-preparation tool and code, we hope to further collaboration and
               adaptation and thus improvement of existing tools and counteract the multiplication
               of tools. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            Xenophon's treatise <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> lets support-verb constructions do all the hard work for his community of practice. 
            <p/>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head></head>
          <p>The classical Greek historian Xenophon (5th / 4th c. BC) is best known for his
                  literary works (<title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, <title rend="italic">Hellenica</title>)
                  describing war-time challenges. However, amongst his minor works is a treatise <title
                     rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title>. Xenophon’s hands-on guide to choosing,
                  caring for and training a horse differs from the descriptions of the equines of
                  Greek literature, e.g. Achilles’ Xanthos (in Homer’s <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>)
                  and Bellerophon’s Pegasus (in Hesiod’s <title rend="italic">Theogony</title>). In the
                  epic, Xanthos is immortal (Iliad 16.148ff), weeps after Patroclus’ death (Iliad
                  17.426ff), and prophecies Achilles’ destiny (Iliad 19.392ff). Pegasus is immortal,
                  winged and born out of Medusa’s blood (Hesiod, Theogony 280ff). In the literary
                  genres, the focus lies with the horses as protagonists rather than with the
                  real-life challenges of horse keeping. Conversely, Xenophon’s <title rend="italic">On
                     Horsemanship</title> is interested in the latter. It reflects attention to detail
                  <ptr target="#greer2015"/> along with literacy in scientific discourse. </p>
               <p>The treatise <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> is comparatively short (7,139
                  words), divided into twelve chapters <ptr target="#bowersock2014"/>, and written
                  in prose. It covers (i) the conformation and character of the horse so as to be
                  fit for the intended purpose [sections 1–3], (ii) the care for the horse by the
                  groom [sections 4–6], (iii) the ridden education of the horse [sections 7–8], (iv)
                  special cases (e.g. the spirited horse, the warhorse, and the parade horse)
                  [sections 9–11], and (v) the arms for horse and rider [section 12]. Each section
                  finishes with a brief interims summary. </p>
               <p>Despite this clear sectioning, Xenophon’s text ‘flows’, that is information is
                  communicated effectively, comprehensibly and systematically to the reader.
                  Linguistically, we cast this flow into the notions of coherence and cohesion.
                  Coherence refers to how building blocks of a sentence are tied together; cohesion
                  refers to the tying together of clauses and sentences <ptr target="#webster2019" loc="41"/>. Both
                  are needed for information to be communicated in such a way that the reader can
                  establish links with the preceding discourse and the author can add new pieces of
                  information incrementally. Classical Greek relies on a range of morpho-syntactic,
                  lexical and pragmatic strategies to achieve coherence and cohesion. </p>
               <p>Our aim in this article is threefold. We want to show how to use an application
                  (Sketch Engine) widely used for modern languages for classical Greek and provide
                  the reader with a corpus preparation tool that can be used (and adapted) for their
                  own purposes, thus counteracting the multiplication of digital tools and
                  refocusing on their functionalities. We want to show how an understudied category
                  of lexico-syntactic device (support-verb constructions) in classical Greek majorly
                  aids discourse cohesion, structurally and contextually speaking. We want to show
                  how an understudied text in the form of a technical treatise (<title rend="italic">On
                     Horsemanship</title>) majorly furthers insight into scientific literacy of the
                  classical period. These aims translate into the following three research questions
                  which underpin the following sections: </p>
            
              <list type="ordered"> 
                 <item>How can we choose and facilitate the application of existing corpus-analysis
                  tools for Ancient Greek in a way that is cohesive, text-agnostic, scalable,
                  flexible and freely-reusable?</item>
               <item>How do support-verb constructions by means of the structural properties aid
                  discourse cohesion and coherence? </item>
               <item>How do support-verb constructions by their register-related properties aid
                  discourse cohesion and coherence? </item></list>
            
               <p>Research question 1 explains our choice of Xenophon’s <title rend="italic">On
                     Horsemanship</title>. The treatise is not part of and differs in genre and
                  register from the large literary classical Attic corpus which the Sketch Engine
                  corpus was originally built for<note> Thucydides, Histories I–V; Xenophon,
                     Anabasis I–IV, Memorabilia I–IV, Hellenica I–IV; Antiphon, Speeches 1–6;
                     Isocrates, Speeches 1–6 and 13; Isaeus, Speeches 1–8; Lysias, Speeches 1, 3, 7,
                     12, 14, 19, 22, 30–32; Demosthenes, Speeches 1–4, 6, 9, 18; Plato, Gorgias,
                     Phaedrus, Republic I–III; Aristotle, Rhetoric, Politics I–III.</note>. We thus
                  showcase adaptability and extensibility of our tool.</p>
               <p>The article falls into five sections. Section 1 introduces the notions of
                  coherence and cohesion and explains our choice of Sketch Engine. Section 2
                  outlines the process of building the corpus-preparation tool, adapting it for
                  Xenophon’s <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> and implementing the corpus into
                  Sketch Engine. Section 3 uses this Sketch Engine corpus to examine support-verb
                  constructions, a discontiguous lexical device creating both coherence and
                  cohesion. Section 4 moves beyond coherence and cohesion achieved through
                  structural means, assessing the adherence to the scientific register. Section 5
                  summarises the results and offers conclusions.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>1 Introduction</head>
               <p>Greek relies on a range of morpho-syntactic, lexical and pragmatic strategies to
                  achieve coherence and cohesion. Relevant single-word items can relatively easily
                  be extracted from a lemmatised corpus of text. However, the same is not true for
                  multi-word items, especially discontiguous ones (e.g. <emph>to have an
                     idea</emph> in <emph>I </emph>had<emph> a great
                     </emph>idea<emph> yesterday</emph>). The below describes means to
                  achieve coherence and cohesion in classical Greek discourse before introducing the
                  reader to the structures of choice and the challenges they pose for automated
                  extraction.</p>
               <p>Morpho-syntactically, coherence and cohesion can be achieved by means of
                  structuring particles (e.g. <foreign xml:lang="grc">μέν – δέ</foreign> <q>on the one hand – on the other hand,</q> <foreign xml:lang="grc">οὖν</foreign>
                  <q>thus,</q> <foreign xml:lang="grc">γάρ</foreign> <q>for</q>) <ptr target="#bonifazi2016"/>, conjunctions (e.g. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀλλά</foreign> <q>but</q> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὅτι</foreign>
                  <q>because</q>), and pronouns, which must have a clear anaphoric or kataphoric link to
                  the item they stand in for (e.g. <emph>I met Will yesterday.
                     </emph>He<emph> is very well.</emph> where <q>he</q> can only be used once
                  we have established who it refers to) <ptr target="#halliday1976"/> <ptr target="#luraghi2003"/> <ptr target="#rysova2017"/>.
                  Moreover, word-order choices play a role since Greek word order is
                  information-structure driven <ptr target="#celano2013a"/> <ptr target="#celano2013b"/> <ptr target="#dik1995"/> <ptr target="#mastronarde2013"/>
                  Slots in the word-order frame are not indicative of an argument function (e.g.
                  subject, object), but of an information-structural value (e.g. topic / known
                  information, focus / new information). E.g. in Herodotus, <title rend="italic"
                     >Histories</title> 5.3.5 <foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμοισι δὲ οὗτοι παραπλησίοισι πάντες χρέωνται κατὰ
                  πάντα</foreign> usages.dat – yet.particle – these.nom – alike.dat – all.nom – they.use – in
                  everything <q>Yet all of them have similar habits in all things,</q> initial <foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμοισι</foreign> is
                  the topic component, an unmarked element follows <ptr target="#beschi2018" loc="181–182"/>. In
                  Sophocles, <title rend="italic">Oedipus Colonus</title> 1656 <foreign xml:lang="grc">Μόρῳ δ᾽ ὁποίῳ κεῖνος ὤλετ᾽</foreign>
                  death.dat – yet.particle – what.dat – that.nom – destroy.aor.pass.3sg <q>Yet through
                  which type of death did he die?,</q> <foreign xml:lang="grc">μόρῳ</foreign> is the topic component, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁποίῳ</foreign> is a focus
                  component, and an unmarked element follows <ptr target="#beschi2018" loc="179"/>. Setting, topic
                  and focus components are optional in the sentence, yet can aid discourse coherence
                  <ptr target="#beschi2018" loc="181"/>. </p>
               <p>Lexically, coherence and cohesion can be achieved by the use of synonyms (e.g. <emph>love</emph> and <emph>adore</emph>) or antonyms (e.g. <emph>love</emph> and <emph>hate</emph>), the repetition of
                  keywords (e.g. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασία</foreign> <q>horse exercise</q> in Xenophon’s treatise) (cf. <ptr target="#hutchinson2017"/>), and scene-setting adverbial phrases, such as <q>in this treatise</q> or <q>to sum up the previous discussion.</q> </p>
               <p>Pragmatically, coherence and cohesion can be achieved by the adherence to a
                  register and genre, any derivation from which would derail the reader. A genre is
                  a culturally determined norm for a text type <ptr target="#biber2009" loc="16"/>, with
                  genre markers appearing at the start and end of the text, e.g. once upon a time
                  and they lived happily ever after in English fairy tales. A register is a
                  situationally conditioned shape of a text <ptr target="#biber2009" loc="6"/>, with
                  register markers appearing throughout a text, e.g. <foreign xml:lang="fr">tu</foreign> as opposed to <foreign xml:lang="fr">vous</foreign> in French
                  informal vs formal discourses (see also <ptr target="#adams2013" loc="107–110"/> <ptr target="#bentein2013"/> <ptr target="#bentein2016"/>
                  <ptr target="#willi2003"/> <ptr target="#willi2010"/>). The choice of and adherence to a genre and register
                  determines the amount of drawing on shared / background knowledge (cf. inference),
                  the amount of repetition needed, and the way of presenting several events (e.g.
                  impressionistic vs sequential). </p>
               <p>The present article focuses on a type of lexico-syntactic device which contributes
                  to discourse cohesion at the lexical, syntactic and pragmatic levels, that is
                  support-verb constructions, such as <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασίαν X ποιέομαι</foreign> to <q>do X horse-exercise.</q>
                  Support-verb constructions are lexical devices in that their two elements (the
                  verb and the noun) form a unit as regards meaning <ptr target="#lipka1992"/>. However, given
                  their frequent discontiguity, the two elements must be linked together by means of
                  syntactic dependency, with the noun filling the object slot of the verb.
                  Support-verb constructions contrast with simplex verbs of similar meaning, e.g.
                  for <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασίαν ποιέομαι</foreign>, there would be <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππεύω</foreign> <q>to ride</q> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππάζομαι</foreign> <q>to drive /
                  to ride</q> (Xenophon, <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> 10.13), which are
                  regular denominal formations (in -<foreign xml:lang="grc">ευω</foreign> and -<foreign xml:lang="grc">άζω/άζομαι)</foreign> <ptr target="#vanemdeboas2019" loc="274–275"/>.</p>
               <p>Support-verb constructions are characterised by their variability (e.g. <emph>he breaks/broke her/the heart</emph>), ambiguity (e.g. <emph>he broke her chocolate heart</emph> which has a literal reading),
                  and discontinuity (e.g. <emph>he broke her young heart</emph>) <ptr target="#pasquer2018" loc="2585"/>. All three characteristics are problematic for automated
                  extraction, since <quote rend="inline">if MWEs [sc. multi-word expressions] are treated by general,
                  compositional methods of linguistic analysis, there is … an overgeneration
                  problem</quote> <ptr target="#sag2002" loc="3"/>. Overgeneration means that false positives are
                  included in the output and impact on the F1 score, which indicates the accuracy of
                  the result: </p>
             <dhq:example>  <p>
                  <mml:math>
                     <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>F</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mn>1</mn>
                        </mrow>
                     </msub>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">=</mo>
                     <mfrac xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mn>2</mn>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <msup>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>r</mi>
                                 <mi>e</mi>
                                 <mi>c</mi>
                                 <mi>a</mi>
                                 <mi>l</mi>
                                 <mi>l</mi>
                              </mrow>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mo>-</mo>
                                 <mn>1</mn>
                              </mrow>
                           </msup>
                           <mo>+</mo>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <msup>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>p</mi>
                                 <mi>r</mi>
                                 <mi>e</mi>
                                 <mi>c</mi>
                                 <mi>i</mi>
                                 <mi>s</mi>
                                 <mi>i</mi>
                                 <mi>o</mi>
                                 <mi>n</mi>
                              </mrow>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mo>-</mo>
                                 <mn>1</mn>
                              </mrow>
                           </msup>
                        </mrow>
                     </mfrac>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">=</mo>
                     <mn xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">2</mn>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mfrac xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>p</mi>
                           <mi>r</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>c</mi>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>o</mi>
                           <mi>n</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mo>×</mo>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>r</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>c</mi>
                           <mi>a</mi>
                           <mi>l</mi>
                           <mi>l</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>p</mi>
                           <mi>r</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>c</mi>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>o</mi>
                           <mi>n</mi>
                           <mo>+</mo>
                           <mi>r</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>c</mi>
                           <mi>a</mi>
                           <mi>l</mi>
                           <mi>l</mi>
                        </mrow>
                     </mfrac>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">=</mo>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mfrac xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mn>2</mn>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>p</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mn>2</mn>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>p</mi>
                           <mo>+</mo>
                           <mi>f</mi>
                           <mi>p</mi>
                           <mo>+</mo>
                           <mi>f</mi>
                           <mi>n</mi>
                        </mrow>
                     </mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <mml:math>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">p</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">r</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">e</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">c</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">i</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">s</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">i</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">o</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">n</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">=</mo>
                     <mfrac xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>n</mi>
                           <mi>u</mi>
                           <mi>m</mi>
                           <mi>b</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>r</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>o</mi>
                           <mi>f</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>r</mi>
                           <mi>u</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>p</mi>
                           <mi>o</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>v</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>r</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                           <mi>u</mi>
                           <mi>l</mi>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>o</mi>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>a</mi>
                           <mi>l</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>n</mi>
                           <mi>u</mi>
                           <mi>m</mi>
                           <mi>b</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>r</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>o</mi>
                           <mi>f</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>p</mi>
                           <mi>o</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>v</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>r</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                           <mi>u</mi>
                           <mi>l</mi>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                        </mrow>
                     </mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <mml:math>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">r</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">e</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">c</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">a</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">l</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">l</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">=</mo>
                     <mfrac xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>n</mi>
                           <mi>u</mi>
                           <mi>m</mi>
                           <mi>b</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>r</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>o</mi>
                           <mi>f</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>r</mi>
                           <mi>u</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>p</mi>
                           <mi>o</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>v</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>r</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                           <mi>u</mi>
                           <mi>l</mi>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>o</mi>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>a</mi>
                           <mi>l</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>n</mi>
                           <mi>u</mi>
                           <mi>m</mi>
                           <mi>b</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>r</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>o</mi>
                           <mi>f</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                           <mi>a</mi>
                           <mi>m</mi>
                           <mi>p</mi>
                           <mi>l</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>h</mi>
                           <mi>a</mi>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                           <mi>h</mi>
                           <mi>o</mi>
                           <mi>u</mi>
                           <mi>l</mi>
                           <mi>d</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>h</mi>
                           <mi>a</mi>
                           <mi>v</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>b</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>n</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>d</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>n</mi>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>f</mi>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                           <mi>d</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>a</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <mi>p</mi>
                           <mi>o</mi>
                           <mi>s</mi>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>t</mi>
                           <mi>i</mi>
                           <mi>v</mi>
                           <mi>e</mi>
                        </mrow>
                     </mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
               </p>
               <p>tp = a <q>true positive</q> (a support-verb construction the algorithm returns that is
                  one)</p>
               <p>fp = a <q>false positive</q> (a support-verb construction the algorithm thinks is one
                  but is not)</p>
               <p>fn = a <q>false negative</q> (a support-verb construction the algorithm does not think
                  is one but is)</p>
               <p>The F1 score oscillates between ideal 1, i.e. maximum accuracy, and 0.</p></dhq:example>
               <p> Furthermore, automated tools rely on training data, such as the annotated PARSEME
                  shared task (<ref
                     target="https://typo.uni-konstanz.de/parseme/index.php/results/shared-task"
                     >https://typo.uni-konstanz.de/parseme/index.php/results/shared-task</ref>) for
                  18 modern languages, and very large and expandable corpora (e.g. <ptr target="#scheible2013"/>).<note> They accommodate only the <quote rend="inline">full, auxiliary and modal verb</quote> options
                     <ptr target="#scheible2013" loc="4"/>. Support verbs are neither full verbs nor
                     auxiliaries, in that they retain a reduced argument grid <ptr target="#butt1997" loc="145f"/> <ptr target="#cinque2004" loc="172, n.31"/> <ptr target="#loporcaro2022" loc="216"/>. In the further uses, they
                     only accommodate verb-prepositional phrase structures (cf. <ptr target="#kamber2008"/>). <ptr target="#cap2015"/> however expand their approach to support-verb constructions in the
                     form of verb-object structures.</note> Conversely, the classical Greek corpus
                  of data is comparatively small and cannot be expanded easily, such that training
                  data is difficult to obtain (see also <ptr target="#sheinfux2019"/>). Furthermore, when
                  drawing on previous work on languages other than classical Greek<note> Classical
                     and modern Greek differ significantly, such that e.g. the PARSEME shared task
                     modern Greek corpus is not of use as training data. </note>, it must be borne
                  in mind that support-verb constructions are language-specific, such that
                  cross-linguistic studies can only point the direction (e.g. <emph>eine
                     Reise </emph>machen vs <emph>to </emph>take<emph> a
                     trip</emph>). Finally, contiguity / adjacency is not compulsory in support-verb
                  constructions <ptr target="#pasquer2018"/> <ptr target="#sheinfux2019"/>. In Greek, no word-order
                  constraint akin to the English subject-verb-object exists (e.g. Lysias, Speech
                  3.22 <foreign xml:lang="grc">συνθήκας πρὸς αὐτὸν ποιησάμενος</foreign> agreements.acc – with him – making <q>making
                  agreements with him</q>).<note> Automated tools often had to restrict either the
                     number and type of verbs or nouns, thus limiting the range of support-verb
                     constructions from the outset and rarely detecting candidates such as
                     reconceptualised concrete nouns, e.g. in <emph>to take a photo</emph>
                     <ptr target="#radimsky2011"/> and verbs of realisation, e.g. <emph>on </emph><foreign xml:lang="fr">a
                     donné <emph>˂</emph>imposé<emph>, </emph>infligé,
                     collé, filé<emph>˃ à Jean une amende de 30 euros
                     </emph></foreign> <ptr target="#melcuk2004"/>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fully automated approaches rely on algorithms that classify the input data into
                  output categories (here support-verb construction vs not support-verb
                     construction).<note> The exact definition of support-verb constructions differs
                     between researchers, not just approaches, such that comparison of approaches
                     and results is often difficult. </note> These are trained on a suitably
                  prepared training corpus. Techniques of analysis combatting the above issues have
                  been suggested in the literature, such as <quote rend="inline">listing words with spaces,
                  hierarchically organized lexicons, restricted combinatoric rules, lexical
                  selection, idiomatic constructions, and simple statistical affinity</quote> <ptr target="#doucet2004"/> <ptr target="#sag2002" loc="15"/>. Furthermore, marking up support verbs in
                  the training data improved support-verb-construction identification <ptr target="#cap2015"/>.<note> Support-verb constructions are identified by means of the
                     word-association measure of the log-likelihood. The log-likelihood is
                     calculated based on item frequency. </note> <ptr target="#cordeiro2019" loc="103"/>
                  find a noticeable difference in performance between seen structures (max. F1 =
                  0.83) and unseen structures (max. F1 = 0.31), across classifiers evaluated. </p>
               <p>We are not aware of existing work that algorithmically extracts support-verb
                  constructions from classical Greek texts, nor have we opted for a fully automated
                  approach. We build a corpus for Sketch Engine <ptr target="#kilgarriff2014"/>. Sketch
                  Engine is a web-based corpus-analysis tool that allows the user to inspect the
                  lexical makeup of a text (cf. keyword lists), explore the surroundings of select
                  items (cf. concordances) and identify fixed expressions in a text (cf. n-grams)
                  (see also <ptr target="#maiko2020"/> <ptr target="#mcgillivray2013"/>).<note> Concordances are
                     vertical tables that put the attestations of the word form or lemma queried for
                     in a corpus one underneath the other with the context to the left and the
                     right. N-grams are sequences of lemmata or word forms that always appear in
                     exactly the same order (e.g. English <emph>in spite of </emph>which
                     forms a compound preposition would be a strong n-gram in a corpus of modern
                     English). </note> Sketch Engine combines the following functionalities: (i)
                  operation on lemmata rather than word forms, (ii) definition of any corpus, (iii)
                  concordancing, and (iv) creation of n-grams. </p>
               <p>Tools that operate on the word form as attested in the text are less informative
                  for classical Greek than for e.g. English as classical Greek is a morphologically
                  rich language, such that e.g. verbal lemmata change stems through the tenses (e.g.
                  <q>to see</q> – <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁράω</foreign> present, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὄψομαι / ὀφθήσομαι</foreign> future, <foreign xml:lang="grc">εἶδον / ὤφθην</foreign> aorist,
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἑώρακα / ἑώραμαι / ὄπωπα / ὦμμαι</foreign> perfect). Tools that predefine or/and allow
                  for limited modification of the corpus of analysis only necessitate extensive
                  manual correction when a different corpus is selected due to research objectives. </p>
               <p>Concordances and n-grams make possible the extraction of support-verb
                  constructions when one component is known (either the verb or the noun).<note>
                     This distinguishes them from fully automated tools. </note> Our approach does
                  not take the human researcher out of the equation but facilitates their analysis
                  by providing ranked and easily interpretable collocation metrics. For example,
                  Sketch Engine provides the feature of analysed concordance tables, which can be
                  sorted by various lexical affinity measures. We opt below for the <title
                     rend="italic">logDice</title>. The <title rend="italic">logDice</title> is a measure of
                  lexical affinity between two items with a maximum value of 14 <ptr target="#rychly2008"/>: </p>
               <dhq:example><p>
                  <mml:math>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">l</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">o</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">g</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">D</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">i</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">c</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">e</mi>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">=</mo>
                     <mn xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">14</mn>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">+</mo>
                     <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>l</mi>
                           <mi>o</mi>
                           <mi>g</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mn>2</mn>
                        </mrow>
                     </msub>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">=</mo>
                     <mn xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">14</mn>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">+</mo>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>l</mi>
                           <mi>o</mi>
                           <mi>g</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mn>2</mn>
                        </mrow>
                     </msub>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mfrac xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mn>2</mn>
                           <msub>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>f</mi>
                              </mrow>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>x</mi>
                                 <mi>y</mi>
                              </mrow>
                           </msub>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <msub>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>f</mi>
                              </mrow>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>x</mi>
                              </mrow>
                           </msub>
                           <mo>+</mo>
                           <mi> </mi>
                           <msub>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>f</mi>
                              </mrow>
                              <mrow>
                                 <mi>y</mi>
                              </mrow>
                           </msub>
                        </mrow>
                     </mfrac>
                  </mml:math>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <mml:math>
                     <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>f</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>x</mi>
                        </mrow>
                     </msub>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">=</mo>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">n</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">u</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">m</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">b</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">e</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">r</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">o</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">f</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">o</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">c</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">c</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">u</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">r</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">e</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">n</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">c</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">e</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">s</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">o</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">f</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">w</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">o</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">r</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">d</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">X</mi>
                  </mml:math>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <mml:math>
                     <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>f</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>y</mi>
                        </mrow>
                     </msub>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">=</mo>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">n</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">u</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">m</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">b</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">e</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">r</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">o</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">f</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">o</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">c</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">c</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">u</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">r</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">e</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">n</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">c</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">e</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">s</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">o</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">f</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">w</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">o</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">r</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">d</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Y</mi>
                  </mml:math>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <mml:math>
                     <msub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>f</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mrow>
                           <mi>x</mi>
                           <mi>y</mi>
                        </mrow>
                     </msub>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">=</mo>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">n</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">u</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">m</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">b</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">e</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">r</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">o</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">f</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">c</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">o</mi>
                     <mo xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">-</mo>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">o</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">c</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">c</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">u</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">r</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">e</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">n</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">c</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">e</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">s</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">o</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">f</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">w</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">o</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">r</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">d</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">s</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">X</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">a</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">n</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">d</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Y</mi>
                     <mi xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> </mi>
                  </mml:math>
               </p></dhq:example>
               <p>Co-occurrence needs to be defined either with regard to distance (i.e. number of
                  intervening items) or with regard to structure (e.g. syntactic relationship
                  between X and Y). Co-occurrence is here defined as appearing within 5 items of
                  each other and in the same syntactic projection. Sketch Engine allows for
                  individual definitions of co-occurrence to be applied. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2 The Fabric of the Text: Building a Sketch Engine Corpus for Classical
                  Attic</head>
               <p>We built a corpus for Sketch Engine based on a large sample of classical literary
                  Attic historiography, oratory and prose<note> See footnote 1. </note> and adapted
                  the code for <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title>.</p>
               <div><head>Approach</head><p>It is necessary to tag each word in the source text (the input) and
                  prepare the tagged corpus for import to Sketch Engine (the output). We rely on
                  existing tools for tagging and analysis as far as possible and present a Python
                  program that applies an existing tagging tool (Perseus) to each word in the
                  original text and prepares the corpus for import to Sketch Engine.</p></div>
               <div><head>Choice of External Tools</head><p> For analysing words, correctness and completeness are
                  critical. We chose the Perseus Digital Library Project as an established, widely
                  reviewed and freely-available source of analyses for individual words. We chose
                  the commercial Sketch Engine tool due to its large feature set and ease-of-use. We
                  are confident in the correctness of the tool due to widespread commercial use in
                  other languages. Commercial applications enable development of a large feature set
                  and easy-to-use user interface that could not be built within the scope of a
                  research project.</p></div>
               <div><head>Overview</head><p>A Python program was written that converts TEI<note> TEI describes a
                     family of standards for electronically representing texts. More details on the
                     TEI format can be found under <ref
                        target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ST.html"
                        >https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ST.html</ref> and <ref
                        target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html"
                        >https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html</ref>.</note>-conformant
                  Greek texts into a tagged corpus for the Sketch Engine tool. The program is
                  extensible and could easily be used with other TEI-conformant texts. To enable
                  anyone to run our open-source program and convert their own texts to a format that
                  can be used by Sketch Engine, we make our program accessible in two formats:</p></div>
               <list rend="numbered">
                  <item>as a web-based tool (powered by Google Colab), so that anyone can use our
                     tool on their own texts with the click of a single button in their web browser,
                     without having to download or install software;</item>
                  <item>for advanced users, a Python script in a git repository, so that our program
                     can be used within other scripts, and any changes that users wish to make can
                     be easily shared with us.</item>
               </list>
               <p>We hope that releasing our code as a web-based tool (that does not require any
                  software to be downloaded or installed, or the user’s computer to be configured in
                  any way) enables the community to reproduce our results at the click of a single
                  button. We also hope that by making all of our code open-source and easily
                  accessible, the community may be able to apply Sketch Engine in their own
                  work.</p>
               <div><head>Accessing and Running the Program </head><p>Our system is easy to use and we facilitate
                  access through two platforms. The first option suitable for annotating small
                  texts; the second option is more useful for large corpora.</p></div>
               <div>
               <head>Option 1: Run the Tool in Your Web Browser</head>
               <p>Open the Google Colab notebook: <ref
                     target="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1JEuEWVe1t0AyBROb3NwnVMfufPOtzX_8?usp=sharing"
                     >https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1JEuEWVe1t0AyBROb3NwnVMfufPOtzX_8?usp=sharing</ref>
               </p>
               <p>Click <q>Runtime -˃ Run All.</q> When prompted, choose an input file to upload. When
                  the tagging is finished, the output vertical file will be downloaded
                  automatically, as shown in Figure 1.</p>
              
               <figure>
                  <head>Python program</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Screenshot of a python program which defines a class called <q>PerseusAnalysis</q>. </figDesc>
               </figure>
               </div>
               <div>
               
               <head>Option 2: (Advanced) Clone the Git Repository</head>
               <p>The repository can be found here: <ref
                     target="https://github.com/MatthewIreland/xml_lemmatiser_tagger"
                     >https://github.com/MatthewIreland/xml_lemmatiser_tagger</ref>.</p>
                  <div><head>The Python Program</head><p>In the main loop, an analysis is looked up in Perseus and then
                  appended to the output file for Sketch Engine (and also recorded in the Analysis
                  Cache in case the word form appears again later in the text). Care is taken to
                  make sure that metadata corresponding to markers in the source text (such as
                  section numbers, chapter numbers or line numbers) is also recorded in the correct
                  place in the output file so it can be used in Sketch Engine. If an error occurs
                  (e.g. Perseus cannot analyse a word) we record this. Some words that cause errors
                  can be manually annotated (the analysis cache can be initialised with these words
                  on startup). The flowchart in Figure 2 provides an overview of the process:</p></div>
               
               <figure>
                  <head>Web-based conversion tool</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                  <figDesc>
                     Screenshot of a flowchart for thge conversion process. The process outlines the workflow for processing XML tags, analyzing tags that exist, logging errors, and storing analysis from Perseus
                  </figDesc>
               </figure>
               
               <p>If the same word appears multiple times in the source text, it is only looked up
                  once in Perseus and the same results are printed to the vertical file wherever the
                  word appears. After the word has been looked up using Perseus for the first time,
                  it is added to the Analysis Cache. If the word appears again, the analysis will be
                  retrieved from the Analysis Cache rather than from Perseus. This reduces the
                  overall execution time as fewer network requests are required.</p>
                  <div><head>Input and Output Formats</head><p>The input files are obtained from the Perseus Digital
                  Library. They are in a TEI-compliant format. The output format is a <q>vertical
                  file</q> that can be imported into Sketch Engine. For each word in the corpus, the
                  vertical file includes a lemma, POS tag, and nominal/verbal morphology tags.<note>
                     Perseus contains tags regarding (i) verbal morphology, (ii) nominal morphology,
                     (iii) part of speech, (iv) dialect, (v) genre, (vi) word formation, (vii)
                     semantics and the tag <q>rare</q> regarding the attestation of items. The tags found
                     in the classical Attic literary corpus were grouped manually into the above
                     categories. Xenophon’s <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> did not show any tags that would have
                     necessitated the creation of a new category.</note>
               </p></div> </div>
               <div><head>Errors</head><p>We focus on the reliability of our results. All errors (i.e. where Perseus
                  fails to lemmatise or tag a word) are logged and manually inspected. Where errors
                  can be corrected (e.g. through manual lemmatising or tagging), the manual
                  annotations are added to the analysis cache on startup so that Perseus is not
                  required for lemmatising/tagging and the words will be correctly lemmatised/tagged
                  on a second pass through the data.<note> Note that Perseus does not currently have
                     access to pre-defined multi-word expression structures in the form of
                     <quote rend="inline">listening words with spaces</quote> or listing <quote rend="inline">idiomatic expressions</quote> <ptr target="#constant2017" loc="844"/>. </note>
               </p></div>
               <div><head>Design Choices</head><p>Many have previously built parsers for TEI-compliant texts. Why
                  build another one? We needed a fine level of control over the parser in order to
                  manage errors and ensure reliability of results. Hence, we used Python’s XML
                  parsing libraries rather than an existing parser specifically for TEI texts.</p></div>
               <p>Another tool considered was Morpheus. However, we found that the results from
                  Morpheus were very sensitive to the changes in the build configuration. Results
                  may change when Morpheus has been built on different computers, such that it is
                  difficult to trust the results. Hence, we opted to use the online version of
                  Perseus, which seems to generate consistent and more reliable analyses.</p>
               <p>The Perseus API permits the lemmata and tags to be returned in a structured
                  format. However, a bug means that API parameters are not correctly parsed when
                  data is returned in XML format. This bug was fixed by the Perseus authors when
                  data is returned in HTML format, but not when data is returned in XML format. To
                  see the bug (source version 20110527), look at the Perseus source code and compare
                  [3a] and [3b]:</p>
               
              <dhq:example> <p>[3a] ./sgml/reading/src/perseus/controllers/document/MorphController.java</p>
               <p>[3b] ./sgml/reading/src/perseus/controllers/document/XmlMorphController.java</p></dhq:example>
               
               
               <p>Note in MorphController.java the presence of the following code to decode a UTF-8
                  input parameter:</p>
               
               <eg lang="java"><![CDATA[
               word = URLDecoder.decode(word, "utf-8");
               word = new String(word.getBytes("8859_1"),"UTF-8");
               if (language.equals(Language.GREEK)) {
                  word = GreekEncodingAnalyzer.transcode(word, "PerseusBetaCode");
               }]]>
               </eg>
          
               <p>This is not present in the XmlMorphController but would be required in order to
                  correctly parse inputs. Note in MorphController, the presence of the comment
                  <quote rend="inline">//don't need this because user is only entering BetaCode,</quote> which is not correct
                  because forward and back slashes may be used in betacode. Since they will be
                  encoded as URL parameters, they need decoding correctly in the Java source.</p>
               <div><head>Modifications for <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title></head><p>A small modification was required for Xenophon’s
                  <title rend="italic">Minor Works</title>, which <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> is one of, as it
                  included a <q>group</q> XML tag that had not been seen in any previous text. By
                  default, the program throws an error if it sees an unknown tag, so that the user
                  can decide how this tag should be processed (e.g. should metadata from this tag be
                  copied to the output). However, as there is only one <q>group</q> tag in the text, the
                  software did not need to take any further action upon seeing this tag. Therefore,
                  the only modification required was to add <q>group</q> to the list of known XML tags so
                  that this tag did not cause an error. The Perseus analysis succeeded for every
                  word in <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> text and there were no errors. The
                  processing of this text executed in 11 minutes at 4 seconds.</p></div>
               <div><head>Implementation in Sketch Engine</head><p>In order for our .vert file to be correctly read
                  by Sketch Engine, especially with regard to (i) the column names (lemma, POS tag,
                  verbal morphology, nominal morphology), (ii) the section and sentence markers and
                  (iii) the types of metadata we include, we produced a modified corpus
                  configuration file: <ref
                     target="https://github.com/MatthewIreland/linguini/blob/main/files/configFile.txt"
                     >https://github.com/MatthewIreland/linguini/blob/main/files/configFile.txt</ref>.<note>
                     We owe thanks go to Barbara McGillivray (Turing Institute London) for letting
                     us see the configuration file for her Latin Sketch Engine corpus for
                     comparison.</note>
               </p></div>
               <div><head>Accuracy Tests</head><p>The errors.txt file is created by the Python program while looking
                  up each word form of a text on Perseus. The word forms for which the lookup fails
                  are appended to errors.txt. Word forms can cause errors related to the POS tag
                  (<q>cannot find POS tag</q>), the morphological tag (<q>cannot find verbal / nominal
                  morphology</q>) and the lemma (<q>cannot find lemma</q>). The error.txt file is then
                  processed to find unique errors, i.e. the minimum set of words that would have to
                  be manually annotated and used for initialising the analysis cache to reduce the
                  total error count to zero. Table 1 summarises the error rates for the classical
                  literary corpus<note> See footnote 1.</note>, a manually annotated sub-sample of
                  this corpus<note> Thucydides, Histories V; Xenophon, Anabasis I–IV; Isocrates,
                     Speech 4; Lysias, Speeches 1, 3, 7, 12, 14, 19, 22, 30–32; Plato, Gorgias;
                     Aristotle, Politics I.</note>, and <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title>. </p></div>
              
               <table>
                  <head>error.txt file</head>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell>Corpus</cell>
                     <cell>Number of Words</cell>
                     <cell>Number of Unique Errors in error.txt</cell>
                     <cell>Percentage of Error</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>Corpus of text</cell>
                     <cell>492,620</cell>
                     <cell>451</cell>
                     <cell>0.09%</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>Test sample</cell>
                     <cell>117,783</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                     <cell>0.05%</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>
                        <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>7,144</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0.00%</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>The second measure is manual assessment of the Test sample using the <title
                     rend="italic">Thesaurus Linguae Gracae </title>(TLG henceforth), in Text search –
                  proximity – lemma. The results for select items are presented in Table 2.</p>
              
               <table>
                  <head><title rend="italic">Thesaurus Linguae Graecae</title> vs Sketch Engine</head>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell>Lemma</cell>
                     <cell><title rend="italic">Thesaurus Linguae Graecae</title></cell>
                     <cell>Sketch Engine Test Sample</cell>
                     <cell>LogDice</cell>
                     <cell></cell>
                     <cell></cell>
                     <cell></cell>
                     <cell></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>Total </cell>
                     <cell>Co-occurrence with PN</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <emph>logDice</emph>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Total </cell>
                     <cell>Co-occurrence with PN </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <emph>logDice</emph>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>error vis-à-vis TLG data</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>δίκη (PN)</cell>
                     <cell>114</cell>
                     <cell>n/a</cell>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>113</cell>
                     <cell>n/a</cell>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>λαμβάνω</cell>
                     <cell>257</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>11.27</cell>
                     <cell>253</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                     <cell>11.18</cell>
                     <cell>0%</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>δίδωμι</cell>
                     <cell>171</cell>
                     <cell>53</cell>
                     <cell>12.57</cell>
                     <cell>171</cell>
                     <cell>47</cell>
                     <cell>12.40</cell>
                     <cell>1.4%</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>ἀπολείπω </cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>ø</cell>
                     <cell>n/a</cell>
                     <cell>15<note> Lemmatised as ἀπολιμπάνω</note>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>ø</cell>
                     <cell>n/a</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>φέυγω</cell>
                     <cell>92</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>8.898</cell>
                     <cell>102</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>8.84</cell>
                     <cell>0%</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>συμμαχία (PN)</cell>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                     <cell>n/a</cell>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                     <cell>n/a</cell>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>ποιέω</cell>
                     <cell>608</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>9.71</cell>
                     <cell>622</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>9.50</cell>
                     <cell>2.2%</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>ἀνίημι</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>10.02</cell>
                     <cell>80<note> The preposition ἄνευ ‘without’ and the adverb ἄνω ‘above’ can be
                           parsed as forms of ἀνίημι.</note>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>ø</cell>
                     <cell>n/a</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>ἀφίημι</cell>
                     <cell>34</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>9.52</cell>
                     <cell>62<note> ἄπειμι ‘I will go’ shares several forms with ἀφίημι. </note>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>ø</cell>
                     <cell>n/a</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>ὅπλον (PN)</cell>
                     <cell>75</cell>
                     <cell>n/a</cell>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>75</cell>
                     <cell>n/a</cell>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>ἔχω</cell>
                     <cell>760</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>8.75</cell>
                     <cell>756</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>8.76</cell>
                     <cell>0%</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>παραδίδωμι</cell>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>11.53</cell>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>11.27</cell>
                     <cell>2.3%</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>As both the number of attestations and the number of co-occurrences factor into
                  the <title rend="italic">logDice</title>, we calculate the percentage of error for the
                     <title rend="italic">logDice </title>as an overall measure of performance. Sketch
                  Engine performs at the 2.5% threshold, i.e. the percentage of error for all the
                  measurements taken falls below this threshold. </p>
               <p>Errors that are likely to appear when using our code on a new corpus include (i)
                  <emph><foreign xml:lang="grc">hapax legomena</foreign></emph>, (ii) personal names (that are not
                  catalogued in standard dictionaries), (iii) words that are misspelled and (iv) any
                  not yet considered punctuation marks or textcritical marks that are fused with
                  word forms and thus prevent the lookup from being successful. Moreover, e.g. epic,
                  dialectal or post-classical word forms (and associated lemmata) cause errors due
                  to the limitations of the standard dictionaries which Perseus accesses. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>3 Cohesion / Coherence through Discontinuity: Support-Verb Constructions </head>
               <p>Support-verb constructions are combinations of a verb and a noun that fill the
                  predicate slot of a sentence (e.g. <emph>I </emph>took the decision<emph> to do it</emph>) <ptr target="#butt1995"/>. The noun is the semantic head of the
                  construction <ptr target="#nagy2013" loc="329"/> and since filling the predicate slot needs
                  to be predicative or reconceptualised as predicative (e.g. <emph
                     >I</emph> took a picture<emph> of him</emph> <ptr target="#radimsky2011"/>).<note>
                     This is unlike in internal-object structures, such as English to run a race, in
                     which the verb is the semantic head and the noun qualifies this head <ptr target="#vanemdeboas2019" loc="364–365"/>. 
                        <ptr target="#pompei2006"/> argues for such structures to
                        univerbate in the form of noun incorporation (e.g. <foreign xml:lang="grc">οἰκοδομέω</foreign> from <foreign xml:lang="grc">οἶκος</foreign> <q>house</q>
                        + <foreign xml:lang="grc">δομέω</foreign> <q>to build</q>). The same cannot happen for support-verb constructions
                     given their differing internal structure. </note> The agent of the event
                  referred to by the noun must be co-referential with the grammatical subject of the
                  verb, at least in non-causative and non-passive support-verb constructions (e.g.
                     <emph>I </emph>paid attention<emph> to the talk</emph> vs
                     <emph>I </emph>caught his attention vs <emph>I
                  </emph>directed their attention<emph> to him</emph>).<note> The link
                     between active, causative and passive support-verb-construction patterns in the
                     sense of the causative and passive as derivations of the active is captured in
                     the idea of prototypes by <ptr target="#gross1998"/>, <ptr target="#melcuk1996"/> <ptr target="#melcuk2004"/> <ptr target="#kamber2008"/>.
                  </note> The noun and the verb contribute to the argument structure (e.g. <emph>I </emph>gave<emph> him </emph>the impression<emph> that I wanted to leave</emph>, where the verb is the head of the
                  indirect object (sc. <emph>him</emph>) but the noun is the head of the
                  direct object (sc. <emph>that I wanted to leave</emph>)), unlike in
                  auxiliary-verb constructions (e.g. <emph>I </emph>have read<emph> him the book</emph>) <ptr target="#bowern2008"/>
                  <ptr target="#butt2010"/> <ptr target="#butt2013a"/> <ptr target="#butt2013b"/>. The noun and the verb contribute to the semantic
                  structure (e.g. <emph>I gave him the impression that …</emph> vs <emph>I got the impression that …</emph>), such that removal of either
                  component would break up the support-verb construction.<note> For a formal
                     decision tree, which illustrates the many decisions to be made: <ref
                        target="https://parsemefr.lis-lab.fr/parseme-st-guidelines/1.0/?page=060_Specific_tests_-_categorize_VMWEs/020_Light-verb_constructions"
                        >https://parsemefr.lis-lab.fr/parseme-st-guidelines/1.0/?page=060_Specific_tests_-_categorize_VMWEs/020_Light-verb_constructions</ref>
                     (accessed 28 June 2021).</note> Support-verb constructions in classical Greek
                  have not received much scholarly attention, with the exception of the support verb
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">ποιέομαι</foreign> <q>to do</q> <ptr target="#banos2015"/> <ptr target="#cock1981"/> <ptr target="#fendel2021"/> <ptr target="#jimenezlopez2011"/>
                  <ptr target="#jimenezlopez2012"/> <ptr target="#jimenezlopez2016"/> <ptr target="#jimenezlopez2021"/> <ptr target="#marini2010"/>
                  <ptr target="#zilliacus1956"/> <ptr target="#zilliacus1956"/>. </p>
               <p> For their functioning as devices to further discourse cohesion, three aspects of
                  support-verb constructions are of interest (see also <ptr target="#storrer2009"/>): </p>
               <list type="ordered" rend="numbered"><item>They are multi-morphemic, thus (often) allowing modification of either
                  component (e.g. <emph>He confidently gave a long speech</emph>, where the
                  verb is modified by the adverb of manner <emph>confidently</emph>,
                  whereas the noun is modified by the adjective of degree <emph
                     >long</emph>).<note> Diachronically, there is the potential for univerbation
                        under certain circumstances, e.g. <foreign xml:lang="grc">λόγον ποιέομαι</foreign> into later <foreign xml:lang="grc">λογοποιέομαι</foreign> <q>to
                        report</q> <ptr target="#creissels2016"/> <ptr target="#lehmann2020"/> <ptr target="#rosen2020"/>.</note> This allows for the
                  fine-tuning of the predicate expression <ptr target="#didakowski2020"/>. Moreover,
                  their being multi-morphemic and in many cases internally analytic allows for the
                  condensation of several support-verb constructions by deletion of a recurring
                  support verb (e.g. <emph>He made </emph>a suggestion and an
                  assumption<emph> at the same time </emph> <ptr target="#gross1998"/>); it also
                  allows for the expansion of a support-verb construction across a stretch of
                  discourse, e.g. by means of relativisation (e.g. <emph>The idea
                     </emph>which<emph> I had yesterday was really useful</emph>) and
                  pronominalisation (e.g. <emph>I had a great idea yesterday, I suddenly
                     had </emph>it<emph> on the train to London</emph>).<note> In Greek,
                     inference of a contextually salient support verb and / or predicative noun is
                     permissible even without pronominalisation (e.g. Plato, <title rend="italic"
                        >Gorgias</title> 479d <foreign xml:lang="grc">καὶ ἀεὶ τὸν ἀδικοῦντα τοῦ ἀδικουμένου
                     ἀθλιώτερον εἶναι καὶ τὸν μὴ διδόντα δίκην τοῦ διδόντος</foreign> <q>and that the
                     wrongdoer is always more wretched than the wronged and the unpunished than the
                     punished</q>). </note> Finally, it allows for the noun to be used recurringly in
                  the discourse without being part of the same support-verb construction at all
                  times (see <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασία</foreign> <q>horsemanship / horse exercise</q> in <title rend="italic">On
                     Horsemanship</title>) <ptr target="#jackson2016" loc="16–21"/>.</item>
               <item>They are discontiguous, thus (often) allowing for items to intervene between
                  the noun and the verb, while the support-verb construction is held together by the
                  syntactic dependency relation between the verb and the noun (e.g. <emph>I had </emph>a great<emph> idea</emph>).<note> <quote rend="inline">The
                     syntactic distance between two components is defined as the number of elements
                     in the syntactic dependency chain between these two components, regardless of
                     the direction of the dependencies and excluding the components themselves</quote>
                     <ptr target="#pasquer2018" loc="2589"/>.</note> This allows for the bracketing of pieces
                  of information, thus assigning them unequivocally to the support-verb
                  construction, e.g. Lysias, Speech 3.22 <foreign xml:lang="grc">συνθήκας πρὸς αὐτὸν ποιησάμενος</foreign>
                  agreements.acc – with him – making <q>making agreements with him.</q> More generally,
                  this ties in with Lakoff and Johnson’s (<ref target="#lakoff1980">1980 p. 130</ref>) observation that a semantic
                  link is reflected in the formal expression (cf. principle of iconicity). They
                  conclude that <emph>I taught Greek to Harry</emph> and <emph
                     >I taught Harry Greek</emph> differ in that only the latter refers to the
                  acquisition of Greek, which is reflected in the formal expression by the
                  positioning of <emph>Harry</emph> (see also <ptr target="#frenda2017"/>). </item>
               <item>They are semi-compositional, thus (often) developing a meaning different
                  from and more specific than the related simplex verb <ptr target="#sanromanvilas2009"/> <ptr target="#storrer2009"/> <emph><foreign xml:lang="de">unterrichten</foreign></emph> <q>to teach</q> vs <emph><foreign xml:lang="de">Unterricht erteilen</foreign></emph> <q>to give a lesson</q>). Support-verb constructions
                  reflect a range of degrees of compositionality. For example, in<emph>
                     to have an idea</emph>, abstracting from concrete <emph>to possess /
                     to have</emph> to <emph>to belong to / to have</emph> explains the
                  meaning of the support-verb construction <ptr target="#hermann2020" loc="58–61"/>; in <emph>to take a picture</emph>, we need to reconceptualise the meaning of
                  the noun to refer to the process resulting in the object rather than the concrete
                  object <ptr target="#radimsky2011"/>; in <emph>to take heart</emph>, we need to
                  metaphorically extend the meaning of the noun to refer to feelings / emotions and
                  specifically courage <ptr target="#nunberg1994"/> <ptr target="#sheinfux2019"/>. They are also
                  semi-productive in the lexicon, such that they cannot be generated at random or
                  according to a fixed set of rules <ptr target="#kamber2008"/>, e.g. <emph>to make a
                     trip</emph> is unnatural in English.<note> For later tendencies with <foreign xml:lang="la">facere</foreign> <q>to
                        do</q> in Latin, see however <ptr target="#galdi2018"/>. </note> Rather, lexical affinity
                  between the verb and the noun governs the creation of support-verb
                  constructions.</item></list>
               <p>In Xenophon’s short treatise, three support-verb constructions recur, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασίαν
                  ποιέομαι</foreign> <q>to do horse exercise</q> including the topical keyword <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασία</foreign>, along with
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">τεκμήρια παρέχομαι</foreign> <q>to give an indication</q> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">πεῖραν λαμβάνω</foreign> <q>to put to the
                  test,</q> which refer to the scientific method of finding evidence and drawing
                  conclusions based on it. In the below we focus on those support-verb
                  constructions. A full list of support-verb constructions in <title rend="italic">On
                     Horsemanship</title> can be found in the appendix. </p>
               <p><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασία</foreign> is a keyword in the treatise. It appears 17 times in differing syntactic
                  environments, as shown in Figure 3.</p>
             
               <figure> 
                  <head>Sketch Engine Concordance of <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασία</foreign> in <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title></head>
                     <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Screenshot of the concordances in <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title>. The concordances are displayed with a left context, a KWIC, and and right context. The text is in Greek and incudes numerical ordering</figDesc>
               </figure>
               
               <p>In 8 of 17 instances, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασία</foreign> appears in an adverbial phrase (with a preposition)
                  (rows 1, 3, 6, 9, 10, 15, 16, 17). In 2 of 17 instances, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασία</foreign> takes the form of
                  an adverbial dative with a verb of emotion (rows 13 and 14). In 4 of 17 instances,
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασία</foreign> is the subject (row 4) or object (rows 5, 7, 8) of the sentence. The
                  remaining three passages are instances of support-verb constructions.</p>
               <p> In [7], <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασία</foreign> is combined with the support verb <foreign xml:lang="grc">ποιέομαι</foreign> to mean <q>to do horse
                  exercise / to exercise the horse.</q> The qualifying adjectives (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μακράς</foreign> <q>long,</q>
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">βραχείας</foreign> <q>short,</q> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁμοίας</foreign> <q>similar</q>) are spaced out across the sentence. </p>
               <dhq:example>[7] Xenophon, <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> 8.9
               <quote rend="block"><foreign xml:lang="grc">Ὀρθῶς δ’ ἔχει καὶ τὸ ἄλλοτε μὲν ἐν ἄλλοις τόποις, ἄλλοτε δὲ μακράς, ἄλλοτε δὲ
                  βραχείας τὰς ἱππασίας ποιεῖσθαι. ἀμισέστερα γὰρ καὶ ταῦτα τῷ ἵππῳ τοῦ ἀεὶ ἐν τοῖς
                  αὐτοῖς τόποις καὶ ὁμοίας τὰς ἱππασίας ποιεῖσθαι</foreign>. </quote>
               <p><quote rend="block">It is right to do exercise sometimes in different places, sometimes for a long
                  time, sometimes for a short time. For these things (i.e. exercising in different
                  places and with diversity of exercises) are less troublesome to the horse than to
                  do exercise in the same places and the same exercise all the time.</quote> </p></dhq:example>
               <p>This allows for a contrast to be established between lengths of exercise (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μακράς,
                  βραχείας</foreign>) and for these lengths of exercise to be linked to different spatial
                  settings without repetition of the predicate but while maintaining that this
                  refers to one and the same event (<q>to exercise the horse</q>). The same support-verb
                  construction appears in the second sentence in [7], yet this time the adjective
                  accompanying the noun is an adjective of manner forming the final part of a climax
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀεί</foreign> <q>always</q> – <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐν τοῖς αὐτοῖς τόποις</foreign> <q>in the same places</q> – <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁμοίας τὰς ἱππασίας</foreign>
                  <q>the same exercises</q>) highlighting what is to be avoided when training a
                  horse.<note> The comparative <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀμισέστερα</foreign> explicitly links the two instances of
                     the support-verb construction. The type of link is not left to contextual
                     inference. </note>
               </p>
               <p>The use of a simplex verb would change the type of parallelism underlining the
                  contrast in length in the first sentence and the type of climax underlining the
                  degree of preference/dispreference in the second sentence. A simplex verb could
                  only be modified externally, by means of an adverb, but not internally, by means
                  of an adjective <ptr target="#didakowski2020"/>. E.g. <emph>to give a
                     good speech</emph> evaluates the content of the speech vs <emph>to
                     give a speech well </emph>comments on the presentation of the speech. Equally,
                     <emph>to do an extended / short exercise</emph> evaluates the
                  exercise itself, whereas <emph>to do exercise for a long / short
                     time</emph> comments on the execution of the exercise.<note> Support-verb
                     constructions in Greek can be modified by both adverbs and adjectives. While
                     the modification by adverbs is not constrained, the modification by adjectives
                     is constrained as analysability and compositionality of the support-verb
                     construction is required in many cases, except if the adjective is a fixed
                     component of the structure (e.g. German <foreign xml:lang="de">erste Hilfe leisten</foreign>).</note> In the
                  former, the focus is on the exercise itself and its type; in the latter, the focus
                  is on the circumstances of doing the exercise. Xenophon’s passage evaluates the
                  type of exercise rather than the circumstances of the exercise. </p>
               <p> In [8], <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασία</foreign> is combined with the support verb <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἔχω</foreign> to mean <q>to have ridden
                  work / to behave under saddle.</q> Unlike in [7], the noun is not only qualified by
                  adjectives of manner (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γοργοτέραν</foreign> <q>fiercer</q> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἰσχυροτέραν</foreign> <q>more powerful</q>) but is
                  also conjoined with a second noun <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὑπόβασίν</foreign> <q>movement.</q> </p>
               <dhq:example>[8] Xenophon, <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> 1.14 <quote rend="block"><foreign xml:lang="grc">τοῦτο δὲ ποιῶν ἅμα
                  γοργοτέραν τε καὶ ἰσχυροτέραν ἕξει τὴν ὑπόβασίν τε καὶ ἱππασίαν καὶ ἅπαντα βελτίων
                  ἔσται ἑαυτοῦ</foreign>.</quote>
               <quote rend="block">Doing this, (the horse) will have a fiercer and more powerful movement / gait and
                  ridden work and he will be better than his former self in every way.</quote></dhq:example>
               <p>While [7] illustrated how a support-verb construction can tie together many pieces
                  of information about the event in question seamlessly, [8] shows how a
                  support-verb construction can be used to condense information. Since the two
                  co-ordinated nouns in [8] can both function as nouns in a support-verb
                  construction and both accept the support verb <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἔχω</foreign>, one instance of the verb is
                  deleted <ptr target="#gross1998"/>. </p>
               <p>Similar condensation appears with the one-off structures <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀσχολίαν / ἀθυμίαν παρέχω</foreign>
                  <quote rend="inline">to provide a lack of rest / a lack of confidence</quote> in section 3.12. Their
                  combination underlines the unpleasantness of the situation for the rider,
                  accentuated by the parallel alpha privative at the start of both nouns. The focus
                  on contrasting items by means of a support-verb construction may underlie <foreign xml:lang="grc">κόσμον
                  παρέχω</foreign> <q>to adorn</q> in section 12.2, there describing the rider’s headwear. The verb
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">παρέχω</foreign> <q>to give</q> is contrasted in the parallel structure with <foreign xml:lang="grc">δέχομαι</foreign> <q>to receive</q>
                  and the noun <foreign xml:lang="grc">κόσμον</foreign> <q>ornament</q> with <foreign xml:lang="grc">τὸ πρόσωπον</foreign> <q>the face.</q> While the parallel
                  structure does not qualify as a support-verb construction, the parallelism
                  underlines the interplay between the armour and its wearer. </p>
               <p> The other two recurring support-verb constructions concern not the keyword but
                  the key aim of Xenophon’s treatise, that is a scientific approach to horse care
                  and training. In [9], the support-verb construction <foreign xml:lang="grc">πεῖραν λαμβάνω</foreign> recurs three
                  times in quick succession. </p>
              <dhq:example>[9] Xenophon, <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> 3.7
               <quote rend="block"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐπεὶ δὲ πολεμιστήριον ἵππον ὑπεθέμεθα ὠνεῖσθαι, ληπτέον πεῖραν ἁπάντων ὅσωνπερ καὶ
                  ὁ πόλεμος πεῖραν λαμβάνει. ἔστι δὲ ταῦτα, τάφρους διαπηδᾶν, τειχία ὑπερβαίνειν,
                  ἐπ’ ὄχθους ἀνορούειν, ἀπ’ ὄχθων καθάλλεσθαι· καὶ πρὸς ἄναντες δὲ καὶ κατὰ πρανοῦς
                  καὶ πλάγια ἐλαύνοντα πεῖραν λαμβάνειν· πάντα γὰρ ταῦτα καὶ τὴν ψυχὴν εἰ καρτερὰ
                  καὶ τὸ σῶμα εἰ ὑγιὲς δοκιμάζει.</foreign></quote>
               <quote rend="block">Since we hypothesized that the horse fit for war is to be bought, it must be put
                  to the test in everything which war usually puts it to the test in too. These
                  aspects are (i) leaping across ditches, (ii) overcoming walls, (iii) jumping up a
                  bank, (iv) leaping down from banks. In addition, (it is necessary that) by riding
                  uphill and downhill and sideways he put (sc. the horse) to the test. For all these
                  tests indicate whether (the horse) is strong in spirit and healthy in the
                  body.</quote></dhq:example>
               <p>Unlike <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασίαν ποιέομαι, πεῖραν λαμβάνω</foreign> seems to assume a highly specific
                  meaning, possible acquired through lexicalisation.<note> <ptr target="#lipka1981" loc="120"/>:
                     <quote rend="inline"><foreign xml:lang="de">Unter Lexikalisierung verstehe ich die Erscheinung, daß einmal gebildete
                     komplexe Lexeme bei häufigem Gebrauch dazu tendieren, eine einzige
                     lexikalische Einheit mit spezifischem Inhalt zu werden. Durch die
                     Lexikalisierung geht der Syntagmacharakter in mehr oder weniger starkem Maße
                     verloren</foreign></quote> <ptr target="#lipka1992"/>. Examples are compounds such as <emph>housewife</emph> <ptr target="#hopper2003" loc="53"/> and <emph>Feierabend</emph>. The meaning of the compound is in both cases
                     a lexical unit with a meaning different from the meaning of its parts. </note>
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">πεῖραν λαμβάνω</foreign> seems to mean specifically <q>to put to the test.</q> The subject slot
                  seems to be filled by who or what is doing the testing (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁ πόλεμος</foreign> <q>the war</q> and
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐλαύνοντα</foreign> referring to the implied subject <q>the rider</q>). The entity to be tested
                  (here the horse) is contextually salient but is not explicitly mentioned. This is
                  not surprising given the general observation that support-verb constructions help
                  to de-transitivise, that is to decrease the number of event participants (e.g. to
                  suggest (something) vs to make a suggestion) <ptr target="#marini2010"/>. The focus is thus
                  shifted to the event of testing and away from the patient of the event <ptr target="#foley2007"/>. The area of testing is indicated by means of an objective genitive (see
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἁπάντων</foreign> <q>everything</q>), thus it seems to be specifically the patient that the
                  structure is intended to eliminate. Xenophon’s choice of the support-verb
                  construction (<q>to put to the test</q>) over the simplex verb (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πειράω, πειράζω</foreign> <q>to
                  examine / to test</q>) focuses the reader’s attention on the event of testing in more
                  fact-based a way than the integration of a second participant (the horse)
                  could.<note> The same may be true of <foreign xml:lang="grc">φόβον παρέχω</foreign> in section 6.15 <quote rend="inline"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οἱ δὲ πληγαῖς
                     ἀναγκάζοντες ἔτι πλείω φόβον παρέχουσιν· οἴονται γὰρ οἱ ἵπποι, ὅταν τι χαλεπὸν
                     πάσχωσιν ἐν τῷ τοιούτῳ, καὶ τούτου τὰ ὑποπτευόμενα αἴτια εἶναι.</foreign></quote> <quote rend="inline">Those forced
                     with beating show even greater fear. For the horses believe, when they suffer
                     something terrible in a certain situation, that the thing which they are
                     suspicious of is responsible (for that too).</quote> <foreign xml:lang="grc">φόβον παρέχω</foreign> is here not
                        causative (<q>to scare</q>) but intransitive (<q>to show fear / to be afraid</q>) <ptr target="#ittzes2007"/>
                        <ptr target="#ittzes2015"/> <ptr target="#machounis2004"/> <ptr target="#marini2018"/>. </note>
               </p>
               <p> Similarly, <foreign xml:lang="grc">τεκμήρια παρέχομαι</foreign> <q>to give an indication of</q> in [10a] and [10b]
                  reflects Xenophon’s interest in the scientific method. However, unlike <foreign xml:lang="grc">πεῖραν
                     λαμβάνω</foreign> <q>to put to the test</q> and more like <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασίαν ποιέομαι</foreign> <q>to do horsemanship /
                  horse exercise,</q> he availed himself of the option of qualifying just one component
                  of the support-verb construction. Thus, in both [10a] and [10b], we find
                  adjectives of manner qualifying the noun (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πάνυ σαφῆ</foreign> <q>very clear</q> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱκανά</foreign>
                  <q>strong</q>). </p>
               <dhq:example>[10a] Xenophon, <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> 1.1 
               <quote rend="block"><foreign xml:lang="grc">τοῦ μὲν τοίνυν ἔτι ἀδαμάστου πώλου δῆλον ὅτι τὸ σῶμα δεῖ δοκιμάζειν· τῆς γὰρ ψυχῆς
                  οὐ πάνυ σαφῆ τεκμήρια παρέχεται ὁ μήπω ἀναβαινόμενος</foreign>.</quote>
               <quote rend="block">It is obvious that it is necessary to assess the body (sc. only) with regard to a
                  still unbroken colt. For the one who has not yet been mounted does not give any
                  clear indication of his temperament.</quote></dhq:example>
               <dhq:example>[10b] Xenophon, <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> 3.11 
               <foreign xml:lang="grc"><quote rend="block">ὅσοι δ’ ἂν πεπονηκότες ἐθέλωσι πάλιν ὑποδύεσθαι πόνους ἱκανὰ τεκμήρια παρέχονται
                  ταῦτα ψυχῆς καρτερᾶς.</quote></foreign>
               <quote rend="block">All those (horses) who are willing to delve into work again after having worked
                  out give (this as) a strong indication of a steadfast character.</quote><note> An
                     anonymous reviewer pointed out correctly that the anaphoric pronoun <foreign xml:lang="grc">ταῦτα</foreign>
                     functions as the object and <foreign xml:lang="grc">τεκμήρια</foreign> thus moves closer to a predicative element
                     in [10b]. This is true and structures like this are otherwise omitted from the
                     data collection. However, firstly, Greek support-verb constructions are on
                     occasion found with an accusative object (e.g. <ptr target="#ittzes2007"/>; but also <ptr target="#lowe2017"/>), and secondly, one could equally argue that <foreign xml:lang="grc">ταῦτα</foreign> is appositional or even
                     parenthetical, thus functioning outside the sentence grammar <ptr target="#koev2022"/>, or
                     that the predicative relation works the other way round, i.e. with ταῦτα as the
                     predicative element. The parallel with [10a] makes us include the passage here,
                     yet with the caveats just outlined.</note>
               </dhq:example>
               <p>The aspect indicated is specified in the form of an objective genitive in [10a]
                  and [10b] (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τῆς ψυχῆς</foreign> <q>of the disposition</q> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">ψυχῆς καρτερᾶς</foreign> <q>of the steadfast
                     character</q>). The simplex verb <foreign xml:lang="grc">τεκμαίρομαι</foreign> <q>to judge from signs</q> differs in
                  meaning; the active <foreign xml:lang="grc">τεκμαίρω</foreign> <q>to make proof</q> comes closer to the meaning of the
                  support-verb construction but is rare throughout the history of Greek as searches
                  in the <title rend="italic">Thesaurus Linguae Graecae</title> show (<ref
                     target="http://stephanus.tlg.uci.edu">http://stephanus.tlg.uci.edu</ref>). Of
                  the 51 instances only 3 are classical. These appear in Pindar’s odes (6th / 5th c.
                  BC) and Aeschylus’ tragedies (6th / 5th c. BC).<note> Pindar, Olympia 6.73;
                     Pindar, Nemea 6.8; Aeschylus, Prometheus vinctus 605. The fourth instance
                     appears in Aratus, Phaenomena 1.18. Aratus’ work is a didactic poem and dates
                     slightly later (4th / 3rd c. BC). </note> Thus, it seems that the support-verb
                  construction here may not only provide Xenophon with advantages as regards
                  discourse cohesion but may also have filled a gap in the paradigm of the verb (see
                  also <ptr target="#aerts1965"/> <ptr target="#bentein2016" loc="76"/> <ptr target="#ledgeway2022"/>). Similarly, in
                  the case of <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐξουσίαν παρέχω</foreign> <q>to give the power to</q> in section 6.9, a related
                  simplex verb only develops in later Greek. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>4 Scientific Language as a Specialised Literacy: Cohesion through Register
                  Continuity</head>
               <p>Xenophon defines his intended audience at the beginning of his treatise as the
                  next generation of horsemen (section 1.1 <foreign xml:lang="grc">τοῖς νεωτέροις τῶν φίλων</foreign> <q>the younger
                  ones amongst the friends / companions</q>). Thus, he seems to expect his audience to
                  belong to the same community of practice as himself, that is people interested in
                  the purchase, care and training of horses especially for cavalry purposes. A
                  community of practice is a group of people that share knowledge and/or skills,
                  often related to a specific area of expertise, through interactions <ptr target="#unwin2007"/>.<note> <ptr target="#greer2015"/> aligns Xenophon’s treatise with modern approaches to
                     horsemanship. While differences certainly exist, which may partly be due to the
                     intended purpose of Xenophon’s horses, his focus on the care and the behaviour
                     of horses is noticeable (cf. <ptr target="#mcgreevy2012"/> <ptr target="#mcilwraith2011"/>).
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p> Xenophon’s treatise is only accessible to someone who has domain-specific
                  literacy, that is a <q>competence or knowledge in a particular area</q> (OED s.v.
                  literacy 2). However, in addition to basic background knowledge in the care and
                  training of horses (<ptr target="#maienschein1998"/> science literacy), Xenophon’s reader must
                  also be familiar with his way of arriving at and presenting pieces of information
                  (Maienschein’s (1998) scientific literacy). This familiarity, the reader gains
                  partly through engagement with the process of knowledge production in a scientific
                  context (see also <ptr target="#durant1994"/> <ptr target="#howell2021"/>), partly through
                  engagement with the norms governing the communication of knowledge (the scientific
                  register). </p>
               <p> The support-verb constructions discussed in Section 3 reflect three aspects of
                  scientific writing that are evident from Xenophon’s text also elsewhere, that is
                  (i) precision, through the use of specialised terms, (ii) methodical working,
                  through the establishment of a clear structure, and (iii) incremental results,
                  through the linking backwards and forwards in the discourse. We illustrate these
                  three traits one by one before mapping them onto support-verb constructions.</p>
               <div><head>Precision</head><p>In section 4.2, Xenophon considers the case of a horse that is unwell
                  as indicated by the horse not taking in food normally (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ὅταν [μὴ] ἐκκομίζῃ τὸν
                  σῖτον ὁ ἵππος</foreign> <q>when the horse does not take in his feed</q>). Xenophon considers the
                  options of (i) too much blood in the body, (ii) exhaustion, and (iii) ailments
                  such as laminitis (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κριθίασις</foreign>). <foreign xml:lang="grc">κριθίασις</foreign> is throughout Greek literature a word
                  that is rare and which appears exclusively in treatises on horsemanship, as
                  searches in the <title rend="italic">Thesauraus Lingae Graecae</title> show.<note> Apart
                     from Xenophon, we find it in (i) the grammarian Aristophanes (3rd / 2nd c. BC),
                     (ii) the rhetorician Pollux (2nd c. AD), (iii) in the compilation of the
                     Hippiatrica (9th c. AD), and finally in the (iv) the encyclopaedia of the Suda
                     (10th c. AD). 17 instances are attested in total.</note> <foreign xml:lang="grc">κριθίασις</foreign> seems
                  etymologically related to <foreign xml:lang="grc">κριθή</foreign> <q>barley</q> / <foreign xml:lang="grc">κριθάω</foreign> <q>to be fed with barley.</q>
                  <ptr target="#anderson1961" loc="162 and 207"/> argues for it to refer to laminitis rather than
                  colic, both specific illnesses affecting horses. Xenophon, by using the word,
                  shows not only great attention to detail but displays familiarity with technical
                  terms of the community of practice of horsemen. Moreover, <foreign xml:lang="grc">κριθίασις</foreign> fits in with
                  the scheme of the creation of a <q>systematic scientific</q> vocabulary in the 5th /
                  4th c. BC by means of deverbal derivations in -<foreign xml:lang="grc">σις</foreign>, such as <foreign xml:lang="grc">διαλέγω / διάλεξις</foreign>
                  <q>argumentation,</q> <foreign xml:lang="grc">περιλέγω / περίλεξις</foreign> <q>circumlocution,</q> <foreign xml:lang="grc">καταλαμβάνω / κατάληψις</foreign>
                  <q>comprehension,</q> <foreign xml:lang="grc">κρούω / κροῦσις</foreign> <q>attempts at deception</q> in Aristophanes, <title
                     rend="italic">Clouds</title> 316–318, all related to rhetoric <ptr target="#galdi2018" loc="242"/> <ptr target="#langslow2000"/> <ptr target="#willi2003" loc="67"/>. </p></div>
               <div><head>Methodical Working</head><p>The introduction to <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title>
                  shows Xenophon justifying himself as a competent author, stating unequivocally the
                  objective of his work and aligning himself with past work in the same area of
                  expertise. </p></div>
               <dhq:example>[11] Xenophon, <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> 1.1 
               <quote rend="block"><foreign xml:lang="grc"><p>[qualification of author] Ἐπειδὴ διὰ τὸ συμβῆναι ἡμῖν πολὺν χρόνον ἱππεύειν
                  οἰόμεθα ἔμπειροι ἱππικῆς γεγενῆσθαι,</p>
               <p>[objective of the work] βουλόμεθα καὶ τοῖς νεωτέροις τῶν φίλων δηλῶσαι ᾗ ἂν
                  νομίζομεν αὐτοὺς ὀρθότατα ἵπποις προσφέρεσθαι.</p>
               <p>[past research] συνέγραψε μὲν οὖν καὶ Σίμων περὶ ἱππικῆς, ὃς καὶ τὸν κατὰ τὸ
                  Ἐλευσίνιον Ἀθήνησιν ἵππον χαλκοῦν ἀνέθηκε καὶ ἐν τῷ βάθρῳ τὰ ἑαυτοῦ ἔργα
                  ἐξετύπωσεν·</p>
               <p>[procedure] ἡμεῖς γε μέντοι ὅσοις συνετύχομεν ταὐτὰ γνόντες ἐκείνῳ, οὐκ
                  ἐξαλείφομεν ἐκ τῶν ἡμετέρων, ἀλλὰ πολὺ ἥδιον παραδώσομεν αὐτὰ τοῖς φίλοις,
                  νομίζοντες ἀξιοπιστότερα εἶναι ὅτι κἀκεῖνος κατὰ ταὐτὰ ἡμῖν ἔγνω ἱππικὸς ὤν· καὶ
                  ὅσα δὴ παρέλιπεν ἡμεῖς πειρασόμεθα δηλῶσαι.</p></foreign></quote>
               <quote rend="block"><p>[qualification of author] Because we have been involved in horsemanship for a
                  long time and believe to be experienced in horsemanship,</p>
               <p>[objective of the work] we want to show to our younger friends how we think that
                  they treat horses correctly.</p>
               <p>[past research] In fact, also Simon has written about horsemanship, a man who
                  offered a bronze horse at the Athenian Eleusinium and inscribed his own
                  achievements on the pedestal.</p>
               <p>[procedure] However, we do not leave out all those points in which we concur with
                  him, but we will present these to the friends with great pleasure, considering
                  them to be even more reliable because he too, such a great horseman, concurred.
                  All those points which he has left out, we will try to clarify.</p></quote></dhq:example>
               <p>While the quoting of past works either verbatim or with modifications was a
                  regular process in Greek literature <ptr target="#adams2015"/> <ptr target="#finnegan2011" loc="chap. 8"/>, Xenophon’s scientific interest seems to be to fill gaps in the
                  community’s knowledge. He positions himself with regard to his contemporary’s work
                  in particular, Simon’s <title rend="italic">De forma et delectu equorum</title>, as
                  Simon covered the same area of expertise. Xenophon’s introduction in [11] is more
                  than a condensed overview of the plot, it characterises him as a valid member of
                  the community of practice to whose knowledge base he wants to contribute.<note> At
                     the very end, in section 12.14, he reiterates almost like a disclaimer that his
                     notes only pertain to the private person, whereas the cavalry leader is
                     directed to another book. </note>
               </p>
               <div><head>Incremental Results</head><p>Throughout <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title>, Xenophon
                  facilitates it for the reader to tie pieces of the discourse together by means of
                  interims summaries (e.g. sections 1.17, 2.3, 3.12, 9.1, and 10.17) and topic
                  sentences foreshadowing what is to come next (e.g. 7.1, 9.1, and 12.1). In section
                  8.2, he explains why what may seem like repetition (διλογέω <q>to say twice</q>) is
                  necessary rather than redundant: <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὅτε μὲν γὰρ ἐωνεῖτο, πειρᾶσθαι ἐκελεύομεν εἰ
                  δύναιτο ὁ ἵππος ταῦτα ποιεῖν· νῦν δὲ διδάσκειν φαμὲν χρῆναι τὸν ἑαυτοῦ καὶ
                  γράψομεν ὡς δεῖ διδάσκειν.</foreign> <quote rend="inline">For when he bought (the horse), we said to try out
                  whether the horse can do these things. But now we say that it is necessary to
                  teach one’s own horse and we will write down how this must be done.</quote> Xenophon’s
                  aim with these metatextual notes is to guide the reader through his work, so as to
                  ensure that the reader appreciates the logical progression through the aspects
                  discussed. </p></div>
               <p> Support-verb constructions play a role in all three aspects – precision,
                  methodical working, and incremental results. Firstly, they can develop, often
                  through lexicalisation, a meaning that is different from that of the related
                  simplex verb and often more specific. In Section 3, we saw the domain-specific
                  support-verb construction <foreign xml:lang="grc">τεκμήρια παρέχομαι</foreign> <q>to give an indication of.</q> Many of
                  these lexicalised support-verb constructions are structurally rather fixed,
                  although this is not a compulsory relation between structure and meaning (<ptr target="#ledgeway2022"/> see <ptr target="#nunberg1994"/> vs. <ptr target="#sheinfux2019"/>. </p>
               <p>Secondly, support-verb constructions seem to be involved in the development of a
                  systematic vocabulary for the purposes of a community of practice. As mentioned,
                  the 5th / 4th c. BC saw an increase in deverbal derivations in -<foreign xml:lang="grc">σις</foreign> in the context
                  of creating a systematic terminology for areas such as rhetoric. These nouns were
                  integrated into the predicate slot of a sentence by means of the support verb
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">ποιέομαι</foreign>. This is visible when drawing up the collocational field of common
                  support verbs in a large corpus of classical literary Attic by means of Sketch
                  Engine: <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄγω</foreign> <q>to act,</q> <foreign xml:lang="grc">δέχομαι</foreign> <q>to receive,</q> <foreign xml:lang="grc">δίδωμι</foreign> <q>to give,</q> <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἔχω</foreign> <q>to have,</q>
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">λαμβάνω</foreign> <q>to take / receive,</q> <foreign xml:lang="grc">παρέχω</foreign> <q>to provide,</q> <foreign xml:lang="grc">ποιέομαι</foreign> <q>to do,</q> <foreign xml:lang="grc">τίθημι</foreign> <q>to
                     put,</q> <foreign xml:lang="grc">φέρω</foreign> <q>to bring,</q> <foreign xml:lang="grc">τυγχάνω</foreign> <q>to get</q> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">χράομαι</foreign> <q>to use</q>.<note> See footnote
                        1. </note> All the candidates except for <foreign xml:lang="grc">ποιέομαι</foreign> form strong collocations with
                  a small number of nouns, which can receive a support-verb construction reading
                  <ptr target="#pasquer2018" loc="2583"/>. By contrast, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ποιέομαι</foreign> enters into a large number of
                  lose combinations with nouns in -<foreign xml:lang="grc">σις</foreign> (deverbal formations) and -<foreign xml:lang="grc">ία</foreign> (deadjectival
                  formations). This resembles Galdi’s (<ref target="#galdi2018">2018 pp. 239–240 and 242</ref>) findings for later
                  Latin <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">facere</foreign></emph> <q>to do</q> support-verb constructions, which
                  specifically in technical contexts flourish with nouns in -<emph
                     >io</emph> (deverbal formations), e.g. <title rend="italic">Mulomedicina
                     Chironis</title>, 26 <foreign xml:lang="la"><emph>simili modo sanguinis </emph>detractionem<emph> in eis </emph>facies<emph>, sicut in prioribus
                     demonstravi</emph></foreign> <quote rend="inline">in the same way you will do the extraction of blood in them,
                        as I have described before</quote> (vs <emph><foreign xml:lang="la">detraho</foreign></emph> <q>to
                     extract</q>).<note> The other context in which Galdi’s Latin and our Greek <q>to do</q>
                     support-verb constructions are common is multilingual contexts (e.g.
                     translations), which pose their own problems <ptr target="#bakker2003" loc="132"/> <ptr target="#myersscotten2002" loc="134–139"/>
                        <ptr target="#reintges2001"/> <ptr target="#ronan2012" loc="231"/> <ptr target="#rutherford2010" loc="203"/>.</note> <foreign xml:lang="grc">ποιέομαι</foreign> support-verb constructions almost seem like a
                  default systemic means to integrate the newly-created technical terms (cf. <ptr target="#langer2004"/>). Section 3 examined topical <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασίαν ποιέομαι</foreign> <q>to do horsemanship / horse
                  exercise.</q></p>
               <p> Thirdly, support-verb constructions serve to tie pieces of information together
                  within sentences (coherence) and across sentences (cohesion) by means of their
                  discontiguity and analyticity, as explained in Section 3. This happens through
                  bracketing pieces of information with the predicate (cf. Lysias, Speech 3.22
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">συνθήκας πρὸς αὐτὸν ποιησάμενος </foreign><q>to reach agreements with him</q>), establishing
                  long-distance relationships through pronominalisation and/or inference of one
                  component (e.g. Plato, <title rend="italic">Gorgias</title><foreign xml:lang="grc"> 479d καὶ ἀεὶ τὸν
                  ἀδικοῦντα τοῦ ἀδικουμένου ἀθλιώτερον εἶναι καὶ τὸν μὴ διδόντα δίκην
                  τοῦ διδόντος </foreign><q>and that the wrongdoer is always more wretched than the wronged
                  and the unpunished than the punished</q>), and the repetition of keywords (cf.
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασία</foreign> in <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title>). Furthermore, support-verb
                  constructions can serve to focus attention on the event by eliminating
                  participants which could act as distractors, as shown for <foreign xml:lang="grc">πεῖραν λαμβάνω</foreign> <q>to put
                  to the test</q> in <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title>. This allows Xenophon to
                  focus the audience’s attention on the logical progression of events in the
                  treatise. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>5 Summary and conclusion </head>
               <p>We have built a Sketch Engine corpus for the classical scientific treatise <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title>. We used this corpus to detect discontiguous
                  verbal multi-word expressions, specifically support-verb constructions. We
                  examined how support-verb constructions – through their structural and lexical
                  properties – aid discourse coherence and cohesion throughout Xenophon’s treatise. </p>
               <p> Section 1 introduced the means of achieving coherence, which refers to how
                  building blocks of a sentence are tied together, and cohesion, which refers to the
                  tying together of clauses and sentences, in classical Greek. Section 2 presented
                  the corpus preparation tool, which we built to tag and lemmatise a classical Greek
                  corpus for Sketch Engine, and the modified corpus configuration file to implement
                  the corpus into Sketch Engine. Section 3 discussed the support-verb constructions
                  in <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> from the angle of coherence and
                  cohesion, especially <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασίαν ποιέομαι</foreign> <q>to do horsemanship / horse exercise,</q>
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">πεῖραν λαμβάνω</foreign> <q>to put to the test,</q> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">τεκμήρια παρέχομαι</foreign> <q>to give an indication
                  (of).</q> Section 4 outlined the features of scientific writing in <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> and mapped these onto the support-verb constructions
                  identified. </p>
               <p> We find that our Sketch Engine corpus performs with an error rate below 2.5%.
                  Support-verb constructions are detected through the generation of collocations and
                  n-grams, with specific items. This implies a focus on the identification of seen
                  structures rather than discovery of new structures <ptr target="#pasquer2020"/>. This
                  limitation concerns research on support-verb constructions in general, e.g.
                  <ptr target="#cordeiro2019"/> find that at best 31% of unseen support-verb
                  constructions are detected by their tool. The issues surrounding automatic
                  discovery of support-verb construction is linked to (i) their variability, both
                  internally (e.g. inflection of the verb and the noun involved) and externally
                  (e.g. their discontiguous structure) <ptr target="#constant2017" loc="844"/> <ptr target="#pasquer2018"/>, (ii) their mostly discontiguous structure which necessitates reliance on
                  syntactic analysis <ptr target="#constant2017" loc="842"/> <ptr target="#pasquer2017" loc="8"/> <ptr target="#savary2018" loc="112 and 123"/>, and (iii) their semi-productivity such that unseen
                  structures with some support verbs abound because they appear rarely <ptr target="#nagy2013" loc="331"/> <ptr target="#savary2018" loc="123"/>. We can determine the most frequent
                  support verbs in classical Greek based on a large corpus of classical literary
                  Attic and draw up collocational fields using Sketch Engine for each support verb
                  in question. Sketch Engine has been successfully used for the study of
                  support-verb constructions in English <ptr target="#sheinfux2019"/>, Italian and Russian
                  <ptr target="#maiko2020"/>, for instance. </p>
               <p>In the future, the performance of Sketch Engine on classical Greek could be improved
                  by writing and implementing a dependency grammar for classical Greek in order to
                  disambiguate the analysis of word forms that return a long list of options (e.g.
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀνίημι</foreign> with <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄνευ</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄνω</foreign>). Furthermore, the integration of classical Greek in
                  projects such as PARSEME, which provides manually annotated corpora for verbal
                  multi-word expressions in 18 languages including modern Greek could improve
                  discovery of new items (yet <ptr target="#savary2018"/> on issues).<note>
                     <ref
                        target="https://parsemefr.lis-lab.fr/parseme-st-guidelines/1.0/?page=060_Specific_tests_-_categorize_VMWEs/020_Light-verb_constructions"
                        >https://parsemefr.lis-lab.fr/parseme-st-guidelines/1.0/?page=060_Specific_tests_-_categorize_VMWEs/020_Light-verb_constructions</ref>
                     (accessed 01 July 2022).</note>
               </p>
               <p> We find that support-verb constructions in <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title>
                  aid coherence and cohesion throughout the treatise, both structurally and
                  lexically speaking, as exemplified for the recurring support-verb constructions:
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασίαν ποιέομαι</foreign> <q>to do horsemanship / horse exercise</q> contains the keyword
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασία</foreign> which appears throughout the treatise and thus ties pieces of information
                  together through lexical repetition, thus aiding cohesion. Aiding coherence
                  structurally, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασίαν</foreign> in <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασίαν ποιέομαι</foreign> is used to spread out pieces of
                  information across a sentence while tying them together through their linking to
                  one event (see adjectival modifiers with <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασίαν</foreign>); <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασίαν</foreign> in <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασίαν ἔχω</foreign> <q>to
                  have riding-related skill</q> is co-ordinated with another predicative noun thus
                  condensing information by fusing two support-verb constructions under the same
                  support verb.<note> The subject of <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασίαν ἔχω</foreign> is the horse, thus riding-related
                     skill are here in the sense of accepting and working with the rider. </note>
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">πεῖραν λαμβάνω</foreign> <q>to put to the test</q> focuses attention on the event by eliminating
                  event participants from the surface structure (here the horse). This helps the
                  reader not to lose the golden thread. <foreign xml:lang="grc">τεκμήρια παρέχομαι</foreign> <q>to give an indication
                     of</q> fills a gap in the lexicon since <foreign xml:lang="grc">τεκμαίρω</foreign> (in the active voice) remains rare
                  throughout the history of Greek. Using a support-verb construction allows Xenophon
                  to express precisely what he wants to say. </p>
               <p>Extra-linguistically, all three recurring support-verb constructions reflect an
                  aspect of scientific writing: <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱππασίαν ποιέομαι</foreign> is a representative of the
                  creation of a systematic scientific vocabulary in the 5th / 4th c. BC and its
                  integration in the predicate slot by means of highly productive <foreign xml:lang="grc">ποιέομαι</foreign> <q>to do</q>
                  <ptr target="#savary2018" loc="128"/>, thus broadcasting the author’s methodical working;
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">πεῖραν λαμβάνω</foreign> de-transitivises the event expressed and thus focusses the reader’s
                  attention on the logical progression of events by eliminating distractors (such as
                  event participants); <foreign xml:lang="grc">τεκμήρια παρέχομαι</foreign> fills a gap in the lexicon, thus
                  reflecting the author availing himself of each and any productive patterns in
                  order to achieve maximum precision of the expression. Thus, rather than just
                  through their structural and lexical properties, support-verb constructions in
                  Xenophon’s <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> seem to align with the register
                  of the text and thus align Xenophon with the community of practice of his intended
                  audience.</p>
               <p>We found that support-verb constructions are a mixed bag, as has been observed by
                  others for modern languages (e.g. <ptr target="#kamber2008"/> <ptr target="#nunberg1994"/> <ptr target="#pasquer2017"/>
                  <ptr target="#sheinfux2019"/> <ptr target="#tutin2016"/>). In Xenophon’s <title rend="italic">On
                     Horsemanship</title>, they seem to reflect specificity of expression <ptr target="#storrer2009"/> as well as markedness for register <ptr target="#fendel2020"/>, rather than be related to
                  the colloquial sphere or to stylistic choices <ptr target="#zilliacus1956"/> <ptr target="#zilliacus1956"/>. Their
                  variability makes their automatic identification and especially discovery
                  difficult even in morphologically less rich languages with unlimited corpora of
                  data. We therefore suggest Sketch Engine as a tool for the further study of
                  support-verb constructions while focusing on seen structures, in order to improve
                  tools for the discovery of support-verb constructions in the future <ptr target="#pasquer2020"/>.</p>
            </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head></head>
         <div>
            <head>Appendix: Support-verb constructions in Xenophon’s <title rend="italic">On
               Horsemanship</title> [18 in total]</head>
            <p>*In square brackets, the number of attestations of the verbal lemma in <title
               rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title> is provided. Only instances in which the
               lemma acts as a support verb are listed.</p>
           <table> 
              <row><cell role="label">
                 1 ἄγω [9]</cell>
                 <cell>none</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell></cell></row>
              <row><cell role="label">2 δίδωμι [6]</cell>
               <cell>none</cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell></row>
              <row><cell role="label">3 φέρω [6]</cell>
               <cell>none</cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell><cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
              </row>
              <row><cell role="label">4 τίθημι [1]</cell>
               <cell>none</cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
              </row>
              <row><cell role="label">5 πάσχω [6]</cell>
               <cell>none</cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
              </row>
              <row><cell role="label">6 κομίζω [0]</cell>
                 <cell>none</cell>  <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
              </row>
              <row><cell role="label">7 κτάομαι [4]</cell>
                 <cell>none</cell>  <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
              </row>
              <row><cell role="label">8 λαμβάνω [12]</cell><cell>πεῖραν λαμβάνω <q>to put to the test</q></cell>
            <cell>3.7 <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐπεὶ δὲ πολεμιστήριον ἵππον ὑπεθέμεθα ὠνεῖσθαι, ληπτέον πεῖραν ἁπάντων ὅσωνπερ
               καὶ ὁ πόλεμος πεῖραν λαμβάνει. ἔστι δὲ ταῦτα, τάφρους διαπηδᾶν, τειχία
               ὑπερβαίνειν, ἐπʼ ὄχθους ἀνορούειν, ἀπʼ ὄχθων καθάλλεσθαι· καὶ πρὸς ἄναντες δὲ καὶ
               κατὰ πρανοῦς καὶ πλάγια ἐλαύνοντα πεῖραν λαμβάνειν</foreign>·</cell><cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 </row>
              <row><cell role="label">9 τυγχάνω [4] </cell>
            <cell>ῥᾳστώνης τυγχάνω <q>to get relief</q></cell>
            <cell>7.19<foreign xml:lang="grc"> ὅταν γε μὴν καταβαίνειν ἤδη καιρὸς ᾖ, μήτε ἐν ἵπποις ποτὲ καταβαίνειν μήτε
               παρὰ σύστασιν ἀνθρώπων μήτʼ ἔξω τῆς ἱππασίας, ἀλλʼ ὅπουπερ καὶ πονεῖν ἀναγκάζεται
               ὁ ἵππος, ἐνταῦθα καὶ τῆς ῥᾳστώνης τυγχανέτω.</foreign></cell>
            <cell>11.5 <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἡμεῖς γε μέντοι τὸ κράτιστον τῶν διδασκαλίων νομίζομεν, ὥσπερ ἀεὶ λέγομεν, ἢν
               ἐν παντὶ παρέπηται τὸ ἐν ᾧ ἂν ποιήσῃ τῷ ἀναβάτῃ κατὰ γνώμην τυγχάνειν ῥᾳστώνης
               παρ᾽ αὐτοῦ.</foreign></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 </row>
              <row><cell role="label">10 δέχομαι [10]</cell>
            <cell>κόσμον δέχομαι <q>to get decorated / to get adorned</q></cell>
            <cell>12.2 <foreign xml:lang="grc">τοῦτο γὰρ ἅμα κόσμον τε παρέξει καί, ἢν οἷον δεῖ εἰργασμένον ᾖ, δέξεται ὅταν
               βούληται τῷ ἀναβάτῃ τὸ πρόσωπον μέχρι τῆς ῥινός.</foreign></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 </row>
              <row><cell role="label">11 χρἀομαι [13]</cell>
            <cell> ὅπλοις χράομαι <q>to use weapons / to fight</q></cell>
            <cell>8.10 <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐπεὶ δὲ δεῖ ἐν παντοίοις τε χωρίοις τὸν ἱππέα ἀνὰ κράτος ἐλαύνοντα ἔποχον
               εἶναι καὶ ἀπὸ τοῦ ἵππου τοῖς ὅπλοις καλῶς δύνασθαι χρῆσθαι, ὅπου μέν ἐστι χωρία
               ἐπιτήδεια καὶ θηρία, ἄμεμπτος ἡ ἐν θήραις μελέτη τῆς ἱππικῆς·</foreign></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 </row>
              <row><cell role="label">12 ποιέομαι [42]</cell>
            <cell> ἱππασίας ποιέομαι <q>to do horse exercise</q></cell>
            <cell>8.9 <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ὀρθῶς δ’ ἔχει καὶ τὸ ἄλλοτε μὲν ἐν ἄλλοις τόποις, ἄλλοτε δὲ μακράς, ἄλλοτε δὲ
               βραχείας τὰς ἱππασίας ποιεῖσθαι. ἀμισέστερα γὰρ καὶ ταῦτα τῷ ἵππῳ τοῦ ἀεὶ ἐν τοῖς
               αὐτοῖς τόποις καὶ ὁμοίας τὰς ἱππασίας ποιεῖσθαι</foreign>.</cell>
            <cell>ἕλκη ποιέω / ποιέομαι <q>to get sores / to make sores for themselves</q></cell>
            <cell>5.1 <foreign xml:lang="grc">πολλάκις γὰρ κνῶν ὁ ἵππος ἐπὶ τῇ φάτνῃ τὴν κεφαλήν, εἰ μὴ ἀσινὴς ἡ φορβειὰ
               περὶ τὰ ὦτα ἔσται, πολλάκις ἂν ἕλκη ποιοίη. ἑλκουμένων γε μὴν τούτων ἀνάγκη τὸν
               ἵππον καὶ περὶ τὸ χαλινοῦσθαι καὶ περὶ τὸ ψήχεσθαι δυσκολώτερον εἶναι.</foreign></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 <cell></cell>
                 </row>
              <row><cell role="label">13 παρέχω[13] </cell>
            <cell> τεκμήρια παρέχω <q>to give an indication</q></cell>
            <cell>1.1 <foreign xml:lang="grc">τῆς γὰρ ψυχῆς οὐ πάνυ σαφῆ τεκμήρια παρέχεται ὁ μήπω ἀναβαινόμενος.</foreign></cell>
            <cell>3.11 <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὅσοι δ’ ἂν πεπονηκότες ἐθέλωσι πάλιν ὑποδύεσθαι πόνους ἱκανὰ τεκμήρια
               παρέχονται ταῦτα ψυχῆς καρτερᾶς.</foreign></cell>
            <cell>ἀσχολίαν παρέχω <q>to provide a lack of rest / to make restless</q>; ἀθυμίαν παρέχω <q>to
               provide a lack of confidence / to make insecure</q></cell>
            <cell>3.12 <foreign xml:lang="grc">οἱ δὲ ἢ διὰ βλακείαν ἐλάσεως πολλῆς δεόμενοι ἢ διὰ τὸ ὑπέρθυμοι εἶναι πολλῆς
               θωπείας τε καὶ πραγματείας ἀσχολίαν μὲν ταῖς χερσὶ τοῦ ἀναβάτου παρέχουσιν,
               ἀθυμίαν δ’ ἐν τοῖς κινδύνοις.</foreign></cell>
            <cell> ἐξουσίαν παρέχω <q>to empower (to)</q></cell>
            <cell>6.9 <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁ μὲν γὰρ ἄγαν πρὸς αὐταῖς τυλοῖ τὸ στόμα, ὥστε μὴ εὐαίσθητον εἶναι, ὁ δὲ ἄγαν
               εἰς ἄκρον τὸ στόμα καθιέμενος ἐξουσίαν παρέχει συνδάκνοντι τὸ στόμιον μὴ
               πείθεσθαι.</foreign></cell>
            <cell> φόβον παρέχω <q>to scare</q></cell>
            <cell> 6.15 <foreign xml:lang="grc">οἱ δὲ πληγαῖς ἀναγκάζοντες ἔτι πλείω φόβον παρέχουσιν·</foreign> </cell>
            <cell> κόσμον παρέχω <q>to decorate / to adorn,</q></cell>
            <cell>12.2 <foreign xml:lang="grc">τοῦτο γὰρ ἅμα κόσμον τε παρέξει καί, ἢν οἷον δεῖ εἰργασμένον ᾖ, δέξεται ὅταν
               βούληται τῷ ἀναβάτῃ τὸ πρόσωπον μέχρι τῆς ῥινός.</foreign></cell></row>
            <row><cell role="label">14 ἔχω [37]</cell>
            <cell> σχῆμα ἔχω <q>to have a shape / form</q></cell>
            <cell>1.8 <foreign xml:lang="grc">καὶ βιάζεσθαι δὲ ἥκιστ’ ἂν δύναιτο ὁ τοιοῦτον σχῆμα ἔχων καὶ εἰ πάνυ θυμοειδὴς
               εἴη·</foreign></cell>
            <cell> ὑπόβασιν ἔχω <q>to have power to go forward</q>; ἱππασίαν ἔχω <q>to have riding-related
               skill</q></cell>
            <cell>1.14 <foreign xml:lang="grc">τοῦτο δὲ ποιῶν ἅμα γοργοτέραν τε καὶ ἰσχυροτέραν ἕξει τὴν ὑπόβασίν τε καὶ
               ἱππασίαν καὶ ἅπαντα βελτίων ἔσται ἑαυτοῦ.</foreign></cell>
            <cell>χαλεπότητα ἔχω <q>to have difficulty</q></cell>
            <cell>3.10 <foreign xml:lang="grc">δεῖ δὲ καὶ εἴ τινα χαλεπότητα ἔχοι ὁ ἵππος καταμανθάνειν, εἴτε πρὸς ἵππους
               εἴτε πρὸς ἀνθρώπους, καὶ εἰ δυσγάργαλίς γε εἴη·</foreign></cell>
               <cell></cell>
               <cell></cell>
               <cell></cell>
               <cell></cell>
               <cell></cell>
               </row></table></div>
         <div>
            <head>Abbreviations</head>
            <table><row><cell role="label">NOM</cell> <cell>nominative case (subject case in classical Greek)</cell></row>
               <row><cell role="label">ACC</cell> <cell>accusative case (object case in classical Greek)</cell></row>
               <row><cell role="label">DAT</cell> <cell>dative case (indirect object case in classical Greek)</cell></row>
               <row><cell role="label">OED</cell> <cell> Oxford English Dictionary (<ref target="http://www.oed.com"
               >www.oed.com</ref>)</cell></row></table></div>
         <div>
            <head>Data</head>
            <p>.vert files for Xenophon’s <title rend="italic">On Horsemanship</title>:
               <ref
                  target="https://gist.github.com/MatthewIreland/81e75b4653a3812fca2c02741ba21e34"
                  >https://gist.github.com/MatthewIreland/81e75b4653a3812fca2c02741ba21e34</ref>\
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Credits/funding</head>
            <p>Required credit for Perseus: Texts provided by Perseus Digital Library, with
               funding from The Annenberg CPB/Project. Original versions available for viewing
               and download at <ref target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/"
                  >http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/</ref>.</p>
            <p>This study has been funded by the Leverhulme Trust within the project <title rend="quote">Giving
               gifts and doing favours: Unlocking Greek support-verb constructions</title> at the
               University of Oxford, UK.</p>
         </div>
      </div>
               
        
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="adams2013" label="Adams 2013"> Adams, J. (2013). <title rend="italic">Social variation and the Latin language.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge
                  University Press.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="adams2015" label="Adams 2015"> Adams, S., &amp; Ehorn, S. (2015). <title rend="quotes">What is a Composite Citation? an
                  Introduction.</title> Adams S. &amp; Ehorn S. (eds) <title rend="italic">Composite Citations in Antiquity.</title></bibl>
                  <bibl xml:id="volumeone" label="Library of New Testament Studies"> Volume one, Jewish, Graeco-Roman, and Early Christian uses [electronic resource],
                     <title rend="italic">The Library of New Testament Studies</title>, Vol. 525, pp. 1–16. Bloomsbury T&amp;T
                  Clark: New York.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="aerts1965" label="Aerts 1965"> Aerts, W. (1965). <title rend="italic">Periphrastica: an investigation into the use of εἶναι and ἔχειν
                  as auxiliaries or pseudo-auxiliaries in Greek from Homer up to the present day.</title>
                  Publications (Universiteit van Amsterdam. Byzantijns-Nieuwgrieks Seminarium), Vol.
                  2. Amsterdam: AMHakkert.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="anderson1961" label="Anderson 1961"> Anderson, J. (1961). <title rend="italic">Ancient Greek horsemanship.</title> Berkeley: University of
                  California Press.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bakker2003" label="Bakker 2003"> Bakker, P. (2003). <title rend="quotes">Mixed languages as autonomous systems.</title> Bakker P. &amp; Matras
                  Y. (eds) <title rend="italic">The mixed language debate: Theoretical and empirical advances, Trends in
                  linguistics.</title> Studies and monographs, Vol. 145, pp. 113–56. Mouton de Gruyter:
                  Berlin.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="banos2015" label="Baños 2015"> Baños, J. (2015). <title rend="quotes">Bellum gerere y proelium facere: Sobre las construcciones con
                  verbo soporte en latín (y en griego).</title> Muñoz Garcia de Iturrospe M. &amp; Carrasco
               Reija L. (eds) <title rend="italic">Miscellanea Latina</title>, pp. 227–34. Sociedad de Estudios Latinos:
                  Madrid.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bentein2013" label="Bentein 2013"> Bentein, K. (2013). <title rend="quotes">Register and the diachrony of Post-classical and Early
                  Byzantine Greek,</title> <title rend="italic">Revue belge de Philologie et d’Histoire</title>, 91/1: 5–44. DOI:
                  10.3406/rbph.2013.8407</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bentein2016" label="Bentein 2016"> Bentein, K. (2016). <title rend="italic">Verbal periphrasis in ancient Greek: have- and be- constructions.</title>
                  Oxford: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="beschi2018" label="Beschi 2018"> Beschi, F. (2018). <title rend="quotes">The Ancient Greek sentence left periphery: A study on Homer,</title>
                  <title rend="italic">Journal of Greek Linguistics</title>, 18/2: 172–210. DOI: 10.1163/15699846-01802003</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="biber2009" label="Biber and Conrad 2009"> Biber, D., &amp; Conrad, S. (2009). <title rend="italic">Register, genre, and style</title>. Cambridge
                  textbooks in linguistics. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bonifazi2016" label="Bonifazi et al. 2016"> Bonifazi, A., Drummen, A., &amp; Kreij, M. de. (2016). <title rend="italic">Particles in Ancient Greek
                  Discourse: Exploring Particle Use across Genres. Hellenic Studies Series</title>, Vol. 74.
                  Washington, D.C.: Center for Hellenic Studies.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bowern2008" label="Bowern 2008"> Bowern, C. (2008). <title rend="quotes">The diachrony of complex predicates,</title> <title rend="italic">Diachronica</title>, 25/2:
                  161–85.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bowersock2014" label="Bowersock and Marchant 2014"> Bowersock, G., &amp; Marchant, E. (2014). <title rend="italic">Xenophon. Hiero. Agesilaus. Constitution
                  of the Lacedaemonians. Ways and Means. Cavalry Commander. Art of Horsemanship. On
                  Hunting. Constitution of the Athenians.</title> Cambridge, MA: Harvard University
                  Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="butt1995" label="Butt 1995"> Butt, M. (1995). <title rend="italic">The structure of complex predicates in Urdu.</title> Dissertations in
                  linguistics. Stanford: CSLI Publications.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="butt1997" label="Butt 1997"> Butt, M. (1997). <title rend="quotes">Complex predicates in Urdu.</title> Alsina A., Bresnan J., &amp; Sells P.
                  (eds) <title rend="italic">Complex predicates</title>, pp. 107–49. CSLI Publications: Stanford.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="butt2010" label="Butt 2010"> Butt, M. (2010). <title rend="quotes">The Light Verb Jungle: Still Hacking Away.</title> Amberger M., Baker B.,
                  &amp; Harvey M. (eds) <title rend="italic">Complex Predicates: Cross-Linguistic Perspectives on Event
                  Structure</title>, pp. 48–78. Cambridge University Press: Cambridge.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="butt2013a" label="Butt et al. 2013"> Butt, M., Geuder, W., van Riemsdijk, H., &amp; Corver, N. (2013). <title rend="quotes">On the
                  (semi)lexical status of light verbs.</title> <title rend="italic">Semi-lexical Categories, Studies in
                  Generative Grammar [SGG]</title>, Vol. 59, pp. 323–70. Mouton De Gruyter: Berlin ; Boston.
                  DOI: 10.1515/9783110874006.323</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="butt2013b" label="Butt and Lahiri 2013"> Butt, M., &amp; Lahiri, A. (2013). <title rend="quotes">Diachronic pertinacity of light verbs,</title>
                  <title rend="italic">Lingua</title>, 135: 7–29. DOI: 10.1016/j.lingua.2012.11.006</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="cap2015" label="Cap et al. 2015"> Cap, F., Nirmal, M., Weller, M., &amp; Schulte im Walde, S. (2015). <title rend="quotes">How to
                  Account for Idiomatic German Support Verb Constructions in Statistical Machine
                  Translation.</title> <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 11th Workshop on Multiword Expressions</title>, pp.
                  19–28. Denver, Colorado: Association for Computational Linguistics. DOI:
                  10.3115/v1/W15-0903</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="celano2013a" label="Celano 2013a"> Celano, G. (2013a). <title rend="quotes">Argument-focus and predicate-focus structure in Ancient
                  Greek,</title> <title rend="italic">Studies in Language</title>, 37/2: 241–66.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="celano2013b" label="Celano 2013b"> Celano G. (2013b). <title rend="quotes">Word Order.</title> G. Giannakis, Ed. <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia of Ancient Greek
                  Language and Linguistics.</title> Leiden; Boston: Brill.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cinque2004" label="Cinque 2004"> Cinque, G. (2004). <title rend="quotes">Restructuring and functional structure.</title> <title rend="italic">Structures and
                  beyond: The cartography of syntactic structures</title>, Vol. 3, pp. 132–91. Oxford
                  University Press: Oxford.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="cock1981" label="Cock 1981"> Cock, A. (1981). <title rend="quotes">ΠΟΙΕΙΣΘΑΙ: Πoiein. Sur les critères déterminant le choix entre
                  l’actif Πoiein et le moyen ΠΟΙΕΙΣΘΑΙ,</title> <title rend="italic">Mnemosyne</title>, 34/1/2: 1–62.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="constant2017" label="Constant et al. 2017"> Constant, M., Eryiğit, G., Monti, J., van der Plas, L., Ramisch, C., Rosner, M.,
                  &amp; Todirascu, A. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Multiword expression processing: A survey,</title>
                  Computational Linguistics, 43/4: 837–92. DOI: 10.1162/COLI_a_00302</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="cordeiro2019" label="Cordeiro and Candito 2019"> Cordeiro, S. R., &amp; Candito, M. (2019). <title rend="quotes">Syntax-based identification of
                  light-verb constructions.</title> <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 22nd Nordic Conference on
                  Computational Linguistics (NoDaLiDa)</title>, September 30 - October 2, Turku, Finland,
                  pp. 97–104. Presented at the Proceedings of the 22nd Nordic Conference on
                  Computational Linguistics (NoDaLiDa), Turku: Linköping Electronic Conference
                  Proceedings.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="creissels2016" label="Creissels 2016"> Creissels, D. (2016). <title rend="quotes">Univerbation of light verb compounds and the obligatory
                  coding principle.</title> Nash L. &amp; Samvelian P. (eds) <title rend="italic">Approaches to complex
                  predicates, Syntax and semantics,</title> Vol. 41, pp. 46–69. Brill: Leiden ; Boston.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="didakowski2020" label="Didakowski and Radtke 2020"> Didakowski, J., &amp; Radtke, N. (2020). <title rend="quotes">Verwendung der deutschen Stützverbgefüge
                  mit Adjektiven und ihre Ermittlung mithilfe des DWDS-Wortprofils.</title> De Knop S.
                  &amp; Hermann M. (eds) <title rend="italic">Funktionsverbgefüge im Fokus</title>, pp. 101–36. Mouton De
                  Gruyter: Berlin ; Boston.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dik1995" label="Dik 1995"> Dik, H. (1995). <title rend="quotes">Word Order in Ancient Greek: A Pragmatic Account of Word Order
                  Variation in Herodotus.</title> Amsterdam Studies in Classical Philology, Vol. 5. Leiden;
                  Boston: Brill.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="doucet2004" label="Doucet and Ahonen-Myka 2004"> Doucet, A., &amp; Ahonen-Myka, H. (2004). <title rend="quotes">Non-Contiguous Word Sequences for
                  Information Retrieval.</title> <title rend="italic">Second ACL Workshop on Multiword Expressions: Integrating
                  Processing,</title> July 2004, pp. 88–95. Barcelona: ACL Anthology. DOI:
                  10.3115/1613186.1613198</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="durant1994" label="Durant 1994"> Durant, J. (1994). <title rend="quotes">What is scientific literacy?,</title> <title rend="italic">European Review,</title> 2/1: 83–9.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="vanemdeboas2019" label="van Emde Boas 2019"> van Emde Boas, E., Rijksbaron, A., Huitink, L., &amp; de Bakker, M. (2019).
                  <title rend="italic">Cambridge grammar of classical Greek.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="fendel2020" label="Fendel 2020"> Fendel, V. (2020). <title rend="quotes">Taking Stock of Support-Verb Constructions in Journalistic
                  French,</title> <title rend="italic">Xanthos: A Journal of Foreign Literatures and Languages</title>, 2: 13–44.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="fendel2021" label="Fendel 2021"> Fendel, V. (2021). <title rend="quotes">Greek in Egypt or Egyptian Greek? Syntactic regionalisms (IV CE).</title>
                  Bentein K. &amp; Janse M. (eds) <title rend="italic">Varieties of Post-classical and Byzantine Greek,
                  Trends in Linguistics. Studies and monographs,</title> Vol. 331, pp. 115–40. Mouton De
                  Gruyter: Berlin.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="finnegan2011" label="Finnegan 2011"> Finnegan, R. (2011). <title rend="italic">Why do we quote?: the culture and history of quotation.</title>
                  Cambridge: Open Book Publishers.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="foley2007" label="Foley 2007"> Foley, W. (2007). <title rend="quotes">A typology of information packaging in the clause.</title> Shopen T.
                  (ed.) <title rend="italic">Language Typology and Syntactic Description: Volume 1: Clause Structure</title>, 2nd
                  ed., Vol. 1, pp. 325–61. Cambridge University Press: Cambridge. DOI:
                  10.1017/CBO9780511619427.006</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="frenda2017" label="Frenda 2017"> Frenda, A. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Non-conventional arguments: Finite and non-finite verbal
                  complementation in Sicilian.</title> Nolan B. &amp; Diedrichsen E. (eds) <title rend="italic">Argument
                  realisation in complex predicates and complex events: Verb-verb constructions at
                  the syntax-semantics interface, Studies in language companion series,</title> Vol. 180,
                  pp. 117–36. John Benjamins: Amsterdam ; Philadelphia.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="galdi2018" label="Galdi 2018"> Galdi, G. (2018). <title rend="quotes">On the use of facio as support verb in late and Merovingian
                  Latin,</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of Latin Linguistics</title>, 17/2: 231–57.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="greer2015" label="Greer 2015"> Greer, A. (2015). <title rend="italic">Xenophon and the Ancient Greek Cavalry Horse: an Equestrian
                  Perspective</title> (PhD thesis). National University of Ireland, Galway, Galway.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gross1998" label="Gross 1998"> Gross, M. (1998). <title rend="quotes">La fonction sémantique des verbes supports,</title> <title rend="italic">Travaux de
                  Linguistique : Revue Internationale de Linguistique Française,</title> 37/1: 25–46.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="halliday1976" label="Halliday 1976"> Halliday, M. (1976). <title rend="quotes">Cohesion in English.</title> <title rend="italic">English language series,</title> Vol. 9. London:
                  Longman.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="hermann2020" label="Hermann 2020"> Hermann, M. (2020). <title rend="quotes">Über Funktionsverbgefüge und verbale Mehrwortverbindungen.
                  Eine Analzse am Beispiel von stellen.</title> De Knop S. &amp; Hermann M. (eds)
                  <title rend="italic">Funktionsverbgefüge im Fokus</title>, pp. 39–74. Mouton De Gruyter: Berlin ; Boston.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hopper2003" label="Hopper and Traugott 2003"> Hopper, P., &amp; Traugott, E. (2003). <title rend="quotes">Grammaticalization.</title> <title rend="italic">Cambridge textbooks in
                  linguistics,</title> 2nd ed. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="howell2021" label="Howell and Brossard 2021"> Howell, E., &amp; Brossard, D. (2021). <title rend="quotes">(Mis)informed about what? What it means to
                  be a science-literate citizen in a digital world,</title> PNAS, 118: 1–8.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="hutchinson2017" label="Hutchinson 2017"> Hutchinson, G. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Repetition, range, and attention: The Iliad.</title> Tsagalis C.
                  &amp; Markantonatos A. (eds) <title rend="italic">The winnowing oar – new perspectives in Homeric
                  studies,</title> pp. 145–70. Mouton De Gruyter: Berlin ; Boston.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ittzes2007" label="Ittzés 2007"> Ittzés, M. (2007). <title rend="quotes">Remarks on the Periphrastic Constructions with the Verb 'to
               make, to do' in Sanskrit, Greek and Latin.</title> Csaba D. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Indian Languages and
                  Texts Through the Ages</title>. Essays of Hungarian Indologists in Honour of Prof. Csaba
                  Töttössy, pp. 1–40. Manohar: New Delhi.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ittzes2015" label="Ittzés 2015"> Ittzés, M. (2015). <title rend="quotes">Light verb constructions in Vedic,</title> <title rend="italic">Manas: Tradition and modernity
                  in Indian culture</title>, 2/1: 1–19.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jackson2016" label="Jackson 2016"> Jackson, R. (2016). <title rend="italic">The pragmatics of repetition, emphasis, and intensification</title>
                  (PhD). University of Salford, Salford.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jimenezlopez2011" label="Jiménez López 2011"> Jiménez López, M. (2011). <title rend="quotes">El uso de ποιεῖσθαι en Lisias: construcciones con
               verbo soporte,</title> <title rend="italic">Lingüística en la Red</title>, 9: 1–20.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jimenezlopez2012" label="Jiménez López 2012"> Jiménez López, M. (2012). <title rend="quotes">Construcciones con verbo soporte, verbo simple y nombre
                  predicativo: un ejemplo en griego antiguo / Support Verb Constructions, Simple
                  Verb and Predicative Noun: An Example in Ancient Greek,</title> <title rend="italic">Minerva</title>, 25: 83–105.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jimenezlopez2016" label="Jiménez López 2016"> Jiménez López, M. (2016). <title rend="quotes">On Support Verb Constructions in Ancient Greek,</title> <title rend="italic">Archivio
                  glottologico italiano</title>, 51/2: 180–204.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jimenezlopez2021" label="Jiménez López 2021"> Jiménez López, María. (2021). <title rend="quotes">Γίγνομαι as the Lexical Passive of the Support Verb
                  ποιέω in Ancient Greek.</title> Giannakis G., Conti L., de la Villa J., &amp; Fornieles
                  R. (eds) <title rend="italic">Synchrony and Diachrony of Ancient Greek: Language, linguistics and
                  philology</title>, pp. 227–40. Mouton De Gruyter: Berlin ; Boston.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kamber2008" label="Kamber 2008"> Kamber, A. (2008). <title rend="quotes">Funktionsverbgefüge — empirisch: eine korpusbasierte
                  Untersuchung zu den nominalen Prädikaten des Deutschen,</title> Reihe Germanistische
               <title rend="italic">Linguistik</title>, Vol. 281. Tübingen: Max Niemeyer.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="kilgarriff2014" label="Kilgarriff et al. 2014"> Kilgarriff, A., Baisa, V., Bušta, J., Jakubíček, M., Kovář, V., Michelfeit, J.,
                  Rychlý, P., et al. (2014). <title rend="quotes">The Sketch Engine: ten years on,</title> <title rend="italic">Lexicography</title>, 1/1:
                  7–36. DOI: 10.1007/s40607-014-0009-9</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="koev2022" label="Koev 2022"> Koev, T. (2022). <title rend="quotes">Parenthetical meaning,</title> <title rend="italic">Oxford studies in semantics and
                  pragmatics,</title> Vol. 14. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lakoff1980" label="Lakoff and Johnson 1980"> Lakoff, G., &amp; Johnson, M. (1980). <title rend="italic">Metaphors we live by.</title> Chicago ; London:
                  University of Chicago Press.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="langer2004" label="Langer 2004"> Langer, S. (2004). <title rend="quotes">A linguistic test battery for support verb constructions,</title>
                  <title rend="italic">Lingvisticæ Investigationes</title>, 27/2: 171–84. DOI: 10.1075/li.27.2.03lan</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="langslow2000" label="Langslow 2000"> Langslow, D. (2000). <title rend="italic">Medical Latin in the Roman Empire.</title> Oxford classical
                  monographs. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lehmann2020" label="Lehmann 2020"> Lehmann, C. (2020). <title rend="quotes">Univerbation,</title> <title rend="italic">Folia Linguistica Historica</title>, 41/1: 205–52.
                  DOI: 10.1515/flih-2020-0007</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="lipka1981" label="Lipka 1981"> Lipka, L. (1981). <title rend="quotes">Zur Lexikalisierung im Deutschen und Englischen.</title> Lipka L.
                  &amp; Günther H. (eds) <title rend="italic">Wortbildung, Wege der Forschung</title>, Vol. 564, pp. 119–32.
                  Wissenschaftliche Buchgesellschaft: Darmstadt.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="lipka1992" label="Lipka 1992"> Lipka, L. (1992). <title rend="quotes">Lexicalization and Institutionalization in English and German,</title>
                  <title rend="italic">Linguistica Pragensia</title>, 1: 1–13.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="loporcaro2022" label="Loporcaro 2022"> Loporcaro, M. (2022). <title rend="quotes">The morphological nature of person-driven auxiliation.</title>
                  Ledgeway A., Smith J. C., &amp; Vincent N. (eds) <title rend="italic">Periphrasis and inflexion in
                  diachrony: a view from romance</title>, Oxford studies in diachronic and historical
                  linguistics, pp. 213–37. University Press: Oxford.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lowe2017" label="Lowe 2017"> Lowe, J. (2017). <title rend="italic">Transitive Nouns and Adjectives: Evidence from Early Indo-Aryan</title>.
                  Oxford Studies in Diachronic and Historical Linguistics. Oxford: Oxford University
                  Press. DOI: 10.1093/oso/9780198793571.001.0001</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="luraghi2003" label="Luraghi 2003"> Luraghi, S. (2003). <title rend="quotes">Definite referential null objects in Ancient Greek,</title>
                  <title rend="italic">Indogermanische Forschungen</title>, 108: 167–94. DOI: 10.1515/9783110243482.167</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="machounis2004" label="Machounis 2004 "> Machounis, P. (2004). <title rend="quotes">Nominalizations of English Neutral Verbs.</title> Leclère C.,
                  Laporte É., Piot M., &amp; Silberztein M. (eds) <title rend="italic">Lexique, Syntaxe et
                  Lexique-Grammaire / Syntax, Lexis &amp; Lexicon-Grammar: Papers in honour of
                  Maurice Gross, Lingvisticae Investigationes Supplementa</title>, Vol. 24, pp. 413–21. John
                  Benjamins: Amsterdam.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="maienschein1998" label="Maienschein 1998"> Maienschein, J. (1998). <title rend="quotes">Scientific Literacy,</title> Science, 281: 917. DOI:
                  10.1126/science.281.5379.917</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="maiko2020" label="Maiko 2020"> Maiko, T. (2020). <title rend="quotes">What Can You Give in Italian that You Can’t Give in Russian? A
                  Contrastive Study of Constructions with the Light Verbs dare in Italian and
                  davat’/dat’ in Russian.</title> Szerszunowicz J. &amp; Awier M. (eds) <title rend="italic">Reproducible
                  Multiword Expressions from a Theoretical and Empirical Perspective</title>, pp. 33–53.
                  University of Bialystok Publishing House: Białystok.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="marini2010" label="Marini 2010"> Marini, E. (2010). <title rend="quotes">L’antipassivo in greco antico: ποιείσθαι come verbo supporto
                  in Aristotele,</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of Latin Linguistics</title>, 11/1: 147–80. DOI:
                  10.1515/joll.2010.11.1.147</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="marini2018" label="Marini 2018"> Marini, E. (2018). <title rend="quotes">La fonction support et ses facettes: facere [+support] {+causatif]
                  dans le type sacra facere.</title> Spevak O. &amp; Bodelot C. (eds) <title rend="italic">Les constructions à
                  verbe support en latin, Cahier du Laboratoire de Recherche sur la Langage,</title> Vol. 7,
                  pp. 129–47. Presses Universitaires Blaise Pascal: Clermont-Ferrand.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="mastronarde2013" label="Mastronarde 2013"> Mastronarde, D. (2013). <title rend="quotes">Ancient Greek Tutorials (atticgreek.org) as complementary
                  content for use with Introduction to Attic Greek, Second Edition (University of
                  California Press 2013),</title>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="mcgillivray2013" label="McGillivray and Kilgarriff 2013"> McGillivray, B., &amp; Kilgarriff, A. (2013). <title rend="quotes">Tools for historical corpus
                  research, and a corpus of Latin.</title> Bennett P., Durrell M., Scheible S., &amp; Whitt
                  R. (eds) <title rend="italic">New Methods in Historical Corpora, Korpuslinguistik und interdisyiplinäre
                  Perspektiven auf Sprache,</title> Vol. 3, pp. 247–57. Narr: Tübingen.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcgreevy2012" label="McGreevy 2012"> McGreevy, P. (2012). <title rend="italic">Equine behavior: a guide for veterinarians and equine
                  scientists.</title> 2nd ed. Edinburgh: Saunders Elsevier.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcilwraith2011" label="McIlwraith and Rollin 2011"> McIlwraith, C. W., &amp; Rollin, B. (2011). <title rend="italic">Equine welfare</title>. UFAW animal welfare
                  series. Oxford: Wiley-Blackwell.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="melcuk1996" label="Mel’čuk 1996"> Mel’čuk, I. (1996). <title rend="quotes">Lexical functions: a tool for the description of lexical
               relations in a lexicon.</title> Wanner L. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Lexical Functions in Lexicography and
                  Natural Language Processing</title>, pp. 37–102. John Benjamins: Amsterdam.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="melcuk2004" label="Mel’čuk 2004"> Mel’čuk, I. (2004). <title rend="quotes">Verbes supports sans peine,</title> <title rend="italic">Lingvisticæ Investigationes</title>,
                  27/2: 203–17. DOI: 10.1075/li.27.2.05mel</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="myersscotten2002" label="Myers-Scotton 2002"> Myers-Scotton, C. (2002). <title rend="italic">Contact Linguistics: Bilingual Encounters and
                  Grammatical Outcomes.</title> Oxford: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="nagy2013" label="Nagy et al. 2013"> Nagy, I., Vincze, V., &amp; Farkas, R. (2013). <title rend="quotes">Full-coverage Identification of
                  English Light Verb Constructions.</title> <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Sixth International Joint
                  Conference on Natural Language Processing</title>, pp. 329–37. Presented at the IJCNLP
                  2013, October, Nagoya, Japan: Asian Federation of Natural Language Processing.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nunberg1994" label="Nunberg et al. 1994"> Nunberg, G., Sag, I., &amp; Wasow, T. (1994). <title rend="quotes">Idioms,</title> <title rend="italic">Language</title>, 70: 491–538.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pasquer2017" label="Pasquer 2017"> Pasquer, C. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Expressions polylexicales verbales : étude de la variabilité
                  en corpus (Verbal MWEs : a corpus-based study of variability).</title> Flamein H. &amp;
                  Parmentier Y. (eds) <title rend="italic">Actes des 24ème conférence sur le traitement automatique des
                  langues naturelles</title>. 19es REncontres jeunes Chercheurs en Informatique pour le TAL
                  (RECITAL 2017), Orléans (France), pp. 161–74. ATALA.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pasquer2020" label="Pasquer et al. 2020"> Pasquer, C., Savary, A., Ramisch, C., &amp; Antoine, J. (2020). <title rend="quotes">Verbal Multiword
                  Expression Identification: Do We Need a Sledgehammer to Crack a Nut?.</title> The 28th
                  <title rend="italic">International Conference on Computational Linguistics</title> (COLING-20). Barcelona,
                  Spain: ACL Anthology.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pasquer2018" label="Pasquer et al. 2018"> Pasquer, C., Savary, A., Ramisch, C., &amp; Antoine, J.-Y. (2018). <title rend="quotes">If you’ve seen
                  some, you’ve seen them all: Identifying variants of multiword expressions.</title>
                  <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 27th International Conference on Computational Linguistics</title>, pp.
                  2582–94. Presented at the COLING 2018, Santa Fe, New Mexico, USA: Association for
                  Computational Linguistics.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pompei2006" label="Pompei 2006"> Pompei, A. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Tracce di incorporazione in greco antico.</title> Cuzzolin P. &amp;
                  Napoli M. (eds) <title rend="italic">Fonologia e tipologia lessicale nella storia della lingua greca</title>.
                  Atti del Incontro Internazionale di Linguistica Greca, Bergamo, 15–17 September
                  2005, pp. 216–37. FrancoAngeli: Milan.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="radimsky2011" label="Radimský 2011"> Radimský, J. (2011). <title rend="quotes">Noms prédicatifs, noms de résultat et noms concrets dans les
               constructions à verbe support,</title> <title rend="italic">Lingvisticæ Investigationes</title>, 34/2: 204–27. DOI:
                  10.1075/li.34.2.02rad</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="reintges2001" label="Reintges 2001"> Reintges, C. (2001). <title rend="quotes">Code-mixing strategies in Coptic Egyptian.</title> Goldwasser O.
                  &amp; Sweeney D. (eds) <title rend="italic">Structuring Egyptian syntax: a tribute to Sarah Israelit-
                  Groll, Lingua Aegyptia</title>, Vol. 9, pp. 193–237. Widmaier: Hamburg.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ronan2012" label="Ronan 2012"> Ronan, P. (2012). <title rend="quotes">Make peace and take victory: support verb constructions in old
               English in comparison with old Irish.</title> <title rend="italic">North-Western European language evolution
                  Supplement</title>, Vol. 24. Odense: University Press of Southern Denmark.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rosen2020" label="Rosén 2020"> Rosén, H. (2020). <title rend="quotes">Composite predicates in the layers of Latin,</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of Latin
                  Linguistics</title>, 19/2: 231–79. DOI: 10.1515/joll-2020-2009</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="rutherford2010" label="Rutherford 2010"> Rutherford, I. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Bilingualism in Roman Egypt? Exploring the archive of
                  Phatres of Narmuthis.</title> Evans T. &amp; Obbink D. (eds) <title rend="italic">The language of the papyri</title>,
                  pp. 198–207. Oxford University Press: Oxford.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rychly2008" label="Rychlý 2008"> Rychlý, P. (2008). <title rend="quotes">A Lexicographer-Friendly Association Score.</title> Sojka P. &amp;
               Horak A. (eds) <title rend="italic">Proceedings of Recent Advances in Slavonic Natural Language
                  Processing</title>, RASLAN 2008, pp. 6–9. Brno: Masaryk University.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rysova2017" label="Rysová 2017"> Rysová, K. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Possibilities of text coherence analysis in the Prague
               Dependecy Treebank.</title> Menzel K., Lapshinova-Koltunski E., &amp; Kunz K. (eds) <title rend="italic">New
                  perspectives on cohesion and coherence: implications for translation, Translation
                  and multilingual natural language processing</title>, Vol. 6, pp. 35–48. Language Science
                  Press: Berlin.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="sag2002" label="Sag et al. 2002"> Sag, I., Baldwin, T., Bond, F., &amp; Copestake, A. (2002). <title rend="quotes">Multiword
                  expressions: A pain in the neck for NLP.</title> Gelbukh A. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 3rd
                  International conference on Computational Linguistics and Intelligent Text
                  Processing</title>, pp. 1–15. Springer: Berlin; Heidelberg.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="sanromanvilas2009" label="Sanroman Vilas 2009"> Sanroman Vilas, B. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Diferencias semanticas entre construcciones con verbo
                  de apoyo y sus correlatos verbales simples,</title> <title rend="italic">Estudios de Lingüística</title>. Universidad
                  de Alicante, 23: 289–314.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="savary2018" label="Savary et al. 2018"> Savary, A., Candito, M., Mititelu, V., Bejček, E., Cap, F., Čéplö, S., Cordeiro,
                  S., et al. (2018). <title rend="quotes">PARSEME multilingual corpus of verbal multiword expressions.</title>
                  Markantonatou S., Ramisch C., Savary A., &amp; Vincze V. (eds) <title rend="italic">Multiword
                  expressions at length and in depth: Extended papers from the MWE 2017 workshop</title>,
                  pp. 87–147. Language Science Press: Berlin.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="scheible2013" label="Scheible et al. 2013"> Scheible, S., Schulte im Walde, S., Weller, M., &amp; Kisselew, M. (2013). <title rend="quotes">A
                  Compact but Linguistically Detailed Database for German Verb Subcategorisation
                  relying on Dependency Parses from Web Corpora: Tool, Guidelines and Resource.</title>
                  <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 8th Web as Corpus Workshop (WAC-8) @Corpus Linguistics 2013</title>.
                  Presented at the 8th Web as Corpus Workshop (WAC-8).</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="sheinfux2019" label="Sheinfux et al. 2019"> Sheinfux, L., Greshler, T., Melnik, N., &amp; Winter, S. (2019). <title rend="quotes">Verbal multiword
                  expressions: Idiomaticity and flexibility.</title> Parmentier Y. &amp; Waszczuk J. (eds)
                  <title rend="italic">Representing and parsing of multiword expressions, Phraseology and Multiword
                  Expressions</title>, Vol. 3, pp. 35–68. Language Science Press: Berlin.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="storrer2009" label="Storrer 2009"> Storrer, A. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Corpus-based investigations on German support verb
                  constructions.</title> Fellbaum C. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Idioms and collocations: Corpus-based linguistic
                  and lexicographic studies, Research in corpus and discourse</title>, pp. 164–87.
                  Continuum: London.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tutin2016" label="Tutin 2016"> Tutin, A. (2016). <title rend="quotes">Comparing morphological and syntactic variations of support
                  verb constructions and verbal full phrasemes in French: a corpus based study.</title>
                  <title rend="italic">PARSEME COST Action. Relieving the pain in the neck in natural language
                  processing: 7th final general meeting. Dubrovnil, Croatia</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="unwin2007" label="Unwin et al. 2007"> Unwin, L., Hughes, J., &amp; Jewson, N. (2007). <title rend="italic">Communities of practice: critical
                  perspectives</title>. London: Routledge.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="webster2019" label="Webster 2019"> Webster, J. (2019). <title rend="quotes">Key Terms in the SFL Model.</title> Thompson G., Bowcher W.,
                  Fontaine L., &amp; Schönthal D. (eds) <title rend="italic">The Cambridge Handbook of Systemic
                  Functional Linguistics</title>, pp. 35–54. Cambridge University Press: Cambridge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="willi2003" label="Willi 2003"> Willi, A. (2003). <title rend="italic">The languages of Aristophanes: aspects of linguistic variation
                  in Classical Attic Greek</title>. Oxford classical monographs. Oxford: Oxford University
                  Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="willi2010" label="Willi 2010"> Willi, A. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Register Variation.</title> Bakker E. (ed.) <title rend="italic">A Companion to the Ancient
                  Greek Language</title>, pp. 295–310. John Wiley &amp; Sons: Chicester; Malden.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="zilliacus1956" label="Zilliacus 1956"> Zilliacus, H. (1956). <title rend="quotes">Zur Umschreibung des Verbums in spätgriechischen Urkunden,</title>
                  <title rend="italic">Eranos</title>, 54: 160–6.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="willi1967" label="Willi 1967"> Willi, A. (1967). <title rend="quotes">Zur Abundanz der spätgriechischen Gebrauchssprache</title>. <title rend="italic">Commentationes
                  humanarum litterarum</title>, Vol. 41/2. Helsinki: Societas Scientiarum Fennica.</bibl>
            
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
