<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Making the Whole
               Greater than the Sum of its Parts: Taxonomy Development as a Site of Negotiation and
               Compromise in an Interdisciplinary Software Development Project</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Jennifer C. <dhq:family>Edmond</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9991-1637</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Trinity College Dublin</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>edmondj@tcd.ie</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Alejandro <dhq:family>Benito Santos</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5317-6390</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Salamanca</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>abenito@usal.es</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Michelle <dhq:family>Doran</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7850-6886</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Digital Repository of Ireland</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>m.doran@ria.ie</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Roberto <dhq:family>Therón</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6739-8875</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Salamanca</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>theron@usal.es</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Michał <dhq:family>Kozak</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8715-9326</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation/>
               <email>mkozak@man.poznan.pl</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Cezary <dhq:family>Mazurek</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Institute of Bioorganic Chemistry of the Polish Academy of
                  Sciences</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>mazurek@man.poznan.pl</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Eveline <dhq:family>Wandl-Vogt</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Austrian Academy of Sciences</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>eveline.wandl-vogt@oeaw.ac.at</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Aleyda Rocha <dhq:family>Sepulveda</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Austrian Academy of Sciences</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>aleyda.rocha@oeaw.ac.at</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000701</idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->017</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->3</idno>
            <date when="2023-07-10">10 July 2023</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
			<term corresp="#collaboration"/>
			<term corresp="#project_report"/>
			<term corresp="#interdisciplinarity"/>
			<term corresp="#dh"/>
			<term corresp="#data_curation"/>
			<term corresp="#markup"/>
		</keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000701/000701.xml">GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>This paper describes the experience of a group of interdisciplinary researchers and
               research professionals involved in the PROgressive VIsual DEcision-making in Digital
               Humanities (PROVIDEDH) project, a four-year project funded within the CHIST-ERA call
               2016 for the topic <title rend="quotes">Visual Analytics for Decision Making under
                  Uncertainty — VADMU</title>. It contributes to the academic literature on how
               digital methods can enhance interdisciplinary cooperative work by exploring the
               collaboration involved in developing visualisations to lead decision-making in
               historical research in a specific interdisciplinary research setting. More
               specifically, we discuss how the cross-disciplinary design of a taxonomy of sources
               of uncertainty in Digital Humanities (DH), a <quote rend="inline">profoundly
                  collaborative enterprise</quote> built at the intersection of computer science and
               humanities research, became not just an instrument to organise data, but also a tool
               to negotiate and build compromises between different communities of practice.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>We discuss how the cross-disciplinary design of a taxonomy of sources of uncertainty
               in Digital Humanities (DH) became not just an instrument to organise data, but also a
               tool to negotiate and build compromises between different communities of
               practice.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>1. Introduction and Overview</head>
            <p>Increasingly, research policy-makers and funders are calling for inter- and
               transdisciplinary approaches to be applied in response to complex socio-scientific
               questions. Whilst the most exciting and ground-breaking innovations, to paraphrase
               Carlos Moedas, former European Commissioner for Research, Science and Innovation, may
               indeed be happening at the intersection of disciplines, this kind of
               cross-disciplinary collaboration poses many challenges, among which are the
               individual disciplinary values, concepts of proof and evidence, languages, technical
               cultures and methodologies employed by different domains (<ptr target="#bruce_etal2004"/>; <ptr target="#lowe_ecology_2009"/>; <ptr target="#edmond_deliverable_2018"/>). It is perhaps unsurprising that overcoming
               the challenges associated with specialised terminology/vocabulary is often
               instrumental to the success of cooperative work involving individuals of different
               disciplinary backgrounds and expertise levels (<ptr target="#skeels_revealing_2008"/>; <ptr target="#bruce_etal2004"/>). This may be, in particular, the case when the
               goal of the cooperation is to build a software platform, within and behind which
               mutual misunderstandings can become encoded, creating dissonances in structure and
               function, and potentially leading to difficulties for future users. This paper
               contributes to the academic literature on how a specific kind of technical artifact –
               in this case, a taxonomy of uncertainty – was used to enhance the functionality of a
               technical team and their co-developed platform itself created for the purpose of
               supporting interdisciplinary cooperative work. More specifically, we discuss how the
               cross-disciplinary design of this taxonomy became not just an instrument to organise
               data, but also a tool to negotiate and build compromises between four different
               communities of practice, each of which came to the project with a very different
               epistemically ‘native’ approach to issues of uncertainty. In order to illustrate the
               many interlinked functions, the taxonomy was required to perform, we will briefly
               introduce the project, its aims, and the four diverse but complementary partners that
               came together to deliver it. We will then discuss the taxonomy itself, how it needed
               to be adapted from earlier, similar work, and some of the issues it allowed the
               project team to negotiate and discuss. In the final section, we will look at the
               application of the taxonomy and how it informs system function in a manner that is
               sensitive to the requirements of all of the disciplinary stakeholders in the
               project.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>2. Background and Context of the Collaboration</head>
            <p>The project in question is the PROgressive VIsual DEcision-Making in Digital
               Humanities (PROVIDEDH) project, which aimed to develop a web-based multimodal
               collaborative platform for the visual analysis of uncertainty in the Digital
               Humanities (DH) data analysis pipeline (discussed in further detail below). The
               consortium can be described as both complex and nonroutine <ptr target="#strauss_articulation_1988"/>, comprising a multinational team of four
               institutional partners and two overlapping sub-teams (composed of the two technical
               partners and two partners representing the arts and humanities). Further, the
               individual partner teams combine researchers and engineers of varying levels of
               expertise in specific branches of computer science and humanities disciplines as well
               as in open innovation and DH.</p>
            <p>The PROVIDEDH project was originally conceptualised according to the imperatives of
               computer science as a discipline. The coordinator, based in the Visual Analytics and
               Information Visualisation Research Group (VisUsal) at the University of Salamanca
               (USAL), brought expertise in visual analytics, research methods, software
               engineering, and human-computer interaction (HCI). In addition to the project
               coordination activities, USAL led both the development of user interfaces and
               evaluation and the research for the definition and management of uncertainty in DH.
               The second technical partner, the Poznan Supercomputing and Networking Center (PSNC),
               brought extensive experience designing and building large-scale DH infrastructures,
               and led the development of the PROVIDEDH platform. Considering its intended user
               base, however, the technological expertise of USAL and PSNC alone would not have been
               sufficient to realise the PROVIDEDH platform. Realising the principle <quote rend="inline">that [Digital Humanities] tool builders must consider themselves as
                  entering into a social contract with tool users</quote>
               <ptr target="#gibbs_building_2012"/>, two further partners, Trinity College Dublin
               and the Austrian Academy of Science (in conjunction with the Ars Electronica Research
               Institute Knowledge for Humanity), were brought on to contribute from the perspective
               of Digital Humanities and Open Innovation Science respectively, and led research
               regarding user needs, user engagement, and exploitation and dissemination of
               results.</p>
            <p>One of PROVIDEDH’s first objectives was to define and describe the key types of
               uncertainty in DH research datasets. To date, various definitions, classifications
               and taxonomies of uncertainty have been proposed, but much of this work on the
               characterisation of uncertainty has been delivered within isolated domains. As Kouw
               et al. (2012) argue, typologies of this kind are valuable tools in the attempt to
               determine the extent to which uncertainties can in fact be explained. Perhaps more
               importantly from the perspective of PROVIDEDH is the authors’ assertion that new
               forms of knowledge production that challenge our understanding of uncertainty <quote rend="inline">almost always occur at the boundaries between different
                  disciplines.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>3. Overcoming the Communicative Factor: Establishing a Baseline for
               Collaboration</head>
            <p>As described above, the PROVIDEDH team is diverse with goals that could only be met
               via closely aligned collaboration. A recent report by the EU-funded SHAPE-ID project,
               which addressed the challenge of improving inter- and transdisciplinary cooperation
               between Arts, Humanities and Social Sciences (AHSS) and Science, Technology,
               Engineering, Mathematics, and Medicine (STEMM) disciplines, identified 25 factors
               that influence interdisciplinary success or failure, depending on the circumstances
               of a project <ptr target="#vienni_baptista_final_2020"/>. One of the first and
               primary challenges faced by the PROVIDEDH team relates to what Vienni and Baptista
               (among others) describe as the <q>Communicative</q> factor, which refers to the
               different <q>languages</q> employed by different disciplines (<ptr target="#lowe_ecology_2009"/>; <ptr target="#boix_mansilla_shared_2016"/>; <ptr target="#vienni_baptista_final_2020"/>). The absence of a common transdisciplinary
               language/terminology to discuss shared concepts such as uncertainty can substantially
               hinder interdisciplinary research and, conversely, processes to resolve this gap are
               exceptionally useful for illustrating how the development of shared intellectual
               artifacts can create a common ground for exchange.</p>
            <p>Even among groups with apparently similar disciplinary backgrounds, conceptual
               frameworks may differ substantially (<ptr target="#jeffrey_smoothing_2003"/>; <ptr target="#pennington_cross-disciplinary_2008"/>). To cite one example, research
               conducted by the Knowledge Complexity (KPLEX) project found that inconsistent and
               contradictory statements in academic literature on such a foundational word as ‘data’
               are manifold, even and indeed especially, within the field of computer science. In a
               series of interviews conducted with computer scientists, the project team found the
               trend <quote rend="inline">point[ing ]towards an epistemic cultural bias towards
                  viewing data, whatever it is, as broadly encompassing, and in terms of its
                  function or utility in the research project, rather than a complex set of
                  information objects that come with biases built in to them, and which might merit
                  a certain amount of meta-reflection</quote>
               <ptr target="#edmond_power_2022"/>. In essence, the discourse of data in computer
               science appears indicative of what Edward Hall would call a ‘high context’ culture in
               which the precise context, in which a word is used, can determine its intended
               meaning in a way that might be opaque to outsiders. Needless to say, if the
               possibility for variant understandings can be so high within a single discipline, the
               gaps between the humanities (a much lower context culture) and computer science
               surely add to the difficulty of creating a unified classification of certain
               phenomena. The discourse, or more accurately discourses, on key terminology such as
               data or uncertainty can have a serious delimiting effect on the potential of
               cross-disciplinary, cooperative projects:</p>
            <p>”[O]ur traditional reliance on community ties to overcome the flaws in both our data
               and the terminology we use to speak of it do not translate well to larger scale
               interdisciplinary endeavours, to environments where the backgrounds or motivations of
               researchers/participants are not necessarily known or trusted or to environments
               where either the foundations of the research objects (such as is found in big data)
               or those of the algorithmic processing results (such as found in many AI
               applications) are not superficially legible to a human researcher.” <ptr target="#edmond_deliverable_2018" loc="p. 10"/>. </p>
            <p>In this same report, the KPLEX project also set forth a number of recommendations for
               fostering fruitful interdisciplinary collaboration, including a commitment to the
               negotiation of key terminology and hierarchies <ptr target="#edmond_deliverable_2018" loc="p. 13"/>. As a first step then, a project must establish a baseline for
               collaboration. However, the requirements for this baseline, what can and cannot be
               taken for granted, are very much predicated on the starting position of those seeking
               to cooperate, which we outline briefly below.</p>
            <div>
               <head>3.1. The HCI Perspective</head>
               <p>Although not specialised in the Digital Humanities, USAL brought previous
                  experience working in this context into the PROVIDEDH project. From this
                  experience, they were sensitised to how the increasing use of computational and
                  visualisation artefacts in the humanities had been able to produce important
                  results on both sides of the collaboration, but also to critical voices that had
                  risen to point to the perils of producing visual representations that may prevent
                  humanities researchers from performing correct critical interpretations of the
                  analysed data <ptr target="#drucker_graphical_2015"/>. The pernicious potential
                  results of this effect have been at the centre of many debates among humanities
                  and visualisation researchers and continue up to this day (<ptr target="#coles_think_2017"/>; <ptr target="#lamqaddam_when_2018"/>; <ptr target="#lamqaddam_introducing_2021"/>). The root of this problem may be
                  related to the abuse of black-box approaches that diminish the users’ capabilities
                  to understand the inner workings of the algorithms at play and interpret results
                     <ptr target="#theron_sanchez_towards_2019"/>. Whereas the correct application
                  of visualisation techniques is known to resolve some of these problems, there is
                  still an urgent need for conceptual HCI and visualisation frameworks that are able
                  to translate the needs of humanities researchers into the computational plane and
                  use them to generate adequate user interfaces that can overcome the aforementioned
                  problems. Along this line, uncertainty visualisation has been found necessary to
                  effectively open the algorithmic black-box and effectively expose it to a human
                  operator. However, the visualisation of uncertainty has been recently reconsidered
                  in connection with how the persons actually perceive the visualisations trying to
                  convey uncertainty, which unfortunately is not usually happening in the way the
                  creator of the visualisation would expect <ptr target="#padilla_uncertainty_2021"/>, and much of the current work focuses on producing visualisations for
                  evaluating decision-making in ad-hoc use-cases that can hardly be applied to a
                  real humanities research context. To fill in this gap, the efforts presented in
                  this paper are oriented precisely towards building a theoretical visualisation
                  framework that enables collaboration between many human and computational actors,
                  in a temporally and spatially distributed manner.<lb/>The newly developed taxonomy
                  fills a gap in the field of Humanities by addressing the issue of uncertainty from
                  the perspective of Human-Computer Interaction. It lays the foundation for creating
                  general guidelines and tools to help answer questions about when and how to
                  communicate uncertainty in Digital Humanities workflows.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>3.2. The Humanities Perspective</head>
               <p>As one of the intended groups of end users of any tool or resource PROVIDEDH might
                  build, it was critical that the needs and expectations of humanists would be
                  central to the development of the project’s platform. However, as a collective
                  descriptor the term ‘(the) Digital Humanities’ (DH) captures a broad range of
                  research and research-related activities, sectors and stakeholders. This often
                  obscures important differences between individual disciplines that bear on the
                  ways they position themselves in relation to digital technology and with other
                  disciplines. This perspective was represented in the project by Trinity College
                  Dublin’s Digital Humanities Centre, which brings together a team highly
                  experienced in fostering the work of a range of traditional humanities
                  disciplines, including history. This work focused on the experiences of historians
                  and literary scholars with exposure to building and/or using digital research
                  tools. The aim of this segmentation was first and foremost to establish the
                  expectations of a specific intended user base, as only through such specificity
                  could the questions of uncertainty be adequately broached.</p>
               <p>Even within this context, there is great room for variation in interpretation and
                  practices. As the user modelling work of the DH@TCD team showed, a historian may,
                  on one level, question her ability to read a historic text or question the date
                  attributed to a certain event within an earlier interpretation. She may also,
                  however, question whether an event was understood at the time as it is generally
                  described now, or indeed whether the records of a given event have become
                  corrupted or biased over time. The novelty and complexity of DH research combined
                  with the idiosyncratic challenges of working with cultural heritage data mean that
                  uncertainty can hinder substantially in the use and reuse of digital cultural
                  resources, which might make it more difficult for a user to probe the context or
                  provenance of a given fact or interpretation. Throughout the DH analysis pipeline,
                  many decisions have to be made which depend on managing uncertainty, pertaining to
                  both the datasets and the models behind them. Traditional humanities tools for
                  managing uncertainty, such as corroboration among multiple sources, or inclusion
                  of footnotes or explications to note a point of uncertainty, are themselves built
                  on the preservation of complexity and scrutability. This is an epistemic cultural
                  bias that can lead to resistance to taxonomy-based approaches, as the reduction of
                  parameters to fit a simplified model can be perceived as an opening to un- or
                  misinformed conclusions. Yet without such tools, these disciplines cannot benefit
                  from purpose-built ancillary tools in the form of interactive visualisations or
                  novel user interfaces in the digital research environment. The successful
                  development of a fit-for-purpose digital research environment – defined here as
                  the adoption of the tool by the intended user base – is therefore highly dependent
                  on the correct categorisation of the different types of heterogenous phenomena,
                  including uncertainty, within DH.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>3.3. The Open Innovation Perspective</head>
               <p>The PROVIDEDH project and its taxonomy were not intended to have an impact only in
                  historical research but also more widely as a way to understand the complex,
                  tacit, or compound forms of uncertainty. Under the paradigm of Open Innovation,
                  inflows and outflows of knowledge are positioned with the purpose to advance and
                  expand possibilities of external through stakeholders. Thus, the boundaries
                  between sourcing and the utilisation of an organisation’s external environment
                  become flexible with more opportunities for innovation. The application of inbound
                  Open innovation in the Digital Humanities allows organisations to reframe
                  knowledge behind activities that recombine, search and capture technologies in a
                  prompt manner that on-board current and urgent issues. Open Innovation becomes a
                  social process derived from key factors such as declining knowledge hegemony,
                  mobility of workers and growing influence of start-ups in supporting information
                  and communication technologies. In other words, Open innovation provides new
                  channels to knowledge transfer and dissemination that ignite broader accessibility
                  and diffusion of knowledge. The presence of Open Innovation practices creates new
                  areas to stretch outreach that currently does not fit in existing subfields. As
                  innovation is not a linear process, stakeholders feed into the development of work
                  combining physical and digital engagements that centre people within new models
                  that adapt to new bubbling markets.</p>
               <p>Open Innovation goes across the boundaries of organisations touching into a wide
                  set of fields, such as low-tech industries, small and medium-sized enterprises
                  (SMEs), or not-for-profit organisations. Thus, the linkage of policies with
                  innovation and science could help close gaps of uneven growth in productivity and
                  prosperity by opening datasets along with public/private partnerships to enhance
                  universities’ relations with industries. Additionally, policies with an Open
                  Innovation perspective embrace uncertainty not only by new funding schemes but by
                  intersecting programmes for frontier science where complex problems are
                  confronted.</p>
               <p>The research reads, applies, and interacts with the apparatus that conforms system
                  transitions in everyday life through a set of intersectional theories across a
                  variety of points of design with the goal to demonstrate the complex interactions
                  shaping and impacting our understanding of uncertainty within data and data
                  collection practice. To answer these questions, the Austrian project team
                  undertook a number of events and interventions to explore possible approaches that
                  prioritise collaboration around uncertainty in data as a socialising experience
                  challenging the current status quo. </p>
               <p>The taxonomy developed in the project supports the Open Innovation paradigm by
                  making it possible to explicitly express information about data uncertainty using
                  characteristics relevant to the Digital Humanities and similar fields. The
                  expression of the information is not only theoretical but can be applied in
                  practice using the well-known and accepted TEI guidelines, as described in the
                  following section. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>3.4. The Standards Perspective (TEI)</head>
               <p>To resolve the tensions raised by USAL in a manner able to meet the needs of both
                  the professional historian and the citizen scientist, a particular development
                  approach would be required. As with USAL, in recent years, researchers at PSNC had
                  been involved as technical partners in a number of Digital Humanities projects.
                  Through these projects in particular, they developed a sensitivity to the use of
                  the TEI (Text Encoding Initiative) standard as an accepted mechanism for providing
                  a common structure to digital editions and other digital artefacts created by
                  humanistic researchers. The TEI standard enables simple text processing, corpus
                  linguistic queries and other quantitative approaches to the texts. As such,
                  understanding how the TEI might contribute to an accepted and ultimately
                  sustainable expression of uncertainty seemed an exceptionally fertile
                  approach.</p>
               <p>Although the TEI specification includes several mechanisms to express uncertainty
                  or precision (e.g., the &lt;certainty&gt; element, the &lt;precision&gt; element,
                  or the @cert attribute), using them is not a common practice. In an attempt to
                  establish a baseline understanding of precisely how well used they were, project
                  team members used their presentation slot at the TEI 2019 conference <ptr target="#kozak_analyzing_2021"/> to ask an audience of nearly 100 TEI users how
                  many of them used this markup in their research work: only one person responded
                  positively.</p>
               <p>Clearly, the challenge is not just about having tags in the most widely accepted
                  annotation standard to manage uncertainty in the humanities research process. It
                  is about managing uncertainty within data and facilitating approaches to make it
                  more explicit. To harness the affordances already inherent in the standard,
                  however, the PROVIDEDH project focused its platform-building efforts on
                  TEI-encoded texts, creating a collaborative platform <title rend="italic">(<ref target="https://providedh.ehum.psnc.pl">https://providedh.ehum.psnc.pl</ref>)</title> that allows users to load their
                  TEI files and analyse them in many ways. The platform also allows users to enrich
                  the annotation layer of files with new entities or doubts about existing
                  (annotated) entities and fragments. Furthermore, the annotation scenarios
                  implemented in the platform allow the TEI uncertainty annotation specification to
                  be tested and ultimately expanded by the project.</p>
               <p>For the TEI guidelines, the taxonomy and the project itself served as a test case.
                  In fact, the internal project requirements to express specific uncertainty
                  characteristics, with the usage of TEI, initiated a number of discussions on how
                  to improve the TEI guidelines themselves. Some of the discussions have already led
                  to changes in the TEI guidelines (e.g., categories of uncertainty - <hi rend="italic">https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1934</hi>) and some of them
                  are ongoing (e.g., expanding possibilities of TEI tags - <hi rend="italic">https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2067</hi>).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>3.5. Assessment of the Collaborative Team</head>
               <p>As the above profiles indicate, the four PROVIDEDH partners came to the project
                  with aligned but still divergent goals for the project and different
                  understandings of uncertainty in the research process. This range of attitudes
                  towards the fundamental concerns of the PROVIDEDH project (such as what we can
                  tolerate in terms of uncertainty and what we need to participate in decision
                  making, as shown in Figure 1 below) made for a challenging, if potentially very
                  rich, interdisciplinary exploration of the limits of computer supported
                  cooperative work.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Ranked order of epistemic cultures in PROVIDEDH with regards to tolerance
                     for imprecision.</head>
                  <figDesc>Line with ends labeled <q>Greater tolerance for imprecision</q> (left)
                     and <q>Lesser tolerance for imprecision</q> (right). Arranged along the line in
                     order from greater to lesser tolerance are the labels <q>Citizen User</q>,
                        <q>Historian</q>, <q>Visualization Practitioner</q>, and
                     <q>Standards</q>.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
               </figure>
               <p>These four perspectives, each representing the expertise and biases of one of the
                  diverse partners in the PROVIDEDH project, have each enabled certain kinds of
                  insight to be developed in the project. This was a strength of the collaborative
                  team, but could also be a weakness, as gaps in the boundary languages <ptr target="#bowker_sorting_2000"/> between disciplines can often remain hidden for
                  too long. In particular, we uncovered gaps not only in understanding, but also in
                  epistemic cultures and values between the members of the team, which would need to
                  be managed if the team was to achieve its aims in a way that could be validated
                  equally by the whole multidisciplinary team.</p>
               <p>Given the risk inherent in the variations exposed in Figure 1, the team realised
                  it would be required to negotiate and place at the foundation of any system it
                  would build a formally agreed mechanism by which to encode a shared interpretation
                  of such key terminology, in particular the central issue of uncertainty. To do
                  this, the partners co-created a formal taxonomy that seemed to hold the most
                  potential, as it would both expose hidden disagreements and be able to form a
                  backbone for the annotation and standardisation processes foreseen for the
                  platform. For this, we were able to begin from significant work.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>4. Developing the Taxonomy</head>
            <p>In recent years, the graphical display of uncertainty has become an important trend
               in visualisation research (<ptr target="#kay_when_2016"/>; <ptr target="#hullman_pursuit_2018"/>; <ptr target="#kale_hypothetical_2018"/>; <ptr target="#hullman_why_2020"/>). For this, Digital Humanities represents an exciting
               field of experimentation <ptr target="#benito-santos_data-driven_2020"/>. In this
               regard, the first notable efforts to address the visual representation of uncertainty
               originated in the fields of geography and spatial data visualisation with proposals
               describing uncertainty taxonomies whose categories could be mapped to the different
               available visual channels (<ptr target="#maceachren_visualizing_1992"/>; <ptr target="#fisher_models_1999"/>). For example, MacEachren’s employed the concept of
                  <q>quality</q> to build his first uncertainty taxonomy, and accounted for the
               different manners in which uncertainty could be introduced into the data according to
               the stages of the typical data analysis pipeline. According to this, he described
               concepts such as accuracy – the exactness of data –, and precision – the degree of
               refinement with which a measurement is taken. Later in the text, MacEachren mapped
               these concepts to several visual variables (e.g., saturation), building on the famous
               previous work on semiology by the French cartographer Jacques Bertin <ptr target="#bertin1983"/>. In more recent work, MacEachren completed his previous
               work with two empirical studies focused on uncertainty visualisation in which a
               typology of uncertainty was matched against the spatial, temporal and attribute
               components of data <ptr target="#maceachren_visual_2012"/>.</p>
            <table>
               <head>Variant definitions of Uncertainty and Decision-Making among the PROVIDEDH
                  project partners.</head>
               <row role="label">
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>Open Innovation</cell>
                  <cell>Humanities</cell>
                  <cell>HCI</cell>
                  <cell>Standards</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell role="label">Definition of Uncertainty</cell>
                  <cell role="data">Uncertainty can refer to a state of not knowing, not
                     understanding, or not being aware of something; having incomplete or wrong
                     information; not remembering certain information, or not knowing a certain
                     outcome.</cell>
                  <cell role="data">Uncertainty is a necessary condition for all humanistic research
                     that can only be managed, never removed.</cell>
                  <cell role="data">Uncertainty is a state of limited knowledge (imperfect or
                     unknown information) where it is impossible to exactly describe the existing
                     state or future outcome(s).</cell>
                  <cell role="data">Uncertainty is a lack of complete true knowledge about
                     something.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell role="label">Sources of Uncertainty</cell>
                  <cell role="data">A more or less complex process involving one or more actors that
                     are working towards a common goal.</cell>
                  <cell role="data">As a part of the research process, a mechanism by which to weigh
                     possible interpretations and choose avenues to explore and attempt to
                     corroborate.</cell>
                  <cell role="data">The cognitive process resulting in the selection of a belief or
                     a course of action among several possible alternative options.</cell>
                  <cell role="data">A process in which the beings decide what to do in the near or
                     far future in some aspects of their life</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>In a different approach, Fisher <ptr target="#fisher_models_1999"/> proposed an
               uncertainty taxonomy elaborating the concepts of well- and poorly-defined objects,
               which are used to define the categories into which uncertainty can be classified.
               More concretely, Fisher’s taxonomy presents a particular point of view within the
               more verbose taxonomy of ignorance developed by <ptr target="#smithson_ignorance_1989"/>. According to Fisher’s views, uncertainty
               related to well-defined objects is caused by errors and is probabilistic in nature.
               This type of uncertainty is typically referred to as <q>aleatoric</q> or
                  <q>irreducible</q>. On the contrary, poorly defined objects relate to the concept
               of epistemic uncertainty, which can in fact be reduced. More recently, Simon and his
               colleagues adapted Fisher’s taxonomy in their work on numerical assessment of risk
               and dependability <ptr target="#simon_data_2018"/>, which in turn served us a
               starting point to propose our own uncertainty taxonomy in the context of Digital
               Humanities research. Simon et al.’s adaptation of Fisher’s taxonomy is reproduced in
               Figure 2 below:</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Simon et al.’s adaptation of Fisher’s taxonomy of uncertainty.</head>
               <figDesc>Flowchart beginning with <q>Uncertainty</q> and continuing to either
                     <q>Epistemic</q> or <q>Aleatory</q>. From Epistemic the chart continues to one
                  of the following: <q>Imprecision</q>, <q>Ignorance</q>, <q>Credibility</q>, or
                     <q>Incompleteness</q>. </figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The original uncertainty taxonomy by Simon et al. includes four more categories into
               which epistemic uncertainty might be classified: imprecision, ignorance, credibility
               and incompleteness. According to the authors, <quote rend="inline">imprecision
                  corresponds to the inability to express the true value because the absence of
                  experimental values does not allow the definition of a probability distribution or
                  because it is difficult to obtain the exact value of a measure.</quote> The next
               category, ignorance (which can be partial or total), refers to <quote rend="inline">the inability to express knowledge on disjoint hypotheses.</quote> Incompleteness
               makes reference to <quote rend="inline">the fact that not all situations are
                  covered.</quote> This is especially applicable to Digital Humanities research
               objects which may have been degraded or partially lost due to natural processes or
               the different transformations that may have been applied to the originals. Finally,
               credibility concerns <quote rend="inline">the weight that an agent can attach to its
                  judgement,</quote>
               <ptr target="#jarlbrink_cultural_2017"/> and it is also of special importance to the
               aims of our project. For example, a researcher may or may not trust the observations
               made by other agents who have previously worked on the same data, according to her
               degree of grounded knowledge on the subject and personal preference and/or bias.</p>
            <p>Although a strong starting point, none of the existing taxonomies was able to satisfy
               all of the partners in PROVIDEDH, as the balance between refinement and actionability
               was, in each case, never mutually recognisable. As Skeels and his colleagues noted in
               2008, uncertainty is referred to inconsistently both within and among domains, they
               continue that <quote rend="inline">[w]ithin the amorphous concept of uncertainty
                  there are many types of uncertainty that may warrant different visualisation
                  techniques.</quote>
               <ptr target="#skeels_revealing_2008"/> The challenge is, therefore, not to arrive at
               a single definition that obscures differences of uncertainty, but to build dialogue
               between different research domains while recognising their differences, and ensuring
               that any definition of uncertainty the project as a whole would adopt could be
               applied and implemented by all partners in their own research contexts. This
               challenges the idea that it is possible to create a single view of uncertainty.
                  <quote rend="inline">While any group’s ontology is unlikely to match that of every
                  individual within the group, the extent of mismatch tends to increase with the
                  scale of the group and the differences between the purpose of individual and group
                  ontologies</quote>
               <ptr target="#wallack_srinivasan2009" loc="p. 2"/>. The reality is that the
               development of a taxonomy, which must cater to the needs of a range of disciplines
               and stakeholders, may often lead to a result in which the specific requirements of
               not one subject area or stakeholder group are fully met, and yet which all can still
               use at some level of granularity.</p>
            <p>Building on these insights, the group organised a series of shared workshops
               exploring the issue of conceptions of uncertainty and its relationship to
               decision-making in different contexts. These workshops commenced from existing
               taxonomies, such as Fisher’s (reproduced above), and sought to revise them so as to
               reach consensus, if not agreement, about how conceptions of uncertainty might be made
               concrete and actionable in a historical research system. The three workshops each
               approached a different aspect of the overall challenge, focusing first on the
               historian’s requirements for decision-making as compared to the system's needs for
               clarity and simplicity. The second continued this discussion with a wider and more
               diverse group of potential users, and the third looked at the same challenge from the
               perspective of open innovation. Robust discussions and negotiations about the
               taxonomy occurred at every one of these discussion points. For example, in the
               interaction designed to bridge what was perceived as a back-end processing ‘optimal’
               with the perspective of the historian, nearly every term had to be renamed, glossed
               and refined, with, for example, the descriptor of ‘error’ being rejected as lacking
               sufficient precision. The domain experts also strongly advocated for the recognition
               of time-based element tracing the possible source of uncertainty from the original
               moment of a source’s creation through the many transformations over time (physical
               damage, cataloguing, transcribing, translating, digitisation, etc.) all the way
               through to the task of the researcher itself. Although later discussions continued to
               be active and important for the purpose of converging both understanding and usage
               patterns (in particular the meeting to discuss how to further extend the taxonomy’s
               use in the Open Innovation context), fewer changes were implemented over time.</p>
            <p>Departing from the taxonomies proposed by <ptr target="#fisher_models_1999"/> and
               Simon et al. <ptr target="#simon_data_2018"/> that were introduced in the previous
               section, the project partners developed an HCI-inspired uncertainty taxonomy aimed at
               producing effective visualisations from humanities textual data and related
               annotations (see Figure 4). Findings in these workshops suggested that a matrix-based
               taxonomy would be of the most use to the project and the potential users of its
               outputs. This substantiated the earlier work conducted in the context of the KPLEX
               project (discussed above) which suggested that something like Peterson’s uncertainty
               matrix for simulation uncertainties in climate change <ptr target="#petersen_simulating_2012"/> would provide the most effective approach for
               all sides. The key differentiator was the location or site of uncertainty. For
               example, Pang and his collaborators describe the different processes through which
               uncertainty can be introduced into data as: <quote rend="inline">the introduction of
                  data uncertainty from models and measurements, derived uncertainty from
                  transformation processes, and visualisation uncertainty from the visualisation
                  process itself</quote>
               <ptr target="#pang_approaches_1997"/>. Petersen similarly distinguishes a number of
               locations of uncertainty: see his model below in Figure 3. </p>
            <figure>
               <head>Petersen’s Uncertainty Matrix <ptr target="#petersen_simulating_2012"/>.</head>
               <figDesc>Table categorizing uncertainty by location, level, and nature.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The matrix shown in Figure 4 was built as a result of the PROVIDEDH development
               process.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>The PROVIDEDH Taxonomy.</head>
               <figDesc>Table separating uncertainty by type (<q>Epistemic</q> or <q>Aleatoric</q>)
                  and location (<q>Researcher Task</q>, <q>Processing or Transformation</q>, or
                     <q>Primary Source</q>).</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Although it maintains the overall simplicity of having four categories of uncertainty
               (about which much negotiation of terminology was required) the final taxonomy also
               incorporates a number of other dimensions deemed important for the notation of
               uncertainty. First, on the y-axis, it incorporates a sensitivity to time and the
               possible actors that might have introduced uncertainty into a system. This is
               particularly important for historical research, as an uncertainty introduced by a
               more recent process (such as dirty OCR of historical texts) may be much easier to
               manage in a decision-making process than an original gap in what was seen or
               reported. Similarly, the matrix follows Fisher in applying the concepts of epistemic
               and aleatory uncertainty, with the former more likely to be a result of human lack of
               understanding, and the latter more likely to be one of imperfect sources and tools.
               Truly epistemic uncertainty is the hardest to address, but, as we can see in the
               taxonomy, there is only one of twelve possible states of uncertainty that is indeed
               fully epistemic, along with five others that are partially so. Knowing how uncertain
               a given uncertainty is, makes it much easier to build systems and annotation
               standards to accommodate it, but it also allows historians and citizen users to
               maintain their sense of uncertainty itself which is often a complex and potentially
               hybrid state. Through this instrument, we can see differences between those places
               that are likely to have wide agreement as to the nature of the uncertainty and what
               it would take to optimally resolve it (a gap in a primary source), and those areas
               where the questions are much more individualised, closer to the work of a single
               historian.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>5. Implementing the Taxonomy</head>
            <p>The final taxonomy was deployed as a fundamental element in the PROVIDEDH
               demonstrator platform for the investigation of uncertainty in historical texts. Its
               primary functionality was to structure the manner in which users could indicate the
               nature and level of uncertain passages in the text and to visualise patterns in these
               annotations. This enabled a like-with-like comparison of annotations across users and
               documents. The use of the taxonomy in the system (for example in the visual
               annotator, see Figure 5, is based upon a conceptualisation of uncertainty that has
               two well-defined sources: 1) tool-induced and 2) human-induced, which can be
               respectively mapped to the two main categories devised by <ptr target="#fisher_models_1999"/> that were introduced in previous sections of this
               paper.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Screenshot of the visual annotator that was implemented in the project’s
                  platform. Here, users can annotate texts using at least four categories of
                  epistemic uncertainty (ignorance, non-credibility, imprecision and
                  incompleteness).</head>
               <figDesc>User interface showing annotated text excerpt with options for
                     <q>Entities</q> and <q>Annotations</q>.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The first uncertainty category, tool (or machine)-induced (Figure 5, bottom), can be
               mapped to aleatoric uncertainty (well-defined objects in Fisher’s taxonomy) and
               results from the application of computational algorithms (or other historic tools) to
               the data. These often give their results with a variable degree of bounded
               uncertainty (e.g., topic models <ptr target="#blei_probabilistic_2012"/> or word
               embeddings <ptr target="#mikolov_distributed_2013"/>). For this reason, this type of
               uncertainty is better represented as a continuous probability distribution.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Proposed n+1 uncertainty taxonomy model. Top: human-Induced category with four
                  predefined categories that map to the epistemic categories previously introduced
                  by Simon and Fisher. To the right, user-defined categories can be added during the
                  project’s lifetime. Users can add more categories if required. Bottom:
                  machine-induced uncertainty showing different runs of the same or different
                  algorithms.</head>
               <figDesc>Six bar charts showing human uncertainty and three line charts showing
                  machine-induced uncertainty</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>In addition, this representation allows a better understanding of speculative runs of
               a given algorithm and enhances the what-if analysis process. For example, a
               researcher could parametrise an algorithm with a fixed set of inputs and launch it a
               number of times, obtaining a range of mean values and deviations encoded in a
               document which, if correctly displayed, would allow her to get an idea of how the
               algorithm behaves. Analogously, the algorithm could be parametrised with a variable
               set of inputs created by the user running the computation or, as we will see next, by
               other past researchers. This operation mode would provide an answer to the question
                  <q>What happens if I run the algorithm a million times using my assumptions?</q>
               or <q>What happens if I run the algorithm a million times using another person’s
                  assumptions?</q>. As in the case of running the algorithm with the same parameters
               many times, the results of running the algorithm with different parameters many times
               could also be summarised in a continuous document allowing the said kind of what-if
               analysis. This would answer the question of <q>What happens if I use these other
                  person’s assumptions?</q> or <q>What happens if I decide not to trust another
                  actor’s assumptions?</q>. We argue that the insights obtained from the described
               experiments are highly valuable for the user, specifically in the case of algorithms
               that are probabilistic in nature, such as topic models, and whose results – and
               interpretations – can vary greatly between different runs <ptr target="#alexander_task-driven_2016"/>.</p>
            <p>The other category, human-induced uncertainty (bottom), arises from 1) direct
               interpretations of the raw data (which in turn may be based on others’ previous
               interpretations and grounded expert knowledge of the user) and 2) interpretations of
               computational analyses performed on the data or 3) a combination of the two. This
               category is reported by users of our system in a 5-point Likert scale and thus it is
               best modelled as a discrete probability function. Moreover, we devised the dependency
               relationships between the categories in our taxonomy to be bidirectional and
               self-recurring, since, for example, the input parameters and data fed to the
               algorithms – and therefore their results – are derived from a user’s previous
               interpretations of textual data and related machine- or human-generated annotations.
               In turn, these interpretations must necessarily be built upon previous insight
               obtained by the same or other users who apply computational techniques to the data,
               effectively forming a temporal belief network <ptr target="#druzdzel_causality_1993"/> that is fixated on the different versions of a dataset. In a first stage, we
               modelled human-induced uncertainty according to the uncertainty taxonomy of Figure 4
               in what was called the 4+1 uncertainty model. Later, and following a series of
               evaluation sessions and workshops, we evolved the model to support a variable number
               of human-induced categories. This change was introduced after a series of user-driven
               experiments and evaluations in which we asked the participants to annotate different
               types of historical texts (poetry and historical recipes). As we describe in our
               previous contribution, the uncertainty taxonomy was received positively by the
               Digital Humanities experts and lay users we engaged with during the design sessions
               that took part throughout the project <ptr target="#benito-santos_evaluating_2021"/>.
               From these experiences, we could check first-hand the latent need, as perceived by
               the participants, for a more nuanced and flexible way of communicating uncertainty in
               Digital Humanities projects, as well as the potential benefits that this could bring
               for collaborative work on Digital Humanities datasets. Specifically, we discovered
               that, sometimes, users could not pick one of the predefined categories when making
               annotations on the texts. Furthermore, we also detected that there almost never was a
               100% consensus on the uncertainty type different users chose to annotate the same
               portion of text: e.g., whereas for some a linguistic variant of a word implied
               imprecision (e.g., they were more or less sure about a word’s meaning, but the word
               varied from a standard form), for others it meant ignorance (e.g., they did not know
               what the word meant). These differences, we argue, are often subtle and very much
               depend on the mental state, ground knowledge on the subject and other traits of the
               particular user making the annotation. Beyond that, some users showed preference for
               labelling uncertainty in a particular annotation as a combination of different types.
               For example, a user could be more or less sure that a word found in the text
               represents a dialectal variation but at the same time not be sure of the word’s
               meaning in a certain context. In this case, the user should be able to reflect her
               views using a combination of categories (e.g., imprecision + ignorance + 0/5
               non-credibility + 0/5 gaps). This way of communicating uncertainty, we argue, allows
               a higher level of expressiveness and is able to capture the nuances of the user’s
               mental state that needs to be captured and presented to other users working in the
               same dataset. To allow for even better communication of uncertainty between actors,
               we allow users to dynamically create new categories as required, which are
               established on a per project-basis in what is called the n+1 uncertainty model. This
               departs from the observed effect in our experiments that a group of users working on
               the same data will naturally establish their own uncertainty taxonomy that covers the
               needs and particularities of the specific tasks to be performed on the data. As such,
               they will use it as a communication tool to collaborate in a distributed manner in
               time and space by appending their annotations to the dataset according to these
               ad-hoc categories, effectively fulfilling one of the project’s main objectives.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>6. Conclusion</head>
            <p>The function of the system ultimately built by the PROVIDEDH team, as a visualisation
               supported tool for historical research under conditions of uncertainty, was
               predicated upon the deployment of the taxonomy that underpins it. Interestingly,
               however, it was also the process of negotiating the taxonomy that allowed the team to
               function, overcoming the challenges inherent in interdisciplinary work and achieving
               the goals of their collaborative project. Lee described the effect of <quote rend="inline">boundary-negotiating artifacts</quote> as twofold, having (1) an
               effect on the recipient, for whom information is more easily grasped, and 2) an
               effect on the artifact creator, who must strive to construct an artifact that is
               easily grasped <ptr target="#lee_boundary_2007"/>. The results of the PROVIDEDH
               project can certainly attest to this effect and to the largely invisible, but
               essential, taxonomy and its development delivered.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>This research was funded by the CHIST-ERA programme under the following national
               grant agreements PCIN-2017-064 (MINECO Spain), 2017/25/Z/ST6/03045 (National Science
               Centre, Poland), national grant agreement FWF (Project number I 3441-N33, Austrian
               Science Fund, Austria).</p>
            <p>Alejandro Benito-Santos acknowledges support from the postdoctoral grant ’Margarita
               Salas’, awarded by the Spanish Ministry of Universities.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conflict of Interest</head>
            <p>The authors declared that they have no conflict of interest.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="maceachren_visualizing_1992" label="MacEachren 1992"> MacEachren, A. M.
               (1992) <title rend="quotes">Visualizing Uncertain Information</title>, <title rend="italic">Cartographic Perspectives</title>, 0(13), pp. 10-19. {Available at:
                  <ref target="http://www.cartographicperspectives.org/index.php/journal/article/view/cp13-maceachren">http://www.cartographicperspectives.org/index.php/journal/article/view/cp13-maceachren</ref>
               or <ref target="https://doi.org/10.14714/CP13.1000">10.14714/CP13.1000</ref> (Accessed: 14 February
               2018)}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pang_approaches_1997" label="Pang, Wittenbrink, and Lodha 1997"> Pang, A.
               T., Wittenbrink, C. M., and Lodha, S. K. (1997) <title rend="quotes">Approaches to
                  uncertainty visualization</title>, <title rend="italic">The Visual
                  Computer</title>, 13(8), pp. 370-390. {Available at: <ref target="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s003710050111">https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s003710050111</ref> (Accessed: 14
               February 2018).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="smithson_ignorance_1989" label="Smithson 1989"> Smithson, Michael. (1989)
                  <title rend="italic">Ignorance and uncertainty: emerging paradigms</title>. New
               York: Springer-Verlag. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fisher_models_1999" label="Fisher 1999"> Fisher, P. (1999) <title rend="quotes">Models of uncertainty in spatial data</title>, <title rend="italic">Geographical information systems</title>, vol. 1, pp. 191–205.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kay_when_2016" label="Kay et al. 2016"> Kay, M., Kola, T., Hullman, J. R.,
               and Monson, S. A. (2016) <title rend="quotes">When (Ish) is My Bus?: User-centered
                  Visualizations of Uncertainty in Everyday, Mobile Predictive Systems</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2016 CHI Conference on Human Factors in
                  Computing Systems</title>, pp. 5092–5103, New York, NY, USA, 2016. New York: ACM.
               {Available at: <ref target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/2858036.2858558">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/2858036.2858558</ref> (Accessed 18 September
               2018).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kale_hypothetical_2018" label="Kale et al. 2018"> Kale, A., Nguyen, F.,
               Kay, M., and Hullman, J. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Hypothetical Outcome Plots Help
                  Untrained Observers Judge Trends in Ambiguous Data</title>, <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>, p. 1. {DOI:
               10.1109/TVCG.2018.2864909}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="skeels_revealing_2008" label="Skeels et al. 2008"> Skeels, M., Lee, B.,
               Smith, G., and Robertson, G. (2008) <title rend="quotes">Revealing Uncertainty for
                  Information Visualization</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Working
                  Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces</title>, pp. 376–379, New York, NY, USA.
               New York: ACM. {Available at: <ref target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1385569.1385637">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1385569.1385637</ref> (Accessed 27 October
               2018).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hullman_pursuit_2018" label="Hullman et al. 2018"> Hullman, J., Qiao, X.,
               Correll, M., Kale, A., and Kay, M. (2018) <title rend="quotes">In Pursuit of Error: A
                  Survey of Uncertainty Visualization Evaluation</title>, <title rend="italic">IEEE
                  Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>, p. 1. {DOI:
               10.1109/TVCG.2018.2864889}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lamqaddam_when_2018" label="Lamqaddam et al. 2018 "> Lamqaddam, H.,
               Brosens, K., Truyen, F., Beerens, J., Prekel, I., and Verbert, K. (2018) <title rend="quotes">When the Tech Kids are Running Too Fast: Data Visualisation Through
                  the Lens of Art History Research</title>, <title rend="italic">Proc. 3rd Workshop
                  on Visualization for the Digital Humanities (VIS4DH)</title>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="coles_think_2017" label="Coles 2017"> Coles, K. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Think Like a Machine (or not)</title>, <title rend="italic">Proc.
                  2nd Workshop on Visualization for the Digital Humanities (VIS4DH)</title>, pp.
               1-5.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="blei_probabilistic_2012" label="Blei 2012"> Blei, D. M. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Probabilistic Topic Models</title>, <title rend="italic">Commun.
                  ACM</title>, 55(4), pp. 77–84. {Available at: <ref target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/2133806.2133826">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/2133806.2133826</ref> (Accessed 31 October 2018).} </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mikolov_distributed_2013" label="Mikolov et al. 2013"> Mikolov, T.,
               Sutskever, I., Chen, K., Scorrado, G., and Dean, J. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Distributed Representations of Words and Phrases and their
                  Compositionality</title> in Burges, C.J.C., bottou, L., Welling, M., Ghahramani,
               Z., and Weinberger, K. Q., (eds.) <title rend="italic">Advances in Neural Information
                  Processing Systems 26</title>. Red Hook: Curran Associates, Inc. pp. 3111–3119.
               {Avilable at: <ref target="http://papers.nips.cc/paper/5021-distributed-representations-of-words-and-phrases-and-their-compositionality.pdf">http://papers.nips.cc/paper/5021-distributed-representations-of-words-and-phrases-and-their-compositionality.pdf</ref>} </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="theron_sanchez_towards_2019" label="Therón Sánchez et al. 2019">Therón
               Sánchez, R., Benito-Santos, A., Santamaría Vicente, R., and Losada Gómez, A.
                  (2019)<title rend="quotes">Towards an Uncertainty-Aware Visualization in the
                  Digital Humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Informatics</title>, 6(3), p. 31.
               {Avilable at: <ref target="https://www.mdpi.com/2227-9709/6/3/31">https://www.mdpi.com/2227-9709/6/3/31</ref> (Accessed 02 September 2019).} </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="alexander_task-driven_2016" label="Alexander and Gleicher 2016">
               Alexander, E., amd Gleicher, M. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Task-Driven Comparison of
                  Topic Models</title>, <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and
                  Computer Graphics</title>, 22(1), pp. 320-329. {DOI:
               10.1109/TVCG.2015.2467618}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gibbs_building_2012" label="Gibbs and Owens 2012"> Gibbs, F., and Owens,
               T. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Building Better Digital Humanities Tools: Toward
                  broader audiences and user-centered designs</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital
                  Humanities Quarterly</title>, 006(2) {Available at: <ref target="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/2/000136/000136.html">https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/2/000136/000136.html</ref>}.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker_graphical_2015" label="Drucker 2015"> Drucker, J. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Graphical Approaches to the Digital Humanities</title> in <title rend="italic">A New Companion to Digital Humanities</title>. Hoboken:
               Wiley-Blackwell, pp. 238-250. {Available at: <ref target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/9781118680605.ch17">https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/9781118680605.ch17</ref>
               (Accessed 29 October 2018)} </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="maceachren_visual_2012" label="MacEachren 2012"> MacEachren, A. M., Roth,
               R. E., O'Brien, J., Li, B., Swingley, D., and Gahegan, M. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Visual Semiotics Uncertainty Visualization: An Empirical Study</title>, <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>,
               18(12), pp. 2496-2505. {DOI: 10.1109/TVCG.2012.279}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hullman_why_2020" label="Hullman 2020"> Hullman, J. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Why Authors Don't Visualize Uncertainty</title>, <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>,
               26(1), pp. 130-139. {DOI: 10.1109/TVCG.2019.2934287} </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lamqaddam_introducing_2021" label="Lamqaddam et al. 2021"> Lamqaddam, H.,
               Vandemoere, A., VandenAbeele, V. Brosens, K., and Verbert, K.<title rend="quotes">Introducing Layers of Meaning (LoM): A Framework to Reduce Semantic Distance of
                  Visualization In Humanistic Research</title>, <title rend="italic">IEEE
                  Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>, 27(2), pp. 1084-1094.
               {DOI: 10.1109/TVCG.2020.3030426}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="benito-santos_data-driven_2020" label="Benito-Santos and Therón Sánchez 2020"> Benito-Santos, A., and Therón Sánchez,
               R. (2020) <title rend="quotes">A Data-Driven Introduction to Authors, Readings, and
                  Techniques in Visualization for the Digital Humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>, 40(3), pp. 45-57.
               {DOI: 10.1109/MCG.2020.2973945}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="benito-santos_evaluating_2021" label="Benito-Santos et al. 2021">
               Benito-Santos, A., Doran, M., Rocha, A., Wandl-Vogt, E., Edmond, J., and Therón, R.
               (2021) <title rend="quotes">Evaluating a Taxonomy of Textual Uncertainty for
                  Collaborative Visualisation in the Digital Humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Information</title>, 12(11), p. 436. {Avaialble at: <ref target="https://www.mdpi.com/2078-2489/12/11/436">https://www.mdpi.com/2078-2489/12/11/436</ref> or DOI: 10.3390/info12110436
               (Accessed 21 October 2021).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="simon_data_2018" label="Simon, Weber, and Sallak 2018"> Simon, C., Weber,
               P., and Sallak, M. (2018) <title rend="italic">Data Uncertainty and Important
                  Measures</title>. Hoboken: John Wiley and Sons. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vienni_baptista_final_2020" label="Vienni Baptista et al. 2020"> Vienni
               Baptista, B., Fletcher, I., Maryl, M., Wciślik, P., Buchner, A., Lyall, C., Spaapen,
               J., and Pohl, C.<title rend="italic">Final Report on Understandings of
                  Interdisciplinary and Transdisciplinary Research and Factors of Success and
                  Failure</title>. {Available at: <ref target="https://zenodo.org/record/3824839">https://zenodo.org/record/3824839</ref> (Accessed 03 February 2022).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="druzdzel_causality_1993" label="Druzdzel and Simon 1993"> Druzdzel, M. J.,
               and Simon, H.A. (1993) <title rend="quotes">Causality in Bayesian Belief
                  Networks</title> in Heckerman, D., and Mamdani, A. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence</title>. Burlington: Morgan Kaufmann, pp.
               3-11. {Available at: <ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/B9781483214511500056">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/B9781483214511500056</ref>
               (Accessed 04 February 2022).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="petersen_simulating_2012" label="Petersen 2012"> Petersen, A.C. (2012)
                  <title rend="italic">Simulating Nature: A Philosophical Study of
                  Computer-Simulation Uncertainties and Their Role in Climate Science and Policy
                  Advice, Second Edition</title>. Boca Raton: CRC Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="padilla_uncertainty_2021" label="Padilla, Kay, and Hullman 2021"> Padilla,
               L., Kay, M., Hullman, J. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Uncertainty
                  Visualization</title> in <title rend="italic">Wiley StatsRef: Statistics Reference
                  Online</title>. Hoboken: John Wiley and Sons, Ltd, pp. 1-18. {Avilable at: <ref target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/9781118445112.stat08296">https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/9781118445112.stat08296</ref>
               (Accessed 04 February 2022)}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="edmond_power_2022" label="Edmond et al. 2022"> Edmond, J., Horsley, N.,
               Lehmann, J., and Priddy, M. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Power through
                  datafication</title> in <title rend="italic">The Trouble With Big Data : How
                  Datafication Displaces Cultural Practices</title>. {1st edn.} London: Bloomsbury
               Academic, pp. 135-157. {Available at: <ref target="http://www.bloomsburycollections.com/book/the-trouble-with-big-data-how-datafication-displaces-cultural-practices/ch7-power-through-datafication/">http://www.bloomsburycollections.com/book/the-trouble-with-big-data-how-datafication-displaces-cultural-practices/ch7-power-through-datafication/</ref>
               (Accessed 13 December 2021).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="edmond_deliverable_2018" label="Edmond et al. 2018"> Edmond, J., Doran,
               M., Horsley, N., Huber, E., Kalnins, R., Lehman, J., Nugent-Folan, G., Priddy, M.,
               and Stodulka, T. (2018) <title rend="italic">Deliverable Title: D1.1 Final report on
                  the exploitation, translation and reuse potential for project results</title>.
               {Available at: <ref target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01842365">https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01842365</ref> (Accessed 04 February
               2022).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bowker_sorting_2000" label="Bowker and Star 2000"> Bowker, G. C., and
               Star, S. L. (2000) <title rend="italic">Sorting Things Out: Classification and Its
                  Consequences</title>. Cambridge: MIT Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pennington_cross-disciplinary_2008" label="Pennington 2008"> Pennington,
               D. D. (2008) <title rend="quotes">Cross-Disciplinary Collaboration and
                  Learning</title>, <title rend="italic">Ecology and Society</title>, 13(2).
               {Available at: <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/26267958">https://www.jstor.org/stable/26267958</ref> (Accessed 08 February 2022).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jeffrey_smoothing_2003" label="Jeffrey 2003"> Jeffrey, P. (2003) <title rend="quotes">Smoothing the Waters: Observations on the Process of
                  Cross-Disciplinary Research Collaboration</title>, <title rend="italic">Social
                  Studies of Science</title>, 33(4), pp. 539-562. {Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0306312703334003">https://doi.org/10.1177/0306312703334003</ref> (Accessed 08 February
               2022).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="boix_mansilla_shared_2016" label="Boix Mansilla, Lamont, and Sato 2016">
               Boix Mansilla, V., Lamont, M., and Sato, K. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Shared
                  Cognitive–Emotional–Interactional Platforms: Markers and Conditions for Successful
                  Interdisciplinary Collaborations</title>, <title rend="italic">Science,
                  Technology, and Human Values</title>, 41(4), pp. 571-612. {Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243915614103">https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243915614103</ref> (Accessed 08 February
               2022).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lowe_ecology_2009" label="Lowe, Whitman, and Phillipson 2009"> Lowe, P.,
               Whitman, G., and Phillipson, J. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Ecology and the social
                  sciences</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Applied Ecology</title>, 46(2)
               pp. 297-305. {Available at: <ref target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1365-2664.2009.01621.x">https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1365-2664.2009.01621.x</ref>
               (Accessed 08 February 2022).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kozak_analyzing_2021" label="Kozak et al. 2021"> Kozak, M., Rodríguez, A.,
               Benito-Santos, A., Therón, R., Doran, M., Dorn, A., Edmond, J., Mazurek, C., and
               Wandl-Vogt, E. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Analyzing and Visualizing Uncertain
                  Knowledge: The Use of TEI Annotations in the PROVIDEDH Open Science
                  Platform</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding
                  Initiative</title>, Issue 14. {Available at: <ref target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/4239">https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/4239</ref> (Accessed 06 April
               2023).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bertin1983" label="Bertin 1983"> Bertin, J. (1983) <title rend="italic">The semiology of graphics: Diagrams, networks, maps</title>. Translated by W. J.
               Berg. Madison: University of Wisconsin Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="strauss_articulation_1988" label="Strauss 1988"> Strauss, A. (1988) <title rend="quotes">The Articulation of Project Work: An Organizational Process</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">The Sociological Quarterly</title>, 29(2), pp. 163-178
               {Available at: <ref target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1533-8525.1988.tb01249.x">https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1533-8525.1988.tb01249.x</ref>
               (Accessed 03 May 2023).} </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lee_boundary_2007" label="Lee 2007"> Lee, C. P. (2007) <title rend="quotes">Boundary Negotiating Artifacts: Unbinding the Routine of Boundary
                  Objects and Embracing Chaos in Collaborative Work</title>, <title rend="italic">Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW)</title>, 16(3), pp. 307-339.
               {Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10606-007-9044-5">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10606-007-9044-5</ref> (Accessed 12 May 2023).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jarlbrink_cultural_2017" label="Jarlbrink and Snickars 2017"> Jarlbrink,
               J., and Snickars, P. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Cultural heritage as digital noise:
                  nineteenth century newspapers in the digital archive</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title>, 73(6), pp. 1228-1243. {Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1108/JD-09-2016-0106">https://doi.org/10.1108/JD-09-2016-0106</ref> (Accessed 12 May 2023)).}</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wallack_srinivasan2009" label="Wallack and Srinivasan 2009">Wallack, J.
               S., and Srinivasan, R. (2009) <title rend="quotes">Local-Global: Reconciling
                  Mismatched Ontologies in Development Information Systems</title>, <title rend="italic">2009 42nd Hawaii International Conference on System
               Sciences</title>, Waikoloa, HI, USA: IEEE, pp. 1-10. DOI:
               10.1109/HICSS.2009.295.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>