<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
	xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
	xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
	xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
				<title type="article" xml:lang="en">Visualization of Categorization: How to See the
					Wood and the Trees</title>
				<!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Ophir <dhq:family>Münz-Manor</dhq:family> </dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6333-345X</idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>The Open University of Israel</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>ophirmm@openu.ac.il</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p/>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Itay <dhq:family>Marienberg-Milikowsky</dhq:family> </dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1150-7259</idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>Ben-Gurion University of the Negev</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>itay.marienberg@gmail.com</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p/>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
				<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
				<!--This information will be completed at publication-->
				<idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
				<idno type="volume"
					><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
				<idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
				<date/>
				<dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
				<availability status="CC-BY-ND">
					<!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
					<cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>This is the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
						target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
						>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref> </bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
					<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
						target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
						>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref> </bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en" extent="original"/>
				<!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
					<!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
					<!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
					<list type="simple">
						<item>computational literary studies</item>
						<item>visualization</item>
						<item>annotation</item>
						<item>tagset</item>
						<item>medieval Hebrew poetry</item>
						<item>hermeneutics</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
			<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
				target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000703/000703.xml"
				>GitHub </ref> </change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en" type="original">
		<front>
			<dhq:abstract>
				<!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
				<p>In the article, we present, theorize and contextualize an investigation of
					figurative language in a corpus of Hebrew liturgical poetry from late antiquity,
					from both a manual and a computational point of view. The study touches upon
					questions of distribution and patterns of usage of figures of speech as well as
					their literary-historical meanings. Focusing on figures of speech such as
					metaphors and similes, the corpus was first annotated manually with markers on
					papers, and a few years later it was annotated manually again, this time in a
					computer-assisted way, following a strictly categorized approach, using CATMA
					(an online literary annotation tool). The data was then transferred into
					ViS-À-ViS (an online visualization tool, developed by Münz-Manor and his team)
					that enables scholars to <q>see the wood</q> via various visualizations that
					single out, inter alia, repetitive patterns either at the level of the text or
					the annotations. The tool also enables one to visualize aggregated results
					concerning more than one text, allowing one to <q>zoom out</q> and see the
					<q>forest aspect</q> of the entire corpus or parts thereof. Interestingly, after
					visualizing the material in this way, it often turns out that the categories
					themselves need to be re-assessed. In other words, the categorization and
					visualization in themselves create a sort of hermeneutical circle in which both
					parts influence one another reciprocally.</p>
				<p>Through the case study, we seek to demonstrate that, by using correct methods and
					tools (not only ViS-À-ViS but others also), one can ultimately use visualization
					of categorization as the basis for what might be called <q>established
					speculation</q>, or <q>not-trivial generalization</q>, which means, an
					interpretative act that tries to be based on clear findings, while at the same
					time enjoying the advantages of <q>over interpretation</q>. This approach, we
					argue, enables one to see the trees without losing sight of the wood, and vice
					versa; or <quote rend="inline" source="#weingart2022">to give definition</quote>
					– at least tentatively – <cit><quote rend="inline">to the microcosms and
					macrocosms which describe the world around us</quote><ptr target="#weingart2022"
					/></cit>, be they factual or fictional.</p>
			</dhq:abstract>
			<dhq:teaser>
				<!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
				<p/>
			</dhq:teaser>
		</front>
		<body>
			<epigraph>
				<cit><quote rend="block">Four talked about the pine tree. One defined it by genus,
					species, and variety. One assessed its disadvantages for the lumber industry.
					One quoted poems about pine trees in many languages. One took root, stretched
					out branches, and rustled.<note>Dan Pagis, Conversation. Translated from Hebrew
					by Stephen Mitchell; <ref
					target="https://matthewsalomon.wordpress.com/2008/04/03/dan-pagis-conversation/"
					>https://matthewsalomon.wordpress.com/2008/04/03/dan-pagis-conversation/</ref></note></quote><bibl>Dan
					Pagis</bibl></cit>
			</epigraph>
			<div>
				<head>Introduction: Figurative Language in Late Antiquity Hebrew Liturgical Poetry –
					between the Manual and the Computerized</head>
				<p>The experiment described and discussed in this article began with Münz-Manor’s
					doctoral dissertation entitled <title rend="quotes">Studies in the Figurative
					Language of Pre-Classical Piyyut</title>, submitted to the senate of the Hebrew
					University of Jerusalem in 2006 <ptr target="#munzmanor2006a"/>. The
					dissertation explored the use of metaphor, simile, epithets, and other
					figurative devices in the earliest stratum of Hebrew liturgical poetry, composed
					in the Galilee in the fifth century of the Common Era, also known as piyyut, a
					Greek loan word meaning poetry. The corpus includes all the known poems from
					that time period and was recovered from medieval manuscripts of the Cairo
					Genizah. It includes 211 poems by various poets, most of them anonymous, with a
					word count of 47,556. Earlier studies suggested that, unlike in many other
					corpora of poetry, figurative language in early piyyut is rather marginal, and
					the main goal of the dissertation was to corroborate (or refute) this rather
					intuitive assertion and to some extent to quantify it. At the same time, the
					dissertation had a qualitative and literary goal, namely to carefully analyze
					the poems by reading them closely, and to draw poetic conclusions from the
					usage, or lack thereof, of figurative language by the poets <ptr
					target="#munzmanor2011"/>.</p>
				<p>At the beginning of the century, long before the computational approach began to
					bring its influence to bear on the Israeli academy, the method used was rather
					simple.<note>For some aspects of the history of the digital humanities in Israel
					and their lack of what can be called a computational hermeneutics, especially in
					the context of Hebrew literature studies, see Marienberg-Milikowsky (2019;
					2022).</note> The poems in the corpus were read, word by word, using colored
					highlighters to mark the different figurative devices, such as metaphors,
					metonymies, and similes. This was painstaking, to be sure, but by the end of a
					process that took several months, the entire corpus was annotated. In hindsight,
					although there existed a notion of a clear-cut categorization of figurative
					language in the corpus, no well-defined <q>tagset</q> was created. To put it
					another way, even though this phase was managed in a relatively systematic way,
					it was not based on ontological thinking in the full sense of the term. The
					major figurative devices were annotated in an entirely flat hierarchy of
					metaphor, metonymy, synecdoche and simile. The use of these concepts was of
					course based on a strong theoretical foundation, but the definitions bore some
					flexibility. Indeed, at the time, the notion of a tagset as a defined and more
					or less stable logical representation of the categories was not an idea
					Münz-Manor had thought of.</p>
				<p>As previously noted, in the second stage, an analysis was carried out in which
					different examples were drawn from the annotated corpus. Here, a more detailed
					analysis of literary phenomena was carried out, such as metaphors with biblical
					connotations <ptr target="#munzmanor2006b"/>, similes that were created due to
					structural features of the poems <ptr target="#munzmanor2009"/>, figurative
					epithets <ptr target="#munzmanor2016"/> and the like. In other words, only after
					annotating the entire corpus on a very rudimentary level was the <q>tagset</q>
					enhanced, in a process which was neither efficient, systematic nor clever. At
					any rate, the main phenomena that were discovered were grouped into chapters and
					analyzed in depth. Despite this there remained a gap between the scope of the
					textual infrastructure prepared for the research and the doctoral chapters,
					which were theoretical and interpretive in nature, and did not necessarily
					exhaust the quantitative potential that was encapsulated in the preparatory
					work.</p>
				<p>The conclusion of the dissertation was that the use of figurative language was
					indeed relatively marginal in the corpus, but that at the same time the usage
					that did occur was interesting and innovative. Although most of the discussion
					and conclusion was qualitative, a short passage did touch upon the quantitative
					aspects, even if in a scant way: <cit><quote rend="block">Out of approximately
					5000 poetic lines, only 1000 contained figurative devices of any description,
					namely 20 percent. Moreover, the number of lines that contained developed
					figurative usage, which in most cases means a usage that runs across the entire
					line, was scarce, only 100…. the piyyutim [= piyyut in the plural] employ almost
					exclusively metaphors; the number of similes is surprisingly small, as well as
					the number of metonymies and synecdoches</quote><ptr target="#munzmanor2006a"
					loc="pp. 238–239"/>.</cit>These comments were not further developed or expanded
					upon, and remain almost the only reference to the quantitative aspects that
					emerged from the painstaking preparatory work. In retrospect, this fact should
					probably be understood as a reflection of the well-known hesitancy of literature
					studies with regard to numbers <ptr target="#english2010" loc="p. xiii"/> <ptr
					target="#goldstone_etal2014" loc="359–362"/>. Many of the dissertation’s
					chapters were published as journal articles and it seemed that this scholarly
					chapter in the author’s career had ended.</p>
				<p>That being said, fifteen years later, as our shared interest in computational
					literary studies grew, we came across CATMA (Computer Assisted Text Markup and
					Analysis), a web annotation tool developed at the University of Hamburg and now
					at the Technical University of Darmstadt <ptr target="#gius_etal2022"/>, and a
					new scholarly project emerged. CATMA enables the annotation of every element in
					the text (and not the text as a whole – an issue that we will discuss later)
					according to tagsets defined by the user. Once the tagging has been
					accomplished, the user can execute queries concerning both the text and the
					tagged text. Working with this tool, the first thing that caught Münz-Manor’s
					eye was that the interface seemed almost identical to his dissertation’s
					print-outs, namely the text highlighted with colors to depict the different
					annotations. But, unlike the initial work which was entirely manual, the main
					advantage of CATMA, or of any other computer-based annotation tool, is the
					ability to run basic or complex queries and to retrieve data. Thus, for example,
					in a hypothetical digital project equivalent to the doctoral thesis described
					earlier, the researcher could retrieve in seconds, and for the first time, a
					distribution of the figurative devices in the entire corpus, whether in a set of
					poems or a specific one; a list of frequent metaphoric words; or a percentage of
					figurative versus literal words. Such data is foundational for a combined
					qualitative-quantitative research. Moreover, the un-dogmatic conceptual
					principle of CATMA <ptr target="#horstmann2020"/> enables the annotators to
					enhance, refine or redefine the tagset on the go.<note>For a broader historical
					and theoretical background of the undogmatic principle of CATMA, see <ref
					target="#fluh_etal2021">Flüh et al. 2021</ref>.</note> As previously noted, the
					manual tagging during the initial phase of writing the dissertation forced
					Münz-Manor to use a one-dimensional and rigid <q>tagset</q> that, on the one
					hand, facilitated the tedious endeavor but, on the other, restricted the
					potential for complex analysis.</p>
				<p>We began to wonder what would happen if CATMA were used to explore figurative
					language in <hi rend="italic">piyyut</hi>, transforming the hypothetical idea
					described above into a reality. This experiment would have twofold importance;
					firstly, it would provide another perspective on the literary question at hand,
					and secondly it would serve as an unusual methodological trial of digital versus
					analogue approaches. We decided to run an experiment: we would <q>upload</q> the
					manual annotations from the doctoral print-outs to the system and see where it
					would take us <ptr target="#munzmanor2022"/>. Here we took another important
					decision, which was to stick strictly to the original annotations in order for
					the experiment to be as sound as possible. As literary scholars, who cannot
					ignore the subjective nature of interpretation, it was an intuitive act: the
					decision whether a word is figurative or not is a hermeneutical one, and
					different scholars would tend to annotate the word differently. Moreover, even
					the same annotator might interpret the word differently at a later date or in a
					different context. It was because of this that we decided not to touch the
					original annotations when migrating from the analogue dissertation to the
					digital experiment; but we shall return to this point towards the end of this
					article.</p>
				<p>The results of the experiment will be presented in two sections. In what follows
					we discuss some general quantitative results, then we continue with a more
					theoretical discussion of the annotating double experience and its function in
					the research development. Finally, we present our visualization tool and follow
					with another case study that builds upon the capabilities of the tool.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Case Study (A): Corroboration and Refutation </head>
				<p>Once the corpus of poetry and the annotations were uploaded to CATMA it was very
					easy to run basic queries and to (re)assess some of the key findings of the
					dissertation <ptr target="#munzmanor2022"/>, 370-3). The most pressing question
					was whether figurative language in the corpus is marginal or not. Interestingly,
					it turns out that the question is not that simple. Let us consider some numbers:
					the corpus includes 47,556 words, out of which 5113 are figurative. In other
					words, the share of figurative words in the corpus is 11%, a small fraction to
					be sure. In that sense, we can say that the quantitative results corroborate the
					qualitative ones from the dissertation. But <q>small</q> in comparison to what?
					In the dissertation this question could not have been answered and probably did
					not seem worthwhile at the time. In order to correlate the results, we examined
					them against two new corpora that have now been annotated for figurative
					language: the Book of Psalms from the Bible and the poetry of Pinchas the
					Priest, a ninth-century poet from Tiberias. These corpora were selected for a
					particular reason; the Book of Psalms is the foundational corpus of Hebrew
					poetry and <hi rend="italic">piyyut</hi> has a direct connection to it even if
					the late antique poets sought to distance themselves from the canonical text.
					The <hi rend="italic">oeuvre</hi> of Pinchas, on the other hand, builds heavily
					on the early <hi rend="italic">piyyut</hi> and represents the inner development
					of this specific literary tradition after three hundred years of development.
					Simply put, the original corpus of the PhD dissertation was placed in diachronic
					comparison with an early and a late corpora.</p>
				<p>The percentage of figurative words in the Book of Psalms is 14% and in the poetry
					of Pinchas 9%. So, on comparing the two, it appears that the original corpus of
					the dissertation was not so under-figurative as seemed at first sight. In fact,
					it stands in between the classical book of Hebrew poetry, the Psalms, and a
					later poet that belonged directly to the literary tradition of piyyut. It is
					hard to draw a conclusion solely from these quantitative observations with
					regard to the history of Hebrew poetry in its diachronic development as far as
					the usage of figurative language is concerned, yet it definitely marks a
					promising scholarly path for future studies.</p>
				<p>In other cases, the digital reexamination refuted findings in the dissertation.
					One of the meaningful categories for the analysis in the dissertation was the
					relation between figurative language and the specific genre or sub-genre of the
					poems. Piyyut is characterized by a strict generic classification and naturally
					some (sub)genres tend to use figurative language more than others. The
					quantification of the results allowed one to examine easily what the figurative
					density (the ratio between figurative and non-figurative words) of each genre
					might be, and here, too, the results corroborated some of the initial findings
					while refuting others. Most notably is the genre of the Hosha’not (hosanna),
					which ranked at 25% of figurative density. That is to say, in general, every
					fourth word is figurative. If we compare this phenomenon to the overall
					figurative density of the corpus, which is 11%, it really stands out. Curiously,
					in Münz-Manor’s dissertation it was noted, in passing to be honest, that this
					genre is low on figurative language <ptr target="#munzmanor2006a" loc="p. 61"/>.
					Where did such an incorrect assertion come from? The Hosha’not are very short
					and in the style of a litany, a list of attributes of the people of Israel. So
					even if many of these epithets are figurative, the poem as a whole does not
					sound very figurative. Here we encounter an interesting case where the
					quantitative and the qualitative represent separate lines that do not meet while
					both are valid. Quantitatively, there are many figurative words, however, their
					aesthetic impression is low and possibly does not call for a detailed literary
					analysis; or does it? We do not think we can or should decide on such matters,
					but it demonstrates quite nicely that opening the door to quantitative
					considerations expands the literary toolkit and the hermeneutical
					possibilities.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Manual Annotating in the Digital Age as a Close Reading Practice</head>
				<p>At first glance, the transition described above from paper-based manual
					annotating to computer-assisted manual annotating, which undoubtedly provides
					better analytical capabilities <ptr target="#jacke2018"/>, should lead to
					research which can be measured quantitatively, and whose conclusions will –
					almost by definition – be more robust. Simply put, although the research
					procedure was essentially the same, what Münz-Manor was able to do for the first
					time with the digital tool allowed him to say clearer things about the entire
					corpus. In other words, even in this seemingly modest case, the transition to a
					digital tool might well have coincided with a certain and widespread perception
					of the adopting of the computational option as a move in the direction of
					objectivity, scientification, and the like. However, as we shall see, and as
					other scholars have already argued (for example: <ptr target="#rieder_etal2012"
					/>, the picture is more complex, since, even in such a case, this move has a
					price.</p>
				<p>To begin with, we must ask ourselves if, and to what extent, the
					computer-assisted manual annotating is really so conceptually similar to the
					non-computerized manual one. Manual annotation in the digital humanities is
					sometimes described as an area of the good old close reading within the new
					realm of distant reading. This is both true and not true: it is true because,
					unlike some algorithmic analytic methods which are now very common in
					computational literary studies, human digital annotation is based on sensitive
					attention to every detail in the text, and is definitely a way of reading. And
					it is not true, because, unlike close reading, annotation in digital humanities
					is usually supposed to be based not only on clearly defined categories, but also
					on much more developed systematic thought, which, in turn, affects the scope of
					annotation: Often, a modest and well-defined annotating task is expanded to
					encompass many more phenomena, in an attempt to fully exploit the opportunities
					inherent in more and more annotated data. Traditional close reading is not
					adversely affected by this consideration. This problem, in brief, stems from the
					multifaceted nature of digital modeling operations – including annotating, as a
					form of modeling: such operations sometimes seek to focus on a specific
					pre-defined research question, at the same time as seeking to prepare the
					research object for future analysis, based on as-yet-unknown questions <ptr
					target="#flanders_etal2016"/>. As a result, manual-annotation-based projects
					tend to lack (or, better, to challenge) another important and characteristic
					feature of close reading: sampling. As Paul Fleming puts it, <cit><quote
					rend="inline">an essential element of close reading relies not just on the
					quality of the reading performed, but also on the example chosen. It has to be
					the right example</quote><ptr target="#fleming2017" loc="p. 437"/></cit>. It is
					not surprising, then, that in Münz-Manor’s initial work, a sort of disconnect
					between the annotation process and the body of the dissertation chapters becomes
					apparent: while each chapter chooses the <q>right example</q>, these examples
					weren’t chosen for their representativity, but because they were interesting or
					important to the author for some reason or other. The aim of the annotating
					process, by contrast, was only to prepare an infrastructure, and in the end that
					infrastructure remained largely in the shadows.</p>
				<p>How much room is there for sample-based research in a computationally-based
					annotation process? Could a particular concept of categorization support it?
					Sampling of a certain portion of a larger corpus is certainly justified in the
					context of traditional literature research. It reflects the gap between the
					amount of data prepared and the relatively free discussions that do not
					necessarily derive from it. It is, among other things, what gives this kind of
					research freedom of interpretation and room for creative conceptualization which
					is not necessarily less reliable. Choosing the right example, then, is one of
					the most effective ways of moving between detail-orientedness and
					generalization, which is the traditional way to see the wood for the trees.
					However, a quantitative approach that takes itself seriously may necessarily
					limit itself from using such a method, even in relatively simple cases which do
					not give up on human reading in favor of completely computational automation.
					Instead of highlighting the most interesting cases, it will highlight only those
					that <q>actually</q> – that is, statistically – represent something broader than
					themselves. That being said, how can one bridge this gap in computational
					literary studies, without giving up systematic category-based annotation? Even
					when annotation is driven by interpretive considerations, at the end of the
					process a layer of information is obtained that is perceived as rigid, whose
					reprocessing with statistical tools may not reveal its interpretive richness.
					Doesn’t the meticulousness of manual annotating avoid the additional
					interpretive step beyond what emerges directly from the accumulation of data? Do
					generalizations, in the digital age, have to be more modest, more
					data-driven?</p>
				<p>To put it another way, is the transition between the carefully annotated data to
					what can (and should) be said about such data still possible? This becomes even
					more complicated when – typically of digital humanities – <q>the wood</q> is not
					one text, but many, which are now being observed and analyzed through a
					well-developed abstract category system.</p>
				<p>Taking the analogy further, if the text is a tree, then, when we label its parts,
					we also give names and definitions to the shape of its branches, to the texture
					of its leaves, to the taste of its fruits. But since our corpus is a forest that
					contains many texts – many <q>trees</q> – as is usually the case in
					computational literary studies, when we then want to understand the forest as
					such, we can no longer pay attention to every branch, leaf, and fruit.
					Generalizing about a tree means talking about the entirety of its branches,
					leaves, roots, and fruits. Generalizing about a forest means talking about the
					entirety of its trees. At this point, the connection between the parts of
					individual trees and the entire forest might become increasingly blurred. To be
					clear, this is not another version of Franco Moretti’s distant reading, because,
					unlike Moretti, when we seriously annotate text after text we <hi rend="italic"
					>do </hi>interpret it. However, in the end, even if we find the most creative
					ways to build a database of texts that classifies them on the basis of a
					complicated calculation of all their annotations and internal relationships, in
					the end, some degree of reduction is almost inevitable.</p>
				<p>Admittedly, it is complicated even at the level of one tree taken as a whole:
					Anyone who has experienced the transition from text annotation to text
					classification knows that it is not an easy transition. Text annotation is a
					device designed to break down texts; text classification – and genre
					classification is a good example of this – is a device designed to connect their
					parts together, in order to achieve at least one generalization regarding the
					text – one that facilitates comparing it to other texts on a well-defined
					basis.<note>We suggest the term <q>in-line annotation</q> to refer to the
					practice of annotating specific aspects in a text, rather than producing a label
					for the text as a whole.</note></p>
				<p>If we follow Andrew Piper’s attitude to generalizations, as described in <title
					rend="quotes">Can We Be Wrong? The Problem of Textual Evidence in a Time of
					Data</title> (2020), it seems that the answers to the challenge phrased above
					would be relatively clear. In response to one of his book’s manuscript’s
					readers, who wrote that <quote rend="inline">this sounds awfully boring</quote>,
					Piper playfully agrees: <cit><quote rend="inline">It is! Generalizations should
					be boring, cautious, incremental, and slow</quote><ptr target="#piper2020"
					loc="p. 60"/></cit>. It is impossible to deny the logic of this approach, which
					expresses a central element in the research experience in the age of data. It is
					hard, however, not to feel the stark contrast between this approach and that of,
					say, Jonathan Culler, who offers the opposite perspective of the
					pre-computational age: <cit><quote rend="block">Moderate interpretation […]
					though it may have value in some circumstances, is of little interest […]. Many
					<q>extreme</q> interpretations, like many moderate interpretations, will no
					doubt have little impact, because they are judged unpersuasive or redundant or
					irrelevant or boring, but if they are extreme, they have a better chance […] of
					bringing to light connections or implications not previously noticed or
					reflected on than if they strive to remain <q>sound</q> or moderate</quote><ptr
					target="#culler1992" loc="110"/>.</cit></p>
				<p>The question then is – can we do both? Is it possible to be content with modest
					generalizations, as Piper recommends, while at the same time going far into the
					bold realms of over-interpretations, as Culler recommends?</p>
				<p>In answering this question, we assume that Culler is not talking about <hi
					rend="italic">false </hi>generalization, but speculative ones: Thought-provoking
					generalizations that are not derived directly from the data, and whose relation
					to the data may even be questionable, but nevertheless reveal a different kind
					of truth. When we put the debate this way, with all due respect to data-driven
					research, there is no reason to deny the importance and the fruitfulness of more
					radical hypothesis-driven research – especially not in computational literary
					studies (or other sub-fields of digital humanities). And here, we believe,
					categories, which sometimes appear to serve as a means to enrich data in a
					relatively robust manner, do not have to be thought of as a hindrance – a device
					that prevents speculation – but rather as something to work with; as a valuable
					source of inspiration. Indeed, in what follows we introduce a tool that is
					designed, among other things, to enable just that: at one and the same time to
					take advantage of categorization while also fostering speculation.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Visualization as Hermeneutical Tool: Introducing ViS-À-ViS<note>ViS-À-ViS will
					be able to interface with other annotation services in the future (such as <ref
					target="https://inception-project.github.io/">INCEpTION</ref>, accessed 27 May
					2023), at the moment it works exclusively with CATMA. </note> </head>
				<p>One of the problems with annotating projects of the type that Wendell Piez
					described as <q>hermeneutic markup</q> <ptr target="#piez2010"/>, and which
					CATMA reflects <ptr target="#meister2014"/> <ptr target="#horstmann2020"/>, is
					that this type of tagging strongly encourages a focusing on details – on the
					parts of the tree – and often makes it difficult to see the whole picture, the
					<q>wood</q>. Even when the user analyzes the annotated material, their analysis
					is usually question-dependent, revealing a small subset of the dimensions of the
					tagging. At this point, we believe, the need for an advanced visualization of
					the hermeneutic metadata, that is, the manual annotations, becomes urgent – and
					this is where the tool that will be described below comes into play. While
					visualization can be question-dependent, it can also be used more freely. And
					despite all the problems associated with it, we assume, like many others, that
					this is one of the most important paths for distant reading; there is no other
					way to see all the details from above <ptr target="#drucker2011"/> <ptr
					target="#moretti_etal2019"/>. Recently Franco Moretti commented that no way has
					yet been found for an adequate synthesis of text-interpretation with
					corpus-visualization <ptr target="#moretti2020"/>. We hope that the idea
					presented here advances us towards a possible solution.</p>
				<p>It should be noted in this context that, unlike close reading, where the scholar
					actually reads the text closely, distant reading – regardless of its specific
					history <ptr target="#ross2014"/> <ptr target="#herrnsteinsmith2016"/> <ptr
					target="#underwood2017"/> – is better understood as a metaphor. In other words,
					the reader extracts meaning from the corpus without actually reading it, à la
					Moretti. Analyzing text via visualization, then, is a perfect example of
					<q>reading</q> a text, without reading it at all. But, in our case, the fact
					that the visualization of the entire corpus is based on actual reading – on
					quite sensitive reading – makes this act of reading-through-visualization <hi
					rend="italic">a bit more</hi> a way of reading in the original sense: the
					<q>trees</q>, if you like, are still there.</p>
				<p>CATMA is a powerful and flexible tool that focuses on annotation, hence its
					visualization capabilities are basic. This reality was the incentive for the
					creation of a separate tool, <ref target="http://visavis.ouproj.org.il/"
					>ViS-À-ViS</ref>, that enables the user to visualize the annotated text, the
					annotations (by one or more annotators) and even the tagset itself <ptr
					target="#munzmanor_etal2020"/>. That being said, following Johanna Drucker’s
					call for more humanities-oriented visualizations <ptr target="#drucker2011"/>,
					the tool seeks to provide users with more than mere visualizations, namely, it
					provides an interface that supports what might be called speculative
					hermeneutics, by allowing for a smooth transition between the smallest detail
					and the entire picture, and doing so in a playful manner. By this, we mean that
					the tool provides the opportunity to <q>play</q> with the visualizations of the
					individual texts, and group them in various configurations according to their
					similarity or dissimilarity, with the aim of providing the users with a fresh
					insight into the text and its annotations. One can think in this context of a
					partial similarity between this tool and the famous visualization tool Voyant
					<ptr target="#sinclair_etal2016"/>: while Voyant focuses on the text, in a way
					that encourages free speculations, our tool does the same with annotations as
					the object of analysis.</p>
				<p>In more than one way, ViS-À-ViS is following in the footsteps of another project
					in the CATMA ecosystem, Stereoscope.<note><ref
					target="https://stereoscope.threedh.net"
					>https://stereoscope.threedh.net</ref>.</note> According to the developers:
					<cit><quote rend="inline">Stereoscope is a web-based software prototype for
					visualizing two core processes of literary studies: hermeneutic exploration of
					textual meaning and construction of arguments about texts</quote><ptr
					target="#kleymann_etal2021"/></cit>. According to Kleymann and Stange, the
					developers of the tool, its core principle is what they call Hermeneutical
					Visualization, which is defined as follows: <quote rend="inline">The use of
					computer-supported, interactive, visual representations of text annotations to
					manipulate, reconfigure and explore them in order to create visual
					interpretations that can be used as arguments and allow a critical reflection of
					the hermeneutic process in light of a research question</quote>. ViS-À-ViS
					continues Stereoscope’s vector, but shapes and conceptualizes it
					differently.</p>
				<p>In what follows, we present a number of screenshots from the tool that exemplify
					its various features and capabilities.<note>ViS-À-ViS is a web-based tool using
					AmCharts library for Java Script; its front end is written in Vue.js while the
					back end is based on Python Flask. The data is imported through CATMA’s Gitlab
					using a unique user access token. The data is then built in XML files using a
					hierarchy of text, tagset, tags and annotations. The development team of the
					tool consists of Dr. Oren Mishali, the tool’s architect, Moshe Schorr and Yuval
					Erez, the programmers. </note> We are using texts from the above-mentioned
					project on figurative language in piyyut, but the tool supports any other
					language supported by CATMA. The main user interface of the tool is shown below
					(figure no. 1):</p>
				<figure>
					<head>ViS-À-ViS’ Main Interface</head>
					<figDesc>The main interface of ViS-À-ViS upon open</figDesc>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>The left-hand pane presents different viewing modes (Browse Texts, Browse Tagset,
					Gallery and Boards) as well as the Import Manager. Each of the viewing modes
					enables the user to look at the annotated corpus from a different perspective:
					in Browse Texts, the view which is selected in this screenshot, the list of
					texts appears to the left, with the associated charts (in this case a Gantt)
					showing the annotations according to the different tags in the tagset, and, on
					the right, the text itself with the specific tag that the user is hovering over
					highlighted. The Gantt itself presents the different tags across the text, with
					the beginning of the text furthest on the left and the end furthest on the
					right. In other words, what we are visualizing here is the distribution of the
					various annotations as they are spread out in the text. A selection of specific
					tags from the tagset is available in a feature that will be described later.</p>
				<p>On the upper pane on the right hand side, five different charts are available:
					Gantt, Stacked Area, Sunburst, Force-Directed Network and Bubble. Here, for
					example, is a screenshot of the same text with Stacked Area selected (figure no.
					2):</p>
				<figure>
					<head>Stacked Area View</head>
					<figDesc>The main interface of ViS-À-ViS with "stacked area view"
						selected</figDesc>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>This visualization is similar on the one hand to the Gantt as it presents a
					<q>diachronic</q> (x-axis) overview of the annotations in the text. On the other
					hand, it provides a more nuanced representation of the dynamics between the
					various annotations on the <q>synchronic</q> (y-axis) level. Hence it enables
					the scholar to detect general patterns throughout the course of the text as well
					as patterns in the interaction between the tags at specific parts thereof. What
					is more, this visualization is interactive, and with a single click a tag can be
					added or withdrawn from the screen, thus enabling the user to play with the
					visualization and consider different views and interpretation modes. Here, one
					of the core features of the tool comes into play, one that gives it its
					experimental nature, namely, the ability not only to visualize the annotations
					statically but also to add or eliminate some of them in order to reveal
					different aspects of the texts and the patterns embedded within them.</p>
				<p>Other charts offer the opportunity to present aggregative views. For example, in
					the sunburst chart, the user can visualize one text (figure no. 3):</p>
				<figure>
					<head>Sunburst View</head>
					<figDesc>The main interface of ViS-À-ViS with "sunburst view" selected</figDesc>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>Or several (figure no. 4):</p>
				<figure>
					<head>Sunburst View - Aggregated</head>
					<figDesc>The main interface of ViS-À-ViS with "agregated sunburst view"
						selected</figDesc>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>In each case the interactive chart presents the distribution of the selected tags
					in terms of their percentage in the entire text(s) – a very useful feature that
					offers a quantitative appraisal of the annotations. In practice, this
					functionality provides a powerful analytical tool for the scholar, who can
					precisely equate or differentiate between different texts in the corpus or to
					compare different corpora. Here, too, the interactivity of the visualization
					offers the scholar a high degree of flexibility in the exploration process.</p>
				<p>Browse Tagset is another meaningful visualization option and one that needs to be
					singled out in the context of this article. Large, hierarchical tagsets are hard
					to grasp and visualize in CATMA, and ViS-À-ViS offers an interactive
					representation of the tagset in a network-oriented chart (figure no. 5):</p>
				<figure>
					<head>Browse Tagset View</head>
					<figDesc>The ViS-À-ViS interface with the "browse tagset" sub-menu
						selected</figDesc>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>Here a representation of the tagset is visible and the interactive chart enables
					one to collapse or uncollapse the various levels. The size of each level relates
					to the number of children it has, which once more offers a useful insight into
					the structure and inner hierarchy of the tagset. Another option that relates to
					this chart is the ability to visualize the actual annotations in one text or
					again in an aggregated view (figure no. 6):</p>
				<figure>
					<head>Force-Directed Network Tagest View</head>
					<figDesc>The ViS-À-ViS "tagset view" with the "force-directed network" option
						selected</figDesc>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>In this case, the size of each category represents the number of annotations in a
					specific category in each text. Here, the visualization of categorization is not
					merely a metaphor but rather a concrete feature that enables the user ‘to see
					the wood <hi rend="italic">and</hi> the trees’. That is to say, if the Browse
					Tagset option visualizes the idea (in the platonic sense) of the tagset, here we
					can watch the manifestation thereof in actual text(s). In other words, we see
					here the <q>wood</q> and the <q>trees</q> synchronically.</p>
				<p>As was previously noted, CATMA, and thus also ViS-À-ViS, support multiple
					annotations and annotators. This way the user can view side-by-side the
					annotations of two or more annotators in order to compare and analyze them. This
					turns the attention of the scholar to the individual and subjective
					interpretation of each annotator and presents therefore another insight into
					potential patterns in the text. This in turn provides additional evidence for
					the corroboration or refutation of scholarly hypotheses about the text and about
					the differences and similarities between the different annotators (figure no.
					7):</p>
				<figure>
					<head>Multi-Annotator Mode</head>
					<figDesc>The ViS-À-ViS interface with the "multi-annotator" mode
						selected</figDesc>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>Inter-annotator agreement (or lack thereof) is a fundamental term in
					computational linguistics and natural language processing, fields that seek to
					minimize human variation and to create standards <ptr target="#plank2022"/>. In
					<q>traditional</q> literary studies variation is frequently the driving force of
					the hermeneutical process – and, as we argued elsewhere, we think it can and
					should be the same in the field of computational literary studies <ptr
					target="#marienbergmilikowsky_etal2022"/>. Instead of collapsing the variation
					into a gold or a silver standard, ViS-À-ViS advocates for the visualization of
					multiplicity. In other words, instead of providing an answer concerning the
					<q>correct</q> annotation, it raises a question about it and promotes once more
					literary speculation.</p>
				<p>ViS-À-ViS offers additional functionalities that enable the user to view
					miniature visualizations of different texts side by side (figure no. 8):</p>
				<figure>
					<head>Gallery View</head>
					<figDesc>The ViS-À-ViS interface's miniaturized "gallery view"</figDesc>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>By aggregating the texts, the user can detect similar (or dissimilar) patterns
					and use the Boards option to collect and divide them into different groups
					(figure no. 9):</p>
				<figure>
					<head>Boards View</head>
					<figDesc>The ViS-À-ViS interface with the "boards view" selected</figDesc>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>This exemplifies perfectly the speculative potential of ViS-À-ViS that enables
					the user to group, re-group and de-group texts according to flexible categories
					defined by him- or herself. Indeed, in the next section, we will exemplify how
					using these features enabled us to detect an unusual pattern, to explore it, and
					reach an interesting scholarly conclusion.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Case Study (B): Hermeneutical Visualization </head>
				<p>The process of playful visualizations can sometimes lead to new revelations.
					Using ViS-À-ViS’ various modes the scholar can skim through the corpus and look
					for (recurring) patterns or other notable features of the tagged texts. Indeed,
					it is very difficult to frame exactly this exploratory phase, to predict how
					long will it take or to predict its fruitfulness. In this case we set out by
					using the Gallery View the Gantt and Stacked Area charts visualizations of the
					entire corpus, genre by genre. We then created some Boards with
					<q>interesting</q> visualizations of specific poems and compared them one to the
					other. The whole process took roughly two weeks and at the end, this cross-genre
					exploration highlighted an <q>unusual</q> similarity in one of the Boards and
					sent us back to one of the sub-genre of the corpus, the Seder Avodah (order of
					sacrifices). The genre is a lengthy poem for the Day of Atonement that narrates
					and associates the creation of the world and the history of the first
					generations with the sacrificial ritual of the high priest in the Jerusalem
					Temple <ptr target="#swartz_etal2005"/>. The pattern that we recognized is
					characterized by a drop in the number of usages of figurative devices at a
					certain point in the poems, while towards the end of the composition the number
					rises again. The figures below visualize the annotations’ distribution in four
					Avodah poems. The left-hand side represents the beginning of the text, and the
					right-hand side its end. The vertical axis represents the number of figurative
					usages, aggregated per ten-percent chunks of the texts (figures no. 10):</p>
				<figure>
					<head>Distribution of figurative devices in Ata konanta olam berov khesed</head>
					<figDesc>Graph of stacked areas which steeply declines left to right</figDesc>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
				</figure>
				<figure>
					<head>Distribution of figurative devices in Azkir gevurot eloah</head>
					<figDesc>Graph of stacked areas which rises sharply, then steeply declines left
						to right</figDesc>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure11.png"/>
				</figure>
				<figure>
					<head>Distribution of figurative devices in Aromem bekhol et</head>
					<figDesc>Graph of stacked areas which exhibits three steep peaks</figDesc>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure12.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>Here, another important phase comes into play, in the interplay between the
					distant and close reading. We went back to the text and discovered that this
					shift appears in the transition from the description of the history of the world
					to the description of the cult of the high priest. This phenomenon had gone
					almost entirely unnoticed in scholarly discussion and was hinted only in passing
					in Münz-Manor’s dissertation. Interestingly, in one poem this pattern
					breaks:</p>
				<figure>
					<head>Distribution of figurative devices in Az be’ein kol</head>
					<figDesc>Graph of stacked areas which dips slightly in the middle</figDesc>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure13.png"/>
				</figure>
				<p>Interestingly, but not necessarily surprisingly. There is an ongoing dispute
					among scholars whether it is very early (ca. fifth century CE) or very late (ca.
					ninth century CE) and the structural analysis suggests that it is the latter
					<ptr target="#munzmanor2022" loc="373–378"/>.</p>
				<p>The case of the Avodah poems thus nicely illustrates the <q>zoom-in/zoom out</q>
					dynamic of close versus distant reading that such a tool offers. The discovery
					of the latent pattern began with a close reading of the poems and the manual
					annotation process; continued with a distant-reading visualization that exposed
					the patterns, without ignoring the fact that these patterns are based on a very
					sensitive reading; and concluded with going back to the text in order to
					interpret the finding – and sometimes reinterpret the text. This workflow
					demonstrates how the introduction of quantitative methods and data
					visualization, when done from a literary studies point of view, can expand and
					enrich the toolbox of the literary scholar. In future versions of ViS-À-ViS we
					envision an enhancement of the workflow by implementation of automated pattern
					detection, a task already underway <ptr target="#munzmanor_etal2020" loc="2–3"
					/>. Obviously, the automatic detection of patterns would not replace the scholar
					and the hermeneutical process, but it has the potential to broaden the
					interpretative possibilities and to make the workflow less cumbersome.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>From the Analogue to the Digital: The Conclusions of the Reexamination (and a
					Note on Pedagogy)</head>
				<p>Literary studies can benefit greatly from walking a moderate line, where one
					piece of evidence after another is gathered, and everything is done in a
					measured and balanced way, with openness to criticism, rather than indulging in
					generalizations based on rhetorical persuasion. Our approach here is not very
					different from Piper’s, although we believe that this argument goes quite
					naturally hand in hand with computational research projects that rely heavily on
					the systematic annotation of texts, rather than on machine learning algorithms,
					which – despite being based on pre-existing annotated texts – emphasize the
					distance from the text itself. As long as we still wish to <hi rend="italic"
					>read</hi> – in a purely literal sense – this is probably the safest approach.
					It could also respond to Adam Hammond's justified call for the validation of
					research findings in the digital humanities <ptr target="#hammond2017"/>.
					However, the price of such a procedure is not only that too much focusing on
					details can hide the bigger picture, and sometimes even leave the researcher
					with the feeling that reaching it is impossible, or that it is insufficiently
					well founded, but also such research may lose some of its significance, its
					raison d'être, and so become, in one way or another, less meaningful. If we echo
					again what was presented before as a kind of (imagined) dispute between Piper
					and Culler, the question is how to find the golden path between a
					textual-anchored generalization on the one hand, and, on the other, a
					<q>healthy</q> speculation that will advance the research – with a calculated
					risk – into new and unexpected areas.</p>
				<p>Here, we argue, a different attitude to categories can help: It is usually
					difficult to move directly from the smallest details to the bigger picture. We
					therefore suggest focusing on categories, as a research object located somewhere
					in the middle, and anyway requiring some abstraction – while bearing in mind
					that categories might have non-trivial relationships with both the details and
					the picture. Simply put, we propose a more playful approach to the
					epistemological status of categories, one that does not leave them solely as the
					cornerstone of the annotation process, but returns to examine them again and
					again from a critical perspective. From a more philosophical point of view, it
					can be said that this approach offers a back-and-forth movement between two
					different types of categorization: a categorization based on generalizations –
					that is, collecting and extracting all the data until categories that contain
					them correctly are defined – versus a categorization based on formalization,
					that is, by removing all actual data until an abstract category is formed (see
					<ptr target="#thomasson2022" loc="§ 1.3"/>.</p>
				<p>This approach also has a pedagogical aspect, which in our opinion is fundamental
					for the teaching of computational research to humanities students, and
					symptomatic of the subject at hand. We can demonstrate this from our shared
					experience in teaching manual digital annotating of literary texts. When we
					teach CATMA to our students – and we do it a lot – we are used to telling them
					that the main place where their traditional theoretical thinking is supposed to
					undergo computational operationalization is in setting the tagset, that is, in
					the translating of abstract concepts into a category system. The daring ones
					usually adopt the proposal and try to formulate a whole world of fuzzy ideas as
					a tagset, which, flexible as it may be, is more rigid by definition than the
					primordial thoughts with which the students set out. But then, when they are
					starting to annotate, they want to tag everything; they want to add new tags, or
					correct the old ones; and that almost always happens. In a way, they are good
					students. Once they are exposed to the power of systematic annotation, they
					become addicted to it. They fall in love with the straight-forward use of a
					category system: it offers them an attractive intellectual alternative in its
					solidity, in its precision, in its caution. They start like Culler, and end like
					Piper. When, later, they analyze their annotations through a concrete query,
					with or without some basic visualizations, they transform their annotations into
					something tangible, and the process comes to a head: metadata becomes data, and
					interpretation becomes a rigid text. <q>A Trojan horse</q>, is what Johanna
					Drucker (2011) once called visualizations with too much explanatory power. When
					we try to challenge the students and say – <said>now speculate, please!</said> –
					they find it difficult to achieve. They see, of course, the richness of the
					data; they see – hopefully – the preciseness and carefulness of the local
					annotations; after all the hard work they have invested, they can treat it as
					reliable information. This is all good. But the leap towards a certain kind of
					reduction, or more creative speculation, or a bit less grounded but nonetheless
					legitimate generalization, ends up being viewed with circumspection and as a
					serious challenge.</p>
				<p>The tool presented here was constructed not only based on the lessons we had
					learned from moving the research discussed above from a paper-based environment
					to a computerized environment, but also with these students in mind. We argue
					that excessive textual anchoring of speculations and hypotheses comes with a
					price, and offer a visualization approach that tries to deal with this; not only
					in order to achieve the digital equivalent of <q>the right example</q> chosen –
					a speculative generalization of the entire <q>tree</q>, or <q>wood</q>, based on
					the careful annotation of its parts – but also in order to push the researcher
					to rethink or rephrase their categories, by moving as freely as possible between
					generalization-based categorization and formalization-based categorization. It
					might encourage the researcher to redefine his or her category system, and this
					time not only on the basis of detailed interpretation, but also on the basis of
					a (careful) reduction.</p>
				<p>Finally, we want to offer a sort of thought experiment for a workflow that is not
					yet possible with the tool presented here, but in our opinion can outline one of
					the next steps in research. What if we take to an extreme the promise of a
					tension between the data-driven attitude and hypothesis-driven attitude. Many
					human annotators hope that at some point the machine will learn how to annotate
					the text, and continue automatically with their own manual sensitive work;
					actually, some annotation tools already do this.<note>For example, tools like
					Recogito (<ref target="https://recogito.pelagios.org/"
					>https://recogito.pelagios.org</ref>, accessed 27 May 2023) or INCEpTION (<ref
					target="https://inception-project.github.io/"
					>https://inception-project.github.io</ref>, accessed 27 May 2023). In addition,
					Münz-Manor and colleagues from the Technion, Israel Institute of Technology are
					currently training deep machine learning models, based on the manual annotations
					from the doctoral dissertation, to automatically detect metaphors in the
					medieval corpus of <hi rend="italic">piyyut</hi> (<title rend="quotes">FigureOut
					- Automatic Detection of Metaphors in Hebrew Across the Eras</title>, DH2023,
					Graz, Austria, poster session).</note> But what if we try it the other way
					around, and speculate about the opposite possibility, where we start from the
					forest, from generalization about the trees or the wood as a whole – that is,
					from a hypothesis – and only then present it to the annotator, while asking him
					or her: Can you reject this generalization? Can you interpret the text
					differently so that the data will ultimately undermine the validity of the
					generalization?<note>This idea, we believe, has a lot of potential; we hope to
					discuss it in detail elsewhere.</note> Or, alternatively, can you explain the
					validity of this claim by abstraction instead of generalization? Such an
					exercise’s purpose is not to encourage the interpreter to manipulate (in a
					negative sense) the data, but to challenge him or her in a very concrete way; to
					aid him or her in thinking differently about the data and generalizations
					associated with them.</p>
				<p>Trees and woods, after all, may look different at any given moment, and there is
					no reason to confuse systematicity with stability. It might be helpful, perhaps,
					to quote here Roland Barthes’ adaptation of Nietzsche, who said that <quote
					rend="inline" source="offline">a tree is a new thing at every instant: we affirm
					the form because we do not seize the subtlety of an absolute moment</quote>. And
					Barthes: <quote rend="inline" source="#barthes1975">The text too is this tree
					whose (provisional) nomination we owe to the coarseness of our organs. We are
					scientific</quote> – please note – <cit><quote rend="inline">because we lack
					subtlety</quote><ptr target="#barthes1975"/></cit>.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Acknowledgment</head>
				<p>This research was generously supported by grant No. 1223 from the Israeli
					Ministry of Science and Technology.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<listBibl>
				<bibl xml:id="barthes1975" label="Barthes 1975">Barthes, R. (1975) <title
					rend="italic">The Pleasure of the Text </title>(translated by Richard Miller)
					New-York: Hill and Wang.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="culler1992" label="Culler 1992">Culler, J. (1992) <title rend="quotes"
					>In Defence of Overinterpretation</title>, in Colini S. (ed.) Umberto Eco,
					<title rend="italic">Interpretation and Overinterpretation – with Richard Rorty,
					Jonathan Culler and Christine Brooke-Rose. </title>Cambridge: Cambridge
					University Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="drucker2011" label="Drucker 2011">Drucker, J. (2011) "Humanities
					Approaches to Graphical Display", in <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital
					Humanities Quarterly</title> 5:1.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="english2010" label="English 2010">English, J. F. (2010) "Everywhere
					and Nowhere: The Sociology of Literature After ‘the Sociology of Literature’",
					in <title rend="italic">New Literary History</title> 41:2, pp. v-xxiii.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="flanders_etal2016" label="Flanders and Jannidis 2016">Flanders, J. and
					Jannidis, F. (2016) "Data Modeling", in Schreibman, S., Siemens, R., Unsworth,
					J. (eds.) <title rend="italic">A New Companion to Digital Humanities</title>,
					Malden: Wiley Blackwell, pp. 229-237.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="fleming2017" label="Fleming 2017">Fleming, P. (2017) <title
					rend="quotes">Tragedy, for Example: Distant Reading and Exemplary Reading
					(Moretti)</title>, <title rend="italic">New Literary History</title> 48, pp.
					437-455.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="fluh_etal2021" label="Flüh et al. 2021">Flüh, M., Horstmann, J.,
					Jacke, J., Schumacher, M. (2021) "Introduction: Undogmatic Reading - from
					Narratology to Digital Humanities and Back", in Flüh, M., Horstmann, J., Jacke,
					J., Schumacher, M. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Toward Undogmatic Reading:
					Narratology, Digital Humanities and Beyond</title>, Hamburg: Hamburg University
					Press, pp. 11-29.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="gius_etal2022" label="Gius et al. 2022">Gius, E., Meister, J. C.,
					Meister, M., Petris, M., Bruck, C., Jacke, J., Schumacher, M., Gerstorfer, D.,
					Flüh, M., Horstmann, J. (2022) <title rend="italic">CATMA 6</title> (Version
					6.5) Zenodo. DOI: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1470118"
					>10.5281/zenodo.1470118</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="goldstone_etal2014" label="Goldstone and Underwood 2014">Goldstone,
					A., Underwood, T. (2014) "The Quiet Transformations of Literary Studies: What
					Thirteen Thousand Scholars Could Tell Us," in <title rend="italic">New Literary
					History</title> 45:3, pp. 359-384.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="hammond2017" label="Hammond 2017">Hammond, A. (2017) "The Double Bind
					of Validation: Distant Reading and the Digital Humanities’ ‘Trough of
					Disillusionment’", in <title rend="italic">Literature Compass</title>
					14:e12402.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="herrnsteinsmith2016" label="Herrnstein-Smith 2016">Herrnstein-Smith,
					B. (2016) "What Was "Close Reading"?: A Century of Method in Literary Studies",
					in <title rend="italic">Minnesota Review</title> 87, pp. 57-75.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="horstmann2020" label="Horstmann 2020">Horstmann, J. (2020) <title
					rend="quotes">Undogmatic Literary Annotation with CATMA</title>. <title
					rend="italic">Annotations in Scholarly Editions and Research</title>,
					pp.157-176.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="jacke2018" label="Jacke 2018">Jacke, J. (2018) <title rend="quotes"
					>Manuelle Annotation</title>, in <title rend="italic">forTEXT. Literatur digital
					erforschen</title>. <ref
					target="http://fortext.net/routinen/methoden/manuelle-annotation"
					>http://fortext.net/routinen/methoden/manuelle-annotation</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="janicke_etal2015" label="Jänicke et al. 2015">Jänicke, S., Franzini,
					G., Scheuermann, G., Cheema, M. S. (2015) "On Close and Distant Reading in
					Digital Humanities: A Survey and Future Challenges", in Borgo, R., Ganovelli F.,
					and Viola I. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Eurographics Conference on
					Visualization</title>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="jockers_etal2015" label="Jockers and Underwood 2016">Jockers and
					Underwood 2016Jockers, M. L., Underwood, T. (2016) "Text-Mining the Humanities",
					in Schreibman, S., Siemens, R., Unsworth, J., (eds.) <title rend="italic">A new
					Companion to Digital Humanities</title>, Malden: Wiley Blackwell, pp.
					291-306.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="marienbergmilikowsky2019" label="Marienberg-Milikowsky 2019"
					>Marienberg-Milikowsky, I. (2019) "Beyond Digitization: Digital Humanities and
					the Case of Hebrew Literature", in <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in
					the Humanities</title> 34:4, pp. 908-913.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="marienbergmilikowsky2022" label="Marienberg-Milikowsky 2022"
					>Marienberg-Milikowsky, I. (2022) "It Functions, and that’s (almost) All:
					Tagging the Talmud", in Fiormonte, D., Ricaurte, P., Chahudhuri, S. (eds.)
					<title rend="italic">Global Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>,
					Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, pp. 141-150.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="marienbergmilikowsky_etal2022"
					label="Marienberg-Milikowsky et al. 2022">Marienberg-Milikowsky et al.
					2022Marienberg-Milikowsky, I., Vilenchik, D., Krohn, N., Kenzi, K., Portnikh, R.
					(2022) <title rend="quotes">An Experimental Undogmatic Modelling of (Hebrew)
					Literature: Philology, Literary Theory, and Computational Methods</title>, in
					Horstmann J., Fischer, F. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Digital Methods in
					Literary Studies - Special Issue of Textpraxis. Digital Journal for
					Philology</title> 6.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="meister2014" label="Meister 2014">Meister, J. C. (2014) <title
					rend="quotes">Toward a Computational Narratology,</title> in Maristella, A.,
					Tomasi, F. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Collaborative Research: Practices and
					Shared Infrastructures for Humanities Computing</title>, Padova: CLEUP, pp.
					17–36.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="moretti2020" label="Moretti 2020">Moretti, F. (2020) <title
					rend="quotes">Simulating Dramatic Networks.</title> <title rend="italic">Journal
					of World Literature</title> 6, 1, 24-44, Available From: Brill <ref
					target="https://doi.org/10.1163/24056480-20201001"
					>https://doi.org/10.1163/24056480-20201001</ref> [Accessed 28 June 2023]</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="munzmanor2006a" label="Münz-Manor 2006a">Münz-Manor, O. (2006) <title
					rend="quotes"><title rend="italic">Studies in Figurative Language of
					Pre-Classical Piyyut</title>,</title> PhD diss., Jerusalem: Hebrew University of
					Jerusalem.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="munzmanor2006b" label="Münz-Manor 2006b">Münz-Manor, O. (2006) <title
					rend="quotes">Structural Ornamentations and Figurative Language in the Ancient
					Piyyut,</title> in <title rend="italic">Jerusalem Studies in Hebrew Literature
					</title>21, pp.19–38 (Hebrew)</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="munzmanor2009" label="Münz-Manor 2009">Münz-Manor, O. (2009) <title
					rend="quotes">'As the Apple Among Fruits, so the Priest When He Emerges': Poetic
					Similies in Pre-Classical Poems of the 'How Lovely' Genre,</title> in <title
					rend="italic">Ginzei Qedem</title> - <title rend="italic">Genizah Research
					Annual </title>5, pp. 165-188 (Hebrew)</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="munzmanor2011" label="Münz-Manor 2011">Münz-Manor, O. (2011) <title
					rend="quotes">Figurative Language in Early Piyyut,</title> in Katsumata, N., van
					Bekkum, W. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Giving a Diamond: Essays in Honor of
					Joseph Yahalom on the Occasion of His Seventieth Birthday</title>, Leiden:
					Brill, pp. 51–68.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="munzmanor2016" label="Münz-Manor 2016">Münz-Manor, O. (2016) <title
					rend="quotes">The Payytanic Epithet and its Connections with Figurative
					Language,</title> in <title rend="italic">Jerusalem Studies in Hebrew Literature
					28</title>, pp. 93-112 (Hebrew)</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="munzmanor2022" label="Münz-Manor 2022">Münz-Manor, O. (2022) <title
					rend="quotes">Quantifying Piyyut: Computerized Explorations of Ancient Hebrew
					Poetry,</title> in <title rend="italic">Jewish Studies Quarterly</title> 29, pp.
					370-388.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="munzmanor_etal2020" label="Münz-Manor et al 2020">Münz-Manor et al
					2020Münz-Manor, O., Schorr, M., Mishali O., Kimmelfeld, B. (2020) <title
					rend="quotes">ViS-À-ViS : Detecting Similar Patterns in Annotated Literary
					Text,</title> in <title rend="italic">VIS4DH,</title> <ref
					target="https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.02063"
					>https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.02063</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="piez2010" label="Piez 2010">Piez, W. (2010) "Towards Hermeneutic
					Markup: An architectural outline", in <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
					2010 Conference Abstracts Book</title>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="plank2022" label="Plank 2022">Plank, B. (2022) <title rend="quotes"
					>The 'Problem' of Human Label Variation: On Ground Truth in Data, Modeling and
					Evaluation</title>, <ref target="https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.02570"
					>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.02570</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="piper2020" label="Piper 2020">Piper, A. (2020) <title rend="italic"
					>Can We be Wrong? The Problem of Textual Evidence in a Time of Data</title>
					(Cambridge Elements: Digital Literary Studies), Cambridge: Cambridge University
					Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="rieder_etal2012" label="Rieder and Röhle 2012">Rieder, B., &amp;
					Röhle, T. (2012) Digital Methods: Five Challenges. En D. M. Berry (Ed.), <title
					rend="italic">Understanding Digital Humanities</title>. Palgrave Macmillan UK,
					pp. 67-84. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1057/9780230371934_4"
					>https://doi.org/10.1057/9780230371934_4</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ross2014" label="Ross 2014">Ross, S. (2014) <title rend="quotes">In
					Praise of Overstating the Case: A review of Franco Moretti, Distant
					Reading</title>, in DHQ 8:1.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="sinclair_etal2016" label="Sinclair and Rockwell 2016">Sinclair. S.,
					Rockwell, G. (2016) Voyant Tools. Web. <ref target="http://voyant-tools.org/"
					>http://voyant-tools.org/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="thomasson2022" label="Thomasson 2022">Thomasson, Amie, "Categories",
					The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy (Winter 2022 Edition), Edward N. Zalta
					&amp; Uri Nodelman (eds.), <ref
					target="https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2022/entries/categories/"
					>https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2022/entries/categories/</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="weingart2022" label="Weingart 2022">Weingart, S. B. (2022) <title
					rend="quotes">Networked Society: The Moral Role of Computational Research in a
					Data-Driven World,</title> <ref target="http://scottbot.net/2014/09/"
					>http://scottbot.net/2014/09/</ref> (accessed 22 June, 2022)</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="swartz_etal2005" label="Swartz and Yahalom 2005">Swartz, M., Yahalom,
					J. (2005) <title rend="italic">Avodah: An Anthology of Ancient Poetry for Yom
					Kippur,</title> University Park: Pennsylvania State University Press.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="underwood2017" label="Underwood 2017">Underwood, T. (2017) <title
					rend="quotes">A Genealogy of Distant Reading</title>. <title rend="italic"
					>Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 11(2).</bibl>
			</listBibl>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
