<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">The Ludii Games Database: A Resource for
               Computational and Cultural Research on Traditional Board
               Games<!--article title in English--></title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->

            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Walter <dhq:family>Crist</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  >https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5460-9511<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Leiden University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>wcrist@asu.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Walter Crist is an archaeologist working as a Lecturer in the Leiden University
                     Centre for the Arts in Society. He earned his PhD from Arizona State University
                     with a thesis on Bronze Age board games in Cyprus. His research focuses on the
                     sociality of games in prehistory, as well as traditional forms of gaming
                     throughout the world. He has researched ancient games in Cyprus, Azerbaijan,
                     Greece, Turkey, the Netherlands, and Egypt. He is Vice Chair of the COST Action
                     GameTable, and was the main contributor of archaeological, historical, and
                     anthropological research for the Digital Ludeme Project.</p>
               </dhq:bio>

            </dhq:authorInfo>

            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Walter <dhq:family>Crist</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  >https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5460-9511<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Leiden University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>wcrist@asu.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Walter Crist is an archaeologist working as a Lecturer in the Leiden University
                     Centre for the Arts in Society. He earned his PhD from Arizona State University
                     with a thesis on Bronze Age board games in Cyprus. His research focuses on the
                     sociality of games in prehistory, as well as traditional forms of gaming
                     throughout the world. He has researched ancient games in Cyprus, Azerbaijan,
                     Greece, Turkey, the Netherlands, and Egypt. He is Vice Chair of the COST Action
                     GameTable, and was the main contributor of archaeological, historical, and
                     anthropological research for the Digital Ludeme Project.</p>
               </dhq:bio>

            </dhq:authorInfo>


            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Matthew <dhq:family>Stephenson</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  >https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3867-5842<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Flinders University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>matthew.stephenson888@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Dr. Matthew Stephenson is a Lecturer with the College of Science and
                     Engineering at Flinders University, where he specialises in Game AI. His
                     research interests centre predominantly around the use of Artificial
                     Intelligence, Machine Learning and Data Science techniques applied to games.
                     This includes research that uses such techniques to play, create and analyse
                     games; but also how we can utilise games as a testbed for developing solutions
                     to real-world problems. His current research focus is on data-driven approaches
                     for both procedural content generation and general game playing.</p>
               </dhq:bio>

            </dhq:authorInfo>

            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Éric <dhq:family>Piette</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  >https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8355-636X<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>UCLouvain</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>eric.piette@uclouvain.be</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Éric Piette is an Assistant Professor at UCLouvain in the ICTEAM institute and
                     INGI department, specializing in Game Artificial Intelligence (AI) and its
                     applications. His expertise encompasses Machine Learning (ML), Explainable AI
                     (XAI), Constraint Satisfaction Problems (CSP), and Knowledge Representation and
                     Reasoning (KRR) in General Game Playing (GGP). As the Chair of the GameTable
                     COST Action CA22145, he leads an international network focused on using game AI
                     to study, reconstruct, and preserve the cultural heritage of games. Among his
                     contributions, he contributed to the ERC-funded Digital Ludeme Project,
                     developing the Ludii General Game System to model traditional strategy games.
                     He also introduced a novel approach to GGP using stochastic constraint
                     satisfaction and bandit-based sampling, exemplified by WoodStock, the last
                     International General Game Playing Competition winner.</p>
               </dhq:bio>

            </dhq:authorInfo>


            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Cameron <dhq:family>Browne</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  >https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2997-3255<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Independent Scholar</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>cambolbro@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Cameron Browne received the Ph.D. degree in Computer Science from the
                     Queensland University of Technology (QUT), Brisbane, Australia, in 2008,
                     winning the Dean’s Award for Outstanding Thesis. He was Canon Research
                     Australia’s Inventor of the Year for 1998, won the 2012 GECCO "Humies" gold
                     medal for human-competitive results in evolutionary computation, and has
                     written the books "Hex Strategy", "Connection Games" and "Evolutionary Game
                     Design". Dr Browne ran the ERC-funded Digital Ludeme Project (Consolidator
                     Grant #771292) at Maastricht University over 2018–2023, in which he designed
                     and developed the Ludii general game system.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>

         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
               <term corresp="#games"/>
               <term corresp="#databases"/>
               <term corresp="#archaeology"/>
               <term corresp="#dh"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item> Game Studies</item>
                  <item>Computer Science</item>
                  <item>Databases</item>
                  <item>Archaeology</item>
                  <item>History</item>
                  <item>Anthropology</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000756/000756.xml"
               >GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>As commercial tabletop and video games become increasingly popular throughout the
               world, traditional board games are becoming a form of endangered intangible cultural
               heritage, and in many places what were once widely played games have largely been
               abandoned. The Digital Ludeme Project applies artificial intelligence and
               computational techniques to the incompletely documented rules of traditional board
               games from 3500 BCE until the present to help preserve accurate knowledge of these
               games. The project engages with the historiography of knowledge about traditional
               games, determining which parts of the rules are provided by various textual,
               archaeological, artistic, and ethnographic sources. To document this knowledge and
               situate it geographically and chronologically, the Ludii Games Database provides the
               first comprehensive and rigorous Open Access database of scholarship on the global
               history of board games. Furthermore, the database is used as a source for data for
               the Ludii general game system, which makes the games playable and provides the
               analytical tools that will be used in future reconstruction work. Finally, the
               database may also serve as a reference tool for scholars pursuing research on
               games-related topics.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>The Ludii Games Database presents a view on the traditional board games from the past
               5000 years and lets you play them online.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>

         <div>

            <head>1. The Need for A Database of Games </head>

            <div>
               <head>1.1 Introduction</head>

               <p>Games are a particular type of cultural heritage that have not been a particular
                  focus of study in archaeology, anthropology, and history. Despite this, there is a
                  hunger for information on games of the past, and books and websites about games
                  have emerged in the public sphere which cover the topic. Even where this
                  information is available, such research often does not accurately engage with the
                  historical and archaeological record, since much games-related research is very
                  old or not easily accessible. Furthermore, the recent explosion of game studies as
                  a discipline of research in its own right, as well as the thirst for games
                  knowledge among gaming communities and the interested public, demonstrate that
                  there is an audience for research on games. Because of this, we developed the
                  Ludii Games Database to document the preserved knowledge of board games. The
                  database functions as the basis for the Ludii general game system, which uses a
                  human-readable programming language to digitally model these games to make them
                  playable. Importantly, this software facilitates research on games using AI-driven
                  playout simulation. This paper discusses the need for a database of games and
                  situates its construction around the task of modeling games digitally, while
                  explaining how the Ludii games database solves many of these issues and provides a
                  reliable knowledge base to seed future research on games in cultural and
                  computational fields. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>1.2 State of Traditional Games Research</head>

               <p>Such a task is not without challenges considering the history of games research.
                  Though games have been a part of human life for at least the past 5500 years, the
                  disciplines studying human society and its past (anthropology, archaeology,
                  history, among others) have largely ignored games in favor of other areas of human
                  life, such as power relations, economics, and religion. As a result, research on
                  games is hindered by a lack of methodological and theoretical development that
                  have characterized other topics of inquiry. There has been a reliance on certain
                  key works (e.g., <ptr target="#murray_1951"/>, <ptr target="#bell_1979"/>) that
                  are outdated in their approaches, and the information they contain has
                  proliferated in the Digital Age, leading to a situation where a large amount of
                  information is readily available online but outdated, not referenced, or
                  unreliable. The appetite for information and historical data on the games of the
                  past is palpable, but historians, archaeologists, and anthropologists have not
                  provided easy access to this information to the public, and so gamers and game
                  enthusiasts have relied on old data and conclusions that are uninformed by
                  theoretical and methodological advances. One salient example is the repeated
                  assertion, from Henry Parker’s <hi rend="italic">Ancient Ceylon</hi>
                  <ptr target="#parker_1909"/>, that incised patterns on the roof of the Mortuary
                  Temple of Seti I at Qurna are evidence for the presence of games such as Mancala,
                  Nine Men’s Morris, and Alquerque in New Kingdom Egypt and thus dating to the
                  middle of the second millennium BCE, despite the fact that they appear alongside
                  graffiti with Christian iconography <ptr target="#schadler_2021"/>!</p>

               <p>In addition, starting in the twentieth century, the increased global market for
                  proprietary tabletop and video games has changed the ways that people play around
                  the world, and many traditional games have been lost since then <ptr
                     target="#komariah_salim_2019"/>, <ptr target="#fabian_2023"/>, <ptr
                     target="#appadurai_1995"/>, <ptr target="#mukherjee_in_press"/>.</p>

               <p>While early research on games largely used hyper-diffusionist paradigms to
                  pinpoint origins and used imaginative reasoning to reconstruct the rules of games
                  (e.g. <ptr target="#murray_1951"/>[Murray 1951], <ptr target="#tylor_1879"/>[Tylor
                  1879]), over the last thirty years research on the games of the past has received
                  considerable more theoretical and methodological rigour (see <ptr
                     target="#de_voogt_1995"/>, <ptr target="#mackenzie_finkel_2004"/>, <ptr
                     target="#finkel_2007"/>
                  <ptr target="#finkel_2007"/>). Moving past these topics, more attention was paid
                  to board morphology, examining games as social processes <ptr
                     target="#crist_et_al_2016a"/>, and using quantitative methods to calculate
                  similarities and classifications of games <ptr target="#de_voogt_et_al_2013"/>.
                  Now, with modern computational methods, it is possible to address some of the
                  older research questions within a scientific framework. This was not possible
                  before the advent of the techniques available to modern AI researchers, and
                  provides not only another avenue for examining daily life in the past, but also
                  the possibility to preserve this form of intangible cultural heritage <ptr
                     target="#crist_soemers_2023"/>.</p>

               <p>All of these challenges and new opportunities present the need for a centralized,
                  well-referenced database that records the known traditional games of human
                  history, placing them within their geographic and chronological context, while
                  clearly stating what rules are known to have been part of them. The Ludii Games
                  Database <ptr target="#digital_ludeme_project_2022"/> was created to document the
                  knowledge of these traditional games, to serve as a resource for anyone interested
                  in games, and to function as a knowledge base for proposing reconstructions of
                  incompletely preserved games using AI. Defining games is, nevertheless, not always
                  straightforward, especially when games are mechanically identical but
                  geographically or chronologically distant. The Ludii Games Database takes a
                  cultural and game-mechanical approach to defining games, which not only helps to
                  highlight the different versions of similar games played by disparate cultures,
                  but which also provides an analytical framework to examine the variability in
                  games through time and space. </p>
            </div>
         </div>


         <div>

            <head>2. Digitally Modeling Traditional Games </head>

            <div>
               <head>2.1 Ludemes and the Ludii General Game System</head>

               <p>The Digital Ludeme Project (<ref target="www.ludeme.eu">www.ludeme.eu</ref>)
                  investigates traditional games throughout human history to examine how human play
                  has changed through time, and attempts to reconstruct playable rulesets using AI
                  for those games for which complete rules have not been preserved <ptr
                     target="#browne_et_al_2019"/>, <ptr target="#soemers_et_al_2019"/>. Though the
                  scope of traditional games is large, the project focuses on board games, which
                  have been the most comprehensively documented form of traditional game for the
                  last 5500 years of human history The Ludii general game playing software <ptr
                     target="#piette_et_al_2020"/>, which was created for the project to be able to
                  perform the necessary analyses for AI reconstruction, is able to accommodate
                  analysis of other strategy-based games such as card and domino games as well. As
                  of this writing, the project has documented 1057 board games for which enough
                  information has been preserved to contribute to this research.</p>

               <p>Games are modelled as structured sets of ludemes which represent fundamental
                  elements of play. While different definitions of this term exist (e.g. <ptr
                     target="#parlett_2006"/>, we understand ludemes to be any aspect of a game that
                  is transferable between individuals and whose modification produces a functional
                  change in play <ptr target="#browne_2022"/> [Browne 2022]. This can include not
                  only the rules of play, but also the equipment on which the game is played, in so
                  far as its inherent geometry has a fundamental impact on the game. The following
                  example shows the game Tic Tac Toe described in ludemic form in Ludii:</p>

               <eg lang="code-general"><![CDATA[(game "Tic-Tac-Toe"
        (players 2)					
        (equipment {
            (board (square 3))
            (piece "Disc" P1)
            (piece "Cross" P2)
        }) 
        (rules
            (play (move Add (to (sites Empty))))					
            (end (if (is Line 3) (result Mover Win)))
        )
 )]]></eg>

               <p>Ludemes, a term coined by Pierre Berloquin in 1970 <ptr
                     target="#browne_et_al_2019"/>, <ptr target="#sorin_1970"/>, can be thought of
                  as game memes, even though their usage pre-dates the invention of the meme <ptr
                     target="#dawkins_1976"/>, as both represent units of cultural information that
                  are transmitted from person to person. And just as memes composed of multiple
                  sub-memes are called memeplexes, we define ludemeplexes as compound structures of
                  ludemes that combine fortuitously to provide a useful higher-level game concept.
                  For example, the following ludemeplex describes the action of adding a piece to an
                  empty site on the board, which is a concept used in many games and so convenient
                  to wrap up into its own unit of game-related information:</p>

               <p> (move Add (to (sites Empty)))</p>

               <p>This approach to deconstructing games into their constituent ludemic elements
                  makes it possible to digitally model the full range of traditional games required
                  in a single consistent format. It exposes underlying correspondences between games
                  that might otherwise not be obvious and allows the possibility of tracing
                  fundamental concepts from game to game, throughout history, through the mechanisms
                  of cultural transmission <ptr target="#de_voogt_et_al_2013"/>.</p>

               <p>The language also uses specialized syntax to allow for the recording of missing
                  rules in the implementation of games. Where it can be identified that rules are
                  missing from our knowledge base, this can be indicated in the language. </p>

               <p>This capability enables the automated identification and suggestion of potential
                  rules to bridge these gaps <ptr target="#crist_et_al_in_press"/>. Subsequently,
                  the system can compile and playtest these games using AI-simulated play. Notably,
                  Ludii features a variety of game-playing agents that not only enhance user
                  interaction by allowing people to play against varied AI opponents but also
                  facilitate AI research by providing diverse challenges and scenarios for testing
                  and development.</p>

               <p>The Digital Ludeme Project uses this ludemic approach to games, both in the
                  compiling of the database and in the implementation of games in the Ludii
                  software, which will utilize the data contained in the database to create playable
                  digital versions of the games which have been fully documented. Ludii will also be
                  the tool through which reconstructions of games will be achieved by testing
                  possible rulesets and maximizing them for historical accuracy and playability
                  metrics.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>2.2 Preserving the Lost Knowledge of Traditional Games</head>

               <p>Describing the ways that games change through time and the ways that new cultures
                  adopt and alter the rules of play requires a conceptualization of games based on
                  their means of transmission. The process of cultural transmission has been
                  recently demonstrated as a valuable framework under which processes of change can
                  be examined over large timescales <ptr target="#de_voogt_et_al_2013"/>. The
                  process of cultural transmission of games is dependent on the oral or experiential
                  mechanism by which people learn games. That is to say, that for the vast majority
                  of human existence, games were, and still are, taught and learned by teaching
                  another person the rules, either by explaining them or through playing together.
                  This practice is largely the reason why the rules for most ancient and historical
                  games are lost. They were rarely written down because people learned the games
                  from others, and the vast majority of people who played could not write. Written
                  rules did not become a major force for the cultural transmission of games until
                  the Industrial Era, when games became a focus for commercial activity and were
                  invented or appropriated for profit. Writing down rules creates a defined
                  standard, fixed form of play that is refereed by a corporation, inventor, or
                  governing body, which is drastically different from how games were more
                  traditionally governed, which is by consensus of the players. The traditional form
                  of transmission allows for changes to take hold through time and across cultures,
                  creating different forms which are locally and, often, culturally bound.</p>

               <p>Nevertheless, pieces of information that provide details about the rules of play
                  for some of humanity’s traditional games have survived in other media. Game
                  equipment (boards, playing pieces, randomizers) have survived from antiquity,
                  authors have discussed games and used rules of play as metaphors, artists have
                  depicted games in their works, and ethnographers have documented games they
                  observed or were taught, and, in rare occasions, historians and authors with
                  particular interests in games have written treatises on game strategies and
                  documented rules of games. In some cases, such as the ancient Egyptian game Senet,
                  there are hundreds of references to the game and artifacts which survive (see );
                  others, such as Aksadyuta, are only known from one source (in <ptr
                     target="#piccione_1990"/> this case, the Mahabharata, an Indian saga <ptr
                     target="#syed_2020"/>).</p>

               <p>The key to determining what is known about these games is to compile the preserved
                  rules knowledge for each game to determine what is known and what is absent. Under
                  the Digital Ludeme Project, for the purposes of game reconstruction and for the
                  purposes of software implementation, games are conceived as a collection of
                  ludemes. The artifacts, artistic representations, texts, and ethnographic accounts
                  of game rules provide information about which ludemes were used in any given game.
                  For the purposes of this project, any source which provides a ludeme or which
                  places a game chronologically or geographically is referred to as evidence. The
                  suite of evidence for a particular game provides an honest accounting of what is
                  known about the rules of a particular game, and where and when that knowledge is
                  situated in time and space (Figure 1). This allows for the identification of what
                  knowledge is missing for the game to be playable, as well as allowing for
                  comparison with games in similar times and places, which could suggest ludemes for
                  reconstruction purposes.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Figure 1. Board and pieces for the game of 58 Holes. These artifacts provide
                     the board geometry and number of pieces per player for the game. From Asasif,
                     Egypt, ca. 1814–1805 BCE. Metropolitan Museum of Art 26.7.1287a–k.</head>
                  <figDesc>A small ivory game board with holes for spaces and pegs with the heads of
                     dogs and jackals inserted into them.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="media/image5.jpg"/>
               </figure>

               <p>The game Ludus Latrunculorum provides an illustrative example of how rules can be
                  identified from evidence. The game is known from Roman sources, and was played
                  between the second century BCE until possibly the seventh century CE. Varro (De
                  Lingua Latina 10.22) indicates that the game is played on a quadrangular board;
                  Ovid (Tristia 2.477–478) states that a piece is captured when it is between two of
                  the opponent’s pieces, and pieces move along a straight path and can move
                  backwards. The anonymous author of Laus Pisonis 192–193 states that the pieces are
                  placed on an empty board to begin play, indicating the existence of a placement
                  phase in the game (i.e. there is not a fixed starting position). Actual boards
                  have been found in many parts of the Roman Imperium stretching from the Antonine
                  Wall in Britain to Egypt’s southern border, consisting of a rectangular board with
                  of a grid between six and ten squares per side, the sides sometimes being equal
                  but often, unequal — six-by-seven, six-by-eight, eight-by-eight, and eight-by-nine
                  are some that are attested (see <ptr target="#crist_et_al_2024"/>, <ptr
                     target="#schädler_1994"/>). The game also appears in art. A terracotta model of
                  a Ludus Latrunculorum game from the Fayyum Oasis of Egypt depicts a six-by-seven
                  board with seventeen pieces placed in the squares of the board <ptr
                     target="#petrie_1927"/>, showing that the pieces were placed in the squares
                  rather than on the corners (as is the case with some games), and that there were
                  at least seventeen pieces in the game, assuming that the uneven number represented
                  shows that some have been captured.</p>

               <p>Because of the state of game research, much of what is known about the games of
                  the past is obscured by assumptions, misconceptions, and overly imaginative
                  interpretations that have become repeated as fact, particularly in
                  publicly-accessible resources. Thus, secondary texts are not very reliable when
                  they report on the history and known rules for games. Indeed, sites such as
                  BoardGameGeek and Wikipedia, which contain a great deal of information about
                  games, typically rely on popular works with outdated methodological approaches and
                  data such as A History of Board Games Other than Chess by H.J.R.<ptr
                     target="#murray_1951"/>, or those which do not consistently report the source
                  of their information about games, such as R. C. Bell’s Board and Table Games of
                  Many Civilizations <ptr target="#bell_1979"/>. For this purpose, a database of the
                  games from humanity’s past, connecting them to the evidence for what their rules
                  are and placing them within their chronological and geographic context, is
                  required to first be able to identify what is known and what needs to be
                  reconstructed. This database not only functions as a data source for the Digital
                  Ludeme Project, but also as an Open Access resource for anyone researching board
                  games. </p>
            </div>

         </div>
         <div>
            <head>3 The Ludii Games Database</head>
            <div>
               <head>3.1 Conceptual Framework — Games</head>
               <p>To identify connections between games and document their changes through time,
                  defining boundaries between discrete games becomes a challenge. Although games are
                  largely defined based on mechanical considerations, i.e., the rules of play; there
                  is some question of when to determine that a game is different enough from another
                  to consider it a separate game. Furthermore, there are many simple games which are
                  identical in their rules, but which are separated in time and/or space to such a
                  degree that cultural transmission seems to be an implausible explanation, and thus
                  should not be considered the same game because they could have been independently
                  invented or the product of convergent evolution. Therefore, the Ludii Games
                  Database takes a hybrid cultural-functional approach to defining games. A game is
                  considered different from another game if it has non-trivial rule differences from
                  another game, or if two games are separated from one another chronologically or
                  geographically in such a way that combining the history of the games as played in
                  different places does not make sense.</p>

               <p>For example, the English game Backgammon and the Greek game Portes are nearly
                  identical in their rules <ptr target="#malaby_2003"/> [Malaby 2003], and though
                  they are very obviously connected to each other in some way, it does not make
                  sense to connect the history of Backgammon in England with that in Greece, because
                  the history of these places is subject to different cultural interconnections and
                  nearby gaming cultures that could have contributed to changes in game play.
                  Furthermore, Chess in medieval Europe is virtually identical to the game Shatranj
                  as it was played in Southwest Asia at the same time, and undoubtedly Chess was
                  derived from Shatranj itself <ptr target="#murray_1913"/>. Though the rules are
                  identical, Chess in Europe had a different history, with different social
                  connotations and divergent future developments into the modern game, so these
                  games are catalogued separately in the database.</p>
            </div>


            <div>
               <head>3.2 Rulesets</head>
               <p>Games data in the database operates as a high-level, societal description of
                  games. Rulesets, however, function as medium-level descriptions of how the games
                  were played. Rulesets describe the specific equipment and rules of play associated
                  with a game. They are considered differently from games because, for the purposes
                  of game reconstruction, games may have multiple rulesets. For example, the game
                  Alquerque, known from medieval Spain, was described differently by two different
                  authors, Alfonso X <ptr target="#"/> and Covarrubias [1674]. The rules are
                  compatible with each other, but Covarrubias describes capturing in greater detail
                  than Alfonso X. Because it cannot be assumed that these capturing details were
                  played in Alfonso’s time, these rulesets are considered distinct for the purpose
                  of analysing the game.</p>

               <p>In addition, many of the games of antiquity have been reconstructed by other
                  scholars and game enthusiasts, and it will be useful to analyse their rulesets for
                  historical accuracy and playability. Functionality allowing multiple rulesets per
                  game makes this possible. In addition, during the process of game reconstruction,
                  it will be necessary to consider multiple possible rulesets as potential
                  reconstructions. It is likely that some games will have multiple plausible
                  reconstructions, which will be considered as separate rulesets associated with one
                  game, rather than as separate games unto themselves.</p>

               <p>Because rulesets serve these different roles, they are assigned to the following
                  categories for analytical purposes:</p>

               <list type="unordered">
                  <item>• Described rulesets are those which were written by someone who was part of
                     a culture in which the game was regularly played;</item>
                  <item>• Observed rulesets are those which are reported by someone from outside the
                     culture playing the game, for example, in an ethnographic account;</item>
                  <item>• Scholarly rulesets are those which are proposed by an expert on that
                     particular game or to the culture from which it belongs, such as rules for
                     Senet as proposed by an Egyptologist;</item>
                  <item>• Suggested rulesets are those which were created by someone interested in
                     or knowledgeable about games more generally, who has proposed rules for a
                     game;</item>
                  <item>• Reconstructed rulesets are those which are identified through analysis in
                     the Ludii software;</item>
                  <item>• Incomplete rulesets are those which are missing key portions of the rules
                     which render them unplayable. Incomplete rulesets most often appear as
                     compilations of the known rules for a game as presented by the evidence
                     documented for that game, but they can also be rulesets described by an author
                     that are known to be incomplete because they leave out an important piece of
                     information that renders the game unplayable — such as starting position,
                     winning condition, or other crucial game mechanism.</item>
               </list>

               <p>As already mentioned, games within Ludii are described using keywords known as
                  ludemes. Multiple ludemes can also be combined together into ludemeplexes, which
                  describe certain aspects of a game such as a piece of equipment, or a rule for how
                  a player moves. In a similar manner, each ruleset is made up of many of these
                  ludemeplexes. Due to similar mechanics being present across multiple games, many
                  of our rulesets will share ludemeplexes, and many of these ludemeplexes will share
                  ludemes. As such, the ludemes portion of the database records which ludemplexes
                  are associated with each ruleset, as well as the ludemes which are used in these
                  ludemplexes (and by extension the rulesets as well). Ludemeplexes can also be
                  associated with specific mathematical keywords (e.g. addition, subtraction,
                  rational numbers, etc.) and gameplay-based concepts (e.g. stochastic,
                  hidden-information, asymmetric rules, etc.)</p>
            </div>


            <div>
               <head>3.3 Evidence</head>

               <p>Finally, the portion of the database which is most crucial for historical
                  reconstruction and cultural heritage preservation relates to the evidence.
                  Evidence consists of primary sources of information that provide information about
                  where, when, how, and by whom a game was played. Evidence is crucial to
                  empirically document which ludemes can be included as part of particular games,
                  which allows for the identification of candidate ludemes to fill in lacunae during
                  the game reconstruction process. It also allows us to identify which cultures
                  played certain games, and to position them in time and space.</p>

               <p>Because the game reconstruction process will also trace games geographically and
                  chronologically, each piece of evidence must provide geographical or chronological
                  information, which can be expressed either as a point/date or region/date range.
                  This can be, for example: the date and findspot of an artifact, the date a
                  manuscript was written and the place it was written (or describes), the place
                  where a person observed a game and the dates they were there. This is the minimum
                  amount of information required for a piece of evidence, which will only identify
                  the presence of a game in a particular place and time. Evidence which provides
                  information about game rules, such as board geometry, number of pieces, type of
                  randomizer used, starting position of the pieces, capturing and movement rules,
                  and so forth, are more important for determining the rules for games. Preference
                  is given to collecting this kind of evidence in the database, where it is
                  possible. </p>

               <p>In addition, certain information on the social context of these games is
                  collected. Because the Digital Ludeme Project is interested in tracking the
                  dispersal of ludemes through person-to-person contact, it must be recognized that
                  games were sometimes restricted to people by social class, age, gender, and other
                  social factors. Documenting these will allow us to account for situations where,
                  for example, a game played by non-elite children in one culture is less likely to
                  be connected to one played by elite adults in a neighboring culture than another
                  game that was also played by elites or adults. </p>

               <p>The game, ruleset, and ludeme data is all supported and drawn from the evidence
                  data (see Figure 2). Evidence can provide single ludemes, full or partial
                  rulesets, or contextual, geographic, or chronological data that can be assigned to
                  a game. Evidence need not inform all three categories of data, but must inform at
                  least one of them.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Figure 2. Conceptual diagram of the relationship between games, rulesets,
                     ludemes, and evidence.</head>
                  <figDesc>Diagram showing how ludemes combine to make rulesets, which make up
                     games, all supported by the presence of evidence.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="media/image1.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>.</p>
               <p>Description: </p>
            </div>


            <div>
               <head>3.4 Database Format </head>
               <p>The Ludii Games Database is stored as a MySQL-based database structure, made up of
                  many linked tables. These tables can be split into the same four conceptual groups
                  mentioned previously, Games, Rulesets, Ludemes, and Evidence. Each group contains
                  a single "Fact" table, which lists all elements (games, rulesets, ludemes or
                  evidence) of its corresponding conceptual group. Each group also contains multiple
                  "Dimension" tables, which list different possible values for certain element
                  properties (e.g. Periods, Regions, Categories), and "Junction" tables, which pair
                  specific elements in the Fact tables with values in the Dimension tables. </p>
               <p>Figure 3 shows a complete Entity Relationship Diagram (ERD) of the Ludii Games
                  Database. Each section is coloured based on its conceptual group: evidence in
                  green, games in red, rulesets in yellow, and ludemes in blue. Please note that the
                  three tables in the orange section belong to multiple sections. Blue coloured
                  tables signify Fact tables, purple coloured tables signify Dimension tables, and
                  pink coloured tables signify Junction tables.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Figure 3. Entity Relationship Diagram (ERD) of the Ludii Games
                     Database.</head>
                  <figDesc>Entity Relationship Diagram which shows how all tables in the Ludii Games
                     Database relate to each other.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="media/image3.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>The Games section describes all of the games which are present within the Ludii
                  Games Database. This includes data which pertains to the game — its name, a short
                  description of what it is, other names it is known by, references that talk about
                  the game in a general sense, and the person who entered the game in the database.
                  Other information is calculated from the Evidence section (originPoint, source,
                  evidenceRange), and assigned values for the ease of users to explore the database.
                  The originPoint is the earliest piece of evidence for that game in the database;
                  the evidenceRange is determined by taking the values of the earliest and latest
                  dates of evidence in the database. Period is calculated as Ancient (before 500
                  CE), Medieval (500–1500 CE), or Modern (after 1500 CE) based on the dates of the
                  evidence, and the Region is assigned based on the which United Nations Statistical
                  Division Geographic Region(s) the evidence falls into <ptr
                     target="#united_nations_2021"/>. </p>

               <p>The Rulesets section describes all the rulesets which are used by games within the
                  Ludii Games Database. This includes information about the ruleset directly (name,
                  rules, etc.), as well as information sourced from the Evidence section
                  (originPoint, source, evidenceRange), and information sourced from the Games
                  section (associated Game Id).</p>

               <p>The Ludemes section describes all the ludemeplexes which are present in the Ludii
                  game descriptions for any ruleset within the Ludii Games Database. This includes
                  information about the ludemeplex directly (ludemes, MathKeyword, Concepts, etc.),
                  as well as information sourced from the Evidence section (EvidenceLudemeplexes),
                  and information sourced from the Rulesets section (corresponding RulesetId). </p>

               <p>The Evidence section describes every piece of evidence within the Ludii Games
                  Database. This includes the specific data as it relates to the pieces of evidence:
                  what it is, where it is located, what dates are associated with it, the social
                  factors (age, gender, space, SocialStatus) with which it is associated, and
                  pertinent references. Geographic location can be expressed in latitude and
                  longitude coordinates or by a KML file specifying the region, which is stored
                  separately on the Ludii server. The Sources table contains the bibliographic data
                  for references used throughout the database. Data in this section is not
                  calculated by or drawn from that in any of the other database sections.</p>

               <p>Specific entries within the Ludii Games Database can be individually accessed
                  using its unique identifier. The unique identifier for an entry is represented in
                  the form DLP.T.N, where T is the name of the table within the Ludii Games Database
                  and N is the Id field value of the entry (e.g. DLP.Games.426 or DLP.Evidence.532).
                  The field values associated with a unique identifier can be viewed using the link
                  https://ludii.games/identifier?Id=DLP.T.N (e.g.
                  https://ludii.games/identifier?Id=DLP.Games.426). </p>
            </div>

         </div>


         <div>
            <head>4. Presenting the Database</head>

            <div>
               <head/>
               <p>The information stored in the Ludii Games database is publicly accessible via the
                  Ludii Portal (<ref target="https:\www.ludii.games">https:\www.ludii.games</ref>).
                  This website provides the front-end interface for downloading the complete
                  database, but also for users to explore the database in a manner more accessible
                  to them. The complete list of games can be found at
                  https://www.ludii.games/library.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Figure 4. Game page for Senet, <ref
                        target="https://ludii.games/details.php?keyword=Senet"
                        >https://ludii.games/details.php?keyword=Senet</ref>.</head>
                  <figDesc>Screenshot of a webpage for the game Senet, showing the presentation of
                     this game’s data.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="media/image4.jpg"/>
               </figure>


               <div>
                  <head>4.1 Game Pages</head>
                  <p>Every game that is being investigated as part of the Digital Ludeme Project has
                     a corresponding page dedicated to it (see Figure 4). The page collects the
                     information relevant to that game and its associated rulesets from the database
                     into a single page and presents it in a manner that is more user-friendly.
                     Importantly, it also embeds a playable version of the Ludii-based
                     implementation — when a playable ruleset has been identified. This
                     stripped-down instantiation of Ludii allows a single player to play against an
                     AI game-playing agent. </p>

                  <p>Relevant information, such as its rules, historical information, references,
                     and an interactive map of any associated evidence are also included to inform
                     the user about the game. References are linked either to the original document,
                     when they are available in an Open Access digital format, or to their WorldCat
                     entry. Information such as period and region are calculated from the
                     chronological and geographical range for the evidence for that game, allowing
                     users to search for games pertinent to their interests.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Figure 5. World maps from the Ludii Games Database. Top with the earliest
                        piece of evidence for every game (<ref
                           target="https://ludii.games/worldMap.php"
                           >https://ludii.games/worldMap.php</ref>), bottom with every piece of
                        evidence with a specified location (<ref
                           target="https://ludii.games/worldMapEvidence.php"
                           >https://ludii.games/worldMapEvidence.php</ref>).</head>
                     <figDesc>Two world maps, one with points for the earliest evidence of each game
                        and one with a point for every piece of evidence in the database.</figDesc>
                     <graphic url="media/image6.jpg"/>
                  </figure>

               </div>

               <div>
                  <head>4.2 World Maps</head>
                  <p>Two world maps (Figure 5) provide visualization of the evidence for games that
                     have been compiled in the database. The first displays a complete visual
                     representation of all games with evidence around the globe. Each identified
                     game has a single point placed on this map, with its location based on the
                     earliest known piece of evidence associated with it. The colour of each point
                     is based on its game mechanisms category (e.g. Mancala, Race, Hunt), which is
                     based on Parlett’s classification [Parlett 1999]. The tone of each point is
                     based on its age (darker represents earlier, whilst lighter represents later).
                     Each point links to the relevant game page. The map includes a slider which
                     allows users to define a beginning and end year to select a time period,
                     causing the map to display the games that existed between those years.</p>
                  <p>Another map provides a complete visual representation of all pieces of evidence
                     around the globe. Each identified piece of evidence with a specific location
                     has a single point placed on this map. The shape of each point is based on the
                     kind of evidence it is (i.e. artifact, art, text, or ethnography). The tone of
                     each point is based on its age (darker represents earlier, whilst lighter
                     represents later). Clicking on a point displays the information about that
                     particular piece of evidence. </p>
               </div>


               <div>
                  <head>4.3 Forum</head>
                  <p>The Ludii Forum provides a message board interface for allowing users to
                     communicate with members of the Digital Ludeme Project team, as well as each
                     other. This forum is divided into several different categories (General,
                     Questions, Suggestions, Problems, Competitions) where users can enquire about
                     various different aspects of Ludii and the Digital Ludeme Project. Engagement
                     with users is crucial for not only identifying software bugs, but also has the
                     potential for engaging with users who are familiar with traditional games which
                     are not published in the scholarly literature. The forum also provides
                     announcements of any new updates or changes to Ludii, as well as information
                     about upcoming events such as AI competitions or conferences. As of the time of
                     writing, the Ludii Forum has over 800 registered users. </p>
               </div>

               <div>
                  <head>4.4 Concepts</head>

                  <p>Concepts represent aspects of game mechanics and metrics that can be shared
                     between different games [Piette et al. 2021]. Each concept is expressed in
                     game-terms well-known by game players and designers. A concept can be
                     associated with the game itself, a particular state that occurs during
                     gameplay, or a move played. They can be related to the equipment of the game
                     (board or pieces), to the rules of the game (game setup, ending conditions, or
                     movement of the pieces), and to more general aspects such as various properties
                     (e.g. symmetries, information type, time model). These data are particularly
                     interesting to compare, analyse and evaluate games.</p>

                  <figure>
                     <head>Figure 6. Concepts search page on the Ludii portal. The concept "1.2.1
                        Num Players" has been selected, along with the value "&amp;gt;4".</head>
                     <figDesc>Screenshot of webpage with the list of game Concepts showing the
                        search function.</figDesc>
                     <graphic url="media/image2.jpg"/>
                  </figure>

                  <p>The Concept Search page allows users to search for games that contain specific
                     combinations of these concepts (see Figure 6). Instructions are provided at the
                     top of the page, below which users can select specific concepts and associated
                     values. In Figure 6, the concept "1.2.1 Num Players" has been selected, along
                     with the value "&amp;gt;4". Additional concepts can also be added as needed.
                     Clicking the "Search" button will return all the games which satisfy this
                     request, in this case, those which have more than four players. At the bottom
                     of the page, a complete hierarchy of all concepts is also provided. </p>

                  <p>Within Ludii, AI agents are used to compute specific concept values, crucial
                     for reconstructing games with enhanced historical accuracy and improved
                     playability. Ludii represents gaps in game rules using symbols and compiles
                     this information into structured data to pinpoint ludemes that can complete
                     these rules. After identifying potential matches from its database, Ludii ranks
                     these based on their cultural, geographical, and conceptual proximity
                     [Stephenson et al. 2023] to the original game rules. This process enables Ludii
                     to generate comprehensive rulesets, which are then filtered to align with
                     established board game concepts and the evidence gathered for these games.</p>
               </div>

               <div>
                  <head>4.5 Data Management</head>
                  <p>The Ludii Games Database is archived at DataverseNL [DANS and Maastricht
                     University 2022], an Open Access data archiving platform. It is managed by DANS
                     [Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts, Sciences and Dutch Research Council 2022],
                     the Dutch National Centre of Expertise and Repository for Research Data, and
                     partner institutions including Maastricht University. New versions of the
                     database are uploaded with each update of the Ludii software, and the version
                     number of the database matches the version of Ludii associated to it.
                     DataverseNL preserves the data for at least ten years after the last
                     publication based on the dataset, after which time the data will be migrated to
                     one of the archival platforms managed solely by DANS.</p>
               </div>
            </div>


         </div>


         <div>
            <head>5. From Data Collection to Research</head>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>5.1 Challenges and Opportunities in Data Collection</head>
            <p>Because the Ludii Games Database was built specifically to support Ludii in achieving
               the Digital Ludeme Project’s AI-based game reconstruction research, there have been
               challenges in translating game-related evidence from historical and archaeological
               data in ways that provide meaningful representations of what is known about a
               particular game. For example, as described above, we considered games where evidence
               documents identical complete rules in different cultures to be different games. This
               model is difficult to apply in the deep past, where evidence is both sparse and
               incomplete for games. One example is for the Egyptian game Senet, which was played
               for roughly three thousand years in Egypt, Nubia, West Asia, and Cyprus, at various
               points in time [Crist et al. 2016b]. For ancient games like this, we decided to use a
               different model where a given piece of evidence may provide only a portion of the
               rules. For example, a limited selection of evidence for Senet indicates the track
               along which the pieces move through the sequence of squares on the board. We want
               this evidence to be considered as part of the game everywhere it was found. Where
               there is evidence to suggest there may be variations in the way this game was played,
               such as boards that are marked with distinct patterns in the playing squares to
               presumably indicate certain gameplay events, these were separated into different
               rulesets for Senet, so they can be considered separately from one another, but still
               as part of the set of evidence that more broadly defines what we know about this
               game.</p>

            <p>The structure of the Ludii Games Database allows for flexibility in different kinds
               of game research, while also handling the complexity of defining boundaries between
               games. The relationships between entities in the database allow us to easily tie
               games, rulesets, and evidence to one another, but also provide flexibility in
               situations where we decide that ancient or historical evidence should actually be
               associated with separate games or rulesets, rather than one. For example, boards from
               the Roman Empire were originally connected to the English game Nine Men’s Morris
               because they shared the same board, but it was later decided that the Roman material
               should be considered separately, and the existing evidence tied to the newly entered
               game "Roman Merels" instead. Such flexibility allows for easy changes that will occur
               as analysis of different games progresses, as the project anticipates identifying
               connections between different games that may indicate that two separate games should
               be considered the same, or that one should be separated into two different ones. This
               demonstrates the flexibility of the database, as entries can be changed as new
               evidence for games emerges, so games can be redefined and evidence reassigned.</p>

            <p>Other challenges present opportunities for creative solutions in the future. There
               are many boards, objects, and brief accounts that may indicate the existence of board
               games that are not easily defined into ludemes. For example, there are many finds
               throughout the ancient world of singular or small groups of dice or playing pieces,
               which cannot be defined as belonging to a particular game or as a meaningful ludeme.
               Because the Ludii Games Database is built to use evidence to define the ludemes that
               belong to a game, the documentation of these kinds of objects does not add knowledge
               about particular games. Nevertheless, the presence of game-related material in a
               particular place and time, still point to the presence of a game in a given time and
               place. Such is the case, for example, of a recently-discovered group of pieces from
               Başur Höyük, Turkey [Sağlamtimur 2017], which probably consist of several groups of
               pieces belonging to an unknown set of games.</p>

            <p>Some of the emerging conclusions from the ongoing data collection is that a
               considerable amount of documentation needs to be done to achieve the same level of
               resolution of games knowledge across the globe. Particular regions of the world are
               strongly represented in our database either because they are well-published in
               Western European languages, (such as India and Sri Lanka) or because a particular
               researcher took an interest in the games of a particular place and comprehensively
               documented them (such as in Mongolia [Kabzińska-Stawarz 1991] and the Horn of Africa
               [Pankhurst 1971]). Eastern Europe, as well as East and Southeast Asia, are areas
               which could particularly benefit from the collection of further data, as the
               information from games in these areas is either primarily published in local
               languages or not documented. South America is also a place which historically has
               received little attention from games research, and recent work in Argentina suggests
               there is a considerable amount of evidence for indigenous board games that remains
               undocumented [Ferrarese 2005]. </p>
         </div>

         <div>

            <head>5.2 AI-centered research</head>


            <p>The existence of a database such as this one provides numerous unique research,
               pedagogical, and heritage preservation uses related to games. The Ludii software
               provides a powerful tool for AI-based research on games. In computer science, games
               have been a particular focus of research, as games provide simple, discrete,
               rule-based systems that can lead to the development of AI techniques [Crist and
               Soemers 2023]. However, because of the lack of cultural data on traditional games, AI
               research that attempts to use such games must rely on outdated, incompletely
               documented, or speculative sources. Having an academically-sourced database of games
               from which AI researchers can identify candidate games relevant to their research
               adds to the accuracy and relevance of their findings. This can also support
               applications of data mining and machine learning analysis, including automated game
               evaluation, portfolio/ensemble agent training, and personalised user recommendations.
               Furthermore, the Ludii software provides certain advantages that improves the
               accessibility of this research with its human-readable language. </p>

            <p>AI applications to games research can also help to augment our understanding of the
               (pre)history of games. AI-driven simulated play in Ludii offers opportunities for
               researchers to study games by allowing AI agents to play games and generate
               quantitative data that can help to answer research questions, but which would be
               prohibitively time consuming to generate through human play. For example, we
               conducted AI experiments to explore the archeological evidence for the Roman game
               Ludus Latrunculorum, mentioned above. Using the concepts search menu, we manually
               identified games (Kharebga [Bellin 1964] and Seega [Davies 1925], [Lane 1836]) that
               contained all of the rules known to have been used in this game, and simulated play
               to determine their playability on the wide range of sizes of rectangular or square
               boards found at Roman-era sites. This research determined that boards smaller than
               ten-by-ten squares are more likely to have been used for this game, and larger ones
               were probably another game not discussed in the Roman sources, probably one played by
               the indigenous population of Europe outside of Italy, since these boards were found
               largely away from the urban centres of the empire [Crist et al. 2024]. </p>

            <p>"Through the description process embedded in Ludii, we can pinpoint gaps where
               information on game rules is missing. Ludii then procedurally identifies potential
               playable rule sets that might fit these gaps [Crist et al. in press]". Calculations
               based on game distance — i.e., the vector distance between two or more games using
               the shared concepts (rules, mechanics, design and strategies) they contain
               [Stephenson et al. 2023] — can be when coupled with other distance measurements meant
               to model social change across time and space. This methodology allows Ludii to match
               a game with closely related ones, using their rules as a basis to propose new,
               quantitatively plausible rule reconstructions for historical games. Work on this
               process is ongoing. We are also exploring the application of AI-simulated play to
               attempt to identify play that replicates use-wear on archaeological game boards,
               another method that could potentially aid in the identification of rulesets [Crist et
               al. 2022].</p>

            <p>There is also the possibility of examining cross-cultural comparisons of the
               experience of play through the comparison of behaviour metrics generated through
               AI-simulated play. For example, comparison of the number of turns it generally takes
               to play a particular game could inform research on time as experienced during play.
               The identification of mathematical concepts, strategies, and techniques that exist in
               particular games can also be explored using this data [Piette et al. 2022]. Research
               on AI-simuated play as a proxy for the experience of human play is in its infancy,
               and we expect that further applications and research will only grow in coming
               years.</p>

         </div>


         <div>
            <head>5.3 Cultural Research</head>
            <p>In addition to this, there are wide applications outside of AI research for the Ludii
               games database. As discussed above, While game studies has over the past twenty years
               developed as a discipline largely focused on video games and driven by the commercial
               success and cultural prevalence of that industry [Mäyrä 2008], [Nieborg and Hermes
               2008]. Despite the more than five thousand years of documented history of human game
               playing, research on historical, ancient, and traditional games has been embedded
               deep within the literature of the disciplines that research their time periods, in
               multiple different languages, and even still is quite rare. Thus, the kind of data
               necessary to produce high quality cross-cultural and/or diachronic research has been
               prohibitively difficult to access, especially when compared to video games which can
               be experienced as part of contemporary culture, are easily accessible, and provide
               more obvious lines of research because of their complexity and intersection with
               research on other forms of media.</p>

            <p>The Ludii games database thus provides a centralized space for people to research
               traditional board games and to expand some of the phenomena examined in game studies
               as a more universal human experience. Any research must be grounded in documentation
               of the games and cultures of play that surround them, so facilitating connection to
               the sources that discuss the games in a given time and place is crucial to improving
               future research. Research questions that have been discussed in particular cultural
               contexts can then be explored in other cultures or even on a worldwide basis. For
               example, the impact of colonialism on games [Mukherjee in press], [Mukherjee 2022]
               can be discussed in a broader sense with better access to information on games in
               diverse cultural contexts. The database can also provide a resource for studying how
               traditional games change through time — an important process of cultural transmission
               that can help us to model how ideas travel and change that is not dependent on
               exchange of goods or materials [de Voogt et al. 2013]. Many of the games in the
               database were documented in the nineteenth and early twentieth century, but few
               people have reviewed whether these games are still played today. Are the rules
               different now? Do they vary from community to community? The evidence in the database
               can serve as a starting point from which scholars can gather new data on traditional
               games and then compare this data to what was gathered in another time and place to
               explore change through time, to examine cross-cultural contact or how cultural
               practices change within a particular society. Modeling how games changed through time
               and how different social processes affect rule changes could go a long way to
               creating models of cultural change more broadly. These applications discussed here
               are not comprehensive, but the opportunities presented by having accessible data are
               great.</p>

         </div>


         <div>

            <head>5.4 Future Development</head>

            <p>The scope and content of the Ludii games database will continue to expand through the
               help of the COST Action GameTable: Computational Techniques for Tabletop Games
               Heritage. This initiative brings together scholars with research backgrounds spanning
               AI, cultural disciplines, mathematics and education to develop new ways to explore
               the ways these fields intersect to study intangible tabletop games heritage [Piette
               et al. 2024]. One of the main ways that this will expand the database will be to
               include traditional card and domino games in a similar format, as these are crucial
               forms of tabletop games that are not yet represented and are supported by the Ludii
               playing software [Morenville and Piette in press]. We will also explore ways to
               mitigate the challenges indicated above, as well as to incorporate more visual
               material. GameTable will also explore developing more human-like AI algorithms, which
               will allow for AI-simulated play that more closely imitates human behaviour rather
               than optimal play, thus providing scholars with a better research tool for games
               research. It will also explore explainable search techniques for playing agents and
               reinforcement learning approaches to discover interpretable strategies for playing
               these games [Soemers et al. in press].</p>

            <p>Though the Ludii Games Database serves as a depository for information about
               traditional games from around the world and is fundamentally designed to provide data
               to be used by other researchers. Even more importantly, it is accessible to the
               general public and non-specialists who are interested in traditional and historical
               games from all around the world, presenting data on games honestly and transparently.
               But most crucially, it provides a place online where information on traditional,
               historical, and ancient games, many of which are no longer maintained by traditional
               player communities, can be preserved and new communities could form around them,
               since they are playable in Ludii. Through partnerships with museums and cultural
               organizations, we are exploring strategies for further developing methods of
               preservation of gaming heritage. There is also a considerable opportunity for the use
               of the database as a pedagogical resource, not only to teach about game studies, but
               also in many relevant disciplines that could highlight games as cultural practices of
               historical importance. This comprehensive resource therefore contributes to the
               validation of game studies as useful to people studying other kinds of cultural
               phenomena, and provides a new strategy for the preservation of the threatened
               intangible cultural heritage of traditional games. </p>
         </div>

         <div>

            <head>Acknowledgements</head>

            <p>This research was funded by European Research Council Consolidator Grant 771292.
               Discussions that improved this paper were supported by COST (European Cooperation in
               Science and Technology) Action CA22145.</p>

         </div>
      </body>




      <back>


         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="appadurai_1995" label="Appadurai 1995"> Arjun Appadurai. (1995). <title rend="quotes">Playing
               with modernity: the decolonization of Indian cricket</title>. In <title rend="italic">Consuming Modernity: Public
               Culture in a South Asian World</title>, C. A. Breckenridge (ed.). Minneapolis: University of
               Minnesota Press, pp. 3–63. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bell_1979" label="Bell 1979"> Robert C. Bell. (1979) <hi rend="italic"
                  >Board and Table Games from Many Civilizations</hi>. New York: Dover. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bellin_1964 " label="Bellin 1964">Paul Bellin (1964) “L’enfant saharien à
               travers ses jeux”. <hi rend="italic">Journal des Africanistes</hi> 33, pp.
               47–104.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="browne_2022" label="Browne 2022 ">Cameron Browne. (2022) “Everything’s a
               Ludeme. Well, Almost Everything”. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of XXIII Board Game
                  Studies Colloquium — The Evolutions of Board Games, Apr 2021, Paris, France</hi>.
               ffhal-03737317f </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="browne_et_al_2019" label="Browne et al. 2019"> Cameron Browne, Dennis J.
               N. J. Soemers, Éric Piette, Matthew Stephenson, Michael Conrad, Walter Crist,
               Thierry Depaulis, Eddie Duggan, Fred Horn, Steven Kelk, Simon Lucas, João Pedro
               Neto, David Parlett, Abdullah Saffidine, Ulrich Schädler, Jorge Nuno Silva, Alex de
               Voogt, and Mark Winands. (2019) “Foundations of Digital Archaeoludology”. Technical
               Report ArXiv: 1905.13516v1.</bibl>


            <bibl xml:id="crist_soemers_2023" label="Crist and Soemers 2023"> Walter Crist and
               Dennis J.N.J. Soemers. (2023) “The Digital Ludeme Project: combining archaeological
               and computational methods for the study of ancient games”. <hi rend="italic">Journal
                  of Archaeological Science: Reports</hi> 49. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jasrep.2023.104005"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jasrep.2023.104005.</ref>
            </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="crist_et_al_2016a" label="Crist et al. 2016a">Walter Crist, Alex de Voogt,
               and Anne-Elizabeth Dunn-Vaturi. (2016) “Facilitating Interaction: Board Games as
               Social Lubricants in the Ancient Near East”. <hi rend="italic">Oxford Journal of
                  Archaeology</hi> 35, pp. 179–196. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1111/ojoa.12084"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1111/ojoa.12084</ref></bibl>


            <bibl xml:id="crist_et_al_2016b" label="Crist et al. 2016b"> Walter Crist,
               Anne-Elizabeth Dunn-Vaturi and Alex de Voogt. (2016) <hi rend="italic">Ancient
                  Egyptians at Play: Board Games Across Borders</hi>. London: Bloomsbury.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="crist_et_al_2022" label="Crist et al. 2022"> Walter Crist, Éric Piette,
               Matthew Stephenson, Dennis J. N. J. Soemers, and Cameron Browne. (2022) “Ludus
               Coriovalli: Archaeological and Computational Methods for Examining a Potential Game
               from Roman Limburg”. Presented at the Board Game Studies Colloquium, 16–20 May 2022,
               Leeuwarden, the Netherlands.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="crist_et_al_2024" label="Crist et al. 2024"> Walter Crist, Éric Piette,
               Dennis J. N. J. Soemers, Matthew Stephenson, and Cameron Browne. (2024)
               “Computational Approaches for Recognising and Reconstructing Ancient Games: The Case
               of Ludus Latrunculorum”. In <hi rend="italic">Games in the Ancient World: Places,
                  Spaces, Accessories</hi>, Alessandro Pace, Tim Penn, and Ulrich Schädler (eds.).
               Dremil-Lafage: Mergoil, pp. 63–79.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="crist_et_al_in_press" label="Crist et al in press"> Walter Crist, Eric
               Piette, and Cameron Browne. (in press) “Playing the Games of the Past: Digital Tools
               for Resurrecting Traditional Board Games”. In <hi rend="italic">The Interactive Pasts
                  Conference 3 Proceedings</hi>, Angus Mol, Aris Politopoulos, and Corine Gerritsen
               (eds.). Van Hout: Sidestone Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="dans_mu_2022" label="DANS and Maastricht University 2022"> Data Archiving
               and Networked Services and Maastricht University. (2022) “DataverseNL”. Retrieved
               September 30, 2022 from <ref target="https://dataverse.nl/"
                  >https://dataverse.nl/</ref></bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="davies_1925" label="Davies 1925">Davies, Robert. (1925) “Some Arab Games
               and Puzzles”. <hi rend="italic">Sudan Notes and Records</hi> 8, pp. 137–152.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="dawkins_1976" label="Dawkins 1976">Richard Dawkins. (1976) <hi
                  rend="italic">The Selfish Gene</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="covarrubias_1674" label="Covarrubias 1674">Sebastián de Covarrubias.
               (1674) <hi rend="italic">Tesoro de la lengua castellana, o española</hi>. Madrid:
               Melchor Sanchez. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="de_voogt_1995" label="de Voogt 1995">Alex de Voogt (ed.). (1995) <hi
                  rend="italic">New Approaches to Board Game Research: Asian Origins and Future
                  Perspectives</hi>. Leiden: International Institute for Asian Studies. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="de_voogt_et_al_2013" label="de Voogt et al. 2013">Alex de Voogt,
               Anne-Elizabeth Dunn Vaturi, and Jelmer Eerkens. (2016) “Cultural Transmission in the
               Ancient Near East: Twenty Squares and Fifty-Eight Holes”. <hi rend="italic">Journal
                  of Archaeological Science</hi> 40, pp. 1715–1730.
               https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jas.2012.11.008 </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="dlp_2022" label="Digital Ludeme Project 2022">Digital Ludeme Project.
               (2022) Ludii Games Database Version 1.3.6. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.34894/BP8G8U"
               >https://doi.org/10.34894/BP8G8U</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="fabian_2023" label="Fabian 2023">Tom Fabian. (2023) “The revival of
               traditional games in Central Asia: heritage, spectacle, and ethnos”. In <hi
                  rend="italic">Indigenous, Traditional, and Folk Sports Contesting
               Modernities</hi>, Mariann Vaczi and Alan Bairner (eds.). London: Routledge, pp.
               57–69.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="ferrarese_2005" label="Ferrarese 2005">Stela Maris Ferrarese. (2005) <hi
                  rend="italic">Juegos étnicos de América y documentos sobre educación física
                  intercultural</hi>. Neuquén: Proyecto Rescate e Inserción Comunitaria y Pedagógica
               de los Ancestrales Juegos de los Pueblos Indoamericanos. Finkel 2007 Irving Finkel
               (ed.). (2007) <hi rend="italic">Ancient Board Games in Perspective</hi>. London: The
               British Museum Press.Golladay n.d. Sonja Musser Golladay. (n.d.) “Alfonso X’s Book of
               Games”. Unpublished Manuscript. Translated by Sonja Musser Golladay.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="finkel_2007" label="Finkel 2007">Irving Finkel (ed.). (2007) <title
                  rend="italic">Ancient Board Games in Perspective.</title> London: The British
               Museum Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="golladay_nd" label="Golladay n.d.">Sonja Musser Golladay. (n.d.) <title
                  rend="quotes">Alfonso X’s Book of Games.</title> Unpublished Manuscript.
               Translated by Sonja Musser Golladay.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="kabzinska-stawarz_1991" label="Kabzińska-Stawarz 1991">Iwona
               Kabzińska-Stawarz. (1991) <hi rend="italic">Games of Mongolian Shepherds</hi>.
               Warsaw: Polish Academy of Sciences.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="komariah_salim_2019" label="Komariah and Salim 2019">Imas Komariah, and
               Tamara Adriani Salim. (2019) “Kampoeng Hompimpa: preserving traditional games amidst
               the barrage of online games”. UI Proceedings on Social Science and Humanities
               3.1.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="lane_1836" label="Lane 1836">Edward Lane. (1836) <hi rend="italic">An
                  Account of the Manners and Customs of the Modern Egyptians. </hi>London: John
               Murray.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mackenzie_finkel_2004" label="Mackenzie and Finkel 2004">Colin Mackenzie
               and Irving Finkel (eds.). (2004) <title rend="italic">Asian Games: The Art of
                  Contest.</title> New York: Asia Society.Malaby 2003 Thomas Malaby. (2003) <hi
                  rend="italic">Gambling Life: Dealing in Contingency in a Greek City</hi>.Urbana,
               IL: University of Illinois Press</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="malaby_2003" label="Malaby 2003">Thomas Malaby. (2003) Gambling Life:
               Dealing in Contingency in a Greek City.Urbana, IL: University of Illinois
               Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mayra_2008" label="Mäyrä 2008">Franz Mäyrä. (2008). <title rend="italic"
                  >An Introduction to Game Studies. Games and Culture.</title> London: Sage.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="morenville_piette_in_press" label="Morenville and Piette in press"
               >Morenville, Achille and Éric Piette. In press. “Vers une approche polyvalente pour
               les jeux à information imparfaite sans connaissance de domaine”. <hi rend="italic"
                  >Rencontres des Jeunes Chercheurs en Intelligence Artificielle.</hi></bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mukherjee_2022" label="Mukherjee 2022">Souvik Mujkherjee, (2022). <title
                  rend="italic">Videogames in the Indiabn Subcontinent. Development, Culture(s), and
                  Representations.</title> New Delhi: Bloomsbury.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mukherjee_in_press" label="Mukherjee in press">Souvik Mukherjee. (in
                  press)<hi rend="italic"> Indian boardgames, colonial avatars: transculturation,
                  colonialism and boardgames</hi>. Oldenbourg: De Gruyter</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="murray_1913" label="Murray 1913"> Harold James Ruthven Murray. (1913) <hi
                  rend="italic">A History of Chess</hi>. London: Oxford University Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="murray_1951" label="Murray 1951"> Harold James Ruthven Murray. (1951) <hi
                  rend="italic">A History of Board-Games Other Than Chess</hi>. Oxford: Clarendon
               Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="nieborg_hermes_2008" label="Nieborg and Hermes 2008">Daniel Nieborg and
               Joke Hermes. (2008) What is Game Studies Anyway? <hi rend="italic">European Journal
                  of Cultural Studies</hi> 11, pp. 131–147. https://doi.org/10.1177/1367549407088328 </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="pankhurst_1971" label="Pankhurst 1971">Richard Pankhurst. (1971) “Gabata
               and Related Board Games of Ethiopia and the Horn of Africa”. <hi rend="italic"
                  >Ethiopia Observer</hi> 14, pp. 154–206.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="parker_1909" label="Parker 1909">Henry Parker. (1909) <hi rend="italic"
                  >Ancient Ceylon</hi>. New Delhi: Asian Educational Services.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="parlett_1999" label="Parlett 1999"> David Parlett. (1999) <hi
                  rend="italic">The Oxford History of Board Games</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University
               Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="parlett_2006" label="Parlett 2006">David Parlett. (2006) “What’s a Ludeme?
               And Who Really Invented It?” Retrieved February 21, 2022 from
               https://www.parlettgames.uk/gamester/whatsaludeme.html.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="petrie_1927" label="Petrie 1927">William Matthew Flinders Petrie. (1927)
                  <hi rend="italic">Objects of Daily Use</hi>. London: British School of Archaeology
               in Egypt.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="piccione_1990" label="Piccione 1990">Peter Piccione. (1990) “The
               Historical Development of the Game of Senet and its Significance for Egyptian
               Religion”. Ph.D. Dissertation. University of Chicago, Chicago, IL.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="piette_et_al_2020" label="Piette et al. 2020">Éric Piette, Dennis J. N.
               J. Soemers, Matthew Stephenson, Chiara Sironi, Mark Winands, and Cameron Browne.
               (2020) “Ludii — The Ludemic General Game System”. In <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of
                  the 24th European Conference on Artificial Intelligence (ECAI 2020) Frontiers in
                  Artificial Intelligence and Applications</hi>, pp. 411–418.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="piette_et_al_2021" label="Piette et al. 2021">Éric Piette, Matthew
               Stephenson, Dennis J. N. J. Soemers, and Cameron Browne. (2021) “General Board Game
               Concepts”. <hi rend="italic">In Proceedings of the 2021 IEEE Conference on Games
                  (CoG)</hi>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="piette_et_al_2022" label="Piette et al. 2022">Éric Piette, Lisa Rougetet,
               Walter Crist, Matthew Stephenson, Dennis Soemers, and Cameron Browne (2022). A Ludii
               Analysis of the French Military Game. Presented at the Board Game Studies Colloquium,
               13–16 April 2021, Paris, France.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="piette_et_al_2024" label="Piette et al. 2024">Éric Piette, Walter Crist,
               Dennis J.N.J. Soemers, Lisa Rougetet, Summer Courts, Tim Penn, and Achille Morenville
               (2024) “GameTable COST Action: Kickoff Report”. <hi rend="italic">International
                  Computer Games Association Journal</hi>. https://doi.org/10.3233/ICG-240245</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="royal_netherlands_academy_of_arts_sciences_dutch_research_council_2022"
               label="Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts, Sciences and Dutch Research Council 2022">
               Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts, Sciences, and Dutch Research Council. (2022) “DANS
               Data Archiving and Networked Services”. Retrieved September 30, 2022 from
               https://dans.knaw.nl/en/</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="saglamtimur_2017" label="Sağlamtimur 2017">Haluk Sağlamtimur. (2017)
               “Siirt-Başur Höyük Erken Tunç Çağı I Mezar-ları: Ön rapor". <hi rend="italic"
                  >Arkeoloji Dergisi</hi> 22, pp. 1–18.Schädler 1994 Ulrich Schädler. (1994)
               “Latrunculi — ein verlorenes strategisches Brettspiel der Römer”. <hi rend="italic"
                  >Homo Ludens: Der spielende Mensch</hi> 4, pp. 47–67.</bibl>

            <bibl>Schädler 1994 Ulrich Schädler. (1994) “Latrunculi—ein verlorenes strategisches
               Brettspiel der Römer”. Homo Ludens: Der spielende Mensch 4, pp. 47–67.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="schadler_2021" label="Schädler 2021">Ulrich Schädler. (2021) “Some
               Misconceptions about Ancient Roman Games’. <hi rend="italic">Board Game Studies
               </hi>15: pp. 79–97.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="soemers_et_al_2019" label="Soemers et al. 2019">Dennis J. N. J. Soemers,
               Walter Crist, and Cameron Browne. (2019) “Report on the Digital Ludeme Project”. <hi
                  rend="italic">International Computer Games Association Journal</hi> 41, pp.
               138–142. https://doi.org/10.3233/ICG-190118</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="soemers_et_al_in_press" label="Soemers et al. in press">Dennis J. N. J.
               Soemers, Jakub Kowalski, Éric Piette, Achille Morenville, and Walter Crist. (in
               press) “GameTable Working Group 1 Meeting Reporton Search, Planning, Learning, and
               Explainability”. <hi rend="italic">International Computer Games Association
                  Journal.</hi></bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="sorin_1970" label="Sorin 1970">Raphaël Sorin. (1970) “Les échecs, le go,
               l’écriture”. <hi rend="italic">Le Monde</hi> (3 October 1970), pp. 47–67. Interview
               with Pierre Berloquin.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="stephenson_et_al_2023" label="Stephenson et al. 2023 ">Matthew Stephenson,
               Dennis J. N. J. Soemers, Éric Piette, and Cameron Browne. (2023) “Measuring board
               game distance”. In <hi rend="italic">Computers and Games - International Conference,
                  CG 2022, </hi>Cameron Browne, Akihiro Kishimoto, and Jonathan Schaeffer (eds.).
               Cham: Springer, pp. 121–130. </bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="syed_2020" label="Syed 2020">Renate Syed. (2020) “The Aksadyuta in the
               Mahabharata”. In <hi rend="italic">Playing with the Past: National Conference on
                  Ancient and Medieval Indian Games</hi>, Raamesh Gowri Raghavan and Dnyaneshwari
               Vinayak Kamath (eds.). Mumbai: India Study Centre Trust, pp. 116–129.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="tylor_1879" label="Tylor 1879">Edward Burnett Tylor. (1879) “On the Game
               of Patolli in Ancient Mexico, and Its Probable Asiatic Origin”. <hi rend="italic"
                  >Journal of the Anthropological Institute of Great Britain and Ireland</hi> 8, pp.
               116–129.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="united_nations_2021" label="United Nations 2021">United Nations. (2021)
               “Standard Country or Area Codes for Statistical Use”. Retrieved February 21, 2022
               from https://unstats.un.org/unsd/methodology/m49/</bibl>
         </listBibl>

      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
