<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>
               <q>May the Text Rise up to Meet You</q>: New Ways of Reading Old Manuscripts</title>
            <author>Eugene Lyman</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Eugene <dhq:family>Lyman</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Rhode Island</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>elyman@foundation.uri.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Eugene Lyman is the Associate Dean for Development at the University of Rhode
                     Island Foundation, URI Graduate School of Oceanography.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000058</idno>
            <idno type="volume">003</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2009-09-29">29 September 2009</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace"
                  rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword
                     taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2009-06-16" who="jhf">Initial encoding</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>This poster demonstrates the suite of programs I created for the Society of Early
               English and Norse Electronic Texts (SEENET) to facilitate the display of its
               TEI-compliant documentary and critical editions of medieval texts.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Society of Early
               English and Norse Electronic Texts (SEENET) programs created to facilitate the display of its
               TEI-compliant documentary and critical editions of medieval texts.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Poster Abstract</head>
            <p>Interface design was the uppermost concern when I set out to create a suite of
               programs for the Society of Early English and Norse Electronic Texts (SEENET) to
               facilitate the display of its TEI-compliant documentary and critical editions of
               medieval texts. From its inception, my project has been shaped by the tremendous
               potential of electronic textuality to redefine our experience of what it means to
               possess and read a text. This poster demonstrates these programs and surveys the
               principles that have given rise to their creation. </p>
            <p>The SEENET interface project has been carried out as an iterative process moving
               between (1) identifying the broad parameters of questions that readers might be
               tempted to ask of a text and (2) shaping an electronic <foreign xml:lang="fr">mise en
                  page</foreign> that will engage a reader’s inquisitive eye, promoting curiosity
               and thus the development of new insight and knowledge. The process of developing such
               an interface has led to the articulation of a set of axioms that have guided my work:
                  <list type="unordered">
                  <item>Seek tight coordination in the display of text and facsimile image</item>
                  <item> Incorporate visual cueing to guide/reinforce reader attention</item>
                  <item> Provide unobtrusive, but handy, analytical tools</item>
                  <item> Promote ease of navigation – build in linkages that are likely to answer
                     and/or provoke a reader’s curiosity</item>
                  <item> Work in one visual space for text and images – no windows or frames, no
                     scrolling when possible</item>
                  <item> Supply information at likely points of need – avoid overload, expose what
                     the text <q>knows</q> selectively</item>
                  <item> Keep decoration to a minimum: no chrome, don’t frame the view, don’t let
                     the tools distract or overwhelm.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p> In addition to demonstrating programs designed to display documentary and critical
               editions of Piers Plowman (which serves as the locus for all examples shown), the
               poster describes programs written to permit electronic markup of facsimile images of
               the medieval manuscripts as well as programs that assist editors in the TEI-compliant
               markup of documentary and critical texts. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Poster</head>
            <p>Download <ref target="resources/images/figure01.pdf">poster</ref> (PDF file) <graphic
                  url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
