<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Tracing <q>Toxicity</q> Through Code: Towards a
               Method of Explainability and Interpretability in Software</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>David M. <dhq:family>Berry</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7737-5586</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Sussex</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>d.m.berry@sussex.ac.uk</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>David M. Berry is Professor of Digital Humanities at the University of Sussex.
                     His most recent book is <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities: Knowledge and
                        Critique in a Digital Age</title>. His forthcoming research examines the
                     Idea of a Digital University. He is now working on early AI as part of a
                     collaborative international research project examining the recently unearthed
                     original ELIZA source-code, its cultural significance, and the emergence of the
                     Chatbot.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000706</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->017</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->2</idno>
            <date/>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>explainability</item>
                  <item>algorithms</item>
                  <item>Critical Code Studies</item>
                  <item>Software Studies</item>
                  <item>Digital Humanities</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000706/000706.xml"
               >GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>The ubiquity of digital technologies in citizen’s lives marks a major qualitative
               shift where automated decisions taken by algorithms deeply affect the lived
               experience of citizens. This has created many new social experiences and improved
               contemporary life. However, a lack of public understanding of how algorithms work
               also makes them a source of distrust, especially concerning the way in which they can
               be used to create frames or channels for social and individual behaviour. This public
               concern has been magnified by election hacking, social media disinformation, data
               extractivism, and a sense that Silicon Valley companies are out of control. The wide
               adoption of algorithms into so many aspects of peoples’ lives, often without public
               debate, has meant that increasingly algorithms are seen as mysterious and opaque,
               when they are not seen as inequitable or biased. Up until recently it has been
               difficult to challenge algorithms or to question their functioning, especially with
               wide acceptance that software’s inner workings were incomprehensible, proprietary or
               secret (cf. open source). Asking why an algorithm did what it did often was not
               thought particularly interesting outside of a strictly programming context. This
               meant that there has been a widening explanatory gap in relation to understanding
               algorithms and their effect on peoples’ lived experiences. This paper argues that
               Critical Code Studies offers a novel field for developing theoretical and code-based
               practices to reflect on the explanatory deficit in modern societies from a reliance
               on information technologies. The challenge of new forms of social obscurity from the
               implementation of technical systems is heightened by the example of machine learning
               systems that have emerged in the past decade. A key methodological contribution of
               this paper is to show how concept formation can be traced through key categories and
               classifications deployed in code structures (e.g. modularity and layering software)
               but also how these classifications can appear more stable than they actually are by
               the tendency of software layers to obscure even as it reveals. Using this broadened
               notion of explainability, it argues that critical code studies can make important
               theoretical and methodological contributions of to digital humanities, computer
               science and related disciplines.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>The software explanability deficit in modern societies can be addressed in part by
               tracing concept formation through code structures.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>In the past decade, due to the perceived lack of accountability of algorithmic
               systems, particularly automated decision systems, a new explanatory demand has
               crystallized in an important critique of computational opaqueness and new forms of
               technical transparency called <q>explainability.</q> We see this, for example, in
               challenges to facial recognition technologies, public unease with algorithmic
               judicial systems and other automated decision systems. There have been new regulatory
               attempts to capture some of the ideas that stem from explainability such as the
                  <title rend="italic">Algorithmic Accountability Act 2022</title> in the US, and
               the <title rend="italic">General Data Protection Regulation 2016/679</title> (GDPR)
               in the European Union. These forms of regulation mandate a requirement for a user of
               algorithms to be able to seek a representation (or <q>explanation</q>) of an
               algorithm used in an automated decision by a computer system and that the developers
               should provide one (see <ptr target="#goodman2017"/>, <ptr target="#lum2021"/>, <ptr
                  target="#selbst2017"/>, cf <ptr target="#wachter2017"/>). These are important
               issues and are changing the way in which algorithms are designed and
                  implemented.<note> In relation to these requirements, it is interesting to
                  contrast the notion of <q>explainability,</q> which is intended to create
                  explanations, with the notion of <quote rend="inline">observability</quote>
                  developed by <ptr target="#rieder2020"/>. They argue that <quote rend="inline"
                     >observability emphasises the conditions for the practice of observing in a
                     given domain…. We therefore position observability as an explicit means of, not
                     an alternative to regulation</quote>
                  <ptr target="#rieder2020" loc="3–10"/>. In this paper, I seek to explicitly link
                  explainability to critique, so whereas <q>observability</q> is offered as an
                  administrative concept, I aim to use explainability as a critical concept (see
                  also footnote 4). </note>
            </p>
            <p>This public concern has been magnified by election hacking, social media
               disinformation, data extractivism, and a sense that Silicon Valley companies are out
               of control. The wide adoption of algorithms into so many aspects of peoples’ lives,
               often without public debate, has meant that increasingly algorithms are seen as
               mysterious and opaque, when they are not seen as inequitable or biased. Up until
               recently it has been difficult to challenge algorithms or to question their
               functioning, especially with wide acceptance that software’s inner workings were
               incomprehensible, proprietary or secret (cf. <ptr target="#berry2008"/>
               regarding open source). Asking why an algorithm did what it did was often not thought
               to be particularly interesting outside of a strictly programming context. This meant
               that there has been a widening explanatory gap in relation to
               understanding algorithms and their effect on peoples’ lived experiences.<note>The
                  example of this is the <q>mutant algorithm</q> described by Boris Johnson in the
                  case of UK students’ exam results showing the gap between expectation and output
                  from algorithms (see <ptr target="#coughlan2020"/>).</note>
            </p>
            <p>However, in this paper rather than focus on the regulative aspect, I want to use the
               insights of critical code studies to explore how the code itself might usefully be
               analysed in situ, rather than through a secondary representation created by an
                  <q>explainable</q> black-box.<note> Many of the explainability systems currently
                  under development are actually interpretative automated systems, often using
                  machine-learning themselves, to create explainable products that can be presented
                  to a user. This raises the interesting question of a double hermeneutic when
                  understanding as not one but two black-boxes are in evidence, with the explainable
                  system itself not subject to explanation itself. See for example <ref
                     target="https://fetch.ai">https://fetch.ai</ref>
               </note> Explainability is a key new area of research within the fields of artificial
               intelligence and machine-learning and argues that a computational system should be
               able to provide an explanation for an automated decision. This has become known as
               the problem of explainability for artificial intelligence research and has led to the
               emergence of the subfield of Explainable Artificial Intelligence (XAI) (see also <ptr
                  target="#darpa"/>, <ptr target="#sample2017"/>, <ptr target="#kuang2017"/>). There
               has been an important theoretical distinction within this field of explainability
               between the notions of <term>explanation</term> and <term>interpretation</term>. An
               interpretable system can be understood as designed as a human-readable system from
               the bottom up. This often uses <q>simple</q> models, straightforward calculations or
               filtering which can be communicated easily. In contrast, an explainable system is a
               system that incorporates a secondary automated system, usually using machine
               learning, to machine-read and model the primary system, and thereby to provide an
               explanation of how this system works. Explainability has therefore emerged as a term
               that usually seeks to close an explanatory gap by means of responses generated by
               technology itself. As Rudin argues, <quote rend="inline">the field of
                  interpretability / explainability / comprehensibility / transparency in machine
                  learning has strayed away from the needs of real problems…. Recent work on
                  explainability of black boxes – rather than interpretability of models – contains
                  and perpetuates critical misconceptions that have generally gone unnoticed, but
                  that can have a lasting negative impact on the widespread use of machine learning
                  models in society</quote>
               <ptr target="#rudin2019" loc="2"/>. Indeed, I argue that the idea of a technological
               response to an interpretability problem is doomed to failure while explainability is
               understood through such narrow technical criteria and instead requires
               interdisciplinary approaches.</p>
            <p>The aim in this paper is to develop the insights developed through critical code
               studies which uses methods of interpretation and close reading of the code to
               contribute to re-thinking the notion of explainability by looking at a case study. In
               this paper I use <term>explainability</term> to gesture towards a method of tracing
               the underlying mechanisms and interactions within software towards an explanation of
               the functioning of the code. Within artificial intelligence, explainability is
               sometimes explicitly linked to automated processes of producing explanations, whereas
               interpretability is linked to human-readable code that is easily understood by a
               human programmer. In both cases an explanation is sought, so here I prefer to use the
               term <term>explainability</term> as a critical method for seeking an explanation, and
               highlight <q>automated explainability</q> where this is undertaken by software
               (Explainable AI). This can be usefully compared with <term>interpretability</term> as
               the use of a model for the code that is explicitly written to be easily read and
               understood by humans (Interpretable AI) (see <ptr target="#rudin2019"/>). Broadly
               speaking, explainability has tended to become an automated approach, and here I want
               to argue that if it were re-articulated through the concept of interpretability it
               could become a strong analytical method for reading computer code critically. I also
               hope to show that critical code studies and explainability are ways of thinking about
               the digital and computation that would be extremely useful for digital humanities
               more widely but also for STEM education and computer science more generally (see also
                  <ptr target="#marino2020" loc="230"/>).<note> For an interesting discussion of the
                  value of the social sciences and interpretation to computer science see Connolly
                  2020. </note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>1. Theoretical Context</head>
            <p>In this paper, therefore, I seek to widen its applicability through Critical Code
               Studies and in doing so, to create connections to ideas of explanation, the paratextual<note>
                  <date when="2022-11-02T16:38:29Z"/>changed here and elsewhere from
                  extra-functional to avoid namespace confusion</note> of computer source code, and
               the value of close-reading code as an explanatory approach. By the paratextual
               elements I am gesturing to the importance of a more capacious notion of source code
               that includes documentation, commentary, blog-posts and even social media related to
               the code. In this case I look at the <title rend="quotes">WIT Toxicity Text Model
                  Comparison</title> (What-If-Tool) developed by Jigsaw and Google (both units
               within Alphabet) that aims to classify <q>toxic text</q> in a dataset and which
               contains a remarkable normative structure incorporated into its algorithms.<note>
                  Jigsaw <quote rend="inline">is a unit within Google that explores threats to open
                     societies, and builds technology that inspires scalable solutions</quote>
                  <ptr target="#jigsaw2021"/>. </note>
            </p>
            <p>Within the code that I examine in this paper, the notion of <q>toxic</q> and
                  <q>toxicity</q> and the relation of these words to their deployment in software
               are crucial for this analysis. By using approaches from critical code studies, the
               aim is to help explain how a machine learning model can classify <q>toxicity</q> by
               tracing the concept through layers of software, the so-called software stack, by
               close attention to the source code serves as a document of its usage.<note> The word
                     <q>toxic</q> is commonly defined as <q>poisonous</q> and <quote rend="inline"
                     >first appeared in English in the mid-seventeenth century from the medieval
                     Latin toxicus, meaning <q>poisoned</q> or <q>imbued with poison</q></quote>
                  <ptr target="#oup2018"/>. As Oxford Languages go on to explain, <quote
                     rend="inline">the medieval Latin term was in turn borrowed from the
                     Latin toxicum, meaning <q>poison</q>, which has its origins in the
                     Greek toxikon pharmakon – lethal poison used by the ancient Greeks for smearing
                     on the points of their arrows. Interestingly, it is not pharmakon, the word for
                     poison, that made the leap into Latin here, but toxikon, which comes from the
                     Greek word for <q>bow</q>, toxon</quote>
                  <ptr target="#oup2018"/>.</note> The is that code can be made explainable by
               tracing concepts through a close reading of the source code. </p>
            <p>Critical code studies has been developed and supported by a range of scholars working
               particularly at the level of code to attempt to apply humanistic interpretative
               approaches to the study of the source code in computer systems.<note> In providing
                  explanations of code, software and algorithms, and more generally in the case of
                  computational systems and platforms, the differing ways of presenting these
                  descriptions is reminiscent of the <q>Rashomon Effect</q> used in computer science
                  to discuss the <quote rend="inline">multitude of different descriptions</quote>
                  presented by models (see <ptr target="#breiman2001"/>). The use of a cultural
                  artefact, in this case Rashomon, a Japanese film from 1950, directed by Akira
                  Kurosawa, as an explanatory device in statistics and computer science is itself
                  fascinating, although outside the scope of this paper. </note> One of the latest
               examples of this is Mark Marino’s <title rend="italic">Critical Code Studies</title>
               which includes a number of examples of reading source code in practice <ptr
                  target="#marino2020"/>. He writes,</p>
            <cit><quote rend="block">in our digital moment, there is a growing sense of the
                  significance of computer source code. It has moved beyond the realm of programmers
                  and entered the realm of mainstream media and partisan political blogosphere.
                  Those discussing code may not be programmers or have much fluency in the languages
                  of the code they are quoting, but they are using it to make, refute, and start
                  arguments. There is also a growing sense that the code we are not reading is
                  working against our interests.</quote>
               <ptr target="#marino2020" loc="3"/></cit>
            <p>Marino’s approach foregrounds the use of case studies and close reading of the code
               to develop a number of strategies drawn from the humanities for understanding code.
               Indeed, he argues critical code studies <quote rend="inline">was born of the
                  humanities</quote>
               <ptr target="#marino2020" loc="228"/>. Essentially Marino foregrounds the importance
               of <quote rend="inline">understanding</quote> and exegesis for this approach <ptr
                  target="#marino2020" loc="20, 237"/>. </p>
            <p>I would like to start with a discussion of this theoretical approach inasmuch as when
               we come to understand computer source code we are immediately faced with a dilemma in
               terms of a reading which is attentive to this interpretative dimension together with
               the explanatory aspect. In a sense I want to present a double aspect theory in
               relation to computer source code, in particular the way in which it is both a
               casual-deterministic mode of what we might call mechanical agency, and its
               interpretative mode of textuality. Marino highlights the understanding applied
               through approaches which privilege the interpretative dimension, but I argue it is
               crucial that we are able to move between these two aspects (explanatory/
               interpretative) if we are to provide a full account of computer code. This is also a
               useful distinction to make if we are to make sense of the current debates over
               explainability. We might note that a broadly interpretative approach which focuses on
               case studies may lose the explanatory aspect of the mechanical operation of computer
               code. In other words, it might lose the value of explaining why code has the
               structure it does and why a particular computer language has the value it does for
               its programmers, which could be its effective or expressive potentialities, for
               example. </p>
            <p>In contrast I would like to use a <emph>realist</emph> notion of computer code, which
               involves an attempt to describe the real structures, entities, and processes that
               make up computer code and which exist independently of our descriptions of them. So,
               we should be attentive to the tendencies that emerge from the causal power of
               entities, structures, and mechanisms. That is, to focus on the real, operative
               mechanisms which may or may not produce observable results. This is because computer
               source code consists of a number of sub-systems which draw on a <quote rend="inline"
                  >multiplicity of casual mechanisms at work at any time</quote> and can be
               explained through a broadly realist explanatory framework <ptr
                  target="#outhwaite1987" loc="175"/>. This opens up a number of useful complements
               to interpretative approaches to understanding code because it allows reference to
               unobservable entities which go beyond our direct experience, and which therefore help
               to demonstrate the existence of non-obvious determinations of observable events
               within code in operation, or which can be inferred from the inclusions or references
               of programmers to paratexts in the code. This is not to descend into metaphysics,
               indeed one should follow the advice of Whitehead and avoid <quote rend="inline"
                  >misplaced concreteness,</quote> that is, to too easily assume that concepts are
               entities that are unproblematically in existence. Here we might follow <ptr
                  target="#hacking1983" loc="27"/> and distinguish between <quote rend="inline"
                  >realism about theories from realism about entities</quote>
               <ptr target="#outhwaite1987" loc="178"/>. As Outhwaite explains, <quote rend="inline"
                  >to put it a bit crudely, true theories state what is the case. A realism about
                  entities simply asserts that some thing or things exist</quote>
               <ptr target="#outhwaite1987" loc="178"/>. In avoiding the notion of determinate
               entities we instead focus on the provisional understanding of computational
               structures and mechanisms. So that the practices of computer programmers and users
               cannot be understood except in terms of the computational structures within which
               they participate. This is to highlight how the explanatory dimension of computer code
               can usefully contribute to <q>filling out</q> interpretative textual approaches to
               understanding code. </p>
            <p>In terms of understanding a particular case study of computer code, I therefore argue
               that we would need to include in any account of source code the explanatory layers
               that might be found upstream from the code under investigation. Not so much
               black-boxes as obscure networks of code which are formed from the social and economic
               factors (or para-textual elements) which surround code. This includes both networks
               in a technical sense, as the code is structured into self-standing objects, functions
               and applications, but also in a social sense, especially in terms of the social
               networks that are important in creating and maintaining the code in operation. These
               can be thought of as the infrastructures of code. These are instantiated within
               computational frameworks, operating system structures, data structures, language
               constraints, hardware specificities, or any number of wider sociological structures
               that might be not observable directly but which are sedimented within code downstream
               from these larger structural frameworks or the code situation with which we are
               working. Clearly, in this case <quote rend="inline">the nature of the object should
                  determine the most appropriate methods of investigation</quote> in terms of the
               whether one attempts to determine micro or macro studies in relation to it <ptr
                  target="#outhwaite1987" loc="182"/>. This brings forward the importance of the
               selection made as a researcher and the reflexivity that should be foregrounded in any
               analysis of critical code study. </p>
            <p>Additionally, it is crucial to understand the conditions of action and the goals
               towards which a particular piece of code is aimed. The <q>conditions</q> or
                  <q>goals</q> may be defined as givens. If directed by a project or work situation
               these may often be fixed, unexaminable or relatively unchangeable. These conditions
               or goals defined as givens will therefore variously limit and constrain the resultant
               focus of the code and may impact directly the language choice, framework, approach
               and dependencies used. They can usually be discerned in the surrounding documentation
               of code or in the comments where programmers often highlight the direction of
               processing and its intended function. Indeed, sometimes programmers may express their
               feeling or complain about the code quite explicitly if they feel constrained by the
               framework or language choice foisted upon them (see <ptr target="#berry2011" loc="69"
               />). Some organisations also have a <q>house style</q> of code, which guides the
               choice of words representing variables, capitalisation, functional relations (e.g.,
               internal libraries and dependencies), commenting practices and even the formatting of
               the code. This may be an established or published naming and coding standard within
               an organisation. But any bureaucratic discipline laid on the coding practices and
               source-code format is grounded in the expectation of resistance. Indeed, source code
               can sometimes reveal the pressures between technical practice and bureaucratic
               limitation, most notably expressed in the comments sections, or sometimes in variable
               naming. However, if the code produced is too much at variance with the style or
               practices of an organisation then there can be a <q>return of the repressed</q> in
               which the repressed element of the freedom of the programmer in a <q>house style</q>
               may manifest itself in idiosyncratic code or resistance expressed in the coding (see
                  <ptr target="#berry2011" loc="68–70"/>). Indeed, the fundamental repression on
               which bureaucratic organisations are based on, in terms of standardisation and
               process management, may surface when programmers stray too far from the limits set by
               organisations and result in heavy-handed responses including possible expulsion of
               the programmer from a project, or even their termination of employment. Hence, to
               avoid conflict in technical work such as programming a certain degree of autonomy
               tends to be present and the bureaucratic concern with the software may leave the
               technical process to the programmer and confine judgement to the appraisal of the
               final code product. By the means of assessment by result, normal bureaucratic
               management can be maintained over software development. This is helpful for critical
               code studies as within the source code there can often be traces left behind which
               give clues as to the way in which a particular algorithm was formulated, the
               assumptions or limitations of the code, and occasionally the conflictual aspects of
               code-writing which are documented in comments. </p>
            <p>Within the source code although we can sometimes observe this conflict play out, but
               more often code is presented in the form of a prosaic matter-of-factness stripped of
               its individuality. It has, so to speak, been painted grey in grey, as Hegel observed
               about uncreative philosophy. This common style in programming, which we might call
                  <q>coding from nowhere</q> is seen where code is presented as apolitical,
               disinterested and placed <q>above struggle.</q> Many examples of this can be seen in
               open source and free software projects where the values of the project may be more
               easily observed in the code, documentation and debates that are often freely
               available to examine on mailing lists and social media (see <ptr target="#berry2008"
               />). As we will see in the case of the code later examined in this paper, although a
               technical project might aim to align with the interests, values and goals of society
               in terms of notions of communicative discussion free from domination, which in this
               case they define as <q>toxicity,</q> close reading the code demonstrates the devotion
               of the programmers to the development of means and instruments. By focussing on
               technical means they thereby repress the ends and morality they purport to support.
               Indeed, in this case the code acts to automate the processes of judgement over the
                  <q>toxicity</q> of online discussions creating abstractions and a misplaced
               concreteness which results in a simplistic binary characterisation of discourse. That
               is, the models either find a comment toxic or not toxic. This process of technical
               hollowing out of the ends is also apparent in the processes of debiasing one of the
               text models, by application of a set of weightings on crowd-sourced judgements
               self-declared identity characteristics, in an attempt to normalise model judgements.
               The technical regress this opens up is clear when one asks <q>who debiases the
                  debiasers?</q><note> An attempt to deal with this regress was the Civil Comments
                  project which used peer-review of human moderators to manage the process of
                  preventing uncivil commenting in a discussion. However, as they observed, <quote
                     rend="inline">as much as everyone might like to see higher-quality, less-toxic
                     comments on their favorite news sites, the reality is that the number of sites
                     willing and able to pay for comments software of any quality is not large, or
                     growing</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bogdanoff2017"/>. Revealingly this project folded as although
                  everyone claims to want better quality online discussions few are willing to pay
                  for it <ptr target="#bogdanoff2017"/>. Nonetheless Civil Comments chose to make
                  their ~2m public comments from their platform available in an open archive
                  available at <ref target="https://figshare.com/articles/dataset/data_json/7376747"
                     >https://figshare.com/articles/dataset/data_json/7376747</ref> . See also Coral
                  for another project with similar aims, <ref target="https://coralproject.net"
                     >https://coralproject.net</ref>
               </note> A question, incidentally that the system builders do not tend to ask.<note>
                  One way in which the datasets are debiased is by running competitions, such as the
                  Jigsaw Unintended Bias in Toxicity Classification Challenge where an open
                  competition is run over to stages with an award of $65,000 split over four prizes
                  to the <q>best</q> algorithms that debiase data. The challenge states, <quote
                     rend="inline">you're challenged to build a model that recognizes toxicity and
                     minimizes this type of unintended bias with respect to mentions of
                     identities,</quote> see <ref
                     target="https://www.kaggle.com/c/jigsaw-unintended-bias-in-toxicity-classification/overview"
                     >https://www.kaggle.com/c/jigsaw-unintended-bias-in-toxicity-classification/overview</ref>
               </note> To paraphrase György Lukács, who sarcastically lampooned the debates of the
               Frankfurt School philosophers in the 1930s who would build critical theories whilst
               enjoying a privileged economic condition, we might say that machine learning is
               similarly a beautiful hotel, equipped with every comfort, on the edge of an abyss, of
               nothingness, of absurdity. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>2. Reading Code</head>
            <p>I now want to turn from this theoretical and methodological discussion to look at how
               these insights might inform a realist critical code studies reading of code. The aim
               is to think about the way in which a notion of explainability can be incorporated
               into a reading of a source code corpus. Due to limitations of space, I narrow the
               focus to look at an explanation of how <q>toxicity</q> itself is deployed and
               understood in the code under review. To do this I look at the <title rend="quotes"
                  >What-If Tool toxicity text model comparison</title> text-processing project.<note>
                  <ref
                     target="https://colab.research.google.com/github/pair-code/what-if-tool/blob/master/WIT_Toxicity_Text_Model_Comparison.ipynb#scrollTo=UiNxsd4_q9wq"
                     >https://colab.research.google.com/github/pair-code/what-if-tool/blob/master/WIT_Toxicity_Text_Model_Comparison.ipynb#scrollTo=UiNxsd4_q9wq</ref></note>
               This uses a tool developed by Google, called the <title rend="quotes">What-if
                  Tool</title>, that allows a user to,</p>
            <cit><quote rend="block">test performance in hypothetical situations, analyze the
                  importance of different data features, and visualize model behavior across
                  multiple models and subsets of input data, and for different ML fairness metrics.
                  </quote><ptr target="#wit"/></cit>
            <p>The <title rend="quotes">What-if Tool</title> offers a <quote rend="inline">range of
                  interactive visualizations and guided explorations of a TensorFlow model, allowing
                  developers to explore how their model interpreted its training data and how subtle
                  changes to a given input would change its classification</quote>
               <ptr target="#leetaru2019"/>. The WIT Toxicity Text Model Comparison (TTMC) uses this
                  <title rend="quotes">What-if Tool</title> to <quote rend="inline">compare two text
                  models from ConversationAI that determine sentence toxicity, one of which has had
                  some debiasing performed during training</quote>
               <ptr target="#ttmc2021"/>. This is quite a complex piece of software, drawing on a
               number of libraries and data sources, and applied to the wikipedia comments
                  dataset.<note> Text processing involves mechanical processing of text data to
                  classify it in particular ways. This is different to text understanding which
                  seeks to provide an understanding of the meaning within textual materials. In the
                  code discussed here, the aim is the mechanical identification of <q>toxicity</q>
                  rather than understanding it within context. </note> This dataset is a tsv files
               which includes over <quote rend="inline">100k labeled discussion comments from
                  English Wikipedia. Each comment was labeled by multiple annotators via Crowdflower
                  on whether it is a toxic or healthy contribution</quote>
               <ptr target="#wikipediatalklabels2021"/>. <note> A tsv file is a tab-separated values
                  (TSV) file which is a simple text format for storing data in a tabular structure,
                  for example, database table or spreadsheet data, so that it can be transferred
                  between different programs or systems. In a tsv file each record in a source table
                  or database record is represented as one line of the text file. The TSV files are
                  similar to CSV files but use tabs instead of commas to separate the data.</note>
               Essentially this is a dataset with labelling using a machine learning model trained
               by crowd-sourced using a simple machine learning classifier based on a set of 4053
               people being asked whether a comment on Wikipedia contained a personal attack or
               harassment <ptr target="#wulczyn2017" loc="2"/>.<note> See also <ptr
                     target="#wulczyn2016"/> for the <title rend="quotes">Wikipedia Talk Labels:
                     Personal Attacks</title> dataset. </note> This was enumerated in one of five
               sub questions for classification by the programmers, see figure 1. </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure01">
               <head>The question posed to Crowdflower annotators (<ptr
                     target="#toxicityquestion2017"/>, <ptr target="#wulczyn2017"/>)</head>
               <figDesc>Screenshot of question <quote rend="inline">Does the comment contain a
                     personal attack or harrassment?</quote> with five response options.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>It is important to note that the machine learning model applied to the wikipedia
               comments dataset by Crowdflower is different from the ones tested in the TTMC tool.
               Crucially it is the result of a different crowd-sourcing process and therefore the
               concept of <q>toxic</q> in the dataset is different to the concept of <q>toxic</q>
               used in the TTMC. Nonetheless the Crowdflower toxicity classification is left as a
               trace, or data field, in the dataset tsv file. This Crowdflower toxicity
               classification is then utilised in the TTMC tool as a static value so that it can be
               compared to the other models it compares. Although complex, understanding the
               different ways in which <q>toxicity</q> is being algorithmically produced as a value
               is an important part of making an explanatory account of this code. </p>
            <p>The WIT Toxicity Text Model Comparison is hosted on the Google Colab or Colaboratory
               which is a free Jupyter notebook environment that runs in the cloud on a browser and
               stores its notebooks on Google Drive. Jupyter Notebook is a web-based interactive
               computational environment for creating and running notebook documents, which are
               browser-based <q>REPL</q> (Read–eval–print loops) containing <quote rend="inline">an
                  ordered list of input/output cells and which can contain code, text, mathematics,
                  plots and rich media</quote>
               <ptr target="#wikipedia2021"/>. This environment allows the development of code in an
               interactive fashion and has become very popular as a way of doing data science and
               other programming activities which are exploratory. The ease with which a Jupyter
               notebook can work with data and code allows a program to be viewed, edited and run in
               real-time to test ideas. This means that it is an ideal environment for facilitating
               critical code studies projects. </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure02">
               <head>The What-If Tool Data Visualiser</head>
               <figDesc>Screenshot of dataviz interface with configuration on left and scatterplot
                  on right.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The main part of the analysis of the WIT Toxicity Text Model Comparison compares two
               models drawn from ConversationAI, an <quote rend="inline">initiative to protect
                  voices in conversation,</quote> to apply to the Wikipedia comments dataset.
               ConversationAI claims to develop tools so that <quote rend="inline">globally, fewer
                  people are silenced and more people are able to safely engage in good faith
                  discussion online.</quote><note> The project presents its values as: Community:
                  Communities should responsibly shape their discussions; Transparency: Open
                  processes enable better outcomes and trust; Inclusivity: Diverse points of view
                  make discussions better; Privacy: We are privacy conscious in design and
                  execution; Topic-neutral: Good faith discussion can happen on controversial topics
                     <ptr target="#conversationai2021a"/>.</note> They further argue that their team
                  <quote rend="inline">leads as an example of ethical practices in building
                  technology</quote>
               <ptr target="#conversationai2021a"/>.<note> ConversationAI is made up of three main
                  parts, (1) Perspective API which <quote rend="inline">API uses machine learning to
                     analyze a string of text and predict the perceived impact it might have on a
                     conversation,</quote> (2) Tune, which is a <quote rend="inline">Chrome
                     extension that helps people adjust the level of toxicity they see in comments
                     across the internet,</quote> and (3) Moderator, which is <quote rend="inline"
                     >an open-source tool that uses machine learning to help moderators identify and
                     reduce toxicity in forums and comment sections</quote>
                  <ptr target="#conversationai2021a"/>.</note> ConversationAI is developed by Jigsaw
               and the Google Counter-Abuse Technology Team and hosted on GitHub.</p>
            <p>The two main pre-trained models used in the analysis are cnn_wiki_tox_v3_model.h5 and
                  cnn_debias_tox_v3_model.h5.<note> See <ref
                     target="https://storage.googleapis.com/what-if-tool-resources/computefest2019/cnn_wiki_tox_v3_model.h5"
                     >https://storage.googleapis.com/what-if-tool-resources/computefest2019/cnn_wiki_tox_v3_model.h5</ref>
                  and <ref
                     target="https://storage.googleapis.com/what-if-tool-resources/computefest2019/cnn_debias_tox_v3_model.h5"
                     >https://storage.googleapis.com/what-if-tool-resources/computefest2019/cnn_debias_tox_v3_model.h5</ref>
               </note> The latter has had debiasing performed during its training. Both models are
               convolutional neural network models, accessed using the Kera open-source software
               library (see <ptr target="#liu2019"/> for a comprehensive explanation of generating
               models from sentence templates).<note> A good overview of convolutional neural
                  network models can be found at <ref
                     target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convolutional_neural_network"
                     >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convolutional_neural_network</ref>
               </note> CNNs work by modelling animal visual perception, and can therefore be applied
               to automatic recognition of patterns. CNNs are made up of multiple layers of
               individual software sensory neurons (so-called receptive fields, which are made up of
               clusters of these neurons). The word <q>convolution</q> comes from its use to
               describe a mathematical operation on two functions which produces a third function.
               These models were created for the Computefest 2019 conference using a set of Sentence
               Templates datasets developed by Jigsaw which have been <quote rend="inline">generated
                  by plugging identity terms, occupations, and modifiers into a set of templates,
                  e.g., <q>I am a &lt;modifier&gt; &lt;identity&gt;,</q> to form test
                  sentences.</quote> They claim that <quote rend="inline">As only the identity term
                  varies, examples using the same template — e.g., <said>I am a kind American</said>
                  and <said>I am a kind Muslim</said> — should return similar toxicity scores.
                  Scores that vary significantly may indicate identity term bias within the
                  model</quote>
               <ptr target="#vasserman2021"/>. As can already be seen from this initial simple
               mapping of the software, there are a number of complex dependencies between the
               software being looked at, namely the WIT Toxicity Text Model Comparison, and the way
               in which it draws on a software toolet, (the What-If Tool), other models
               (ConversationAI), Sentence Templates (Jigsaw), software libraries (Keras), and
               datasets shared on figshare (Wikipedia Talk Labels). </p>
            <p>In developing a notion of explainability that considers the specificity of software
               system design and operation we can draw from Manovich’s principles of new media which
               he outlines as (1) numerical representation, (2) modularity, (3) automation, (4)
               variability and (5) transcoding <ptr target="#manovich2001" loc="27–48"/>. In reading
               the TTMC code I want to particularly focus on the principle of modularity to help
               trace concepts. Complex software such as the TTMC is often built on a number of
               layers which can be understood as akin to a building, with higher levels of the code
               resting on lower levels until eventually a key foundational level might be discerned.
               This forms part of the practice of well-structured modularity in code that enables
               software abstraction to be used whilst also simplifying complexity and creating more
               maintainable code bases. A key methodological practice I want to use here is the
               tracing of a fundamental organising concept used, often unproblematically in higher
               levels of the code, back to its original specification or construction. This is made
               easier in well-structured code as the different layers of the software can be
               understood as distinct and performing low-, mid-, or high-level processing functions.
               Using this modular principle in the interpretative practice can help explain the code
               functioning and provide a method for tracing conceptual usage within and across
               software. </p>
            <p>In the case of TTMC, the code level at which the comparison tool is accessed directly
               makes use of a key framing concept and deploys it in its code operations which are
               then spread horizontally and vertically through the source code. Due to limitations
               of space I can only give limited textual examples from the source code, but my aim is
               to trace how toxicity becomes instantiated within the code, losing its nuance and
               context. By allowing the constellation of code, libraries and data formed around it
               to reify it into a thing that can be calculated and used to test other textual
               discourse we are able to see how a social concept becomes concretised into a
               technical concept of <q>toxicity.</q> The first place we see the introduction of this
               concept is within the form <quote rend="inline">Read the dataset from CSV and process
                  it for model</quote> in the code cells of the TTMC, </p>
            <eg lang="code-general"><![CDATA[# Read the dataset from the provided CSV and print out information about it.
df = pd.read_csv(csv_path, names=csv_columns, skipinitialspace=True)
df = df[['is_toxic', 'comment']]]]></eg>

            <p>This code simply reads in the data from the wiki dataset and adds it to a
               dataframe(df).</p>

            <eg lang="code-general"><![CDATA[label_column = 'is_toxic'
make_label_column_numeric(df, label_column, lambda val: val)]]></eg>

            <p>This is then labelled and turned into a numeric field as <q>is_toxic</q> is a value
               either 0 or 1. This is drawn from the Wikipedia Comments Corpus and available on
               Figshare <ptr target="#wikipediatalklabels2021"/>.<note> To generate the Wikipedia
                  Comments Corpus made up of discussion comments, <ptr target="#wulczyn2017"/>
                  processed a public dump of the full history of English Wikipedia. The corpus
                  contains 63 million comments from discussions relating to user pages and articles
                  dating from 2004-2015. They used human annotators and machine learning to classify
                  comments to identify certain forms of behaviour to understand with the aim of
                  reducing the level of what they describe as <quote rend="inline">toxic
                     discussions</quote> in online fora <ptr target="#wulczyn2017"/>. Toxicity in
                  this work is linked to user behaviour, and each user is assigned a <quote
                     rend="inline">toxicity level</quote> used to understand and predict user
                  behaviour. </note> It is important to note that in this corpus the problem of
               identifying personal attacks is treated as a binary text classification problem, </p>
            <quote rend="block">toxicity: Indicator variable for whether the worker thought the
               comment is toxic. The annotation takes on the value 1 if the worker considered the
               comment toxic (i.e worker gave a toxicity_score less than 0) and value 0 if the
               worker considered the comment neutral or healthy (i.e worker gave a toxicity_score
               greater or equal to 0). Takes on values in {0, 1}. (<ptr target="#detox2021"/>, <ptr
                  target="#toxicityquestion2017"/>)</quote>
            <p>We should note that the toxicity defined from the wiki dataset is already normalised
               to a binary true or false value and that the majority of the toxicity calculation in
               this dataset was created using the machine learning model described above. However,
               nowhere in this code level is toxicity defined or explained, to understand this key
               concept for the code we will need to widen our investigation to one of the key
               dependencies within the ConversationAI models and look to another project <ptr
                  target="#conversationai2021b"/>. By accessing the click through link to the source
               code in Github we find the underlying ConversationAI code <ptr
                  target="#conversationai2021a"/>. Within the file
               unintended_ml_bias/new_madlibber/madlibber.py we find, </p>

            <eg lang="python"><![CDATA[self.__template_word_categories = set([]) 
self.__toxicity = set(["toxic," "nontoxic"])]]></eg>

            <p>As explained in a comment in the files fat-star-bias-measurement-tutorial.ipynb
               and<lb/>
               FAT_Star_Tutorial_Measuring_Unintended_Bias_in_Text_Classification_Models_with_Real_Data.ipynb, </p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <p>"Let's examine some rows in these datasets. Note that columns like toxicity and
                  male are percent scores.\n,"</p>
               <p>"* toxicity: this is the percentage of raters who labeled this comment as being
                  toxic.\n,"</p>
            </quote>
            <p>However, the definition of toxicity, beyond a percentage value, is under specified
               and again we are required to dig deeper into the code dependencies where in the
               ConversationAI Perspective API we find a definition. However we might note the
               beginning of a slippage between the definition of toxicity as a thing and toxicity as
               a probability value. In the ConversationAI system <q>toxicity</q> is defined as
                  <quote rend="inline">as a rude, disrespectful, or unreasonable comment that is
                  likely to make someone leave a discussion</quote>
               <ptr target="#perspective2021"/>. Toxicity’s effects are understood as, </p>
            <quote rend="block">stop[ing] people from engaging in conversation and, in extreme
               cases, [it] forces people offline. We’re finding new ways to reduce toxicity, and
               ensure everyone can safely participate in online conversations. <ptr
                  target="#jigsaw2021"/></quote>
            <p>Perspective API also helpfully documents how its model is able to classify text into
               a number of different outputs, all of which are interesting in and of themselves, but
               here it is the Toxicity value that we are investigating (see figure 2) (see also <ptr
                  target="#developers2021"/>).<note> Interestingly the Severe_Toxicity output is the
                  result of a more recent model which deals with the problems of the original
                  Toxicity model so that it identifies <quote rend="inline">a very hateful,
                     aggressive, disrespectful comment or otherwise very likely to make a user leave
                     a discussion or give up on sharing their perspective. This attribute is much
                     less sensitive to more mild forms of toxicity, such as comments that include
                     positive uses of curse words</quote>
                  <ptr target="#perspectivesattributes2021"/>. This the developers describe as
                     <quote rend="inline">a different experimental model that detects more severe
                     toxicity and is less sensitive to milder toxicity</quote>
                  <ptr target="#jigsaw2017"/>. Clearly the same problems of definition and meaning
                  are apparent in both Toxicity and Severe_Toxicity scores. </note>
            </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure03">
               <head>Overview of Perspective API <ptr target="#perspective2021"/></head>
               <figDesc>Chart showing Perspective API's process of calculating toxicity based on
                  input</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Using the machine learning model the Perspective API returns what they call the
                  <quote rend="inline">flagship Toxicity attribute</quote>
               <ptr target="#perspective2021"/>. The further one digs into the ConversationAI
               documentation the more slippery the notion of toxicity becomes, from either 0 or 1 in
               the TTMC tool (and drawn from the Wikimedia dataset) to toxicity as a perception
               probability between 0 and 1. The documentation explains, </p>
            <p>the model output is a probability. As such, a comment with a TOXICITY score of 0.9 is
               not necessarily more toxic than a comment with a TOXICITY score of 0.7. Rather, it’s
               more likely to be perceived as toxic by readers. <ptr
                  target="#perspectivemodelcards2021"/></p>
            <figure xml:id="figure04">
               <head>Toxicity Calculation <ptr target="#perspective2021"/></head>
               <figDesc>Input of <q>Shut up, you're an idiot!</q> shown with levels of Toxicity,
                  Sexually Explicit, Profanity, Insult, and Threat given as decimal
                  values.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>As we move through the layers of the code, and indeed through the layers of meaning
               attached to the notion of <q>toxicity</q> we find that the inputs to the toxicity
               value eventually start to hit what we might call a humanistic level. That is, the
               actual source of the value is revealed as a calculation based on a set of human users
               asked to review and annotate a comment dataset. </p>
            <p>Each comment is tagged by 3-10 crowdsourced raters from Figure Eight, Appen and
               internal platforms. The raters tag whether or not a comment contains an attribute
               (e.g., TOXICITY). We then post-process the tags to obtain labels corresponding to the
               ratio of raters who tagged a comment as toxic. For example, we label a comment as 0.6
               for TOXICITY if 6 out of 10 raters tagged a comment as toxic. <ptr
                  target="#perspectivedata2021"/></p>
            <p>Here we are not given the actual datasets which underlie the model, and we are only
               told they are drawn from <quote rend="inline">a variety of sources, including
                  comments from online forums such as Wikipedia (CC-BY-SA3 license) and The New York
                  Times</quote>
               <ptr target="#perspectivedata2021"/>. However, we do discover that toxicity is a
               calculated numeric value, so if 6 out of 10 <q>raters</q> tagged a comment as
                  <q>toxic</q> it would be assigned a value of 0.6 toxicity and if 4 out of 10
                  <q>raters</q> tagged it, then it would be given 0.4 toxicity. So the toxicity
               value is not, as one might assume, that the greater the value the higher its
               toxicity, rather that it merely indicates the number of raters as a percentage who
               thought a comment was <quote rend="inline">toxic,</quote> and the number of raters
               per comment averaged between 3-10 people looking at the comment. This implies that
               comments may actually be rated by different numbers of people, which therefore
               implies the <q>toxicity</q> ratings between comments are also not directly
               comparable. </p>
            <p>As far as I was able to discern, there is no indication of the number of raters per
               comment in the dataset, so already toxicity has been abstracted from the underlying
               concrete data. Jigsaw claims elsewhere that <quote rend="inline">toxicity is a global
                  problem, and has potentially dire consequences for freedom of expression</quote>
               and that <quote rend="inline">toxicity is pervasive online</quote>
               <ptr target="#jigsaw2020"/>. However, using Jigsaw’s own definition of toxicity as a
               percentage of the number of commentators on a crowd-sourced platform between 3-10 who
               thought a comment would cause someone to leave a conversation, then these claims seem
               somewhat confused.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>3. Discussion</head>
            <p>One of the key issues that remains problematic in these the models is not only is
               toxicity treated as a binary value but they classify toxicity out of context as a
               text processing issue through a form of <q>feature analysis.</q> One of the
               side-effects of this approach is that sentence classification can produce unintended
               and sometimes discriminatory or biased outcomes. Indeed, Jigsaw explain, <quote
                  rend="inline">higher numbers represent a higher likelihood that the patterns in
                  the text resemble patterns in comments that people have tagged as toxic. The
                  number is not a score of <q>how toxic</q> a particular entry is</quote>
               <ptr target="#jigsaw2017"/>. A result of this approach is that the model can produce
               not so much <q>toxicity</q> classifications as what have been identified as
                  <q>biased</q> results, as documented by Jessamyn West and shown in figure 4. </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure05">
               <head>PerspectiveAPI results <ptr target="#west2017"/></head>
               <figDesc>Two tables of about 30 sentences with <q>seen as toxic</q> ratings, e.g.
                  from <quote rend="inline">I am a man</quote> = 20% to <quote rend="inline">I am a
                     gay black woman</quote> = 87%.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure05a+b.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Jigsaw developers in responding to these results explained, <quote rend="inline"
                  >identity terms for more frequently targeted groups (e.g., words like
                     <q>black,</q>
                  <q>muslim,</q>
                  <q>feminist,</q>
                  <q>woman,</q>
                  <q>gay</q> etc) often have higher scores because comments about those groups are
                  over-represented in abusive and toxic comments</quote>
               <ptr target="#jigsaw2018"/>. This means that the data Jigsaw used to train their
               machine learning models have the same problem and the names of targeted groups appear
               far more often in abusive comments in the dataset they compiled. As the training data
               used to train their machine learning models contain these comments, the machine
               learning models adopt these biases in the <quote rend="inline">underlying
                  distributions, picking up negative connotations as they go. When there’s
                  insufficient diversity in the data, the models can over-generalize and make these
                  kinds of errors</quote>
               <ptr target="#jigsaw2018"/>. They further explained, </p>
            <quote rend="block">After the initial launch of Perspective API in 2017, users
               discovered a positive correlation between identity terms containing information on
               race or sexual orientation and toxicity score. For example, the phrase "I am a gay
               Black woman" received a high toxicity score. In this case, the identity terms are not
               being used pejoratively, so this example was classified incorrectly. <ptr
                  target="#jigsaw2020"/></quote>
            <p>And further that,</p>
            <quote rend="block">The source of the error was the training data itself — the training
               set did not contain sufficient examples of nontoxic comments containing identity
               terms for the model to learn that the terms themselves were neutral. This was because
               the vast majority of usage of these words in online forums is toxic — the model was
               truly reflecting the state of the world. But the context of that usage matters <ptr
                  target="#jigsaw2020"/>.</quote>
            <p>As a result of these criticisms, Jigsaw has created a debiased ConversationAI model
               which attempts to mitigate some of these problems. So <q>toxicity</q> is reweighted
               to take account of identity characteristics in calculating the toxicity value. In
               essence it is the original and the debiased model that the TTMC software is comparing
               and which enables the slightly different toxicity classifications to be compared and
               visualised for exploration. But again, this is not made clear in the ConversationAI
               models descriptions, and clearly there is a very different notion of toxicity being
               produced in each of the models.<note> One wonders, with all the problems of
                  definition, why use the term <q>toxicity</q> at all for this code? There may,
                  perhaps, be a cultural explanation that helps us understand this. Toxic was a word
                  that was clearly in the air whilst this software was being developed. The word
                     <q>toxic</q> was noted by Oxford University Press to have increased in usage
                  dramatically prior to and during 2018 <ptr target="#guardian2018"/>. With the
                  Novichok poisoning in the UK toxic chemicals were widely reported in the news,
                  together with toxic chemical stockpiles, toxic substances following hurricanes in
                  the US and toxic waste in India being reported. Toxic gases were discussed and
                  toxic air was a public health concern especially in relation to air quality. The
                  toxic algae disaster in Florida and had a central role in the state’s Senate
                  mid-terms race. Additionally, the notion of a toxic environment and the effect on
                  workplace mental health and worries about toxic culture in corporations, such as
                  Google were in the news. Toxic relationships were identified in relation to
                  family, partners and politicians and the notion of toxic masculinity became much
                  discussed following the #MeToo movement. It was no surprise therefore that
                     <q>toxic</q> was chosen as word of the year in 2018 by the Oxford English
                  Dictionary because <quote rend="inline">intoxicating descriptor for the year’s
                     most talked about topics</quote> and <quote rend="inline">the sheer scope of
                     its application</quote>
                  <ptr target="#oup2018"/>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Jigsaw explains that <quote rend="inline">research suggested that toxicity is an easy
                  concept for annotators to understand</quote> and therefore <quote rend="inline">it
                  was easier for more people to agree on what constituted <q>toxic</q> speech —
                  comments likely to make someone leave a conversation — than it was for people to
                  agree on other terms to describe problematic comments</quote>
               <ptr target="#jigsaw2020"/>. Jigsaw reference a study conducted in December 2018 by
               the Anti-Defamation League which they claim shows that marginalized groups
               experienced the most <q>toxicity</q> online, however the report does not use the term
                  <q>toxicity,</q> preferring to use the terms <q>hate</q> or <q>harassment</q> (see
                  <ptr target="#adl2018"/>). The notion of <q>toxicity</q> which appears to be a
               quasi-scientific metric for analysis through the machine learning models increasingly
               begins to look less stable as a descriptor. Toxicity, as Jigsaw themselves
               acknowledge, was a term that was easy for people to understand as <quote
                  rend="inline">comments likely to make someone leave a conversation.</quote> This
               enabled easier classification by the human raters, and was, therefore, simpler to use
               to train the machine learning model or use it beyond limited specific contexts (for
               example, see <ptr target="#wulczyn2017" loc="3"/>).<note> Detecting whether a user
                  leaves a conversation is a much simpler and less computational complex question
                  than attempting to understand the sophisticated deployment of language by human
                  participants in a conversation. In effect it becomes a binary question of
                  leaves-conversation/stays-in-conversation which is much easier to recognise and
                  automate using software. </note> Along the way, the notion of <q>toxicity</q>
               develops a much more scientific connotation as it is mediated through the black-boxes
               of ConversationAI and Perspective. </p>
            <p>In other words, through coding into software, a poorly defined term
               (<q>toxicitiy</q>) becomes reinforced into a set of software functions, which through
               layering and the resultant obscuring of the action of the functions, becomes a
               definitional and categorical classifier which is then applied unreflexively to text.
               Without attention to the way in which code can legitimate and operationalise concepts
               in particularly instrumental ways, we stand to lose the subtle interpretative
               flexibility of language use in particular contexts. In this example, toxicity which
               is defined and implemented as a particular operational function, shifts subtlety into
               standing in for a justificied use of software to detect something which it actually
               does not have a strong claim to identify, namely <q>hate</q> or <q>harassment.</q>
               This is a problem common across the domain of machine learning and artificial
               intelligence, which often over-claims and under-delivers on its promise to provide
               solutions to complex problems. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>4. Conclusion</head>
            <p>In this article I have attempted to demonstrate the value of focussing on the source
               code using a method of critical explainability in order to explore specific
               transformations of meaning in code. This method enables a set of principles that can
               be deployed in reading computational artifacts including: (1) criticism of
               computational systems which is not afraid of the results it arrives at, nor conflicts
               with power structures that it might encounter, (2) a distrust of closed-systems and
               hidden structures, (3) a striving for open-mindedness in relation to a readiness to
               revise its approach, methods and theories, (4) a suspicion of metaphysical or
               idealist approaches to understanding computation (e.g., the invasion of myth into
               understanding software, code and algorithms), (5) a standpoint that challenges
               irrationalism in relation to understanding computation, and lastly (6) a belief in
               the value of seeking defensible explanatory and interpretative accounts of systems,
               objects, networks, and other computationally mediated structures. </p>
            <p>As shown in this paper, the TTMC automates the decision as to whether a comment in a
               text is classified as <q>toxic</q> or not. But the coding of <q>toxicity</q> is not a
               simple matter and its deployment in this and related software dependencies requires
               explanation. By drawing on normative notions from explainability and
               interpretability, which highlights the need for an answer to the <q>why question,</q>
               we can ask why code functions in a particular way. We can also outline how it does
               this by following the logic of the code through the various layers of the software.
               By analysing the source code and other related contextual documentation, new readings
               of the assumptions sedimented within the code are revealed. Indeed, when elements of
               discourse are computationally measured it can transform and refigure our concepts, as
               shown in the example of <q>toxicity</q> here. A key methodological contribution of
               this paper is to show how concept formation can be traced through key categories and
               classifications deployed in code structures (e.g., modularity and layering software)
               but also how these classifications can appear more stable than they actually are by
               the tendency of software layers to obscure even as they reveals<note> One might also
                  note the extra-algorithmic discursive elements of textual descriptions which
                  surround the code on webpages and in the code archives which obfuscate, or even
                  provide minimal explanation of, what <q>toxicity</q> is. These textual elements,
                  and here I do not mean code commentary but rather the more general textual
                  penumbra, can also serve to shape or direct human interpretation of the code
                  functionality. This might be helpfully thought of as the difference between the
                  hard-core of a computational system (e.g., the code) and the soft-core (e.g., the
                  surrounding documentation, the textual descriptions and the marketing materials
                  around a system). </note> Much work remains in developing methods for working with
               code, especially as it becomes of more archival and historical interest. Approaches,
               such as the one developed in this article, will be needed by the digital humanities
               and other humanistic fields to trace and interpret code. Critical code studies by
               working with the methodological principle that source code can inform our
               understanding of computation and digital culture is an important field for
               contributing to these debates. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="adl2018" label="ADL 2018"> ADL. <title rend="quotes">Online Hate and
                  Harassment: The American Experience,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Anti-Defamation League</title>, 2018. <ptr
                  target="https://www.adl.org/onlineharassment"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="berry2008" label="Berry 2008"> Berry, D. M. <title rend="italic">Copy,
                  Rip, Burn: The Politics of Copyleft and Open Source</title>, Pluto Press, 2008. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="berry2011" label="Berry 2011"> Berry, D. M. <title rend="italic">The
                  Philosophy of Software: Code and Mediation in a Digital Age</title>, Palgrave
               Macmillan, 2011. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bogdanoff2017" label="Bogdanoff 2017"> Bogdanoff, A. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Saying goodbye to Civil Comments,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Medium</title>, 2017. <ptr
                  target="https://medium.com/@aja_15265/saying-goodbye-to-civil-comments-41859d3a2b1d"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="breiman2001" label="Breiman 2001"> Breiman L. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Statistical modeling: The two cultures,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Statistical science</title>, 16(3):199–231, 2001. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="connolly2020" label="Connolly 2020"> Connolly, R. <title rend="quotes">Why
                  Computing Belongs Within the Social Sciences,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Communications of the ACM</title>, Vol. 63 No. 8, Pages 54-59,
               August 2020. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="conversationai2021a" label="ConversationAI 2021a"> ConversationAI.
               Conversation AI, 2021. <ptr target="https://conversationai.github.io"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="conversationai2021b" label="ConversationAI 2021b"> ConversationAI.
               Conversation AI Bias, 2021. <ptr target="https://conversationai.github.io/bias.html"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="coughlan2020" label="Coughlan 2020"> Coughlan, Sean. <title rend="quotes"
                  >A-levels and GCSEs: Boris Johnson blames <q>mutant algorithm</q> for exam
                  fiasco,</title>
               <title rend="italic">BBC</title>, 2020. <ptr
                  target="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/education-53923279"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="darpa" label="DARPA n.d."> DARPA. <title rend="italic">Explainable
                  Artificial Intelligence (XAI),</title> n.d. <ptr
                  target="https://www.darpa.mil/program/explainable-artificial-intelligence"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="detox2021" label="Detox 2021"> Detox. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Research:Detox/Data Release,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Wikimedia</title>, 2021. <ptr
                  target="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Research:Detox/Data_Release#Schema_for_toxicity_annotations.tsv"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="developers2021" label="Developers 2021"> Developers. <title rend="italic"
                  >Attributes Languages</title>, 2021. <ptr
                  target="https://developers.perspectiveapi.com/s/about-the-api-attributes-and-languages"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="goodman2017" label="Goodman and Flaxman 2017"> Goodman, B. and Flaxman, S.
                  <title rend="quotes">European Union Regulations on Algorithmic Decision- Making
                  and a <q>Right to Explanation</q>,</title>
               <title rend="italic">AI Magazine</title>, 38(3):50–57, 2017. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="guardian2018" label="The Guardian 2018"> The Guardian. <title
                  rend="quotes"><q>Toxic</q> beats <q>gammon</q> and <q>cakeism</q> to win Oxford
                  Dictionaries' word of 2018</title>, 2018. <ptr
                  target="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2018/nov/15/toxic-oxford-dictionaries-word-of-2018"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hacking1983" label="Hacking 1983"> Hacking, I. <title rend="italic"
                  >Representing and Intervening</title>, Cambridge University Press, 1983. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jigsaw2017" label="Jigsaw 2017"> Jigsaw. <title rend="quotes">What do
                  Perspective’s scores mean?</title>, 2017, <ptr
                  target="https://medium.com/jigsaw/what-do-perspectives-scores-mean-113b37788a5d"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jigsaw2018" label="Jigsaw 2018"> Jigsaw. <title rend="quotes">Unintended
                  Bias and Identity Terms</title>, 2018, <ptr
                  target="https://medium.com/jigsaw/unintended-bias-and-names-of-frequently-targeted-groups-8e0b81f80a23"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jigsaw2020" label="Jigsaw 2020"> Jigsaw. <title rend="quotes">Why we use
                  the term <q>toxicity,</q> Toxicity 003,</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Current</title>, 2020, <ptr
                  target="https://jigsaw.google.com/the-current/toxicity/"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jigsaw2021" label="Jigsaw 2021"> Jigsaw. <title rend="quotes">Jigsaw: A
                  Safer Internet Means A Safer World</title>, 2021. <ptr
                  target="https://jigsaw.google.com"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kuang2017" label="Kuang 2017"> Kuang, C. <title rend="quotes">Can A.I. Be
                  Taught to Explain Itself?</title>, 2017, <title rend="italic">The New York
                  Times</title>, <ptr
                  target="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/11/21/magazine/can-ai-be-taught-to-explain-itself.html"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="leetaru2019" label="Leetaru 2019"> Leetaru, Kalev. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Google's What-If Tool And The Future Of Explainable AI,</title> 2019, <title
                  rend="italic">Forbes</title>, <ptr
                  target="https://www.forbes.com/sites/kalevleetaru/2019/08/05/googles-what-if-tool-and-the-future-of-explainable-ai/"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="liu2019" label="Liu  Anci 2019"> Liu, F. and Anci, B. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Incorporating Priors with Feature Attribution on Text Classification,</title>
               2019, <ptr target="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.08286.pdf"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lum2021" label="Lum  Chowdhury 2021"> Lum, K. and Chowdhury, R. <title
                  rend="quotes">What is an <q>algorithm</q>? It depends whom you ask,</title> 2021,
                  <title rend="italic">MIT Technology Review</title>, <ptr
                  target="https://www.technologyreview.com/2021/02/26/1020007/what-is-an-algorithm/"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="manovich2001" label="Manovich 2001"> Manovich, L. <title rend="italic">The
                  Language of New Media</title>, MIT Press, 2001. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="marino2020" label="Marino 2020"> Marino, M. <title rend="italic">Critical
                  Code Studies</title>, MIT Press, 2020. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oup2018" label="OUP 2018"> OUP. <title rend="quotes">Word of the Year
                  2018,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Oxford Languages</title>, Oxford University Press, 2018, <ptr
                  target="https://languages.oup.com/word-of-the-year/2018/"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="outhwaite1987" label="Outhwaite 1987"> Outhwaite, <title rend="quotes">O.
                  Laws and Explanations in Sociology</title> in R.J. Anderson et al. (eds.), <title
                  rend="italic">Classic Disputes in Sociology</title>, Allen Unwin, pp. 157-183,
               1987. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="perspective2021" label="Perspective 2021"> Perspective. <title
                  rend="quotes">Perspective API,</title> 2021, <ptr
                  target="https://www.perspectiveapi.com/how-it-works/"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="perspectivesattributes2021"
               label="Perspectives Attributes and Language 2021"> Perspectives Attributes and
               Language. <title rend="quotes">Model Cards: Attributes and Language,</title> 2021,
                  <ptr
                  target="https://support.perspectiveapi.com/s/about-the-api-attributes-and-languages"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="perspectivedata2021" label="Perspective Data 2021"> Perspective Data.
                  <title rend="quotes">Model Cards: Data,</title> 2021, <ptr
                  target="https://developers.perspectiveapi.com/s/about-the-api-model-cards"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="perspectivemodelcards2021" label="Perspective Model Cards 2021">
               Perspective Model Cards. <title rend="quotes">Model Cards: Uses and Limits,</title>
               2021, <ptr
                  target="https://developers.perspectiveapi.com/s/about-the-api-model-cards?tabset-20254=2"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rieder2020" label="Rieder  Hofmann 2020"> Rieder, B., Hofmann, J. <title
                  rend="quotes">Towards platform observability,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Internet Policy Review</title>, 9(4), 2020, <ptr
                  target="https://doi.org/10.14763/2020.4.1535"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rudin2019" label="Rudin 2019"> Rudin, C. <title rend="quotes">Stop
                  explaining black box machine learning models for high stakes decisions and use
                  interpretable models instead,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Nat Mach Intell</title>, 1, 206–215, 2019, <ptr
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s42256-019-0048-x"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sample2017" label="Sample 2017"> Sample, I. <title rend="quotes">Computer
                  says no: why making AIs fair, accountable and transparent is crucial,</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Guardian</title>, 2017, <ptr
                  target="https://www.theguardian.com/science/2017/nov/05/computer-says-no-why-making-ais-fair-accountable-and-transparent-is-crucial"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="selbst2017" label="Selbst  Powles 2017"> Selbst, A. D., Powles, J. <title
                  rend="quotes">Meaningful Information and the Right to Explanation,</title>
               <title rend="italic">International Data Privacy Law</title>, 7(4):233–242, 2017. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="toxicityquestion2017" label="ToxicityQuestion 2017"> ToxicityQuestion.
                  <title rend="quotes">toxicity_question.png,</title> 2017, <ptr
                  target="https://github.com/ewulczyn/wiki-detox/blob/master/src/modeling/toxicity_question.png"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ttmc2021" label="TTMC 2021"> TTMC. <title rend="quotes">What-If Tool
                  toxicity text model comparison,</title> 2021, <ptr
                  target="https://colab.research.google.com/github/pair-code/what-if-tool/blob/master/WIT_Toxicity_Text_Model_Comparison.ipynb#scrollTo=UiNxsd4_q9wq"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vasserman2021" label="Vasserman et al. 2021"> Vasserman, L., Acosta, T.,
               Dos Santos, L., Chvasta, A., Thorpe, R., Saxe, R. <title rend="quotes">Identifying
                  Machine Learning Bias With Updated Data Sets,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Medium</title>, 2021, <ptr
                  target="https://medium.com/jigsaw/identifying-machine-learning-bias-with-updated-data-sets-7c36d6063a2c"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wachter2017" label="Wachter, Mittelstadt,  Floridi 2017"> Wachter, S.,
               Mittelstadt, B., Floridi L. <title rend="quotes">Why a Right to Explanation of
                  Automated Decision-Making Does Not Exist in the General Data Protection
                  Regulation,</title>
               <title rend="italic">International Data Privacy Law</title>, 7(2):76–99, 2017. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="west2017" label="West 2017"> West, J. <title rend="quotes">I tested 14
                  sentences for <q>perceived toxicity</q> using Perspectives. Least toxic: I am a
                  man. Most toxic: I am a gay black woman. Come on, Twitter,</title> 2017, <ptr
                  target="https://twitter.com/jessamyn/status/901476036956782593"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wikipedia2021" label="Wikipedia 2021"> Wikipedia. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Project Jupyter,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Wikipedia</title>, 2021, <ptr
                  target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Project_Jupyter"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wikipediatalklabels2021" label="Wikipedia Talk Labels 2021"> Wikipedia
               Talk Labels. <title rend="quotes">Wikipedia Talk Labels: Toxicity,</title> 2021, <ptr
                  target="https://figshare.com/articles/dataset/Wikipedia_Talk_Labels_Toxicity/4563973"
               />. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wit" label="WIT"> WIT. <title rend="quotes">Visually probe the behavior of
                  trained machine learning models, with minimal coding,</title> n.d., <ptr
                  target="https://pair-code.github.io/what-if-tool/"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wulczyn2016" label="Wulczyn, Thain,  Dixon 2016"> Wulczyn, E., Thain, N.,
               and Dixon, L. <title rend="quotes">Wikipedia Detox,</title>
               <title rend="italic">figshare</title>, 2016, <ptr
                  target="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.4054689"/>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wulczyn2017" label="Wulczyn, Thain,  Dixon 2017"> Wulczyn, E., Thain, N.,
               and Dixon, L. <title rend="quotes">Ex Machina: Personal Attacks Seen at
                  Scale,</title> 2017, <ptr target="https://arxiv.org/abs/1610.08914"/>. </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
