<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Introduction: Digital Humanities &amp; Colonial
                    Latin American Studies</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Hannah <dhq:family>Alpert-Abrams</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation/>
                    <email/>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Clayton <dhq:family>McCarl</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation/>
                    <email/>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000531</idno>
                <idno type="volume"
                    ><!-- volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue"><!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date/>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p/>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>This is the introduction to a special issue on Digital Humanities and Colonial
                    Latin American Studies.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><emph>For Linda M. Rodriguez</emph></p>
                <p>This special issue of <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>
                    examines intersections between colonial Latin American studies
                        (CLAS)<note>Though the abbreviation <emph>CLAS</emph> is not widely used, we
                        employ it for the sake of brevity, in parallel with the more common use of
                            <emph>DH</emph>. Below we introduce another abbreviation,
                            <emph>DCLAS</emph>, to designate the intersection of these two
                        fields.</note> and digital humanities (DH) theory and practice. The essays
                    collected here touch on matters that pertain to numerous fields, including
                    anthropology, archaeology, art history, history, linguistics, and literature. By
                    doing so in a digital context, they blur the lines between many of these fields,
                    and point to several major themes that predominate across digital humanities
                    scholarship today.</p>
                <p>The project was motivated by the recognition of three realities. First, digital
                    practice has become fundamental to how scholarly work is conducted in the study
                    of the colonial world. Second, scholarship being carried out today demonstrates
                    that digital methods have the potential to significantly enhance the field going
                    forward. Third, in order to realize that potential, the diverse community of
                    practitioners engaged in such work needs to better articulate how digital
                    scholarship is understood and conducted within CLAS.</p>
                <p>In this introduction, we briefly provide context for understanding the two areas
                    of inquiry at the center of this discussion. To do so, we first consider in
                    broad strokes the central concerns of each, proposing ways we believe the two
                    overlap in terms of objectives and methods. We then step back to examine the
                    evolution of digital work within CLAS, arguing that such scholarship has
                    followed a different path than in digital humanities communities based in the
                    United States and Europe. We propose that legacies of colonialism have shaped
                    this development by obliging scholars to confront material realities and
                    theoretical problems that are often distinct from those that drive digital
                    humanities practice elsewhere.</p>
                <p>Working from this premise, we then suggest parameters for identifying a set of
                    tendencies that can define the field we term <hi rend="italic">digital colonial
                        Latin American studies</hi> (DCLAS). To do so, we analyze trends in digital
                    scholarship within the field, examining, in particular, how those ideas and
                    concerns inform the articles in this special collection. We conclude by
                    reflecting on the challenges that the broader community of scholars who work on
                    colonial Latin America must face before being able to more fully harness digital
                    methods to transform research and teaching about the colonial world.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Two parallel, overlapping fields</head>
                <p>This project brings together two areas of study that are both broadly and
                    capaciously defined. We offer our working definitions here with the purpose of
                    better orienting readers towards the content of this special issue.</p>
                <p>Defining DH in precise terms has long presented a challenge. Certainly, there is
                    a sense in which we are all, as researchers and teachers who use computers,
                    participants in DH, whether we are conducting our research through online
                    databases and search engines, composing scholarly monographs using word
                    processing software, or teaching with digital images or remote learning
                        technologies.<note>For a discussion of general problems in working with
                        digital sources, see Putnam 2016 and Daut 2019.</note> However, for many
                    scholars, and for the purposes of this special issue, this work becomes
                        <soCalled>digital humanities</soCalled> when the critical and theoretical
                    apparatus surrounding research, teaching, and publication — which already
                    encompasses disciplinary and cross-disciplinary frameworks — extends to the use
                    of digital technologies.<note>For some recent volumes that survey the current
                        state of DH, see Crompton et al. 2016, Balkun and Deyrup 2020, and Crompton
                        et al. 2020.</note></p>
                <p>Even calling DH a <soCalled>field</soCalled> is problematic, with many scholars
                    asserting that it is better understood as a collection of scholarly tendencies
                    than as clearly defined areas of inquiry. Much work within the digital
                    humanities consists of reflection on those tendencies, and in the sense of such
                    scholarship, DH does exist as a category with its own boundaries. Beyond such
                    work, however, DH is, to a large extent, something that must be done
                        <emph>within</emph> other scholarly areas. Put another way, DH is a space in
                    which other scholarly areas can be carried out.</p>
                <p>One basic defining tension within DH in recent years has been a struggle for
                    diversity and inclusion. DH as a field of study has been marked by the
                    predominance of European and U.S.-based institutions, scholars, and languages.
                    Uneven access to digital technologies has contributed to this outcome, but other
                    factors are also involved, such as differing levels of institutional support and
                    access to the financing needed to support large-scale DH endeavors. In part to
                    counter this tendency, the global and multilingual movements within DH have
                    worked to make the field more expansive and diverse by actively engaging with
                    questions of access and equity, and by drawing on critical frameworks including
                    feminist and decolonial studies (Burns 2020, Risam 2018).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="adorno2006" label="Adorno 2006">Adorno, Rolena. <title rend="quotes"
                        >About the transcription and its critical apparatus</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Guaman Poma Website</title>. Det Kongelige Bibliotek.
                    2006. <ref target="http://www5.kb.dk/permalink/2006/poma/info/en/foreword.htm"
                        >http://www5.kb.dk/permalink/2006/poma/info/en/foreword.htm</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="adorno2009" label="Adorno 2009">Adorno, Rolena. <title rend="quotes"
                        >1989–2009: Revising Colonial Latin American Studies’ <q>New
                        Paradigm</q></title>. Modern Language Association Conference, 27-30 December
                    2009, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="afanador2019" label="Afanador Llach 2019">Afanador Llach, María José.
                        <title rend="quotes">Tecnología al servicio de las Humanidades.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Telos</title>. 11 Dec. 2019. <ref
                        target="https://telos.fundaciontelefonica.com/telos-112-cuaderno-central-humanidades-en-un-mundo-stem-maria-jose-afanadortecnologia-al-servicio-de-las-humanidades/"
                    />https://telos.fundaciontelefonica.com/telos-112-cuaderno-central-humanidades-en-un-mundo-stem-maria-jose-afanadortecnologia-al-servicio-de-las-humanidades/.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="alpert2016" label="Alpert-Abrams 2016">Alpert-Abrams, Hannah. <title rend="quotes"></title>Machine
                    Reading the Primeros Libros." Digital Humanities Quarterly 10.4 (2016). <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/4/000268/000268.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/4/000268/000268.html</ref>.</bibl>
                Alpert-Abrams 2017. Alpert-Abrams, Hannah. Unreadable Books: Colonial Mexican
                Documents in Circulation. 2017. University of Texas, PhD Dissertation. Alpert-Abrams
                2018. Alpert-Abrams, Hannah. "Colonial Copying in an Imperial Age." Catalyst 4.2
                (2018).
                https://link.gale.com/apps/doc/A561685883/AONE?u=21246_dol&amp;sid=AONE&amp;xid=2c6e866b
                Balkun and Deyrup 2020. Balkun, Mary McAleer, and Marta Mestrovic Deyrup.
                Transformative Digital Humanities: Challenges and Opportunities. Routledge, 2020.
                https://www.taylorfrancis.com/books/9780429399923 Bolãnos and Verdesio 2002.
                Bolãnos. Alvaro F́elix, and Gustavo Verdesio, eds. "Colonialism Past and Present :
                Reading and Writing About Colonial Latin America Today." Albany, NY: SUNY Press,
                2002. Bueno 2018. Bueno, Christina. "La Biblioteca Nacional de Antropología e
                Historia de México: un legado del nacionalismo porfiriano." In Carlos Aguirre and
                Ricardo D. Salvatore, Bibliotecas y cultura letrada en América Latina: siglos XIX y
                XX. Lima: Pontificia Universidad Católica, Fondo Editorial, 2018. 205-225. Burns
                2020. Burns, Patrick and Quinn Dombrowski. "Language is not a Default Setting:
                Countering Digital Humanities’ English Problem." Matthew Gold and Lauren Klein, eds.
                Debates in the Digital Humanities 2021. University of Minnesota Press. Forthcoming.
                Crompton et al. 2016. Crompton, Constance Louise Kathleen, Richard J. Lane, and
                Raymond George Siemens. 2016. Doing Digital Humanities: Practice, Training,
                Research. Routledge, 2016. Crompton et al. 2020. Crompton, Constance, Richard J.
                Lane, and Raymond George Siemens. Doing More Digital Humanities: Open Approaches to
                Creation, Growth, and Development. Routledge, 2020. Daut 2019. Daut, Marlene. "Haiti
                @ the Digital Crossroads: Archiving Black Sovereignty." Archipelagos 3 (2019). Díaz
                2014. Díaz, Mónica. "El ‘nuevo paradigma’ de los estudios coloniales
                latinoamericanos," Revista de Estudios Hispánicos 48:3 (2014): 519–47. Dombrowski
                2020. Dombrowski, Quinn. "The Stakes of Multilingual DH in the United States."
                quinndombrowski.com. March 13, 2020. Emory Center 2020a. Emory Center for Digital
                Scholarship and collaborators. "About the Project."
                https://www.slavevoyages.org/about/about# Emory Center 2020b. Emory Center for
                Digital Scholarship and collaborators. "History of the Project."
                https://www.slavevoyages.org/about/about#history/1/en/ Flores-Marcial 2020.
                Flores-Marcial, Xóchitl. "Zapotec-Language Use in Social Media Platforms as a
                Pedagogical Method for Undergraduate Students." Presentation at Virtual Conference
                of the Latin American Studies Association, May 16, 2020. Glover and Gil 2019.
                Glover, Kaiama and Alex Gil. "The Caribbean Won't Stand Still." Archipelagos 3
                (2019). Jacob 2020. Jacob, Arun. "Punching Holes in the International Busa Machine
                Narrative." IDEAH 1.1 (May 30, 2020). doi: 10.21428/f1f23564.d7d097c2 Johnson 2019.
                Johnson, Jessica Marie. "We Are Deathless (Slavery in the Machine)." Archipelagos 3
                (2019). Lillehaugen 2020. Lillehaugen, Brook. "TEI Encoding and the Creation of
                Digital Editions of Zapotec-Language Texts in an Undergraduate Classroom."
                Presentation at Virtual Conference of the Latin American Studies Association, May
                16, 2020. McCarl et al. 2020. McCarl, Clayton, Amarilys Sánchez and Emilia Thom.
                "Reevaluating the History of Africans and their Descendants in Antioquia, Colombia,
                through a Digital-Editing-on-Site Study Abroad Experience." Presentation at Virtual
                Conference of the Latin American Studies Association, May 16, 2020. Mundy and
                Leibsohn 1996. Mundy, Barbara and Dana Leibsohn. "Of Copies, Casts, and Codices:
                Mexico on Display in 1892." RES: Anthropology and Aesthetics, no. 29/30 (April 01,
                1996): 326-43. Mundy and Leibsohn 2017. Mundy, B., & Leibsohn, D. "Digital
                Resources: The State of Digital Research on the Visual Culture of Spanish America."
                Oxford Research Encyclopedia of Latin American History. 2017. DOI:
                10.1093/acrefore/9780199366439.013.117 Padilla 2020. Padilla, Thomas. "Always
                Already Computational: Collections as Data." https://collectionsasdata.github.io/
                Palacios 2020. Palacios, Albert A. "From the Colonial Page: Introducing DH through
                Transcription." Virtual Conference of the Latin American Studies Association, May
                16, 2020. Putnam 2016. Putnam, Lara. "The Transnational and the Text-Searchable:
                Digitized Sources and the Shadows They Cast." The American Historical Review, 121.2,
                April 2016. 377–402. https://doi.org/10.1093/ahr/121.2.377 Recovery 2020.
                "Recovering the US Hispanic Literary Heritage." Arte Publico Press 2020.
                https://artepublicopress.com/recovery-program/ Rodriguez and Ferrer 2019.
                "Collaborating with Aponte: Digital Humanities, Art, and the Archive." Archipelagos
                3 (2019). Risam 2018. Risam, Roopika. New Digital Worlds. Chicago: Northwestern
                University Press, 2018. Trettien 2020. Trettien, Whitney. "A Hornbook for Digital
                Book History with Whitney Trettien." Rare Book School. YouTube. Zamora 2004. De
                Zamora, Rosa María Fernández. "Hacia un mundo visible del patrimonio bibliográfico
                mexicano: Retos y acciones que las bibliotecas deben alcanzar." Encuentro Nacional
                de Bibliotecas con Fondos Antiguos (2004). </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
