<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Fading Away... The challenge of sustainability in
               digital studies</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Christine <dhq:family>Barats</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Cerlis, University of Paris Descartes</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>c.barats@wanadoo.fr</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Christine Barats is a Professor in Information and Communication Studies at the
                     University of Paris Descartes and a member of the Cerlis (<ref
                        target="http://www.cerlis.eu/team-view/barats-christine/"
                        >http://www.cerlis.eu/team-view/barats-christine/</ref>). Her work has
                     focused on the politicization and media coverage of immigration in France as
                     well as on the discourse aimed at the integration of information and
                     communication technologies (ICT) in higher education and research (ESR) and the
                     discourses on evaluation in ESR. In parallel, she examines the methodological
                     issues related to the analysis of web-based corpora and text statistics tools.
                     ORCID ID: 0000-0002-8097-6622</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Valérie <dhq:family>Schafer</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>C²DH, University of Luxembourg</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>Valerie.schafer@uni.lu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Valérie Schafer has been a Professor in Contemporary European History at the
                     C²DH (Luxembourg Centre for Contemporary and Digital History) at the University
                     of Luxembourg since February 2018. She previously worked at the CNRS in France
                     and is still an Associate Researcher at the Center for Internet and Society
                     (CNRS UPR 2000). She specialises in the history of computing,
                     telecommunications and data networks. Her main research interests are the
                     history of the Internet and the Web, the history of European digital cultures
                     and infrastructures, and born-digital heritage (especially Web archives). She
                     is Vice-Chair of the ECREA Communication History Section, a member of the
                     Management Committee of the <title rend="quotes">Tensions of Europe</title>
                     network, and General Secretary of the Society for the History of Media (SPHM).
                     She is a co-founder of the journal <title rend="italic">Internet
                        Histories</title>. ORCID ID: 0000-0002-8204-1265</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Andreas <dhq:family>Fickers</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>C²DH, University of Luxembourg</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>andreas.fickers@uni.lu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Andreas Fickers is the director of the Luxembourg Centre for Contemporary and
                     Digital History (C²DH) and head of the DH-Lab. He studied history, philosophy
                     and sociology and is currently Professor for Contemporary and Digital History
                     at the University of Luxembourg. He's head of the FNR funded Doctoral Training
                     Unit <title rend="quotes">Digital History &amp; Hermeneutics</title> (DTU) and
                     coordinates the Trinational doctoral school together with Prof. Dr Dietmar
                     Hüser (Universität des Saarlandes) and Prof. Dr Hélène Miard-Delacroix
                     (Université Paris-Sorbonne). He's also prinicipal investigator of the Impresso
                     project and was co-editor of <title rend="italic">VIEW, the Journal of European
                        Television History and Culture</title>. He's currently the Luxembourg
                     national coordinator of DARIAH-EU and member of the joint research board of
                     Humanities in the European Research Area (HERA).</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000484</idno>
            <idno type="volume">014</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2020-09-25">25 September 2020</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2020-07-23" who="jmurel">Finished encoding</change>
         <change when="2020-07-16" who="jmurel">Created file, began encoding</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
         	<p>This paper emphasizes the need to think about sustainability as a key element of
         		digital studies and digital hermeneutics. It addresses the inherent tensions between
         		the long-term needs of data preservation and maintenance on the one side, and the
         		short life cycles of the data formats, platforms and infrastructures on the other
         		side. Challenges are not limited to the technical maintenance of software, tools and
         		data, but also apply to the wider institutional contexts, epistemic traditions and
         		social practices in which the doing of research in social sciences and humanities are
         		embedded. We explore these tensions at several levels, temporalities and key stages
         		in research – namely data access and building a corpus, establishing a research
         		framework and analysis, and finally the use/dissemination of results.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>Sustainability in DH as a shared issue of data maintenance and institutional contexts.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <epigraph>
            <p><cit><quote rend="block">The dominant economy of the traces of each era are based on
                     agents of different ages. Within the framework of slow-moving institutions
                     whose role is precisely to make the system stagnate, the rules of this economy
                     change at the faster pace of social changes, which it adjusts with technologies
                     that change even faster - and which can produce unexpected or contrary effects
                     on the logic of the first two levels. This stratification of collective
                     equilibriums induces an interweaving of technical environments and innovative
                     societal projects with older or even archaic beliefs or hierarchies.</quote>
                  <ref target="#merzeau1998">Merzeau 1998, our translation</ref></cit></p>
         </epigraph>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>The question of future access to knowledge production was asked long before the
               digital era. The risk of losing (analogue) data dates back to before digitisation and
               care was reinforced for example through transfer of data onto magnetic strips before
               computer memory storage <ptr target="#borghoff2006"/>. However, data preservation has
               recently attracted new attention within research: questions of sharing data and
               reproducibility of science, open access and maintenance have become more and more
               pertinent as the websites and digital productions come of age. <q>404 not found</q>
               messages now replace a growing number of hyperlinks, and the Web as scientific
               platform is full of digital wastelands, caused by the end of research projects. As
               underlined by Smithies and al., <quote rend="inline">finding a comprehensive and
                  scalable approach to sustainable development in digital humanities labs is a
                  non-trivial problem</quote>
               <ptr target="#smithies2019" loc="2"/></p>
            <p>In 2011, the Manifesto for Digital Humanities has made a plea <quote rend="inline"
                  >for open access to data and metadata, which must be documented and interoperable,
                  both technically and conceptually</quote>
               <ptr target="#dacos2012"/>. Transdisciplinary studies published around the same time
               underline that <quote rend="inline">sustainability challenges require new ways of
                  knowledge production,</quote> recommending a collaborative approach and new
               scientific agencies in the academic field <ptr target="#lang2012"/>. Without doubt,
               the challenge of sustainability has turned into a key concern for the field of
               digital humanities at large as illustrated by the theme choosen by the Digital
               matters (an interdisciplinary research agenda) at the University of Utah.<note>
                  <ref target="https://digitalmatters.utah.edu/digital-matters-lab/"
                     >https://digitalmatters.utah.edu/digital-matters-lab/</ref>
               </note> Large scale research infrastructures such as Huma-Num, Dariah and
                  OPERAS<note>See <ref target="https://www.huma-num.fr/presentation/reseau"
                     >https://www.huma-num.fr/presentation/reseau</ref>; <ref
                     target="https://www.dariah.eu/">https://www.dariah.eu/</ref>; <ref
                     target="https://operas.hypotheses.org/">https://operas.hypotheses.org</ref>.
               </note> seriously consider the sustainability of humanities and social sciences (HSS)
               research, and funding bodies increasingly make <q>data management plans</q> a must in
               research applications.</p>
            <p>As defined by the Stanford Libraries: <quote rend="inline">A data management plan
                  (DMP) is a written document that describes the data you expect to acquire or
                  generate during the course of a research project, how you will manage, describe,
                  analyse, and store those data, and what mechanisms you will use at the end of your
                  project to share and preserve your data.</quote><note>
                  <ref
                     target="https://library.stanford.edu/research/data-management-services/data-management-plans"
                     >https://library.stanford.edu/research/data-management-services/data-management-plans</ref>
               </note> These sentences underline that data management is not just about the data
               that are used, but also about those, which are produced (metadata, results of
               research, etc.). In fact, data management covers the whole life cycle of a research
               project, from data selection to their curation and description, from analyse and
               interpreting data to its publication and long term storage. Therefore, a sustainable
               stewardship of research data includes a strategy for the readability, maintenance and
               transparency of those data <ptr target="#hoekstra2018"/>. While this plea for data
               stewardship – often based on the FAIR principles (FAIR stands for Findable,
               Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable, see <ref target="#wilkinson2016">Wilkinson
                  et al. 2016</ref> and <ref target="#mons2018">Mons 2018</ref>) – has become a
               shared ambition in earth or climate sciences, it remains a theoretical discussion
               rather than a shared practice in the field of humanities and social sciences.</p>
            <p>This paper will focus in particular on HSS, in order to uncover the centrality of
               this question and the diversity of the researchers’ responses to the many challenges
               at stake. The aim is to give a voice to researchers from different disciplines that
               are basically facing the same problems when it comes to data management issues and
               the question of sustainability. The present study examines all stages of research,
               from data collection to the dissemination of knowledge, and underlines that
               challenges are not limited to the technical maintenance of software, tools and data,
               but also apply to the wider institutional contexts, epistemic traditions and social
               practices in which the doing of research in humanities and social sciences are
               embedded. As highlighted by <ref target="#bachimont2017" loc="95">Bachimont
                  (2017)</ref>, a loss of intelligibility - that is an understanding of the context
               in which data are generated and interpreted – is as critical as the technical or
               material loss of data, if not more. Therefore, the topic at stake necessitates a
               broader reflection on the institutional, economic and political dimensions of
               knowledge production, dissemination and conservation in the digital era <ptr
                  target="#musiani2017"/>.</p>
            <p>In order to identify the conflicts between the ephemeral, the flow of data, and the
               safeguarding of knowledge production for future needs, our analysis is largely based
               on personal experiences of French researchers in the field of digital
               studies. A qualitative survey was submitted to senior colleagues in the field who
               have carried out larger research projects and as such responsible for maintaining and
               preserving data. The survey includes colleagues working in disciplines such as
               history, information and communication studies, digital humanities, and linguistics.
               In total, twenty colleagues answered our indicative interview-based online
                  survey<note>10 colleagues are historians, 5 are researchers in Information and
                  Communication Studies, 3 in linguistics and 2 in sociology. Despite disciplines,
                  all colleagues were concerned with data access and data preservation for
                  individual analysis as well as collective projects. Quotations were translated
                  from French to English.</note> in the period between May 2018 and October 2018.
               The survey included five open questions concerning data access, methods and tools of
               data gathering and curation, approaches to data preservation, reflections on
               sustainability, and the place devoted to long-term preservation. Longer face-to-face
               or telephone interviews were carried out with ten respondents in order to dig deeper
               into specific questions or problems raised in the survey.</p>
            <p>The aim of our project was not to produce strict guidelines for sustainable data
               management for open science in the field of social sciences or humanities. We fully
               agree with <ref target="#smithies2019" loc="2">Smithies et al. (2019)</ref> that
               complex projects may share common and generic solutions, but also often need to rely
               on <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> solutions, taking into account the specific
               characteristics of a research project. We therefore want to emphasise the need to
               think about sustainability as a key element of digital hermeneutics, encompassing the
               critical reflection on the epistemic role of data management and stewardship in the
               entire life cycle of knowledge production and dissemination <ptr
                  target="#fickers2020"/>. In promoting this holistic approach, we aim at addressing
               the inherent tension between different temporalities at stake: between the long-term
               needs of data preservation and maintenance on the one side, and the paradoxically
               short life cycles of the data formats, platforms and infrastructures on the other
               side. We seek to explore these tensions between the necessary stability and
               reproducibility <ptr target="#osullivan2019"/> of research and the instability of the
               digital domain it depends on at several levels and temporalities. The
               often-contradictory logics of these different temporalities will be discussed in a
               multilevel perspective, including the institutional, human and technical dimensions
               of a phenomenon we qualify as <q>fading away.</q> This study therefore considers
               three key stages in research – namely data access and building a corpus, establishing
               a research framework and analysis, and finally the use/dissemination of results.</p>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>1. From data access to corpus building</head>
            <p><quote rend="inline">There are a great number of difficulties. The API of Facebook, a
                  semi-private, semi-public social network, prevents automatic data crawling and
                  makes the archiving of data a tedious process that involves numerous screenshots
                  and the difficulty of organising manually collected data. I also encountered
                  difficulties linked to the plasticity of devices and therefore the loss of data:
                  the closure of pages or Facebook profiles, deleted comments or posts... as well as
                  problems related to ethical issues for data collection: what data can I use, and
                  how? Does access to <q>private</q> data also permit the use of said data? Is the
                  consent of the respondents sufficient to publish the data?</quote> (ICS interview,
               July 2018).</p>
            <p>By explaining her working methods, this scholar in information and communication
               studies highlights realities that are frequently invisible in research papers and
               remain hidden from public view: digital studies are more often than is usually
               assumed a mixture of science and handicraft, a kind of <quote rend="inline"
                  >thinkering</quote>
               <ptr target="#fickers2017"/> process which involves several challenges and
               difficulties along the way, and whose solutions may sometimes be very manual,
               empirical and pragmatic. This is far from the methodology which may then be outlined
               in a published paper, but this hidden struggling and the iterative logic of science
               in the making remains a reality for many research projects that are characterised by
               a mixed method and hands-on learning by doing approach trying to deal with
               screenshots, time-consuming manual curation, changing access conditions, obsolete
               hyperlinks, unclear legislation – in short, the normal grappling with the instability
               of data, devices, and tools.</p>
            <div>
               <head>1.1 Diversity and instability of data search and gathering</head>
               <p>Researchers using digital data in the field of humanities and social sciences
                  mainly work with social media data originating from commercial platforms such as
                  Facebook, Twitter or Instagram. These data are often collected in real time. In
                  the following paragraph, we will discuss some French examples of such projects in
                  order to highlight the different possibilities of scraping or gathering online
                  data and to reflect on both the opportunities and challenges that come with the
                  different approaches.</p>
               <p>Twitter-data are certainly one of the favourite digital-born sources to be studied
                  by digital humanists. French examples are the study carried out by <ref
                     target="#badouard2016">Badouard (2016)</ref> on the #jenesuispasCharlie hashtag
                  after the attacks against the editorial staff of Charlie Hebdo in January 2015,
                  and Frédéric Clavert’s project on the commemorations of the First World War <ptr
                     target="#clavert2018"/>. As noticed by Dagiral and Pailler, <quote
                     rend="inline">one of the main constraints in building corpus from Twitter is
                     the inability to obtain the entire stream, even for an extremely short period
                     of time; there is not technical reason for this restriction, which actually
                     results from the choices made when designing the site</quote>
                  <ptr target="#dagiral2018" loc="117"/> (our translation). In order to have the
                  entire stream, Twitter does offer the researchers to purchase data. However, this
                  option strongly depends of available funding and raises some concerns about
                  research ethics as well.</p>
               <p>Next to the rather time-consuming tasks of building ones own dataset, researcher
                  mostly rely on available data, which are shared online, often through platforms
                  such as Github<note>See for example <ref
                        target="https://ruebot.net/post/twitterdatasets/"
                        >https://ruebot.net/post/twitterdatasets/</ref>. Nick Ruest shares Twitter
                     IDs, not tweets.</note> or through special collections made available by
                  archives, libraries, and other cultural heritage institutions. In 2010, the
                  Library of Congress (LoC) reached an agreement with Twitter to archive all the
                  tweets issued since 2006 <ptr target="#raymond2010"/>. It took the library until
                  2013 to complete the data collection for the period 2006-2010 – a fact
                  demonstrating the enormous time and work required for indexing such a vast
                  dataset. The volume of data (170 billion tweets and more than 300 terabytes of
                  information from 2006 to 2010) led the LoC to announce in December 2017 that it
                  would restrict collection to data concerning specific themes and events. For
                  technical reasons but also ethical (consent) and legal (privacy rights) issues,
                  data collected by the LoC are still not available to researchers <ptr
                     target="#zimmer2015"/>.</p>
               <p>However, other institutions with smaller perimeters are offering access to Twitter
                  collections. Examples include the archives of the INA (French National Institute
                  for Audiovisual) and the BnF (French National Library), which are both related to
                  the French Internet legal deposit. These institutions do not collect all the
                  Twitter data, but have Twitter archives linked to their archiving perimeters.
                  Although these archives are really valuable, they are biased on choices that do
                  not necessarily coincide with the expectations of researchers. One respondent to
                  our survey revealed the potential use of the French BnF archives, whilst
                  underlining certain limitations: <quote rend="inline">I generally find it very
                     difficult to work on traces, and particularly old ones. I use the BnF web
                     archives, but the search tool isn’t very good. On top of that, anything that
                     isn’t from ‘public’ pages isn’t archived</quote> (ICS interview, May 2018).
                  This may lead to research questions that are based on the availability of relevant
                  archives (thus merely updating questions that researchers have already been aware
                  of for some time). <quote rend="inline" source="#schafer2018">The idea of the
                     patrimonial value of web content</quote> influences the criteria for
                  safeguarding data and <quote source="#schafer2018" rend="inline">threatens the
                     existence of content that does not fit the criteria set by web archiving
                     organisations for the preservation of data [...]. Certain contents and formats
                     can also be excluded – this is particularly true of images in 1990s web
                     archives, and also banner advertising and pop-ups</quote>
                  <ptr target="#schafer2018" loc="53"/>.</p>
               <p>This small overview of the ways researchers can access social networks sources
                  (researcher's collect, use of sample made by others, purchase of data,
                  institution’s collections) already underline several challenges in terms of
                  sustainability and highlight several temporalities at stake: <list
                     type="unordered">
                     <item>Researchers (and librarians) who collect data in real time in Twitter run
                        the risk of lacking distance and potentially overlooking important trends.
                        As explained by Thomas Drugeon, who works at INA in France and launched an
                        emergency Twitter collection during the Charlie Hebdo attack in 2015: <quote
                           rend="block">I added hashtags to the collection at lunchtime on the day
                           after the events in the editorial offices at Charlie Hebdo. We acted more
                           quickly for the events of 13 November. The Twitter flows weren’t
                           organised in quite the same way either. The hashtags were more varied in
                           November, whereas in January nearly everything was concentrated on the
                           #jesuischarlie hashtag. In November, at least five hashtags emerged and
                           we could observe movements, cycles too, for example day/night reflecting
                           the different time zones at international level. For #jesuischarlie we
                           missed the peak at the beginning. [...] Valérie Schafer: And did you also
                           collect #jesuisahmed, #jenesuispascharlie? Thomas Drugeon: No, we didn’t
                           capture them ourselves, but we could access them indirectly, as a side
                           effect. We didn’t want to start adding hashtags along the way as we
                           wanted to make sure that we would have a homogeneous set.<note>
                              <ref target="https://asap.hypotheses.org/173#more-173"
                                 >https://asap.hypotheses.org/173#more-173</ref>. Interview
                              conducted during the Asap project dedicated to the born-digital
                              heritage of Paris terrorist attacks, in 2016 (our
                           translation).</note></quote></item>
                     <item>Researchers who react after an event will not be able to fully access
                        data unless they buy them from Twitter or use datasets which were created by
                        others (where available), may they be individuals or librarians. Researchers
                        then face other challenges: although the datasets may be documented,
                        stressing the importance of metadata <ptr target="#pomerantz2015"/>, they
                        are reliant on the choices of others – maybe even robots.</item>
                     <item>As pointed out by Thomas Bottini and Virginie Julliard, who used INA
                        archives to analyze the semiotic dimension of the <q>gender theory
                           controversy</q> that played out on Twitter,<note>As underlined by their
                           abstract, <quote rend="inline">this paper sets out the method developed
                              in a study that explores the production of Gender during the
                              controversy over <q>Gender theory,</q> on Twitter. The method
                              articulates semiotics and computer science to further our
                              understanding of how the techno-editorial properties of this
                              micro-blogging platform influence that production.</quote> The
                           controversy emerged after the adoption in May 2013 of a law allowing
                           same-sex marriage. It has sparked much debates, some of them linked to
                           gender studies, whose opponents depicted as a <q>gender
                           theory.</q></note> researchers need to <quote rend="inline">consider the
                           often non-explicit archiving logic of these databases, as well as changes
                           in their architecture and editorial policies</quote>
                        <ptr target="#bottini2017" loc="47"/>. The massive availability of data in
                        archiving collections is not synonymous with <quote rend="inline"
                           >turnkey</quote> corpora <ptr target="#barats2016"/>
                        <ptr target="#brunet2012"/> as collecting involves specific criteria and
                        curation, which claim for a knowledge of archiving choices.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Coping with the sheer volume of data is a further challenge. The Info-RSN project,
                  funded by the French National Research Agency (ANR), which focused on the
                  circulation and sharing of information on Twitter and changes in journalism <ptr
                     target="#mercier2018"/>, may help to illustrate this problem. The researchers
                  used a private company to collect the data, i.e. all the tweets that contained a
                  URL link to one of the 31 French news entities included in the survey. The raw
                  data collected corresponded to roughly 40 million tweets, and it took one and a
                  half years to develop tools and ultimately obtain a final corpus of 17 million
                  tweets (after the elimination of duplicates and tweets that were outside the
                  research criteria).</p>
               <p>From a methodological point of view, building large datasets renews the
                  traditional criteria mobilised for the constitution of research corpora
                  (representativeness, exhaustiveness, homogeneity, etc.). The heterogeneous nature
                  of data (alphanumeric, audio, visual or timestamped data), their ephemerality
                  (including for the short term), the design-specific limitations of platforms
                  (websites, socio-digital networks, internet portals), and finally the
                  hardware-specific nature of devices and means of reception (computers, tablets,
                  smartphones) make corpus-building a highly complex and critical hermeneutic
                  practice. For researchers working with open access datasets, it can be difficult
                  to detect the blind spots of a search query or to reconstruct the selection
                  criteria that have informed the creation of the corpus. The archiving of Twitter
                  by the BnF and INA can serve as a speaking example here again. INA compiles its
                  archive through the public Twitter API, whereas the BnF uses Heritrix - the
                  crawler also used by Internet Archive and many libraries around the world. The
                  results are very different in terms of data as well as metadata: the BnF’s Twitter
                  archives look more like screenshots, whereas the INA collections are more
                  flexible, allowing comparisons of metadata while giving access to results that no
                  longer look like the original tweet. This may be a disadvantage or not, depending
                  on the type of research being conducted: studying a Facebook or Twitter news feed
                  from a semiotic and discursive point of view requires being able to retain the
                  format of the broadcast.</p>
               <p>Despite their apparent accessibility digitised texts also raise challenges. Some
                  of them are common with born-digital heritage. Some databases are unstable over
                  time. This is the case of private press databases like Factiva,<note>
                     <ref target="https://professional.dowjones.com/factiva/"
                        >https://professional.dowjones.com/factiva/</ref>
                  </note> which depend on agreements concluded between the publisher of the database
                  and the owners of the data that is collected. Digitisation is not neutral either,
                  and affects the digitised text <ptr target="#fohr2017"/> from a semiotic point of
                  view: <cit><quote rend="block">The source text [...] is then turned into various
                        types of semiotic text, including a first, the <q>digital</q> text per se,
                        in which it is encoded using 0s and 1s. This text is generally illegible for
                        humans. A second, known as an <q>image text,</q> can be displayed on a
                        screen or printed on paper and read as such, but any analysis of this
                        version is typically <q>manual.</q> Then come the dynamic text, the
                        annotated text and the edited text, and finally the readable, analysable
                        text. So [...] digitisation does not produce a single <q>digital</q> copy of
                        the text, but an entire galaxy of digitised texts which, interlinked and
                        organised hierarchically, open up new avenues for interpretation and
                        analysis.</quote><ptr target="#meunier2018"/></cit> Factiva, for example,
                  collects and digitises the texts without preserving the layout and format of
                  distribution. These choices should be accessible to researchers whether they are
                  stable or not. Etienne Brunet compared the Frantext<note>This database includes
                     more than 5000 references to French works or texts from the 10thto the 21st
                     century, and over 251 million words. See <ref target="https://www.frantext.fr/"
                        >https://www.frantext.fr/</ref>. </note> textual database with the French
                  works on Google books. Frantext provides the researcher with a defined and
                  explicit database for collection criteria <ptr target="#brunet2012"/>.</p>
               <p>Dealing with datasets as <q>sources</q> for humanities and social sciences
                  research not only requires a critical understanding of the production and
                  indexical logic of databases and its structured information, but also a
                  hermeneutic reflection on the dual nature of digital data as both content
                     <emph>and</emph> form. <quote rend="inline">When working with digital objects
                     it’s essential to remember that what they look like on the screen is a
                     performance,</quote> says Trevor Owens <ptr target="#owens2020" loc="6"/>, head
                  of the Digital Content Management department at the Library of Congress in
                  Washington D.C. Next to the challenge of determining the authenticity of data in
                  terms of their physical integrity, one has to consider the performative volatility
                  of data representations in different formats and on different devices. New skills
                  such as interface criticism which make us think about the framing of <quote
                     rend="inline">in-form-ation</quote>
                  <ptr target="#drucker2014"/> are therefore necessary in order to critically
                  evaluate the <quote rend="inline">integrity of representation</quote> of digital
                  data <ptr target="#fohr2017"/>.</p>
               <p>Finally, there is also the question of internal metadata and of metadata <ptr
                     target="#pomerantz2015"/> added by the researcher during her/his annotations.
                  Regarding the first ones, let’s mention the case of retweets. Although retweets
                  are useful to study the popularity or even the virality of a tweet, the number of
                  retweets that researchers may find in Web archives is linked to the exact time the
                  tweet was archived, meaning that they may miss the real popularity of a given
                  tweet if it was archived at the beginning of its dissemination and before the
                  climax of its popularity. Regarding the second ones <ptr target="#salvador2017"/>,
                  the durability of taxonomies and their readability remain a central question: the
                  choice of metadata and taxonomy is not always stable even within an organisation
                  and this can make longitudinal or diachronic approaches more difficult, as the
                  researcher has to consider not only changes in the Web, but also in its archiving,
                  interfaces, supports, algorithms, descriptions and taxonomies. A rigorous
                  documentation of metadata is therefore needed to facilitate searchability,
                  analysis and quotations.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>1.2 Long-term preservation, trial and error</head>
               <p>Another question we addressed in our surveys is: what happens to the data at the
                  end of the project? In the field of biology, Timothy H. Vines and his team
                  conducted a survey on data sustainability through the analysis of 516 articles
                  published from 1991 to 2011. They noted that scientific data are lost two years
                  after the publication of an article, after which the chances of accessing
                  scientific data would fall by 17% per year. This was mainly due to the failure of
                  storage tools or obsolete email addresses that prevented any contact with the
                  authors <ptr target="#vines2014" loc="95"/>. Is the situation different in social
                  sciences and humanities? Probably not! The answers to our survey show a great
                  difficulty when it comes to implementing a sustainable storage and sharing
                  approach in a medium and the long-term perspective (i.e. periods of up to ten
                  years or beyond ten years, respectively).</p>
               <p>A first finding of ours is, that testimonials show a focus on the “here and now”
                  rather than on future uses of research data. The mastering of data and tools is
                  often driven by a learning-by-doing approach, shifting the focus to pragmatic
                  solutions rather than investing time into more fundamental speculations about open
                  science in a sustainable perspective. Many researchers highlight the large amount
                  of short-term difficulties: <quote rend="inline">I don’t have much time to think
                     about the long term, because I am too busy with my current collection and
                     analysis problems! And above all, I don’t have the time or the technical means
                     to go into it in detail</quote> (ICS interview, May 2018). However, many of the
                  scholars interviewed keep screenshots on their computers and external hard drives.
                  They do their own archiving, but without sharing it or without any guarantee that
                  they will be able to transfer their archives from one machine to another in order
                  to preserve the data. This problem is sometimes <q>solved</q> by the use of online
                  storage and sharing tools (OwnCloud, Dropbox, Google Drive, Huma-Num), <quote
                     rend="inline">for practical reasons but without any real thought about the long
                     term, especially after the project has ended</quote> (ICS interview, July
                  2018).</p>
               <p>But doing research is of course an iterative process that comes with a lot of
                  surprises and unforeseen challenges which force the researcher to adapt methods
                  and tools as the project progresses. It would be an error to underestimate the
                  researcher’s adaptability and flexibility in this regard. As one historian
                  confessed: <quote rend="inline">My current project (traces of the First World War
                     on Twitter) was not originally designed as a research project. So initially,
                     data archiving, storage and so on were not part of my plan. Today, they are
                     increasingly central to my reasoning, as the project will end in 2019. For
                     archiving, I can use the DH Now project. I also think that adapting to the GDPR
                     is something to contemplate for the long term</quote> (History interview, May
                  2018).</p>
               <p>In terms of maintenance let’s return to the trio of data, corpus and results we
                  underlined: they all can have similar stakes, but they involve different actors,
                  research problems and management methods. Institutions such as the BnF preserve
                  the data, without necessarily keeping the corpus created by the researchers. This
                  complementary approach is currently being explored in the Internet Lab platform
                  (made available to the researchers of the Web90 and ASAP projects in 2016), or in
                  the prospective study conducted by <ref target="#moiraghi2018">Moiraghi
                     (2018)</ref>. Although data maintenance can be carried out by legal
                  repositories and institutions, it can also be a private sector initiative, for
                  example, for the Newsgroups of the Usenet community: these exchanges between early
                  adopters of computer-mediated communications are a rich source of information for
                  digital historians, and the maintenance of this data is entirely dependent upon
                  Google’s interest in preserving these exchanges. Yet users were rapidly
                  disappointed by the organisation of these archives, which were experienced as
                  unclear and difficult to use and search <ptr target="#poulsen2009"/>. Camille
                  Paloque-Bergès notes that <quote rend="inline">the non-standardised archives of
                     the Web are the result of the succession of transitional and informal states of
                     digitalised document cycles; this succession is due to the development of
                        <q>wild</q> documentation on the Internet before professional archivists
                     started their work</quote>
                  <ptr target="#paloque-berges2017"/>.</p>
               <p>The problem of citability of research data and final research outputs is of course
                  not a new one. As Emmanuelle Bermès (BnF) noted, this concern existed way before
                  the era of digitalisation: from 2006 onwards, the BnF was concerned about the
                  sustainability of identifiers, notably for websites. A choice had to be made
                  between <q>opaque identifiers</q> based on existing standards such as UUID
                  (Universal Unique Identifier), or more <q>significant</q> identifiers that
                  facilitated the citability and accessibility of resources. <quote rend="inline"
                     >This duality illustrates the problem libraries have always had: the dilemma of
                     choosing between communication and conservation</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bermès2006"/> (our translation). There are further issues to
                  address: <quote rend="inline">Indeed, sustainability and unicity both have a
                     problem of scale. It is now commonly accepted that identifiers can be reused
                     for different websites or even destroyed on the web. Sustainability cannot
                     therefore be considered as ensuring that data is ‘eternal’, but rather that it
                        <q>lasts long enough</q> for the needs of the institution managing the
                     resource</quote> (<ref target="#bermès2006">idem</ref>). Sustainability
                  therefore involves other challenges such as the independence of the authority
                  maintaining the data or the ability to integrate pre-existing models and envision
                  post-existing models.</p>
               <p>Maintenance requires the consideration of both the temporality of the research
                  questions, methods, and tools and of the stakeholders and users involved. It
                  requires time, effort and resources that are rarely available to researchers if
                  not planned from the outset. It is rare for the researcher’s institution to carry
                  out this maintenance. Researchers may therefore decide to rely on <hi
                     rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> solutions. However, the question of the
                  responsibility for data preservation remains: within an institutional framework,
                  research is not the sole property of researchers. They could rightly argue that
                  there is a mutual obligation of maintenance within the institution they have
                  developed their research. Yet such solutions have been more often provided for
                  article repositories and platforms than for research data. In this respect a
                  system like HAL<note>
                     <ref target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/"
                        >https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/</ref>
                  </note> in France offers an effective response that is increasingly used by
                  researchers for making articles available through open access (preprints, author
                  drafts, final publications, etc.). Similarly, sound archive repositories, like the
                     <q>Phonothèque</q> at the MMSH (the Maison méditerranéenne des sciences de
                  l’homme, or Mediterranean Centre for Humanities),<note>
                     <ref
                        target="http://phonotheque.mmsh.huma-num.fr/dyn/portal/index.seam;jsessionid=ba99be050dd4cea60bb98fbe5e32?page=home&amp;"
                        >http://phonotheque.mmsh.huma-num.fr/dyn/portal/index.seam;jsessionid=ba99be050dd4cea60bb98fbe5e32?page=home&amp;</ref>
                  </note> offer a means of heritagising and preserving collections. But there are
                  hardly any integrated solutions for projects using heterogeneous data. It is worth
                  noting that various new solutions are under consideration at national level in
                  France, for example the <quote rend="inline">feasibility study for a [shared]
                     warehousing service for simple data.</quote><note>
                     <ref
                        target="https://www.ouvrirlascience.fr/principes-et-lignes-directrices-de-locde-pour-lacces-aux-donnees-de-la-recherche-financee-sur-fonds-publics/"
                        >https://www.ouvrirlascience.fr/principes-et-lignes-directrices-de-locde-pour-lacces-aux-donnees-de-la-recherche-financee-sur-fonds-publics/</ref>
                  </note> The way this study will deal with <title rend="quotes">Big Data, Little
                     Data, No Data</title>
                  <ptr target="#borgman2015"/> and with the precise scope of <q>simple data</q>
                  remains to be seen, as in practice it is generally for complex data that
                  researchers need help and support. But there are also question marks as to the
                  need to create new solutions rather than building on existing ones proposed by
                  research infrastructures in this area and to the utility of a nationwide scheme
                  for an issue that is of international or global scope (not least because of
                  cross-border research projects).</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>2. Conflicting temporalities and distributed materialities</head>

            <p>As mentioned in the introduction, the different temporalities of research practices
               and preservation initiatives have to be problematised in order to tackle the problem
               of readability and intelligibility of research data in a long-term perspective.
               Dealing with digital sources or data in terms of sustainability requires taking into
               consideration the historicity of the <quote rend="inline">layered</quote> or <quote
                  rend="inline">distributed</quote> materiality <ptr target="#blanchette2011"/> of
               digital datasets and objects, which is characterised by the interweaving of hardware
               and software environments. As Johanna Drucker has stressed, <quote rend="inline">the
                  distributed concept requires attention to the many layers and relationships of
                  hardware, software, bandwidth, processing, storage, memory, and other factors. The
                  distributed approach registers a shift from materiality grounded in a single
                  feature or factor to an approach based on multiple systems of interrelated
                  activity</quote>
            	<ptr target="#drucker2013" loc="¶21"/>. Although the interviews show that
               the colleagues interviewed take various dimensions of the distributed materiality of
               digital artefacts into account, the solutions are fragmented and often specific to
               individual researchers or a project, rather than shared and disseminated.</p>
            <div>
               <head>2.1 Tools’ evolution and obsolescence</head>
               <p>The interviews we conducted indicate that researchers use a wide range of data
                  analysis tools (Nvivo, Iramuteq, Gephi, etc.), and also reveal tools developed by
                  researchers. Thomas Bottini and Virginie Julliard developed their own tool to
                  observe the semiotic dimension of the controversy around gender studies on
                  Twitter. This raises the question of the long-term registration of these <quote
                     rend="inline">custom-made</quote> tools, their diffusion and their readability
                  in the medium term <ptr target="#bottini2017"/>. This is true for the case of the
                  Calico project (communities of e-learning, instrumentation and collaboration),
                  which ran from 2006 to 2009 and examined distance learning platforms and online
                  discussion lists <ptr target="#blondel2011"/>. A set of analytical tools were
                  developed during this project which are no longer available – be it because of
                  professional mobility of researchers or the lack of funding to maintain the tools.
                  This lack of sustainability directly affects the readability and the
                  intelligibility of the results of this research project.</p>
               <p>As noticed by J. Smithies and al. <quote rend="inline">digital projects benefit
                     from being planned and executed with their longevity in mind from the
                     start</quote>
                  <ptr target="#smithies2019" loc="8"/>. The consideration of collection
                  environments and conditions as well as the documentation work may enrich
                  reflections on the choices of the observable elements <ptr target="#fuchs2018"/>
                  and the choice of methodologies <ptr target="#paveau2014"/>
                  <ptr target="#venturini2014"/>. A good illustration of this point is an ANR-funded
                  research project on online petitioning. The research group behind this project
                  (Pluridisciplinary Analysis of On Line Petitioning) had access to data from one of
                  the main French-speaking online petitioning websites (lapetition.be): the dataset
                  included 12,000 petitions which had received a total of 3.25 million signatures
                  over the period between 31 October 2006 and 12 February 2015. The richness of the
                  data (data entered by Internet users and generated by the system), as well as
                  their heterogeneity (alphanumeric data, number of signatories, site sections and
                  forms, etc.), led to the development of different approaches, both qualitative
                  (interviews with the designer, <q>manual</q> analyses) and quantitative (textual
                  statistical tools), in order to look at the characteristics of online petitioning
                  as well as the limitations and incentives induced by the system that affect the
                  petitioning dynamic. The interviews proved to be essential in order to assess the
                  stability of the system over time and avoid bias in interpreting the collected
                  data. Before the end of the project, i.e. 2018, the website was no longer
                  accessible, confirming the importance of taking screenshots in order to be able to
                  contextualise the data <ptr target="#barats2016"/>. This example underlines the
                  crucial importance of documentation – and the emergence of data stewards as a new
                  and promising profession in the field of digital humanities. As query tools evolve
                  over time and can thus change data collection conditions, a professional
                  documentation of the creation of research data should not only provide technical
                  information (standards, protocols, formats), but must include search modalities
                  used to constitute the corpora. The lack of <quote rend="inline">thick
                     description</quote> of both the metadata and the process of gathering,
                  curating, and publishing or recontextualising research data is certainly one of
                  the biggest risks when it comes to the long-term and sustainable contribution of
                  digital humanities research to the long tradition of <quote rend="inline"
                     >analogue</quote> knowledge production in humanities and social sciences <ptr
                     target="#toth-czifra2020"/>.</p>
               <p>Until now, historians had been probably better protected from the obsolescence of
                  their sources than their counterparts working with contemporary data, but they are
                  now increasingly concerned by this risk. The ANR Web90<note>
                     <ref target="https://web90.hypotheses.org/le-projet-web90"
                        >https://web90.hypot</ref>
                     <ref target="https://web90.hypotheses.org/le-projet-web90"
                        >heses.org/le-projet-web90</ref>
                  </note> project carried out from 2014 to 2018 is a prime example: when it was
                  launched in 2014, searches conducted in the Web archives (may it be the Wayback
                  Machine of Internet Archive or collections of national institutions) only allowed
                  URL requests. Subsequently, the BnF implemented a full-text search in its
                  archives, thus widening the search capacities, affecting the results and
                  influencing data analysis. In addition to changes in data access and the
                  consequent disruption caused by full text and the possibility of classifying the
                  results according to different facets (time, format, domain name), other
                  additional tools provided an answer to a blatant problem: the temporally disparate
                  composition of archived pages, which included anachronistic elements that had not
                  been updated (for example, calendars that are not routinely re-archived for
                  reasons of duplication, etc) <ptr target="#brugger2018"/>. Internet Archive
                  recently introduced a system to date the archives of each element making up a
                     webpage,<note>See the article posted by the Internet Archive foundation
                     (05/10/2017): <title rend="quotes">Wayback Machine Playback… now with
                        Timestamps!</title>
                     <ref
                        target="https://blog.archive.org/2017/10/05/wayback-machine-playback-now-with-timestamps/"
                        >https://blog.archive.org/2017/10/05/wayback-machine-playback-now-with-timestamps/</ref>
                  </note> thus removing the opacity of these temporal patchworks. It is also
                  important to document collection tools - they may sometimes exclude advertisings,
                  gifs or emoticons in the case of automatic collection tools - or consultation
                  terminals that modify the display of data, a central aspect in the case of works
                  that emphasise a semiotic perspective. In the Web archives it should be noted that
                  the fonts and characters may also differ from the original pages, as enlightened
                  by Musiani et al.: <quote rend="inline">If at the time of archiving, a Web page
                     font was not written explicitly in its original source code, but rather used by
                     default, the default settings set by the browser in its current version will
                     appear on the archived page</quote>
                  <ptr target="#musiani2019"/>. Archiving data can also remove the original
                  formatting of the platform. This is the case, for example, for Twitter data stored
                  by INA as explained earlier: the form and the interface are not preserved, because
                  the choices that have prevailed favour manageability and interoperability between
                  the data. It is also important to note that the archiving or displaying of data
                  can evolve over time: initially, INA archived emojis but did not display in the
                  results to researchers, thus removing the heterogeneity and complexity of data
                  that is characteristic of web writings <ptr target="#halte2016"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2.2 Temporalities of users</head>
               <p>One respondent noted that the main difficulty <quote rend="inline">is to
                     reconstruct the temporal dynamics of the discussions studied (often I only have
                     access to the final data)</quote> (ICS interview, May 2018). Elements that have
                  not been collected have to be reconstructed to account for the complexity of the
                     <term>dispositif</term>
                  <note>The French term <term>dispositif</term>, as defined by Michel Foucault, is
                     sometimes translated as apparatus. See <ref target="#callewaert2017">Callewaert
                        (2017)</ref>: <quote rend="inline">I use the French term
                           <term>dispositif</term>, even in English, because I feel the usual
                        translations such as <q>apparatus</q> or <q>deployment</q> are misleading
                        when used in connection with Foucault’s texts. These terms contained
                        different meaning in the trend of philosophy in France at the time of the
                        development of the term dispositif.</quote></note> and its functionalities.
                  This was undertaken by the INA, who collected data collection limit messages via
                  Twitter’s public API and developed documentation on missing data. Research on the
                  history of the Web has also shown that it is difficult (but not impossible) to
                  identify the users of 1990s Newsgroups and establish their sociological profile,
                  or even to consider the representativeness of their posts. The same question could
                  arise for Twitter’s archives and its users. Preservation is also about the
                  readability of the article in the future. Therefore, one should also consider
                  future users. A publication may describe facts that may no longer be
                  readable/understandable fifty years later, as the digital environment studied has
                  evolved or even disappeared. If we imagine, for example, the disappearance of
                  Twitter, how could we guarantee the documentation of the data in such a way as to
                  reproduce their context and their techno-semiotic environment? This is already the
                  case when reading an article about the Minitel - a videotext system broadly used
                  in the 80s and 90s in France, with students, especially strangers to the French
                  context, who have absolutely no knowledge of the technical ecosystem and the small
                  beige box. Some current analyses can be difficult to understand even now:
                  hyperlink analysis and maps can lack readability, for example in the field of
                  scientific controversies when the data are not visible. This difficulty could be
                  further accentuated if Gephi, Iramuteq or Lexico, are no longer usable, or even
                  documentable. If the tools as well as the data disappear, is the analysis still
                  readable? The design of the tools and <term>dispositifs</term>, studied for
                  example by <ref target="#monnoyer-smith2016">Monnoyer-Smith (2016)</ref> or <ref
                     target="#mabi2016">Mabi (2016)</ref>, introduce restrictions and develop a
                  specific type of research and results (graphs, clouds, link maps <ptr
                     target="#plantin2013"/>), which also claim for digital hermeneutics.</p>
               <p>In addition to the different temporalities of research data and the distributed
                  materiality of the research devices and infrastructures, there are also temporal
                  questions that are specific to the individual experiences of researchers. Amongst
                  the researchers who were especially sensitive to data sustainability in our
                  survey, one colleague – who has the ability to carry out <quote rend="inline"><hi
                        rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> programming and programming for the exploitation
                     of XML databases</quote> (DH and Language interview, May 2018) – has been
                  particularly attentive to sustainability issues: <cit><quote rend="block">In
                        general, we deal with the volatility of the data on a day-to-day basis: we
                        have transferred our servers three times. Part of the corpus data is hosted
                        on personal servers, outside the research institutions. However, we are
                        fortunate to have redundant servers in the laboratory that we manage
                        internally: all our data are saved in XML format (txt) that is always
                        accessible and guarantees their use in the long-term, and in a compressed
                        form that goes from one server to another several times a day. In each of
                        our projects, a substantial part of out funding is earmarked for 1 / the
                        legal protection of the data, ensuring the sharing and the diffusion of the
                        data entered (without confiscation) and 2 / the saving of data without a
                        subscription (even if the data is hosted by a provider to avoid giving
                        priority to one university project over another. No <q>cloud</q> storage is
                        used, but hard drives are purchased and CRON backup programming is used on
                        the websites of both project partners, etc.) Each time, the solution is to
                        reinvent, according to the type of financing and the project itself: an
                        editorial project? A <q>pure data</q> project? etc.</quote> (DH and Language
                     Interview, May 2018)</cit></p>
               <p>The capacity to think about data maintenance and the constant reworking of ideas
                  seems to develop as soon as the researcher is no longer in <q>discovery mode</q>
                  and fully immersed into the difficult daily control of tools and data (as
                  underlined by one respondent to our survey: <quote rend="inline">[...] It has been
                     more difficult since I started trying to integrate source code into the
                     analysis for critical code studies. However, I am interested in discourse, the
                     practices and the uses - accessing the source code and becoming familiar with
                     it can help to understand the active role code plays in human-machine
                     interactions</quote> (ICS interview, July 2018)). For those starting a
                  DH-project with rather limited technical or data management skills, the need for
                  support by computer scientists and engineers might be a necessity right from the
                  start of a project. As underlined by a researcher in ICS: <quote rend="inline"
                     >Accessing (and processing) data seems increasingly dependent either on
                     researchers learning IT methods that are not part of their initial background
                     and that may be costly to acquire, or on working in conjunction with computer
                     scientists (technicians, engineers or researchers) whose methods and research
                     interests may be significantly different. We may therefore witness a narrowing
                     of research aims or questions because of the need to master certain
                     tools</quote> (ICS Interview, May 2018).</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>3. Open Access and Digital Wastelands</head>

            <p>National and international research infrastructures and institutions are seeking to
               provide answers to the transformations that challenge current research. The French Progedo<note>
                  <ref target="http://www.progedo.fr/progedo/">http://www.progedo.fr/progedo/</ref>
               </note> VRLI (Very Large Research Infrastructure for production and management of
               data) was created to preserve survey data. In the United States, Harvard University
               has initiated Dataverse,<note>
                  <ref target="https://dataverse.org/about">https://dataverse.org/about</ref>
               </note> a social science data storage project intended to facilitate Web access to
               verified web and non-web data and ensure their preservation <ptr target="#king2007"
               />. Similarly, to name but a few, the CESSDA (Consortium of European Social Science
               Data Archives) has added sustainability to its main objectives,<note>See <ref
                     target="https://www.cessda.eu/About">https://www.cessda.eu/About</ref>
               </note> while OPERAS, a European Research Infrastructure for the development of open
               scholarly communication in the social sciences and humanities, and COPIM
               (Community-led Open Publication Infrastructures for Monographs) have recently been
               launched.</p>
            <p>Despite such initiatives, at present, most born-digital heritage of HSS research is
               unequally preserved. While mailing lists and some research projects have been
               particularly well preserved,<note>See for example <ref
                     target="http://liste.theuth.fr/">http://liste.theuth.fr/</ref> (archives of
                  this mailinglist are available from 2004). See also the astonishing stability and
                  durability of a founder public history project: The Valley of the Shadow, launched
                  from 1993. <ref target="http://valley.lib.virginia.edu/"
                     >http://valley.lib.virginia.edu</ref>
               </note> a quick look at the archives of digital research projects on the Web reveals
               many broken links. Some researchers have tackled these issues, including <ref
                  target="#nanni2017">Nanni (2017)</ref>, who in <title rend="quotes">Reconstructing
                  a website’s lost past - Methodological issues concerning the history of
                  www.unibo.it</title> explains his efforts to rebuild the evolution of the website
               of the University of Bologna, which has lost much of its content. The challenges
               linked to the loss of devices or digital materials and software can no longer be
               ignored; this includes CD Roms during the 80s and 90s, floppy disks, etc. Whilst
               emulation is often carried out for data archiving, it is rarely achieved for
               production and valorisation.</p>
            <div>
               <head>3.1 Sharing and Open Access</head>
               <p>Open access is central to the concerns of researchers and of publishers, but is
                  also of importance to European funders, especially in the framework of H2020
                  projects, thus continuing a movement that began with early initiatives such as ArXiv<note>
                     <ref target="https://arxiv.org/">https://arxiv.org</ref>
                  </note> in the field of physics or biology. Although this study does not intend to
                  detail the policies of open access in Social and Human Sciences, it is important
                  to note that these policies are a quintessentially economic and political
                  challenges <ptr target="#cotte2017"/>. This is a regular subject of debate <ptr
                     target="#girard2017"/>
                  <ptr target="#valluy2017"/>, which leaves researchers faced with a paradoxical
                  demand: <quote rend="inline">first, to publish, then publish more, in highly rated
                     journals, in journals that are increasingly evaluated, graded, ranked and
                     second, to make results public, disseminate them to as many people as possible,
                     get them online as quickly as possible</quote>
                  <ptr target="#farchy2010"/> (our translation).</p>
               <p>Open access has found its way through platforms like the French multidisciplinary
                  open archive HAL<note>
                     <ref target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/"
                        >https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/</ref>
                  </note> or the research notebooks platform Hypotheses.<note>
                     <ref target="https://fr.hypotheses.org/">https://fr.hypotheses.org/</ref>
                  </note> These collaborative efforts have definitely fostered best practices and
                  paved the way for a greater acceptance of open access publication and data
                  sharing. Sure, one could argue that the maintenance and the searchability of these
                  platforms aren’t free from biases and institutional dependences too. However,
                  these biases and dependences appears less worrying than the ones specific for
                  private companies with their opaque and questionable system of ranking, visibility
                  and referencing. Beyond the independence of these academic databases, attention
                  needs to be paid to questions of interoperability of data formats. But like the
                  open access, interoperability comes at a price regarding policies of
                  standardisation, negotiations and debates they may raise, technical developments
                  and implementation, updates, gateways, etc., and the human effort it implies. The
                  question of the economic model is clearly posed when funded researchers can
                  publish articles in open access by paying publishers, while others are prevented
                  from doing so because they are unable to pay the high fees.<note>See <ref
                        target="https://blogs.mediapart.fr/edition/au-coeur-de-la-recherche/article/130418/transition-vers-l-acces-libre-le-piege-des-accords-globaux-avec-les-editeur"
                        >https://blogs.mediapart.fr/edition/au-coeur-de-la-recherche/article/130418/transition-vers-l-acces-libre-le-piege-des-accords-globaux-avec-les-editeur</ref>.
                     Interesting resources on this broad debate are also available at: <ref
                        target="http://blogs.lse.ac.uk/impactofsocialsciences/"
                        >http://blogs.lse.ac.uk/impactofsocialsciences/</ref>. </note></p>
               <p>The question of open access is crucial at all stages of research: it entails
                  strong constraints (as well as opportunities) for the researcher before, during
                  and after the research process, and requires not only specific means (research
                  engineers, data collection tools and short- and long-term storage) but also a
                  detailed knowledge of the rules applying to data sharing (which were for example
                  renewed within European legislation by the recent GDPR - General Data Protection Regulation).<note>
                     <ref target="https://ec.europa.eu/info/law/law-topic/data-protection/reform_fr"
                        >https://ec.europa.eu/info/law/law-topic/data-protection/reform_fr</ref>
                  </note> These rules also evolve over time, when some works enter the public
                  domain. Controversy may sometimes appear, as seen in the debates between <ptr
                     target="#ertzscheid2015"/> and the Anne Frank Foundation. The researcher who
                  currently uses web archives from archival institutions may for her/his part be
                  frustrated by the legal impossibility to copy archives due to intellectual
                  property rights. But he/she can find comfort in the knowledge that they will be
                  traceable through permalinks.</p>
               <p>As <ref target="#zimmer2010">Zimmer (2010)</ref> pointed out in the case of
                  Facebook, this sharing and quotability raise issues of anonymity. Anonymity can be
                  waived by search engines and betrayed by the cited data – despite the best
                  intentions of researchers <ptr target="#latzko-toth2013"/>. It is therefore
                  necessary to anticipate any obstacles to anonymisation, which vary according to
                  the type of data. This difficulty was encountered by the group of researchers
                  working on the ANR-funded project on online petitioning <ptr target="#barats2016"/>.<note>
                     <ref target="http://textopol.u-pec.fr/anr-appel/"
                        >http://textopol.u-pec.fr/anr-appel/</ref> and <ref
                        target="http://textopol.u-pec.fr/anr-appel/index.php/2017/09/19/podcasts-de-la-journee-journee-appel-sur-le-cadre-juridique-applicable-aux-traitements-de-donnees-a-caractere-personnel/"
                        >http://textopol.u-pec.fr/anr-appel/index.php/2017/09/19/podcasts-de-la-journee-journee-appel-sur-le-cadre-juridique-applicable-aux-traitements-de-donnees-a-caractere-personnel/</ref>
                  </note> As mentioned earlier, thanks an agreement with the manager of an
                  e-petitioning platform, this project had access to the entire database and related
                  data (including texts, petitioners, signatories, comments and timestamps) over a
                  period from 2006 to 2016. The data had been previously anonymised (12,000
                  petitions and more than 3 million signatories). However, the researchers quickly
                  realised that entering the quotation of comments by signatories via the Google
                  search engine provided the same information online. The research team had to carry
                  out multiple online checks to be certain before publication that no quotes or
                  excerpts compromised the anonymity of the data, thus restricting the dissemination
                  of results. In addition, the agreement did not allow them to respond to requests
                  for data sharing. This example is typical of the limits of open access to digital
                  data and of the ethical, technical and legal constraints that influence the
                  dissemination of results.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>3.2 <q>404 not found</q> and other challenges raised by time</head>
               <p>Unfortunately, many great digital humanities projects of the past now suffer from
                  their status as <q>digital wasteland.</q> Many research project websites are just
                  abandoned at the end of the project; others may be frozen. However, freezing a
                  project is not sufficient to maintain it or guarantee its sustainability. A good
                  example is the Amsterdam-project DDS (<title rend="italic">De Digital
                  Stad</title>): an online socializing platform created in Amsterdam in the
                  mid-1990s. A team of media archeologists around Gerard Alberts revived the DDS
                  platform using the data that had been preserved, but identified a number of
                  technical issues despite the precautions previously taken: <cit><quote
                        rend="block">On 15–16 January 1996, the DDS servers were down for most of
                        the night to allow for a full backup of De Digitale Stad. A full 1-on-1 disk
                        copy of all the servers running DDS was created on 3 Digital Linear Tapes
                        (DLT). DDS congratulated itself with a city frozen in time, preserved <q>to
                           be studied by archaeologists in a distant future: the FREEZE.</q> [...]
                        In restoring old data, it soon came to light that the package would not
                        simply unwrap, or defrost. The DLT tapes holding the FREEZE did not easily
                        render their content.</quote>
                     <ptr target="#alberts2017"/></cit> The planning of the DDS founders here was
                  remarkable. However, being prepared is not always sufficient to avoid risk. One
                  survey respondent described how the earmarking of funds to store data beyond the
                  end of an international research project was still insufficient to keep the data
                  available on the medium term: <quote rend="inline">The data was hosted by a
                     university institution which could no longer cover the costs of data storage,
                     leading to the loss of all the data. We had planned the financing of data
                     maintenance, but the funding was limited to a ten-year period and could only be
                     temporarily extended, leading to the loss of data that could have been used for
                     future research</quote> (ICS interview, June 2018).</p>
               <p>As we know, many projects stop abruptly or are no longer updated. Although their
                  short-term fate could be considered better than that of the many websites that
                  simply disappear, the high risk of the data disappearing has resulted in multiple
                  preservation efforts. For example, the European Publications Office keeps
                  information about European projects within the CORDIS database,<note>
                     <ref target="https://cordis.europa.eu/">https://cordis.europa.eu</ref>
                  </note> and the websites of these projects can provide extremely useful data for
                  funding bodies, stakeholders or historians interested in the history of science or
                  of the European Union. This determination is also shown by the arquivo.pt website
                  of the Portuguese web archives, which has made an effort to preserve European R
                  &amp; D websites.<note>See <title rend="quotes">Arquivo.pt preserved websites
                        about Research &amp; Development projects funded by the EU</title> on
                     aquivo.pt (10/04/2017). <ref
                        target="http://sobre.arquivo.pt/en/arquivo-pt-preserved-websites-about-research-development-projects-funded-by-the-eu/"
                        >http://sobre.arquivo.pt/en/arquivo-pt-preserved-websites-about-research-development-projects-funded-by-the-eu/</ref>
                  </note></p>
               <p>Some past projects give the feeling that research productions are out of date, but
                  they reflect the state of the digital art of the period: a pioneering 3D
                  production in 1980 rapidly appears to be well below current levels of
                  achievements. Something that was a technical feat in its time becomes one of the
                  first steps of a technique (which may be extremely relevant for analysis by a
                  historian of science). This brings us to a wider examination of obsolescence over
                  time for certain projects and the evaluation of the maintenance efforts necessary
                  to avoid it: this raised the issue of digital databases or research outcomes based
                  on paid images and royalties that must be negotiated on a regular basis.</p>
               <p>It also highlights the broader notion of updatism <ptr target="#pereira2016"/>,
                  which seems inherent to the conflicting temporalities of digital studies. Yet the
                  updating of websites and data are different things. The second case can be
                  illustrated by the Twitter archives concerning the terrorist attacks that occurred
                  in France over the last few years. These archives continue to grow, particularly
                  at INA, as the hashtags are reused by users for tweets about different terrorist
                  attacks or for commemorations, thus continuously producing new results. While
                  living archives are more and more developing <ptr target="#rhodes2013"/>, updatism
                  is a new challenge that may affect the perimeters, the temporalities of projects
                  and even reviews (possibly claiming for post publication reviews<note>Appraisal
                     and revision of a paper occurs or may continue after publication.</note> as a
                  way to reflect the evolving nature of data and knowledge).</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>

            <p><quote rend="inline">Sustainable development is development that meets the needs of
                  the present without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their
                  own needs.</quote> This definition of the concept was formulated by the Brundtland
               Commission in 1987, as commissioned by the UN.ℍ.<note><ref
                     target="https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/content/documents/5987our-common-future.pdf"
                     >https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/content/documents/5987our-common-future.pdf</ref></note></p>
            <p>This definition of sustainable development could be a useful line of thinking in the
               field of human and social sciences, even if it was not designed for this domain. Let
               us take the current example of INA’s policy to homogenise the data and metadata
               resulting from the archiving of socio-digital networks (for example between Twitter
               and Facebook). As explained by Jérôme Thièvre (INA Web Legal Deposit), web archivists
               aim to create common metadata to access Twitter and Facebook archives, despite being
               faced with two different environments and <term>dispositifs</term>. But their work
               has two different goals: beyond the homogenisation of this data / metadata to meet
               the current needs of consultation and cross-checking, they also consider keeping
               other metadata in the <quote rend="inline">back office,</quote> behind the scenes,
               that are not currently available to the researcher but which could be made accessible
               and used for future needs <ptr target="#schafer2018"/>.</p>
            <p>By making the researcher’s <quote rend="inline">toolbox</quote> readable and
               explaining her/his <quote rend="inline">ways of doing things</quote>
               <ptr target="#lecossais2018" loc="8"/>, the working environment and the temporality
               of the research are documented for the long term. This sometimes requires a certain
               curiosity for aspects that can be understated, obscured or considered of little value
               in the production of knowledge but could yet play a role in reinforcing the
               reflective approach that is central to research. The question of the long duration of
               research in comparison to the short cycles of digital innovations and the rapid
               evolution of devices, tools and <term>dispositifs</term> requires to include thinking
               about sustainability into our critical tradition of hermeneutics. Many examples in
               our article are based on born-digital data, although some issues are common to
               retro-digitised archives or digitised collections. However, all these cases involve a
               number of different temporalities (that of data, infrastructure, tools, devices,
               hardware and software, media, research, institutions and funding) and
               multi-stakeholder issues that require collective reflection to clearly identify the
               actors and locations that are best adapted to implement and support the challenges of
               data sustainability. These challenges are deeply transdisciplinary, as evidenced by
               the responses of researchers in ICS, history, sociology, and linguistics.</p>
            <p>Yet they are also interdisciplinary: they require an answer that calls for archivists
               and librarians, ethical and legal approaches and involvement of disciplinary
               expertise. They also claim for awareness-raising and training for researchers, who
               describe the constant tension of dealing with current challenges whilst anticipating
               future issues in research, infrastructure, ethical, legal and political terms. This
               necessary interdisciplinarity poses many difficulties, such as the development of a
               common language that goes beyond technical jargon, as illustrated by the difficulties
               the Bamboo project faced in the United States <ptr target="#dombrowski2014" loc="3"
               />. Finally, these challenges call for taking into account the highly
               internationalised research framework and several environments, such as national data
               protection regulations, where access and protection need to be reconciled, and where
               regulations can also make certain agencies obsolete. All these questions are strongly
               linked to constantly changing legal matters, which are sometimes interpreted in a
               way, as seen in the narrow opposition between the right to memory and the right to be
               forgotten that <ref target="#dulong2017">Dulong de Rosnay and Gadamuz (2017)</ref>
               deconstructed.</p>
            <p>This is also a social and political challenge that brings to light not only funding,
               but also capitalisation on existing structures and scientific legacy to avoid the
               duplication of means, supports and tools. From here onwards, what was seen as the
               constraint of sustainability becomes the challenge to attain efficiency, sharing and
                  responsibility,<note>See the COMETS document (CNRS)<ref
                     target="https://www.univ-paris13.fr/wp-content/uploads/guide_promouvoir_une_recherche_inte_gre_et_responsable_8septembre2014.pdf"
                     >https://www.univ-paris13.fr/wp-content/uploads/guide_promouvoir_une_recherche_inte_gre_et_responsable_8septembre2014.pdf</ref>.</note>
               aiming to also address the inherently ethical issues that could be framed as <quote
                  rend="inline">sustainability ethics</quote>
               <ptr target="#kibert2011"/>.<note>On sustainability ethics: <quote rend="inline">The
                     ethics of sustainability provides a clear sense of the principles that make
                     sustainability more than just a simple problem-solving system, but make it an
                     idea that is grounded in commonly understood ethical principles. In short, the
                     ethics of sustainability provide the moral authority behind sustainability as a
                     fair and equitable approach to making the world a better place.</quote>
                  <ref
                     target="http://rio20.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/Ethics-of-Sustainability-Textbook.pdf"
                     >http://rio20.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/Ethics-of-Sustainability-Textbook.pdf</ref>.
               </note> Although Smithies and al. noticed that <quote rend="inline">maintenance and
                  archiving of digital scholarship is an iterative, continuous process, that does
                  not allow for perfect endings</quote>
               <ptr target="#smithies2019" loc="13"/>, this maintenance, which is well studied in
               infrastructures such as transport <ptr target="#denis2015"/>, should be better
               considered and studied in the domain of knowledge infrastructures. We fully agree
               with <ref target="#russell2018">Russell and Vinsel (2018)</ref> and the maintainers’
               group, who speak out against the fascination with prioritising innovation over
               maintenance. Instead of promoting the rhetorics of newness and digital revolution,
               one should pay more attention to the danger of digital obsolescence and the massive
               fading away of digital data and knowledge.</p>
         </div>

      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="alberts2017" label="Alberts et al. 2017">Alberts, G., Went, M. and Jansma,
               R. <title rend="quotes">Archaeology of the Amsterdam digital city; why digital data
                  are dynamic and should be treated accordingly</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Internet Histories</title>, 1, 1-2 (2017): 146-159.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bachimont2017" label="Bachimont 2017">Bachimont, B. <title rend="italic"
                  >Patrimoine et numérique. Technique et politique de la mémoire</title>. INA
               Editions, Bry-sur-Marne (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="badouard2016" label="Badouard 2016">Badouard R. <title rend="quotes"><q>Je
                     ne suis pas Charlie.</q> Pluralité des prises de parole sur le web et les
                  réseaux sociaux</title>. In P. Lefébure and C. Sécail C. (eds) <title
                  rend="italic">Le défi Charlie. Les médias à l’épreuve des attentats,</title>
               Lemieux Editeur (2016), pp. 187-219.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="barats2016" label="Barats 2016">Barats, C. (ed) <title rend="italic"
                  >Manuel d’analyse du web</title>. Armand Colin, Paris (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baratsetal2016" label="Barats et al. 2016">Barats, C., Dister, A.,
               Gambette, P., Leblanc, J-M., Peres-Leblanc, M. <title rend="quotes">Analyser des
                  pétitions en ligne: potentialités et limites d'un dispositif d'étude
                  pluridisciplinaire</title>, <title rend="italic">JADT</title> 2016, <title
                  rend="italic">Actes des Journées internationales d'Analyse statistique des Données
                  Textuelles</title> (2016). <ref target="http://jadt2016.sciencesconf.org/"
                  >http://jadt2016.sciencesconf.org</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bermès2006" label="Bermès 2006">Bermès, E., <title rend="quotes">Des
                  identifiants pérennes pour les ressources numériques. L’expérience de la
                  BnF</title>, <title rend="italic">BnF</title> (2006) <ref
                  target="http://www.bnf.fr/documents/ark_presentation_bermes_2006.pdf"
                  >http://www.bnf.fr/documents/ark_presentation_bermes_2006.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="blanchette2011" label="Blanchette 2011">Blanchette, J-F. <title
                  rend="quotes">A material history of bits</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of
                  the American Society for Information Science and Technology</title> (2011) <ref
                  target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/asi.21542"
                  >https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/asi.215420</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="blondel2011" label="Blondel et al. 2011">Blondel, F-M., Giguet. E. <title
                  rend="quotes">Analyses et partages de corpus de discussions avec calico- leçons
                  tirées d’une expérience récente</title>. <title rend="italic">EPAL - Echanger
                  Pour Apprendre en Ligne</title>, Jun Grenoble, (2011) <ref
                  target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-02010626/document"
                  >https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-02010626/document</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="borgman2015" label="Borgman 2015">Borgman C. L. <title rend="italic">Big
                  Data, Little Data, No Data</title>. MIT Press, Cambridge MA (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="borghoff2006" label="Borghoff et al. 2006">Borghoff, U., Rödig, P.,
               Scheffczyk, J., Schmitz L. <title rend="italic">Long-Term Preservation of Digital
                  Documents, Principles and Practices</title>. Springer, London (2006).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bottini2017" label="Bottini and Julliard 2017">Bottini T.,Julliard, V.
                  <title rend="quotes">Entre informatique et sémiotique. Les conditions
                  techno-méthodologiques d’une analyse de controverse sur Twitter</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Réseaux</title>, 2017/4: 35-69.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brunet2012" label="Brunet 2012">Brunet, E. <title rend="italic">Au fond du
                  GOOFRE, un gisement de 44 milliards de mots</title>. Conferences Lexicometrica
               (2012) <ref
                  target="http://lexicometrica.univ-paris3.fr/jadt/jadt2012/Conferenciers-invites/Brunet,%20Etienne%20-%20Au%20fond%20du%20GOOFRE.pdf"
                  >http://lexicometrica.univ-paris3.fr/jadt/jadt2012/Conferenciers-invites/Brunet,%20Etienne%20-%20Au%20fond%20du%20GOOFRE.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brugger2018" label="Brügger 2018">Brügger, N. <title rend="italic">The
                  Archived Web. Doing History in the Digital Age</title>. MIT Press, Cambridde MA
               (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="callewaert2017" label="Callewaert 2017">Callewaert, S. <title
                  rend="quotes">Foucault’s Concept of Dispositif</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Praktiskegrunde</title>, 1-2 (2017): 29-52.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="clavert2018" label="Clavert 2018">Clavert, F. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Commémorations, scandale et circulation de l’information: le Centenaire de la
                  bataille de Verdun sur Twitter</title>, <title rend="italic">French Journal for
                  Media Research</title>, 10 (2018) <ref
                  target="http://frenchjournalformediaresearch.com/lodel/index.php?id=1620"
                  >http://frenchjournalformediaresearch.com/lodel/index.php?id=1620</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cotte2017" label="Cotte 2017">Cotte, D. <title rend="quotes">Économies
                  scripturaires, formes documentaires et autorité. Réflexions et esquisse d’analyse
                  des architextes de la <q>science ouverte</q></title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Communication &amp; langages</title>, 2017/2: 117-129.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dacos2012" label="Dacos 2012">Dacos, M. <title rend="quotes">Manifeste des
                  Digital Humanities</title> (2012) <ref target="https://tcp.hypotheses.org/318"
                  >https://tcp.hypotheses.org/318</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dagiral2018" label="Dagiral and Pailler 2018">Dagiral, E., Pailler, F.
                  <title rend="quotes">Des chercheur·e·s et des tweets. Enquêter sous
                  contraintes</title>. In S. Lécossais, N. Quemener, (ed), <title rend="italic">En
                  quête d’archives: bricolages méthodologiques en terrains médiatique</title>, INA
               Éditions (2018): pp. 113-21.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="denis2015" label="Denis and Pontille 2015">Denis, J., Pontille D. <title
                  rend="quotes">Beyond breakdown: two horizons of maintenance work</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">i3 Working Papers Series</title>, 15- SES-08 (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dombrowski2014" label="Dombrowski 2014">Dombrowski, Q. <title
                  rend="quotes">What Ever Happened to Project Bamboo?</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, Volume 29, Issue 3, (2014): 326-39
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqu026"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqu026</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dulong2017" label="Dulong de Rosnay and Guadamuz 2017">Dulong de Rosnay,
               M., Guadamuz, A. <title rend="quotes">Memory Hole or Right to Delist?</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">RESET</title>, 6 (2017) <ref
                  target="http://journals.openedition.org/reset/807"
                  >http://journals.openedition.org/reset/807</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2013" label="Drucker 2013">Drucker, J. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Performative Materiality and Theoretical Approaches to Interface</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 7/1 (2013) <ref
                  target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000143/000143.html"
                  >http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000143/000143.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2014" label="Drucker 2014">Drucker, J. <title rend="italic"
                  >Graphesis. Visual Forms of Knowledge Production</title>. Harvard University
               Press, Cambridge (2014).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ertzscheid2015" label="Ertzscheid 2015">Ertzscheid, O. <title
                  rend="quotes">Anne Frank et le domaine public. Mon combat?</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Affordance.info</title> (2015) <ref
                  target="http://affordance.typepad.com/mon_weblog/2015/10/anne-frank-mon-combat-.html"
                  >http://affordance.typepad.com//mon_weblog/2015/10/anne-frank-mon-combat-.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="farchy2010" label="Farchy et al. 2010">Farchy, J., Froissart, P. and
               Méadel C. <title rend="quotes">Introduction – Sciences.com, libre accès et science
                  ouverte</title>, <title rend="italic">Hermès</title> 2, n° 57 (2010): 9-12.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fickers2017" label="Fickers 2017">Fickers, A. <title rend="quotes">Digital
                  History : On the heuristic potential of thinkering</title>. Keynote lecture at
               DH-Nord Lille (2017) <ref
                  target="https://publi.meshs.fr/ressources/digital_history_on_the_heuristic_potential_of_thinkering"
                  >https://publi.meshs.fr/ressources/digital_history_on_the_heuristic_potential_of_thinkering</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fickers2020" label="Fickers 2020">Fickers A. <title rend="quotes">Update
                  für die Hermeneutik. Geschichtswissenschaft auf dem Weg zur digitalen
                  Forensik?</title>, <title rend="italic">Zeithistorische Forschungen/Studies in
                  Contemporary History</title> (2020): 157-68 <ref
                  target="https://zeithistorische-forschungen.de/1-2020/5823"
                  >https://zeithistorische-forschungen.de/1-2020/5823</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fuchs2018" label="Fuchs and Angel 2018">Fuchs, C., Angel, C. (eds) <title
                  rend="italic">Organization, Representation and Description through the Digital
                  Age, Information in Libraries, Archives and Museums</title>. De Gruyter, Berlin
               (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fohr2017" label="Föhr 2017">Föhr P. <title rend="quotes">Historische
                  Quellenkritik im Digitalen Zeitalter</title>, Doctoral Thesis, University of
               Basel, Faculty of Humanities and Social Sciences (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="girard2017" label="Girard 2017">Girard, C. <title rend="quotes">Les
                  mécanismes de centralisation des données de la recherche</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Revue française des sciences de l’information et de la
                  communication</title>, n°11 (2017). <ref
                  target="http://journals.openedition.org/rfsic/3255"
                  >http://journals.openedition.org/rfsic/3255</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="halte2016" label="Halté 2016">Halté, P. <title rend="quotes">Enjeux
                  pragmatiques et sémiotiques de l’étude des émoticônes</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Réseaux</title>, vol. 197-198, no. 3 (2016): 227-52.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hoekstra2018" label="Hoekstra and Koolen 2018">Hoekstra, R., Koolen, M.
                  <title rend="quotes">Data Scopes: Towards Transparent Data Research In Digital
                  Humanities</title>, DH2018, Mexico (2018) <ref
                  target="https://dh2018.adho.org/data-scopes-towards-transparent-data-research-in-digital-humanities/"
                  >https://dh2018.adho.org/data-scopes-towards-transparent-data-research-in-digital-humanities/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kibert2011" label="Kibert et al. 2011">Kibert, C. J., Thiele, L.,
               Peterson, A., Monroe, M. <title rend="quotes">The Ethics of Sustainability</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Free Textbook List</title> (2011) <ref
                  target="http://www.freetextbooklist.com/the-ethics-of-sustainability/"
                  >http://www.freetextbooklist.com/the-ethics-of-sustainability/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="king2007" label="King 2007">King, G. <title rend="quotes">An Introduction
                  to the Dataverse Network as an Infrastructure for Data Sharing</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Sociological Methods and Research</title>, 36 (2007): 173-99.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lang2012" label="Lang et al. 2012">Lang, D. J., Wiek, A., Bergmann, M.,
               Stauffacher, M., Martens, P., Moll, P., Swilling, M., Thomas, C. J. <title
                  rend="quotes">Transdisciplinary research in sustainability science: practice,
                  principles, and challenges</title>, <title rend="italic">Sustainability
                  Science</title>, 7, (2012): 25-43.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lecossais2018" label="Lécossais and Quemener 2018">Lécossais, S.,
               Quemener, N. (ed). <title rend="italic">En quête d’archives: bricolages
                  méthodologiques en terrains médiatique</title>. INA Éditions, Bry-sur-Marne
               (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="latzko-toth2013" label="Latzko-Toth and Pastinelli 2013">Latzko-Toth, G.,
               Pastinelli M., <title rend="quotes">Par-delà la dichotomie public/privé: la mise en
                  visibilité des pratiques numériques et ses enjeux éthiques</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">tic&amp;société</title>, Vol. 7, 2 (2013) <ref
                  target="http://journals.openedition.org/ticetsociete/1591"
                  >http://journals.openedition.org/ticetsociete/1591</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mabi2016" label="Mabi 2016">Mabi, C. <title rend="quotes">Analyser les
                  dispositifs participatifs par leur design</title>. In C.Barats (ed.) <title
                  rend="italic">Manuel d’analyse du web en Sciences Humaines et Sociales</title>,
               Armand Colin (2016), pp. 33-37.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mercier2018" label="Mercier and Pignard-Cheynel 2018">Mercier, A.,
               Pignard-Cheynel, N. (eds) <title rend="italic">#info Commenter et partager
                  l'actualité sur Twitter et Facebook</title>. Éditions de la Maison des sciences de
               l'homme, Paris (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="merzeau1998" label="Merzeau 1998">Merzeau, L. <title rend="quotes">Ceci ne
                  tuera pas cela</title>, <title rend="italic">Les cahiers de médiologie</title>,
               vol. 6, 2 (1998): 27-39.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="meunier2018" label="Meunier 2018">Meunier, J. G. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Digital text: hermeneutic issues</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                  Quarterly</title>, vol. 12, n°1 (2018) <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/12/1/000362/000362.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/12/1/000362/000362.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="moiraghi2018" label="Moiraghi 2018">Moiraghi, E. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Étude prospective sur les besoins et les attentes des futurs usagers du
                  Laboratoire d’étude et d’analyse de corpus numériques</title>, Paris, <title
                  rend="italic">BnF</title> (2018) <ref
                  target="http://actions-recherche.bnf.fr/BnF/anirw3.nsf/e7cfeb857fb88bebc1257b52004c05f9/cb0177ed072cd5fdc1258264004fdf0b/$FILE/DSR-CORPUS_Etude-de-besoins_Janvier2018_RGB.pdf"
                  >http://actions-recherche.bnf.fr/BnF/anirw3.nsf/e7cfeb857fb88bebc1257b52004c05f9/cb0177ed072cd5fdc1258264004fdf0b/$FILE/DSR-CORPUS_Etude-de-besoins_Janvier2018_RGB.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="monnoyer-smith2016" label="Monnoyer-Smith 2016">Monnoyer-Smith, L. <title
                  rend="quotes">Chapitre 1 - Le web comme dispositif: comment appréhender le
                  complexe?</title>. In C. Barats (ed.), <title rend="italic">Manuel d’analyse du
                  web en Sciences Humaines et Sociales</title>, Armand Colin (2016), pp.
               11-31.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mons2018" label="Mons 2018">Mons, B., <title rend="italic">Data
                  Stewardship for Open Science. Implementing FAIR Principles</title>. CRC Press,
               Boca Rota (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="musiani2017" label="Musiani and Schafer 2017">Musiani, F. and Schafer V.
                  <title rend="quotes">Patrimoine et patrimonialisation numériques</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">RESET</title>, 6 (2017) <ref
                  target="http://journals.openedition.org/reset/803"
                  >http://journals.openedition.org/reset/803</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="musiani2019" label="Musiani et al. 2019">Musiani, F., Paloque-Bergès, C.,
               Schafer, V. and Thierry, B. <title rend="quotes">Qu’est qu’une archive du Web?
                  OpenEdition</title>, <title rend="italic">Marseille</title> (2019) <ref
                  target="https://books.openedition.org/oep/8737?lang=en"
                  >https://books.openedition.org/oep/8737?lang=en</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nanni2017" label="Nanni 2017">Nanni, F. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Reconstructing a website's lost past – Methodological issues concerning the
                  history of www.unibo.it</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                  Quarterly</title>, vol. 11, n°2 (2017) <ref
                  target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/11/2/000292/000292.html"
                  >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/11/2/000292/000292.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="osullivan2019" label="O’ Sullivan 2019">O’ Sullivan, J. <title
                  rend="quotes">The humanities have a <q>reproducibility</q> problem</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Talking humanities</title> (2019) <ref
                  target="https://talkinghumanities.blogs.sas.ac.uk/?s=O%27+Sullivan&amp;submit=Search"
                  >https://talkinghumanities.blogs.sas.ac.uk/?s=O%27+Sullivan&amp;submit=Search</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="owens2020" label="Owens 2020">Owens T., <title rend="quotes">Digital
                  Sources and Digital Archives: The Evidentiary Basis of Digital History</title>. In
               D. Staley (ed), <title rend="italic">A Companion to Digital History</title>, (2020
               forthcoming) <ref target="https://doi.org/10.31235/osf.io/t5rdy"
                  >https://doi.org/10.31235/osf.io/t5rdy</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="paloque-berges2017" label="Paloque-Bergès 2017">Paloque-Bergès, C. <title
                  rend="quotes">Vers des lieux de mémoire réticulaires?</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">RESET</title> 6 (2017) <ref
                  target="http://journals.openedition.org/reset/839"
                  >http://journals.openedition.org/reset/839</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="paveau2014" label="Paveau 2014">Paveau, M-A. <title rend="quotes"
                  >L’alternative quantitatif/qualitatif à l’épreuve des univers discursifs
                  numériques</title>, <title rend="italic">Corela</title>, HS-15 (2014) <ref
                  target="http://journals.openedition.org/corela/3598"
                  >http://journals.openedition.org/corela/3598</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pereira2016" label="Pereira and Lopes de Araujo 2016">Pereira, M., Lopes
               de Araujo V. <title rend="quotes">Historical time reconfigurations: presentism,
                  updatism, and loneliness in digital modernity</title>, rev. Ufmg (Revista da
               Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais), <title rend="italic">belo horizonte</title>,
               v.23, n.1-2 (2016): 290-97 <ref
                  target="https://www.ufmg.br/revistaufmg/pdf/REVISTA_23_web.pdf"
                  >https://www.ufmg.br/revistaufmg/pdf/REVISTA_23_web.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="plantin2013" label="Plantin 2013">Plantin, J.C. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Chapitre 11 - D’une carte à l’autre: Le potentiel heuristique de la comparaison
                  entre graphe du web et carte géographique</title>. In C. Barats (ed.), <title
                  rend="italic">Manuel d’analyse du web en Sciences Humaines et Sociales</title>,
               Armand Colin (2013): pp. 228-245.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pomerantz2015" label="Pomerantz 2015">Pomerantz, J. <title rend="italic"
                  >Metada,</title> MIT Press, Cambride MA (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="poulsen2009" label="Poulsen 2009">Poulsen, K. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Google’s abandonned library of 700 million titles (updated)</title>, Wired (2009)
                  <ref target="https://www.wired.com/2009/10/usenet/"
                  >https://www.wired.com/2009/10/usenet/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="raymond2010" label="Raymond 2010">Raymond, M. <title rend="quotes">How
                  Tweet It Is!: Library Acquires Entire Twitter Archive</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Blog of the LoC</title>, (2010) <ref
                  target="https://blogs.loc.gov/loc/2010/04/how-tweet-it-is-library-acquires-entire-twitter-archive/"
                  >https://blogs.loc.gov/loc/2010/04/how-tweet-it-is-library-acquires-entire-twitter-archive/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rhodes2013" label="Rhodes 2013">Rhodes, T. <title rend="quotes">A Living,
                  Breathing Revolution : How Librarians Can Use <q>Living Archives</q> to Support,
                  Engage, and Document Social Movements</title>, IFLA Wlick 2013, Singapore (2013)
                  <ref
                  target="https://thescholarship.ecu.edu/bitstream/handle/10342/4496/084-rhodes-en-TamaraRhodes.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y"
                  >https://thescholarship.ecu.edu/bitstream/handle/10342/4496/084-rhodes-en-TamaraRhodes.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rygiel2011" label="Rygiel 2011">Rygiel, P. <title rend="quotes">L’enquête
                  historique à l’ère numérique</title>, <title rend="italic">Revue d’histoire
                  moderne &amp; contemporaine</title>, vol. 58-4bis, no. 5 (2011): 30-40.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="russell2018" label="Russell and Vinsel 2018">Russell, A. Vinsel, L. <title
                  rend="quotes">After Innovation, Turn to Maintenance</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Technology and Culture</title>, 59, 1 (2018), pp. 1-25 <ref
                  target="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/692165/pdf"
                  >https://muse.jhu.edu/article/692165/pdf</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="salvador2017" label="Salvador 2017">Salvador, <title rend="quotes">Indexer
                  des documents « du dedans » : quels moyens de répondre à la question du lieu de la
                  donnée (XML, OWL, RDF,REST)?</title> In J. Longhi (ed.), <title rend="italic"
                  >Communication</title>, 35/1, (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schafer2018" label="Schafer 2018">Schafer, V. <title rend="quotes">Les
                  réseaux sociaux numériques d’avant...</title>, <title rend="italic">Le Temps des
                  médias</title>, 2, 31 (2018): 121-36 <ref
                  target="https://www.cairn.info/revue-le-temps-des-medias-2018-2-page-121.htm"
                  >https://www.cairn.info/revue-le-temps-des-medias-2018-2-page-121.htm</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="smithies2019" label="Smithies et al. 2019">Smithies, J., Westling, C.,
               Sichani, A-M., Mellen, P. and Ciula, A. <title rend="quotes">Managing 100 digital
                  humanities projects: digital scholarship &amp; archiving in King’s Digital
                  Lab</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 13, 1
               (2019) <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/1/000411/000411.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/1/000411/000411.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="toth-czifra2020" label="Tóth-Czifra 2020">Tóth-Czifra, E. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Risk of Losing the Thick Description. Data Management Challenges
                  Faced by the Arts and Humanities in the Evolving FAIR Data Ecosystem</title>. In
               J. Edmonds (ed), <title rend="italic">Digital Technology and the Practices of
                  Humanities Research</title>, Open Book Publishers (2020), pp. 235-66.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="valluy2017" label="Valluy 2017">Valluy, J. <title rend="quotes">Libre
                  accès aux savoirs et accès ouvert aux publications</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Revue française des sciences de l’information et de la communication</title>,
               n°11 (2017) <ref target="http://journals.openedition.org/rfsic/3194"
                  >http://journals.openedition.org/rfsic/3194</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="venturini2014" label="Venturini et al. 2014">Venturini T., Cardon D. and
               Cointet J.P. <title rend="quotes">Présentation, Méthodes digitales Approches
                  quali/quanti des données numériques</title>, <title rend="italic">Réseaux</title>,
               vol. 188, 6 (2014): 9-21.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vines2014" label="Vines et al. 2014">Vines, T. H., Albert, A.Y.K., Andrew,
               R. L., Débarre, F., Bock, D., G., Franklin, M. T., Kimberly J. G., Moore, J-S.,
               Renaut, S. and Rennison, D.J. <title rend="quotes">The Availability of Research Data
                  Declines Rapidly with Article Age</title>, <title rend="italic">Current
                  Biology</title>, vol. 24, 1 (2014): 94-7.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wilkinson2016" label="Wilkinson et al. 2016">Wilkinson, M., Dumontier, M.,
               Aalbersberg, I., et al. <title rend="quotes">The FAIR Guiding Principles for
                  scientificdata management and stewardship</title>, <title rend="italic">Sci
                  Data</title> 3, 160018 (2016). <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zimmer2010" label="Zimmer 2010">Zimmer, M. <title rend="quotes"><q>But the
                     data is already public</q>: On the ethics of research in Facebook</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Ethics and Information Technology</title>, 12, 4 (2010):
               313-25.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zimmer2015" label="Zimmer 2015">[Zimmer 2015] Zimmer, M. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Twitter Archive at the Library of Congress: Challenges for
                  Information Practice and Information Policy</title>, <title rend="italic">First
                  Monday</title>, Vol. 20, 7 (2015) <ref
                  target="http://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/5619/4653"
                  >http://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/5619/4653</ref>. </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
