<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Perceptual Effects of
               Hierarchy in Art Historical Social Networks</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Houda <dhq:family>Lamqaddam</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
               	>https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6738-1934<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Leuven</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>lamqaddam.houda@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Houda Lamqaddam is a PhD candidate in Information Visualization and Art History in KU Leuven, Belgium. Her research interests revolve around the usability and relevance of information visualisation techniques for art historical data. She explores the use of humanist theory and practice to inform visualisation design, starting from data interrogation and critical source evaluation, to existing traditions of visual design languages and conventions.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Inez <dhq:family>De Prekel</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Leuven</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>inez.deprekel@kuleuven.be</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Inez De Prekel (1991) received her MA in Art History in June 2017 at the University of Leuven (KU Leuven). She then joined Project Cornelia as a PhD student. Inez studies the interplay between social dynamics and artistic developments in the seventeenth-century Antwerp art world, with a focus on a group of Antwerp tenebrist painters.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Koenraad <dhq:family>Brosens</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
               	>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4335-6512<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Leuven</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>koenraad.brosens@kuleuven.be</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Koenraad Brosens is a Professor in the Art History Department of the University of Leuven (KU Leuven) and Vice-Dean of Education at the Faculty of Arts. He has published widely on Flemish and French tapestry and is PI of Project Cornelia (projectcornelia.be). Koen was visiting professor at the University of Pennsylvania Philadelphia (2007), the Peter Paul Rubens Chair at the University of California Berkeley (2013), and The J.P. Getty Museum Scholar (2019). In 2020 he received the Pioneer Award of the Humanities &amp; Social Sciences Group of the KU Leuven</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Katrien <dhq:family>Verbert</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
               	>https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6699-7710<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Leuven</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>katrien.verbert@kuleuven.be</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Katrien Verbert is an Associate Professor at the HCI research group of the KU Leuven, Belgium. Her research interests include recommender systems, visualization techniques, visual analytics, and applications in healthcare, learning analytics, precision agriculture and digital humanities.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000604</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->1</idno>
            <date when="2022-02-04">04 February 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2022-08-03" who="BRG">added missing ORCIDs, resolved encoding errors</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>Network representation is a crucial topic in historical social network analysis. The
               debate around their value and connotations, led by humanist scholars, is today more
               relevant then ever, seeing how common these representations are as support for
               historical analysis. Force-directed networks, in particular, are popular as they can
               be developed relatively quickly, and reveal patterns and structures in data. The
               underlying algorithms, although powerful in revealing hidden patterns, do not retain
               meaningful structure and existing hierarchies within historical social networks. In
               this article, we question the foreign aspect of this structure that force-directed
               layout create in historical datasets. We explore the importance of hierarchy in
               social networks, and investigate whether hierarchies  - strongly present within our
               models of social structure - affect our perception of social network data. Results
               from our user evaluation indicate that hierarchical network representations reduce
               cognitive load and leads to more frequent and deeper insights into historical social
               networks. We also find that users report a preference for the hierarchical graph
               representation. We analyse these findings in light of the broader discussion on the
               value of force-directed network representations within humanistic research, and
               introduce open questions for future work in this line of research. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>We explore the importance of hierarchy in
               social networks, and investigate whether hierarchies  - strongly present within our
               models of social structure - affect our perception of social network data</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Networks are some of the most commonly found visualizations in digital humanities
               research. Used to represent relationships between persons or concepts, this type of
               graphs has also been implemented through various layouts to better support specific
               tasks and users. </p>
            <p>The wide availability of layout algorithms has multiple advantages for researchers
               who aim to analyze social networks. Force-directed layouts such as the Gephi Atlas
               drastically simplify the visualization – therefore analysis – of large network data.
               They reveal patterns and clusters by using complex physical models, all with limited
               need for user intervention or mathematical expertise. These models excel in domains
               where datasets are large, and where the goal is to identify the structure – or shape
               – of the dataset. </p>
            <p>However, the widened access to these automated graph drawing algorithms drives us to
               interrogate their fitedness for the analysis of humanistic material. On the one hand,
               force-directed layouts visually remove existing structures in the data, even when
               these structures are meaningful to users and their daily tasks. On the other,
               humanistic datasets are often small, but do consist of meaningful inherent clusters,
               distances and relationships. Such a mismatch leads to representations that can be at
               odds with users' internal perceptions of the data structure. For instance, family
               members in a correspondence graph are likely to be spread apart. Similarly,
               non-contemporary actors can be placed side to side if they share a common
               correspondent. This inconsistency between mental models and visual representation can
               become a challenge for users. More critically, it has the potential to impact the
               adoption of visualization tools as a whole as research suggests usability and user
               trust, rather than scalability, are main obstacles to adoption of digital tools in
               the humanities <ptr target="#thoden2017"/>. </p>
            <p>In this paper, we address this challenge by introducing <term
                  >Force-Layered graphs</term>: a novel method for drawing hierarchical graphs<note>
                  also known as hierarchical or Sugiyama-style graphs.</note> using force-directed
               layout. This method uses the existing – and already mature - dynamics of
               force-directed algorithms, and injects a meaningful structure into them to organize
               them in a way that better supports users’ mental models. We describe the results of a
               mixed-methods user study exploring the effect of visual hierarchy for users with
               humanities background. </p>
            <p>Our initial results reveal that force-layered graph layout outperforms force-directed
               layout in terms of number and depth of insights, cognitive load reduction, and user
               preference. We discuss these findings along with implications for design and future
               directions for this line of research. Specifically, we interrogate the artificial
               structure these layouts create, and evaluate whether their disconnect with existing
               data hierarchies affects user understanding, preference, and experience. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Structure &amp; Hierarchy in Network Visualization </head>
            <p>Discussion about the semantics of visual design elements is often neglected within
               technical scholarship on information visualization. In the case of hierarchy, we
               believe this discussion to be critical for two reasons. First, because
               Human-Computer-Interaction research has shown the importance of the consistency
               between users’ mental models of information and its digital representation <ptr target="#doerum2011"/>. Second, because visual hierarchy in network graphs strongly affects their
               spatial organization, and spatial position is believed to be one of the most
               effective channels in information visualization <ptr target="#munzner2014"/> <ptr target="#bertin1973"/>. In
               this section, we present a discussion on the semantics of hierarchical trees on one
               side, and force-directed networks on the other. </p> 
           
               
               <figure>
                  <head> (a) On the left: <title rend="quotes">A newly invented genealogical tree of the last
                     Byzantine emperor...as well as one of the Turkish sultan.</title> ca. 1730-57. Digital
                     image from the Met Museum Collection Gift of Robert W. Hatem. Public Domain. (b)
                     On the right: a network showing relationships between signatories of a 18th
                     century marriage contract in France. This network is an example of graph drawn
                     using a circular<note> This layout is a specific type of force-directed layout
                        that confines nodes to a circular space. The Fruchterman-Reingold layout on
                        Gephi is an example of such algorithms. </note> force-directed layout.
                     <ptr target="#rothschild2014"/>. Reproduced with permission.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/image1.png"/>
                  <figDesc>An image of a genealogical tree on the left and a network diagram on the right</figDesc>
               </figure>
             
            
            <p>First, we illustrate the difference between the two, through the example of two
               visualisations of historical social networks as can be seen in Figure 1. In Figure
               1a, a hand-drawn illustration displays the genealogy of the last Byzantine emperor
               drawn as a collection of trees. This visualization has a strong spatial organization
               based on family lines, roles, and generational hierarchy. In fact, tree structures
               can be found in multiple historical representations of networks because they mirror
               the conception of lineage as a branching linear connected structure. In Figure 1b, we
               see a contemporary representation of a historical network<note> We defaulted to a
                  contemporary representation for the non-hierarchical layout as these can only be
                  found in recent representations. See <ptr target="#freeman2004"/> for a history of network
                  representation of social structures. </note>, this time depicting the list of
               signatories of a marriage contract in Angoulême, France in the 18th century, as well
               as their extended social networks <ptr target="#rothschild2014"/>. This network, developed using
               Gephi shows the global social structure of this historical community, produced using
               a force-directed layout, such that highly connected subgroups attract each other,
               thereby revealing the cliques and subcommunities within the dataset. </p>
            <p>To describe them formally, hierarchical trees (such as Figure 1a) are a sub-category
               of networks that are acyclic (i.e. there are no loop encountered during a traversal
               of the tree) and directed (i.e. the relationships described by the edges are
               one-directional, rather than reciprocal). The hierarchical aspect signifies a certain
               categorization of the nodes so that those placed on the same level hold a similar
               value or meaning. Hierarchical trees are a spatial organization whose traces date
               back to antiquity, and which can be found in a variety of knowledge domains. As
               described by Drucker in her book Graphesis <ptr target="#drucker2010"/>, trees are interesting
               because their spatial organization carries meaning. In the case of social networks,
               this spatial organization becomes an indicator of multiple elements including birth
               order, generational breadth and span, patterns of marriage <ptr target="#drucker2010"/>. Another
               interesting aspect to hierarchical trees is their embedded story-telling. The root
               node(s), typically placed at the top<note> Or at the right, in a right-to-left
                  horizontal spatial organization</note> of the hierarchy, creates a visual anchor
               that drives the reader in, and directs their attention down the edges in a manner
               which is almost a narrative approach to visualization. </p>
            <p>On the other hand, force-directed networks (Figure 1b) are mathematical products,
               where physical simulations ran multiple times on a dataset model attraction and
               repulsion between nodes, therefore automatically placing nodes with high connectivity
               close to one another, or at the opposite, resulting in disconnected nodes being
               placed far from each other, highlighting their disconnect. For Ahnert et al.,
               force-directed networks <q>reject hierarchies</q>, which become hidden and difficult to
               notice, even if they were strongly present within the dataset <ptr target="#ahnert2020"/>. Modern
               readings have argued for the advantages of force-directed networks by justly
               questioning the relevance and accuracy of representing the world in rigidly
               structured hierarchical roles. In actual historical communities, influence does not
               necessarily traverse time and generations in a clear-cut linear way. Similarly, trees
               of knowledge fall short when representing complex webs of information, as the
               distributed aspect of the web and social networks have clearly illustrated in the
               past decades<note> Pushed to its extreme, this urge to categorize the world can be
                  linked to historical movements which have led to similar attempts at categorizing
                  peoples and communities, thereby creating and intensifying the construction of
                  race for example, solidified through its representation as formal scientific
                  truth. This discussion, while outside the scope of this article, cannot be ignored
                  when discussing the role of hierarchy and knowledge in human history.</note>. </p>
            <p>In the context of humanistic research, however, the intentional organization of
               network data has an undeniable value, when compared to the visual organization that
               results of mathematical algorithms. Drucker explains it clearly: </p>
            <cit><quote rend="block">The spatial distribution of network diagrams, topic maps, and other graphical
               expressions of processed text or intellectual content is often determined by the
               exigencies of screen real estate, rather than by a semantic value inherent in the
               visualization. This introduces incidental artifacts of visual information. A point in
               a graph may be far from another because of a parameter in the program that governs
               display, rather than on account of the weight accorded to the information in the data
               set. The argument of the graphic may even be counter to the argument of the
               information, creating an interpretative warp or skew, so that what we see and read is
               actually a reification of misinformation.</quote> <ptr target="#drucker2010"/></cit>
            <p>In that way, network visualizations are no different than other visualizations of
               data, as they themselves can reproduce existing biases, and cement them as neutral
               knowledge. Porras asks us to keep our eyes open to the dangers of network
               visualizations as they can <quote rend="inline">reinscribe historic and contemporary power differentials</quote>
               <ptr target="#porras2017"/>.</p>
            <p>In visualization literature, a growing voice argues for the consideration of
               semantics and connotation in the visualization design, especially within humanistic
               scholarship. In previous work <ptr target="#lamqaddam2020"/>, we report how humanists have
               consistently commented on the connotative dryness of visualization tools, linking it
               to a reduction of rich research material <ptr target="#manovich2012"/>. Through user research, we
               found that humanist scholars felt a <term>semantic distance</term> between
               their experience of their research material and practice and its representation in
               visualization tools. Such tools can end up stripping data of essential meaning-making
               elements such as temporality, physicality, and terminology. More specifically, we
               identified structure in conceptualizations and ontologies as one of the
               characteristics of humanistic research that is often missing in visualizations. We
               also found proof that meaning, intentionally layered into visualization, had the
               potential to reduce the semantic distance experienced by scholars, and alleviate
               their discomfort. In this context, the question of representing data’s hierarchical
               structures within historical social networks is an interrogation of our Layers of
               Meaning (LoM) framework, and an investigation of a larger trend in digital humanities
               scholarship during the data era. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Research Questions</head>
            <p>To build on the previous discussion, we wanted to investigate the effects that
               hierarchical trees and force-directed graphs have on user perception. Because the
               literature on mental models in visualization shows link effects on efficiency and
               user experience, we developed an extensive user evaluation protocol where we compare
               the two representations and investigate the perceptual impacts of each one. In the
               next section, we describe the process we followed, and the findings we can extract
               from it. </p>
            <p>Through this process, we aimed to answer the following research questions:</p>
            <list type="unordered">
               <item>RQ1: Do users have an inherent mental model of social network spatial
                  organizations? How is it visually structured?</item>
               <item>RQ2: How does representing historical social network data using a generational
                  hierarchy affect cognitive load during social networks analysis tasks?</item>
               <item>RQ3: How does hierarchy within social network data affect insight-building and
                  recall? </item>
            </list>
            <p>In order to perform a fair comparison, we developed two visualizations showing both
               hierarchical and standard force-directed visualizations of historical social
               networks. We developed a prototype for hierarchical tree layout visualization using
               the Javascript visualization library D3. We chose to develop this algorithm on top of
               the existing force-directed layout algorithms for multiple reasons. First, the
               existing force-directed layout algorithms are currently mature and deliver
               high-quality performance. Perhaps as a consequence, these layouts are supported by
               major graph drawing libraries and toolkits, which opens future possibilities for
               wider implementation of hierarchical graph layouts. Force-directed layouts also
               include parameters to reduce node collision, occlusion, and bring in useful results,
               such as bringing together highly connected clusters, which, while we do not want it
               to break inherent hierarchy in the data, still proves to be useful in reducing
               edge-crossing. </p>
            <p>We designed and implemented an algorithm that traverses a force-directed graph and
               spatially organizes it based on a user-defined parameter. The full algorithm
               description and code can be found on our <ref target='github.com/HLMQA/egoNahr'>GitHub page</ref>. 
                 Figure 2 shows the same dataset represented as
               both a force-directed graph (left), and a hierarchical network (right). We call the
               graphs produced by our hierarchical layout <term>force-layered graphs.
               </term>This porte-manteau hints at the underlying force-directed layout, and includes
               the layered aspect of hierarchical graphs (alternatively referred to as layered
               graphs, or Sugiyama-graphs). </p> 
            
            
            <figure>
               <head>A dataset of thirteen nodes is visualized using a force-directed
                  layout (left) and a force-layered layout (right).</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image2.png"/>
               <figDesc>An image of a force directed network graph on the left and a force-layered network graph</figDesc>
            </figure>
            
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Study</head>
            <p>In this section, we describe the evaluation protocol used to answer the RQs described
               in section 3. In HCI, user evaluations are a standard way to get feedback and to get
               better insight into users’ needs. It is also a common way to evaluate usability and
               identify obstacles to adoption of digital tools. Since usability and adoption are a
               recurrent issue in DH research, there is real value to be gained from applying such
               methods to pinpoint exact usability issues in collaboration with the intended
               audience. In this section, we describe each step of the methodology together with the
               results found. For each subsection, the full table of results can be found in the
               annex. In this section, we sometimes use the notations <term>F-D</term> and
                  <term>F-L</term> as shorthand for <term>Force-Directed</term>
               or <term>Force-Layered</term> graphs respectively.</p>
            <p>Participants. We recruited 15 participants (12 women, 3 men) with background in Art
               History and Digital Humanities, most of them graduate students in the university’s
               Digital Humanities MSc program. Participants had on average 3.6 years of experience
               in their domain, and 1.2 years of experience using digital tools to support their
               research or study practice. Among participants, most digital tool usage within field
               of study consisted of digital archives (11 out of 15), spreadsheets (10 out of 15),
               and graph visualization tools (9 out of 15). </p>
            <p>Data. We used data extracted from the Cornelia<note> Projectcornelia.be</note>
               database, which uses archival documents to gather historical data on 17th century
               artistic communities<note> Specifically Flemish painters and tapestry
                  producers.</note>. We selected a subset containing 38 persons related through
               ancestry, marriage and godparenthood links. This dataset specifically highlights
               (extra)familial hierarchy structure. </p>
            <p>Graphs. Figure 3 shows the two network visualization used in this study. We used the
               same dataset for both graphs not to introduce bias. However, to minimize learning
               effects, we manually changed the names so that the similarity of the two networks
               would not be obvious.</p> 
            
            <figure>
               <head>The prototypes used in the user study. (a) On the top, the D3
                  force-directed layout. (b) On the bottom, the same data using our force-layered
                  algorithm. The names of the actors were changed in both graphs to reduce learning
                  effects on participants.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image3.png"/>
               <figDesc>An image of a force directed network graph on the left and a force-layered network graph</figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            
            <div>
               <head>Mental model elicitation</head>
               <p>Understanding users' existing mental models (i.e. the representation they
                  internally make of specific information structures or processes) is key if we aim
                  to support similar structures in building visualizations. Previous work in the HCI
                  field has demonstrated the value of asking participants to draw their mental
                  models as a way to externalize them <ptr target="#zhang2008"/> <ptr target="#kodama2017"/>.</p>
               <p>Before showing participants the graphs, we first started by asking each one to
                  freely draw a social structure of their choosing, in order to elicit their mental
                  mapping of social structures. They were invited to sketch out any fictional or
                  existing social structure network (from stories, movies or books, or their own
                  personal life<note> We asked participants to anonymize any personal information in
                     the case they wanted to draw their personal social structure, in order to
                     maintain privacy for them and their social circles.</note>). They were
                  encouraged to consider lineage relationships, but also non-blood ties such as
                  extended families, and close friends. We then extracted the recurring themes
                  present in the produced sketches. A few of these sketches can be seen in Figure
                  4.</p> 
               
               
               <figure>
                  <head>From left to right, top to bottom: initial drawings for
                     participants P13, P4, P15 and P10. These sketches show networks represented as
                     layered graphs, similar to traditional ancestry tree visualizations.
                     Participants made use of labels, symbols and shape.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/image4.jpeg"/>
                  <figDesc>Sketches of network graph</figDesc>
               </figure>
               
               
               <p>We found that in all<note> We excluded a single sketch from our analysis (P11) as
                     it represented an evolutionary tree rather than a social network.</note> cases,
                  participants sketched graphs had a hierarchical structure. These representations
                  were mainly tree structures, with many of them structured as layered graphs. We
                  also found that most participants used the vertical axis as a single indicator of
                  generational division. However, in some cases, this pattern was broken as
                  different relationships (edges towards friends for instance) were represented as
                  orthogonal to the family links (Figure 4, P15). Indeed, almost a third (35\%) of
                  participants chose to represent multiple relationship types within the graphs.</p>
               <p>Familiar structure, or expression of an internal mental model? While we can use
                  the results from this elicitation task to induce the existence of a ‘natural’
                  hierarchical mental model of such data for the users, the exposure to family-tree
                  type representations is an equally likely explanation for the phenomenon. Family
                  trees are an old form of representations that are commonly seen by the public
                  [Mitchell, 2014]. They are also commonly used in (art) historical teaching, which
                  makes our participants even more likely to have built familiarity towards them. In
                  reality, our participants have likely interacted with similar representations in
                  the past, and may have defaulted to recreating a similar structure. We consider
                  that these results do inform us of the internal model within the participants,
                  itself caused by either inherent hierarchization of this data, or unvoluntary
                  training caused by previous exposure. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Think aloud study</head>
               <p>We asked participants to explore the dataset in each condition while vocalizing
                  their thought process. Similar to the mental model elicitation approach, this
                  method allows to make the thought process of participants explicit. We then
                  captured and transcribed participants think-aloud process and analyzed it using a
                  thematic analysis to uncover patterns of insight<note> In order to categorize the
                     insight level of participants, we used the framework defined by Claes et al.
                     <ptr target="#claes2015"/> distinguishing three levels of insight depth: factual insight,
                     referring to a description of visible data, interpretive insight, where data is
                     synthesized along with additional objective or experienced information, then
                     reflective, which also includes subjective or emotional response.</note> and
                  identify differences between the force-directed and the force-layered
                  conditions.</p>
               <p>We found that the force-layered visualization triggered more interpretative<note>
                     In our study, factual insight describes statements such as <q>he dies in 1668</q>
                     or <q>this person has children.</q> Interpretative insight includes <q>it's just
                     close family I see,</q> <q>This person has children, but not with this one I
                     think.</q> Finally, in reflective insight, we included comments about the data
                     quality (<q>I got the feeling this [dataset] is more documented than the other
                     one</q>) and emotional engagement with the data (<q>oh they had *many* children
                     *laughs*</q>).</note> and reflective insights. We also find more occurrences of
                  intrigue or curiosity about the portrayed social structures (<emph><q>
                     It's too bad you can't see more about the person, you can't tell for example
                     what their profession is,</q> <q>I don't know the person, but I imagine if I were
                     researching these people, it can be really interesting to see</q></emph>). Some
                  participants also found contradictions in the underlying data, and offered
                  hypotheses to explain those, or simply pointed them out (<q>[This person]<emph> has an offspring but it's somehow not an
                     event for </emph>[their wife]<emph> — it's not an event for her,
                     although it is with her"</emph></q>). Finally, we found a clear divide in the number
                  of negative emotions such as overwhelmingness or defeat in the condition of
                  force-directed network usage (<emph><q>There are a lot of persons, and
                     here a lot of events. I’m trying to see who’s linked to who but it’s really
                     difficult here.</q></emph>, <q><emph>I don’t like this one. Yeah it’s really confusing and I
                     don’t find … ugh</emph> [trails off]</q>).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Exploration Tasks</head>
               <p>To complement the open nature of the think-aloud exploration, we conducted a more
                  structured exploration task where we asked participants to answer specific
                  questions about the social dynamics portrayed in the visualization. We designed
                  these questions based on the existing literature on graph exploration tasks<note>
                     We used the taxonomy proposed by Lee et al. <ptr target="#lee2006"/> and partly aimed
                     towards evaluators who wish to compare graph visualizations. From a domain
                     point of view, we looked at Lamqaddam et al. task categorization <ptr target="#lamqaddam2018"/>, which is more specific to the domain of family tree visualization in the
                     humanities.</note> and categorized them into easy questions (e.g. <q><emph>find the most connected actor</emph></q>, <q><emph>Find all
                     people who knew both X and Y</emph></q>) and difficult questions (<q><emph
                     >How does the graph evolve between birth of person X and their death</emph></q>, <emph><q>Describe the network at a specific year</q></emph>).</p>
               <p>We assessed the answers to the exploration tasks based on complete and partial
                  correctness. We found that for easy questions, a similar number of participants
                  (F-D: n=11; F-L: n=10) gave correct answers with both conditions. However, in the
                  force-directed condition, half of these answers were incomplete. To the difficult
                  questions, more participants gave correct answers using the force-layered
                  condition (n=6). Notably, however, none of the participants were able to answer
                  the same questions using the force-directed condition completely and correctly.
                  The number of participants who gave incomplete answers was the same for both
                  conditions.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Perception Task</head>
               <p>In order to measure how the perception of the graphs compared with their actual
                  characteristics, we collected participants recollection of some quantitative graph
                  characteristics such as network size, and number of generations. We also asked
                  about the perceived complexity of the social structure. Both networks contained
                  the same number of nodes thirty-eight nodes. We found that participants perceived
                  the force-layered graph to contain <emph>fewer</emph> nodes (median=30)
                  than was the case. They were more slightly accurate when using the force-directed
                  graph (median=35). </p>
               <p>Finally, a majority of participants reported feeling that the social structure
                  displayed in the force-layered condition was of a simpler nature one than the
                  force-directed. This corroborates the difference in perceived graph size, as
                  participants perceived networks in the force-layered condition to have fewer
                  nodes.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Recall task</head>
               <p>To assess recall, we aimed to see how well participants remembered the graph in
                  its entirety. We then asked them to draw the graph to their best recollection
                  after having diverted their attention for a brief moment<note> We used this time
                     to ask participants to fill out the NASA-TLX questionnaire, described in the
                     next paragraph. This step had the advantage to distract participants from the
                     screen and the graph itself, while not being too distracting that it led them
                     to unrelated trains of thought.</note>. We then analyzed the resulting sketch
                  based on categories including the restitution of meaningful sub-communities,
                  node-link structure, and visual detail. </p>
               <p>We found differences in specific metrics between the recall sketches of the two
                  versions, specifically on the identification of bridge nodes, as well as the
                  retention of the multiple types of relationships. In the force-directed recall
                  sketches, participants have retained the “dog-bone” structure of the graph
                  consisting of two large clusters representing the two main families and tied
                  together through a bridge node. Most participants also retained - at least
                  partially - the lower antennas formed by the two loosely connected pairs nodes. In
                  the force-layered condition, the drawings have retained the left-to-right
                  organization of the nodes, as well as the two distinct subgraphs representing the
                  two families. The bridge node bringing these two groups together was not
                  systematically included. Finally, participants retained the existence of multiple
                  types of relationships better in the force-layered condition, as they recalled
                  more of the godparent type links. Example drawings from participants for each
                  condition can be seen in Figure 5.</p> 
               
               <figure>
                  <head>Selected participants recall sketches in each condition. On the
                     left, sketches representing the force-directed network (3a). On the right,
                     sketches representing the force-layered (3b).</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/image5.png"/>
                  <figDesc>Sketches of network graph</figDesc>
               </figure>
               
             
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Cognitive load</head>
               <p>While evaluating performance can provide a good understanding of efficiency
                  achieved using a system, the mental effort required is not answered by these
                  approaches. We therefore measure participants' cognitive load<note> Cognitive load
                     is a multidimensional construct representing mental effort – or load imposed on
                     the cognitive system by performing a certain task. Evaluation of this measure
                     has been found to be useful to complement performance-based evaluations of
                     effectiveness in visualization. </note> when using the two conditions.</p>
               <p>As a measure for cognitive load, we used a raw NASA-TLX questionnaire [Hart, 1998]
                  The NASA-TLX questionnaire is a widely used metric for measuring cognitive load in
                  the HCI field. It consists of a self-reported scale capturing workload across six
                  dimensions: Mental, Physical, and Temporal Demands, Frustration, Effort, and
                  Performance [Hart, 1998]. Participants are asked to score each of these variables
                  on a 0 — 100 scale where a lower value represents a lower demand<note> In the full
                     version of a NASA-TLX, participants are also asked to weigh these variables
                     depending on their perceived relevance to the task. The final score of a full
                     NASA-TLX is a weighed average of the user score based on the overall weight
                     distribution. However, many researchers report using a <emph
                        >raw</emph> version of the test, where the scores are simply averaged with no
                     consideration of weights. Since little difference in sensitivity has been found
                     between raw and weighed TLX, we decided for a raw-TLX to keep evaluation time
                     short.</note>. </p>
               <p>Comparing the raw NASA-TLX scores, we find that the force-layered visualization
                  (average score of 26.3) was found to be less demanding than the force-directed
                  graph (average score of 35.78), the metrics with most variance between conditions
                  being mental demand, effort, and frustration (see Figure 6).</p> 
               
               <figure>
                  <head>Results of the raw TLX for the force-layered and force-directed
                     conditions</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/image6.png"/>
                  <figDesc>An image of a bar graph</figDesc>
               </figure>
               
               
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>User preference</head>
               <p>Finally, we performed a preference-based ranking. Participants were asked to
                  subjectively rank the force-directed and the force-layered graphs on a Likert
                  scale on aspects such as perceived suitability to task and data, or visual appeal. </p>
               <p>Figure 7 shows the average results of the preference rankings for each category.
                  Globally, participants ranked the force-layered condition higher than the
                  force-directed condition in suitability to both data and tasks. They indicated
                  that the force-layered condition needed less effort to understand than the
                  standard one, and that they had higher confidence in their answers. Finally, the
                  force-layered graphs also scored higher in visual appeal, and overall preference. </p> 
               
               
               <figure>
                  <head>Results of the preference ranking for the force-layered and force-
                     directed conditions</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/image7.png"/>
                  <figDesc>An image of a bar graph</figDesc>
               </figure>
               
              
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Results &amp; Discussion</head>
            <p>Based on a task of mental model elicitation, we found that participants
               overwhelmingly relied on generational hierarchical structure to draw familial social
               networks. This can be either because of inherent structure perceived in the data, or
               association of this type of dataset with traditional ancestry tree representations. </p>
            <p>When exploring two different versions of a social network where one is layered
               hierarchically and the other one isn’t, we found that participants expressed more –
               and deeper – insights in the case of the force-layered visualization. They also
               engaged more critically with the dataset, for instance by pointing out
               inconsistencies. The force-directed version, however, drew more comments and
               descriptions about the visualization features, suggesting that participants engaged
               more with the <emph>visualization</emph> in the force-directed condition,
               and with the <emph>data</emph> in the force-layered condition. We also
               found that the force-layered representation elicited more positive emotions such as
               curiosity and expressions of enjoyment or interest, that were not as frequent using
               the force-directed version. Moreover, our results reveal that users perceived the
               social structure shown in force-layered graphs to be smaller, and less complex than
               similar structure visualized through a force-directed layout. However, they were more
               accurate in size estimation using the force-directed layout. </p>
            <p>Concerning recall, we found that participants retained more of the significant
               clusters with the force-layered condition, although they retained more of the bridge
               nodes after using the force-directed version. In both cases, the bridge nodes were
               placed in the center of the visualization, so saliency does not explain the
               difference in these results. We suggest that can be caused by the topology of each
               graph. In the force-layered version, the ties among each family create two horizontal
               substructures that become the major ground of the visual, while the dog-bone
               structure in the force-directed layout represent the major part of the ground figure,
               and the bridge node is an essential part to its structure. Finally, using a raw
               NASA-TLX questionnaire and a preference ranking, we found that participants found the
               force-layered visualization less demanding cognitively. They also judged it to be
               more suited to the tasks and data, and more visually appealing.</p>
            <p>As we analyze these findings in conversation with the literature on visualization in
               humanistic research, we identify emerging discussion points:</p>
            <list type="unordered">
               <item>Engagement with data &amp; engagement with visualization. In the think-aloud
                  study results, we describe how hierarchical trees seemingly elicit an engagement
                  with the <emph>data</emph>, while force-directed layouts trigger
                  comments about the features and characteristics of the <emph>tool</emph>
                  itself. This subtle distinction has relevant implications, as it suggests that the
                  spatial organization of the network affects the perception of the data
                  representation. Visualized data can therefore be integrated in users’ mental
                  models in a way that allows them to analyze and question it; or it can be obscured
                  by the layer of foreign conceptualization that does not allow it to blend with
                  their existing knowledge. As it is, it is critical to encourage representations
                  that allow a connection with the research material itself, and where the
                  visualization features themselves do not become the center of attention for users.
                  We also see this finding as a validating step of the guidelines developed in the
                  Layers of Meaning framework <ptr target="#lamqaddam2020"/>. In this case, by layering meaning
                  through the structure of network graphs, we find that there is an effect to the
                  level of engagement users have with research data. What seems to be a slight
                  visual difference appears to affect the very focus of users’ attention, which in
                  turn reveals the critical aspect of connotative elements and intentional design
                  choices in visualization. </item>
               <item>Force-directed network structure as artifact. In the analysis of the recall of
                  social structure information, we note that more participants recalled the
                  existence of a bridge node between the two clusters with the force-directed
                  network. We suggest that this is due to the singular topology of the generated
                  network. In truth, what is a particular visual characteristic of a network
                  topology (a bridge node between two tight clusters) is an abstraction of a
                  significant piece of information in the dataset (a common person bringing together
                  two large families). In a way, the fact that the force-directed layout created
                  this artificial shape helped highlight a very important information in the data,
                  which has been better remembered by participants. From this perspective, we can
                  thus defend that force-directed layouts also <emph>create</emph> meaning
                  through the specific topologies they generate. These shapes are often singular, or
                  unique, because they are not a product of intentional design. Rather, then come as
                  the result of computations unique to the dataset, the canvas space and the set
                  parameters. We therefore defend the concept of a force-directed network
                  organization as an artifact in itself. One that holds the potential to carry
                  meaning; to be recognized, analyzed, and categorized. </item>
            </list>
            <list type="unordered">
               <item>Defending the importance of challenging mental models. We argue throughout this
                  article that one of the strengths of hierarchical tree structures is that they
                  reproduce existing mental models, therefore making it easier to read and grasp
                  information they represent as it fits within scholars’ existing knowledge.
                  However, existing models of knowledge are not necessarily correct, accurate, or
                  good to perpetuate. For instance, conventional family trees carry a variety of
                  assumptions about social structures that make them both limited and limiting when
                  representing real-life data. Worse, these representations, when uncritically
                  absorbed, function as prescriptive principles of how communities should exist in
                  society. There is therefore an undeniable larger implication in the discussion
                  about how social network data should be represented. The improved understanding,
                  preference and lower effort that hierarchical trees bring needs to be balanced –
                  or perhaps complemented - by the novel perspectives that force-directed layouts
                  create.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Implications &amp; Future work</head>
            <p>More research is needed to assess the effect of other types of structure in network
               visualizations. Once these effects are clearly understood, it would be interesting to
               evaluate how novel graph layout such as our FL algorithm can be introduced to
               existing visualization packages. It would also be interesting to make them
               customizable to specific needs outside of family and generational structures. Indeed,
               an important implication of this work is that any singular off-the-shelf technique
               cannot be sufficient for a solid support of DAH research. Rather than promote the use
               of a specific visualization technique over another, we advocate for researchers
               access to a variety of representation techniques that can accompany different tasks,
               data types, and expertise levels. </p>
            <p>Finally, the generalizability of our discussion to other humanistic fields is an
               additional avenue for future research. Since this study was mainly focused on an art
               historical research, our initial results cannot be readily extrapolated to different
               domains. However, similar challenges of historical social networks exist for humanist
               researchers across disciplines. Future research is needed to evaluate how hierarchy
               in historical social network visualizations affects different research fields
               depending on their unique needs and constraints. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>In this article, we explored the perceptual effect of hierarchy in visualizations of
               historical social networks. We have found, based on a user-centered approach, that
               humanist participants had a hierarchical mental model of social networks, indicating
               that there could be advantages to representing social networks in a similarly
               hierarchical structure. Our study confirmed this hypothesis, as we found that users
               reported lower cognitive load, more frequent and deeper insights, as well as a
               significant preference for the hierarchical representations. Despite these results,
               we nuance these findings by calling attention to the fact that force-directed graphs
               can carry meaning in their generated topology, allow users to make conclusions on
               tightness of networks, clusters, and question the accepted dogmas in terms of
               community structure. However, because social networks are so critical to certain
               humanistic research domains, the perceptual benefits to hierarchically structured
               layouts should not be overlooked. As graph-drawing software is often the most
               accessible way for researchers to gather quick visual overview, we suggest that these
               layouts should be more commonly supported as alternatives to allow scholars to have
               multiple perspectives on their data. </p>
            <p>By these findings, we hope to contribute to the necessary critical discussion
               nuancing the role of network visualization in humanistic research. In the future, we
               would like to broaden the scope of this study by investigating the effects of
               hierarchy for other types of historical (social) networks<note> Within the Cornelia
                  database, hierarchical relations such as those between masters and apprentices in
                  a workshop are good candidates for such an exploration.</note>. We believe such an
               interdisciplinary line of research has the potential to trigger novel questions – for
               instance about the impact of structure in network visualization of historical data,
               and the perceptual effects of commonly used design patterns. Only by questioning what
               we assume to be effective can we (re)design visualization tools that blend in with
               scholars’ experience of their material and practice, and ultimately strengthen the
               value of visualization as a research tool for humanists. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>This research is part of Project Cornelia, a project funded by the University of
               Leuven (KU Leuven) and the Flemish Fund for Scientific Research-Belgium
               (FWO-Vlaanderen). We thank our colleagues from AugmentHCI (Department of Computer
               Science, KU Leuven) and Project Cornelia (Faculty of Arts, KU Leuven) who gave
               feedback and insight into this study. We are also deeply grateful to the entire
               NA+DAH team for supporting and encouraging this line of research, and particularly to
               Dr. John Ladd (Denison University) for reviewing and strengthening this manuscript.
            </p>
         </div>
         
  
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ahnert2020" label="Ahnert et al. 2020">Ahnert, R., Ahnert, S.E., Coleman, C.N. and Weingart, S.B., 2020. <title rend="italic">The Network Turn: Changing Perspectives in the Humanities.</title> Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bertin1973" label="Bertin 1973"> Bertin, J. (1973). <title rend="quotes">Sémiologie graphique: les diagrammes, les réseaux, les cartes.</title> <title
               rend="italic">De Gruyter Mouton</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bishop2018" label="Bishop 2018"> Bishop, C. (2018). <title rend="quotes">Against digital art history.</title> <title rend="italic">International
               Journal for Digital Art History</title>, (3). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="claes2015" label="Claes and Moere 2015"> Claes, S., &amp; Moere, A. V. (2015). <title rend="quotes">The role of tangible interaction in
               exploring information on public visualization displays.</title> In <title rend="italic"
                  >Proceedings of the 4th International Symposium on Pervasive Displays</title> (pp.
               201-207).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="doerum2011" label="Dørum amd Garland 2011"> Dørum, K., &amp; Garland, K. (2011). <title rend="quotes">Efficient electronic navigation: A metaphorical
               question?.</title> <title rend="italic">Interacting with Computers</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >23</title>(2), 129-136.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="drucker2010" label="Drucker 2010"> Drucker, J. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Graphesis: Visual knowledge production and representation.</title> <title
               rend="italic">Poetess Archive Journal, 2(1)</title>, 1-50.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="freeman2004" label="Freeman2004"> Freeman, L. (2004). The development of social network analysis. <title rend="italic">A
               Study in the Sociology of Science</title>, <title rend="italic">1</title>(687),
               159-167.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hart1988" label="Hart and Staveland 1988"> Hart, S. G., &amp; Staveland, L. E. (1988). <title rend="quotes">Development of NASA-TLX (Task Load
               Index): Results of empirical and theoretical research.</title> <title rend="italic">In Advances
                  in psychology (Vol. 52, pp. 139-183)</title>. North-Holland.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kienle2017" label="Kienle 2017"> Kienle, M. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Between nodes and edges: Possibilities and limits of network
               analysis in art history.</title> <title rend="italic">Artl@ s Bulletin, 6(3),</title> 1.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kodama2017" label="Kodama et al. 2017"> Kodama, C., Jean, B. S., Subramaniam, M., &amp; Taylor, N. G. (2017). <title rend="quotes">There’s a creepy
               guy on the other end at Google!: engaging middle school students in a drawing
               activity to elicit their mental models of Google.</title> <title rend="italic">Information
                  Retrieval Journal, 20(5)</title>, 403-432.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kurgan2013" label="Kurgan 2013"> Kurgan, L. (2013). <title rend="quotes">Close up at a distance: Mapping, technology, and politics.</title> <title
               rend="italic">MIT Press</title>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lee2006" label="Lee et al. 2006"> Lee, B., Plaisant, C., Parr, C. S., Fekete, J. D., &amp; Henry, N. (2006). <title rend="quotes">Task
               taxonomy for graph visualization.</title> In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2006 AVI
                  workshop on BEyond time and errors: novel evaluation methods for information
                  visualization</title> (pp. 1-5).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lamqaddam2018" label="Lamqaddam 2018"> Lamqaddam, H., Aerts, J., Brosens, K., &amp; Verbert, K. (2018). <title rend="quotes">Nahr: A
               visual representation of social networks as support for art history research.</title> In <title
                  rend="italic">Proceedings of the 10th Nordic Conference on Human-Computer
                  Interaction</title> (pp. 634-641).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lamqaddam2020" label="Lamqaddam et al. 2020"> Lamqaddam, H., Moere, A. V., Abeele, V. V., Brosens, K., &amp; Verbert, K. (2020).
               <title rend="quotes">Introducing Layers of Meaning (LoM): A Framework to Reduce Semantic Distance of
               Visualization In Humanistic Research.</title> <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on
                  Visualization and Computer Graphics, 27(2)</title>, 1084-1094.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="munzner2014" label="Munzner 2014"> Munzner, T. (2014). <title rend="quotes">Visualization analysis and design.</title> <title rend="italic">CRC
               press</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="manovich2012" label="Manovich 2012"> Manovich, L. (2012). <title rend="quotes">Museum without walls, art history without names: visualization
               methods for Humanities and Media Studies.</title> <title rend="italic">Software Studies
                  Initiative</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="porras2017" label="Porras 2017"> Porras, S. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Keeping our eyes open: Visualizing networks and art history.</title> <title
               rend="italic">Artl@ s Bulletin, 6(3)</title>, 3. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rothschild2014" label="Rothschild 2014"> Rothschild, E. (2014) <title rend="quotes">A Marriage Contract in Angouleme.</title> <title rend="italic">Visualizing
               Historical Networks</title>, accessed July 12, 2021, <ref
                  target="https://histecon.fas.harvard.edu/visualizing/angouleme/83.html"
                  >https://histecon.fas.harvard.edu/visualizing/angouleme/83.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zhang2008" label="Zhang 2008"> Zhang, Y. (2008). <title rend="quotes">The influence of mental models on undergraduate students’ searching
               behavior on the Web.</title> <title rend="italic">Information Processing &amp; Management,
                  44(3)</title>, 1330-1345.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="thoden2017" label="Thoden 2017"> Thoden, K., Stiller, J., Bulatovic, N., Meiners, H.L. and Boukhelifa, N., 2017.
               <title rend="quotes">User-centered design practices in digital humanities–experiences from dariah and
               cendari.</title> <title rend="italic">ABI Technik</title>, <title rend="italic">37</title>(1),
               pp.2-11.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
