<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title type="article">History, People, and Informatics: A Conversation between Sharon
               Irish and Wendy Plotkin</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Sharon <dhq:family>Irish</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Interim Director, Community Informatics Initiative, Graduate School
                  of Library and Information Science, University of Illinois,
                  Urbana-Champaign</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>slirish@illinois.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Sharon Irish has been affiliated with the University of Illinois,
                     Urbana-Champaign, since 1985, the year that she received a Ph.D. in art history
                     from Northwestern University. Irish has published books and articles on art,
                     architecture, building technology, and critical spatial practices. A reviews
                     editor for H-Urban, she also serves as an advisory editor of Technology and
                     Culture. More information is available at <ref
                        target="http://www.sharonirish.org">http://www.sharonirish.org</ref>.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Wendy <dhq:family>Plotkin</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Editor-in-Chief, H-Urban</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>wendyplotkin@wbhsi.net</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Wendy Plotkin is the Editor-in-Chief of H-Urban, and a founder of H-Net, the
                     umbrella organization established in 1993, of which H-Urban was the first
                     scholarly forum. She has written about the digital revolution in a chapter
                     entitled <title rend="quotes">Electronic Texts in the Historical Profession:
                        Perspectives from Across the Scholarly Spectrum</title> in Orville Vernon
                     Burton, ed., <ref target="http://www.press.uillino">
                        <title rend="italic">Computing in the Social Sciences and Humanities</title>
                     </ref> (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 2002); about the educational use
                     of GIS for the <title rend="italic">Journal of the Association for History and
                        Computing</title>; and reviews of books, online exhibits, and digital
                     document collections for the <title rend="italic">Journal of American Planning
                        Association</title>, the <title rend="italic">Journal of American
                        History</title>, and the <title rend="italic">Public Historian</title>. She
                     is completing a book entitled <title rend="italic">Deeds of Mistrust: Race,
                        Housing, and Restrictive Covenants in Chicago, 1900-1953</title>, and has
                     written numerous articles, encyclopedia entries, and conference papers on this
                     and other urban history topics.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000086</idno>
            <idno type="volume">004</idno>
            <idno type="issue">2</idno>
            <date when="2010-09-01">1 September 2010</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2010-06-07" who="Alyssa">initial encoding</change>
         <change when="2013-06-20" who="Tassie Gniady">Changed "dhq:caption" to "head."</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>This extended interview between founding H-Urban editor Wendy Plotkin and H-Urban
               reviews editor Sharon Irish traces the early history of online scholarly
               communication via H-Net, H-Urban, and COMM-ORG, informed by Plotkin’s background as a
               planner and community activist in the 1970s and 1980s. After work with community
               development corporations on the East Coast, Plotkin entered graduate school in urban
               history at the University of Illinois at Chicago. During this period in the early
               nineties, Plotkin had a job with the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI), and then
               collaborated on the development of the forum that became H-Net. In addition to
               standards and protocols about new communication technologies, face-to-face
               relationships grew out of online exchanges, often with lively disagreements about the
               direction of H-Net. Plotkin’s own broadening use of digital tools prompts her
               concluding reflections on historians’ continuing need to use the Internet to overcome
               physical and intellectual fragmentation, and how the Internet has democratized the
               field of history.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>An interview about the early years of urban history online that extends into current
               scholarly debates.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>History, People, and Informatics: A Conversation between Sharon Irish and Wendy
            Plotkin</head>
         <div>
            <head>Preamble</head>
            <p>For three years now (2007-10), I have been the project coordinator for the <ref
                  target="http://www.cii.illinois.edu/">Community Informatics Initiative of the
                  Graduate School of Library and Information Science at the University of
                  Illinois</ref>, Urbana-Champaign (UIUC). Community informatics (CI) is an emerging
               field, with continuing debates about definitions and core questions. Informatics is
               the study of information systems and processes, including computational, social, and
               individual cognition. CI, with its social emphasis, aims to understand not only how
               communities access, create, organize, and share information, but also the types and
               qualities of connections between and among communities. CI scholars and practitioners
               examine the uses of information and communication technologies in
               geographically-distinct and underserved areas, and work with local communities to
               achieve their goals. This focus stresses that reciprocity must characterize
               relationships that involve the distribution and use of information. Community members
               spearhead both naming the issues of the community and the process leading to
               solutions.</p>
            <p>As an historian, I puzzle over which concepts contributed to the emergence of
               community informatics. One convergence of ideas I wanted to investigate occurred in
               the 1990s. Seventeen years ago, in 1993, Wendy Plotkin was a graduate student in
               urban history at the University of Illinois at Chicago (UIC). Her graduate
               assistantship gave her an early entrée to the world of computers and the Internet.
               She used this experience to become a key participant in the launching of <ref
                  target="http://www.h-net.org/">H-Net</ref> (Humanities and Social Sciences on
               Line), an organization devoted to using the Internet for scholarly communication,
               together with a professor of political history, Richard Jensen, and another graduate
               student, Kelly Richter, who specialized in Civil War history. The first of the
               scholarly forums was <ref target="http://www.h-net.org/~urban/">H-Urban</ref>, which
               Wendy established as a model for the later forums, and which is how I came to know
               her.</p>
            <p>Wendy and I met in person for the first time in Chicago, Illinois, in July 2008,
               after having developed a virtual relationship since 2002, when I became review editor
               for H-Urban. I wanted to document her memories and ideas relating to the early years
               of H-Urban. During two conversations in Chicago — one at a noisy restaurant in
               Greektown and a second follow-up meeting in the Italian neighborhood near the campus
               of the University of Illinois at Chicago — Wendy shared her insights about online
               scholarly communication. Our conversations then continued in email exchanges between
               Wendy and me that covered the history of H-Net and H-Urban, her growing interest in
               geospatial technologies, and her ideas for future projects. This article thus takes
               the form of an extended interview in three parts. The first focuses on Wendy’s
               background as a planner and community activist in Boston in the 1970s and 1980s. The
               second examines her decision to become a historian upon her return to Chicago (her
               hometown) in 1990, and her involvement in the creation of H-Net, H-Urban, and
               COMM-ORG, in the subsequent decade. The third considers her broadening use of digital
               tools, reflections on historians’ continuing need to use the Internet to overcome
               physical and intellectual fragmentation, and ideas about how the Internet has
               democratized the field of history.</p>
            <p>— <name>Sharon Irish</name>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Participating in the Community Revolution of the 1970s</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sharon Irish</speaker>
               <p>Wendy, your background in urban planning and policy (especially your years of
                  employment in Boston on housing and economic development issues) really influenced
                  your historical scholarship. Would you talk a bit about this period of your life,
                  and the relationships between planning and your work in urban history?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wendy Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>After graduating from the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign with an
                  undergraduate degree in history (1971), I headed to Boston. I worked in several
                  jobs at the regional planning agency, the <ref target="http://www.mapc.org/"
                     >Metropolitan Area Planning Council (MAPC)</ref>, first in housing and then in
                     transportation.<note>In the late 1970s, the administration of President Jimmy
                     Carter provided funding to regional planning agencies under two initiatives —
                     the Areawide Housing Opportunity Program and the Regional Housing Mobility
                     Program — to promote fair and affordable housing in the nation’s metropolitan
                     regions. The goal of the program was to promote <q>deconcentration</q> of
                     racial minorities from the inner cities to the suburbs. My supervisor was a
                     former community organizer who was opposed to moving African-American residents
                     out of the inner city into the suburbs. While opening up the suburbs to African
                     Americans and other racial minorities was an admirable objective, in the
                     absence of similar initiatives to allow them to stay in improved neighborhoods
                     in the city, it looked a lot like the <q>Negro removal</q> of the urban renewal
                     programs of the 1950s, at a time when the energy crisis was encouraging white
                     gentrification. Staff from regional housing agencies around the country
                     convinced HUD to change the interpretation of the statutory language of the
                     Regional Housing Mobility Program so that, instead of encouraging movement from
                     their neighborhoods, the funds could be used to revitalize the neighborhoods.
                     Watching my supervisor’s participation in these negotiations with HUD, I
                     learned the importance of advocacy and personal contact in shaping how the
                     government implements (or does not implement) legislation, a lesson on the
                     informal processes that affect governance.</note> In the mid-eighties, I got a
                  master’s degree from Tufts University in urban and environmental policy (1983-87),
                  writing a thesis on the Boston Housing Partnership, a major community development
                     project.<note>The Boston Housing Partnership was an umbrella program to garner
                     resources and assist ten community development corporations in rehabilitating
                     and managing a total of 1000 units of multifamily housing in their
                     neighborhoods. The former director, Robert Whittlesey, is now the director of a
                     larger organization, the Housing Partnership Network (<ref
                        target="http://www.housingpartnership.net"
                        >http://www.housingpartnership.net</ref>). The history of the Network is
                     described at <ref target="http://www.housingpartnership.net/about_us/history/"
                        >http://www.housingpartnership.net/about_us/history/</ref>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>After getting my master’s, I worked for the state of Massachusetts (1985-87)
                  during the administration of Governor Michael Dukakis. Amy Anthony, the director
                  of the Executive Office of Communities and Development (EOCD), found innovative
                  ways to help the community development corporations (CDCs) that were becoming
                  prominent players in the creation of Massachusetts housing and business by that
                  time. Then, as now, it was difficult for CDCs to secure operating funds; most of
                  the available funding was for specific projects, putting the proverbial cart
                  before the horse. The CDCs with which we worked didn’t have the money to function
                  and train people in development before becoming involved in complex projects. EOCD
                  provided CEED (Community Economic Enterprise Development) funds that enabled them
                  to do just that, and I worked on <q>Special Projects.</q>
                  <note>The CEED program no longer exists.</note>
               </p>
               <p>From 1987-89, I worked for the city of Boston, helping CDCs get financing for
                  housing and commercial projects. I was the liaison between the banks and the CDCs
                  in securing loans that were packaged with federal and state subsidy and tax credit
                  programs. By that time, I had also became personally involved with the <ref
                     target="http://www.fenwaycdc.org/">Fenway CDC</ref>, which functioned in the
                  neighborhood in which I lived. The Fenway CDC was a nationally known organization
                  that had its roots in fighting arson-for-profit. In the 1980s, it organized
                  against gentrification, developing affordable and ecologically sound housing that
                  included long-term subsidies to maintain a racially and economically diverse
                  neighborhood. I saw up close, not only the economic, but also the social benefits
                  accruing to community members who participated in decisions that affected their
                  lives. They helped to influence the course of development in their neighborhoods,
                  and experienced strong communal ties that grew as a result of their
                  collaboration.</p>
            </sp>
            <figure xml:id="figure01">
               <head>Fensgate Housing Cooperative, <ref
                  target="http://fensgate.com.p6.hostingprod.com/"
                  >http://fensgate.com.p6.hostingprod.com/</ref> The Fenway CDC renovated the
                  Fensgate Housing Cooperative in 1986 in partnership with two private real-estate
                  firms familiar with mixed-income housing. The 1904 building, listed on the
                  National Register of Historic Places, originally had five residential apartments,
                  one on each floor. Today, it has 46 apartments whose different prices reflect the
                  goal of the building to house diverse individuals and households. Courtesy of the
                  Mackin Group</head>
               <graphic url="...000086/resources/figure01.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Burbank Street Building</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>This aspect of your work intersects with community informatics because it values
                  participatory decision-making, using a variety of tools to build strong
                  relationships and coalitions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Yes. And I was particularly impressed by what might be considered an early form of
                  low tech <q>community informatics,</q> in the work of Urban Planning Aid. Urban
                  Planning Aid was a consulting firm established by MIT and Harvard students in
                  Cambridge, Massachusetts, in 1966 to <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#urban1972">provide
                     technical and informational assistance and promote transfer of skills to low
                     income community and workplace groups in Eastern Massachusetts around issues of
                     housing, industrial health and safety, media access, and backup
                     research.</quote><ptr target="#urban1972"/></cit> I became aware of them through their publication <title
                     rend="italic">Less Rent: More Control: A Tenant’s Guide to Rent Control in
                     Massachusetts</title> when I became involved in an action contesting a rent
                  increase in my Beacon Hill building in 1974.<note>
                     <title rend="italic">Urban Planning Aid, Less Rent, More Control: A Tenants
                        Guide to Rent Control in Massachusetts</title> (Cambridge: Urban Planning
                     Aid, 1972).</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Beacon Hill…pretty impressive!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p> Not really - I lived on the less famous side of Beacon Hill, which had a legacy
                  steeped in sailors, prostitutes, and Jewish immigrants. Its housing stock
                  consisted of old three- and four-story apartment buildings, not the Georgian-style
                  mansions on the other side. Massachusetts’ 1972 rent control law required
                  landlords to maintain their properties, and my neighbors and I documented the
                  deficiencies in the building and asked the owners to deal with these prior to
                  being considered for a rent increase.</p>

               <p>Over the years, Urban Planning Aid produced a series of similar manuals, such as
                     <title rend="italic">Tenants First: A Research and Organizing Guide to FHA
                     Housing and How to Use OSHA</title> (the landmark Occupational Health and
                  Safety Act of 1973). They also warned of the perils that existed in reliance on
                  community development corporations because of their roles as developers and
                  owners, which would blunt their potential as activists on behalf of
                     tenants.<note>Emily Achtenberg and Michael Stone, <title rend="italic">Tenants
                        First! A Research and Organizing Guide to FHA Housing</title> (Cambridge:
                     Urban Planning Aid, 1974) and Urban Planning Aid, <title rend="italic">How to
                        Use OSHA</title> (Cambridge: Urban Planning Aid, 1975). The records of Urban
                     Planning Aid, which closed its doors in 1982, are at the University of
                     Massachusetts at Boston (described at <ref
                        target="http://www.lib.umb.edu/node/1645"
                        >http://www.lib.umb.edu/node/1645</ref>). Among those who have assessed
                     their work is Lily M. Hoffman, <title rend="italic">The Politics of Knowledge:
                        Activist Movements in Medicine and Planning</title> (Albany: SUNY,
                     1986).</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <figure xml:id="figure02">
               <head>
                  <title rend="italic">Tenants First! A Research and Organizing Guide to FHA
                     Housing</title> aimed to assist tenants of apartment buildings that were
                  arriving at the end of multi-year contracts with the Federal Housing
                  Administration (FHA). These contracts provided protections against rent increases
                  and evictions. <ptr target="#achtenberg1974"/>
               </head>
               <graphic url="...000086/resources/figure02.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Cover:<title rend="italic">Tenants First! A Research and Organizing Guide to
                     FHA Housing.</title>
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>And yet…you became involved in the Fenway CDC.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>I think that this is because, at heart, I am a moderate, and I wasn’t ready to
                  rule out the benefits to be gained by CDCs, as more radical activists were. While
                  I understood the arguments made by those critical of CDCs, I thought that they
                  represented the possibility of a more socially-conscious, benign type of
                  development, especially if there were external mechanisms — such as the existence
                  of tenant advocacy groups — that would co-exist with them to temper any turn to
                  parochialism and profit orientations. What attracted me to either type of
                  organization — CDC or advocacy group — was their potential for involving
                     <q>ordinary citizens</q> in the decisions that affected their daily lives, the
                  goal that Saul Alinsky so well expressed.</p>

               <p>Because of my more moderate approach to <q>community organizing,</q> it is not
                  surprising that I became an academic and an educator, rather than an activist. I
                  was more interested in investigating society’s dynamics than in siding
                  unequivocally with one side or the other. Furthermore, as an academic, I created
                  H-Urban and Comm-Org to encourage academics and professionals to share scholarship
                  with each other, rather than to disseminate it to <q>ordinary citizens.</q>
               </p>

               <p>These choices suggest the increasing distance that grew between my past and career
                  as an academic. However, my years in Boston impressed on me the value of
                  collaboration, something that was given short shrift in the academic discipline
                  that I chose, history. As a graduate student at Tufts, as a participant in
                  neighborhood organizations, and as a professional providing resources to
                  community-based organizations, I was engaged in enterprises that involved — and
                  were strengthened by — collaboration. When I returned to Chicago in 1989, it was
                  this appreciation for partnership that would be the most important influence on
                  how I applied the digital revolution to the field of history.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>History, the Digital Revolution, H-Net, and H-Urban/Comm-Org</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>1989 was, thus, a major turning point in your life. After working in Boston for
                  seventeen years, you decided to return to Chicago, your hometown, and re-enter
                  academia for a Ph.D. in urban and American history. Why did you decide to leave
                  planning and become a historian?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>In fact, when I returned to Chicago, I considered entering a Ph.D. program in
                     <emph>either</emph> planning or history. I did not feel that I had adequate
                  training to address the complex issues that planners dealt with, and, if I were to
                  continue as a planner, I wished to have more time to explore the theoretical
                  issues (e.g., the <q>greater good,</q> competing visions of the <q>ideal</q>
                  physical environment) and to strengthen my planning skills. This is where chance
                  played a role. I interviewed with both the history and planning departments at the
                  University of Illinois at Chicago; the historian with whom I met was far more
                  interested in my joining the program than the planner. Furthermore, I had never
                  lost my appreciation for history in Boston, and I always saw history as another
                  route to the goal of understanding how cities operated.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>You worked with Perry Duis and Richard Fried at the University of Illinois in
                  Chicago, finishing your doctorate in 1999. Your dissertation was on the dynamics
                  of urban neighborhoods in Chicago, with a special focus on racial deed
                  restrictions and restrictive covenants. These are legal documents that limit
                  access to housing on the basis of racial categories and/or religious affiliation,
                  is that right?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Yes. My interest in racial deed restrictions was stimulated by my community
                  experiences in Boston. CDCs were part of a major movement in the 1960s and 1970s
                  that endorsed the concept of neighborhood-based control, itself an outgrowth of
                  the emphasis on <q>participatory democracy.</q> As a person who had witnessed
                  (during my childhood) the use of such control to thwart racial integration in
                  Chicago — one of the most segregated cities in the nation — I wanted to explore
                  this <q>negative</q> type of community organizing, so as to raise consciousness
                  about the darker side of neighborhood-based control, and alert newer organizations
                  to the dangers of parochialism. I was especially interested in the use of racial
                  deed restrictions by developers and neighborhood groups, because, contrary to
                  public understanding, these were an example of de jure discrimination in the
                  North. My current book, <title rend="italic">Deeds of Mistrust: Race, Housing and
                     Restrictive Covenants in Chicago, 1900-1953</title>, is nearly finished, and I
                  have a website entitled <ref
                     target="http://wbhsi.net/~wendyplotkin/DeedsWeb/index.html">
                     <title rend="quotes">Racial and Religious Restrictive Covenants in the United
                        States and Canada</title>
                  </ref> on the topic. A follow-up project, entitled <title rend="italic">Deeds of
                     Whiteness</title>, will be a national study of these restrictions.<note>For a
                     description of both projects, see Wendy’s webpage at <ref
                        target="http://www.wbhsi.net/~wendyplotkin"
                        >http://www.wbhsi.net/~wendyplotkin</ref>.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <figure xml:id="figure03">
               <head>This 1940 U.S. Supreme Court case involved Carl Hansberry, father of Lorraine
                  Hansberry (author of the 1959 play <title rend="italic">A Raisin in the
                     Sun</title>). Carl was sued by neighbors when, in 1937, he purchased a building
                  covered by a racial restrictive covenant in the Washington Park neighborhood of
                  Chicago, not far from the University of Chicago. The case went through the county
                  and state courts, and ended in the Supreme Court, which ruled that the presence of
                  invalid signatures voided the document. Microfilm edition of <title rend="italic"
                     >Chicago Defender</title> (City Edition). </head>
               <figDesc>
                  <title rend="italic">Chicago Defender</title> headline, <title rend="quotes">Hansberry Decision Opens New Homes to Race</title>
               </figDesc>
               <graphic url="...000086/resources/figure03.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Let’s turn now to your involvement with computers in the early 1990s.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>While I was a graduate student at UIC, I had a job working with the <ref
                     target="http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml">Text Encoding Initiative</ref> (TEI).
                  The TEI is an international collaboration (then funded by the National Endowment
                  for the Humanities and its European counterparts) to pave the way for digital
                  versions of literary and linguistic texts, including historical ones.<note>It did
                     this by creating a <q>mark-up</q> system that would characterize not only the
                     physical content of texts (e.g. title, body, headings), but also the
                     intellectual content (e.g. date, place, war). On the TEI, see <ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml"
                     >http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml</ref>.</note>
               </p>
               <figure xml:id="figure04">
                  <head>Portion of print edition of Alexander Pope's <title rend="italic">The
                     Dunciad</title>. Text Encoding Initiative, <ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/fr/html/SA.html"
                        >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/fr/html/SA.html</ref>.</head>
                  <figDesc>Screenshot of example text.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="...000086/resources/figure04.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="figure05">
                  <head>Several lines of Pope's <title rend="italic">The Dunciad</title> with TEI
                     mark-up. Text Encoding Initiative, <ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/fr/html/SA.html"
                        >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/fr/html/SA.html</ref>.</head>
                  <figDesc>Screenshot of example mark-up.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="...000086/resources/figure05.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p> Working at the TEI triggered my interest in the effects of digitization on the
                  production of history. In 1991, I decided to do an independent study on the
                  subject, and chose faculty member Richard Jensen to guide me. Richard was already
                  legendary for his intellectual contributions to political history (contributing to
                  the <q>ethnocultural</q> and <q>quantitative history</q> schools with his landmark
                     <title rend="italic">The Winning of the Midwest</title>
                  <note>Richard Jensen, <title rend="italic">The Winning of the Midwest: Social and
                        Political Conflict, 1888-1896</title> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
                     1971). In his review for the <title rend="italic">American Historical
                        Review</title>, Lewis Gould described the work as <q>superub</q> and wrote, <quote rend="inline" source="#gould1972">Well
                        written and closely reasoned, <title rend="italic">The Winning of the
                           Midwest</title> brilliantly combines the techniques of the social
                        scientist and the historian to produce a convincing narrative of
                        developments in the principal regional background of partisan conflict at
                        the end of the nineteenth century.</quote> Lewis I. Gould, <title
                        rend="quotes">New Perspectives on the Republican Party, 1877-1913,</title>
                     <title rend="italic">American Historical Review</title> 77:4 (Oct., 1972),
                     1074-1082. Quote on 1076-77. Jensen is routinely included as one of the
                     pioneers of the <q>ethnocultural</q> school in the historical literature; see,
                     for example, <title rend="quotes">The Invention of the Ethnocultural
                        Interpretation,</title>
                     <title rend="italic">American Historical Review</title> 99:2 (April, 1994),
                     453-477, especially 460-463.</note>). However, it was his activities in
                  training historians in the use of computers for quantitative methods that led me
                  to him. From 1971 to 1982, he served as the founding director of the Newberry
                  Library’s Quantitative Institute, which trained over 800 scholars in using
                  quantitative methods in history. Certain similarities existed between Jensen’s
                  goals for the institute and H-Net. Both brought together scholars with similar
                  interests in an emerging field of history, and tended to attract participants from
                  smaller universities and colleges who had fewer networking opportunities than
                  those with larger faculties and student bodies <ptr target="#jensen1983"/>. </p>
               <p> At the time I approached Richard, I think he was already expanding his interest
                  to include the qualitative uses of computers in history, especially in scholarly
                     communication.<note>For the evolution in Jensen’s thoughts on the qualitative
                     uses of the computer among historians, see Richard Jensen, <title rend="quotes"
                        >Historians and Computers: Word Processing,</title>
                     <title rend="italic">OAH</title> Newsletter (1983), 11:2, 15-16; Richard
                     Jensen, <title rend="quotes">The Hand Writing on the Screen,</title>
                     <title rend="italic">Historical Methods</title> 20:1 (Winter, 1987), 35-45; and
                     Richard Jensen, <title rend="quotes">Text Management</title> (Review), <title
                        rend="italic">Journal of Interdisciplinary History</title> 22:4 (Spring,
                     1992), 711-722.</note> Working with him, in 1991-92, I researched and wrote a
                  paper entitled <title rend="quotes">The Use of Electronic Texts in the Historical
                     Profession,</title> interviewing historians, librarians, publishers,
                  archivists, and documentary editors.<note>See <ptr target="#plotkin2003"/>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p> Towards the end of my work on the paper, Richard invited me to meet with him and
                  Kelly Richter, another graduate student in history. The two of them had begun
                  discussing creating an online scholarly history forum, using the <q>bulletin
                     board</q> technology that was one of the early popular means of connecting
                  individual computers. However, I recommended that this new forum instead use
                  Listserv, a more advanced technology I had familiarity with through my work at the
                  TEI. Listserv was superior to the <q>bulletin board</q> technology in a number of
                  ways: it had the advantage of automatically creating <q>logs</q> of all messages,
                  as well as having the capability of storing files. Thus, in creating H-Net,
                  Richard, Kelly, and I decided to use Listserv as the communications software.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>What was H-Net like in its infancy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>It was exhilarating, one of the most exciting times in my life. The three of us
                  took a memorable road trip to Washington, D.C. and the National Endowment for the
                  Humanities (NEH) in October, 1992 (and also celebrated Richard's birthday). We
                  stopped in Gettysburg, Pennsylvania on a crisp, cold, fall day, and Kelly saw the
                  name of an ancestor on one of the gravestones. In Washington, we visited both the
                  American Historical Association (AHA) and the NEH, and shared our ideas with them.
                  Both organizations were encouraging. We went back to UIC and prepared an
                  application for funding by NEH. The first grant was turned down, but the second
                  one, submitted after H-Net had begun operations, succeeded. Thus, H-Net began with
                  funding only from UIC and the volunteer services of people such as Kelly and me,
                  although Jim Mott, a former student of Jensen who was a programmer in statistical
                  analysis (SPSS), soon added his expertise.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>What was your role in creating and shaping H-Net?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>I had proposed to Richard that I create the first H-Net list, on urban history. He
                  agreed, and we discussed a name. I suggested Urban-H, and he said that H-Urban
                  would be better — all of the subsequent lists would begin with <hi rend="quotes"
                     >H-.</hi> I agreed, and began planning H-Urban.</p>

               <p> In 1993, what came to be called the Internet was already in operation, although
                  in its more primitive stages, and there were a few history forums on it. However,
                  these were a mix of serious and amateur historians, and the quality was mediocre,
                  for the most part (the classical scholars were far ahead).<note>
                     <p>The Internet emerged from systems developed by the Defense Advanced Research
                        Projects Agency (DARPA), within the Department of Defense starting in the
                        1960s. These systems were initially set up to allow scientists to exchange
                        large electronic files, but the convenience of exchanging short messages was
                        discovered immediately. The initial civilian system — ARPANET — sent its
                        first message in 1969, but much work remained to develop the physical and
                        systems infrastructure to embrace an entire nation. See Barry M. Leiner et
                        al., <title rend="quotes">All About the Internet: History of the
                           Internet,</title> at <ref
                           target="http://www.isoc.org/internet/history/brief.shtml"
                           >http://www.isoc.org/internet/history/brief.shtml</ref>.</p>
                     <p>For the most part, humanities scholars did not begin to use these systems
                        until the mid-1980s, a decade before the term <term>Internet</term> was
                        adopted for what was, by then, far more seamless and user-friendly than in
                        its early days. Textbook publishers were among the earliest funders of
                        humanities networks, hoping to obtain better information for planning
                        purposes. Among academicians, classicists and literary/linguistic scholars
                        were among the first to use this new tool for group communication, with the
                        creation of <title rend="italic">Humanist</title> and the <title
                           rend="italic">Bryn Mawr Classical Review</title> (BMCR, which only
                        distributed book reviews). In 1985, the <title rend="quotes">Whole Earth
                           ‘Lectronic Link</title> (WELL) brought together <q>authors, programmers, journalists,
                           activists and other creative people</q> to communicate online (<ref
                           target="http://www.well.com/">http://www.well.com/</ref>). At the same
                        time,Professor Lynn Nelson at Kansas State University and others started the
                        first history discussion lists, including Mediev-L, History-L, and HAPSBURG.
                        These lists, while containing some valuable content, did not screen messages
                        or limit their subscriptions to scholars, and were liable to more casual use
                        by amateur historians. For early articles about the Internet and history
                        discussion groups, see Richard W. Slatta, <title rend="quotes">Historians
                           and Telecommunications,</title>
                        <title rend="italic">History Microcomputer Review</title> 2:2 (Fall 1986):
                        25–34; David R. Campbell, <title rend="quotes">The New History Net,</title>
                        <title rend="italic">History Microcomputer Review</title> 3:2 (Fall 1987):
                        25; and Norman R. Coombs, <title rend="quotes">History by
                           Teleconference,</title>
                        <title rend="italic">History Microcomputer Review</title> 4:1 (Spring 1988):
                        37–40.</p>
                  </note> Thus, when we created H-Net and H-Urban, we consciously set out to develop
                  something that would be different — that would be dominated by scholars and
                  practitioners in auxiliary disciplines, and that would have a scholarly tone.
                  Unlike the more free-wheeling online groups on history at the time, H-Net
                  incorporated a strong commitment to core values in academia, including deference
                  to more established scholars and high standards for the content of scholarly
                  communication. Our goal was to wed the best contemporary practices in humanities
                  scholarship to the new possibilities opened up by the Internet. To do this, we
                  created <q>moderated</q> lists, in which all messages would have to go through an
                  advanced graduate student, faculty member, or practitioner. Early on, possibly
                  after the lists had started, we also decided that each list should have a
                     <q>board</q> of the leading scholars in the field. Thus, drawing on the
                  democratic nature of the early Internet, I began to write to urban historians of
                  some repute, and asked them to serve on H-Urban's board. Most agreed. We created
                  the idea of separate lists for the board, and Edboard-Urban was born. </p>
               <p>On February 24, 1993, I sent out the first H-Urban (and H-Net) message; many more
                  followed. The messages were a mix of announcements, queries, and attempts to
                  promote discussion — the latter the least successful, unless we were discussing
                  urban poetry or urban films. In those early days, as a graduate student, I took
                  the time to abstract book reviews in the major journals, and also to develop
                  mini-essays on a variety of urban historical topics. When key urban historians
                  passed away, I'd summarize the major obituaries or write one myself. I began to
                  combine conversations on the same topic, and to store them on the Listserv
                     <q>fileserv</q> (or server), alerting our subscribers that they could obtain
                  this summary with an e-mail with a command such as <q>Get Electric Streetcars.</q>
                  Membership grew from 25 to 50 to over 100. (We are now over 2,000.)</p>
            </sp>
            <figure xml:id="figure06">
               <head>An example of the interface of a Bulletin Board System (BBS), an early group
                  messaging system in the 1980s and 1990s. Vintage Computing and Gaming, <ref
                     target="http://www.vintagecomputing.com/wp-content/bbsmenu_large.jpg"
                     >http://www.vintagecomputing.com/wp-content/bbsmenu_large.jpg</ref>.</head>
               <figDesc>Bulletin Board System Interface Screenshot</figDesc>
               <graphic url="...000086/resources/figure06.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>What about the other early H-Net groups?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>H-Urban was not alone for long. H-Women followed soon, as did H-Ethnic, H-Film,
                  H-Family, H-Teach, H-Labor, H-Law, H-Medieval, H-Politics, H-CivWar, H-South,
                  H-SHGAPE, HOLOCAUS and H-Antisemitism, HAPSBURG, H-Albion, H-Asia, H-Africa,
                  H-Business, H-Diplo, H-Film, H-German, H-Grad, H-Ideas, H-Judaic, H-Latam,
                  H-Local, H-Oz, H-PCAACA, H-State, H-West (I am probably forgetting a few). A few
                  of these lists pre-dated H-Net, and eventually became H-Net lists in the first
                  years of the organization, incorporating H-Net’s more scholarly approach and
                  features when they did.</p>

               <p> Beyond this list of names, I think it is useful to emphasize the extent to which
                  H-Net became a <q>virtual community,</q> one that, for many of us, was more
                  meaningful than the cohort groups at our places of work. At the time, graduate
                  students and faculty members who were interested in the use of the Internet were
                  in the minority, and H-Net brought us together in a medium that allowed ongoing,
                  easy contact. </p>
               <p> Furthermore, in spite of the assertion that involvement in the Internet led to
                  social isolation, important personal and professional relationships formed among
                  us. At least in my own case, the chance to meet these colleagues face to face
                  enhanced, although it did not replace, these relationships. </p>
            </sp>
            <figure xml:id="figure07">
               <head>Sidebar showing early H-Net lists at UIC. Thomas J. DeLoughry, <title
                  rend="quotes">History, Post-Print</title>, <title rend="italic">Chronicle of
                     Higher Education</title> (12 January 1994), A19.</head>
               <figDesc/>
               <graphic url="...000086/resources/figure07.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Did you stay involved in H-Net after you started H-Urban?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Yes, the other lists initially used H-Urban as a model, and I began to teach the
                  other moderators how to use Listserv. We created H-Staff and H-Editor, and used
                  these in-house lists to discuss how to run these new types of forums. Each list
                  had to create standards for subscription and postings, with the goal of nurturing
                     <q>virtual communities</q> of scholars and students in similar fields. There
                  were questions about the extent to which this new tool should be used to
                  democratize scholarly communication; for example, should H-Net conform to
                  traditional scholarly and copyright standards? Some argued that the Internet
                  should be used to do away with many of the hierarchical and proprietary practices
                  within academia; others thought that these should be maintained at the same time
                  that a more informal means of communication was offered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Where did you stand?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>I am a traditionalist, and thus I supported the second of the above views. For
                  example, I argued that all postings should include a signature and an
                  institutional affiliation, and, ideally, the academic status of the author. My
                  argument for doing this was not to defend special privileges for those higher up
                  on the ladder, but to provide H-Urban and H-Net readers with the background
                  necessary to appraise the contributions of those who posted, and to promote the
                  networking goals of the lists.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Would you say that you represented the mainstream or the minority in your
                  views?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Probably the mainstream, at the time. I had significant differences over copyright
                  with Richard Jensen, which led to tension between us. Richard argued for a more
                  liberal approach in borrowing material for use on the Internet; I disagreed.
                  Meanwhile, those who posted to the lists began to test other boundaries early on —
                  from sending e-mail with no capitalization to offering political tracts on current
                  or historical topics.<note>Among the pieces attacking the type of gatekeeping
                     practiced by H-Net, see Jesse Lemisch, <title rend="quotes">The First Amendment
                        is Under Attack in Cyberspace,</title>
                     <title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher Education</title>, 41:19, January 20,
                     1995, A56. For a more recent discussion of the topic, see Thomas W. Zeiler,
                        <title rend="quotes">Is Democracy a Good Thing?</title>
                     <title rend="italic">OAH Council of Chairs</title> Newsletter 34 (November
                     2006), at <ref target="http://www.oah.org/pubs/nl/2006nov/zeiler.html"
                        >http://www.oah.org/pubs/nl/2006nov/zeiler.html</ref>. On the debate over
                     requiring authors of posters to identify themselves, see Lisa Guernsey, <title
                        rend="quotes">Scholars Debate the Pros and Cons of Anonymity in Internet
                        Discussions,</title>
                     <title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher Education</title>, 43:6, October 4,
                     1996, A23-24. See Melvin E. Page, <title rend="quotes">Editing an H-Net
                        Discussion List,</title>
                     <title rend="italic">OAH</title> Newsletter 52 (August 1996), at <ref
                        target="http://www.h-net.org/about/press/oah/page.html"
                        >http://www.h-net.org/about/press/oah/page.html</ref> for a thoughtful
                     overview of the stylistic issues associated with H-Net editing.</note> While
                  this occurred on all lists, lists such as H-Antisemitism and HOLOCAUS had special
                  difficulties, with Holocaust deniers insisting on their rights to post. The
                  editors of these lists stood firm in refusing to entertain discussions of marginal
                  or questionable scholarship, and, in so doing, did H-Net a service in establishing
                  a reputation for scholarliness.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>What were some of the highlights of these early years?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>For me, the most important was when H-Urban became the first list to invite a
                  moderator from outside of the United States (Alan Mayne, then at University of
                  Melbourne, now at University of South Australia). This, and the international
                  membership, added a <q>multicultural</q> element to H-Net. Less traveled scholars
                  such as I learned about the reverse of seasons in the northern and southern
                  hemispheres, the different <q>summer</q> vacations of scholars in different parts
                  of the world, and the range of academic titles and ranks in different
                     countries.<note>See <ptr target="#marcus1996"/> at <ref
                        target="http://www.h-net.org/about/press/oah/intl.html"
                        >http://www.h-net.org/about/press/oah/intl.html</ref> for a good early
                     examination of H-Net’s global reach.</note> The expansion of the list staffs
                  also created a community of editors within each list, among whom policies and
                  practices were discussed and refined. Soon after Alan joined me, others followed:
                  Martha Bianco (a graduate student and then instructor at Portland State
                  University), Mark Peel (a historian at Monash University, Australia), Maureen
                  Flanagan (a historian at at Michigan State University), and Keith Tankard (then a
                  historian at Rhodes University in South Africa). Our first non-historian was
                  Mickey Lauria, a leading planning scholar, who is among the longest serving
                  editors.</p>

               <p>To accommodate decision-making among us, we created the first <q>editors list</q>
                  (Edit-Urban) for discussion of policy. Soon, we established the <q>editors'
                     manual,</q> which was a list of our policies. This grew over time as more
                  decisions were made, and became a resource for training new editors. We debated
                  such things as enforcing proper grammar (after someone sent in a posting in the
                  e.e. cummings mode of all lower case), and agreed that we would require proper
                  grammar and would retain the right to edit postings. We began to check and expand
                  citations of scholarship that were sent in, and, as history resources became more
                  numerous on the World Wide Web (WWW) in 1993 and 1994, we added links to
                  information about scholarship. We also reserved the right to reject
                     <q>non-scholarly</q> postings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Other highlights?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>H-Urban posted the first book review on H-Net (long before we had a formal review
                  system), and also introduced the idea of a subscriber's survey.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>With all of this time given to H-Urban, did you start to shift your focus away
                  from H-Net as a whole?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Yes, for a variety of reasons. I needed to focus on my dissertation and other
                  graduate studies, so as to develop the traditional historical skills and knowledge
                  that would give me credibility within the historical community. Thus, I only had
                  so much time to give to H-Net and H-Urban, and H-Urban increasingly took much of
                  my time. The policy disagreements that I had had with Richard Jensen about H-Net
                  made me more inclined to devote time to H-Urban. Not only that, but I was not
                  primarily interested in the administrative, technical, or even policy aspects of
                  H-Net and H-Urban — I was in it primarily for the scholarly benefits it had to
                  offer.</p>

               <p> Finally, H-Net stayed at UIC for only two years, and moved in 1995 to Michigan
                  State University. Thus, graduate students and faculty at Michigan State University
                  began to take more of the leadership and staffing roles. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Why did H-Net move to Michigan State University?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Michigan State (MSU) was more willing than UIC to invest in H-Net, and H-Net’s
                  rising star, Mark Kornbluh, was a faculty member in the History Department.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>How did the change in location affect H-Net?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Well, first, Michigan State made a major financial commitment to H-Net, and this
                  investment allowed H-Net to take advantage of the powerful technology of the WWW,
                  and to provide a permanent technical and training staff. This was a scenario that
                  fulfilled the commitment of Mark Kornbluh, and another H-Net activist, Peter
                  Knupfer, to move H-Net beyond just e-mail lists.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Was there anyone who disagreed with this scenario?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Yes, in fact — Richard Jensen and Jim Mott — and this turned out to be the crux of
                  the 1997 H-Net election. I should give you a bit of background on this. </p>

               <p> In 1994, H-Net had organized itself and elected Richard Jensen as Executive
                  Director for a three year term. At the same time, Mark Kornbluh was elected as the
                  chair of the H-Net Executive Board. In 1997, H-Net had its first contested
                  election for executive and associate directors: Richard Jensen and Jim Mott
                  against Mark Kornbluh and Peter Knupfer.</p>
               <p>Each of the slates had a different vision for H-Net. Richard Jensen argued for a
                  reliance on the discussion lists as the core of H-Net, while Mark Kornbluh
                  advocated for the development of WWW pages to augment the discussions. In the end,
                  the H-Net editors elected Mark Kornbluh and Peter Knupfer as Executive and
                  Associate Director, and H-Net developed according to their vision (<ptr
                     target="#marcus1996"/>, <ptr target="#guernsey1997"/>).</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Which vision did you support?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>The Kornbluh-Knupfer one. It was my interest in digitization of texts that had led
                  to my involvement in H-Net, and I was fascinated by the possibilities of making
                  primary and secondary documents available on the WWW, as well as teaching and
                  other materials. On H-Urban, we created an annotated list of WWW sites related to
                  urban history. We increased our production of book reviews, and created a Teaching
                  Center, with scores of syllabi.<note>An early description of H-Net’s website is
                     Mark Lawrence Kornbluh, <title rend="quotes">The H-Net Website: Designing
                        OnLine Resources for Scholars and Teachers,</title>
                     <title rend="italic">OAH Council of Chairs</title> Newsletter, 52 (August
                     1996), at <ref target="http://www.h-net.org/about/press/oah/web.html"
                        >http://www.h-net.org/about/press/oah/web.html</ref>. On the H-Net Book
                     Review project, see Patricia Lee Denault, <title rend="quotes">The H-Net Review
                        Project,</title>
                     <title rend="italic">OAH Council of Chairs</title> Newsletter 52 (August 1996),
                     at <ref target="http://www.h-net.org/about/press/oah/essaybr.html"
                        >http://www.h-net.org/about/press/oah/essaybr.html</ref>. On H-Net’s
                     teaching rsources, see Sara Tucker and Robert Wheeler, <title rend="quotes"
                        >H-Net and the Classroom: H-Teach,</title>
                     <title rend="italic">OAH Council of Chairs</title> Newsletter 52 (August 1996),
                     at <ref target="http://www.h-net.org/about/press/oah/teach.html"
                        >http://www.h-net.org/about/press/oah/teach.html</ref>.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Did these features add to H-Urban’s success?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Definitely, largely because we were able to attract dedicated and committed
                  scholars such as Clay McShane, Roger Biles, and you to take on the book review and
                  other features!<note>Clay McShane is a professor at Northeastern University, and a
                     historian of urban technology, with landmark books <title rend="italic">Down
                        the Asphalt Path: American Cities and the Automobile</title> (Columbia,
                     1994) and <title rend="italic">The Horse in the City: Living Machines in the
                        Nineteenth Century</title> (Johns Hopkins University, 2007). Roger Biles is
                     a professor at Illinois State University, and the author of numerous books,
                     including <title rend="italic">Richard J. Daley: Politics, Race, and the
                        Governing of Chicago</title> (Northern Illinois University, 1995) and <title
                        rend="italic">Crusading Liberal: Paul H. Douglas of Illinois</title>
                     (Northern Illinois University Press, 2002).</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Did you have a web designer, as well, or did H-Net do the web design?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>We were extremely fortunate to have Charlotte Agustin, a historian with an M.A. in
                  history, working as a web designer for us. Charlotte was an outstanding designer,
                  who developed and maintained the all of the H-Urban webpages. However, Charlotte’s
                  contribution went well beyond that. She has a fine analytical mind, and
                  participated in the intellectual decisions that went into the Teaching and
                  Weblinks pages, eventually, in effect, taking over all aspects of the teaching
                  site, including editing and posting the syllabi, among our most popular products.
                  Charlotte and I shared a belief in the significance of producing syllabi that had
                  a consistent format and complete citation information on the readings, which added
                  to the time needed to process them. However, I believe that it is this effort that
                  made our syllabus collection stand out from others on the web, although Charlotte
                  had to step back from her intense activity with H-Urban to return to
                  income-producing activities.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>You worked very hard, as I recall, trying to generate discussion on H-Urban. You
                  contacted leading scholars in the field, asking them to contribute substantial
                  commentary on significant urban history questions so that you could post these
                  online and moderate a discussion. It wasn’t a resounding success, was it? Why
                  not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Because those of us who created H-Net had not really taken into account the
                  significant obstacles that stood in the way of online discussion among historians
                  in college and university settings, especially in the United States. Most
                  important was an academic reward system that favored formal, print, peer-reviewed
                  communication (as opposed to ongoing, informal, online communication). Such a
                  system produced so much pressure on academics to publish and teach that there was
                  little time left for informally broadening their horizons in an international and
                  interdisciplinary forum.</p>

               <p> I had hoped to encourage a flowing discussion of major arguments and assertions
                  within urban history. However, most historians preferred to use their research and
                  writing time to put these ideas on paper for publications that would garner them
                  credit rather than on a public Internet list. Note that it is not the online
                  environment that was necessarily the most important aspect here, but the emphasis
                  within academia of formal, peer-reviewed communication manifested in books,
                  articles, and reviews. </p>
            </sp>
            <figure xml:id="figure08">
               <head>A sample of discussions on H-Net Lists this month. Lisa Guernsey, <title
                  rend="quotes">A Humanities Network Considers What Lies Beyond E-Mail</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher Education</title> 43:20 (24 January
                  1997), A23-A24.</head>
               <figDesc>H-Net Lists Sample Discussions</figDesc>
               <graphic url="...000086/resources/figure08.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Were there any other factors that discouraged discussion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>One that relates to urban history, I believe. Urban history has increasingly
                  fragmented into distinct geographical, chronological, and thematic domains.
                  National boundaries still act as barriers to comparative work, and, in the United
                  States, most historians of 18th, 19th, and 20th century cities show little
                  interest in seeking continuities with the earlier cities in the rest of the world.
                  This is partly because they believe that the “modern” city was a significant
                  departure, if not a complete break, from earlier cities, but also because the
                  continents seem so different.</p>

               <p>Similar barriers exist between political, social, cultural and other historians of
                  cities, who have not succeeded, I believe, in establishing connections between
                  their findings.</p>

               <p>These differences limit the ability of many urban historians to develop and
                  discuss their topics in a comparative framework, the type of focus to which the
                  Internet is especially suited. I have often thought that groups with a more narrow
                  focus — e.g., H-UrbTransport, H-UrbHousing, H-UrbReligion — would be more dynamic
                  than H-Urban, because, at this level, historians begin to share more
                  interests.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Was your decision to create <ref target="http://comm-org.wisc.edu/node/"
                     >COMM-ORG</ref> in 1995 an effort to move in this direction?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>In part, although I was also interested in testing a different model from H-Urban.
                  I established COMM-ORG — an on-line seminar on the history of community organizing
                  and community-based development — in November 1995, and served as editor through
                  December 1996. Funded by the University of Illinois at Chicago <ref
                     target="http://uic.edu/cuppa/gci/index.shtml">Great Cities</ref> program,
                  COMM-ORG was an online forum involving periodic presentations of working papers
                  and discussion on the history and practice of community organizing and/or
                  community-based development. It allowed me to examine the possibility of online
                  scholarly collaboration in the specific area of urban history that was closest to
                  my personal and professional experiences in Boston and the dissertation research
                  that evolved from that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Why did you use this more formal approach?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Because of my frustration at the refusal of scholars to engage in substantive
                  discussions on H-Urban. I thought that, if papers were presented, this might
                  trigger discussion – and, even if it didn’t, there would at least be the outcome
                  of an online piece of scholarship.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Was this more successful?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Not really. Again, it was difficult to get leaders in the field to contribute
                  papers, for an obvious reason — COMM-ORG did not include peer-review prior to
                  publishing papers. Thus, there was no academic credit for preparing a paper to
                  post on COMM-ORG. We were lucky to get as many good papers as we did, from senior,
                  Internet-adept scholars who no longer had to worry about tenure and promotion;
                  junior scholars who appreciated the opportunity to post work that had been
                  rejected for formal publication; and academics in disciplines where publishing was
                  less important.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>What happened to COMM-ORG?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Under the current able editorship of Randy Stoecker, who produced one of the best
                  papers during my period overseeing it, COMM-ORG continues to be a vital forum for
                  practitioners and scholars. For the most part, it focuses on current practices and
                  theory of community organizing, rather than its history.<note>COMM-ORG is now an
                     independent list operated by Randy Stoecker of the University of Wisconsin, at
                        <ref target="http://comm-org.wisc.edu/">http://comm-org.wisc.edu/</ref>. In
                     addition to the history there, see Randy Stoecker, <title rend="quotes">Online
                        for Organizing: The Story,</title> June 2000, at <ref
                        target="http://www.plannersnetwork.org/publications/mag_2000_3_mayjun.html"
                        >http://www.plannersnetwork.org/publications/mag_2000_3_mayjun.html</ref>.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Wendy, we have been looking backwards at events that occurred over ten years ago.
                  Since then, you have matured as a scholar and taught at a major university. How
                  has the passage of time affected your perspective on H-Urban? For instance, what
                  is the impact of newer technologies on H-Net and H-Urban?</p>

               <p> In June, the <title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher Education</title> published
                  an article entitled <title rend="quotes">Change or Die: Scholarly E-Mail Lists,
                     Once Vibrant, Fight for Relevance.</title> It quoted T. Mills Kelly, the
                  associate director of the Center for History and New Media at George Mason
                  University, and a former H-Net editor, as saying that the advent of blogging,
                  Twitter, and similar technologies is likely to make <cit>
                     <quote rend="inline" source="#young2009">e-mail lists…increasingly
                        irrelevant</quote>
                     <ptr target="#young2009"/>
                  </cit>. Do you agree with this assessment? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>No, not at all. Mills was basing this assessment on his experience with those
                  lists in which he was involved. According to the <title rend="italic"
                     >Chronicle</title>, Kelly noted that <q>one of
                     those lists shut down for lack of use in 2005, and the activity on the others
                     sputters along with little useful information.</q>
               </p>

               <p>However, H-Urban’s experience has been virtually the opposite. Our subscriptions
                  are coming in at a faster pace than at any other time except in the initial years,
                  with a total of almost 2000 active subscribers from 48 countries. The United
                  States accounts for a high proportion of these — approximately three-quarters —
                  with Canada, the United Kingdom, Australia, Germany, France, and the Netherlands
                  next in order. Most of those joining seem to be younger faculty and graduate
                  students, with an increasing number coming from outside of the United States,
                  although H-Urban subscribers include many — although not all — of the leading
                  international urban historians. A cross-section of subscribers within the last
                  year includes an assistant professor of history at St. Olaf’s College in
                  Minnesota; a Ph.D. candidate in history at the University of Chicago; and an
                  assistant dean of a Maryland pharmacy college who works on environmental health
                  and historical epidemiology.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>To what do you attribute this growth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Largely, to the greater comfort of a new generation with the Internet, and the
                  availability of improved facilities for accessing it. However, two other factors
                  play a role, I believe: H-Urban’s reputation for quality, including posting
                  information that is considered to be relevant, and our outreach to new board
                  members from outside of the United States.</p>

               <p>However, H-Urban occasionally loses subscribers, which is always disappointing to
                  me — and it seems to be some of the older, more established scholars who choose
                  not to stay. I don’t think that this is a result of the medium, but because they
                  have less need for the announcements, calls for papers, book reviews, and syllabi
                  that comprise the major features of H-Urban. It’s not that this material is not of
                  a high quality, but that scholars can obtain this material from journals.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Do you still believe that there is a role for online discussion in the scholarly
                  world, or have you accepted the more traditional preference among historians to
                  record their findings primarily in books and articles?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>I do believe that there is a role for online work, and I have <emph>not</emph>
                  accepted the traditional preference for books and articles at the cost of online
                  discussion. In fact, these years of teaching and research have led me to question
                  the scholarly forms and practices that evolved during the era of print. If one
                  examines these forms and practices closely, one sees that, to a great extent, they
                  arose because of the reliance on print. For example, the high cost of producing
                  and distributing scholarship made it more efficient (in terms of cost and time) to
                  package and deliver lengthy manuscripts and unrelated collections of articles and
                  book reviews at periodic intervals.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Haven’t historians continued to use these forms for intellectual reasons?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Yes and no. I think that, within history, the book form has persisted because
                  history has been considered a humanities discipline, and the art and craft of
                  writing is deemed a key part of historical production. Writing ability carries
                  greater weight among historians than among social scientists — a standard with
                  which I agree.</p>

               <p>In addition, this attitude has been buttressed by the growing belief in the late
                  20th century in the <emph>organic</emph> and <emph>subjective</emph> nature of
                  history. By <q>organic,</q> I mean the sense that most arguments are so complex
                  that they require a book-length document for their exposition — and that a
                  historian must display the skill to grapple with intertwining layers of evidence
                  and analysis over a specified chronological period to be able to reveal the past
                  in all its complexity.</p>

               <p> By <q>subjective,</q> I refer to the effects of the skepticism and linguistic
                  concerns that seeped into all academic disciplines in the 1960s and after. Within
                  history, these factors heightened the sense that authors’ <emph>worldviews</emph>
                  and <emph>assumptions</emph> were the engines that organized the strands of
                  evidence and analysis into unique configurations — and that historian’s books
                  were, in fact, an intricate mix of fact and interpretation that was as much art as
                  science. </p>
               <figure xml:id="figure09">
                  <head>Peter Novick, <title rend="italic">That Noble Dream: The <q>Objectivity
                     Question</q> and the American Historical Profession</title> (Cambridge
                     University Press, 1988). <ref
                        target="http://www.cambridge.org/us/catalogue/catalogue.asp?isbn=0521343283"
                        >http://www.cambridge.org/us/catalogue/catalogue.asp?isbn=0521343283</ref>.
                     This 1988 history of the American historical profession detailed the decreasing
                     faith among historians in the existence of a single objective truth.</head>
                  <figDesc>The cover image of <title rend="italic">That Noble
                     Dream</title>.</figDesc>
                  <graphic url="...000086/resources/figure09.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p> However, I believe that this outlook denies the degree to which good historical
                  monographs consist of <emph>debatable facts</emph> and <emph>ideas</emph> that can
                  be separated and evaluated individually and sequentially in online forums as well
                  as in the <q>manuscript</q> package. I am not saying that books should be
                  abolished, but that historians should begin to develop intermediate evaluative
                  processes in which the ideas and evidence within them are tested, before they are
                  packaged as articles and monographs. </p>
               <p> As for journals, the choice of publishing a group of articles and book reviews in
                  periodic issues is also a reflection of the economies of print. Except for the
                  occasional special issue, these typically combine articles on topics that have few
                  common themes or connections. Online journals have generally continued this
                  packaging of dissimilar materials. With the digital medium, I believe it makes
                  more sense to publish the articles singly, so that it is easier for the scholars
                  to save and organize them. </p>
               <p> There is also a need for a classification system that would tag <emph>all</emph>
                  books and articles, regardless of location or chronological period, in a
                  consistent manner. The classification systems currently in place do not cross
                  national boundaries, and were not created by urban scholars. Even in the digital
                  age, it is difficult for a researcher to find all of the relevant work on a topic
                  – and this process takes up a significant amount of time. If urbanists in a
                  variety of disciplines collaborated to create and maintain a classification system
                  that would encompass existing and new work, this would speed up that part of the
                  research process that involves identifying and retrieving relevant work on a given
                  topic across geographical and chronological lines. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Are your beliefs in this area tied to the latest of the projects in which you are
                  interested — the <title rend="italic">Historical Encyclopedia of
                  Urbanism</title>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Yes. The <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia</title> — a collaborative, online,
                  historical encyclopedia of international urban studies and history — would provide
                  a central place for storing up-to-date knowledge on key concepts in urbanism, in a
                  manner that would promote comparative analysis. The idea for this emerged from my
                  experiences in teaching historical methods to undergraduates. I had always
                  encouraged students to use encyclopedias as a means of obtaining a concise summary
                  of the state of knowledge on a topic at the start of their research. However, when
                  I assigned the entry on <q>the city</q> in the <title rend="italic">Britannica
                     Online</title>, I (and the students) were shocked at the Western bias in the
                  entry, with almost nothing on the cities of Asia, Africa, and Latin America. This
                  led me to investigate the history of encyclopedias, including <title rend="italic"
                     >Encyclopedia Britannica</title>, and to evaluate the importance of
                  encyclopedias, which many scholars dismiss as serious sources for scholarly
                  information.</p>

               <p> This dismissal is ironic, because, in recent years, encyclopedias on all topics
                  have proliferated, leading to what I have labeled <q>intellectual sprawl.</q> The
                  idea of an encyclopedia is to publish concise information about a topic so as to
                  provide a source for scholars who do not have the time to keep up with the
                  thousands of books and articles published each year. I consider this not only a
                  sound rationale for their creation, but one that is increasing in importance each
                  day, as the volume of information on any topic multiplies geometrically. </p>
               <p> However, the proliferation of encyclopedias defeats their ability to serve their
                  audiences, for it forces the reader to keep track of each new encyclopedia on the
                  topic of her interest. Print encyclopedias are expensive, and most individuals can
                  afford only one or two. And, in these days of the Internet, how likely is it that
                  either faculty or students will make a special trip to the library to consult an
                  encyclopedia? </p>
            </sp>
            <figure xml:id="figure10.jpg">
               <head>Kenneth T. Jackson, <title rend="italic">The Encyclopedia of New York
                  City</title> (Yale University Press, 1995).</head>
               <figDesc>Cover of <title rend="italic">The Encyclopedia of New York
                  City</title>.</figDesc>
               <graphic url="...000086/resources/figure10.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>How does the <title rend="italic">Historical Encyclopedia of Urbanism</title> aim
                  to stop this proliferation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>By borrowing some of the lessons learned from Wikipedia. Wikipedia, in spite of
                  its commonly cited flaws, has shown how a single encyclopedia can become a
                     <q>standard</q> if it is easily accessible, current, and of an acceptable
                  quality. Accessibility comes from being online and freely available. Currency of
                  information is obtained through the involvement of groups of individuals in
                  updating it on an ongoing basis, rather than relying on a small number of
                  contributors chosen by an editor to update it once every five or six years, if
                  ever. Quality is secured by having the encyclopedia editors provide ongoing
                  oversight of information for terms of two to four years instead of taking on the
                  massive job of updating all knowledge in a field in one or two years.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Say something more about quality, frequently cited as the <q>Achilles heel</q> of
                  Wikipedia. As Stephen Colbert satirized in his television show on Wikipedia
                  (available at <ref
                     target="http://www.colbertnation.com/the-colbert-report-videos/72347/july-31-2006/the-word---wikiality"
                     >http://www.colbertnation.com/the-colbert-report-videos/72347/july-31-2006/the-word---wikiality</ref>),
                  the veracity of its contents is always vulnerable to the provision (intentional or
                  unintentional) of false or incomplete information by users.<note>See <title
                        rend="quotes">Wikiality,</title> Stephen Colbert’s satirical monologue on
                     Wikipedia, at <ref
                        target="http://www.comedycentral.com/colbertreport/videos.jhtml?videoId=72347"
                        >http://www.comedycentral.com/colbertreport/videos.jhtml?videoId=72347</ref>.
                     There is a growing scholarly literature on Wikipedia; among the most thoughtful
                     by a historian, see Roy Rosenzweig, <title rend="quotes">Can History Be Open
                        Source? Wikipedia and the Future of the Past,</title>
                     <title rend="italic">Journal of American History</title> 93:1 (June, 2006),
                     117-146.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Quality is certainly among the most important issues, and products such as
                  Wikipedia are always suspect on this score. However, I would argue that the
                  traditional model of creating encyclopedias also diminishes quality. The <title
                     rend="italic">Encyclopedia </title> aims to remedy the defects in both the
                  Wikipedia and traditional models.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>You certainly don’t shy away from ambitious goals! How will this project promote
                  quality scholarship?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>In the first place, the <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia </title> would be
                  maintained by editors who are established scholars in the field. One of their
                  roles would be to ensure that all information in the encyclopedia is accurate, and
                  that the entry on any given topic is written in a coherent manner.</p>

               <p> In the second place, the <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia </title> would not
                  rely on a single scholar to summarize the state-of-the-art knowledge on a given
                  topic, as do traditional encyclopedias. Rather, it invites scholars from across
                  the globe to incrementally suggest additions, subject to approval and editing by
                  the original author of the entry or one of the editors. I believe that this will
                  result in a higher quality of information than encyclopedias that require single
                  individuals or an occasional team to cover a broad expanse of information. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Why?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Even the best scholars are not aware of all developments in their area of
                  expertise, especially over time. The number of places to publish is expanding, and
                  it is difficult to keep up with new scholarly information on <emph>any</emph>
                  topic. The lack of incentives for spending time on encyclopedia entries also works
                  against quality, as encyclopedia entries have little weight in the promotional
                  standards that determine scholars’ advancement and salary.</p>

               <p>In addition, the reliance on print for many encyclopedias works as a deterrent
                  against frequent updates. The costs of issuing a new edition (editorial time,
                  printing, distribution) are so great that new editions are done at relatively long
                  intervals, if done at all. Thus, they quickly become out-of-date.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Does Wikipedia offer a model for updating an encyclopedia?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>No — because of the need for quality assurance (in terms of content and writing),
                  something that Wikipedia does not yet offer. Citizendium, which dubs itself <q>a citizen’s compendium of everything,</q> is another project intended to
                  add quality standards to an online encyclopedia by attaching names to the
                  articles. The organizers select editors who are responsible for overseeing
                  additions. However, I don’t believe that <ref
                     target="http://en.citizendium.org/wiki/Welcome_to_Citizendium"
                     >Citizendium</ref> will be accepted among scholars in specific disciplines,
                  because its highest level decision-makers are not specialists in
                     <emph>their</emph> disciplines. </p>

               <p>Thus, I see the need for the <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia </title> to develop
                  an editorial structure that draws on established scholars in urban history. To do
                  this, the editing of the <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia </title> will have to
                  parallel the editing of scholarly journals, i.e, a continuous process. The senior
                  editors of the <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia </title> would serve as long as
                  editors of scholarly journals, with occasional handovers to new editors,
                  consistent with the experience of scholarly journals. Of course, they will have to
                  be assisted by a comprehensive network of contributing editors who are specialists
                  in specific places, time periods, and topics. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>It sounds as if the <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia </title> could really help
                  reshape the field of urban history. What other innovations would this project
                  feature?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>The most important — and the most daunting — is the design of an organizational
                  structure that will depart from the alphabetical organization favored by most
                  encyclopedias. Alphabetical organization, with all of its merits, defeats the
                  possibility of using the vast amount of knowledge collected in scholarly
                  encyclopedias for comparisons across time, place, and topic.</p>

               <p> Let’s take urban transportation, for example. We now have encyclopedias of
                  Chicago, Cleveland, Los Angeles, and New York City (in the U.S.) and Melbourne, in
                  Australia, along with any I’ve not listed here. In most of these, entries on urban
                  transportation are included in alphabetical order, and, unless there is a subject
                  index, there is no way to identify them. While a subject index is of real value,
                  its creation is somewhat arbitrary -- and the subject indexes of different
                  encyclopedias are likely to be different, again defeating easy comparisons. </p>
               <p> The goal for the <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia </title> is to create a
                  structure of broad categories that will be used for each geographical region, so
                  that the historical development within that category can be easily compared to
                  that of other regions. These categories might include transportation, water, food,
                  energy, shelter, security, order, and creative expression, for example. We have
                  involved anthropologists in the design of this structure because they are most
                  familiar with doing broad comparisons over long stretches of time and places. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>How is the <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia </title> related to H-Urban? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>I believe it is a better way to carry out the mission I had when I established
                  H-Urban of promoting international and interdisciplinary work.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>H-Urban has been vitally important to me since I first joined in 1997: the
                  stimulating discussion threads, book reviews, and sharing across disciplinary
                  interests have broadened my research questions. A number of H-Urban editors and
                  readers are at small colleges in non-urban settings, or in a non-academic
                  professional setting, and I think the online support they get for their scholarly
                  interests is invaluable. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>I agree. However, H-Urban, with its loose structure and lack of serious,
                  comparative discussion, does not succeed in taking the next step — integrating
                  scholarly content or ideas, either across space or time. Most historians address
                  fairly narrow topics, because of the time- intensive nature of historical
                  research. Without the availability of concise, easy-to-access, information on the
                  work of other historians, it is difficult to avoid the fragmentation of urban
                  history that has been so much lamented in the last thirty years. Indeed, this
                  fragmentation has increased because of the multiplication of journals relating to
                  urban history and studies, and the increased costs of acquiring journals from
                  other nations.</p>

               <p>When the Internet became available to scholars, others and I hoped that it would
                  serve to overcome this fragmentation. How to do this well, however, has eluded
                  H-Urban — and the international urban history community. Discussions on H-Urban
                  have not thrived because the rewards do not exist to encourage historians to
                  participate, nor to examine the scholarship on their topic in other geographic
                  areas. Pressures to publish in formal journals are too great — and most scholars
                  do not have the time to pursue broader scholarship, save for reading several
                  journals and attending conferences. While these traditional means of sharing our
                  research and our findings remain important, they still do not provide a coherent,
                  international and interdisciplinary framework within which to contextualize one’s
                  work.</p>

               <p>The use of Wikipedia by many of these scholars, in spite of the problems with
                  quality control, has demonstrated to me that scholars are hungry for a single,
                  easily accessible place to record and retrieve a large body of information. The
                     <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia</title> offers the chance to create such a
                  place that would be used to summarize the state of the knowledge in urban history
                  on an ongoing basis, in a form that will facilitate comparisons, overcoming the
                  fragmentation of urban history that has marked the discipline until the
                  present.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>What is your timeline on the <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia</title>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>I hope to introduce discussion of it on H-Urban in May 2010, and, over the summer,
                  conduct research on similar attempts to provide on-line, extensible — and, if
                  available — structured encyclopedias. Hopefully, in the fall, I’ll be able to
                  submit a proposal to the NEH Digital Start-Up Grant program for funding to develop
                  a prototype in consultation with leading scholars of urbanism (e.g., history, art
                  and architectural history, anthropology, architecture, geography, literature,
                  sociology, urban planning, and urban studies). If funded, and if the <title
                     rend="italic">Encyclopedia</title> seems feasible as a concept that is
                  attractive enough to leading scholars to secure their involvement, at the end of
                  the grant period I’ll organize a team to apply for further funding to create a
                  foundational version — one that contains enough core knowledge to induce scholars
                  to augment the existing entries and propose new entries that expand the
                  geographical or chronological scope of the work.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Could you offer some parting thoughts on digitization of scholarly materials and
                  the democratization of history?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>I am glad that you raised this, Sharon, because, up until this point, I have not
                  really demonstrated a <emph>direct</emph> connection between my work and community
                  informatics, in which a key value is the democratization of knowledge. However, I
                  do believe that they are indirectly connected.</p>

               <ab> Let me focus first on the promise of the Internet for democratizing the
                  production of history. As a fairly traditional academic, I believe in the need for
                  historians to acquire a broad knowledge of history, the humanities, and the social
                  sciences, and to combine these with good analytical and writing skills. It takes
                  time and effort, as well as a good intellect, to acquire this foundation, and even
                  then, the historian’s skills improve over time. </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Speedy history is indeed about as good as fast food!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Exactly. However, in spite of this continuing reliance on an intellectual elite,
                  there <emph>is</emph> a need to expand the pool of those who join this select
                  group. That is because it is impossible to create a single, enduring, unchallenged
                  interpretation of history. The difficulty in preserving all evidence of human
                  existence, and the subjectivity inherent in collecting, organizing, and analyzing
                  this evidence, make this a pipe dream. For example, in the nineteenth and early
                  twentieth centuries, the majority of academic historians (almost all white males)
                  wrote primarily about elite politics, society, and culture. They deemed this the
                  only <q>knowledge</q> worthy of study, and overlooked the lives and activities of
                  non-elites — the middle and working classes; racial, ethnic, and religious
                  minorities; women; and children. It is no coincidence that the democratization of
                  the academy during the 1960s and 1970s, with increasing numbers of non-elites
                  entering the historical profession, led to an active interest in the study of
                  non-elites. </p>

               <p>Aside from the social change that expanded the pool of those who became
                  historians, the growth of technology has had a role in decreasing the importance
                  of wealth in undertaking what is often very costly historical research. For
                  example, some scholars have argued that the development of microfilm in the 1930s
                  reduced the costs of doing historical research. This made it possible for students
                  and junior scholars to undertake research that would have formerly required costly
                  travel to libraries and archives. In a similar vein, the creation of on-line
                  primary and secondary resources have reduced, although not eliminated, the need
                  for travel and reproduction.</p>
            </sp>
            <figure xml:id="figure11">
               <head>
                  <title rend="quotes">Developing Microfilm,</title> June 1942. Library of Congress
                  Prints and Photographs, Farm Security Administration, Office of War Information
                  Photograph Collection, <ref
                     target="http://www.loc.gov/rr/microform/images/microfilm.jpg"
                     >http://www.loc.gov/rr/microform/images/microfilm.jpg</ref>.</head>
               <figDesc/>
               <graphic url="...000086/resources/figure11.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Of course information technologies, whether in the form of microfilm or digital
                  archives, have changed the way that we do historical research. Different people
                  ask new and different questions, as you have pointed out.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>Amen! The Internet has also enhanced the quality of good undergraduate education,
                  so that students at a state or community college now have access to some of the
                  same resources that formerly only the elite schools could afford. This
                  availability also allows individuals who were bored by history in their formal
                  education to renew their enthusiasm for the field, and for present day students
                  from K-12 to complement their formal education in a self-directed, interactive
                  manner. This also has the potential for bringing a wider audience, of a range of
                  ages and experience, into the discipline of history.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>What about the effect of the Internet on those who don’t want to become
                  historians?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>In some ways, this is even more important, because all of us are citizens, even if
                  we are not historians. One of the requirements for being a good citizen is being
                  well informed in history as well as current events. And this has not always been
                  easy in the past. Individuals have a variety of learning styles, but traditional
                  education has tended to rely on a single style, emphasizing lecture, reading, and
                  writing. The Internet offers not only an <emph>easier</emph> and
                     <emph>cheaper</emph> way to disseminate information, but also a greater variety
                  of methods of presenting it.</p>

               <p>The use of visuals enhances the understanding of history, as David Staley
                  discusses in his book <ptr target="#staley2002"/>. It is not, as some critics
                  argue, an anti-intellectual concession to the <q>visual</q> generation. The
                  integration of text, visuals, and hypertext can offer a less forbidding means of
                  learning history than in the past, making it available to many more individuals.
                  Online discussion forums such as H-Urban and COMM-ORG can answer questions that
                  students previously were discouraged from asking teachers. Overall, the Internet
                  has become part of the solution to making the study of history more appealing to
                  individuals from all walks of life and with various levels of formal
                  education.</p>

               <p>All of this is for the good, because, as I said above, knowledge of history is
                  essential to becoming an informed citizen. Whether it is learning about the
                  history of exclusionary zoning and redlining or reading the minutes of the
                  planning board of one’s town, the easy availability of this information can make
                  us all more engaged citizens.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irish</speaker>
               <p>Let me take this opportunity to thank you, Wendy, for your engaged scholarship and
                  incomparable dedication to urban history, online and off.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Plotkin</speaker>
               <p>And let me thank you, Sharon, for the time and excellence you have contributed to
                  H-Urban and other scholarly enterprises.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>

      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl label="Achtenberg &amp; Stone 1974" xml:id="achtenberg1974" key="achtenberg1974"
               >Emily Achtenberg and Michael Stone, <title rend="italic">Tenants First! A Research
                  and Organizing Guide to FHA Housing</title>. Cambridge: Urban Planning Aid,
               1974.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="guernsey1997" label="Guernsey 1997" key="guernsey1997">Lisa Guernsey,
                  <title rend="quotes">Election Campaign to Run H-Net, A Popular Network of E-Mail
                  Lists, Turns Nasty,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher Education</title>, 43:32, April 18, 1997,
               A25.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Hoffman 1986" xml:id="hoffman1986" key="hoffman1986">Lily M. Hoffman,
                  <title rend="italic">The Politics of Knowledge: Activist Movements in Medicine and
                  Planning</title>. Albany: SUNY, 1986.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jensen1971" label="Jensen 1971" key="jensen1971">Richard Jensen, <title
                  rend="italic">The Winning of the Midwest: Social and Political Conflict,
                  1888-1896</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1971.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Jensen 1983" xml:id="jensen1983" key="jensen1983">Richard Jensen, <title
                  rend="quotes">The Accomplishments of the Newberry Library Family and Community
                  History Programs: An Interview with Richard Jensen,</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Public Historian</title> 5:4 (August 1983), 49-61.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Marcus 1996" xml:id="marcus1996" key="marcus1996a">Harold G. Marcus,
                  <title rend="quotes">The Internationalization of H-Net,</title>
               <title rend="italic">OAH</title> Newsletter 52 (August 1996), at <ref
                  target="http://www.h-net.org/about/press/oah/intl.html"
                  >http://www.h-net.org/about/press/oah/intl.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="urban1975" label="Urban Planning Aid 1975" key="urban1975">Urban Planning
               Aid, <title rend="italic">How to Use OSHA</title>. Cambridge: Urban Planning Aid,
               1975.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="plotkin2003" label="Plotkin 2003" key="plotkin2003">Wendy Plotkin, <title
                  rend="quotes">Electronic Texts in the Historical Profession: Perspectives from
                  Across the Scholarly Spectrum,</title> in Orville Vernon Burton, ed., <title
                  rend="italic">Computing in the Social Sciences and Humanities</title>. Urbana:
               University of Illinois Press, March 2003.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="staley2002" label="Staley 2002" key="staley2002">David J. Staley, <title
                  rend="italic">Computers, Visualization, and History: How New Technology Will
                  Transform Our Understanding of the Past</title>. M.E. Sharpe, 2002.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="urban1972" label="Urban Planning Aid 1972" key="urban1972">Urban Planning
               Aid, <title rend="italic">Less Rent, More Control: A Tenants Guide to Rent Control in
                  Massachusetts</title>. Cambridge: Urban Planning Aid, 1972.</bibl>
            <bibl label="Young 2009" xml:id="young2009" key="young2009a">Jeffrey R. Young, <title
                  rend="quotes">Change or Die: Scholarly E-Mail Lists, Once Vibrant, Fight for
                  Relevance,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher Education</title>, June 25, 2009.</bibl>
         </listBibl>

      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
