<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Lost Spaces, Lost
               Technologies, and Lost People: Online History Projects Seek to Recover LGBTQ+ Spatial
               Histories</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Alex <dhq:family>Ketchum</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>McGill University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>alexandraketchum@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>N/A</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000580</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date/>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>This article looks at online history projects focused on <soCalled>lost</soCalled> spaces, with an
               emphasis on lost LGBTQ+ spaces. In documenting lost spaces, these projects also
               highlight lost or marginalized historical actors. I position these projects at the
               center of debates surrounding how to recover <soCalled>lost</soCalled> peoples who have been left out or
               erased from mainstream histories. This article will discuss the various techniques
               used by digital humanities projects, focusing particularly on Jan Kurth’s <title rend="quotes">Lost
               Womyn’s Space,</title> Greggor Mattson’s <title rend="quotes">Mapping Lost Lesbian Bars,</title> and my own project,
               <title rend="quotes">The Feminist Restaurant Project.</title> This article discusses the various techniques used
               and the value these open access history websites serve for scholars and non-scholars
               alike. The article finishes by exploring how lost space projects preserve what was
               not previously preserved, while these websites are simultaneously vulnerable to
               similar preservation issues that plague digital humanities projects and community
               archives more broadly, especially those separate from large institutions. These
               challenges raise the questions: is lost space doomed to be lost? Can the history of
               LGBTQ+ space be recuperated? What role do digital humanities have in this work? And
               what does it mean to be found?</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>This article looks at online history projects focused on <soCalled>lost</soCalled> spaces, with an
               emphasis on lost LGBTQ+ spaces.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
         <head>What does it mean to be lost?</head>
            
         <p>In 1983, A Woman’s Coffeehouse of Minneapolis, Minnesota taped an open community meeting
            during which members of the predominately white, working class, lesbian coffeehouse
            could reflect on their experiences. One middle-aged participant remarked that by not
            speaking with younger generations of lesbians about differences between their coming-out
            experiences, she felt that <quote rend="inline">she [had] lost her
               history,</quote> <ptr target="#coffeehousecommunity"/>. This woman’s concern about not having forums in
            which to share and document her own history and that of her community was not unique.
            Archivists and historians have discussed how to preserve and to recover LGBTQ+
            histories; less attention has been given to the ways that digital humanities projects
            have tried to preserve and recover <soCalled>lost</soCalled> LGBTQ+ spatial histories. This article seeks
            to fill this gap in the literature by analyzing online projects focused on the history
            <soCalled>lost</soCalled> LGBTQ+ spaces, particularly women’s spaces. </p>
         <p>In documenting <soCalled>lost</soCalled> LGBTQ+ spaces, these projects highlight previously overlooked
            marginalized historical actors and geographies. Although the scale of projects varies
            from local studies to national or even international, these projects seek to empower
            marginalized communities by acting as testimony to their existence, to provide resources
            for others to build upon the research, and to document particular historical phenomena.
            This paper will discuss the various techniques used by the creators of these projects,
            particularly Jan Kurth’s <title rend="quotes">Lost Womyn’s Space,</title>
            <ptr target="#kurth2011"/> Greggor Mattson’s <title rend="quotes">Mapping Lost Lesbian Bars,</title>
            <ptr target="#mattson2016"/> and my own project, <title rend="quotes">The Feminist Restaurant Project</title>
            <ptr target="#ketchum2015"/>. It is outside of the scope of this article to look at every history website
            devoted to documenting or finding <soCalled>lost</soCalled> LGBTQ+ histories. Instead by narrowing it down
            to the scope of projects devoted to documenting <soCalled>lost</soCalled> spaces, primarily lost lesbian
            and queer women’s and feminist spaces on the national and international scale, this
            paper still provides fruitful comparison. Despite the projects’ emphasis on lesbian
            spatial culture, I use the LGBTQ+ umbrella. The three projects documented spaces that
            served a wider range of people than just lesbians. Furthermore, the problematics raised
            by this article relate to other <soCalled>lost</soCalled> LGBTQ+ projects, even if they are not wholly the
            same. </p>
         <p>For this article, I analyzed the projects themselves, as well as interviewed their
            makers and included my own reflections as a project creator. In doing so, I explore the
            contribution that these websites make to the general public and scholars alike, paying
            particular attention to why documenting lost spaces is so necessary to understanding a
            community’s history. The article concludes by exploring how although lost space projects
            preserve narratives that have all but been erased or forgotten, these websites are
            vulnerable to similar preservation issues that plague both digital humanities projects
            and community archives, particularly those built separate from large institutions. These
            problems raise a number of questions, including: is lost space doomed to be lost? Can
            the history of LGBTQ+ space be recuperated? Is it possible to develop sustainable
            digital preservation initiatives that attempt to document the experiences of LGBTQ+
            spaces? I argue that digital spatial history projects do not replace community archives,
            yet fulfill a different, complementary need. As such, the solution to the preservation
            of these materials rests with institutionalization within an archive large enough to
            provide the necessary financial and technological resources to sustain the project
            beyond the scope of the original, individual creator. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            
         <head>Who and What is “Lost?” And Why Should We Care?</head>
            
         <p>Historians and archivists argue over how to recover missing or marginalized communities.
            Archivists Joan M. Schwartz and Terry Cook posit that conventional record creation and
            archival practices mean that <quote rend="inline">some can afford to create and maintain records and some
            cannot; that certain voices thus will be heard loudly and some not at all; that certain
            views and ideas about society will in turn be privileged and others marginalized</quote>
             <ptr target="#schwartz2002"/>. Historians, such as Judith Bennet and Steven Maynard, and archivists,
            such as Randall Jimerson, have shown that socially and culturally marginalized
            communities, including LGBTQ+ communities, have also been marginalized in archives and
            the discipline of history
            <ptr target="#bennett2000"/> <ptr target="#jimerson2003"/> <ptr target="#maynard1991"/>.
            Resulting from the acknowledgement of this deficit
            and beginning in the 1960s, social history sought to reclaim histories of marginalized
            peoples. Archives, a vital aspect of this shift, transformed collection and preservation
            practices in order to reflect these new historiographical interests. Archivists Marika
            Cifor, Michelle Caswell, Alda Allina Migoni, and Noah Geraci have argued that this
            phenomenon was especially apparent in the development of community archives. When
            community archive movements developed as a response to the social and political
            movements that came to the fore in 1960s and 1970s, <quote rend="inline">within each of these movements
            activists and community groups recognized the significance of writing persons and
            communities whose histories and lives had long been marginalized, erased, or
            misrepresented into the historical record</quote>
            <ptr target="#cifor2018"/>. They show that the process of community archiving was a form of
            <quote rend="inline">self-representation, identity construction, and empowerment,</quote> affecting both past and
            present
            <ptr target="#cifor2018"/>. Melinda Marie Jetté (2019), James Brooks (2019), Jodie Boyd (2019), and
            others have written about how necessary it is to document LGBTQ+ histories in a way that
            is accessible to the public in <title rend="italic">The Public Historian</title>’s Special
            Issue on commemorating queer history. Despite efforts to recover the <soCalled>lost</soCalled> or
            marginalized histories, traditional historical and archival practices, however, do not
            capture all of them. </p>
         <p>As a result, LGBTQ+ community archives began to rectify this gap. These community
            archives, such as the Lesbian Herstory Archives, often function outside of institutional
            support, which enables the community to preserve its own histories, but can also make
            the collections vulnerable to issues of funding and sustainability
            <ptr target="#nestle2015"/>. Community archives also do not preserve the histories of the entire LGBTQ+
            community; in the North American context, when these communities are documented, it is
            often members of that community that live in large urban or coastal areas
            <ptr target="#lee2015"/>. </p>
         <p>While not fully compensating for this deficit, LGBTQ+ archival projects also exist
            online. Archivist Erin O’Meara argues that collecting activists’ papers and documenting
            related social movements has always had inherent problems, but digital techniques
            complicate matters as they raise new questions around preservation
            <ptr target="#omeara2012"/>. Elise Chenier, founder of the Archives of Lesbian Oral Testimony, has several
            articles on the challenges of preserving lesbian digital history projects including
            issues of collection and retention, related to her work with oral histories
            <ptr target="#chenier2010"/> <ptr target="#chenier2015"/>. Similarly, archivist Anthony Cocciolo discusses the challenges of
            establishing a digital community archive, finding that establishing and maintaining a
            community digital archive necessitates navigating a complex set of technological and
            social issues, including methods for capturing records, ownership and copyright,
            digitization and born-digital record keeping, social media and web archiving, and
            digital preservation
            <ptr target="#cocciolo2017"/>. However, art historian, Roxanne Samer continues to believe in the potential of
            feminist and queer digital archives despite these issues, acknowledging that
            intergenerational sharing of knowledge through digital archives may be the key to this
            information surviving
            <ptr target="#samer2014"/>. While archivists have innovated new techniques to include more perspectives,
            online history projects provide complementary and alternative materials yet face similar
            problems. The unique nature of digital humanities projects necessitates different
            solutions than are required for community archives, which have historically been wary of
            institutionalization.</p>
         <p>Access to narratives of marginalized people is impacted by accessibility of information
            and access to technologies. Online public history projects provide new opportunities to
            share materials and create new or different avenues of access apart from physical and
            digital archives
            <ptr target="#jacobs2017"/>(. Jan Kurth’s <title rend="quotes">Lost Womyn’s Space,</title> Greggor Mattson’s <title rend="quotes">Mapping Lost
            Lesbian Bars,</title> and my own project, <title rend="quotes">The Feminist Restaurant Project,</title> are not digital
            archives but rather digital humanities history projects that seek to collect, remember,
            and retain information about LGBTQ+ spaces. These digital history projects build upon a
            tradition of LGBTQ+ individuals creating and utilizing new technological forms to
            advocate about their communities. Their narrowed focus, particularly on the difficulty
            of creating and retaining lesbian and queer women’s spaces, is paralleled by the
            challenge of retaining records about these spaces in digital form. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
           
         <head>What does being <soCalled>found</soCalled> look like? What Makes Digital History Projects Different than
            Community Archives? </head>
         <p>If to be <soCalled>lost</soCalled> is to be marginalized or erased, to be <soCalled>found</soCalled> or <soCalled>to find</soCalled> means
            centering LGBTQ+ histories; some history websites do exactly that. One technique for
            recovering marginalized histories has been to document where marginalized groups spent
            time. As the editors of <title rend="italic">Queers in Space</title>, Gordon Brent Ingram,
            Anne Bouthillette, and Yolanda Retter note, both permanent and temporary spaces were
            important to queer activist organizing and community building
               <ptr target="#ingram1997"/>. Geographer Julie Podmore likewise argues the
            importance of studying space to understand lesbian histories
               <ptr target="#podmore2001"/>. It is not that community archives do not provide evidence of community spaces,
            but rather the emphasis of these websites is on documenting specifically community
            spaces and providing visitors with information with which to explore these spaces
            further. As Kurth notes, <quote rend="inline">Certainly I have seen a lot of projects since I started Lost
            Womyn's Space that focus just on lesbian bars. I find that work of value, but I think we
            miss something when we don't look for parallels and connections with other forms of
            women's space over time and geography</quote> (2018). Since this research started, other
            projects seeking to document lesbian and queer spaces have begun. In 2017, designer
            Lucas LaRochelle began the community generated mapping project, Queering the Map, that
            geo-locates queer moments, memories and histories in relation to a world map. Unlike the
            three projects this article focuses on, Queering the Map seeks to represent queer
            memories outside of fixed queer spaces, such as gay bars or lesbian bookstores, and
            rather on ephemeral moments, published without dates, which happen anywhere in the world
            to mark experiences of queerness wherever they occur <ptr target="#larochelle2017"/>. While there is
            strong value in recording individual memory, documenting the location of more formalized
            geographies with fixed dates does something different; it provides a sense of space,
            situated in specific historical moments, to which future generations can situate
            themselves in relation to and build upon.</p>
         <p>The three projects this article focuses on, take space seriously on a national or
            international scale by attending to an exploration of historical sites of LGBTQ+
            socializing and political organizing. While they differ in their format and exact focus,
            they look at similar communities: lesbians, women with a focus on lesbians, and
            feminists with an emphasis on lesbian feminists. Mattson’s work specifies bars, I target
            restaurants, cafes, and coffeehouses, and Kurth has the widest scope, encompassing all
            kinds of women’s spaces and businesses. Likewise Mattson has the most specific
            geographic focus by looking solely at the United States, the Feminist Restaurant Project
            is U.S. and Canada centered, and Kurth’s work is global
            <ptr target="#kurth2018"/>. The projects have some overlap and directly attribute the work of the other
            creators in their own work
            <ptr target="#mattson2016"/>. </p>
         <p>This article recognizes the different motivations of the sites’ creators and the
            problematic nature of the individual creator being centered. On the one hand, these
            projects work to represent large swaths of lesbian and queer women communities, yet on
            the other hand, the individuals doing the work shape them. The identities of the
            creators impact their ability to do this labor and may influence the willingness of
            others’ view of the authority of the content. That the creators of this work are
            predominately white, and a self identified gay man academic (Mattson), queer woman
            academic (Ketchum), and a lesbian non-academic (Kurth), affects which LGBTQ+ spaces are
            <soCalled>found</soCalled> — through who is willing to share resources with us, through our editorial
            choices, and through how our work is understood as authoritative or non-authoritative.
            Furthermore, a creator’s biases shape the form of the project and risk marginalizing or
            erasing histories of other marginalized groups while doing the work of recovering or
            showcasing <soCalled>lost</soCalled> LGBTQ+ histories. This phenomenon became particularly apparent when in
            2019, Kurth made trans-exclusionary comments while discussing the lack of women’s and
            lesbian venues in a post. In doing so, her project that in fact includes community
            spaces in which transgender people worked, gathered, and socialized, now minimizes or
            erases these histories. Responding to the marginalization, neglect, and deletion of
            trans geographies and trans geographic histories, geographer Kath Browne challenges how
            <quote rend="inline">gender geographies have focused on normatively gendered men and women, neglecting the
               ways in which gender binaries can be contested and troubled</quote> <ptr target="#browne2010"/>. Browne builds on
            the work of Viviane Namaste and Susanne Stryker and argues that <quote rend="inline">trans voices need to be
            heard and new knowledges created from the specific understandings gained through lived
            experiences</quote> <ptr target="#browne2010"/>. This is not to say that cisgendered creators are unable to include
            trans voices or representations of LGBTQ+ communities of color, but rather that the
            predominant whiteness and cisgendered identities of the creators of these projects
            affects the representation of these historical geographies. This issue is especially
            pertinent if the only, or majority, of projects documenting these spaces come from a
            white, cis perspective. While this article focuses on what it means to do the labor of
            recovering lost or missing histories, all to potentially lose these histories again, the
            individual creators’ identities impact the ability to do this work; the willingness to
            include or acknowledge certain people and spaces; and the form that work takes.</p>
         <p>Yielding to the call to think seriously about space, digital representations such as
            online mapping projects, scrapbook databases, and user forums focused on space,
            highlight an aspect of historical preservation not fulfilled in the same manner by an
            archive. The projects surveyed in this article are part of a phenomenon of spatial
            documentation. However, typically spatial projects have focused on local regions.
            Creators benefit from access to insider community knowledge and histories, primarily due
            to the intensity of labor of gathering this information. Projects such as Found San
            Francisco are advantaged by focusing on a targeted local region, which allow the
            creators to delve in detail
            <ptr target="#robb2012"/>. As Jan Kurth reflected, </p>
         <p><quote rend="block">I also enjoy the various projects that put together and catalog <soCalled>lost places,</soCalled> as that
            combines my interest in <soCalled>space</soCalled> and history. Typically, these efforts tend to be
            localized, as hunting down all these places can be pretty labor intensive. So generally,
            most of these projects will be devoted to particular cities, and sometimes, even more
            specifically, to particular bars or LGBT bars in a particular city. I had noticed that
            lesbian bars tend to get <soCalled>lost</soCalled> in the city lists and even the LGBT lists, so I wanted
            to highlight lost lesbian bars as those are rapidly disappearing. But as I played around
            in Google archives (later <ref target="http://newspaper.com/">newspaper.com</ref>), and
            on the Internet in general, I came across all kinds of interesting lost, disappearing,
            or endangered women's spaces. So I thought it would be fun to have a kind of rangy blog
            for collecting all these places in one location
            <ptr target="#kurth2018"/>.</quote></p>
         <p>Although projects focused on a smaller region can be more manageable, as individuals in
            that community can share their stories and collective memory, national and international
            public history projects build awareness of the larger phenomenon of the desire for
            community run spaces that are occurring beyond the local level. Both types of projects
            are useful. Greggor Mattson agrees, remarking, <quote rend="inline">I like all the sites that are trying to
            map gay bars and LGBT spaces. The New York site is the gold standard, in my view, but
            it's one that exceeds my abilities both technically and in terms of time to devote to
            it</quote>
            <ptr target="#mattson2018"/>. He is referring to the NYC LGBT Historic Sites Project website, which consists of
            an interactive map that links to histories of each location
            <ptr target="#historicalsitesproject2017"/>. Mattson’s site, rather, tries <quote rend="inline">to be
            nationally comprehensive,</quote> yet he explains that <quote rend="inline">it's tough to just make sure that all
            the regions are being represented.</quote> Mattson focused only on the United States due to
            language barriers and his own scholarly background. In my own experience, I focused on
            the United States and Canada because as a historian my training has focused on Canadian
            and American historiographies. Furthermore, my digital project was tied to my
            dissertation work in which I wanted to contextualize the development of these spaces
            within the legal and economic context of their times. Researching feminist restaurant
            histories for two countries was complicated to historically contextualize as I wanted to
            be specific about municipal, state/provincial, and federal laws. While my lens allowed
            me to speak to trends and historical phenomena regarding feminist and lesbian feminist
            restaurant creation, I had to sacrifice some precision; however, trying to integrate
            more countries would have required more generalizations than I was comfortable making.
            This article is concerned most specifically with the barriers of preserving LGBTQ+
            spatial national and international projects, as unlike local projects, which are
            typically supported by regional organizations, the larger scale projects are created,
            updated, and preserved by individuals. For smaller scale regional projects without
            institutional or organizational backing, the suggestions at the end of this article will
            be relevant. </p>
         <p>Compiling data on national and international scales can be more difficult as source
            materials are scattered. If this information is available on the Internet, as Kurth
            denoted about some of her source materials, is it really lost? As the Indiana University
            Lilly Library argued, when materials are in libraries, archives, or even on the
            Internet, they are actually the opposite of <soCalled>lost</soCalled> <ptr target="#bahr2019"/>. However, information,
            particularly about marginalized communities, can be so scattered and inaccessible to
            locate that while it may not be formally lost, it can be <soCalled>lost.</soCalled> To be <soCalled>lost</soCalled> is to be
            unable or difficult to find. The sites surveyed in this article collate this
            information, bringing it together for users and often creating duplicate files of these
            records, which can disappear at a moment’s notice, as had been the case with Google
            Archives. This creation of records is not the only way that these digital history
            projects differ from digital archives. Usually, larger projects require input from users
            as the creators may not be familiar with the areas discussed.</p>
         <p>Crowdsourcing information is a key component for revealing histories of lost spaces,
            especially for projects on the national and international scale. LGBTQ+ history projects
            particularly benefit from crowdsourcing as the former users of these spaces are less
            likely to have had their recollections previously recorded, as marginalized communities’
            experiences are not only marginalized in historical and archival contexts, but also in
            the popular media
            <ptr target="#lostpubsproject2018"/>.<note>This technique is not exclusive to LGBTQ+ focused history
               projects. The non-LGBTQ+ project, the <title rend="quotes">Lost Pub Project</title> which documents the decline
               of the English pub, has compiled over 35,000 entries. On the website, which functions
               as a kind of directory, the makers write, <quote rend="inline">Help our community project to archive
               these lost pubs before they are forgotten forever. If you know of a pub which has
               closed at any time in the past, please submit it, together with any anecdotes,
               historical information or photographs that you might have.</quote> They further ask users to
               check for inconsistencies, writing that <quote rend="inline">pubs do re-open from time to time, so if you
               see one on the site that is open please let us know.</quote> The creators share information
               on their website, Facebook, and twitter channels and users can check the database by
               clicking on city/town names and seeing listings. While the Lost Pub Project shows
               that lost LGBTQ+ pages are not unique in their use crowdsourcing, the technique is
               still valuable. As of October 31, 2018, the site features 35, 323 lost pubs, together
               with 20,509 photos.</note> Greggor Mattson’s <title rend="inline">Mapping Lost Lesbian Bars</title> utilizes
            crowdsourcing. He admits on his site that <quote rend="inline">it is inevitable that there are errors in
            this kind of enterprise – please send me corrections and queries to</quote> his email and
            Twitter account. He likewise explains, <quote rend="inline">Eventually I will merge this with a map of
            currently-open lesbian bars, which I’ll launch as a crowdsourcing effort</quote>
            <ptr target="#mattson2016"/>. This kind of community driven research on lost spaces benefits from a wide
            variety of perspectives and experiences. Crowdsourcing also generates publicity through
            the initial launch of the call for submissions and thus also draws more attention to
            these sites. On the Feminist Restaurant Project website, there are multiple calls asking
            visitors to contribute to the project. Although the initial directory and map were based
            on my amalgamation of old travel guides, periodicals, advertisements, and interviews, I
            created the website in part for the purpose of crowdsourcing new information. The
            website has a page called <q>Submissions</q> in which I ask users, <quote rend="inline">Know of a feminist
            restaurant, cafe, or coffeehouse that existed/exists in the United States and Canada?
            Please check if it is listed on the database — if not, email The Feminist Restaurant
            Project to let us know.</quote> Likewise above the directory I have a note asking for feedback
            <ptr target="#ketchum2015"/>. Since I first launched the site in April 2015, I have only received about a dozen
            emails from people who found me through the site, but they were thorough, full of
            information, and quite helpful. The directory and its associated maps thus become living
            documents that grow as readership grows. As Jan Kurth has stayed anonymous on her site,
            her information is not crowdsourced in the same way.<note> She has given me permission
               to use her name for this article.</note> Users can post comments but cannot email her
            through the site. While the Lost Womyn’s Spaces site shows that crowdsourcing is not the
            only technique creators can use to collect information, the method is still valuable.
            The creation of websites with maps and directories, like those of Mattson and my own,
            allow for users to get directly involved, turning the site into a kind of community
            project/ archive. </p>
         <p>Social media works as an invaluable tool for crowdsourcing information for these digital
            history projects. Mattson finds information through social media and spreads awareness
            about his research on Twitter. He found that <quote rend="inline">most gay bars communicate better on
            Facebook than by phone or e-mail</quote>
            <ptr target="#mattson2018"/>. Facebook enabled him to contact bar owners for interviews. He then used his
            social media presence and his website as a way to add credibility to his requests,
            explaining, <quote rend="inline">I thought it would be useful for them to see that they were part of
            something bigger to induce them to accept my request for an interview. I wanted them to
            see that this was something I'd been thinking about for a while and that I was serious</quote>
            <ptr target="#mattson2018"/>. I, likewise, have found social media sites, particularly Facebook and Twitter to
            be invaluable resources
            <ptr target="#ketchum2019"/>. Facebook group administrators allowed me to join their online communities and
            pose questions to the members, asking if people had resources about other feminist
            restaurants or if they wanted to be interviewed. Like Mattson, I used my website, The
            Feminist Restaurant Project, to demonstrate the work I had already done on the topic and
            had a publicly available source that could be shared within these communities. I used
            Twitter to connect with people whose email addresses I did not have or could not find,
            as well as to publicize the project. As my research progressed, I was able to use these
            social media channels as a way to keep the community informed about the state of the
            project and publications. It has been a relationship of reciprocity. </p>
         <p>Community archives do rely on donations from community members, but the kind of exchange
            on these websites is different. Digital LGBTQ+ spatial history projects collect
            scattered information from around the Internet, from physical archives, guide and travel
            books, and the oral histories and shared memories of community members. These digital
            projects thus, do not only gather information that could not be found in a single
            community archive, but the process of creating these sites produces knowledge. Users are
            motivated to share stories that would otherwise perish along with them. While similar to
            community archives, these digital projects do something different. This difference is
            made clear in how their information is displayed.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
         <head>Visuals: Spatial Histories and What Digital History Projects Offer that Community
            Archives Do Not</head>
         <p>To be lost is to be hidden or unseen. To be found is to be revealed. Even our language
            around being lost and found speaks to visual culture. All three sites use visuals in
            different ways to draw in readers and contribute to underlying arguments. In Kurth’s
            scrapbook format, where she pastes any relevant information within the blog post, she
            includes photographs of the businesses when available, Google Streetview images of the
            buildings when an address was known, and other photos and illustrations. Mattson,
            likewise <quote rend="inline">found it touching to use Google street view and have a look at the outside of
            the buildings when it was still a lesbian bar: the rainbows or triangles or posters for
            women's bands</quote>
            <ptr target="#mattson2018"/>. He had a research assistant take the screenshots and post them so that as Google
            Streetview updates with the new exteriors, at least one image of the bar would remain.
            He remarks <quote rend="inline">I have no pictures of the gay bars that I've liked to visit, in part because
            I'm old fashioned about not taking pictures in or around gay bars in case someone is
            closeted,</quote>
            <ptr target="#mattson2018"/> yet he knows how valuable these visuals can also be. While the display of this
            visual information differs between the three sites, none follow the format of digital
            archives’ formatting of folders filled with jpegs of images from the physical archives
            or reproduced text, as is the case with projects like the Queer Zine Archives and the
            Lesbian Herstory Archives.</p>
         <p>Apart from physical pictures, these websites provide other visual cues that speak to the
            existence of <soCalled>lost</soCalled> communities. Kurth’s website’s side bar, that shows the number of
            blog post entries written per month, is another powerful visual that conveys how many
            spaces existed that are now <soCalled>lost.</soCalled> The 644 posts make clear that these spaces were not
            a rare or isolated phenomenon. I was, likewise, motivated by the visual power of numbers
            when I decided to make my directory and maps publicly available. An immediate benefit of
            quantitative mapping techniques is that they show the preponderance of these spaces.
            Based on my initial estimates before beginning my research, I guessed that there were,
            at most, 40 feminist restaurants, cafés, and coffeehouses in America and Canada. In
            fact, the number of verified feminist restaurants, cafés, and coffeehouses from the
            1972-1989 is over 250 and, further, there are over 430 unverified spaces, and it is
            likely, feminist spaces are included in this set. The verified and unverified spaces are
            color coded with pink and blue markings on the site. These visual cues help quantify the
            space.</p>
         <p>One approach to understanding lesbian feminist history is to mark where women gathered.
            Maps can change conceptualizations of the past in ways that narratives cannot alone.</p>
         <p>Both Mattson and I use maps to serve multiple purposes. Some of my maps simply show
            where places actually existed, some show the variety of feminist businesses in a single
            area during a single year, based only on one guidebook, and some are part of a larger
            history project, which takes information from interviewees and provides a space for
            continual community building, through memory sharing. The initial goal was to map out
            the locations of feminist restaurants and cafés, the types of women’s spaces that I have
            chosen to focus on, within the United States and Canada from 1972 to 1989, a process
            never before completed. From this map it is possible construct a sense of what the
            feminist and lesbian community in a particular space and time looked like. A large,
            public map served the goal of drawing attention to the legacy of the women founders of
            feminist restaurants, cafés, and coffeehouses who made this project feasible by making
            this information as publicly accessible as possible and also by developing new forums in
            which former participants could expand their community, during a time when many women’s
            spaces are closing or have closed. Greggor Mattson shared a similar motivation. He
            explains <quote rend="inline">I like making Google maps because they help me visualize things alongside
            other sets of data... for example, I can use Social Explorer to eyeball whether it
            resembles population density, or I can use Google's Street View to have a look at the
            building and neighborhood that the bar is/was located in</quote>
            <ptr target="#mattson2018"/>. The map was both beneficial for visualizing results and analysis. He realized
            that these images could be useful for his readers, noting that, <quote rend="inline">I guess I felt like I'd
            gone to this trouble of helping map where these lesbian bars had been, that I might as
            well share it with others</quote>
            <ptr target="#mattson2018"/>. Maps allow users to interact with information and provide powerful visuals. The
            time has come to take space seriously, not just intellectually but methodologically, in
            researching the past; creating publicly available maps enables this pursuit. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
         <head>Format and the Individual</head>
         <p>Choices regarding format also shapes the way that users interact with the site and
            understand the motivations and intentions of the creators. Mattson’s and my site
            explicitly mention our larger academic projects with which the public sites are
            correlated. The matter is more complicated with Lost Womyn’s Spaces. Kurth notes, </p>
         <p><quote rend="block">I chose the format I have so that I would be highlighting individual places, and
            highlighting the details of that particular place's existence. I like specificity. I
            think that theoretical generalizations are often in danger of wandering too far afield
            if care is not taken. The trade off is that some readers may get caught up in the
            details, and not be able to see the patterns I think are pretty clear that run across
            the histories of many former women's places. Clearly some readers are only interested in
            a particular bar they used to go to back in the 80s, and that's fine. I have sometimes
            thought I should write some sort of essay highlighting the patterns with all the
            documentation I have collected, but honestly, I don't know how many would be interested
            and I really don't have the time
            <ptr target="#kurth2018"/>.</quote> </p>
         <p>She does actually include some editorializing information within her posts, supplying
            commentary in the margins. While Kurth states that the scrapbook style can be utilized
            as users wish, she also somewhat directs readers toward her argument, noting <quote rend="inline">I think my
            motivation has been pretty much the same, which is to create an outlet for a very wide
            range of lost women's spaces. But the more places I collected, the more I saw certain
            patterns that most don't know, so I like to highlight those and bring them to the
            attention of readers</quote>
            <ptr target="#kurth2018"/>. Between March 2011 and June 2019, she wrote over 652 posts. Most posts focus on
            the history of a single space and are typically a collection of newspaper articles,
            advertisements, entries on review sites such as Yelp, and whatever photos and other
            information she can find pasted in what she calls her <soCalled>blog scrapbook</soCalled> formatting.
            However more significantly, Lost Womyn’s Space’s format reflected Kurth’s desire to
            provide records of a smattering of spaces that users can engage with as desired, rather
            than be directed. Kurth believes that <quote rend="inline">it's fun to have a blog to throw things on that
            are interesting. There is so much available on the Internet right now that really needs
            to be curated in some way to make it more accessible in a single location</quote>
            <ptr target="#kurth2018"/>. Having read all 652 posts, these arguments begin to come through clearly, yet if
            a user just reads one or two posts, the details of the scrapbook format tend to dominate
            reader experience. </p>
         <p> What is clear is that each website’s specifics relate to the individuality of their
            creators. As each of these three projects are created primarily by one person, our
            individual experiences, motivations, educational backgrounds, and biases shape the
            projects. Our geographic focuses are influenced by language and cultural knowledge. Even
            when Kurth has tried to include information from countries around the world, she
            <quote rend="inline">realized pretty early that Google search engines keep corralling me back to English
            language sites, which means the focus is on English speaking countries. Occasionally I'd
            figure out a strategy to break free, but I haven't found as much as I would like outside
            the US, Canada, UK, etc</quote>
            <ptr target="#kurth2018"/>. Apart from geographic positioning, our training has shaped our methodologies in
            creating these websites. I had previously worked as a research assistant which tracked
            changes in every edition of the Canadian Medical Directory and that influenced my
            methodology to track edition changes in directories and guidebooks. While we all worked
            on related topics, our specific training and skills impacted our methodological choices
            and thus the end product. And so, while these projects are for the greater public and
            larger community, each site carries its author’s fingerprints. Having an individual’s
            viewpoint does not negate the usefulness of these sites, as individuals also shape
            documentation in community archives. However, it is this tie to the individual that puts
            these projects in danger. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
         <head>Failures and Finishing</head>
         <p> None of these projects were built in a single attempt, but rather were evolving
            undertakings where the creators have adapted, changed, and experimented. Jan Kurth has
            worked on her site since 2011, my site went live in 2015, and Mattson’s page with maps
            launched on September 17, 2016. Each creator dealt with failures that required
            innovation. Mattson had difficulties with his social media accounts. His Twitter project
            (@WhoNeedsGayBars) never really took off like he thought it would. He originally
            believed that users would communicate with him and follow the project through Twitter,
            but most of his followers were bots. Rather than functioning as a news stream about gay
            bars, as it was originally intended, Mattson uses his site as a way to be able to scroll
            through a timeline of articles
            <ptr target="#mattson2018"/>. I had a similar experience of making assumptions about what users would want and
            initially completely missed the mark. I spent months researching different map-making
            applications that would allow users to upload information to the site. I experimented
            with Nunaliit, Postscrap, Google Social Maps Experience, and Esri’s Story Map
            Crowdsource (beta), and eventually chose Story Map.<note> Picking the right kind of
               software to create a public map that invited user feedback was particularly difficult
               in 2013. At first, there was no application that directly suited my needs. Initially
               I considered Nunaliit and Postscrap, both developed by University of Carleton
               geographers. Neither fit the exact needs of the project because of the frameworks
               they necessitated. Further, the Google Social Maps Experience did not give the
               researcher oversight and editing capabilities over the content, leaving the
               opportunity for the map to be trolled. On that application, if a map was publicly
               available, anyone could add or delete data and, because of this, users might be less
               likely to feel safe uploading their content knowing that it could be changed or
               deleted by anyone. In 2016, Esri launched Story Map, a map builder that allowed
               anyone to create an account or use one’s Google profile or Facebook account to post
               onto the map. Story Map Crowdsource (beta) is an ArcGIS web application designed to
               collect photos and captions from anyone and display them on a map that Esri kept in
               beta until 2018. The application was easy to use and configure, and could be used in
               a web browser on laptop and desktop computers, mobile phones, and tablets.
               Contributors can sign in with their Facebook, Google, ArcGIS account, or participate
               as an anonymous guest. Further, creators of the map have oversight over the content.
               The program thus allows for a good balance of permitting users to not have to commit
               too much personal information in order to participate, but still know that their
               contribution is relatively safe. There are some drawbacks however, besides the $2,500
               annual subscription fee, which was thankfully covered by McGill University. It was
               not possible to upload or create a non-editable basemap without it being at risk of
               deletion, due to the Beta status of the program. Ideally it would have been possible
               to just export my master Google Map as a kml file, convert it to an ArcGIs readable
               file, which is readable by ArcGIS, the software Esri relies upon, and then use those
               points as a background layer over which users would be able to only edit a top layer.
               Also, currently, users are supposed to upload a photo and do not have the option to
               solely upload text. As a workaround, I suggested that users just upload a photo of a
               square and then write their text, but this situation is less than ideal. A positive
               aspect of this system is that the Esri program is quite user friendly and requires
               very little web literacy, relative to other mapping software. However, despite the
               friendly interface, some of these issues dissuaded some potential users. Another
               issue is that, unlike QGIS, which uses Python, the Esri site does not allow for the
               development of plugins in the Beta version. Nonetheless, in September 2016, the
               Feminist Restaurant Crowdsource StoryMap launched and was embedded in “The Feminist
               Restaurant Project” website. And after all of that- no one used it. Users preferred
               emailing me about their own narratives or communicating with me in other ways. The
               site’s users were not interested in actually making the map themselves, despite
               saying that they were. People liked the idea of it existing and talked about that
               being an exciting option but ultimately were not interested in map making. It turns
               out that my simpler Google maps were preferable for the communities I was engaging
               with. </note> I later learned that users preferred to communicate with me via email
            and have me make the changes on the map, rather than each person altering the map
            herself. These stories of failure also point to the fact that these projects can
            continuously be improved, begging the question: can a <soCalled>lost</soCalled> project ever truly be
            complete?</p>
         <p>Unlike a published book, public history websites can be updated ad infinitum, forcing
            creators to decide when to end the project. Placing parameters on a project allows for a
            sense of completion. Mattson chose to restrict his project to the 10-year timeframe of
            2006-2016. However, he explains that <quote rend="inline">I've got a larger project that is using LGBT
            guidebooks to track the closures of bars for lesbians, and this mapping project turned
            out to be just an early version of the larger one. In those early stages I thought I was
            going to find that gay bars were just closing, but it turns out it's a much more
            complicated picture. Even for lesbian bars, at least three have opened this year. No one
            has created a <title rend="quotes">Found Womyn's Spaces Blog,</title> so tracking only the closures of what are, in
            the end, small businesses, doesn't capture the new ones that arise</quote>
            <ptr target="#mattson2018"/>. While the Mapping Lost Bars project is complete, it is part of a larger, ongoing
            endeavor. For my project, the completion of my dissertation produced one kind of ending.
            However, as I turn my dissertation into a book manuscript, I continue to update the
            site. Also, as I publish more information about the topic of feminist restaurants,
            including academic articles and non-academic books, I include that information on the
            website. The maps I built originally in 2015 based off of the women’s/lesbian
            guidebooks, a kind of methodology that Mattson has begun to likewise use to track bar
            closures, have only been updated a few times since the website originally launched. I
            have considered working with a research assistant or information studies scholar to
            digitize and make word searchable every copy of Gaia’s Guides and map every single kind
            of business mentioned with color codes. I have also considered making the map specific
            down to addresses, rather than just city centers and include photos, histories, and
            personal stories, similar to the NYC LGBT Historic Sites Project website. However, I
            currently do not have the resources to enact these changes. After years of keeping The
            Feminist Restaurant Project updated, my work on the site has slowed. Jan Kurth shares a
            similar sentiment stating,</p>
         <p><quote rend="block">I suppose I could quit at any time and it would be more or less complete. I still see
            mention of lost lesbian bars now and then, so I'll add those as time permits. Or maybe
            search for an old ad for a ladies cafe from 1900. But because of a lot more demands on
            my time these days, I just don't have the same hours to devote to this as I used to. I
            don't really see an "end goal" as the thing doesn't really have a beginning. It is what
            it is, I suppose
            <ptr target="#kurth2018"/>.</quote> </p>
         <p>Mattson did most of his work over eighteen months. I spent four years actively updating
            the site. Jan Kurth has spent seven years on her site but has decreased her rate of
            posting over the past three years. Between June 2019 and June 2020, she did not write a
            single post. These projects point to the difficulties of sustaining these kinds of
            ventures. <soCalled>lost</soCalled> spaces keep being lost. History keeps expanding. An individual’s
            resources, however, have limitations. The topic of endings speaks to larger questions
            regarding maintenance and preservation. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Preservation: is Lost Space Doomed to be Lost? </head>
         <p> The process of finding lost spaces is about creating a record. The projects discussed
            in this article host their records online. Rapidly changing file formats, domain name
            ownerships lapsing, and new technologies threaten preservation. The struggle to keep
            resources up-to-date and accessible has led historians and archivists to fear that the
            current era will be the digital Dark Ages for future generations. Websites disappear.
            Head of the British Library's web archiving program, Stephen Bury, explained how the
            program preserved important records that only existed online, noting that <quote rend="inline">if we hadn't
            done that nobody would have access to the information, the photographs, the interviews
            on that site</quote>
            <ptr target="#fowler2009"/> <ptr target="#milligan2013"/> <ptr target="#milligan2018"/>.<note> Ian Milligan’s WARC project offers
               another approach to web archiving in a way that allows historians to more easily
               access data. This project also connects to his work on WALK (Web Archives for
               Longitudinal Knowledge). </note> Keeping websites functioning and up-to-date is a
            specific struggle that requires constant maintenance, necessitating labor and financial
            resources. While the British Library has financial resources for this kind of work, all
            three of the projects surveyed in this article are maintained by individuals without any
            dedicated institutional funding.</p>
         <p>Maintaining digital resources, especially projects independent of large institutional
            resources, is difficult. Greggor Mattson explains that his site <quote rend="inline">will live on my Google
            page forever, I guess, but until you asked it never occurred to me that it might be
            something that would interest an archive. But it's true: who archives the exteriors of
            the lesbian bars of Salt Lake City or
            Tulsa?</quote> <ptr target="#mattson2018"/>. Kurth said she has not given thought of how to preserve the work but is
            interested in ideas. I, too, am unsure of how to proceed. I built the site on Google’s
            Blogger platform so that I would not have to pay hosting fees and just pay a modest fee
            of around fifteen dollars yearly to maintain my domain name. However, the site is
            vulnerable to the whims of Google, which could decide to end Blogger and Google Maps.
            The site also requires frequent maintenance and updates. All of this work depends on my
            donated labor and is vulnerable to my own mortality
            <ptr target="#ketchum2018"/>. Outside of saving the posts as Word file documents and saving them on external
            hard drives and digital storage, personal attempts at preservation flounder. When I
            posed this question to readers of my site, the only solution offered was the Internet
            Archive
            <ptr target="#anon2017"/>. The Internet Archive, a 501(c)(3) non-profit, is building a digital library of
            Internet sites and other cultural artifacts in digital form; for example, it saved
            copies of The Feminist Restaurant Project 27 times between May 9, 2015 and August 24,
            2018. Despite the Internet Archive’s Wayback Machine preserving 341 billion web pages
            over the past twenty years, it is only useful if users know what they are searching for.
            Also, it seems precarious to depend exclusively on this single site. While the Internet
            has been touted as a democratization of knowledges and a tool for making knowledge more
            accessible, the ephemeral quality of digital resources challenges this narrative of
            accessibility. How do we as public historians and archivists preserve digital projects?
            Is our work fated to disappear?</p>
         <p>As scholars Marika Cifor and Stacy Wood demonstrate, archives and public history
            projects centered on marginalized, particularly LGBTQ+ communities have often decided to
            remain independent and not join with an institution. Elise Chenier likewise explains
            that <quote rend="inline">one of the major concerns expressed about the current shift of LGBTQ materials
            from community-based archives to institutional libraries, archives, and special
            collections is that collections will no longer be shaped by LGBTQ praxis</quote>
            <ptr target="#chenier2016"/>. They report that organizations such as the Lesbian Herstory Archives (LHA) are
            <quote rend="inline">decidedly suspect of the long-term investment in and commitment to these initiatives
            [and as a result] many organizations chose to keep collecting efforts autonomous and
            community driven, ensuring that collections, policies, and materials were not subject to
            changing priorities within universities</quote>
            <ptr target="#cooper2013"/> <ptr target="#corban2014"/> <ptr target="#mckinney2015"/>. However, as evidenced above, by the example of the
            British Library’s Web Archiving project, institutions provide more funding stability and
            are not predicated on one individual’s circumstances in the same way. </p>
         <p>Perhaps some compromise can be made. Ann Cvetkovich has proposed <term>Queer Archive
            Activism</term> that calls for something beyond the financial and infrastructural support of
            the institution, but also requires space for active engagement with materials and a
            space for housing materials that push against traditional archival notions of
            evidentiary value
            <ptr target="#cvetkovich2011"/>. This debate between institution and community driven projects continues
            <ptr target="#eichhorn2014"/> <ptr target="#juhasz2006"/>. Online history projects serve a kind of counter narrative to the
            erasure or marginalization of LGBTQ+ histories; however, with their creation comes new
            challenges. Since these digital history projects are different than community archives
            and rather than dependent on a small group are so tied to one individual,
            institutionalization within an archive that has the financial and technological
            resources to sustain or retain the project is necessary. To be incorporated within that
            institution would help maintain these projects, which serve as valuable resources to
            understanding LGBTQ+ spatial histories. Moving away from a burden on the individual and
            towards institutionalization will give these projects a greater chance of survival.
            Ideally, community members will be included and the kind of engagement that Cvetkovich
            proposes can exist. As Kurth states, <quote rend="inline">If somebody else wants to take one or more of
            these places and do more research that's great! Or even come up with their own
            observations and generalizations based on the data. I have no problem with that at all.
            I welcome it.</quote>
            <ptr target="#kurth2018"/>. Mattson and I share a similar sentiment, hoping that our work of collecting and
            retaining will be built upon. In order for the future work to be done, these sites must
            be preserved and institutionalization will enable this work. </p></div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
         <p>The stakes of preserving the history of lost LGBTQ+ spaces are high. Directors of the
            Lesbian and Gay Liberation in Canada, Michelle Schwartz and Constance Crompton discuss
            how history-making practices of lesbian feminists offer a model of cultural history
            preservation and transmission for those who create digital resources. They write that
            <quote rend="inline">while this history-making situates researchers and their sisters in relation to lost
            history, there is something in the perpetual reinvigoration and revisiting of these
            lists and projects, often started anew every decade, which leads us to ask about the
            lack of cultural transmission between lesbian generations</quote> <ptr target="#schwartz2018"/>. In particular, they
            argue that even though individuals should maintain a right to privacy and a right to be
            forgotten, <quote rend="inline">we must also weigh the danger to both feminism and queer politics of hiding
            our history, forcing each new generation to start anew, with only the haziest
            stereotypes about previous generations to draw on for strength, or worse, to look on
            with derision, against the threat of confrontation, doxing, or violence to named
            activists</quote> <ptr target="#schwartz2018"/>. Without proper preservation <soCalled>lost</soCalled> history projects risk being <soCalled>lost</soCalled>
            or re-forgotten, forcing future generations to repeat the work of recovery.</p>
         <p>This article has focused on online history projects that center women’s, lesbian, and
            queer women’s spaces within a greater narrative of reclaiming LGBTQ+ spaces as a way to
            study histories of marginalized peoples. Jan Kurth’s <title rend="inline">Lost Womyn’s Space,</title> Greggor
            Mattson’s <title rend="inline">Mapping Lost Lesbian Bars,</title> and my own project, <title rend="inline">The Feminist Restaurant
            Project</title> use crowdsourcing, social media, visuals, and mapping in order to inspire other
            researchers, contribute to the collective memory of LGBTQ+ communities, and further the
            creators’ other work. Lost space projects are important. These digital projects
            highlight lost or marginalized historical actors. In the case of the endeavors studied
            in this article, women’s, lesbian, feminist, and queer spaces bring attention to
            histories that have been lost or forgotten and speak to larger conversations within
            history, archival research, and digital humanities about the need to document and
            preserve materials and stories of marginalized communities. However, as these projects
            rely on the efforts of individuals, and are divorced from institutional support and
            self-funded, they are vulnerable to being re-lost or re-forgotten. Institutionalization
            is necessary for their survival and can free future generations from needing to repeat
            this labor. To institutionalize or archive an individual project merely ends a single
            iteration of the work. By preserving these sites, my hope is that future generations
            will build upon and adapt these projects to new futures and circumstances.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>I would like to acknowledge the helpful feedback I received when presenting this
               research at the Association of Canadian Archivists in 2019. </p>
         </div>
        
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="coffeehousecommunity" label="A Woman's Coffeehouse Community 1983">A Woman’s Coffeehouse Community. <title rend="quotes">Open Community Meeting Tapes</title> [Cassette Tapes]
               (1983).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="anon2017" label="Anon 2017">Anon. <title rend="quotes">The Internet Archive</title> [web site]. <ref target="https://archive.org/about/">https://archive.org/about/</ref> (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bahr2019" label="Bahr 2019">Bahr, S. 2019. <title rend="quotes">'The opposite of lost': IU library claps back at The New Yorker over
               Sylvia Plath story.</title> IndyStar.
               <ref target="https://www.indystar.com/story/news/2019/01/11/iu-lilly-library-lost-sylvia-plath-story-isnt-lost/2546031002/">https://www.indystar.com/story/news/2019/01/11/iu-lilly-library-lost-sylvia-plath-story-isnt-lost/2546031002/</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bennett2000" label="Bennett 2000">Bennett JM. <title rend="quotes">‘Lesbian-like’ and the Social History of Lesbianisms.</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of the History
               of Sexuality</title>, 9 (2000).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="boyd2019" label="Boyd 2019">Boyd, J., 2019. <title rend="quotes">Just Like You Want Me to Be?: Gay and Lesbian Oral History Projects and
               the Frameworks of Public History.</title> <title rend="italic">The Public Historian</title>, 41(2), pp.269-289.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brooks2019" label="Brooks 2019">Brooks, James F. 2019. <title rend="quotes">Commemorating Queer History.</title> <title rend="italic">The Public Historian</title>, 41(2),
               pp.5</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="browne2010" label="Brown, Nash, and Hines 2010">Browne, K., Nash, C. J., &amp; Hines, S. (2010). <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Towards Trans
               Geographies.</title> <title rend="italic">Gender, Place &amp; Culture</title>, 17(5), 573-577.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chenier2010" label="Chenier 2010">Chenier E. <title rend="quotes">Hidden from Historians: Preserving Lesbian Oral History in Canada.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Archivaria</title>, 68 (2010): 247–269.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chenier2015" label="Chenier 2015">Chenier E. <title rend="quotes">Privacy Anxieties: Ethics Versus Activism in Archiving Lesbian Oral History
               Online.</title> <title rend="italic">Radical History Review</title>, 122 (2015):129–141.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chenier2016" label="Chenier 2016">Chenier E. <title rend="quotes">Reclaiming the Lesbian Archives.</title> <title rend="italic">The Oral History Review</title>, 43.1
               (2016):170–182.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cifor2018" label="Cifor et al. 2018">Cifor M et al. <title rend="quotes">‘What We Do Crosses over to Activism’: The Politics and Practice of
               Community Archives.</title> <title rend="italic">The Public Historian</title>, 40.2 (2018):70.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cocciolo2017" label="Cocciolo 2017">Cocciolo A. <title rend="quotes">Community Archives in the Digital Era: A Case from the LGBT Community.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Preservation, Digital Technology &amp; Culture</title>, 45.4 (2017):157–165.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cooper2013" label="Cooper 2013">Cooper D. <title rend="quotes">Welcome Home: An Exploratory Ethnography of the Information Context at the
               Lesbian Herstory Archives.</title> In: <title rend="italic">Keilty P, Dean R, eds. Feminist and Queer Information
               Studies Reader</title>. Sacremento, Litwin Books, (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="corban2014" label="Corban 2014">Corban RF. <title rend="quotes">A Genealogy of the Lesbian Herstory Archives: 1974-2014.</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of
               Contemporary Archival Studies</title>, 1 (2014).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cvetkovich2011" label="Cvetkovich 2011">Cvetkovich A. <title rend="quotes">The Queer Art of the Counterarchive.</title> <title rend="italic">Los Angeles: ONE National Gay and
               Lesbian Archives</title>, (2011).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eichhorn2014" label="Eichhorn 2014">Eichhorn K. <title rend="italic">The Archival Turn in Feminism: Outrage in Order.</title> Philadelphia, Temple
               University Press. (2014).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fowler2009" label="Fowler 2009">Fowler N, Abramsohn J. <title rend="quotes">For Historians and Archivists, Modern Era is a Digital ‘Dark Age’</title>
               [web site].
               <ref target="https://www.dw.com/en/for-historians-and-archivists-modern-era-is-a-digital-dark-age/a-4314304
                  to moreualization Workflttps://ianmilliga/">https://www.dw.com/en/for-historians-and-archivists-modern-era-is-a-digital-dark-age/a-4314304
               to moreualization Workflttps://ianmilliga/</ref>. (2009).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ingram1997" label="Ingram, Bouthillette, and Retter 1997">Ingram GB, Bouthillette A, Retter Y. <title rend="italic">Queers in Space: Communities, Public Places, Sites
               of Resistance</title>. Seattle, Bay Press. (1997).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jacobs2017" label="Jacobs and Murgu 2017">Jacobs HL, Murgu C. <title rend="quotes">Questioning the Past and Possible Futures: Digital Historiography
               and Critical Librarianship.</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of Critical Library and Information Studies</title>,
               1.1(2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jette2019" label="Jetté 2019">Jetté, M.M., 2019. <title rend="quotes">Through the Queer Looking-Glass: The Future of LGBTQ Public
               History.</title> <title rend="italic">The Public Historian</title>, 41(2), pp.6-18.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jimerson2003" label="Jimerson 2003">Jimerson RC. <title rend="quotes">Archives and Memory.</title> <title rend="italic">International Digital Library Perspectives</title>,
               19.3(2003):89–95.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="juhasz2006" label="Juhasz 2006">Juhasz A. <title rend="quotes">Video Remains: Nostalgia, Technology, and Queer Archive Activism.</title> <title rend="italic">GLQ: A
               Journal of Lesbian and Gay Studies</title>, 12.2 (2006):319–328.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ketchum2015" label="Ketchum 2015">Ketchum A. <title rend="quotes">The Feminist Restaurant Project</title> [web site]. <ref
               target="http://thefeministrestaurantproject.com"
               >http://thefeministrestaurantproject.com</ref>. (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ketchum2018" label="Ketchum 2018">Ketchum A. <title rend="quotes">Digital Dark Ages, Documenting Food Histories, and Honoring Lynne Olver</title> [web
               site]. <ref
                  target="http://www.historicalcookingproject.com/2018/08/digital-dark-ages-documenting-food.html"
                  >http://www.historicalcookingproject.com/2018/08/digital-dark-ages-documenting-food.html</ref>.
               (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ketchum2019" label="Ketchum 2019">Ketchum A. <title rend="quotes">Memory Has Added Seasoning: The Legacy of Feminist Restaurants in the United
               States and Canada.</title> <title rend="italic">Anthropology of Food</title>. <ref
                  target="http://journals.openedition.org/aof/9904"
                  >http://journals.openedition.org/aof/9904</ref>. (2019).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kurth2011" label="Kurth 2011">Kurth J. <title rend="quotes">Lost and Found.</title> <title rend="italic">Lost Womyn’s Space</title>. <ref
               target="http://lostwomynsspace.blogspot.com"
               >http://lostwomynsspace.blogspot.com</ref>. (2011).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kurth2018" label="Kurth 2018">Kurth J. <title rend="italic">On Making Lost Womyn’s Space</title>. (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="larochelle2017" label="LaRochelle 2017">LaRochelle, L.<title rend="italic"> Queering the Map</title>. <ref target="https://www.queeringthemap.com"
               >https://www.queeringthemap.com</ref> (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lee2015" label="Lee et al. 2015">Lee KM, Page-Vanore C, Stankrauff A. Partnership in the Preservation of Rustbelt Queer
               HIstory [web site]. (<ref
                  target="http://www.archivejournal.net/essays/partnership-in-the-preservation-of-rustbelt-queer-history/"
                  >http://www.archivejournal.net/essays/partnership-in-the-preservation-of-rustbelt-queer-history/</ref>.
               (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lostpubsproject2018" label="Lost Pubs Project 2018">Lost Pubs Project. Archiving the Decline of the English Pub [web site]. <ref
               target="http://www.closedpubs.co.uk">http://www.closedpubs.co.uk</ref>. (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mattson2016" label="Mattson 2016">Mattson G. <title rend="quotes">Lesbian Bar Closures.</title> <title rend="italic">Who Needs Gay Bars</title>. <ref
               target="https://greggormattson.com/2016/09/17/mapping-lost-lesbian-bars-2006-2016/"
               >https://greggormattson.com/2016/09/17/mapping-lost-lesbian-bars-2006-2016/</ref>.
               (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mattson2018" label="Mattson 2018">Mattson G. <title rend="italic">The Creation of Mapping Lost Lesbian Bars</title>. (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="maynard1991" label="Maynard 1991">Maynard S. <title rend="quotes">‘The Burning, Wilful Evidence’: Lesbian/Gay History and Archival Research.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Archivaria</title>, 33 (1991):195–201.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mckinney2015" label="McKinney 2015">McKinney C. <title rend="quotes">Body, Sex, Interface: Reckoning with Images at the Lesbian Herstory
               Archives.</title> <title rend="italic">Radical History Review</title>,122 (2015):115–128.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="milligan2013" label="Milligan 2013">Milligan I. <title rend="quotes">A WARC to Topic Model Visualization Workflow</title> [web site]. <ref
               target="https://ianmilligan.ca/2013/05/15/warc-to-topic-models/"
               >https://ianmilligan.ca/2013/05/15/warc-to-topic-models/</ref>. (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="milligan2018" label="Milligan 2018">Milligan I. <title rend="quotes">Web Archives for Longitudinal Knowledge</title> [web site]. <ref
               target="http://webarchives.ca/about">http://webarchives.ca/about</ref>. (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nestle2015" label="Nestle 2015">Nestle J. <title rend="quotes">Who Were We to Do Such a Thing? Grassroots Necessities, Grassroots Dreaming:
               The LHA in Its Early Years.</title> <title rend="italic">Radical History Review</title>,122 (2015):233–242.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="historicalsitesproject2017" label="New York City LGBT Historical Sites Project 2017">New York City LGBT Historical Sites Project. <title rend="quotes">Making an Invisible History Visible</title> [web
               site]. <ref target="https://www.nyclgbtsites.org">https://www.nyclgbtsites.org</ref>.
               (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="omeara2012" label="O'Meara 2012">O’Meara E. <title rend="quotes">Perfecting the New Wave of Collecting: Documenting Feminist Activism in the
               Digital Age.</title> In: <title rend="italic">Bly L, Wooten K, eds. Make Your Own History: Documenting Feminist and
               Queer Activism in the 21st Century</title>. Litwin Books, (2012):105–122.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="podmore2001" label="Podmore 2001">Podmore J. <title rend="quotes">Lesbians in the Crowd: Gender, Sexuality and Visibility Along Montreal’s
               Boul.</title> <title rend="quotes">St-Laurent. Gender, Place and Culture</title>, 8.4 (2001):333–355.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="robb2012" label="Robb 2012">Robb S. <title rend="quotes">How the Women’s Building Came to Be</title> [web site]. <ref
               target="http://www.foundsf.org/index.php?title=How_the_Women%27s_Building_Came_To_Be"
               >http://www.foundsf.org/index.php?title=How_the_Women%27s_Building_Came_To_Be</ref>
               (2012).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="samer2014" label="Samer 2014">Samer R. <title rend="quotes">Revising ‘Re-vision’: Documenting 1970s Feminisms and the Queer Potentiality of
               Digital Feminist Archives.</title> <title rend="italic">Ada: A Journal of Gender, New Media and Technology</title>,
               5(2014).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schwartz2002" label="Schwartz 2002">Schwartz JM, Cook T. <title rend="quotes">Archives, Records, and Power: The Making of Modern Memory.</title> <title rend="italic">Archival
               Science</title>, 2 (2002):14.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schwartz2018" label="Schwartz and Crompton 2018">Schwartz, M., &amp; Crompton, C. <title rend="quotes">Remaking History: Lesbian Feminist Historical Methods
               in the Digital Humanities.</title> <title rend="italic">Bodies of Information: Intersectional Feminism and Digital
               Humanities</title>, 131-56 (2018).</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
