<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Digital Methods in Literary Criticism: A Review of <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities
               and Literary Studies </hi>(2022)<!--article title in English--></title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Lili<dhq:family>Wang</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Harbin Engineering University </dhq:affiliation>
               <email>wangliliwaiyu@hrbeu.edu.cn; </email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Lili Wang is a Professor of English at Harbin Engineering University, China.
                     Her major research interests include Digital Humanities and African American
                     literature. She published <hi rend="italic">Recovery from Trauma: A Study of
                        Black Women’s Trauma in Toni Morrison’s Fiction</hi> (2014).</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Tianxiang<dhq:family>Chen</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Harbin Engineering University </dhq:affiliation>
               <email>chentianxiang65@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Tianxiang Chen
                     is a Master’s student in English Language Literature at Harbin Engineering
                     University, China.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
               <term corresp=""/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/NNNNNN/NNNNNN.xml"
               >GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p></p>
         <p>Lili Wang &lt;wangliliwaiyu@hrbeu.edu.cn&gt; and Tianxiang
            Chen&lt;chentianxiang65@gmail.com&gt;, Harbin Engineering University</p>
         <p>Authors Bios: </p>
         <p>Abstract: In <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities and Literary Studies, </hi>Martin Paul
            Eve discusses various cases of digital technology in the analysis of literary studies
            and examines how digital tools influence literary interpretation. Martin skillfully
            navigates the complex landscape of digital methodologies, offering readers a holistic
            view of the transformative influence of literary analysis.</p>
         <p>The progress of contemporary technology, particularly AI, has transformed the
            conventional methods of literary research into digitization, from traditional close
            reading and logical reasoning. Notably, the rise of digital humanities avails literary
            history of research with digital maps and social networks. To extend the research line
            along that vein, Martin Paul Eve has crafted a timely book to present the merits and
            drawbacks of computational approaches and technical analysis integrated into literary
            exploration. Quite different from the prior works on digital humanities, this book
            contributes to literary criticism by embracing both proponents and critics, highlighting
            a more impartial presentation of the cutting edge of digital humanities in literary
            research.</p>
         <p>Martin Paul Eve describes the rise of a new paradigm for the humanities in <hi
               rend="italic">The Digital Humanities and Literary Studies</hi> [Eve 2022]. He
            presents a comprehensive review of current research on digital literature and
            establishes the necessary basis for conducting a more extensive exploration of the field
            in the years to come. Beyond depicting the influence of digital technology on writers,
            visualization, mapping, and literary history, Martin provides his unique recommendations
            and apprehensions regarding the advancement of digital humanities. He examines the
            impact of digital literary studies, both in the past and ongoing, as their potential
            future contributions. He calls on readers to recognize the advancement of digital
            humanities within the field and to prioritize improving researchers’ computer skills to
            enable more comprehensive and efficient literary analysis.</p>
         <p>The book has five sections after an introduction: authors and writing, space and
            visualization, maps and place, distance and history, and a thought-provoking conclusion
            on “ethical digitalism.” Martin delves into the historical context and future
            possibilities of digital humanities development in the introduction. In doing so, he
            succinctly encapsulates the central theme of each section, providing readers with a
            lucid understanding of the emerging literary studies paradigm in the digital humanities
            sphere and a holistic conceptualization of his book. </p>
         <p>Chapter 1 presents a range of methods for digitally quantifying literary style, known as
            stylometry or digital stylistics. By the software named “Delta,” a system for
            calculating the frequency of words, he uncovers the potential possibilities of
            stylometry in relation to authorship and understanding of literary genres. That approach
            makes it feasible to conduct multi-textual comparisons, resulting in a more profound
            appreciation of the authors’ works. It becomes evident that a combination of close and
            distant reading is essential for a comprehensive understanding of both authorship and
            the book. Taking the book <hi rend="italic">Evolution </hi>[Heldén and Jonson 2014] as a
            case study, Martin continues to provide a brief account of computer-generated writing to
            show that the purpose of digital practice isn’t to generate seemingly objective data as
            a substitute for traditional narrative and argumentation, but rather to maintain the
            fundamental function of interpretation and elaboration in literary studies. </p>
         <p>Chapter 2 turns to space and visualization. While acknowledging the limitations of
            visualization in understanding textual differences, he agrees that visualization can
            help us understand textual and intertextual developmental changes and plot connections.
            He provides a glimpse into a scarcely examined illicit digital subculture, which creates
            a unique form of visualized typographic aesthetic artwork. That opens the doors to a new
            era of interpretation centered on the graphs, maps, and trees of digital humanities and
            the textual exploration of visualized digital artifacts. </p>
         <p>Chapter 3 focuses on place and maps. Martin argues the spatial shift in literary
            criticism directs our attention toward how the structure of literary texts can shape our
            perception of space. In this way, we successfully convert space, plot, and authority
            into symbolic visual representations. Taking Matthew Sangster’s project, <hi
               rend="italic">Romantic London,</hi> as an example, Martin explores the relationship
            between Romantic poetry and place. The deployment of maps and timelines significantly
            amplifies readers’ comprehension of the novel. Indeed, digital humanities practice
            intertwined with mapping literary and historical texts has become a trend powered by the
            advancement of Geographic Information Systems (GIS). Consequently, literary mapping has
            blossomed into a substantial subdomain within the field of digital humanities. </p>
         <p>Chapter 4 explores the impact of digital technologies on analyzing literary and digital
            media history. By reemphasizing “distant reading,” a concept often associated with
            large-scale literary history, Martin stresses that digital methods must not be presented
            as apolitical. Instead, they are more connected with diverse perspectives, including
            postcolonialism, disability, race, gender, and class dimensions. Through the lens of
            digital technology, it becomes feasible to question secondary literary criticism and
            existing assumptions to propel the humanities forward. Finally, Martin concludes the
            book with the prospects for developing digital methods and their far-reaching
            implications for literary studies in the contemporary era. </p>
         <p>Martin addresses the benefits and difficulties of digital humanities' progress in
            literary criticism. He argues that integrating digital methods with traditional close
            reading facilitates a deeper appreciation of literary works and fosters a broader
            understanding of their significance within the context of longer literary histories.
            Although he suggests that the combination of distant and close reading presents a novel
            way of interpreting texts, he fails to provide an in-depth exploration of the specific
            methods needed for successfully integrating close and distant reading into analyzing
            literature with digital tools. Rather than focusing on the theory and practice of
            digital humanities, he presents profound possibilities for interpreting literature with
            digital methods such as delta analysis, kernel density estimate, visualization, etc.
            However, some of the digital tools discussed in his book might be obsolete when the book
            reaches readers because the evolution of artificial intelligence agents specializing in
            natural language generation has been extraordinarily swift. He would have never imagined
            that ChatGPT and its ilk hold revolutionary potential for computing in the coming years.
            Moreover, the book’s analysis and examples are limited to works written in English and
            overlooks the realm of multilingual digital humanities practices in a global context. </p>
         <p>Despite the limitations, this book still provokes literary scholars to reconsider the
            approaches to integrating digital methods with conventional literary criticism, and
            assess how digital humanities might change the definition of canonical works and
            literary theories. This book also serves as a valuable resource for individuals
            interested in comprehending digital humanities and specializing in literary research. As
            digital methods challenge practical literary criticism, Martin Paul Eve’s <hi
               rend="italic">Digital Humanities and Literary Studies</hi> offers supplement methods
            and innovative approaches to literary criticism in the digital era. Meanwhile, the
            ongoing progress of digital practices within literary studies is captivating and
            contentious. </p>
         <p>Works Cited</p>
         <p>Eve 2022 Eve, M. P. <hi rend="italic">The Digital Humanities and Literary Studies</hi>.
            Oxford University Press (2022).</p>
         <p>Heldén and Jonson 2014 Heldén, J. and Jonson, H. (2014). <hi rend="italic"
               >Evolution</hi>. http://www.textevolution.net/</p>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl/>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
