<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">From Kindling to Kindles: A Review of Matt Hayler, <title
                        rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of Technology: Embodiment, Expertise
                        and Evolved Knowledge</title> (Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan,
                    2015)</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Richard<dhq:family> Graham</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Exeter</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>richardnvgraham@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p> Richard Graham is a PhD candidate studying the effects of web search
                            engine technologies, particularly Google, on our understanding and
                            perceptions of knowledge. Asking, in what ways might Google change the
                            way we think, learn, and participate in notions of community? Richard
                            keeps an academic blog which can be found at: <ref
                                target="http://richardnvgraham.blogspot.co.uk"
                                >http://richardnvgraham.blogspot.co.uk</ref> and tweets in an
                            academic capacity from <ref target="https://twitter.com/richardnvgraham"
                                >@richardnvgraham</ref>
                        </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000242</idno>
                <idno type="volume">010</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2016-06-07">7 June 2016</date>
                <dhq:articleType>review</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>technology</item>
                        <item>philosophy</item>
                        <item>cognitive science</item>
                        <item>e-reading</item>
                        <item>phenomenology</item>
                        <item>postphenomenology</item>
                        <item>object oriented ontology</item>
                        <item>actor-network theory</item>
                        <item>evolutionary epistemology</item>
                        <item>interdisciplinarity</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="EH" when="2016-02-16">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p><title rend="quotes">From Kindling to Kindles</title> is a review of Matt
                    Hayler's <title rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of Technology:
                        Embodiment, Expertise and Evolved Knowledge</title> (Basingstoke: Palgrave
                    Macmillan, 2015). Hayler's text is an investigation into the current theoretical
                    framework surrounding our contemporary usage of the term
                        <soCalled>technology.</soCalled> To do this <title rend="italic">Challenging
                        the Phenomena of Technology</title> moves through how we define technology,
                    why the same artefacts might be fundamentally different for different users, how
                    this might change our understanding of embodied knowledge, and finally places
                    these issues into a nonhuman context. The book offers exemplary accounts of how
                    to tackle interdisciplinary concerns that relate to so many aspects of our
                    lives.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>A review of Matt Hayler's <title rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of
                        Technology: Embodiment, Expertise andt Evolved Knowledge</title>
                    (Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2015)</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>There are a number of wide-ranging questions embedded throughout Matt Hayler’s
                        <title rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of Technology: Embodiment,
                        Expertise and Evolved Knowledge</title>: How do we read? How do we engage
                    with the world around us? What separates experts and amateurs? Can we think
                    about technology from a nonhuman perspective? To answer these questions, Hayler
                    draws on a wide range of research areas and in doing so produces an exemplary
                    interdisciplinary model. One of the main strengths of <title rend="italic"
                        >Challenging the Phenomena of Technology</title> is that it provides an
                    insight into some of the most contemporary issues currently causing debate in a
                    wide number of disciplines. Hayler’s balanced description of various contexts
                    will introduce readers to a number of discussions occurring behind disciplinary
                    walls and explain why we might want to care about them.</p>
                <p><title rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of Technology</title> will be of
                    particular interest to Digital Humanities scholars. One of the main thrusts of
                    the book is how pervasive a certain kind of language surrounding technology has
                    become in Western discourse. The boundaries between artificial/natural,
                    organic/augmented, tool/technology, practice/expertise are constantly being
                    redrawn in new ways, but ways that are informed by a complex history. <title
                        rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of Technology</title> shows that,
                    rather than being a subset of niche concerns, questioning what we mean by
                    technology relates to everything we do. Therefore, I feel that Hayler’s work
                    speaks directly to the Digital Humanities community (both to our big and small
                    tents). Even those researchers on the fringes of the DH community will be
                    accustomed to the kind of discourse that surrounds our self-clarifications and,
                    at times, self-defences. That DH might be about focusing our attentions to new
                    media, digital content, or the use of digital methods inevitably draws up
                    distinctions between <soCalled>natural</soCalled> humanities scholarship and
                    newer <soCalled>technological</soCalled> departures. <title rend="italic"
                        >Challenging the Phenomena of Technology</title> seeks to dismantle such a
                    distinction, demonstrating how the <soCalled>natural</soCalled> has always been
                    a complex arrangement of constructs. For example, Hayler asks, why should a pen
                    be treated as less technological than a computer? And are either of them in the
                    same technological realm as, say, my microwave or CERN’s Large Hadron Collider?
                    In doing so <title rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of Technology</title>
                    moves through how we define technology, why the same artefacts might be
                    fundamentally different for different users, how this might change our
                    understanding of embodied knowledge, and finally, it places these issues into a
                    nonhuman context. Its comprehensive coverage of such expansive topics in a book
                    of under 250 pages should be commended. Hayler’s sources may come from a diverse
                    group of disciplines but the narrative is focused and bolstered with contextual
                    awareness.</p>
                <p><title rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of Technology</title> covers a lot
                    of ground and for that reason this review will not attempt to address every
                    aspect. However, I have attempted to capture the central argument that builds
                    through Hayler’s work, and have arranged the review into five sections that
                    broadly correspond to the five chapters of <title rend="italic">Challenging the
                        Phenomena of Technology</title>. The first three sections mainly consist of
                    short summaries, which are important for understanding Hayler’s later arguments.
                    In section three I set out how my theoretical perspective differs from Hayler’s
                    and the ways in which they might be productively compatible. The final two
                    sections of this review attend to what I believe to be the most innovative and
                    stimulating aspects of <title rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of
                        Technology</title> and therefore include more analysis and suggestions of
                    possible avenues for further development of Hayler’s work.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>One: What is <q>Technology</q>?</head>
                <p><title rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of Technology: Embodiment,
                        Expertise and Evolved Knowledge</title> aims to do just that: challenge.
                    Challenge our definition of technology, but also any claims to naturalness we
                    might have. The opening chapter outlines various resistances to technology and
                    uses e-reading as a key example. Why have e-readers provoked such
                    resistance?</p>
                <p>Hayler draws on a wide variety of folk phenomenological (non-academic, personal
                    reports), philosophical, and cognitive science arguments. These resistances are
                    then separated into two <q>flavours</q>: the <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015"
                        >romantic: digital technology for reading provides a layer of visceral
                        insulation between us and the sensual world of which printed books are a
                        very pleasant part</quote> and the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">scientific concern: e-reading
                            negatively impacts upon our cognition and impoverishes the experience of
                            reading in a quantifiable way</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="19"/>
                    </cit>. The distinction here is not between the amateur and the academic; Hayler
                    cites various scientific studies that are commonly used in public discourse as
                    well as a number of academic professionals drawing on
                        <soCalled>romantic</soCalled> arguments. Although he does not deny the
                    grounded reality of the complaints, Hayler’s perspective is that both sets of
                    arguments are built on shaky ground. The scientific arguments against e-reading
                    are often based on bad leaps of faith, scientism, and the drawing of conclusions
                    from unrelated studies. As is unsurprising for such a young technology, there is
                    real lack of primary research: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#hayler2015">no study has put anyone in an fMRI,
                            or any other type of machine, with a printed copy of <title
                                rend="italic">A Tale of Two Cities</title> and a digital edition to
                            see what’s different, no one has yet compared like for like.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="32"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>This is also unfortunate due to the number of <soCalled>romantic</soCalled>
                    arguments made recently against e-reading that too draw on science to anchor
                    their concerns to statements about how the brain functions naturally.<note> A
                        movement that Romanticism scholar Steven E. Jones associates with
                            <soCalled>Neo-Luddism</soCalled> (see Steven E. Jones, <title
                            rend="italic">Against Technology: From the Luddites to
                            Neo-Luddism</title> and Nicols Fox, <title rend="italic">Against the
                            Machine: The Hidden Luddite Tradition in Literature, Art, and Individual
                            Lives</title>).</note> However, the main thrust from the
                        <soCalled>romantic</soCalled> camp is that technology <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">separates us from the
                            world</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="4"/>
                    </cit>. In response to this assertion, Hayler draws on archaeological and
                    anthropological research that argues that humans have been technologically
                    embedded from our earliest times as a species. In this vein, Hayler builds on
                    the arguments of Timothy Taylor in <title rend="italic">The Artificial
                        Ape</title>, arguing that <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">the
                        idea of humans versus technology is wrong...Technology is at least as
                        critical to our identity as our soft tissues</quote>
                    <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="189"/>. If technology has been central to our
                    evolution as a species and inextricably embedded in a long history of cultural
                    activities, then perhaps we need to interrogate the word <q>technology</q>. What
                    is it that we <q>really</q> mean when we use this word, with either positive or
                    negative connotations? Rather than avoiding this nebulous term, what happens if
                    we develop a new definition of technology, one that helps us better understand
                    the relationships between humans and artefacts? These are the leading questions
                    of the next section of <title rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of
                        Technology</title>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Two: A New Definition of Technology</head>
                <p>Hayler’s second chapter outlines a number of existing approaches to defining
                    technology in a concise and clear manner that quickly bring the reader up to
                    speed. <note> The clarity of the section, in particular the differentiation
                        between the approaches of similar thinkers, is excellent. The chapter gives
                        short summaries of the approaches of Leo Marx (<title rend="quotes"
                            >Technology: The Emergence of a Hazardous Concept</title>), Bernard
                        Stiegler (<title rend="italic">Technics and Time</title>), Martin Heidegger
                            (<title rend="quotes">The Question Concerning Technology</title>),
                        Jacques Ellul (<title rend="italic">The Technological Society</title>), José
                        Ortega y Gasset (<title rend="italic">Meditación de la Técnica</title>),
                        Paul DeVore (<title rend="italic">Technology: An Introduction</title>), and
                        Michel Foucault (<title rend="quotes">Technologies of the
                        Self</title>).</note> These contextual frameworks prove useful in Hayler’s
                    later arguments, however their main purpose at this stage is to make a
                    foundational statement from which the main body of the book follows. Hayler
                    argues that: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#hayler2015">There is no such thing as
                                <q>technology</q> by any persuasive definition, nothing we can point
                            to or touch, or describe consistent properties of, particularly in its
                            day-to-day use. This is a problem. It is a remarkably loose term; we
                            might often agree on the objects under discussion – computer: yes,
                            coriander: no – but the specifics of why this might be so are vague.
                                <q>Technology</q> is, at best, a consensus description of equipment
                            and practices.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="60"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>This declaration leads to one of the most exciting assertions of <title
                        rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of Technology</title>: for Hayler,
                    technology is <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">not a class of
                        objects, but a class of phenomenological experience with several consistent
                        features</quote>
                    <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="4"/>. His placing the emphasis on practice,
                    process, and active encounters rather than on lists of static objects
                    reconceptualises technology in a number of useful ways. To do so Hayler draws on
                    the philosopher of technology Joseph C. Pitt’s statement that <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">technology is <q>humanity at
                        work</q></quote>
                    <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="61"/>. This allows Hayler to start from, as he
                    puts it, a place of <q>dramatic inclusivity</q>
                    <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="61"/> but one that allows us to pay attention to
                    technological <q>experience</q> that is so integral to this text. Using this
                    broad focus, Hayler draws up four criteria that are important for understanding
                    technology as a phenomenological encounter. Hayler preempts the counterintuitive
                    nature of his criteria by suggesting that his definition <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#hayler2015">will produce some initially
                            strange, but hopefully illuminating, results; the definition that I want
                            to deploy will see, at least potentially, a book, a hunting dog, and a
                            dancer’s body as technologies, but banish the Large Hadron Collider, an
                            ATM machine, and a microwave from the same category. </quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="61"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>This is a dramatic warning shot, designed to provoke: how can such a statement be
                    true? Developing after the first chapter’s contextualisation of reactions
                    towards technology and its deconstruction of certain conceptions of naturalness,
                    this kind of statement should not come as such a surprise, yet it initially
                    comes across as illogical. It is therefore a deserved credit to Hayler’s
                    following criteria that lead such strangeness to become a realistic proposal.
                    Not every reader will be convinced, but all will certainly understand why we
                    might want to suggest that a hunting dog is more technological than a microwave.
                    Hayler’s four criteria are as follows:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Technologies EXTEND our means or ability to accomplish tasks.</item>
                    <item>Technologies are COMMUNAL, existing only in communities of users.</item>
                    <item>Technologies are able to become, if only temporarily, skilfully
                        INCORPORATED into our embodied cognition.</item>
                    <item>Technologies have an effect on their users, they are DOMESTICATING. <ptr
                            target="#hayler2015" loc="71"/></item>
                </list>
                <p>Through the above criteria, <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">dance,
                        language, the use of fire</quote> and even <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#hayler2015">analytic thought</quote>
                    <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="109"/> can be considered technological forms.
                    Hayler’s argument, as becomes clear in his later use of Object Oriented Ontology
                    (OOO), subscribes to a flat ontology. In doing so, techniques and objects can
                    exist on equal grounds as forms of technology. Therefore techniques such as
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">writing, driving,
                        computing</quote> can be seen as technologies in the same way as <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">its accompanying device (pen, car,
                        computer)</quote>
                    <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="109"/>. This allows us to escape from a hierarchy
                    of natural vs. artificial or artefact vs. technique. Using this definition,
                    Hayler forces us to pay more attention to context and histories of practice
                    rather than on material distinctions. Applying such a definition to examples can
                    then help us as readers continue to ask what we mean by the word
                        <q>technology</q>. It is often the most jarring examples that lead to the
                    most productive considerations, moments when Hayler’s definition leads to
                    results that oppose our <q>common sense</q> definitions.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Three: How Do Experts See Things Differently?</head>
                <p>Hayler now moves from his definition of technology to deal specifically with
                    expertise: how the same object can be different to two separate people.
                    Significantly, Hayler wants to portray the interplay between humans and
                    artefacts as distinctly dialogical: he states that artefacts <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">are both objects and shapers of
                        cognition and perception, [and] they are both moulded in and come to mould
                        our minds</quote>
                    <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="119"/>. For Hayler, objects direct our cognition
                    in various ways whilst at the same time our cognition constrains how those
                    objects exist to us. A main part of Hayler’s assertion is that however I might
                    think about an object and whatever my skill or disposition, there is always a
                    real version of that object that I will never fully understand. In doing so,
                    Hayler draws on Edmund Husserl and Maurice Merleau-Ponty’s phenomenological
                    approach to argue that we can draw closer to an artefact, but that this process
                    will never be complete: <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">some element
                        must always escape our comprehension</quote>
                    <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="119"/>. Part of this approach appears to develop
                    within a wider <emph>posthumanist</emph> context: it is hubris to think that a
                    master carpenter fully comprehends every part of the wood and tools she uses. At
                    the very most, the carpenter might understand the grain, flexibilities, and
                    resistances of the wood better than any other human. Even at this stage the
                    carpenter will never grasp the wood as it <emph>really</emph> is. A bacterium,
                    woodworm, or bird will all understand the same wood in ways the carpenter cannot
                    even comprehend. But it is not simply enough to add up all these various
                    interactions the wood might have and draw up a holistic description of the wood
                    that takes all these perspectives into account. For Hayler, the essence of an
                    object will always retreat and can never be fully comprehended. In this context
                    Hayler uses the term <emph>gestalt</emph> to describe how we make composites of
                    separate instances of interactions. The more we think we know about an artefact
                    the more fixed our gestalt becomes. These gestalts are simplifications of
                    artefacts: when someone becomes an expert at interacting with certain objects
                    they are reducing its essence to how it relates to them and their specific task.
                    When we fail at a task it is often because our gestalt does not match the actual
                    nature of the objects at hand. Our expert carpenter is surprised less often by
                    their wood and tools in comparison to an amateur, for whom the saw jars and
                    stutters rather than flowing gracefully. Here we might describe their skill as a
                    developed gestalt; the carpenter is not surprised because they have simplified
                    the wood to a certain set of characteristics within a particular context.</p>
                <p>Placing this back into a phenomenological context, Hayler uses the term
                        <emph>sensual object</emph> to distinguish the personal and incomplete
                    object that the carpenter encounters from the real object of the wood that
                    cannot be fully encountered. It is, in fact, during a skillful sawing action
                    that the wood and tools hide away from the carpenter: a distinction of
                    ready-to-hand that Hayler borrows from Heidegger. Hayler anchors this idea to
                    the theory of metaphor presented by George Lakoff and Mark Johnson in <title
                        rend="italic">Metaphors We Live By</title>. In essence, we navigate the
                    world using metaphors at a fundamental level, and to Hayler, when we turn from
                    one artefact to another we often attempt to treat the latter as the former. This
                    is why many struggle with, for example, e-reading. We bring our gestalt, our
                    experiences and expertise from physical codex reading to bear on an artefact
                    that is not the same. It is not that we understood the essence of books or that
                    we fail to grasp the essence of a Kindle, but that trying to metaphorically
                    treat e-readers as new types of paperbacks results in a mismatch. We must avoid
                    being constrained by old metaphors, in language and in practice. But what is
                    expertise anyway? How much knowledge of an artefact is possible? Although, as
                    stated earlier, Hayler argues we cannot fully understand an object, there is a
                    relationship between the user’s gestalt and object itself. He argues that: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#hayler2015">True expertise must be about
                            experiencing things as closely as possible as what-they-are, not in
                            terms of some other thing; the reliance on metaphor will keep us as
                            amateurs unable to see the true affordances of the artefact that we are
                            working with.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="139"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Here Hayler borrows the term <emph>affordances</emph> from psychologist James
                    Gibson. The term describes the opportunities or potentials for particular
                    actions with an object. For example: a handle affords turning whereas a cord
                    affords pulling. An expert therefore is someone whose expectations align in some
                    way with the true affordances of an artefact. Hayler argues that <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">affordances are real qualities of
                        sensual objects</quote>
                    <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="145 footnote 24"/>. What intrigues me is what
                    happens when certain sets of affordances that overlap are in conflict. To take
                    an example, we can say that a bench affords sitting: it is smooth, horizontal,
                    and free from traffic. We could also say that the same bench affords skateboard
                    grinds. The affordances are, in fact, very similar. However, the more
                    skateboarders grind on the bench, the less it affords sitting; the surface
                    becomes worn and uncomfortable. To Hayler, affordances are part of sensual
                    objects (created through our interaction) rather than the object on its own
                    terms. However, at what point does the wear from the grinds change the essence
                    of the bench into something new, or is it still a version of its original form.
                    If we are to agree that the bench is now a new bench (i.e. only good for grinds
                    and not for sitting) the distinction of its <emph>real</emph> essence becomes
                    subjective (or at least based around the sensual object of the skateboarder). At
                    its core it seems that Hayler’s definition of technology is an attempt to avoid
                    this kind of thinking and to eschew subjectivity.</p>
                <p>A similar query arises later in the book when Hayler sets out the theoretical
                    basis for his ontology of objects: on the one hand we have Actor Network Theory
                    (ANT), Bruno Latour, and Peter-Paul Verbeek, and on the other we have Graham
                    Harman and Object Oriented Ontology. Each has an influence on Hayler’s argument
                    but there is an issue where ontologically he must take sides: which is more
                    primary, entities or relations? Hayler states that: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#hayler2015">the postphenomenology that I’m
                            interested in <emph>does not</emph> find its foundation in relations
                            [...] for me, the foundation for this entanglement is actually a radical
                                <emph>division</emph> [...] Verbeek, as Latour, accepts that
                            relations do not produce entities out of nowhere, but claims that those
                            entities do not function as actants with essential properties until they
                            enter relations which structure what they are as actants. I want to
                            emphasise the importance of all actants before they interact, what they
                            both bring to and withhold from the table.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="162"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Hayler’s ontology is based around real objects that consistently surprise us and
                    evade our full understanding. My trepidation however, is that treating entities
                    as having essences prior to any relations might bias these essences as singular.
                    This choice relates back to the overlapping affordances of skateboards and
                    benches. If we want to claim there is a <q>real hammer</q> that precedes its
                    interactions with the world, then to me, this singularity can only ever be based
                    on <emph>our</emph> (human) version of events. Therefore, I side with the ANT
                    version of events, which places relations at the foundation of its ontology.</p>
                <p>Hayler marks out these two positions (OOO vs. ANT) as incompatible. However, I
                    believe there are some significant ways in which an ANT approach is compatible
                    with many of Hayler’s conclusions. In fact I think an ANT reading of Hayler’s
                    perspective enlarges its scope and that switching between these two viewpoints
                    can be productive. I will therefore, in addition to outlining Hayler’s OOO
                    approach, try and reconcile these perspectives, or at least demonstrate how it
                    might not be necessary to adopt either exclusively, in the context of the book’s
                    conclusions.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Four: Technology as Embodied Knowledge</head>
                <p>The final two sections of <title rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of
                        Technology</title> attach Hayler’s earlier arguments about technology to a
                    pragmatist perspective of knowledge. The argument is that objects are
                    embodiments of knowledge. That is, knowledge is defined as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">any stored data that enables
                            repeatable and successful action within an environment</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="164"/>
                    </cit>. This knowledge lies outside of a human correlationism: it is not simply
                    born out of our relations (what Hayler calls the sensual object or human
                    gestalts) but belongs to <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">things themselves [...] it’s the
                            real things that know</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="155"/>
                    </cit>. Drawing on OOO, Hayler argues that all objects have a realness that
                    cannot be fully satisfied through interactions with either humans or other
                    objects. As elaborated above, when I interact with a saw I will never fully
                    grasp its essence, only what is important to me at that time: what becomes my
                    sensual gestalt. The same is true of object-to-object relations; when rainfall
                    encounters a gorge there is an encounter that exchanges information and changes
                    the form of both the rain and the rock. However, the rock has not encountered
                    the essence of the rain and neither has the water encountered the essence of the
                    gorge. Both entities have encountered only the qualities relevant to them in
                    that particular encounter. OOO allows Hayler to argue that nonhuman entities can
                    interact with other nonhuman entities in a variety of ways that involve
                    knowledge, without needing to affirm cognition upon rocks and rain. As Hayler
                    writes: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">no two objects ever meet each
                            other as they are, but only as they appear to one another</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="178"/>
                    </cit>. Hammers and nails have knowledge of one another, but only as they relate
                    to their own actions. Again, knowledge, as Hayler uses the term, is not about
                    hammers having thoughts and feelings but about objects comprising <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">any stored data that enables
                            repeatable and successful action within an environment</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="164"/>
                    </cit>. Therefore, the flat top edge of a nail constitutes a kind of knowledge
                    about hammers, or at least enacted data that enables hammers and nails to
                    interact.</p>
                <p>Although Hayler agrees with the OOO perspective that we cannot know the real
                    essence of an object, he diverges from Harman (and other OOO proponents) in that
                    he believes we can align our sensual objects (our encounter of an object) closer
                    to the real object through experience and expertise. Therefore, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">the way that all objects encounter
                            other objects, <emph>can</emph> include a potentially asymptomatic
                            approach, through this needn’t imply direct access</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="189"/>
                    </cit>, where asymptomatic refers to a curve on a graph that gets increasingly
                    closer to a value but never reaches it. In this way Hayler places the emphasis
                    on expertise: objects always escape us but that does not stop experts from
                    aligning their sensual objects close to the real thing. This would account for
                    the successful action of experts. By my understanding this does not just refer
                    to experienced craftspeople but also, due to the posthumanist position of OOO,
                    the repeated erosion of a gorge by a regular pattern of rainfall. The rain does
                    not grasp the essence of the rock but perhaps the action of erosion constitutes
                    knowledge in Hayler’s pragmatic outlook of repeatable and successful action.
                    This brings us to why, even though as stated above I side more with an ANT
                    approach at possible odds with Hayler’s project that prioritises relations over
                    entities, I think the conclusions of <title rend="italic">Challenging the
                        Phenomena of Technology</title> still hold true for this alternative
                    outlook. Hayler’s position is open to an outlook that prioritises process. I
                    believe that even if we prioritise relations over entities, much of Hayler’s
                    argument is still persuasive, particularly in the context of distributed
                    knowledge: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#hayler2015">The expert’s knowledge of, for
                            instance, hammering is partly formed of data inside her brain, but the
                            relevant data is also in the hand and the arm that operate the tool, in
                            the tool itself and its feedback, and in the act of hammering with
                                <emph>this</emph> hammer in <emph>this </emph>moment in
                                <emph>this</emph> milieu [...] experience always prompts new data to
                            draw on, and this tends to strengthen the coherence of sensual gestalt
                            and real object. Such data is always dispersed across the contextualised
                            4EDS [the umbrella term Hayler uses for cognition which is distributed,
                            extended, embedded, or embodied] soft-assemblage – it is the
                                <emph>technical encounter</emph> that knows best, not just an expert
                            human brain</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="194"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Hayler stresses the changing and individual nature of objects. His emphasis of <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015"><emph>this</emph> hammer in
                                <emph>this</emph> moment in <emph>this</emph> milieu</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="194"/>
                    </cit> asks us to see technological interactions of objects as specific
                    interactions that generalised critiques of <q>technology</q> overlook. Hayler’s
                    structuring of interactions as a coherence of real objects and sensual gestalts
                    helps us understand objects as mysterious and mostly hidden to everything with
                    which they interact. To me however, placing the emphasis on specific encounters
                    that are unique to a particular context where <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">it is the <emph>technical
                                encounter</emph> that knows best</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="194"/>
                    </cit> prioritises the system rather than individual entities. That we might
                    only be able to engage with the sensual objects part of that assemblage explains
                    why systems can behave in such unexpected ways. Perhaps the fact that the
                    knowledge is held in the interaction of these unknowable objects owes credit to
                    Hayler’s argument that each object has a real essence outside of its relations:
                    we cannot fully know the system of interactions because we cannot fully
                    understand the objects at play. Perhaps we might even want to argue that
                        <emph>relations</emph> can be described with Hayler’s language of real and
                    sensual objects, aligning gestalts of knowledge, just as productively as
                        <emph>entities</emph>. Perhaps such a reading would not lead to an orthodox
                    ANT approach, and instead simply lead Hayler’s method away from Harman and
                    towards a kind of thinking similar to Jane Bennett’s vital materialism <ptr
                        target="#bennett2010"/>.</p>
                <p>Whichever way one reads it the conclusion is exciting. The first reading, which
                    supports Hayler’s insistence that entities come first, is useful in various
                    dynamic contexts. An alternative model, which incorporates an ANT or process
                    disposition into Hayler’s OOO-inspired conclusions, also yields interesting
                    results, one that challenges the distinction between entities and relations.
                    This ambiguity sets the stage for the final argument of <title rend="italic"
                        >Challenging the Phenomena of Technology</title> that I believe is
                    convincing either on its own terms or through an ANT perspective.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Five: The Evolution of Technology</head>
                <p>Hayler’s final section develops his pragmatic distinction of knowledge as
                    embodied in objects by arguing that this knowledge is subject to evolutionary
                    pressures. Hayler traces the roots of this evolutionary epistemology and
                    outlines the modes of thought necessary to treat artefacts as subject to the
                    evolutionary pressures of <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015"><emph>variation</emph> (due to
                            mutation), <emph>selection</emph> (due to pressures from the
                            environment), and <emph>reproduction</emph> (due to an individual’s
                            success)</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="211"/>
                    </cit>. Using the example of the codex, Hayler argues that books are subject to
                        <emph>variation</emph> (for example, mutations such as oversize atlases and
                    pocket editions), <emph>selection</emph> (through pressures of the marketplace),
                    and <emph>reproduction</emph> (by reprinting successful books and more generally
                    the stabilisation of publishing norms). In this way we can treat the range of
                    possible books as the gene pool and the variety of codices that continue to be
                    printed as the phenotypic expression of that gene pool. The books themselves do
                    not have any agency; they are not trying to survive. However, the environment
                    (in this case humans) is shaping their existence through reproduction of forms
                    that are the best <q>fit</q> with that environment. As Hayler expresses it,
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">evolution is all about
                        repeatable successful action</quote>
                    <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="215"/> which we should remember is his definition
                    of knowledge in a nonhuman context <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="164"/>. The
                    distinction Hayler makes between gene pools and offspring as a partial product
                    of that gene pool is quite persuasive in the context of objects having a real
                    but unknowable essence. I think it is more than metaphorical to say that in this
                    context the unexpected nature of epigenetics can echo very well the unexpected
                    ways in which objects can change and react in new contexts, while retaining a
                    concrete, or at least traceable, identity.</p>
                <p>To project this version of artefacts as embodiments of knowledge developed
                    through evolutionary pressures into a truly nonhuman context, Hayler draws on
                    the work of Henry Plotkin. In <title rend="italic">Darwin Machines and the
                        Nature of Knowledge</title>, Plotkin uses stick insects as an example of
                    embodied knowledge. The body of the stick insect, unbeknownst to the insect,
                    embodies knowledge of its surroundings. Hayler argues, through Plotkin, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">the stick insect’s body therefore
                            possesses knowledge of an aspect of the world far greater than its own
                            mind is capable of</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="217"/>
                    </cit>. Placing this in an OOO context, Hayler argues that even though it seems
                    like the body of the insect has knowledge of the plants it lives in, it is only
                    ever a partial knowledge. The body of the insect (or the species as a whole) has
                    knowledge that only relates to the way its predators' eyes function: the rest of
                    the environment recedes. Nor does the knowledge held in the environment fully
                    satisfy the stick insect’s existence, which is a benefit of an OOO outlook. We
                    must be sympathetic to the depths that we will never understand; we cannot
                    simply use descriptive characteristics about the insect or environment to claim
                    that we fully understand them. The knowledge that humans, branches, or a stick
                    insect’s body hold is never exhaustive. To Hayler, knowledge only ever concerns
                    sensual gestalts. This then allows a way of seeing a whole host of individuals,
                    animals, objects, artefacts, and technologies as <q>knowing</q> about the world
                    around them while maintaining their ability to surprise and be surprised by
                    interactions. This also brings us back to one of the opening examples of <title
                        rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of Technology</title>: what is going
                    on when people reject Kindles, even if they <q>work</q> just as well as a codex?
                    Knowing Hayler’s argument, we can say that the evolution of the codex reflects a
                    hard-won journey and one that embodies a vast amount of knowledge concerning
                    reading practices and our relationship with the written word. Disconnected from
                    this history, e-readers have a different (and more recent) set of affordances
                    and characteristics. Kindles have had less time to adapt and reflect their
                    environment and therefore our sensual gestalt does not align with the real
                    essence of the artefact. Nor does the knowledge embodied in the Kindle
                    adequately reflect its users. Hayler argues that we do not <emph>know</emph>
                    e-readers yet, but also, in equal measure, that e-readers are yet to know us
                    well enough either. Hayler articulates that: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#hayler2015">We may feel uncomfortable with the
                            idea that codices possess knowledge rather than simply store it, but
                            this only reflects a prejudice surrounding the use of the word
                                <q>knowledge</q> as a narrow band of human experience, rather than
                            seeing that band as a subset of something that we share with the world
                            that we have emerged from and remain in complex concert with.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="225"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>This posthumanist stance allows human beings to be humble towards the world, and
                    in particular towards technology. I also think that this conclusion, although
                    developed out of an engagement with OOO, does not require us to reject models
                    that place interactions before entities. Much of what Hayler describes as
                        <q>knowledge</q> develops through interactions. To my mind, although many of
                    these leave traces (the shape of an insect’s body), there are also types of
                    knowledge that emerge and dissipate without leaving a permanent trace. Read in a
                    digital context, in which more of our world is governed algorithmically, I think
                    there are countless times in which rapid change is the norm, rather than stable
                    entities. Increasingly our interactions with technology rely on knowledge as
                        <emph>emergent</emph> successful actions rather than <emph>repeatable</emph>
                    ones. If we read Hayler’s conclusions concerning situated knowledge in this
                    context I think the results are very productive.</p>
                <p>Throughout my reading of <title rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of
                        Technology</title> I frequently tried to apply Hayler’s method to various
                    examples. In particular I kept relating Hayler’s model to my own research: that
                    of web search engines. I found this a particularly interesting test case,
                    particularly as it fits Hayler's criteria of a technology. Using Google
                    regularly extends my ability to accomplish tasks, functions through community,
                    is incorporated into my cognition, and domesticates me in various ways. I can
                    also divide Google along the lines of sensual vs. real object. I have knowledge
                    of a sensual gestalt (the data, links, and ranking that takes place) but not the
                    real essence of the process. Everything so far works with Hayler’s definition.
                    The trouble is, Google is in no way a singular or static object. Google is all
                    the varied contexts in which vast datasets are used, the engineers employed, and
                    the vast network of users that change the ranking through daily use. Google
                    search is less like a single technology and more like a coordinated emergent
                    response from a number of different elements that cannot be fully predicted.
                    Google search results are localised and personalised to each user, their ranking
                    reassessed with every query, and they are organised through sets of algorithms
                    that are altered and revised constantly.<note> For more detail, see Steven Levy,
                            <title rend="italic">In The Plex: How Google Thinks, Works and Shapes
                            Our Lives</title> (p. 61) in which he interviews engineering staff at
                        Google about the process of constantly altering algorithms.</note> Even the
                    engineers are not fully in control as the searches and other usages create
                    patterns measured by potentialities rather than firm predictions. The way this
                    network changes can, I think, be described and elaborated using Hayler’s
                    framework very usefully. However, its usefulness lies in the ways it describes
                    processes rather than specific objects. Considering search engines, where can we
                    draw the boundaries around the technology? Is each algorithm a separate and
                    interlocking technology; each engineer, each user? Results change
                    second-by-second in a way that I think differs from the evolution of codices in
                    more than simply speed. Any set of criteria that draws boundaries too firmly
                    around objects is going to misrepresent this kind of technological mode that is
                    becoming increasingly ubiquitous. This is why I think Hayler’s conclusions are
                    valuable beyond a commitment to the OOO project. Because of the evolutionary
                    context, knowledge is described as dynamic and emergent, as Hayler puts it: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#hayler2015">all things never meet one another
                            as they are, always reducing and approximating, always escaping and
                            surprising one another</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hayler2015" loc="231"/>
                    </cit>. In doing so Hayler’s definition works both for <q>traditional</q>
                    technologies or ones which might seem to demonstrate a more stable sense of
                    identity, <emph>and</emph> newer technological modes or systems that seem harder
                    to define. What if we were to describe <emph>relations</emph> in terms of
                    sensual and real objects? What if we argue that an algorithm has a sensual
                    gestalt of a particular dataflow; a dataflow that is obviously real but, due to
                    its speed and the colossal number of contexts in which it becomes meaningful,
                    can only ever be considered through partial knowledge? Perhaps Hayler would see
                    such attempts as a misappropriation of his method, but regardless, the kind of
                    model he presents allows for new ways of theorising complex technological
                    issues. Not only does <title rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of
                        Technology</title> allow us to conceptualise technology in a more nuanced
                    manner but it does so by incorporating usage and context. As Hayler argues in
                    his conclusion: <quote rend="block" source="#hayler2015">whilst we may catch an
                        object’s whatness in glimpses through coherence, all that we can truly rely
                        on remains the equipment’s ‘thatness,’ not what makes it what it is, but
                        simply that it exists to us at this moment as this thing <ptr
                            target="#hayler2015" loc="233"/></quote></p>
                <p>Hayler’s method allows him to capture traditional attitudes towards technology
                    whilst incorporating a temporal and contextual attitude that is key to our
                    emerging digital landscape. In doing so, <title rend="italic">Challenging the
                        Phenomena of Technology</title> excels at historicising our technological
                    circumstances and is convincing in its argument that redefining our contemporary
                    definition of technology is important not only for scholarship but for
                    navigating the world.</p>
                <p><title rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of Technology</title> is most
                    successful in its sensitivity to context and in surveying a number of crucial
                    questions that various disparate disciplines are addressing from different
                    angles. Hayler provides us not only with a specific set of proposals concerning
                    technology, but with an outline of some of the most pressing contemporary
                    debates and arguments being put forward in a variety of research areas. <title
                        rend="italic">Challenging the Phenomena of Technology</title> is important
                    reading for those in the humanities, cognitive sciences, philosophy, and digital
                    humanities. It is of particular importance for those researchers wanting an
                    exemplary account of how to tackle interdisciplinary concerns, and how to
                    address them sensitively by putting forward arguments that will provoke a wide
                    range of stimulating and productive responses.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl label="Bennett 2010" xml:id="bennett2010">Bennett, Jane. <title rend="italic"
                        >Vibrant Matter: A Political Ecology of Things</title>. Durham, North
                    Carolina: Duke University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Fox 2002" xml:id="fox2002"> Fox, Nicols. <title rend="italic">Against
                        the Machine: The Hidden Luddite Tradition in Literature, Art, and Individual
                        Lives</title>. Washington, D.C.: Island Press, 2002.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Hayler 2015" xml:id="hayler2015"> Hayler, Matt. <title rend="italic"
                        >Challenging the Phenomena of Technology: Embodiment, Expertise and Evolved
                        Knowledge</title>. Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2015. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Jones 2006" xml:id="jones2006"> Jones, Steven E. <title rend="italic"
                        >Against Technology: From the Luddites to Neo-Luddism</title>. New York:
                    Routledge, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Levy 2011" xml:id="levy2011"> Levy, Steven. <title rend="italic">In The
                        Plex: How Google Thinks, Works and Shapes Our Lives</title>. New York: Simon
                    &amp; Schuster.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
