<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
	xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
	xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
	xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
				<title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Underlying
					Sentiments in 1867: A Study of News Flows on the Execution of Emperor
					Maximilian I of Mexico in Digitized Newspaper Corpora</title>
				<!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Adán Israel <dhq:family>Lerma Mayer</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID"
						><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>Universidad Anáhuac</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>adan.lermama@anahuac.mx</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Adan Lerma-Mayer is a professor ofLiterature and Digital Media at Universidad Anáhuac. His research interests include dialogical relationships in digital spaces and Digital Communication.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Ximena <dhq:family>Gutierrez-Vasques</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID"
						><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>University of Zurich</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>ximena.gutierrezv@gmail.com</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Ximena Gutierrez-Vasques is a computational linguist, currently a postdoctoral researcher at the University of Zürich, URPP Language and Space. Her interdisciplinary research interests cover computational methods to deepen the study of natural languages. She currently works on approaches for measuring linguistic complexity (at the morphological level) using text corpora and is inspired by information theory.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Ernesto <dhq:family>Priani Saiso</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID"
						><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>epriani@gmail.com</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Ernesto Priani Saisó is Professor of Philosophy at the Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México. His research interests include medieval and renaissance philosophy, and Digital Humanities.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
					<dhq:author_name>Hannu <dhq:family>Salmi</dhq:family>
					</dhq:author_name>
					<idno type="ORCID"
						><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
					<dhq:affiliation>University of Turku</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>hansalmi@utu.fi</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Hannu Salmi is Professor of Cultural History at the University of Turku in Finland. His research interests include digital history, history of the nineteenth century, and media history. </p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
				<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
				<!--This information will be completed at publication-->
				<idno type="DHQarticle-id"
					><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000649</idno>
				<idno type="volume"
					><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
				<idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->4</idno>
				<date when="2022-09-16">16 September 2022</date>
				<dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
				<availability status="CC-BY-ND">
					<!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
					<cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>This is the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
					<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en" extent="original"/>
				<!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
					<!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
					<!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
			<change/>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en" type="original">
		<front>
			<dhq:abstract>
				<!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
				<p>This article focuses on the international news flow regarding the execution of
					Maximilian, the Emperor of Mexico. The execution occurred in June 1867, but it
					received global attention only at the beginning of July when the news started to
					spread over the borders, via telegraph, and rapidly through the network of
					newspapers. The article concentrates on international news on Maximilian's
					execution between 5 and 20 July 1867. The aim of the study is both empirical and
					methodological. It explores the sentiments underlying the news about the
					execution and the regional differences in these sentiments on an empirical
					level. On a methodological level, the article investigates the strategies to
					analyze sentiments via newspaper corpora in a multilingual research setting. The
					study is based on optically recognized historical newspapers in three languages
					(German, Spanish and English), and four regions (Austria, Germany, Mexico, and
					the United States). Our analysis shows content variations in the corpora, mainly
					that news was framed differently in each studied region, indicating that the
					local perception of the event and political interests shaped the news. In our
					corpus, the Mexican press –published in the middle of a political crisis– tended
					towards a neutral stance, the Austrian and German papers mainly were negative,
					and the United States showed mixed sentiments on the incident.</p>
			</dhq:abstract>
			<dhq:teaser>
				<!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
				<p/>
			</dhq:teaser>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div>
			<head>Introduction</head>
			<p>The execution of Maximillian, Emperor of Mexico, by the army of Benito Juarez in
				1867 had international ramifications, and the world became polarized. The press
				around the globe reported it and rallied the population in favor or against the
				event. In this analysis, we explore the underlying sentiments and emotions
				embedded in the texts that circulated inthe press, as a case study of the
				project Oceanic Exchanges, whose aim was to uncover how the international was
				refracted through the local as news, applying text mining methods to a corpus of
				national digitized nineteenth-century newspapers. </p>
			<p> Our hypothesis is that regional emotional content variations of news reveal the
				political undertones and biases of information flows. The latter aspect is
				fostered by the fact that the execution of Maximilian was, from the outset, an
				incident that divided opinions.</p>
			<p>To that goal, we put together a corpus that includes digitized newspapers from
				different regions in North America and Europe, encompassing material from the
				actual arena of the execution, Mexico, from the country of Maximilian's
				ancestry, Austria as well as from the US and Germany<note> It should be noted
					that in the 1860s, there was no Germany in the present understanding but
					independent states that formed the German Confederation. In 1867, the New
					German Confederation was born under the Prussian leadership, excluding
					Bavaria, Württemberg, Baden, and Hesse-Darmstadt (that joined the
					Confederation again in 1870). Austria, in turn, was a multilingual,
					multiethnic empire that reached many present-day areas, for example,
					Northern Italy, Slovenia, and Romania. We have used the expressions
					'German' and 'Austrian region' to cover German-language papers from these
					areas. </note> that covered the news abundantly <ptr target="#priani2019"/>.
				After dividing the corpus into geographical regions, we use quantitative methods
				–word frequency distributions and named entity recognition (NER)–to first look
				at the corpus. Then, using qualitative content analysis, we narrowed the
				information to compare the different regions. Finally, using automated sentiment
				analysis tools, we were able to compare the automatic analysis to the human one,
				showing a similar and clear sentimental trend in both methods depending on the
				geographical region: the Austrian/German press had a negative bias, while the
				Mexican newspapers showed a more positive picture, and the US showed mixed
				sentiments. </p>
			<p>The case of Maximilian is particularly illuminating from the perspective of global
				news flows since it happened soon after the inauguration of the transatlantic
				cable in a country that was fighting a civil war between liberals and
				conservatives. The execution news tells a story of control and manipulation over
				the flow of news and, at the same time, a story that could be wired and rapidly
				forwarded over the Atlantic.</p></div>
			<div>
			<head>Historical background</head>
			<p>In 1860, Mexico was broken. The War of Independence (1810) bankrupted the country
				and fuelled endless confrontations between liberals and conservatives, who came
				and went in the presidency during the century. </p>
			<p>Benito Juarez's introduction of the Reform Laws between 1855 and 1859 separated
				the Church from the State, suppressed military and religious tribunals, declared
				the nationalization of church properties, and introduced free press and civil
				registration, deepening the struggle between these political groups. In 1861,
				Benito Juárez, a liberal, was reelected to the presidency. With minimal
				financial resources, he decided to suspend the payment of debts and interests to
				Britain, Spain, and France.</p>
			<p>According to Josefina Zoraida Vázquez (<ref target="#vazquez2007">2007</ref>), monarchists and conservatives living
				in Europe took advantage of this decision and proposed to Napoleon III the
				establishment of a Mexican monarchy. The idea that an Emperor could put an end
				to the turmoil was extensive among Mexican liberals and conservatives, as Duncan
				(<ref target="#duncan1996">1996</ref>) has pointed out, and with that support, the emperor of France saw the
				opportunity to extend his influence over America and stop the growing power of
				the United States. </p>
			<p>On October 31, 1861, summoned by France, the three countries signed a treaty to
				block Mexico's ports on the Gulf of Mexico to pressure payment of the debt.
				After negotiations, Britain and Spain accepted new terms, but France refused and
				decided to invade Mexico. </p>
			<p>After a year of confrontations, the invaders took the capital. Juárez's government
				was exiled but continued a guerrilla-style confrontation all over the country.
				Two years later, on April 10, 1864, Maximilian of Habsburg –brother of the
				Austrian emperor Franz Joseph I and married to Charlotte of Belgium, daughter of
				King Leopold–, accepted the Mexican throne and traveled to the country.</p>
			<p>In the last months of 1865, circumstances changed. The end of the Civil War in the
				United States opened the doors to new credits to Juárez, which helped fortify
				his army. At the same time, the French army abandoned Mexico, and the Maximilian
				government went bankrupt and started losing battles and territory.</p>
			<p>In May 1867, Maximilian was captured –along with commanders Miguel Miramón and
				Tomás Mejía– by the Republican Army Commanded by Mariano Escobedo in the City of
				Querétaro in central México. Juárez and his Foreign Affairs secretary, Sebastian
				Lerdo de Tejada, resisted international pressure to exile Maximilian back to
				Europe in the following month. After a short trial, on June 19, 1867, Maximilian
				was executed at the Cerro de las Campanas, Querétaro, along with the last
				remaining commanders of the conservative army (Vanderwood 2010, 367-8). This
				execution resulted in an abundant flow of news analyzed in this article. </p></div>
			<div>
			<head>Corpora description </head>
			<p>Our corpus<note> For a complete access to our corpus as a CVS file see <ref
						target="https://zenodo.org/record/3451482"
				>https://zenodo.org/record/3451482</ref> <ptr target="#priani2019"/>.
					All newspaper titles, dates, news items and cities can be consulted
					there.</note> was obtained by searching <q>Maximilian</q> and <q>Death</q> in
				digitized European, Mexican, and United States newspaper collections (on the
				nature of these collections, see <ptr target="#beals2020"/>). The US papers
				originated from Chronicling America, maintained by the Library of Congress, the
				Mexican papers from Hemeroteca Nacional Digital de México. For the
				German-language press, we drew on the Europeana dataset, which includes
				newspapers from Germany (Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Hamburg State Library and
				Teßmann Library) and Austria (Österreichische Nationalbibliothek). In order to
				work with the German-language corpus, we automatically extracted the newspapers'
				publication city and further divided the corpus into two regional categories:
				German and Austrian, resulting in a final corpus of 1,382 news stories published
				between the 5th and 20th of July 1867. Although Maximilian's execution took
				place two weeks earlier, on June 19, 1867, the news did not break until later
				because of the control of the Juarez's army over the telegram around Queretaro
				and the flow of the news from there <ptr target="#mendezmoreno1967"/>. </p>
			<p>Neither the size of the corpora nor the OCR (Optical Character Recognition)
				quality was the same for all subcorpora. Cultural, political, and economic
				differences in each region affected the number of newspapers circulating. Mexico
				was going through a political crisis, and there was much control over the press.
				On the contrary, the United States had a lot of local newspapers. These
				differences result in an imbalance in news coverage, and therefore in the
				regional corpora. The US news occupies as much as 53.1% of the news coverage in
				the whole dataset. The proportion of the Austrian subcorpus is 12.6%, the German
				one 32.5 % and the Mexican one only 1.8 %.</p>
			<p>In addition to the imbalance of digitized contents, another common obstacle is the
				quality of the original OCR from each newspaper library (on the problem of OCR
				noise, see <ptr target="#jarlbrink2017"/>). Each nation establishes its
				newspaper digitization methodology, determining the quality and how and what can
				be extracted from each source. The OCR processes have been different, including
				the scanning practices and OCR software and the quality of the original
				newspapers, the objects of scanning. In most cases, the scanning has been done
				from microfilm, not from paper, and the original typeset, characters, and font
				sizes cause variation in the quality of OCR.</p>
			<p>As a part of the Oceanic Exchanges Project, we decided to work with the OCR from
				each library without cleaning it. According to Beals and Bell (<ref target="#beals2020">2020</ref>), the
				Oceanic Exchanges corpus OCR quality ranges between 60-85%, but it varies within
				each country's corpora. Nonetheless, as Ryan Cordell pointed out, <quote rend="inline">methods such
				as text mining rely not on the nineteenth-century newspapers themselves, but on
				those newspapers as a remediated by mass digitization, a phrase that shorthands
				elaborate systems of scholarship, preservation, bureaucracy, human labor,
				machine processes, and economics</quote> <ptr target="#cordell2017"/>. </p>
			<p>However, following this path, we faced two challenges: one practical and one
				human. The practical challenge was that the US and Mexican subcorpora had poor
				OCR quality compared to the Austrian and German. The human challenge was that as
				an international team, participants from different countries have different
				scholarship cultures. The Mexican team, for example, was not familiar with
				working with dirty OCR and, because the corpus was not large, decided to
				transcribe all of their news items.</p>
			<p>We decided to work with the Mexican corpus as it was prepared by the Mexican team,
				respecting its work and effort. In the case of the US subcorpus, the automatic
				extraction included everything on the page, and there were no breaks between
				news stories and columns –like in the German and Austrian corpus. The raw data
				included the news item about Maximilian's death and any other news stories on
				the page, making it hard to work with. Since there were thousands of hits, we
				narrowed the information down through an automated process, i.e, filtering
				chunks of surrounding text (windows of words to the right and to the left) were
				<q>Maximilian</q> is mentioned. This eliminated most of the unwanted information,
				although it was a superficial strategy prone to some noise. As we assume
				newspapers are remediated by mass digitization, we also assume that our corpus
				expresses how digital humanities are produced in global teams that must manage
				cultural and technological differences. Finally, Table 1 shows the size of the
				text corpora (in terms of number of words) that we used for our analysis.</p>
			<table>
				<head>Corpora size</head>
				<row role="label">
					<cell>Corpus</cell>
					<cell>Tokens</cell>
					<cell>Types (unique words)</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Austria (German)</cell>
					<cell>154012</cell>
					<cell>25590</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Germany (German)</cell>
					<cell>68763</cell>
					<cell>14495</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Mexico (Spanish)</cell>
					<cell>20673</cell>
					<cell>4022</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>US (English)</cell>
					<cell>273115</cell>
					<cell>33773</cell>
				</row>
			</table> 
			</div>
			<div>
			<head>Methodology </head>
			<p>We employed several methodologies to study the sentiments and emotions in news
				stories that circulated in the press after the execution of Maximilian I, the
				Mexican emperor. First, we used existing digital tools that draw on NLP, a
				multidisciplinary field aiming to automatically process large amounts of natural
				language data, and we performed qualitative analysis of the automatically
				extracted named entities (discussed below). After this process, we analyzed the
				emotional contents of the corpora by drawing on such automatic NLP tools. In
				recent years, sentiment analysis has been applied to extensive collections of
				news, online product reviews, and other types of corpora. However, little
				attention has been paid to historical news documents <ptr target="#sprugnoli2016"/>.
				Few works have applied sentiment analysis to drama plays, literary texts, and
				other types of historical sources <ptr target="#schmidt2018a"/> <ptr target="#schmidt2018b"/> <ptr target="#kim2018"/>.</p>
			<p>In our case, we used automatic tools based on machine learning techniques to
				detect named entities and estimate a text's polarity. Thus, these systems are
				not based on explicit rules for each language; instead, they rely on statistical
				methods trained in large amounts of data. Particularly, we used Google Cloud 
				<ref target="https://cloud.google.com/natural-language">Natural Language API</ref>,
				Python programming and the <ref target="https://www.nltk.org/">NLTK toolkit</ref> to
				pre-process the documents and extract information. </p>
			<p>Our initial point of departure was to extract general statistics to explore the
				word frequency distributions in each subcorpus. This provided a general overview
				of the relevant terms in each region. It is essential to mention that the
				corpora were pre-processed, i.e., we tokenized it and filtered the stopwords
				that do not carry semantic content (prepositions, determiners, conjunctions,
				function words). We then used Named Entity Recognition (NER), Natural Language
				Processing (NLP) technology that automatically identifies words (or sequence of
				words) that belong to specific categories, i.e., abstract or physical entities
				denote proper names. Previously, these tools have been used to analyze
				nineteenth-century newspapers, but never in tandem to study news stories'
				underlying sentiments and emotions. For example, some international projects are
				using NLP to study big data corpora, as well as developing analytical and
				visualization tools, like the Media Monitoring of the Past (2020) and the
				NewsEye (2020) projects, as well as Gale's Digital Scholar Lab (2020), which
				offers several NLP tools for researchers.</p>
			<p>There is a growing body of knowledge about the use of Named Entity Recognition
				(NER) to analyze newspaper collections <ptr target="#neudecker2014"/> <ptr target="#mac2015"/> <ptr target="#kettunen2017"/>. Likewise, there is an interest in
				identifying and making more robust computerized tools for historical newspapers
				analysis <ptr target="#yang2011"/> <ptr target="#ehrmann2020"/>.</p>
			<p>There are several approaches for performing NER tasks. In our case, we
				automatically identified the following entities in the documents: person,
				location, organization, event, consumer good, and others (using Google Cloud
				Natural Language API). We extracted named entities from the subcorpora of
				Austria, Mexico, Germany, USA. Once we automatically identified named entities
				for each subcorpus, we performed a manual selection of entities. This selection
				was based on three criteria: 1) frequency of the entity, 2) the entity appears
				in at least two regions, 3) it has historical significance –understood as it
				references an important event, person, location, or organization in the shooting
				of Maximilian. </p>
			<p>We identified the reduced set as "entities of interest." It was helpful to make a
				contrastive analysis across subcorpora, i.e., the different approaches to
				specific events, persons, locations, or organizations., depending on the
				country.</p>
			<p>To facilitate the analysis of these entities of interest, we extracted contexts
				for each entity in the text. We defined context as a window of 20 words to the
				left and the right of each entity (fixed size), as seen in Table 2. Moreover, we
				extracted a list of words that appear in similar contexts to each entity of
				interest using NLP techniques and the NLTK toolkit. Then, Google Translate API
				was used to automatically translate the extracted contexts into English. Since
				we were a multilingual team and we worked with a corpus in several languages, we
				chose English as the lingua franca to communicate and work. Early on, we decided
				to translate all the news stories into English, adding certain complications to
				the analysis, which were controlled but never entirely eliminated.</p>
			<table>
				<head>An example of an named entity of interest (“execution”) in the Mexican
					subcorpus</head>
				<row role="label">
					<cell>City/Region</cell>
					<cell>Newspaper</cell>
					<cell>Date</cell>
					<cell>Original Context</cell>
					<cell>Translated Context</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Ciudad de México, México</cell>
					<cell>Monitor Republicano</cell>
					<cell>05 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>e militar y cumplido el plazo , fueron sacados los reos al patíbulo ;
						al llegar al lugar de la ejecución , se contuvo por orden del
						Supremo_Gobierno , que prorrogó el plazo por otros tres días . El
						1</cell>
					<cell>and military and met the deadline, the prisoners were taken to the
						gallows; to get to the place of execution, it was held by order of
						Supremo_Gobierno, which extended the deadline for another three days.
						The 1</cell>
				</row>
			</table> 
			
			<p>Finally, we ran an Automatic Sentiment Analyzer on the news of each corpus.
				Automatic sentiment analysis is the task of identifying and quantifying the
				polarity of an opinion expressed in a written text, e.g., positive or negative.
				This is done employing NLP and text mining techniques <ptr target="#liu2012"/> <ptr target="#feldman2013"/>. </p>
			<p>The automatic sentiment analysis provided a negative, positive or neutral
				sentimental score for the newspaper publications. This allowed us to determine
				if there were underlying differences between regions.Since we are using models
				already trained by Google Cloud Natural Language API, no external dictionaries
				of setiment/polarity words are needed to perform this task.</p>
				<p>We performed a qualitative content analysis <ptr target="#fernandez2002"/> to identify
				attitudes, beliefs, wishes, values, and interest to understand the sentiments
				and emotions underlying the corpus' news stories and identify geographical
				differences. We extracted the textual contexts for the named entities for each
				region. Each entity was analyzed, and main sentiments and emotions were
				pinpointed by identifying words that carried emotional content, such as
				<q>disgust, horror, revulsion</q> for the entity <q>execution.</q> This produced an
				organic identification of sentiment categories in the new stories selected by
				region, which allowed us to compare and contrast, thus understanding how
				Maximilian's death was perceived.</p>
			<p>It is worth mentioning that the used automatic tools are not explicitly adapted to
				specific domains such as historical news documents. However, these statistical
				methods can cope, to some extent, with language variation and diachrony. This
				means that they do not rely on fixed lexicons and rules. Instead, they focus on
				different features of the text to predict how likely it is that a token is a
				maned entity, e.g., the structure of the sentence, distributional semantics of
				the words, and training with millions of examples before. Due to this, our
				methodology does not entirely rely on the automatic tool's output, but it is
				complemented with a fine-grained qualitative analysis. </p></div>
			<div>
			<head>Results</head>
			<p>This section discusses the results obtained using statistical distributions, NER
				tools, content analysis, and automated sentiment analysis<note> The code for
					processing the data and the results can be consulted at
					<ref target="https://github.com/ximenina/OcEx_Maximilian">https://github.com/ximenina/OcEx_Maximilian</ref></note>.</p> 
			
				<figure>
					<head>Word clouds with the most frequent words (translated). Austria (top),
						Mexico (bottom)</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure15.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure12.png"/>
					<figDesc>Two word clouds with blue, green, and purple text. The largest words in the Austria cloud are the works emperor, maximilian, and mexico while the largest words in the mexico cloud are maximiliano and mexico</figDesc>
				</figure>
				
	
			<p>We started by obtaining word frequency distributions for each region. Function
				words were automatically eliminated to work only with content-filled items. Just
				for the sake of illustration, Figure 1 shows word clouds with the most frequent
				words in Austria’s and Mexico’s corpora. </p>
			<p>Going into more detail, Figure 2 displays the relative frequency of the top 10
				most frequent words per region. These plots show which concepts were the most
				used per region: <q>maximilian,</q> <q>emperor,</q> and <q>mexico</q> were at the top of all of
				the regions, of course — followed by items such as <q>government</q> and <q>death.</q>
				Since this is what the news reports were about, they are expected. </p>
			<p>Nonetheless, the ones that are not repeated are also important to our study. For
				example, in Mexico's media, <q>republic,</q> <q>president,</q> and <q>Queretaro</q> –the city
				where Maximilian was apprehended and shot–, stand out, while <q>emperor</q>
				<q>imperial,</q> <q>majesty,</q> and <q>paris</q> <q>france</q> have more preponderance in the
				European press. In other words, this exposes a Eurocentric point of view: for
				the old continent, it was more important to refer to European cities and the
				idea of a Mexican Empire –since this was the power system held over there– while
				to Mexico’s press, Queretaro is an important city to the country, and the
				Republican president had just taken over. </p>
			<p>Given we only show the top 10 words, some terms may appear in every regional media
				but without the same relevance. Some European newspapers did use words like
				<q>republic,</q> but they got ranked lower in frequency. Likewise, terms like
				<q>emperor</q> and <q>empire</q> are not ranked in the top 10 for Mexico's corpus but
				appear in lower frequency ranks, as seen in Figure 2.</p>
			<p>It is important to mention that the plots show relative frequencies to make them
				more easily comparable across corpora, i.e., each word count is divided by the
				total number of words in the current corpus. As mentioned, the data is
				unbalanced from the outset. The US material is abundant while other subcorpora
				are limited.</p> 
			
			
				<figure>
					<head>Word frequency distributions per subcorpora (top 10)</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure19.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure16.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
					<figDesc>Four bar charts with bars in mauve. The first chart is for Mexico, the second is Austria, the third is Germany, and the fourth is USA</figDesc>
				</figure>
			
			
			</div>
			<div>
			<head>Named Entity Recognition Tools</head>
			<p>As we mentioned before, we used NER techniques for a more detailed analysis by
				identifying the significant entities in each subcorpus. Since NER techniques
				enlist all entities in the subcorpora, meaning thousands of results, we decided
				to only focus on the 100 most frequent entities. Figures 3, 4, 5 and 6 in the
				following section show the named entities frequency distribution for each
				region.</p>
			<p> Although we revised the 100 most frequent entities, we only show the 30 most
				frequent entities on the plots for the sake of illustration. For complete
				results, see the repository.</p>
			<p>The range of absolute frequency values is larger in regions like Austria or
				Germany than in Mexico. This is due to the unbalanced nature of the corpora,
				i.e., the sociopolitical factors that impacted the amount of news produced in
				each country. </p>
			<p>The automatic NER techniques faced some problems when dealing with this corpora.
				Sometimes, the algorithm detected non-content words that did not provide
				relevant information, although they belonged to a specific NER category, e.g.,
				<q>sir,</q> <q>man,</q> <q>mister</q>.</p>
			<p>The algorithm was also affected by the OCR errors, since in some cases, it could
				mislabel broken words, e.g., <q>sp,</q> <q>gr,</q> <q>sch</q> or <q>m,</q> as named entities,
				registered in all regions to some extent. However, these mislabelings did not
				constitute a major problem since they were not within the most frequent named
				entities.</p>
			<p>Moreover, orthographic variations also had an impact on the frequency
				distributions. For instance, we could find entities like Mexico or Maximilian
				written differently and with different frequencies associated.</p>
			<p>In the end, we tried to be careful with all these considerations. We eliminated
				errors and normalized the variations to take them as a single entity.</p>
			<p>Table 3 shows the selected <q>entities of interest</q> list for the content analysis
				from all the entities. In order to obtain this list, first, all the most
				frequent items per entity were contrasted between regions. Then, those that
				appeared in several regions or were of high historical significance were
				selected. </p>
			<p>Although the entities were extracted in the original language, they were then
				translated into English. We extracted reduced lists of named entities for the
				Mexican, Austria, German subcorpora.</p>
			<table>
				<head>Selected list named entities</head>
				<row role="label">
					<cell>Entity</cell>
					<cell>Event</cell>
					<cell>Person</cell>
					<cell>Location</cell>
					<cell>Organization</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell/>
					<cell>Execution</cell>
					<cell>President</cell>
					<cell>World</cell>
					<cell>Army</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell/>
					<cell>Death</cell>
					<cell>Emperor</cell>
					<cell>City </cell>
					<cell>Supreme Government</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell/>
					<cell>Expedition</cell>
					<cell>Prince</cell>
					<cell>Republic</cell>
					<cell/>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell/>
					<cell/>
					<cell>Magnus</cell>
					<cell>Country</cell>
					<cell/>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell/>
					<cell/>
					<cell>French People</cell>
					<cell/>
					<cell/>
				</row>
			</table> 
			
			<p>From these contexts, we found that there are many reprinted stories, especially in
				the regions of Austria and Germany. In other words, some articles reappeared in
				different newspapers, occurring both within and between regions. This points to
				the fact that there is a cultural resemblance among them, viewing Maximilian's
				shooting through a similar lens: a negative one in the European press. We found
				a similar situation in the United States newspaper. Table 4 shows an example of
				these repetitions. Meanwhile, in the Mexican press, this was not as common. This
				probably is the case because new information from far away was harder to get,
				and articles were reused.</p>
			<p>This implies that the emotions, at least in part, are a result of external
				factors. The newspaper's position is determined not just by an editorial
				decision but also by the need to fill space, lack of a correspondent, or the
				popularity of a particular text. This is also important to consider when
				analyzing the score from the automatic sentiment analysis because reprints will
				bias the results.</p>
			<table>
				<head>Examples of reprints between newspapers of different regions</head>
				<row role="label">
					<cell>City/Region</cell>
					<cell>Newspaper</cell>
					<cell>Date</cell>
					<cell>Original Context</cell>
					<cell>Translated Context</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Fürth, Germany</cell>
					<cell>Der Fortschritt (Der Fortschritt auf allen Gebieten des öffentlichen
						Lebens)</cell>
					<cell>
						06
						July, 1867 
					</cell>
					<cell>„ Der unglückliche Fürst , welcher von allen Mächten anerkannt war ,
						wollte nach dem Abzug der Franzosen noch einen äußerste Versuch wagen
						, seine Anhänger zu retten . Indem er sich in einer fast une</cell>
					<cell>"The unfortunate prince, who was recognized by all the powers, wanted
						to venture a supreme test after the withdrawal of the French to save
						his followers. By almost une in a</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Innsbruck, Austria</cell>
					<cell>Innsbrucker Nachrichten </cell>
					<cell>
						08 July,1867
					</cell>
					<cell>. Der unglückliche Fürst , welcher von allen Mächten anerkannt war ,
						wollte nach dem Abzug der Franzosen noch einen äußersten Versuch wagen
						, seine Anhänger zu retten . Indem er sich in einer fast un</cell>
					<cell>, The unfortunate prince, who was recognized by all the powers,
						wanted to venture an extreme attempt after the withdrawal of the
						French to save his followers. By almost un in a</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Clarksville, TN, USA</cell>
					<cell>Clarksville Weekly Chronicle</cell>
					<cell>05 July,1867</cell>
					<cell>d to spar tbe life of Maximilian , but tb pressure from tbe Mexican
						leaders and people for bit execution wat to great that It would be
						almost impos sible to resis sending u 10 Aurope , out ine
						reques</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Charlotte, NC, USA</cell>
					<cell>The Western Democrat</cell>
					<cell>09 July,1867</cell>
					<cell>d to spar tbe life of Maximilian , but tb pressure from tbe Mexican
						leaders and people for bit execution wat to great that It would be
						almost impossible to resis sending u 10 Aurope , out ine reques</cell>
				</row>
			</table> 
			</div>
			<div>
			<head>Content Analysis</head>
			<p>To continue the analysis from the reduced list of entities, we did a qualitative
				content analysis <ptr target="#fernandez2002"/> to understand the sentimental underlying per
				subcorpora qualitatively. These items are essential content words in
				Maximilian's shooting and expose how each region considered the news story
				particularly. The study of the entities of interest showed two different points
				of view about Maximilian's shooting: the Mexican press tends towards neutrality
				with a bit of positivity, and the European and United States press inclines to a
				neutral-negative position. For examples of each entity of interest, see
				appendices 1A-1J.</p>
			<p>For the category "event," four words were the most predominant in the analysis.
				These either appeared in all or most of the regions or refer to key aspects of
				the situation. Figure 3 shows the distribution of these entities within each
				subcorpora.</p> 
			
				<figure>
					<head>Named entities (event) frequencies per subcorpora (top 30)</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure14.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure20.png"/>
					<figDesc>Four bar charts with bars in mauve. The first chart is for Mexico, the second is Austria, the third is Germany, and the fourth is USA</figDesc>
				</figure>
			
			
			<p>The word <q>execution,</q> for example, in the Mexican press, is used in terms of
				official governmental statements about the execution. Most of the published
				documents in Mexican newspapers are the telegrams sent between Mariano Escobedo,
				head of the military army in Queretaro, and Sebastian Lerdo de Tejada, Minister
				of State to President Juarez, in San Luis Potosi, discussing the procedure,
				trial, and shooting of Maximilian. We found few opinion pieces (op-ed) in the
				corpus, which leads us to think that there was governmental control of the
				press, not an unprecedented situation in Mexico. The situation is kept under
				control by publishing short, non-emotional telegrams, probably avoiding a more
				prominent international situation. After the breakthrough of telegram
				connections, international news events were often quickly reported through this
				technology that favored short notices: longer texts, with more emotional
				undertones and editorial considerations, came with a delay <ptr target="#oiva2019"/>. </p>
			<p>In the Austrian and German press, as well as in the United States newspapers,
				there is a clear negative sentiment towards the execution of Maximilian, and it
				is expressed through the use of adjectives such as <q>disgust,</q> <q>horror,</q>
				<q>revulsion,</q> <q>regrettable,</q> <q>tremendous sensation,</q> <q>without mercy,</q> <q>shameful,</q>
				<q>pain,</q> <q>sadness,</q> <q>vigorously protested</q>. For example, Regensburger Anzeiger in
				Germany wrote:</p>
			<cit><quote rend="block">Emperor Maximilian was handed his opponents in his sleep. The assassination of
				the Emperor Maximilian will excite general disgust. This infamous, arranged from
				Juarez (July 06, 1867).</quote><note> Original text: <quote rend="inline">Kaiser Maximilian wurde seinen
					Gegnern im Schlafe überliefert . Die Ermordung des Kaisers Maximilian wird
					allgemeinen Abscheu erregen . Diese infame , von Juarez angeordnet</quote>
					(Regensburger Anzeiger, Germany, July 06, 1867).</note>
			</cit>
			<p>Similarly, outlets from the United States expressed a negative sentiment by
				describing the execution with words like <q>denouncing crime against humanity,</q>
				<q>indignation,</q> <q>horror,</q> <q>brutal,</q> <q>infamous,</q> <q>question international law,</q>
				compared to <q>Louis XVI</q>. In the Mexican press, the word <q>death</q> mainly refers to
				the death sentence in the published official telegrams. Sometimes, though, it
				exposed fake news from the time because they reported about Charlotte's death in
				Europe and Miramón succumbing to his war injuries. Both did not happen at the
				time, but they seem to help the official narrative emotionally.</p>
			<p>The German and Austrian press used <q>death</q> in different ways. Some reports exalt
				Maximilian's positive characteristics: <q>honorable,</q> <q>good,</q> <q>noble,</q> <q>brave,</q>
				<q>amiable,</q> <q>chivalrous,</q> <q>prince</q>. Others concentrate on blaming and finding out
				who was ultimately responsible for his death: Napoleon for abandoning him in
				Mexico or the United States for not stopping Juarez. The third type of news
				story was about European royals and dignitaries mourning. The US press paints
				his death as unfavorable by condemning it. The use of <q>expedition</q> and
				<q>catastrophe</q> (disaster) also alludes to sentiments. Expedition refers to
				England, Spain, and France's 1862 invasion of Mexico, which led to Maximilian's
				proclamation as emperor. German and Austrian newspapers, on the one hand,
				present some criticism towards the expedition, particularly towards France and
				Napoleon III. On the other, they call for an immediate new expedition to avenge
				the destiny of the Austrian Prince. The newspapers from the United States also
				use the term <q>expedition</q> to refer to the attack the European countries charged
				against Mexico but do not publish anything about a new expedition. </p>
			<p>In a similar matter, <q>catastrophe</q> – meaning an emotional disaster, not a natural
				one– is a window into the sentimental biases of the press. While the <q>Mexican
				Expedition</q> was good, Maximilian's death is a <q>Mexican Disaster</q> in the Austrian
				and German corpora. In other words, for some of the European press, an
				expedition that cost thousands of lives the death of one person is a disaster,
				but the killing of thousands of Mexicans during the war is an expedition. As
				seen in the previous analysis of entities, language indicates the newspapers'
				point of view (see Appendix 1c and 1d).</p>
			<p>Meanwhile in the Mexican press, <q>expedition</q> and <q>catastrophe</q> were found only
				once but were depicted differently: the expedition is unfortunate, and the
				results of the expedition were catastrophic. In other words, Maximilian's death
				is not perceived as a disaster. The English, Spanish and French invasion was a
				military intervention to the Mexican press, which became historically known as
				the <q>French Intervention</q> (see appendix 1e).</p>
			<p>For the entity of person, the most notable names or political figures that
				constantly appear in the news are president, Maximilian, prince, Magnus, and
				French people. Once again, they are used differently depending on the regional
				context (see Figure 4). </p> 
			
			
				<figure>
					<head>Named entities (person) frequencies per subcorpora</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure18.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure21.png"/>
					<figDesc>Four bar charts with bars in mauve. The first chart is for Austria, the second is Germany, the third is Mexico, and the fourth is USA</figDesc>
				</figure>
			
			
			
			<p>In the Mexican and USA press, <q>president</q> refers to President Benito Juarez, while
				for the Austrian and German press, it mainly refers to the head of the
				legislative branches of European governments, for example, President Schneider
				of France's Corps Legislative; with very few allusions to President Juarez (see
				appendix 1f). </p> 
			<cit><quote rend="block">ness which <quote rend="inline">will now come back to it was brought. (Stormy interruption.)
				President Schneider: The last words de «honorable gentleman JnleS Favre could be
				facing the whole country</quote> (Das Vaterland, Wien, July 13, 1867).<note> Original
					language: <quote rend="inline">heit gebracht wurde , welche « jetzt auf es zurückkommen wird .
					( Stürmische Unterbrechung. ) Die letzten Worte de « ehrenwerthen Herrn
					JnleS Favre könnten vor dem ganzen Lande</quote> (Das Vaterland, Wien, July 13,
					1867).</note></quote></cit>
			
			<p>Since Juarez won the war against Maximilian, being referred to as President is
				expected, as happened in the USA press. But the European press never mentions
				Juarez as president, showing how newspapers use the title as a way to accept or
				refuse his authority. This does not mean that there are no occurrences, but they
				are rare. </p>
			<p>We found the opposite situation with the item <q>emperor.</q> While it is true that it
				is used in all regions, there are essential differences that contrast with the
				use of president. Primarily, <q>emperor</q> refers to Maximilian and Franz Joseph of
				Austria and Napoleon III of France. Nonetheless, in the Mexican press, it is
				used to refer mostily to Maximilian and is followed by negative descriptors,
				such as <q>usurper</q>: the use of appellatives reveals the emotional underlying of
				news stories (see appendix 1g). </p>
			<p>A similar situation happens in the last three entities – <q>prince,</q> <q>Magnus,</q> and
				<q>French people</q> – (see appendix 1h). <q>Prince,</q> referring to Maximilian, uses
				<q>unfortunate,</q> <q>noble,</q> and <q>brave</q> adjectives in the German and Austrian
				papers. In the Mexican publications, he is alluded to as <q>prince of Europe</q> or,
				in some cases, as <q>prisoner prince.</q> For the rest of the newspapers, the word is
				not associated with anything directly linked to Maximilian's death. </p>
			<p>Magnus was a central person to Maximilian's shooting because he was his lawyer
				during the trial. Many Mexican papers mentioned him because he was constantly
				talked about in governmental correspondence. He is also mentioned in other
				international newspapers because we detected a reprint of a letter he sent.
				Nonetheless, he does not appear among the first 100 frequently used person
				entities. </p>
			<p><q>French People</q> was an interesting case because it is mainly used in the
				German-language newspapers to assign blame for abandoning Maximilian in Mexico
				to his death. It is also used similarly in the USA. In Mexico, this term does
				not appear. Both the mentioning or lack of it helped understand the underlying
				sentiment in news publications in this entity. For example, <q>Juarez!</q> does not
				appear among the most frequent terms in European newspapers. The algorithm
				probably causes this due to an OCR problem: parts of his name can be read often,
				but often cut. If the materials were cleaned, Juarez would probably become more
				prominent. </p>
			<p><q>World</q> and <q>city</q> were the two most relevant location entities. Many cities are
				mentioned because they refer to the publishing place and important landmarks or
				battles, but allusions to Paris and Vienna were most common. In Mexico, the
				press refers to Queretaro constantly. The US papers mainly mention Mexico City.
				There were few references to the Cerro de la campana, where Maximilian was shot
				(figure 5).</p>
			
			
				<figure>
					<head>Named entities (location) frequencies per subcorpora</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure17.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure24.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure26.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure23.png"/>
					<figDesc>Four bar charts with bars in mauve. The first chart is for Austria, the second is Germany, the third is Mexico, and the fourth is USA</figDesc>
				</figure>
			
			
			
			<p>In the Mexican papers, the entity <q>world</q> is used to express that the world will
				understand or that the world mourns the death, but in the European press, the
				world is in <q>terror,</q> <q>condemns,</q> <q>loathes,</q> or claims it was a murder. Also,
				there was a distinction between the civilized world and the barbarians and
				between the old and new world. There are allusions to a shock to the civilized,
				Christian, and old-world in the USA. </p>
			<p>Other entities as <q>republic</q> and <q>country</q> are persistent in some regions but not
				in others, although they appear in all the corpora (see appendix 1i). For
				example, <q>republic</q> is constantly alluded to in the Mexican press, especially
				the president, while this is rarely done in European material. The US press does
				acknowledge this form of government in Mexico. On the other hand, the country
				often does not appear in the Mexican newspapers, but it does in the Austrian
				next to words such as <q>barbarians</q> or <q>misfortune.</q> This antagonism helps create
				a negative sentiment towards Maximilian's death. Nonetheless, since his shooting
				was perceived as a positive moment in Mexico, the negative adjectives and points
				of view are not frequent. </p>
			<cit><quote rend="block">of justice but an act of Mexican revenge and one that will be deprecated by the
				whole civilized world . We reprobate the attempt to establish a foreign empire
				in Mexico , but feel pity for the two c (The Evening Argus, Rock Island IL, July
				05, 1867)</quote></cit>
			<p>The last of the entities is <q>organization</q> (figure 6). In this category, two items
				stood up: <q>army</q> and <q>Supreme government</q> or <q>governmen</q>t (see appendix 1j).
				Each region gave more prevalence to different armies: in the Mexican press, most
				mentions are about the <q>Ejército del Norte,</q> Marino Escobedo's North Division;
				for the German and Austrian press, most references are made to the French army
				abandoning Mexico and leaving Maximilian to his fate, while few mentions allude
				to Juarez's Liberal Army. Similarly, the Mexican press -and sometimes the US
				media-uses <q>Supreme Government</q> to write about Juarez's administration. .
				Meanwhile, in the European press, it primarily refers to the European
				governments.</p>
			
			
				<figure>
					<head>Named entities (organization) frequencies per subcorpora</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure17.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure22.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure13.png"/>
					<figDesc>Four bar charts with bars in mauve. The first chart is for Austria, the second is Germany, the third is Mexico, and the fourth is USA</figDesc>
				</figure>
			
			
			
			<p>Once more, the different use of words depending on the region shows a bias towards
				specific themes or sentiments. While in Mexico, <q>Supreme Government</q> appears
				many times since that is how they referred to Juarez's government. In Europe,
				these words allude to the governments of that continent and only sometimes to
				the Mexican one. The same thing happens with <q>army.</q> In both instances, it is
				clear that, for the Europeans, what matters tends to be local issues, while in
				Mexico, Juarez dealings tend to be exalted. </p>
			<cit><quote rend="block">I Mejía.- 21 1861.- General Mariano Escobedo Citizens division, chief corps of
				Norte.- Queretaro. ( To be continue ) . OFFICER. DOCUMENTS. About the trial of
				archiduqu<q></q> (El Monitor, Ciudad de México, July 06, 1867)<note> Original text:
					<q></q>yo 21 de 1861.- Mejía.- Ciudadanos general de división Mariano Escobedo ,
					en jefe del cuerpo de ejército del Norte.- Querétaro . ( Continuará ) .
					OFICIAL . DOCUMENTOS . Acerca del juicio del archiduqu” (El Monitor, Ciudad
					de México, July 06, 1867)</note></quote>
			</cit>
			<cit><quote rend="block">He then reminded again of the day in the previous year, where the withdrawal of
				the French army from Mexico, the only guarantee of the new throne, be already
				irrevocably decided&gt; v (Neue Freie Presse, Wien, July 10, 1867)<note>
					Original text: <quote rend="inline">er dann wieder sich des Tages im vorigen Jahre erinnert ,
					wo die Zurückziehung der französischen Armee aus Mexico , der einzigen
					Bürgschaft des neuen Thrones , be reits unwiderruflich beschlossen &gt;
					v</quote>(Neue Freie Presse, Wien, July 10, 1867)</note></quote>
			</cit>
			</div>
			<div>
			<head>Automated Sentiment Analysis</head>
			<p>To complement the previous results, we explored emotions using a fully automated
				sentiment analysis that quantifies the sentiment trend in each newspaper story.
				We obtained a sentimental score for the newspaper publications, which allows us
				to know the general sentiment trend per region. </p>
			<p>Table 5 shows the average sentiment score per region — the more negative the
				values, the more negative the polarity. Likewise, positive values indicate
				positive sentiment polarity (zero represents neutrality).</p>
			<table>
				<head>Average sentiment analysis score per region</head>
				<row role="label">
					<cell>Region</cell>
					<cell>Sentiment score<lb/>(mean)</cell>
					<cell>Sentiment </cell>
					<cell>Standard Deviation</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Mexico</cell>
					<cell>+0.04</cell>
					<cell>Positive trend</cell>
					<cell>0.13</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Austria</cell>
					<cell>-0.04</cell>
					<cell>Negative trend</cell>
					<cell>0.13</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Germany</cell>
					<cell>-0.01</cell>
					<cell>Negative trend</cell>
					<cell>0.14</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>USA</cell>
					<cell>-0.02</cell>
					<cell>Negative trend</cell>
					<cell>0.14</cell>
				</row>
			</table>
			
			<p>The following bar charts (Figure 7) show a more detailed overview of the sentiment
				score by region. We have averaged the score of all news stories published by
				each newspaper in the different regions in these plots. Also, it can be observed
				how the number of sources varies in each region. The Austrians and Germans wrote
				many news stories showing a general tendency to one side of the sentiment
				continuum. For example, the Austrian bar chart has mostly negative stories,
				while the Mexican bar chart has mainly positive stories. We have excluded the
				USA from these visualizations since, for this particular case, we did not
				preserve the newspaper source information for each news story. This is due to
				the OCR cleaning and pre-processing steps involved in this specific database,
				where we had to filter just the text portions with relevant information about
				the Maximilian case. Still, the graph shows the sentiment distribution of the
				news stories, albeit without the name of the newspapers (see appendix 2).</p>
				
				<figure>
					<head>Positive and negative news stories for regional subcorpora.</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure11.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
					<figDesc>three bar charts, the first two have bars in mauve and the last has bars in green. The first chart is the sentiment score for Austria, the second is the sentiment score Germany, and the third is the sentiment score for Mexico</figDesc>
				</figure>
				
				
		
			<p>Table 5 shows this general tendency clearly. Mexican newspapers are inclined
				towards a positive direction, while European newspapers and those from the
				United States are prone to consider Maximilian's shooting as negative..
				Meanwhile, the Mexican press shows an alliance with the government in power,
				meaning Juarez's republic. They only printed official statements and
				communications from the events, meaning telegraphic messages between Mariano
				Escobedo in Queretaro's battlefront and Sebastian Lerdo de Tejada –Minister of
				Foreign Affairs under Juarez– in San Luis Potosi. Since they are mostly short
				and to the point messages, the sentiment analysis results closer to neutrality.
				The United States, while it might not agree with the imperial governmental
				system, opposes the actions taken by Juarez. Therefore, news stories tend to
				focus on the negative aspects of the shooting. The German newspapers are less
				extreme than the Austrian ones, maybe because Maximilian was an Austrian
				prince.</p>
			<p>Nonetheless, the averages are very low since both sides are very close to
				neutrality. It should be considered that newspapers, as an institutional ethos,
				tend to strive for certain neutrality. Although not always achieved –like songs,
				poems and op-ed can be found– it does tend towards the middle and away from
				extreme views. </p>
			<p>In summary, the use of fully automated tools to measure sentiment in newspapers
				about Maximilian shooting provided similar results to the analysis previously
				done using other techniques –such as content analysis, obtaining the frequency
				of common words and named entities–, which shows that these digital techniques
				can identify the underlying ideological positions from each region. It is
				important to mention that the differences are small but significant enough to
				evidence the variations. </p></div>
			<div>
			<head>Conclusion</head>
			<p>This study has focused on the international news flows on the execution of
				Maximilian, the Emperor of Mexico. The execution took place in June 1867, and
				the news started to flow across borders at the beginning of July, reaching
				global readership through newspapers. The aim of this study has been twofold.
				First, the study concentrated on finding ways of analyzing sentiments in a
				multilingual research setting. Second, it was to investigate the regional
				differences in sentiments evoked by the execution in the press internationally. </p>
			<p>This study has explored the use of several digitized newspaper corpora on a
				transnational scale. It has drawn on newspapers from four regions: Austria,
				Germany, Mexico, and the United States in three languages. We selected the
				timeframe from 5 July to 20 July, extracted the news on the execution from the
				available corpora, and explored this multilingual data set with several
				strategies. </p>
			<p>Contentwise, our article has been the first study on the transnational reception
				of a significant news event of its time, the execution of the Emperor of Mexico.
				It has covered newspapers from two continents and four geographical regions. The
				case itself is illuminating from the perspective that it happened very near to
				the inauguration of the transatlantic telegraph cable and indicates how quickly
				news circulated. The execution was a politically loaded media event that aroused
				mixed feelings and ambiguous emotions. The execution was not only a domestic
				case to Mexico because the United States and some European countries were deeply
				involved in the affair. Our analysis shows content variations in the corpora,
				meaning that the news was framed differently in each studied region, indicating
				that the local perception of the event and polítical interests shaped the news.
				In our corpus, the Mexican press –published in the middle of a political crisis–
				tended towards a neutral stance, the Austrian and German papers mainly were
				negative, and the United States showed mixed sentiments on the incident. </p>
			<p>Our study faced two limitations that have to be addressed in most newspaper
				projects in the digital humanities. On the one hand, the size of each subcorpora
				varied because of cultural, political, and economic reasons. On the other hand,
				digitized newspapers have been optically recognized with an OCR software based
				on particular scanning practices, which produced differences in quality.
				However, we argue that it is possible to transgress the OCR problem and the
				multilingual nature of the data, as we have done, and conduct transnational
				research. We drew on quantitative solutions such as named-entity recognition,
				frequency distributions, and textual context analysis in conjunction with
				qualitative analysis. This permitted us to study the underlying sentiments in
				the newspapers from the nineteenth century. We have a significant outcome
				contrasting the result of automatic sentiment analysis tools combined with
				quantitative and qualitative analysis that suggested the automatic sentiment
				analysis tools results are trustworthy for our nineteenth-century newspaper
				corpus. </p>
			</div>
			<div>
			<head>Appendix </head>
			<p>1- Examples of various entities of interest’s context, region, source and
				date.</p>
			<p>Appendix 1a. Context of the entity execution in different subcorpus</p>
			<table>
				<row role="label">
					<cell>City/Region</cell>
					<cell>Newspaper</cell>
					<cell>Date</cell>
					<cell>Original Text</cell>
					<cell>Translated Text</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Ciudad de México, México</cell>
					<cell>Monitor Republicano</cell>
					<cell>07 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>DEL JUICIO DEL ARCHIDUQUE MAXIMILIANO , DE D. MIGUEL MIRAMON Y DE
						TOMAS MEJIA , Y ACERDA DE LA EJECUCION QUE SE VERIFICO EN QUERETARO EN
						19 DE JUNIO A LAS SIETE LA MAÑANA . ( Continúa ) . República M</cell>
					<cell>JUDGMENT OF Archduke Maximillian, of Miguel Miramon and Tomas Mejia,
						and acerda of execution that took place in QUERETARO ON JUNE 19 AT
						SEVEN IN THE MORNING. ( Keep going ) . Republic M</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Regensburg, Germany</cell>
					<cell>Regensburger Anzeiger </cell>
					<cell>06 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>bare Stellung nachfolgen . Kaiser Maximilian wurde seinen Gegnern im
						Schlafe überliefert . Die Ermordung des Kaisers Maximilian wird
						allgemeinen Abscheu erregen . Diese infame , von Juarez
						angeordnet</cell>
					<cell>follow bare position. Emperor Maximilian was handed his opponents in
						his sleep. The assassination of the Emperor Maximilian will excite
						general disgust. This infamous, arranged from Juarez</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Wien, Austria</cell>
					<cell>Neue Freie Presse </cell>
					<cell>07 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>Tage nicht halten zu dürfen , an welchem der Moniteur die
						Schaudernachricht von Maximilian 'S Hinrichtung officiell bestätigte .
						Die Achtung vor dem , was sich ziemte , hat Herrn Thiers sehr
						richtig</cell>
					<cell>not being allowed to hold day on which the Moniteur the horror news
						of Maximilian 's execution confirmed officially. Respect for what
						became him, has M. Thiers very properly</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Portland ME, USA</cell>
					<cell>The Portland Daily Press</cell>
					<cell>08 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>The Moniteur to-day has an article express ing detestation of the
						murder of Maximilian. In the Senate and Corps Legislatif, to-day,
						speeches were made denouncing the execution as a crime against
						civilization. Orders have b . n sent out suspending from their
						functions all French Consuls in the Mexican Republic. All festivities
						in this city have ceased, and all preparations for the forthcoming
						fetes have been abandoned out of respect to the memory of the
						ill-fitted Maximilian.</cell>
				</row>
			</table>
			<p>Appendix 1b. Context of the entity death in different subcorpus</p>
			<table>
				<row role="label">
					<cell>City/Region</cell>
					<cell>Newspaper</cell>
					<cell>Date</cell>
					<cell>Original Text</cell>
					<cell>Translated Text</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>
						<p>Ciudad de México, México</p>
					</cell>
					<cell>Boletín Republicano</cell>
					<cell>07 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>1867.- A las 12 h. y 10 ms. de la noche . C. ministro de relaciones.-
						El consejo ha condenado á muerte , por unanimidad , á los tres
						procesados . La causa ha pasado al asesor. — Escobedo .
						Telégrama.</cell>
					<cell>1867.- At 12 h. and 10 ms. of the night . C. Minister Relationship.
						The Council condemned to death, unanimously, the three defendants. The
						cause has passed the asesor.-Escobedo. Telegram.</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>
						<p>Ciudad de México, México</p>
					</cell>
					<cell>Monitor Republicano</cell>
					<cell>13 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>las familias de los generales y varias poblaciones . “ antes de morir
						le dieron la noticia de la muerte de Carlota , entonces proclamó :
						Hasta en esto me ayuda el cielo ” . A la familia de Miramón dej</cell>
					<cell>families of generals and several towns. "Before dying gave him the
						news of the death of Carlota, then he proclaimed: Until this helps me
						in heaven." A family of Miramon Dej</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>
						<p>Ciudad de México, México</p>
					</cell>
					<cell>Monitor Republicano</cell>
					<cell>18 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>gualmente fusilados . Miramon habia sucumbido por sus heridas antes
						de la toma de la ciudad . La muerte lo sustrajo de la venganza de los
						juaristas . De los gefes mexicano que se habian unido al imper</cell>
					<cell>lso shot. Miramon had succumbed to his injuries before taking the
						city. Death subtracted from the vengeance of juaristas. The Mexican
						chiefs who had joined the imper</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Wien, Austria</cell>
					<cell>Neues Fremden-Blatt</cell>
					<cell>18 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>n vertraut hatte . Die Befürchtung war nur zu sehr gerechtfertigt ,
						daß dieser letzte Verrath den Tod des unglücklichen Prinzen zur Folge
						haben werde , dessen Absichten so edel waren , der aber leide</cell>
					<cell>n had trusted. The fear was justified only too well that this last
						betrayal will result in death of the unfortunate prince result, whose
						intentions were so noble, but the suffering</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Neustadt, Haardt, Germany</cell>
					<cell>Pfälzischer Kurier</cell>
					<cell>07 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>ndere zu wälzen . Im Senate hatte man am 5 dS . nichr übel Lust , die
						Vereinigten Staaten für den Tod Maximilians verantwortlich zu machen ,
						weil dieselben daS Kaiftrthum in Mexiko nicht von Anfang a</cell>
					<cell>ther to roll. In the Senate had at 5 dS. nichr good mind to make the
						United States responsible for the death of Maximilian, because the
						same tHe Kaiftrthum in Mexico not initially a</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>München, Germany</cell>
					<cell>Allgemeine Zeitung</cell>
					<cell>09 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>fulminanten Artikels gegen Napoleon III halber , in welchem dem
						Kaiser der Franzosen für die Erschießung Maximilians die diesseitige
						und jenseitige Verantwortung auf die Seele geladen und die
						Aburth</cell>
					<cell>brilliant article against Napoleon III's sake, in which the French
						Emperor loaded for the Execution of Maximilian, the this side and the
						responsibility to the soul and the Aburth</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>München, Germany</cell>
					<cell>Der Bayerische Landbote</cell>
					<cell>07 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>Tel . d. Korr . v. u. f. D. ) Frankreich . Paris , 2 . Juli , Abends
						. „ La Presse “ meldet : Der Tod des Kaisers Maximilian_von_Mexiko
						bestätigt sich . Der kaiserliche Hof wird durch 21 Tage Trauer</cell>
					<cell>Tel. d. Corr. v. u. f. D.) France. Paris, second July evening. "La
						Presse" reports: The death of the Emperor Maximilian_von_Mexiko
						confirmed. The imperial court is 21 days mourning</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Manitowoc WI, USA</cell>
					<cell>The Manitowoc Pilot</cell>
					<cell>07 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>Or leans‚Äî'To Count Wydenbruek : 1 conic from veracruz to telegraph
						you of the condemnation and death of tiic Emperor Maximilian on the
						19th . President Ju e northward . Execution of Maximilian . Ne</cell>
				</row>
			</table>
			<p>Appendix 1c. Context of the entity expedition in different subcorpus</p>
			<table>
				<row role="label">
					<cell>City/Region</cell>
					<cell>Newspaper</cell>
					<cell>Date</cell>
					<cell>Original Text</cell>
					<cell>Translated Text</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Innsbruck, Austria</cell>
					<cell>Innsbrucker Nachrichten</cell>
					<cell>13 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>ehre dieser traurigen Expedition ist , daß eö einer Kontrole und des
						Widerstandes bedarf . Die Expedition nach Mexiko wurde von Niemandem
						in Frankreich gebilligt , und dennoch ausgeführt . Sie hat 6 J</cell>
					<cell>is honor this sad expedition that requires EE an Kontrole and
						resistance. The expedition to Mexico was endorsed by no one in France,
						and yet executed. She has 6 J</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Zweibrücken, Germany</cell>
					<cell>Zweibrücker Wochenblatt </cell>
					<cell>13 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>Budgets für 1868 . Thiers hielt seine Rede über Mexiko . Er führte
						aus , daß die mexikanische Expedition trotz des Widerspruchs der
						öffentlichen Meinung unternommen worden sei , und kam zu dem
						Schluß</cell>
					<cell>Budgets for the 1868th Thiers made his speech about Mexico. He
						pointed out that the Mexican expedition was undertaken in spite of the
						opposition of public opinion, and came to the conclusion</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Wien, Austria</cell>
					<cell>Fremden-Blatt </cell>
					<cell>08 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>r dung des französischen Gesandten in Mexiko sich bestätigte , die
						Ehre Frank reichs eine neue Expedition unabweislich fordere . Es ist
						indeß sehr zweifel haft , ob an maßgebender Stelle diese
						Ansicht</cell>
					<cell>r-making of the French ambassador in Mexico confirmed that honor
						Frank Reich urge a new expedition unavoidable. It is, however, very
						doubtful whether at decisive point this view</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Hamburg, Germany</cell>
					<cell>Börsen-Halle </cell>
					<cell>15 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>2 Frankreich . ZJ_ Paris , den 12 . Juli . Es wäre nicht unmöglich ,
						dab sich die mexicanische Expedition erneuern könnte . Diese Even
						tualität ist sogar nicht so unwahrscheinlich . Man hat hier
						noch</cell>
					<cell>2 France. ZJ_ Paris, the 12th July . It would not be impossible to
						dab the Mexican expedition might renew. This is even tualität even not
						so unlikely. One gets some</cell>
				</row>
			</table>
			<p>Appendix 1d. Context of the entity catastrophe (disaster) in different
				subcorpus</p>
			<table>
				<row role="label">
					<cell>City/Region</cell>
					<cell>Newspaper</cell>
					<cell>Date</cell>
					<cell>Original Text</cell>
					<cell>Translated Text</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Wien, Austria</cell>
					<cell>Das Vaterland </cell>
					<cell>07 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>n angelegt . Kaiser Max . ) Der „ Wdr . '' enthält einige
						Mittheilungen über die mexikanische Katastrophe , die dem Schreiben
						eines Reisen den entnommen sind , der au » Zalisco ( an der Westküste
						Mex</cell>
					<cell>n applied. Emperor Max. ) The "W dr. '' Contains some communications
						on the Mexican disaster that has been taken from the writing of a
						travel, the co »Zalisco (on the west coast Mex</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Kusel, Germany</cell>
					<cell>Pfälzer </cell>
					<cell>05 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>Die „ Aschaffb . Ztg. “ Bringt in ihrem Leitartikel vom 2 . Juli : „
						Die Katastrophe in Mexiko “ folgenden interessanten Satz : „ Bei der
						ritterlichen französischen Nation wird d</cell>
					<cell>The "Aschaffb. Zeitung. "Bring in its editorial on the second July:
						"The disaster in Mexico" following interesting statement: "In the
						chivalrous French nation is d</cell>
				</row>
			</table>
			<p>Appendix 1e. Context of the entity intervention and expedition in different
				subcorpus</p>
			<table>
				<row role="label">
					<cell>City/Region</cell>
					<cell>Newspaper</cell>
					<cell>Date</cell>
					<cell>Original Text</cell>
					<cell>Translated Text</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Ciudad de México, México</cell>
					<cell>El Monitor Republicano</cell>
					<cell>09 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>Este acontecimiento para Luis Napoleón es un rudo golpe, porque todas
						las testas coronadas echarán toda la culta sobre su trono de la
						desgraciada expedición y sus resultados todavía más
						desastrosos.</cell>
					<cell>This event for Luis Napoleón is a rude blow, because all the crowned
						heads will cast all the cult on his throne of the unfortunate
						expedition and its even more disastrous results.</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>
						<p>Ciudad de México, México</p>
					</cell>
					<cell>El Monitor Republicano</cell>
					<cell>07 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>
						<p>Con objeto de que se forme el cuadro histórico de esta época tan
							completo como sea posible, damos á continuación el artículo que
							describe al difunto notable, no con intento de remover sus
							cenizas, sino que habiendo sido el móvil de cuantos sucesos han
							tenido lugar durante la intervencion y el imperio en nuestra
							patria, es indispensable vindicarla de cuantos cargos se le
							hacen, y por tanto citar repetidas veces al que ocasionó las
							tempestades políticas y sociales que la conmovieron </p>
					</cell>
					<cell>In order to form the historical picture of this period as complete as
						possible, we give below the article that describes the notable
						deceased, not with the intent to remove his ashes, but having been the
						motive of how many events have taken place during the intervention and
						the empire in our homeland, it is indispensable to vindicate it of how
						many charges are made, and therefore to repeatedly mention the one
						that caused the political and social storms that moved her</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell/>
				</row>
			</table>
			<p>Appendix 1f. Context of the entity president in different subcorpus</p>
			<table>
				<row role="label">
					<cell>City/Region</cell>
					<cell>Newspaper</cell>
					<cell>Date</cell>
					<cell>Original Text</cell>
					<cell>Translated Text</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Ciudad de México, Mexico</cell>
					<cell>El Monitor Republicano </cell>
					<cell>07 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>hacer lo que seria prudente para un país como México . Tengo entera
						fe en la habilidad del Sr. Presidente Juarez , para que trate á
						Maximiliano de la manera mas benéfica para los intereses de México
						.</cell>
					<cell>do it would be wise for a country like Mexico. I have full faith in
						the ability of President Juarez to try to Maximilian of the most
						beneficial way for the interests of Mexico.</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Wien, Austria</cell>
					<cell>Das Vaterland </cell>
					<cell>
						<p>13 July, 1867</p>
					</cell>
					<cell>heit gebracht wurde , welche « jetzt auf es zurückkommen wird . (
						Stürmische Unterbrechung . ) Die letzten Worte de « ehrenwerthen Herrn
						JnleS Favre könnten vor dem ganzen Lande</cell>
					<cell>ness which "will now come back to it was brought. (Stormy
						interruption.) President Schneider: The last words de «honorable
						gentleman JnleS Favre could be facing the whole country</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>München, Germany</cell>
					<cell>Allgemeine Zeitung</cell>
					<cell>
						<p>06 July, 1867</p>
					</cell>
					<cell>sfest wird morgen gefeiert , ( T. H. ) *Paris , 5 . Juli . Im
						gesetzgebenden Körper zeigte der Präsident den Tod des Kaisers
						Maximilian an . Der Moiteur habe schon gesprochen , aber der Präsident
						hal</cell>
					<cell>sfest (T. H.) * Paris, 5 will be celebrated tomorrow. July . In the
						Legislature, the President pointed to the death of the Emperor
						Maximilian. The Moiteur have already spoken, but the president
						hal</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Clarksville TN, USA</cell>
					<cell>Clarksville Weekly Chronicle </cell>
					<cell>
						<p>05 July, 1867</p>
					</cell>
					<cell>Cms to telegraph yon of tbe condemnation and death or the Emperor
						Maximilian on the 19th Inst President Juarez refuses to deliver np the
						body . Sined . GR0L1BR TEHIFF , Captain Austrian Sloop . Coun</cell>
				</row>
			</table>
			<p>Appendix 1g. Context of the entity emperor in different subcorpus</p>
			<table>
				<row role="label">
					<cell>City/Region</cell>
					<cell>Newspaper</cell>
					<cell>Date</cell>
					<cell>Original Text</cell>
					<cell>Translated Text</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Ciudad de México, México</cell>
					<cell>El Monitor Republicano</cell>
					<cell>18 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>es que nos ha demostrado lo que valemos y lo que México está llamado
						á ser en el porvenir . EL EMPERADOR MAXIMILIANIO.- Con este título
						leemos en la Francia de Paris , del 13 de Junio , lo siguiente</cell>
					<cell>has shown us is that what we are worth and what Mexico is destined to
						be in the future. EMPEROR MAXIMILIANIO.- With this title we read in
						France in Paris, June 13, the following</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Ciudad de México, México</cell>
					<cell>El Monitor Republicano</cell>
					<cell>16 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>iaco osado , Por mexicanos viles escogido , El título á usurpar vino
						atrevido De nuestro rey , emperador deseado . Huyó el frances , rodó
						el usurpador , De vergüenza cubiertos y baldon , Para oprobio</cell>
					<cell>iaco daring, chosen by Mexican vile, usurping the title came daring
						of our king, emperor desired. He fled the French, rolled the usurper,
						covered shame and Baldon, a reproach</cell>
				</row>
			</table>
			<p>Appendix 1h. Context of the entity prince, Magnus and French people in different
				subcorpus</p>
			<table>
				<row role="label">
					<cell>City/Region</cell>
					<cell>Newspaper</cell>
					<cell>Date</cell>
					<cell>Original Text</cell>
					<cell>Translated Text</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Ciudad de México, México</cell>
					<cell>Boletín Republicano </cell>
					<cell>07 July, 1867 </cell>
					<cell>el Rey de Prusia , y todos los Monarcas de Europa , unidos por los
						vínculos de la sangre con el príncipe prisionero , a saber , su
						hermano el emperador de Austria , su prima la reina del Imperio
						Britá</cell>
					<cell>King of Prussia, and all the monarchs of Europe, united by the ties
						of blood with the prisoner prince, namely, his brother the emperor of
						Austria, her cousin Queen Brita Empire</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Wien, Austria</cell>
					<cell>Das Vaterland </cell>
					<cell>05 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>had been constant companions. About the Gefangeunehmung and the
						process of the unfortunate prince a correspondent of the "New Aork
						Herald '' from Queretaro, 25th May WUR of La Cruz</cell>
					<cell>had been constant companions. About the Gefangeunehmung and the
						process of the unfortunate prince a correspondent of the "New Aork
						Herald '' from Queretaro, 25th May WUR of La Cruz</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Würzburg, Germany</cell>
					<cell>Schweinfurter Tagblatt </cell>
					<cell>07 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>ndmoniteur “ meldet : Der Tod des Kaisers von Mexico wird officiell
						bestätigt . Der unglückliche Prinz wollte nach dem Abzug der Franzosen
						das Aeußerste versuchen , um sich mit seinen Parteigängern i</cell>
					<cell>ndmoniteur "reports: The death of the Emperor of Mexico is officially
						confirmed. The unfortunate prince wanted to try the utmost after the
						withdrawal of the French to come up with his partisans i</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Ciudad de México, México</cell>
					<cell>Boletín Republicano </cell>
					<cell>06 July, 1867 </cell>
					<cell>aro para San Luis Potosí.- Recibido a las 6 h. 15 ms. De la tarde ,
						el 3 de junio de 1867.- Sr. Ministro Lerdo de Tejada . - Hoy he
						recibido un mensaje del Sr. Magnus , remitido anoche a las 7 de
						Tepe</cell>
					<cell>aro for San Luis Potosí.- Received at 6 h. 15 ms. Afternoon on 3 June
						1867.- Minister Lerdo de Tejada. - Today I received a message from Mr.
						Magnus, I sent last night at 7 Tepe</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Innsbruck, Germany</cell>
					<cell>Innsbrucker Nachrichten </cell>
					<cell>07 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>Fellow-sufferer, nor downright devastating for the future of his
						reign withdrawal of the French from Mexico was able to shake him, he
						persevered in the self-chosen position, as al</cell>
					<cell>Fellow-sufferer, nor downright devastating for the future of his
						reign withdrawal of the French from Mexico was able to shake him, he
						persevered in the self-chosen position, as al</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Landshut, Germany</cell>
					<cell>Landshuter Zeitung </cell>
					<cell>05 July, 1867 </cell>
					<cell>Uebernahme des mexikanischen Kaiserthrones hatte bestimmen lassen ,
						war nun nah dem Abzuge der Franzosen si &lt; h selbst überlassen .
						Männlih harrte er aus , männlih kämpfte er fort gegen die
						republika</cell>
					<cell>Takeover of the Mexican Emperor throne had determined, was now close
						to the departure of the French si &lt;h left to itself. Männlih he
						persevered, männlih he fought continuously against the
						republika</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Delaware OH, USA</cell>
					<cell>Delaware Gazette</cell>
					<cell>05 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>ximilian has after all not been much to blame . He has been the
						unfortunate tool and dupe of the French Emperor whose skirts will bear
						his blood , and who is chiefly responsible lor the Mexican
						scheme</cell>
				</row>
			</table>
			<p>Appendix 1i. Context of the entity country and republic in different subcorpus</p>
			<table>
				<row role="label">
					<cell>City/Region</cell>
					<cell>Newspaper</cell>
					<cell>Date</cell>
					<cell>Original Text</cell>
					<cell>Translated Text</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Ciudad de México, México</cell>
					<cell>
						<p>Boletín Republicano </p>
					</cell>
					<cell>
						<p>05 July, 1867 </p>
					</cell>
					<cell>uchinas , Mejia a san_antonio y Marimon a otra iglesia . Los pocos
						habitantes que hay ahora en Querétaro , fanáticos como son todos por
						Mejía , se vistieron de luto ; las mujeres enjugaron la sangre</cell>
					<cell>uchinas, Mejia san_antonio and Marimon another church. The few
						inhabitants there now in Queretaro, like all fans by Mejia, dressed in
						mourning; women wiped away the blood</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Wien, Austria</cell>
					<cell>Neue Freie Presse </cell>
					<cell>07 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>d da » Grab aufschaufelten , in welches einige Monate später das
						Kaiserthum versenkt wurde . Alle Welt verdammt in den Ausdrücken des
						tiefsten Abscheues die Ermordung Maximilian 's , und auch der
						Monii</cell>
					<cell>d as "aufschaufelten grave into which the empire was sunk a few
						months later. The whole world condemned in the expressions of the
						deepest repugnance the murder Maximilian's, and also the Moni</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Rock Island IL, USA</cell>
					<cell>The Evening Argus </cell>
					<cell>05 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>of justice but an act of Mexican revenge and one that will be
						deprecated by the whole civilized world . We reprobate the attempt to
						establish a foreign empire in Mexico , but feel pity for the two
						c</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Ciudad de México, México</cell>
					<cell>
						<p>Boletín Republicano </p>
					</cell>
					<cell>
						<p>06 July, 1867 </p>
					</cell>
					<cell>867 , . A las siete de la noche.- C. mariano Riva Palacio.-
						Querétaro.- El C. presidente de la República ha tomado en
						consideración el mensaje que nos dirigió vd . hoy , recibido a las tre
						sy media d</cell>
					<cell>867. A seven night. Marian C. Riva Palacio.- C. Querétaro.- The
						President has taken into consideration the message that directed us
						vd. Today, I received the tre s average d</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Canton MS, USA</cell>
					<cell>American Citizen </cell>
					<cell>06 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>ad . By this cruel and barbarous act , Juarez has , we believe ,
						sealed the fate of the Mexican Republic . Mex ico , as an independent
						n ed with such men as Stephens , : Tooms , Jenkins , Johnston ,
						e</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Wien, Austria</cell>
					<cell>Fremden-Blatt </cell>
					<cell>05 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>alle Gemüther auf 's Tiefste erschüttert . Ueberall , wo menschliches
						Fühlen nicht , wie in dem Lande der mexikanischen Barbaren , zu den
						ausnahmsweisen Tugenden zählt , überall in den civilirten St</cell>
					<cell>all minds shaken on 's deepest. Wherever human feeling not like, one
						in the land of the Mexican barbarians to the exceptional virtues
						throughout the civilirten St</cell>
				</row>
			</table>
			<p>Appendix 1j. Context of the entity army and government in different subcorpus</p>
			<table>
				<row role="label">
					<cell>City/Region</cell>
					<cell>Newspaper</cell>
					<cell>Date</cell>
					<cell>Original Text</cell>
					<cell>Translated Text</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Ciudad de México, México</cell>
					<cell>
						<p>Boletín Republicano </p>
					</cell>
					<cell>
						<p>07 July, 1867 </p>
					</cell>
					<cell>telegrama de ayer , que no puede permitir la entrada á Mexico de mi
						pedido , sin órden del Supremo_Gobierno . Deseo , señor presidente ,
						se sirva ud . espedir esa órden , para que cuanto antes vengan</cell>
					<cell>telegram yesterday, which may not allow entry to Mexico of my order,
						without order of Supremo_Gobierno. I wish, Mr. President, will serve
						you. espedir this order, the sooner you come</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Wien, Austria</cell>
					<cell>Neue Freie Presse </cell>
					<cell>07 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>eues die Ermordung Maximilian 's , und auch der Moniteur konnte den
						Gefühlen der französischen Regierung den entsprechenden Ausdruck geben
						. Aber was der Moniteur gestern geredet , schießt über das Z</cell>
					<cell>ew the murder Maximilian's, and even the Moniteur was able to give
						the corresponding expression to the feelings of the French government.
						But what the Moniteur spoke yesterday, overshoots the Z</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Aschaffenburg, Germany</cell>
					<cell>Aschaffenburger Zeitung </cell>
					<cell>07 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>ung der französischen Interessen der Regierung von Washington
						anvertraut . Andere europäische Regierungen haben ihre Vertreter aus
						Mexiko abberufen und wollen die Regierung des Juarez nicht
						anerkenne</cell>
					<cell>entrusted clothes the French interests of the government of
						Washington. Other European governments have recalled their
						representatives from Mexico and the government of Juarez do not
						recognize</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Clearfield PA, USA</cell>
					<cell>Raftsman's Journal </cell>
					<cell>10 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>wrs ordered to be carried into effect on the 16th . The execution was
						suspended by order of the supreme government until to day . It is now
						seven o'clock in the morning , at which time Maxim ilian of</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Ciudad de México, México</cell>
					<cell>
						<p>El Monitor </p>
					</cell>
					<cell>
						<p>06 July, 1867 </p>
					</cell>
					<cell>yo 21 de 1861.- Mejía.- Ciudadanos general de división Mariano
						Escobedo , en jefe del cuerpo de ejército del Norte.- Querétaro . (
						Continuará ) . OFICIAL . DOCUMENTOS . Acerca del juicio del
						archiduqu</cell>
					<cell>I Mejía.- 21 1861.- General Mariano Escobedo Citizens division, chief
						corps of Norte.- Queretaro. ( To be continue ) . OFFICER. DOCUMENTS.
						About the trial of archiduqu</cell>
				</row>
				<row role="data">
					<cell>Wien</cell>
					<cell>Neue Freie Presse </cell>
					<cell>10 July, 1867</cell>
					<cell>er dann wieder sich des Tages im vorigen Jahre erinnert , wo die
						Zurückziehung der französischen Armee aus Mexico , der einzigen
						Bürgschaft des neuen Thrones , be reits unwiderruflich beschlossen
						&gt; v</cell>
					<cell>He then reminded again of the day in the previous year, where the
						withdrawal of the French army from Mexico, the only guarantee of the
						new throne, be already irrevocably decided&gt; v</cell>
				</row>
			</table>
			
			
				<figure>
					<head>USA sentiment analysis bar chart (without newspaper names)</head>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
					<figDesc>A bar chart representing the sentiment score for the USA. The chart is vertical and has bars on both sides in blue.</figDesc>
				</figure>
				
			</div>
		</body>


		<back>
			<listBibl>
				<bibl xml:id="beals2020" label="Beals and Bell 2020"> Beals, Melodee and Emily Bell, <title rend="quotes">The Atlas of Digitised Newspapers and Metadata:
					Reports from Oceanic Exchanges.</title> Loughborough University, 5.5.2020,
					<ref target="https://figshare.com/articles/online_resource/The_Atlas_of_Digitised_Newspapers_and_Metadata_Reports_from_Oceanic_Exchanges/11560059">https://figshare.com/articles/online_resource/The_Atlas_of_Digitised_Newspapers_and_Metadata_Reports_from_Oceanic_Exchanges/11560059</ref>
					Accessed November 9, 2020.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="cordell2017" label="Cordell 2017"> Cordell, R. <title rend="quotes">‘Q i-jtb the Raven’: Taking Dirty OCR Seriously,.</title> <title rend="italic"
					>Book History</title> 20 (2017), 188-225</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="ehrmann2020" label="Ehermann et al. 2020"> Ehrmann, M., Romanello, M., Bircher, S. &amp; Clematide, S. <title rend="quotes">Introducing the CLEF
					2020 HIPE Shared Task: Named Entity Recognition and Linking on Historical
					Newspapers.</title>. <title rend="italic">European Conference on Information Retrieval ECIR 2020: Advances in
					Information Retrieval</title> (2020): 524-532</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="feldman2013" label="Feldman 2013"> Feldman, R. <title rend="quotes">Techniques and Applications for Sentiment Analysis.</title> <title rend="italic">Communications
					of the ACM</title>, 56(4), (2013): 82-89.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="fernandez2002" label="Fernandez 2002"> Fernández, F. <title rend="quotes">El análisis de contenido como ayuda metodológica para la
					investigación.</title>. <title rend="italic">Ciencias Sociales</title>, June, 2-96,
					(2002):35-53 </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="gale2020" label="Gale 2020"> Gale Digital Scholar Lab (2020) Accessed July 11, 2020. <ref target="https://www.gale.com/intl/primary-sources/digital-scholar-lab">https://www.gale.com/intl/primary-sources/digital-scholar-lab</ref></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="jarlbrink2017" label="Jarlbrink 2017"> Jarlbrink, J., Snickars, P. <title rend="quotes">Cultural Heritage as Digital Noise: Nineteenth
					Century Newspapers in the Digital Archive.</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title>, 6
					(2017):1228–1243.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="kettunen2017" label="Kettunun et al. 2017"> Kettunen, K., Mäkelä, E., Ruokolainen, T., Kuokkala J. &amp; Löfberg, L <title rend="quotes">Old
					Content and Modern Tools – Searching Named Entities in a Finnish OCRed
					Historical Newspaper Collection 1771–1910.</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 11, 3,
					(2017)</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="kim2018" label="Kim 2018"> Kim, E., &amp; Klinger, R. <title rend="quotes">A Survey on Sentiment and Emotion Analysis for
					Computational Literary Studies.</title> <title rend="italic">arXiv preprint </title>arXiv:1808.03137 (2018).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="liu2012" label="Liu 2012"> Liu, B. <title rend="quotes">Sentiment Analysis and Opinion Mining.</title> <title rend="italic">Synthesis Lectures on Human
					Language Technologies</title>, 5(1), (2012): 1-167.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="mac2015" label="Mac and Cassidy 2015"> Mac, K. S. &amp; Cassidy, S. <title rend="quotes">Finding Names in Trove: Named Entity Recognition
					for Australian Historical Newspapers.</title>. In <title rend="italic">Proceedings of Australasian Language
					Technology Association Workshop</title>, (2015): 57−65.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="mediamonitoring" label="Media Monitoring 2020"> Media Monitoring of the Past: Mining 200 years of historical newspapers (2020).
					Accessed July 11, 2020 <ref target="https://impresso-project.ch/">https://impresso-project.ch/</ref></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="mendezmoreno1967" label="Méndez Moreno 1967"> Méndez Moreno, R. <title rend="quotes">El telégrafo en el destino nacional.</title> <title rend="italic">México Imprenta Arana</title>
					(1967). </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="neudecker2014" label="Neudecker et al. 2014"> Neudecker, C., Wilms, L., Jan Faber, W. &amp; van Veen, T. <title rend="quotes">Large-scale refinement
					of digital historic newspapers with named entity recognition.</title> in <title rend="italic">IFLA
					Newspapers/GENLOC Pre-Conference Satellite Meeting</title> (2014)</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="newseye2020" label="NewsEye 2020"> NewsEye (2020) Accessed July 11, 2020. <ref target="https://www.newseye.eu/">https://www.newseye.eu/</ref></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="oiva2019" label="Oiva et al. 2019"> Oiva, M., Nivala, A., Salmi, H., Latva, O., Jalava, M., Keck, J., Martínez
					Domínguez, L., Parker, J. <title rend="quotes">Spreading News in 1904: The Media Coverage of Nikolay
					Bobrikov’s Shooting.</title> Media History, (2019), DOI:
					<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/13688804.2019.1652090">https://doi.org/10.1080/13688804.2019.1652090</ref></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="priani2019" label="Priani et al. 2019"> Priani Saiso et al. <title rend="italic">Intercambios oceánicos Minicorpus.
					Retrieved</title> (2019). June 26, 2020, from <ref target="https://zenodo.org/record/3451482">https://zenodo.org/record/3451482</ref></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="sprugnoli2016" label="Sprugnoli et al. 2016"> Sprugnoli, R., Tonelli, S., Marchetti, A., &amp; Moretti, G. <title rend="quotes">Towards Sentiment
					Analysis for Historical Texts.</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 31(4), (2016): 762-772.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="schmidt2018a" label="Schmidt 2018a"> Schmidt, T., &amp; Burghardt, M. <title rend="quotes">An Evaluation of Lexicon-Based Sentiment
					Analysis Techniques for the Plays of gotthold ephraim lessing.</title>. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
					the Second Joint SIGHUM Workshop on Computational Linguistics for Cultural
					Heritage, Social Sciences, Humanities and Literature</title> (2018a):139-149.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="schmidt2018b" label="Schmidt et al. 2018b"> Schmidt, T., Burghardt, M., &amp; Dennerlein, K. <title rend="quotes">Sentiment Annotation of Historic
					German Plays: An Empirical Study on Annotation Behavior.</title> (2018b).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="vanderwood2010" label="Vanderwood 2010"> Vanderwood, P. <title rend="quotes">Betterment for Whom? The Reform Period: 1855-75.</title> In W. H. Beezley and M. C. Meyer (eds),<title rend="italic"> The Oxford History of Mexico</title>, Oxford,
					Oxford University Press (2010): 349-72 </bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="yang2011" label="Yang 2011"> Yang, T., Torget, A. &amp; Milhacea, R. <title rend="quotes">Topic Modeling on Historical Newspapers.</title>
					<title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 5th ACL-HLT Workshop on Language Technology for Cultural
					Heritage, Social Sciences, and Humanities</title>, (2011): 96–104,</bibl>
			</listBibl>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
