<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">An <soCalled>Open Lab?</soCalled> The Electronic
                    Textual Cultures Lab in the Evolving Digital Humanities Landscape</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Randa <dhq:family>El Khatib</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>khatib@uvic.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Randa El Khatib is the Assistant Director (Open Knowledge Initiatives) of
                            the Electronic Textual Cultures Lab (ETCL) and the Associate Director of
                            the Digital Humanities Summer Institute (DHSI). She is also the Managing
                            Editor of <title rend="italic">Early Modern Digital Review</title> and a
                            doctoral candidate in English at the University of Victoria. Her
                            research focuses on early modern literature, geospatial humanities, and
                            open scholarship.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Alyssa <dhq:family>Arbuckle</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>alyssaa@uvic.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Alyssa Arbuckle is the Associate Director of the Electronic Textual
                            Cultures Lab (ETCL) at the University of Victoria, where she serves as
                            the Project Manager for the Implementing New Knowledge Environments
                            (INKE) Partnership, and is a member of the Directorial Group and the
                            Operational Team for the Digital Humanities Summer Institute (DHSI).
                            Alyssa is also an interdisciplinary PhD Candidate at the University of
                            Victoria, studying open social scholarship and its implementation.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Lynne <dhq:family>Siemens</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>siemensl@uvic.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Lynne Siemens is an Associated Researcher in the Electronic Textual
                            Cultures Lab and an Associate Professor in the School of Public
                            Administration, University of Victoria. Her research interests include
                            academic entrepreneurship, teams, collaboration and project management
                            with a focus on knowledge mobilization and transfer at individual,
                            organizational and community levels.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Ray <dhq:family>Siemens</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>siemens@uvic.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Ray Siemens (<ref target="http://web.uvic.ca/~siemens/"
                                >http://web.uvic.ca/~siemens/</ref>) directs the Electronic Textual
                            Cultures Lab, the Implementing New Knowledge Environments project, and
                            the Digital Humanities Summer Institute. He is Distinguished Professor
                            in the Faculty of Humanities at the University of Victoria, in English
                            and Computer Science, and past Canada Research Chair in Humanities
                            Computing (2004-15); in 2019-20, he is also Leverhulme Visiting
                            Professor at Loughborough U (2019-20) and Global Innovation Chair in
                            Digital Humanities at U Newcastle (2019-22).</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Caroline <dhq:family>Winter</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>winterc@uvic.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Caroline Winter is the Open Scholarship Facilitator at the Electronic
                            Textual Cultures Lab (ETCL). She is also a PhD candidate in English at
                            the University of Victoria, where she studies British Romantic
                            literature and digital humanities. Her other research interests include
                            Gothic literature, women’s writing, literature and economics, and book
                            history.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>ETCL Research Group <!--<dhq:family/>--></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>etcl@uvic.ca</email>
                    <!--<dhq:bio>
                        <p/>-->
                    <!--</dhq:bio>-->
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000480</idno>
                <idno type="volume">014</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2020-09-25">25 September 2020</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2022-08-10" who="BRG">updated research group documentation to pass validation</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>As the scholarly landscape evolves into a more <q>open</q> plain, so do the
                    shapes of institutions, labs, centres, and other places and spaces of research,
                    including those of the digital humanities (DH). The continuing success of such
                    research largely depends on a commitment to open access and open source
                    philosophies that broaden opportunities for a more efficient, productive, and
                    universal design and use of knowledge. The Electronic Textual Cultures
                    Laboratory (ETCL; <ref target="https://etcl.uvic.ca/">etcl.uvic.ca</ref>) is a
                    collaborative centre for digital and open scholarly practices at the University
                    of Victoria, Canada, that engages with these transformations in knowledge
                    creation through its umbrella organization, the Canadian Social Knowledge
                    Institute (C-SKI), that coordinates and supports open social scholarship
                    activities across three major initiatives: the ETCL itself, the Digital
                    Humanities Summer Institute (DHSI; dhsi.org), and the Implementing New Knowledge
                    Environments (INKE; inke.ca) Partnership, including sub-projects associated with
                    each. Open social scholarship is the practice of creating and disseminating
                    public-facing scholarship through accessible means. Working through C-SKI, we
                    seek ways to engage communities more widely with publicly funded humanities
                    scholarship, such as through research creation and dissemination, mentorship,
                    and skills training.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>This article discusses how the Electronic Textual Cultures Lab aims to promote
                    open social scholarship.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The digital medium has impacted modes of scholarly communication, as well as
                    research practices including collaboration, knowledge dissemination, and
                    engagement. Over the last few decades, the scholarly landscape has been steadily
                    shifting toward embracing open scholarship, defined as the <quote rend="inline"
                        >wide and broad dissemination of scholarship by a variety of interconnected
                        means (e.g., technology, licensing) aiming to broaden knowledge and reduce
                        barriers to access to knowledge and information</quote>
                    <ptr target="#veletsianos2016" loc="16"/>. Open scholarship comprises open
                    access publications, open educational resources, open data, and open source
                    software, among other things, and provides the foundation for an evolving
                    research culture that privileges broad accessibility and participation by
                    academics and non-academics. Committing to open scholarship practices is an
                    ethical and practical option for scholarly communication and knowledge creation
                        <ptr target="#guedon2008"/>, fulfilling the mandate of scholarship to
                    create, share, and disseminate knowledge <ptr target="#cohen2010"/>
                    <ptr target="#willinsky2006"/>. More efficient workflows and work environments
                    result when practitioners can draw from, borrow, repurpose, and build on
                    already-developed research and data.</p>
                <p>Collectively, we consider this embrace of a more public, accessible, and
                    participatory research culture as <hi rend="italic">open social
                    scholarship</hi>. As a concept, open social scholarship has grown from roots in
                    open access and open scholarship movements, the digital humanities’
                    methodological commons and community of practice <ptr target="#siemens2016"/>,
                    contemporary online practices, and citizen scholarship. The Implementing New
                    Knowledge Environments (INKE) Partnership has defined open social scholarship as
                        <quote rend="inline">creating and disseminating research and research
                        technologies to a broad, interdisciplinary audience of specialists and
                        non-specialists in ways that are accessible and significant</quote>
                    <ptr target="#powell2017" loc="3"/>. Within this conception of the term, open
                    social scholarship manifests in different ways, including by developing,
                    sharing, and implementing research in ways that consider the needs and interests
                    of both academic specialists and communities beyond academia. Open social
                    scholarship also provides opportunities to co-create, interact with, and
                    experience openly available cultural data. Moreover, this type of engagement
                    encourages the exploration, development, and creation of public tools and
                    technologies under open licenses to promote wide access, education, use, and
                    repurposing. Overall, open social scholarship practices enable productive
                    dialogue between academics and non-academics, resisting what is often perceived
                    as a closed circuit of academic knowledge. Refiguring scholarly communication as
                    open access to knowledge enables the public to occupy a more central position in
                    community-engaged university practices; in turn, this has the potential to lead
                    to more democratic and participatory knowledge production.</p>
                <p>As the scholarly landscape evolves into a more open plain, so does the shape of
                    institutions, labs, centres, and other places and spaces of research, including
                    those of the digital humanities (DH). Both a theory- and practice-based field,
                    digital humanities (DH) attracts practitioners with a theoretical understanding
                    of knowledge creation, as well as the skills to modify existing forms of
                    knowledge production and dissemination and to create new tools and platforms
                        <ptr target="#jones2014"/>. Digital humanists often encourage open social
                    scholarship by using technology to engage with members of the public through
                    projects that involve crowdsourcing or citizen scholarship <ptr
                        target="#ridge2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#rockwell2012"/>. Additionally, DH operates through highly
                    collaborative structures <ptr target="#siemens2010b"/> spanning
                    cross-departmental and -campus research, and often extending between
                    collaborators in different universities, countries, or even continents. This,
                    then, grounds open social scholarship in both physical and virtual spaces,
                    harnessing the benefits of both. The coming together of researchers in a
                    physical space allows for the development of shared values and common ground
                    around values of openness, which can then be extended through virtual networks
                    of researchers. The continuing success of such research largely depends on a
                    commitment to these philosophies that broaden opportunities for more efficient,
                    productive, and universal design and use of knowledge.</p>
                <p>Consequently, this paper is based on the premise that there is a correlation
                    between the developing knowledge landscape and the structure of an intellectual
                    centre, especially when it is committed to <soCalled>open</soCalled> values
                    (e.g., open access, source, data, knowledge); the evolution of the knowledge
                    landscape necessarily affects the intellectual structures built upon it.
                    Specifically, we focus on the Electronic Textual Cultures Lab (ETCL; <ref
                        target="https://etcl.uvic.ca/">etcl.uvic.ca</ref>) — a collaborative centre
                    for digital and open scholarly practices at the University of Victoria, Canada —
                    and demonstrate how the lab’s <soCalled>intellectual space</soCalled> has
                    shifted to espouse open social scholarship in research, skills training, and
                    community-oriented initiatives in response to a changing knowledge landscape.
                    The ETCL’s “intellectual space” is based in the physical lab but operates
                    through in-person and virtual collaborations across different initiatives and
                    projects. Within this intellectual space, we engage with intersecting areas of
                    new media, digital humanities, open access, and digital publishing. Leading
                    scholarly communication researcher Kathleen Fitzpatrick (2019) contextualizes
                    these many threads within a framework of public engagement, calling for a shift
                    in mindset toward what she calls <quote rend="inline">generous thinking</quote>:<cit>
                        <quote rend="block">By finding ways to connect with readers and writers
                            beyond our usual circles of experts, in a range of different registers,
                            and in ways that move beyond enabling <emph>them</emph> to listen to
                                <emph>us</emph> to instead allow for meaningful dialogue and
                            collaboration, we can create the possibilities for far more substantial
                            public participation in and engagement with a wide range of kinds of
                            academic work. We can build programs and networks and platforms that do
                            not just bring the university to the world, but also involve the world
                            in the university. <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2019" loc="135"/></quote>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>For Fitzpatrick, the evolution of the university must include more purposeful
                    connection between academics and the public they serve. The ETCL is attempting
                    to make such connections with its local and global communities — acknowledging
                    that perspectives on research and its engagement, like the important
                    relationships that bring us together in collaboration with others, change over
                    time. To this end, we have adopted a versatile lab structure and infrastructure:
                    today in support of open social scholarship in the many branches of the ETCL,
                    but previously in support of research-related antecedents to this current
                    focus.</p>
                <p>In what follows, we will situate the ETCL in the current knowledge landscape
                    alongside other digital scholarship centres to explore the various roles these
                    units occupy with respect to the communities they serve, focusing on the larger
                    cultural change toward more open, accessible, and inclusive practices. The
                    second part of this paper will address how the ETCL’s intellectual space and
                    infrastructure model has shifted to espouse open scholarship across its
                    research, teaching, and service aims by launching the Canadian Social Knowledge
                    Institute (C-SKI), the umbrella organization that facilitates the ETCL itself,
                    as well as the Digital Humanities Summer Institute (DHSI) and Implementing New
                    Knowledge Environments (INKE). Overall, we aim to demonstrate how the place and
                    space of a research lab can engage communities more widely with publicly funded
                    humanities output, including through research creation and dissemination,
                    mentorship, and skills training.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>I. Lab infrastructure and the evolving knowledge landscape</head>
                <p>Humanities scholars have been experimenting with computational modes of inquiry
                    for decades now. But in the early 2000s, this activity became formalized under
                    the banner of <soCalled>digital humanities.</soCalled> As Matthew Kirschenbaum
                    remarks in his foundational article <title rend="quotes">What Is Digital
                        Humanities and What Is It Doing in English Departments?,</title> the 2001
                    debate over the naming of an anthology — <title rend="italic">A Companion to
                        Digital Humanities</title> (2004), co-edited by Ray Siemens, Susan
                    Schreibman, and John Unsworth — is often considered to be the point when the
                    digital humanities was officially named as such <ptr target="#unsworth2010"/>.
                    Founded in 2004 by Siemens, the ETCL was an early-established DH lab. Currently
                    led by Ray Siemens as Director, Alyssa Arbuckle as Associate Director, Randa El
                    Khatib as Assistant Director (Open Knowledge Initiatives), Luis Meneses as
                    Assistant Director (Technical Development), and Jannaya Friggstad Jensen as
                    Assistant Director (Coordination and Operations), the lab serves as an
                    intellectual centre for the activities of about 40 local faculty, staff,
                    students, visiting scholars, and community members, and more than 150 since
                    inception. Through a series of highly collaborative relationships, the ETCL’s
                    international community comprises more than 300 researchers and more than 50
                    collaborative partners.</p>
                <p>The ETCL was initially modeled on the structure of successful university-based
                    science research labs, adapted for DH researchers. In 2012, Lynne Siemens and
                    Ray Siemens outlined a number of research lab models in <title rend="quotes"
                        >Notes from the Collaboratory,</title> a presentation at the annual
                    international Digital Humanities conference. In this piece, Siemens and Siemens
                    generally divide collaborative research modes into collaboratories and
                    faculty-directed laboratories. Collaboratories, also known as <soCalled>centres
                        without walls,</soCalled> are shared spaces for researchers who create,
                    contribute to, and draw from common resources such as databases and
                    supercomputers within an overarching research area, although their direct
                    research projects may be different <ptr target="#siemens2012" loc="1"/>. Other
                    models for collaboration include those of a multiple-researcher directed
                        <soCalled>co-laboratory</soCalled> and single-researcher director
                        <soCalled>collaborat-ory,</soCalled> both of which are adaptable to a
                    humanities context <ptr target="#glasner1996" loc="111"/>
                    <ptr target="#siemens2012" loc="1"/>. The ETCL’s current structure is an
                    expansion of the faculty-directed laboratory, where the lab’s overall success is
                    measured through outputs that meet <quote rend="inline">standard academic and
                        funding agency benchmarks that [include] measurable research resource
                        intake, provision of teaching and service, and research outputs, such as
                        books, articles, conference papers, and other types of production, more
                        DH-oriented research outputs in the form of tools and prototype development,
                        and further issues</quote>
                    <ptr target="#siemens2012" loc="2"/>. Although still relying on the
                    faculty-directed structure outlined in 2012, the ETCL has significantly expanded
                    its team and operational model since that time; it currently operates under the
                    leadership of the director and directorial team who all produce academically
                    measurable outputs, in part as a means to reach formal targets tied to grant
                    funding and ongoing use of research space <ptr target="#cantwell2011"/>. These
                    measurable outputs are integral to the continuous operation of a lab <ptr
                        target="#siemens2012"/>.</p>
                <p>Our shared thinking about the lab, what our roles and functions are, and how that
                    is manifest in our structure and operation are quite conscious and deliberate —
                    as are, for us, the contexts in which we work. Aligned with Vivian Lewis, Lisa
                    Spiro, Xuemao Wang, and Jon E. Cawthorne in their report <title rend="italic"
                        >Building Expertise to Support Digital Scholarship: A Global
                        Perspective</title> (2015), we agree that digital scholarship is <quote
                        rend="inline">thriving</quote>
                    <ptr target="#lewis2015" loc="vii"/> and have noted that the landscape of
                    scholarship has changed dramatically in just a few years, encompassing a new set
                    of methodologies, tools, and research materials that enable researchers to ask
                    new types of questions but also require new sets of skills <ptr
                        target="#lewis2015" loc="viii"/>. We have seen ourselves situated in this
                    milieu from the start — as a type of digital scholarship centre essential in
                    this new scholarly landscape because we offer space, both physical and social,
                    for collaboration and access to technology and technological expertise that is
                    often not available elsewhere on campus.</p>
                <p>We have noted that digital scholarship centres take different forms at different
                    institutions, but generally speaking, a common function regardless of size and
                    scope is to be a hub for digital scholarship that facilitates and provides both
                    physical and virtual space for collaboration, access to tools and resources, and
                    services for researchers broadly defined, including students, faculty, and staff
                    from across campus and citizen scholars from the local community. Discussion
                    about digital scholarship centres within the academic community tends to focus
                    on the role of institutional libraries in establishing centres and supporting
                    digital scholarship (see <ptr target="#cox2016"/>). Libraries are uniquely
                    appropriate sites for digital scholarship centres because they serve all
                    departments and faculties, making them a central hub for research within an
                    institution and a neutral space for interdisciplinary collaboration <ptr
                        target="#bergstrom2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#lippincott2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#sinclair2014"/>. In addition, academic libraries are already
                    innovators in digital scholarship, and librarians have expertise to collaborate
                    with researchers and support digital scholarship projects. Rebecca Dowson notes,
                    for example, that Simon Fraser University Libraries’ Research Commons model
                    developed in response to changes in the scholarly landscape, supporting digital
                    scholarship just as the Information Commons model supports the transition from
                    print to digital research resources and the Learning Commons model supports
                    learning and academic communication (2016). Dowson points out that, although
                    Research Commons support different kinds and stages of research creation, and
                    are therefore not necessarily sites of digital scholarship, <quote rend="inline"
                        >the two concepts share a number of core values, including an ethos of
                        openness, interdisciplinarity, collaboration, and focus on knowledge
                        creation and new modes of production</quote>
                    <ptr target="#dowson2016"/>.</p>
                <p>Each digital scholarship centre is designed to meet the needs of its own research
                    community, so they vary in size, structure, and function <ptr
                        target="#bergstrom2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#lewis2015"/>. For example, the ETCL is situated in the Digital
                    Scholarship Commons of the McPherson Library at the University of Victoria. The
                    Digital Scholarship Commons is a space for community training in digital tools
                    and methodologies, interdisciplinary work, and presentations; it also houses the
                    Humanities Computing and Media Centre — a space supported by the Faculty of
                    Humanities in which software developers and experts in research and
                    instructional design provide service and support for faculty members and their
                    projects. Many times, lab, centre, and commons all denote the same thing, and,
                    at times, the choice of one over the other is made because of local preferences
                    or issues such as administratively-controlled vocabularies.</p>
                <p>Although there is no standard nomenclature for digital scholarship centres, they
                    can generally be categorized in two ways: commons-type centres and lab- or
                    makerspace-type centres. Commons-type centres tend to be service-driven,
                    providing access to shared resources much like the collaboratory model described
                    above, and serving the entire institutional community and often the local
                    community as well <ptr target="#siemens2012" loc="1"/>. Many have stronger
                    relationships with the social sciences and humanities research communities than
                    with other disciplines, possibly because similar resources for STEM (Science,
                    Technology, Engineering and Mathematics) disciplines are available elsewhere on
                    campus <ptr target="#bergstrom2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#ippoliti2016"/>. In contrast, digital scholarship labs and
                    makerspaces are generally open to a specific group of researchers only and may
                    focus on DH specifically, although, like the ETCL, they often engage with the
                    associated researchers from across the university and the local community as
                    well. Lab-type centres tend to be research-driven, aligning them with the
                    faculty-directed <soCalled>co-laboratory</soCalled> and
                        <soCalled>collaborat-ory</soCalled> models discussed above, although many —
                    again, like the ETCL — also embrace some service and teaching functions related
                    to their research mandates. Some educational programming is common across all
                    types of digital scholarship centres, including workshops and other training
                    programs and talks by in-house or visiting speakers. Many centres also provide
                    access to technologies that are otherwise difficult for their community to
                    access, such as 3D printing equipment and software, virtual reality technology,
                    specialized software and, importantly, training and technological support.
                    Typical services offered by commons-type centres to the entire university
                    community, for example, include consultation, data preservation, support for
                    digital scholarly communication, and metadata creation and management <ptr
                        target="#ippoliti2016"/>.</p>
                <p>Studies about digital scholarship centres tend to emphasize their innovative
                    nature and the vibrancy of their communities. While most such studies to date
                    have a US or global focus (see, for example, <ptr target="#bergstrom2016"/> and
                        <ptr target="#ippoliti2016"/>), similar innovations are evident in the
                    Canadian context, and the number of Canadian digital scholarship centres
                    continues to increase. The digital scholarship ecosystem in Canada is complex,
                    comprising numerous centres uniquely designed to meet the needs of their
                    particular institutional community. Regardless of their idiosyncrasies, these
                    centres can be broadly categorized as either commons-type or lab-type.</p>
                <p>Many of the commons-type centres are located within the university library and
                    are open to the entire university community. They offer collaborative learning
                    spaces, pedagogical support, research collaboration and consultation, workshops,
                    events, and scholarly communication support, including for open scholarship.
                    Examples of these centres in Canada include the Digital Scholarship Lab at Brock
                    University, Lab NEXT at the University of Calgary,<note>Christie Hurrell
                        discusses the development of Lab NEXT in <title rend="quotes">Aligning the
                            Stars: Understanding Digital Scholarship Needs to Support the Evolving
                            Nature of Academic Research</title> (<ref target="#hurrell2019"
                            >2019</ref>).</note> the Innovation Commons at McGill University, the
                    Centre for Digital Scholarship at the University of New Brunswick, and the
                    Digital Scholarship Commons at the University of Victoria (the larger group of
                    which the ETCL is a part). York University’s Digital Scholarship Centre appears
                    unique insofar as it is open to the entire university community, but is located
                    within the library serving students and researchers in the Humanities and Social
                    Sciences, Fine Arts, and Environmental Studies. In its focus on a particular
                    research community within the university, York’s centre is like many other
                    commons-type digital scholarship centres that are located in the university
                    library but open to specific groups of researchers, particularly graduate
                    students, postgraduate researchers, and faculty. This type of centre offers many
                    of the same services and programming as those described above, but is geared
                    toward supporting research and publication — including open forms of publication
                    — rather than undergraduate learning, although most welcome undergraduate
                    students who are part of a faculty-led project. Some examples of these
                    research-focused commons-type centres include the Lewis &amp; Ruth Sherman
                    Centre for Digital Scholarship at McMaster University, the Digital Research
                    Centre at the University of Saskatchewan, the Research Commons at Simon Fraser
                    University, UBC’s Advanced Research Computing, the Humanities Computing and
                    Media Centre at the University of Victoria, the University of Windsor’s Centre
                    for Digital Scholarship, and the University of Guelph’s Digital Scholarship
                    support program, which — unlike the other centres — is a cluster of services
                    based in the library rather than a physical space within it. Brock University
                    has a second digital scholarship centre — the Centre for Digital Humanities —
                    that offers many similar services to its Digital Scholarship Lab, but outside of
                    the library and for students in specific Humanities programs only.</p>
                <p>Similar to commons-type digital scholarship centres, lab- and maker-space type
                    centres tend to be highly collaborative and interdisciplinary. Although they are
                    generally faculty-led and research oriented, most also offer talks, workshops,
                    and other programming open to the university community. The ETCL and the Centre
                    for Digital Humanities at Ryerson University are examples of labs with interests
                    in teaching and training, as well as open scholarship. Some are located within
                    university libraries and learning centres, such as the ETCL, the University of
                    Alberta’s Canadian Institute for Research in Computing and the Arts (CIRCA), and
                    the Digital Humanities Innovation Lab (DHIL) at Simon Fraser University, while
                    others are not. Many focus on specific themes or clusters of themes, or
                    otherwise target specific community needs. The Centre de recherche
                    interuniversitaire sur les humanités numériques (CRIHN) at the University of
                    Montréal, for example, brings together digital humanities researchers from
                    several universities in Québec, while Western University’s Cultureplex Lab
                    enables collaboration between humanities scholars, entrepreneurs, computer
                    scientists, and engineers. Other examples of lab-type digital humanities centres
                    in Canada include the University of British Columbia’s Emerging Media Lab (EML),
                    the AMP Lab at UBC Okanagan, Carleton University’s Hyperlab, the University of
                    Ottawa’s Humanities + Data Lab, and the MeTA Digital Humanities lab at Vancouver
                    Island University. As this brief survey reveals, each of these digital
                    scholarship centres is unique in structure and focus; they all, however,
                    emphasize interdisciplinarity and collaboration within the Canadian research
                    context.</p>
                <p>In this vital and thriving context of digital scholarship in Canada, and
                    especially in consideration of ETCL’s move to the UVic Digital Scholarship
                    Commons in January 2017, it is important to note that ETCL has expanded in size
                    and scope as part of its evolution over time. Although we still undertake many
                    digital humanities projects and initiatives — most notably by facilitating the
                    annual Digital Humanities Summer Institute — many ETCL constituents are now
                    active in open social scholarship through theoretical and practical engagements,
                    as described in the following section. The ETCL is not the only digital
                    humanities group to shift focus toward more open and more social practices. In
                    fact, this movement could be considered as emblematic of a larger cultural
                    change in the field. Among other venues, this shift is emphasized in the
                    thematic community focus of representative collections like <title rend="italic"
                        >Collaborative Research in the Digital Humanities</title>
                    <ptr target="#deegan2012"/>, <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities</title>
                    <ptr target="#gold2012"/>, <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities 2016</title>
                    <ptr target="#goldklein2016"/>, as well as <title rend="italic">Doing Digital
                        Humanities</title>
                    <ptr target="#crompton2016"/> and <title rend="italic">Doing More Digital
                        Humanities</title>
                    <ptr target="#crompton2020"/> that have emanated from the DHSI community. Most
                    notably in these collections, see Brennan (2016) and Hsu (2016) on public
                    humanities; Brown (2016) on collaborative knowledge production; Gil and Ortega
                    (2016) and Liu (2012) on the necessity of racial diversification; Hockey (2012)
                    on cross-community collaboration; Losh (2012) on the role of activism; McPherson
                    (2012) on inequality; Wernimont and Losh (2016) on the need for intersectional
                    feminism; and Williams (2012) on the value of accessibility. Many digital
                    humanities practitioners are reconsidering their role in local, national, and
                    international contexts that extend beyond the academic world. Such a
                    disciplinary turn toward matters of social justice, collaboration, and social
                    media acknowledges a changing tide of consciousness around how the humanities is
                    constituted as an academic field, as well as what its role is (or could be) in
                    the larger social sphere.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>II. Lab practices that engage open social scholarship across research,
                    teaching, and service</head>
                <p>Recognizing our community’s distinct momentum toward open social scholarship, the
                    ETCL and INKE launched the Canadian Social Knowledge Institute (C-SKI; <ref
                        target="https://inke.ca/projects/canadian-social-knowledge-institute/"
                        >https://inke.ca/projects/canadian-social-knowledge-institute/</ref>) in
                    2015. C-SKI helps coordinate and support INKE-related and other open social
                    scholarship activities across our three major initiatives: the ETCL itself, the
                    Digital Humanities Summer Institute (DHSI; dhsi.org), and the INKE Partnership
                    (inke.ca), including sub-projects associated with each. Through research
                    creation and dissemination in open venues, mentorship, and skills training,
                    C-SKI seeks ways to engage communities more widely with publicly funded
                    humanities output.</p>
                <p>Once the C-SKI structure was in place, we held a visioning meeting in spring 2018
                    with select current and past members in order to reflect formally on the
                    developments and infrastructural changes of the ETCL and to plan the lab’s next
                    steps. In addition to our thinking about how the intellectual space of the ETCL
                    is interconnected, the outcome of this exercise was to reflect our shifting
                    direction by updating the ETCL mandate, mission, and values statements. Our ETCL
                    mandate is to be <quote rend="inline">a collaborative centre for digital and
                        open scholarly practices. We are a multidisciplinary team of faculty, staff,
                        students, and visiting scholars who engage on- and off-campus partners
                        through research, skills training, and community-oriented
                        initiatives</quote>
                    <ptr target="#etclhome"/>. Our mission is to engage, facilitate, and promote
                    cross-community digital initiatives at the University of Victoria, as well as in
                    the larger regional, national, and international contexts by cultivating the
                    practices and values of open social scholarship <ptr target="#etclhome"/>. These
                    tie into our values — namely our dedication to community-driven scholarship that
                    recognizes collaborative models of knowledge sharing; open practices in digital
                    research, production, and dissemination; the intellectual development and
                    well-being of our communities; shared mentorship, accountability, and support
                    across multiple disciplines, professions, and groups; and inclusive and ethical
                    practices, as outlined in the DHSI Statement on Ethics and Inclusion (see <ptr
                        target="#dhsi"/>) <ptr target="#etclvalues"/>. These values reflect the
                    ETCL’s main direction over the last few years: to understand and practice open
                    social scholarship.</p>
                <p>Another goal of the ETCL visioning meeting was to propose various infrastructural
                    models that may best describe how C-SKI transfuses its open social scholarship
                    mandate to other aspects of the lab. Two models that seemed particularly
                    relevant were <quote rend="inline">lab as incubator</quote> and <quote
                        rend="inline">lab as tree.</quote> Not to be confused with
                        <soCalled>academic incubator,</soCalled> which typically refers to an
                    informal space to develop partnerships between students / the university and
                    non-university / industry-based representatives or investors with the goal of
                    facilitating entrepreneurship <ptr target="#gensler"/>, the <quote rend="inline"
                        >lab as incubator</quote> reflects the ETCL’s goal of developing and
                    sustaining an environment that cultivates open social scholarship. The incubator
                    metaphor also reflects the idea that a lab should be a positive space for growth
                    — in our case, one that has facilitated ETCL, DHSI, and INKE to develop into
                    their current forms, and also to embrace a larger frame of collaborative
                    research with others as they move toward open social and scholarship themselves.
                    The second model, <quote rend="inline">lab as tree,</quote> represents something
                    living and growing that serves as a foundation and support for new growth. A
                    tree also depends on communication between all of its constituent parts, and
                    more accurately reflects the sub-branches that grow out of the separate
                    branches. As early as the 13th century, trees have been employed as metaphors
                    for structuring and categorizing knowledge, such as in Ramon Llull’s structuring
                    of the sciences in <title rend="italic">Arbor Scientiae</title> (1295), or Tree
                    of Science <ptr target="#gontier2011" loc="523"/> (figure 1).</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Ramon Llull, <title rend="italic">Arbor scientie.</title> Image Provided
                        by Harvard University: <ref
                            target="https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/ids:28468922"
                            >https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/ids:28468922</ref></head>
                    <figDesc>Two people standing under a tree with text woven into the roots and
                        tree branches.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The tree metaphor for organization and categorization has been widely employed as
                    a strategy to aid thinking and categorization in numerous disciplines,
                    especially the sciences, in fields like biology <ptr target="#mindell2013"/>,
                    and is often used in computing <ptr target="#forisek2013" loc="20"/>.
                    Additionally, the tree metaphor at once reflects the deep, 16-year roots of the
                    ETCL at both the University of Victoria and in the DH community. In either
                    representation, as an incubator or the trunk of a tree, the lab is a
                    foundational element that supports the whole. By extending this metaphor of
                        <quote rend="inline">lab as tree,</quote> the rest of this article will
                    follow the main branches of the Canadian Social Knowledge Institute, the goals
                    of each, and the ways that they intersect.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>1. First Branch: Electronic Textual Cultures Lab (ETCL)</head>
                    <p>The ETCL is the research-intensive component of the tree, and houses multiple
                        graduate research assistants, postdoctoral fellows, and a number of staff
                        members, and is also open to the rest of the university and the public
                        through directed practicums and fellowships.</p>
                    <p>According to Amy Earhart (2015), DH labs resemble science labs in that they
                            <quote rend="inline">contain equipment utilized by digital humanists,
                            emphasize collaborative research, and focus on theoretical and applied
                            research</quote>; however, they also train and mentor students and
                        faculty, <quote rend="inline">serving as pedagogical and outreach or service
                            arms dedicated to growing work within the field</quote> — tasks that are
                        typically carried out by separate bodies in the sciences <ptr
                            target="#earhart2015" loc="392"/>. Another difference between science
                        and DH labs that applies to the ETCL is the different layout of the two:
                            <quote rend="inline">[w]hile science labs are often clustered by area,
                            equipment or topic, digital humanities labs are often broader,
                            multipurpose, and more inclusive by both design and funding
                            limitations</quote>
                        <ptr target="#earhart2015" loc="392"/>. The ETCL’s intellectual space
                        operates in both physical place and virtual space. The physical place is
                        grounded in the ETCL and its associated programs, which are described below.
                        The physical layout of the ETCL comprises a large room with multiple
                        workstations and meeting spaces. The open setup promotes collaboration, as
                        do the meeting spaces that are used for ETCL team members and partners
                        beyond the lab. Equipment, such as 3D printers, scanners, and software can
                        be used by everyone working in the lab. There is also a lab library that
                        includes many print texts on digital humanities, digital scholarship,
                        publishing, and open scholarship, among other topics including many in the
                        traditional, historical humanities. Based in the physical place, the virtual
                        space comprises a network of associated researchers and communities beyond
                        the lab. ETCL members have confirmed that despite the growth of virtual
                        tools (such as Skype, listservs, emails, project coordination websites,
                        etc.), face-to-face interactions in a physical space remain important <ptr
                            target="#daft1987"/>
                        <ptr target="#siemens2010a"/>. By meeting in this context, the network of
                        ETCL members and affiliates develop common ground and shared values. Having
                        shared values means that we can more easily communicate with each other and
                        be more connected as a network able to support mutual goals related to open
                        social scholarship <ptr target="#bos2010"/>
                        <ptr target="#carroll2009"/>
                        <ptr target="#olson2000"/>
                        <ptr target="#olson2014"/>.</p>
                    <p>The lab itself can be thought of as <quote rend="inline">the place where it
                            all happens,</quote> since it is the physical place in which we
                        cultivate the ETCL’s intellectual space, organize DHSI, and develop the
                        research infrastructure that supports a significant portion of INKE’s
                        intellectual direction and activity; these are discussed as separate
                        branches below. Beyond coordinating DHSI and INKE, the lab also supports
                        multiple projects of its own and largely functions as a mechanism for
                        community building across and beyond campus. In part this occurs through
                        multiple speaker series — including the Nuts and Bolts discussions designed
                        to focus on the pragmatics of digital research and the Digital Scholarship
                        on Tap interdisciplinary lecture series that brings together researchers to
                        share their different disciplinary perspectives on a common topic (e.g.,
                        digital mapping), each evolving out of years of earlier, less formal
                        presentations about ongoing research that typically took place mid-day and
                        to which people brought their packed lunches and ate while they listened and
                        discussed. Through these collegial talks and discussions, the lab builds a
                        community around developments in digital scholarship, research, and teaching
                        in an increasingly digitized world. The ETCL also supports activities in
                        open social scholarship through the Open Knowledge Program, through which it
                        opens up the physical place of the lab for fellows across campus, and from
                        the local and global communities. In what follows we discuss the Open
                        Knowledge Program and how it relates to or embodies the ETCL’s open social
                        scholarship ethos.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>1.1 Open Knowledge Program</head>
                    <p>In the last few decades, academic institutions have witnessed a recurring
                        call to engage the public more actively. Engagement is considered both in
                        terms of opening the space of the institution and in reorienting its focus
                        towards more public-facing scholarship, culminating in the rise of the
                        public humanities <ptr target="#brown1995"/>
                        <ptr target="#jay2012"/>. More recently, this call has been answered by
                        projects that draw on citizen scholarship, citizen science, and other forms
                        of community-engaged scholarship, made easier with the development of more
                        user-friendly and accessible technologies <ptr target="#bonney2009"/>
                        <ptr target="#newman2012"/>
                        <ptr target="#hoy2013"/>. We see this shift toward more publicly-engaged
                        scholarship as an opportunity to open up the physical place of the ETCL to
                        university and community members and to expand the dissemination of
                        lab-related research through more public-facing scholarly communication
                        channels. One of the ways the lab embraces this shift is through the Open
                        Knowledge Program (<ref target="https://etcl.uvic.ca/okp/"
                            >https://etcl.uvic.ca/okp/</ref>), launched in 2017 from earlier
                        informal origins, which comprises a suite of activities that include the
                        Open Knowledge Practicum, the Open Knowledge Practicum@DHSI, and the Open
                        Knowledge Residency.<note>The ETCL’s Open Knowledge Program also hosts the
                            Honorary Resident Wikipedian initiative, in partnership with the
                            University of Victoria Libraries, the Implementing New Knowledge
                            Environments, and the Federation for the Humanities and Social Sciences.
                            The role of the Honorary Resident Wikipedian is to give lectures,
                            consult on Wikipedia pages, as well as set the theme for and lead two
                            Wikipedia edit-a-thons annually. Dr. Christian Vandendorpe (U Ottawa)
                            served in this role from 2014–16, and contributed his expertise to
                            improving pages on book history, the encyclopedia, and electronic
                            publishing. Dr. Constance Crompton (U Ottawa) served from 2017–18, and
                            focused on women in STEM on Wikipedia, making Wikipedia a more reliable
                            resource, and contributing to other Wikimedia Foundation projects,
                            especially Wikidata. Dr. Erin Glass (DigitalOcean) assumed this position
                            for the 2019–2020 academic year, and focused on open access in the age
                            of surveillance technology and the role of public imagination in
                            conceptualizing alternative technologies to the status quo. The incoming
                            2020-2021 Honorary Resident Wikipedian is Silvia Gutiérrez De la Torre
                            (El Colegio de México) who will be leading virtual Wikipedia
                            edit-a-thons that address how students, faculty, and staff can mitigate
                            the barriers to diversity in Wikipedia by tackling the free-time and
                            gender gap, the digital divide, and the lack of resources for certain
                            subjects.</note></p>
                    <p>The Open Knowledge Practicum invites non-lab affiliates from the local on-
                        and off-campus community in the Greater Victoria Region to bring their own
                        public-facing project interests and research into the lab. As of spring
                        2020, the practicum is in its fourth year, and consists of four-month
                        fellowships, although fellows may choose to extend their practicum for more
                        than one term. The lab’s role is to provide support, consultation, and
                        mentorship and to strategize research plans with fellows. As part of the
                        practicum, fellows are also offered honorariums, often in the form of DHSI
                        tuition scholarships that provide training in technical and theoretical
                        areas necessary to fellows’ projects. Fellows contribute to Wikipedia and
                        publish their projects in online, public venues, and are also involved in
                        the day-to-day lab life and events on and off campus. Recently, the Open
                        Knowledge Practicum has expanded to support faculty partnerships, where the
                        ETCL houses larger projects and their lead investigators in the lab, while
                        providing support, training, and mentorship to the student researchers
                        working on that project through fellowship positions.</p>
                    <p>The Open Knowledge Practicum@DHSI is a highly focused version of the
                        practicum that runs annually over the three days preceding DHSI, and is open
                        to DHSI attendees and instructors. During the practicum, fellows develop a
                        well-defined project related to their work, with the goal of sharing the
                        project in a public venue such as Wikipedia. Honorariums for this fellowship
                        constitute accommodation and per diems, meant to support those travelling to
                        Victoria for the additional stretch preceding DHSI.</p>
                    <p>The third and most recent addition to the program is the Open Knowledge
                        Residency, a one-week intensive residency open to MA and PhD students in any
                        discipline at UVic to develop an aspect of their thesis, dissertation, or
                        any other formal project, with the support of the ETCL’s community and
                        resources. Like other programs in this stream, residents will contribute
                        some aspect of their project to an online, public venue, and will more
                        generally be exposed to the value of making scholarship accessible. The
                        residency is also meant to give graduate students a more formal experience
                        of working in a DH lab and help them develop digital skills by offering two
                        DHSI spots for each residency; together, these skills are meant to help
                        graduate students complete their projects but also help them develop
                        experience and transferable research skills in preparation for the job
                        market. With nearly 40 participants from the Open Knowledge Program in the
                        three years since its inception, and cohorts increasing steadily, the ETCL
                        is conscious about trying to keep the physical place of the lab open and
                        making research more broadly accessible to the public.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2. Second Branch: Digital Humanities Summer Institute (DHSI)</head>
                    <p>A global community is also involved in the <soCalled>place</soCalled> of the
                        lab annually at DHSI by spending up to two weeks on campus for the duration
                        of the institute. DHSI is a productive environment for acquiring and
                        developing digital humanities skills via knowledge transfer, networking,
                        collaboration, and community building. Launched in 2001, DHSI offers the
                        largest digital humanities curriculum in the world. It originated at
                        Malaspina University-College (now Vancouver Island University) as a
                        collection of early-career scholars who wished to build a supportive
                        community of practice around computational applications in the arts and
                        humanities; it was supported there by the Centre for Digital Humanities
                        Innovation, a predecessor of ETCL. Moving to the University of Victoria in
                        2004 when the ETCL was established there, DHSI grew from its roots as an
                        informal event (which we might today call an unconference) that initially
                        drew some 20–30 people to, by 2019, a formal institute with an annual
                        planning and operation cycle drawing some 850+ participants, with an
                        involved international collegiate of approximately 4,500 alumni. Since we
                        were unable to hold an in-person DHSI in 2020 due to the coronavirus disease
                        (COVID-19), the workshops and featured speakers originally scheduled for
                        DHSI 2020 were postponed to 2021. However, in lieu of the in-person
                        gathering, we hosted our first ever virtual institute, DHSI 2020 — Online
                        Edition, that moved several affiliated events online, including the DHSI
                        Conference and Colloquium and Alliance of Digital Humanities (ADHO) Special
                        Interest Group for DH Pedagogy and Training mini-conference, the Project
                        Management in the Humanities conference, the RTL (Right to Left) workshop,
                        and an EPoetry event #GraphPoem [<ref target="https://dhsi.org/dhsi-2020/"
                            >DHSI 2020 — Online Edition</ref>]. The event took place in the first
                        two weeks of June and brought together over 1200 participants from around
                        the world. Similarly, in 2016 we worked with the Electronic Literature
                        Organization (ELO) to host its annual international conference with DHSI, in
                        2017 with the Society for the History of Authorship, Reading, and Publishing
                        (SHARP) for its annual international conference, and in 2018 with the
                        Council on Library and Information Resources’ Digital Library Federation
                        (CLIR DLF) as well as the Symposium for Indigenous New Media.</p>
                    <p>In this way, DHSI is more than course-based training alone; rather, it offers
                        a recognized intermediary space for scholars, researchers, and students to
                        connect with colleagues from other disciplines and professions in and around
                        the digital humanities. Through a mix of courses, workshops, colloquiums,
                        conference activities, and networking events, participants meet to share
                        their research, interests, and expertise across traditionally divergent
                        lines of knowledge creation. DHSI’s participants include those on the
                        academic track seeking skills training and professionalization
                        opportunities, but they also readily come from outside the university
                        setting, such as those involved with cultural heritage activities, working
                        for the government or in the private sector, or simply curious non-academic
                        researchers or citizen scholars who want to acquire new skills and learn
                        about the work of our community.</p>
                    <p>A key point in DHSI’s commitment to openness and open social scholarship,
                        which exists on a number of levels, is that we welcome those who wish to
                        participate, from all backgrounds and interests. Many attendees are awarded
                        significant tuition scholarships to offset the cost of participating in the
                        institute. At times upward of 30% (~300) of attendees receive tuition
                        scholarships from DHSI or assistance from related external sponsorship. In
                        this way, we can offer opportunities that might not exist otherwise and
                        support participants by providing tangible means to help them attend and
                        participate in the institute. We also encourage course proposals from
                        members of our community; called <soCalled>community courses,</soCalled>
                        these offerings are intended to align with current interests, passions, and
                        areas of expertise among those in our group. Further, in its intellectual
                        direction, since 2017 DHSI has brought open scholarship into a pedagogical
                        setting by offering a number of courses that engage open scholarship and
                        open knowledge.<note>The DHSI courses that engage open scholarship and open
                            knowledge may be grouped into several categories: 1) Open scholarship:
                                <title rend="quotes">Open Access and Open Social
                                Scholarship,</title> by Arbuckle (U Victoria) and “Digital Public
                            Humanities” by Mia Toothill (Cornell U); 2) Diversity, inclusion, and
                            accessibility: <title rend="quotes">Accessibility and Digital
                                Environments,</title> by Erin E. Templeton (Converse C) and George
                            H. Williams (U South Carolina Upstate); <title rend="quotes">Ethical
                                Data Visualization: Taming Treacherous Data</title> by Chris Church
                            and Katherine Hepworth; <title rend="quotes">Intersectional Feminist
                                Digital Humanities: Theoretical, Social, and Material
                                Engagements,</title> by Elizabeth Losh (C William and Mary), Jessica
                            M. Johnson (John Hopkins U), and Anne Cong-Huyen (U Michigan); <title
                                rend="quotes">Race, Social Justice, and DH: Applied Theories and
                                Methods</title> by Dorothy Kim (Vassar C) and Angel David Nieves
                            (San Diego State U); and <title rend="quotes">Queer Digital Humanities:
                                Intersections, Interrogations, Iterations</title> by Jason Boyd
                            (Ryerson U) and James Howe (Rutgers U); and 3) Scholarly communication:
                                <title rend="quotes">Digital Games as Interactive Tools for
                                Scholarly Research, Communication &amp; Pedagogy,</title> by Jon
                            Saklofske (Acadia U); <title rend="quotes">Digital Publishing in the
                                Humanities</title> by Sarah Melton (Boston C) and Anandi Salinas
                            (Emory U); and <title rend="quotes">Digital Storytelling,</title> by
                            John Barber (Washington State U, Vancouver).</note></p>
                    <p>We also offer DHSI events at other points of the year aside from its summer
                        offering. For the sixth time, in January 2020 we hosted DHSI events at the
                        annual Modern Language Association (MLA) convention. The first workshop,
                            <title rend="quotes">DH Curious? Digital Humanities Tools and
                            Technologies for Students, Emerging Scholars, Faculty, Librarians, and
                            Administrators,</title> offered novices in DH a broad overview of
                        theoretical and hands-on branches of DH tools, methodologies, and
                        pedagogical engagements. The workshop attracted a broad audience including
                        graduate students, faculty, librarians, and administrators from different
                        disciplinary backgrounds. In 2020 we also offered a new workshop, <title
                            rend="quotes">Digital Humanities and Open Scholarship: An
                            Introduction,</title> which focused on open access tools, open
                        scholarship policy, open annotation, and Wikipedia. Similar training is
                        offered at the annual Congress of the Humanities and Social Sciences as
                        well. Through these skills training initiatives and the active online DHSI
                        community on platforms such as Twitter and the DHSI listserv, DHSI continues
                        to foster local and global communities throughout the year.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3. Third Branch: Implementing New Knowledge Environments (INKE)</head>
                    <p>Initially funded by the SSHRC Major Collaborative Research Initiatives
                        Program, INKE officially began in 2008 as a seven-year interdisciplinary
                        initiative spawned in the methodological commons of the digital humanities.
                        INKE’s goal at that time was to understand the future of reading and the
                        book through a historical perspective aligned with the current and emerging
                        tools and techniques of scholarly communication. For this work, INKE brought
                        together <quote rend="inline">researchers and stakeholders at the forefront
                            of computing in the humanities, text analysis, information studies,
                            usability and interface design into a network comprised of those who are
                            best-poised to understand the nature of the human record as it
                            intersects with the computer</quote>
                        <ptr target="#inke"/>. INKE’s focus on electronic text during those first
                        seven years reflected the wider interests of the digital humanities at
                        large, as evident in field-defining collections from the same era (e.g.,
                            <title rend="italic">A Companion to Digital Literary Studies</title>
                        <ptr target="#schreibman2007"/>; <title rend="italic">Collaborative Research
                            in the Digital Humanities</title>
                        <ptr target="#deegan2012"/>; <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                            Humanities</title>
                        <ptr target="#gold2012"/>).</p>
                    <p>Over time, this focus has evolved with pertinent movements in the fields that
                        inform our work. The INKE Partnership was recently awarded a 7-year SSHRC
                        Partnership grant to support the collaborative work of its community of
                        researchers, librarians, and other partners who are involved in implementing
                        proactive strategies and solutions that will realize robust, inclusive,
                        participatory, and publicly engaged digital scholarship: <hi rend="italic"
                            >open social scholarship</hi>. The international INKE Partnership
                        consists of 35 researchers across 20 institutions and 21 partner agencies,
                        with work involving some 19 postdoctoral research fellows and 53 graduate
                        research assistants since inception. Closely aligned to and affiliated with
                        the INKE Partnership is the Canadian-Australian Partnership for Open
                        Scholarship (CAPOS), a collaboration between Canadian and Australian
                        researchers, policy makers, libraries, computing organizations, research
                        groups, and postsecondary institutions [<ref
                            target="https://inke.ca/projects/canadian-australian-partnership-for-open-scholarship/"
                            >CAPOS</ref>]. Building upon the open scholarship research and
                        development interests of its community, the INKE Partnership seeks to
                        advance understanding of and resolve crucial issues in the production,
                        distribution, and widespread engagement of digital scholarship.</p>
                    <p>The INKE Partnership interest in open social scholarship has intellectual
                        forbears in related areas including open access, public humanities,
                        scholarly communication, and citizen science. In order to explore the
                        possibilities of such a shift, the INKE Partnership generates accessible
                        research and research technologies for a broad audience of specialists and
                        active non-specialists. INKE also discovers and shares the most effective
                        ways to create, translate, and share knowledge with research,
                        administration, policy, and other communities, and disseminates this
                        knowledge through the in-progress Open Scholarship Policy Observatory. In
                        addition, through the in-development Canadian Humanities and Social Sciences
                        Commons, INKE employs approaches that foster and encourage openness by
                        collaborating on innovative and inclusive open social scholarship projects
                        and initiatives.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3.1 Open Scholarship Policy Observatory</head>
                    <p>The Open Scholarship Policy Observatory (first prototyped in 2017) is based
                        in the ETCL and supported by INKE Partnership members who track, research,
                        and collect findings on policy changes related to open social scholarship —
                        such as citizen science, citizen scholarship, open access, and data
                        management — on a national (Canadian) and international level <ptr
                            target="#openscholarship"/>. In doing this, the Open Scholarship Policy
                        Observatory discovers and shares the most effective ways to create,
                        translate, and share knowledge with research, administration, policy, and
                        other communities. The observatory’s primary activity is to publish
                        observations of policies that shape open scholarship. For instance, in 2018
                        the <title rend="quotes">Naylor Report</title> was released, a survey of the
                        Canadian higher education funding schema that sent waves through government,
                        universities, and the public alike as it suggested that Canadian research is
                        not funded appropriately <ptr target="#naylor2017"/>
                        <ptr target="#semeniuk2017"/>. We developed a summary of the report (<ref
                            target="https://ospolicyobservatory.uvic.ca/canada-fundamental-science-review/"
                            >https://ospolicyobservatory.uvic.ca/canada-fundamental-science-review/</ref>)
                        outlining the key points and reactions from various stakeholders. More
                        recent observation topics include major events in the open access world such
                        as Plan S (<ref
                            target="https://ospolicyobservatory.uvic.ca/plan-s-and-coalition-s/"
                            >https://ospolicyobservatory.uvic.ca/plan-s-and-coalition-s/</ref>) and
                        the University of California’s decision to not review subscriptions to
                        Elsevier journals (<ref
                            target="https://ospolicyobservatory.uvic.ca/the-university-of-californias-split-with-elsevier/"
                            >https://ospolicyobservatory.uvic.ca/the-university-of-californias-split-with-elsevier/</ref>).</p>
                    <p>Beyond observations, the site also features responses by INKE Partnership
                        members, a list of open scholarship policies from other countries, and
                        policy clusters, which refer to groups of smaller, interrelated policies. A
                        primary purpose for these findings and activities is to inform the various
                        partners and stakeholders of INKE, in addition to local institutions,
                        government bodies, and other organizations and initiatives, about recent
                        policies and provide the appropriate context for a timely and informed
                        response. The Open Scholarship Policy Observatory is available open access
                        under a CC-BY-SA<note>A CC-BY-SA license refers to a Creative Commons open
                            license that dictates that the material in question can be shared
                            openly, but must include attribution (<title rend="quotes">BY</title>)
                            and be shared following this same guideline in the future (i.e., share
                            alike or <title rend="quotes">SA</title>). It is a liberal reuse license
                            that ensures authorial attribution will remain as the material gets
                            shared and reused.</note> license in order to encourage access, uptake,
                        and reuse of any posted materials.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3.2. Canadian Humanities and Social Sciences Commons (HSS Commons)</head>
                    <p>As a collaborative approach to affecting change in scholarly communication
                        through open social scholarship practices, the INKE Partnership draws from
                        contemporary theory and practice predicated on the understanding that those
                        in the Humanities and Social Sciences (HSS) could and should re-orient their
                        work to be much more engaged with the public at large. All of INKE’s
                        research questions and activity clusters are informed by conceptions of
                        evolving scholarly communication, opening access to research, and creating
                        knowledge in more social ways. With the rise of networked technologies and
                        major computing infrastructure, we witness rapid and substantial changes in
                        knowledge creation — every year brings new possibilities and increased
                        levels of innovation. This is reflected across academic and societal
                        developments that change the way knowledge is produced, shared, distributed,
                        and developed, such as open access and online publishing, the rise of
                        digital scholarship, personal (and often mobile) computing devices, social
                        media, citizen scholars, and shifting information access regulations. The
                        widespread production and adoption of online tools and platforms, such as
                        Wikipedia, presents an opportunity for the public and HSS researchers to
                        participate in shared knowledge-based activities, as well as in inclusive
                        and representative public spaces.</p>
                    <p>One way that INKE provides open social scholarship infrastructure is by
                        prototyping the Canadian HSS Commons, an online network that connects
                        academics and broader communities. Inspired by the Modern Language
                        Association’s Humanities Commons platform (<ref
                            target="https://hcommons.org/">https://hcommons.org/</ref>), the
                        Canadian HSS Commons fosters an environment for Canadian HSS researchers to
                        share and access research, publications, and resources, as well as form
                        communities, forge collaborations, create data, and use digital scholarship
                        tools. This commons includes a subject repository for open access
                        publications that assigns digital object identifiers (DOIs) upon upload and
                        follows FAIR (Findable, Accessible, Interactive, Reusable) guidelines for
                        data management; a project development environment that can integrate with
                        Google Drive or Dropbox; individual user profiles, with federated
                        login/identity authorization, including with ORCID; blogging capabilities;
                        and mechanisms to support subject interest groups and member interactions
                        (e.g., profile building, messaging). The Canadian HSS Commons offers an
                        alternative to problematic commercial repositories: it is a not-for-profit,
                        open access, and Canada-specific version of an HSS scholarly communication
                        and interaction platform. By making Canadian humanities and social science
                        research data and tools visible and accessible, we encourage a culture that
                        builds on already-developed applications and information rather than
                        repeatedly reinventing the wheel.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>The ETCL has developed extensive scholarship focusing on social knowledge
                    creation and open social scholarship over the years <ptr target="#arbuckle2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#arbuckle2017"/>
                    <ptr target="#elkhatib2019a"/>, which provides a theoretical framework and
                    historical context that trace the movement of academia towards open social
                    scholarship, as well as the opportunities and challenges that arise with this
                    transition. This intellectual direction lies at the core of INKE Partnership,
                    which is actively engaged in tracing this transition through the Open
                    Scholarship Policy Observatory and provides a platform that supplies a virtual
                    space for academic communities to connect, collaborate, and disseminate research
                    through the Canadian HSS Commons.</p>
                <p>As the ETCL evolves with the scholarly landscape toward publicly-engaged, open
                    social scholarship, we return to a key question repeatedly: how do we reflect
                    this direction in our physical place and intellectual space? At the core of this
                    question is a commitment to remain dynamic, with an infrastructure provided by
                    ETCL and C-SKI that allows us to grow into a more open lab and to readjust to
                    the most effective models that reflect this commitment within a DH lab context.
                    Over the last three years, we have formalized this shift in the physical place
                    of the ETCL itself, including by launching programs that open our doors to
                    community members and support a wide variety of public-facing projects. We also
                    continuously foster interdisciplinary local communities through our speaker
                    series, and broader international communities through our annual DHSI and the
                    international INKE Partnership. Through highly collaborative projects and the
                    open physical layout of the ETCL, our <quote rend="inline">laboratory has become
                        a space to challenge the isolated scholar model</quote>
                    <ptr target="#earhart2015" loc="398"/>, and to engage citizen scholars more
                    broadly. Taken together, the ETCL and its initiatives foster partnership and
                    community relationships that span the region, our nation, and the international
                    community as we, together, investigate what is needed to facilitate open
                    knowledge and open scholarship at scale in a humanistic context.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="arbuckle2014" label="Arbuckle et al. 2014">Arbuckle, A., Belojevic,
                    N., Hiebert, M., and Siemens, R. G., with Wong, S., Siemens, D., Christie, A.,
                    Saklofske, J., Sayers, J., and the INKE &amp; ETCL Research Groups. <title
                        rend="quotes">Social Knowledge Creation: Three Annotated
                        Bibliographies.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Scholarly and Research Communication</title>, 5.2 (2014):
                    n.p. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.22230/src.2014v5n2a150"
                        >https://doi.org/10.22230/src.2014v5n2a150</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="arbuckle2017" label="Arbuckle et al. 2017">Arbuckle, A., Belojevic,
                    N., El Hajj, T., El Khatib, R., Seatter, L, and Siemens, R. G., with Christie,
                    A., Hiebert, M., Saklofske, J., Sayers, J., Siemens, D., Wong, S., and the INKE
                    and ETCL Research Groups. <title rend="quotes">An Annotated Bibliography of
                        Social Knowledge Creation.</title> In A. Arbuckle, A. Mauro, and D. Powell
                    (eds), <title rend="italic">Social Knowledge Creation in the Humanities Volume
                        I</title>, Arizona (2017), pp. 29–264.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bergstrom2016" label="Bergstrom 2016">Bergstrom, T. <title
                        rend="quotes">Digital Scholarship Centres: Converging Space and
                        Expertise.</title> In A. Mackenzie and L. Martin (eds), <title rend="italic"
                        >Developing Digital Scholarship: Emerging Practices in Academic
                        Libraries</title>, London (2016). <ref
                        target="https://books.google.ca/books?id=f9tiDQAAQBAJ&amp;printsec"
                        >https://books.google.ca/books?id=f9tiDQAAQBAJ&amp;printsec</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bonney2009" label="Bonney et al. 2009">Bonney, R., Cooper C. B.,
                    Dickinson, J., Kelling, S., Phillips, T. Rosenberg, K. V., and Shirk, J. <title
                        rend="quotes">Citizen Science: A Developing Tool for Expanding Science
                        Knowledge and Scientific Literacy.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">BioScience</title> 59.11(2009): 977–84. <ref
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1525/bio.2009.59.11.9"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.1525/bio.2009.59.11.9</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bos2010" label="Bos et al. 2010"> Bos, N., Buyuktur, A. G., Olson, J.
                    S., Olson, G. M., Voida, A. <title rend="quotes">Shared Identity Helps Partially
                        Distributed Teams, but Distance Still Matters.</title> GROUP '10 Proceedings
                    of the 16th ACM International Conference on Supporting Group Work, Sanibel
                    Island, Florida, January 2010. <ref
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/1880071.1880086"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/1880071.1880086</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brennan2016" label="Brennan 2016">Brennan, S. A. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Public, First.</title> In M. K. Gold and L. A. Klein (eds), <title
                        rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016</title>, University of
                    Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2016), pp. 384–89.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brown1995" label="Brown 1995">Brown, D. W. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Public/Academic Disconnect.</title> In <title rend="italic">Higher Education
                        Exchange Annual</title>, 38–42. Kettering Foundation, Dayton, OH
                    (1995).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brown2016" label="Brown 2016">Brown, S. <title rend="quotes">Towards
                        Best Practices in Online Collaborative Knowledge Production.</title> In C.
                    Crompton, R. Lane, and R. G. Siemens (eds), <title rend="italic">Doing Digital
                        Humanities</title>, London and New York (2016), pp. 47–64.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cantwell2011" label="Cantwell
                2011">Cantwell, B.
                        <title rend="quotes">Academic In-sourcing: International Postdoctoral
                        Employment and New Modes of Academic Production.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Higher Education Policy &amp;
                    Management</title>, 33.2 (2011): 101-114.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="carroll2009" label="Carroll, J. M. et al. 2009">[] Carroll, J. M.,
                    Rosson, M. B., Farooq, U., Xiao, L. <title rend="quotes">Beyond Being
                        Aware.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Information and Organization</title>, 19.3(2009): 162-185.
                        <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.infoandorg.2009.04.004"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.infoandorg.2009.04.004</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cohen2010" label="Cohen
                2010"> Cohen, D. J. <title
                        rend="quotes">Open Access Publishing and Scholarly Values.</title> [Online].
                    2010. Available at <ref
                        target="https://dancohen.org/2010/05/27/open-access-publishing-and-scholarly-values/"
                        >https://dancohen.org/2010/05/27/open-access-publishing-and-scholarly-values/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cox2016" label="Cox 2016">Cox, J. <title rend="quotes">Communicating
                        New Library Roles to Enable Digital Scholarship: A Review Article.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Academic Librarianship</title>, 22.2–3(2016): 132–147. <ref
                        target="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/13614533.2016.1181665?src=recsys"
                        >https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/13614533.2016.1181665?src=recsys</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="crompton2016" label="Crompton et al. 2016">Crompton, C., Lane, R.J.,
                    and Siemens, R. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Doing Digital Humanities: Practice,
                        Training, Research.</title> Routledge, London (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="crompton2020" label="Crompton et al. 2020">Crompton, C., Lane, R.J.,
                    and Siemens, R. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Doing More Digital Humanities: Open
                        Approaches to Creation, Growth, and Development.</title> Routledge, London
                    (2020).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="daft1987" label="Daft et al. 1987">Daft, R. L., Lengel, R. H., and
                    Trevino, L. K. <title rend="quotes">Message Equivocality, Media Selection, and
                        Manager Performance: Implications for Information Systems.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">MIS Quarterly</title>, 11.3(1987): 355–366.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="deegan2012" label="Deegan
                and McCarty 2012">Deegan,
                    M., and McCarty, W. (eds). <title rend="italic">Collaborative Research in the
                        Digital Humanities</title>, Surrey (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dhsi" label="DHSI Statement on Ethics and Inclusion">DHSI Statement on
                    Ethics and Inclusion. [Online]. <ref
                        target="https://dhsi.org/statement-of-ethics-inclusion/"
                        >https://dhsi.org/statement-of-ethics-inclusion/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dowson2016" label="Dowson 2016">Dowson, R. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Research Commons: Site of Innovation, Experimentation, and Collaboration in
                        Academic Libraries.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Scholarly and Research Communication</title>, 7.2 (2016):
                    n.p. <ref target="https://src-online.ca/index.php/src/article/view/259/504"
                        >https://src-online.ca/index.php/src/article/view/259/504</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2013" label="Drucker 2013"> Drucker, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Intro to Digital Humanities.</title> [Online]. 2013. UCLA Center for
                    Digital Humanities. <ref target="http://dh101.humanities.ucla.edu/?page_id=13"
                        >http://dh101.humanities.ucla.edu/?page_id=13</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="earhart2015" label="Earhart 2015">Earhart, A. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Digital Humanities as a Laboratory.</title> In D. T. Goldberg and P.
                    Svensson (eds), <title rend="italic">Humanities and the Digital</title>, Boston
                    (2015), pp. 391–400.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="elkhatib2019a" label="El Khatib et al. 2019a">El Khatib, R., Arbuckle,
                    A., and Siemens, R. <title rend="quotes">Foundations for On-Campus Open Social
                        Scholarship Activities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">KULA: Knowledge Creation, Dissemination, and Preservation
                        Studies</title>, 3.1 (2019): 3. <ref target="http://doi.org/10.5334/kula.14"
                        >http://doi.org/10.5334/kula.14</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="elkhatib2019b" label="El Khatib et al. 2019b">El Khatib, R., Seatter,
                    L., El-Hajj, T., and Leibel, C. with Arbuckle, A., Siemens, R.G., Winter, C.,
                    and the ETCL Research Group. <title rend="quotes">Open Social Scholarship
                        Annotated Bibliography.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">KULA: Knowledge Creation, Dissemination, and Preservation
                        Studies</title>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="etclabout" label="ETCL About n.d."><title rend="quotes">Electronic
                        Textual Cultures Lab.</title> [Online]. n.d. <ref
                        target="https://etcl.uvic.ca/about/"
                    >https://etcl.uvic.ca/about/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="etclhome" label="ETCL Home Page n.d."><title rend="quotes">Electronic
                        Textual Cultures Lab.</title> [Online]. n.d. <ref
                        target="https://etcl.uvic.ca/">https://etcl.uvic.ca/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="etclvalues" label="ETCL
                Values n.d."><title
                        rend="quotes">Electronic Textual Cultures Lab.</title> [Online]. n.d. <ref
                        target="https://etcl.uvic.ca/values/"
                    >https://etcl.uvic.ca/values/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="etclopen" label="ETCL Open Knowledge Program"><title rend="quotes"
                        >Electronic Textual Cultures Lab.</title> [Online]. n.d. <ref
                        target="https://etcl.uvic.ca/okp/">https://etcl.uvic.ca/okp/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fitzpatrick2019" label="Fitzpatrick 2019">Fitzpatrick, K. <title
                        rend="italic">Generous Thinking: A Radical Approach to Saving the
                        University.</title> Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore (2019).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fitzpatrick2011" label="Fitzpatrick 2011">Fitzpatrick, K. <title
                        rend="italic">Planned Obsolescence: Publishing, Technology, and the Future
                        of the Academy.</title> New York University Press, New York (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="forisek2013" label="Forišek and Steinová 2013">Forišek, M. and
                    Steinová, M. <title rend="italic">Explaining Algorithms Using Metaphors</title>.
                    Springer Science &amp; Business Media, London (2013). <ref
                        target="https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007%2F978-1-4471-5019-0.pdf"
                        >https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007%2F978-1-4471-5019-0.pdf</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gensler" label="Gensler n.d.">Gensler. <title rend="quotes">The Rise
                        of Academic Incubators.</title> [Online]. n.d. <ref
                        target="https://www.gensler.com/research-insight/in-focus/the-rise-of-academic-incubators"
                        >https://www.gensler.com/research-insight/in-focus/the-rise-of-academic-incubators</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gil2016" label="Gil and Ortega 2016"> Gil, A., and Ortega, É. <title
                        rend="quotes">Global Outlooks in Digital Humanities.</title> In C. Crompton,
                    R. Lane, and R. G. Siemens (eds), <title rend="italic">Doing Digital
                        Humanities</title>, London and New York (2016), pp. 22–34.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="glasner1996" label="Glasner 1996">Glasner, P. <title rend="quotes"
                        >From Community to 'Collaboratory'? The Human Genome Project and the
                        Changing Culture of Science.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Science and Public Policy</title>, 23.2(1996):
                    109-116.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gold2012" label="Gold 2012">Gold, M. (ed). <title rend="italic"
                        >Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, University of Minnesota Press,
                    Minneapolis (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="goldklein2016" label="Gold
                and Klein 2016">Gold, M.,
                    and Klein L. A. (eds). <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities
                        2016</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="goldberghart2016" label="Goldenberg-Hart 2016">Goldenberg-Hart, D.
                        <title rend="quotes">Report of a CNI-ARL Workshop: Planning a Digital
                        Scholarship Center 2016.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Coalition for Networked Information (CNI)</title>,
                    Washington (2016). <ref
                        target="https://www.cni.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/report-DSCW16.pdf"
                        >https://www.cni.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/report-DSCW16.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gontier2011" label="Gontier 2011">Gontier, N. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Depicting the Tree of Life: the Philosophical and Historical Roots of
                        Evolutionary Tree Diagrams.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Evolution: Education and Outreach</title>, 4.3 (2011):
                    515-538. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12052-011-0355-0"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1007/s12052-011-0355-0</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="guedon2008" label="Guédon 2008">Guédon, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Digitizing and the Meaning of Knowledge.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Academic Matters</title> (October–November): 23–26 (2008).
                        <ref target="http://www.academicmatters.ca/assets/AM_SEPT’08.pdf"
                        >http://www.academicmatters.ca/assets/AM_SEPT’08.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hockey2012" label="Hockey 2012">Hockey, S. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Digital Humanities in the Age of the Internet: Reaching Out to Other
                        Communities.</title> In M. Deegan and W. McCarty (eds), <title rend="italic"
                        >Collaborative Research in the Digital Humanities</title>, Surrey (2012),
                    pp. 81–92.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hoy2013" label="Hoy and Johnson 2013">Hoy, A., and Johnson, M. (eds).
                        <title rend="italic">Deepening Community Engagement in Higher
                        Education</title>. Palgrave Macmillan, New York (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hsu2016" label="Hsu 2016">Hsu, W. <title rend="quotes">Lessons on
                        Public Humanities from the Civic Sphere.</title> In M. K. Gold and L. A.
                    Klein (eds), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities
                    2016</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2016), pp.
                    280–86.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hurrell2019" label="Hurrell 2019">Hurrell, C. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Aligning the stars: Understanding Digital Scholarship Needs to Support the
                        Evolving Nature of Academic Research.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Partnership: The Canadian Journal of Library and
                        Information Practice and Research</title>, 14.2(2019): 1–17. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.21083/partnership.v14i2.4623"
                        >https://doi.org/10.21083/partnership.v14i2.4623</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="inke" label="INKE n.d.">Implementing New Knowledge Environments.
                    [Online]. n.d. <ref target="https://inke.ca/projects/about/"
                        >inke.ca/projects/about/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ippoliti2016" label="Ippoliti 2016">Ippoliti, C. 2016. <title
                        rend="quotes">Survey of Digital Scholarship Centers Final Report.
                        Association of College and Research Libraries.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">ACRL Digital Scholarship Centres Interest Group</title>
                    (2016). <ref
                        target="https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B6OjJzCOmpfudDNzVG1vTUE3ck0/view"
                        >https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B6OjJzCOmpfudDNzVG1vTUE3ck0/view</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jay2012" label="Jay 2012">Jay, G. <title rend="quotes">The Engaged
                        Humanities: Principles and Practices for Public Scholarship and
                        Teaching.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Community Engagement and Scholarship</title>
                    3.1(2012): 51–63.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jones2014" label="Jones 2014">Jones, S. E. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Publications.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">In The Emergence of the Digital Humanities</title>. 147–77.
                    Routledge, New York (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2012" label="Kirschenbaum 2012">Kirschenbaum, M. <title
                        rend="quotes">What Is Digital Humanities and What’s It Doing in English
                        Departments?</title> In M. Gold (ed), <title rend="italic">Debates in the
                        Digital Humanities</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis
                    (2012). <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5749/minnesota/9780816677948.003.0001"
                        >https://doi.org/10.5749/minnesota/9780816677948.003.0001</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lewis2015" label="Lewis et al. 2015">Lewis, V., Spiro, L., Xuemao W.,
                    and Jon E. Cawthorne. 2015. <title rend="italic">Building Expertise to Support
                        Digital Scholarship: A Global Perspective</title>. Council on Library and
                    Information Resources (CLIR), October 2015. <ref
                        target="https://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub168/"
                        >https://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub168/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lippincott2013" label="Lippincott et al.
                2013">
                    Lippincott, J. K. <title rend="italic">Trends in Digital Scholarship
                        Centers</title>: CNI Fall Membership Meeting, Washington, DC, December 2013,
                        <ref
                        target="https://www.cni.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/B41-10-04-01_JLippincott_TrendsDigScholarCtr_CNI2013F.pdf"
                        >https://www.cni.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/B41-10-04-01_JLippincott_TrendsDigScholarCtr_CNI2013F.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2012" label="Liu
                2012">Liu, A. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Where is Cultural Criticism in the Digital Humanities?</title> In M. K.
                    Gold (ed), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>,
                    University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2012), pp. 490–510.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="losh2012" label="Losh 2012">Losh, E. <title rend="quotes">Hacktivism
                        and the Humanities: Programming Protest in the Era of the Digital
                        University.</title> In M. K. Gold (ed), <title rend="italic">Debates in the
                        Digital Humanities</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis
                    (2012), pp. 161–86.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2012" label="McPherson 2012">McPherson, T. <title
                        rend="quotes">Why are the Digital Humanities So White? or Thinking the
                        Histories of Race and Computation.</title> In M. K. Gold (ed), <title
                        rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, University of
                    Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2012), pp. 139–60.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mindell2013" label="Mindell 2013">Mindell, D. P. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Tree of Life: Metaphor, Model, and Heuristic Device.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Systematic Biology</title>, 62.3(2013): 479–48. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/sys115"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/sys115</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="naylor2017" label="Naylor et al. 2017">Naylor, David et al. <title
                        rend="quotes">Investing in Canada’s Future: Strengthening the Foundation of
                        Canadian Research.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Canada’s Fundamental Science Review</title> (2017). <ref
                        target="http://www.sciencereview.ca/eic/site/059.nsf/vwapj/ScienceReview_April2017-rv.pdf/$file/ScienceReview_April2017-rv.pdf"
                        >http://www.sciencereview.ca/eic/site/059.nsf/vwapj/ScienceReview_April2017-rv.pdf/$file/ScienceReview_April2017-rv.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="newman2012" label="Newman et al. 2012">Newman, G., Wiggins, A., Crall,
                    A., Graham, E., Newman, S., and Crowston, K. <title rend="quotes">The Future of
                        Citizen Science: Emerging Technologies and Shifting Paradigms.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment</title>,
                    10.6(2012): 298–304. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1890/110294"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1890/110294</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="olson2000" label="Olson and Olson 2000">Olson, G., and Olson, J.
                        <title rend="quotes">Distance Matters.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Human-Computer Interaction</title>, 15.2-3(2000):
                    139-178.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="olson2014" label="Olson and Olson 2014">Olson, J., and Olson, G.
                        <title rend="italic">Working Together Apart: Collaboration over the
                        Internet</title>, 6, Morgan &amp; Claypool, n.p. (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="openscholarship" label="Open Scholarship Policy Observatory"><title
                        rend="quotes">Open Scholarship Policy Observatory.</title> [Online]. n.d.
                        <ref target="https://ospolicyobservatory.uvic.ca/"
                        >https://ospolicyobservatory.uvic.ca/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="modernlanguage" label="Modern Language Association"> Modern Language
                    Association. [Online]. <title rend="italic">Humanities Commons</title>. <ref
                        target="https://hcommons.org/">https://hcommons.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="powell2017" label="Powell et al. 2017">Powell, D., Mauro, A., and
                    Arbuckle. A. <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Tracing the Movement of Ideas:
                        Social Knowledge Creation in the Humanities.</title> In A. Arbuckle, A.
                    Mauro, &amp; D. Powell (eds), <title rend="italic">Social Knowledge Creation in
                        the Humanities</title>, 1 (2017): 1–28.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ridge2013" label="Ridge 2013">Ridge, M. <title rend="quotes">From
                        Tagging to Theorizing: Deepening Engagement with Cultural Heritage through
                        Crowdsourcing.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Curator</title> 56.4(2013): 435–50.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rockwell2012" label="Rockwell 2012">Rockwell, G. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Crowdsourcing the Humanities: Social Research and Collaboration.</title> In
                    M. Deegan and W. McCarty (eds), <title rend="italic">Collaborative Research in
                        the Digital Humanities</title>, Ashgate, Surrey (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schreibman2004" label="Schreibman
                    et al. 2004"
                    >Schreibman, S., Siemens, R., and Unsworth, J. (eds). <title rend="italic">A
                        Companion to Digital Humanities</title>. Blackwell, Oxford (2004).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schreibman2007" label="Schreibman and Siemens 2007">Schreibman, S.,
                    and Siemens, R. (eds). <title rend="italic">A Companion to Digital Literary
                        Studies</title>. Blackwell, Oxford (2007). <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companionDLS/"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companionDLS/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="semeniuk2017" label="Semeniuk 2017">Semeniuk, I. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Massive Review of Federal Science Funding Reveals Risks To Younger
                        Researchers.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Globe and Mail</title>, April 2017. <ref
                        target="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/review-calls-for-new-entity-to-oversee-federal-science-funding/article34650444/"
                        >https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/review-calls-for-new-entity-to-oversee-federal-science-funding/article34650444/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="siemens2012" label="Siemens and Siemens 2012">Siemens, L., and
                    Siemens, R. <title rend="quotes">Notes from the Collaboratory: An Informal Study
                        of an Academic DH Lab in Transition.</title> Paper Presented at Digital
                    Humanities Conference. Hamburg, July, 2012. <ref
                        target="http://www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de/conference/programme/abstracts/notes-from-the-collaboratory-an-informal-study-of-an-academic-dh-lab-in-transition.1.html"
                        >http://www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de/conference/programme/abstracts/notes-from-the-collaboratory-an-informal-study-of-an-academic-dh-lab-in-transition.1.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="siemens2016" label="Siemens 2016">Siemens, R. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Communities of Practice, the Methodological Commons, and Digital
                        Self-determination in the Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Studies/le Champ Numérique</title>. <ref
                        target="http://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.31"
                        >http://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.31</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="siemens2010a" label="Siemens 2010">Siemens, L. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Time, Place and Cyberspace: Foundations for Successful E-Research
                        Collaboration.</title> In M. Anandarajan &amp; A. Anandarajan (eds.),
                    E-Research Collaboration: Theory, Techniques and Challenges. Berlin,
                    Springer-Verlag (2010): 35-48.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="siemens2010b" label="Siemens et al. 2010">Siemens, L., Cunningham, R.,
                    Duff, W. and Warwick, C. <title rend="quotes"><q>More Minds are Brought to Bear
                            on a Problem</q>: Methods of Interaction and Collaboration within
                        Digital Humanities Research Teams.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Studies/Le champ numérique</title>, 2.2 (2010):
                    n.p. <ref target="http://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.80"
                        >http://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.80</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sinclair2014" label="Sinclair 2014">Sinclair, B. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The University Library as Incubator for Digital Scholarship.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Educause Review</title> (2014): n.p. <ref
                        target="https://er.educause.edu/articles/2014/6/the-university-library-as-incubator-for-digital-scholarship"
                        >https://er.educause.edu/articles/2014/6/the-university-library-as-incubator-for-digital-scholarship</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="unsworth2010" label="Unsworth 2010">Unsworth, J. E-mail message to
                    Matthew Kirschenbaum. April, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="veletsianos2016" label="Veletsianos 2016">Veletsianos, G. <title
                        rend="italic">Social Media in Academia</title>. Routledge, New York
                    (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wenimont2016" label="Wernimont and Losh 2016">Wernimont, J., and Losh,
                    E. <title rend="quotes">Problems with White Feminism: Intersectionality and
                        Digital Humanities.</title> In C. Crompton, R. Lane, and R. G. Siemens
                    (eds), <title rend="italic">Doing Digital Humanities</title>, London and New
                    York (2016), pp. 35–46.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="willinsky2006" label="Willinsky 2006">Willinsky, J. <title
                        rend="italic">The Access Principle: The Case for Open Access to Research and
                        Scholarship</title>. MIT Press, Cambridge (2006).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="williams2012" label="Williams 2012">Williams, G. H. <title
                        rend="quotes">Disability, Universal Design, and the Digital
                        Humanities.</title> In M. K. Gold (ed), <title rend="italic">Debates in the
                        Digital Humanities</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis
                    (2012), pp. 202-212.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
