<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
	xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
	xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
				<title type="article" xml:lang="en">Rogue Performances: A Review of Abigail De
					Kosnik’s <title rend="italic">Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and
						Media Fandom</title></title>
				<!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
				<dhq:authorInfo>
					<!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
					<dhq:author_name>Brian M. <dhq:family>Watson</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
					<dhq:affiliation>Indiana University — Bloomington</dhq:affiliation>
					<email>briwats@iu.edu</email>
					<dhq:bio>
						<p>Brian M. Watson is the Graduate Archivist at the Kinsey Institute
							Library and Special Collections and the Archivist-Historian of
							American Psychological Association’s Division 44 Taskforce. Brian
							holds a master’s degree in the history of sexuality and the book
							from Drew University and is finishing their MLIS degree at
							Indiana University Bloomington with plans to apply for a PhD.
							Their research focuses on linked data vocabularies, critical
							cataloging and sexual nomenclature in cultural heritage contexts.
							He tweets @brimwats.</p>
					</dhq:bio>
				</dhq:authorInfo>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
				<publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
				<!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
				<idno type="DHQarticle-id">000446</idno>
				<idno type="volume">014</idno>
				<idno type="issue">1</idno>
				<date when="2020-03-20">20 March 2020</date>			
				<dhq:articleType>review</dhq:articleType>
				<availability status="CC-BY-ND">
					<cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>

			<sourceDesc>
				<p>This is the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
					<bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
							target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
							>http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
					<bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en" extent="original"/>
				<!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
					<!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
					<!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
					<list type="simple">
						<item/>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
			<change when="2020-01-16" who="murelj">Created file and encoded review</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
	<text xml:lang="en" type="original">
		<front>
			<dhq:abstract>
				<p>In <title rend="italic">Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media
						Fandom </title> (2016), Abigail de Kosnik establishes the idea of
						<term>rogue archives</term> as easily available, copyright-agnostic,
					and amateur-run digital archives that preserve non-traditional material.
					More than just a concept, De Kosnik’s interdisciplinary and wide-ranging
						<term>rogue archives</term> are used as a framework to understand
					shifts in media, internet culture, and as sites of individual and community
					social media performances. This review, which was originally livetweeted,
					also considers its own performance, situating Twitter reviews as a
					continuation of eighteenth-century book culture.</p>
				<p>This review was originally livetweeted. You can read the original threads
					here: <ref
						target="https://twitter.com/historyofporn/status/1107292610597515266?s=21"
						>https://twitter.com/historyofporn/status/1107292610597515266</ref>
					and here: <ref
						target="https://twitter.com/HistoryOfPorn/status/1107388760868704257"
						>https://twitter.com/HistoryOfPorn/status/1107388760868704257</ref></p>
			</dhq:abstract>
			<dhq:teaser>
				<p>Review of Abigail De Kosnik’s <title rend="italic">Rogue Archives: Digital
						Cultural Memory and Media Fandom</title> (MIT Press, 2016)</p>
			</dhq:teaser>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p>When I began reading Abigail De Kosnik’s <title rend="italic">Rogue Archives:
					Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom</title> (MIT Press, 2016) with a
				professional eye, I was struck by the number of ways that it connected and
				resonated with my personal life and practice. Although I work at the Kinsey
				Institute Library and Special Collection as a graduate archivist and I am
				receiving the benefits of a traditional archival education, I have also been
				involved in independent and community archives for a number of years.
				Particularly, I have been working to preserve the communities and materials of
				marginalized groups from the generalized decay of the internet. <title
					rend="italic">Rogue Archives</title> then, was a self-discovery. It also
				became an exploration: this book review was originally livetweeted as part of a
				year-long experiment to engage with authors and their communities while reading
				their work. As a result, this journal review will conclude with some thoughts on
				what the experience of a performative livetweet <q>remix</q> of an academic work
				is like for both the reviewer and the reviewed.</p>
			<p>Beginning in a way that is now almost traditional for archival studies, De Kosnik
				proclaims that <quote rend="inline">memory has gone rogue ... memory has
						<emph>fallen into the hands of rogues</emph>. From the late nineteenth
					through the late twentieth century, memory — not private, individual
					memory, but public, collective memory — was the domain of the state</quote>
				<ptr target="#dekosnik2016" loc="1"/>. Her work, she declares, is not about
				outdated and possibly moribund analog archives, but about a new type of digital
				archive that she sees as avant-garde, a precursor of what is to come across all
				of the humanities. Although archival scholars might take exception at some of
				her characterizations, De Kosnik is deliberately setting her <term>rogue</term>
				archives in definitional opposition to <term>traditional</term> ones — and also
				drawing heavily on media studies criticism.</p>
			<p>The difference between <term>traditional</term> and <term>rogue</term> archives,
				is sometimes hard to express as is witnessed by De Kosnik’s varying definitional
				approaches and levels of emphasis on one or more aspects throughout. Although
				another reader might complain about this drift, my feeling is that the subjects
				of the book are difficult to define and are sometimes deliberately
				boundary-challenging and queering. Regardless, the traits of rogue archives that
				are the most persistent from chapter to chapter are that they are: (1) largely
				run by people that do not have training or expertise in library and information
				studies, but dub themselves archivists; (2) available 24 hours a day, seven days
				a week to anyone with an internet connection; (3) nominally barrier-less to
				access; (4) ignorant, purposefully-ignorant, or maliciously ignorant of
				copyright laws and restrictions; (5) homes for “content that has never been, and
				would never likely be, contained in a traditional memory institution;” (6) home
				as well to people that have never been or would never likely be traditional; (7)
				identity-and culture-generating; and (8) achrontic and intertextual sites of
				identity and community performance, inspiration, reaffirmation, and repertoire
					<ptr target="#dekosnik2016" loc="2–4, 75–6, 152, 161, 255, 276, 288"/>. I
				will explore these traits further below.</p>
			<p>There are a number of quibbles that can be taken with individual aspects of this
				definition. For example, one could argue that figures such as Henry Spencer
				Ashbee, the Victorian businessman-bibliophile who maintained an apartment in
				London filled with erotica and pornography and provided 24/7 access to select
				people, meets at least a few of the aspects of a <term>rogue archive</term>.
				However, it would not be possible for <emph>any</emph> physical archive to meet
				all of the requirements to become a De Kosnikian <term>rogue</term> archive.
				That, I would argue, points us to one of the most essential features of rogue
				archives: they <emph>must</emph> be digital. Copyright also emerges as a central
				differentiator of rogue archives. Though De Kosnik includes some discussion of
				archives that limit themselves to public domain material (i.e. The Gutenberg
				Project), the majority of the book is aimed at the historical senses of rogue:
					<quote rend="inline">vagabond, mischievous, wayward, and anomalous</quote>
				<ptr target="#oed2019"/>. As many <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> readers know,
					<term>traditional</term> institutionally-affiliated digital archives like
				the Internet Archive or Whitman Archive cannot throw their concerns to the wind
				— they must be careful and sometimes overly-cautious about copyright
				infringement. However, they also have robust digital preservation frameworks and
				infrastructure in place to ensure the survivability of material for decades.</p>
			<p><title rend="italic">Rogue Archives</title> is structured in a rather unique way:
				each chapter is separated by what De Kosnik calls <quote rend="inline"
					>breaks</quote>, which <quote rend="inline">are more informal, some are
					more experimental, and the rest are simply less rounded-out and more
					fragmentary than the chapters,</quote> which she says are more structured
				and written in a <quote rend="inline">straightforward academic style</quote>
				<ptr target="#dekosnik2016" loc="21"/>. For example, Chapter Two considers
				archival <quote rend="inline">styles</quote>, which De Kosnik breaks down into a
				taxonomy of universal, community, and alternative. Universal archives <quote
					rend="inline">seek to replace canonicity and selective archiving” and the
					critics and experts that support and enable canons, with “comprehensive
					archiving, a process that strives to collect as many cultural texts as
					possible, to make all the texts equally accessible to the public, and to
					present all the texts as equally valuable</quote>
				<ptr target="#dekosnik2016" loc="75"/>. Community archives, by contrast, support
				the <quote rend="inline">canon-expansion work that was begun by university
					reformists, striving to assemble and preserve texts that originate from, or
					bear direct relevance to, cultures that have been historically
					marginalized</quote>
				<ptr target="#dekosnik2016" loc="75"/>. De Kosnik’s alternative archiving style,
				however, ignores this binary, proposing <quote rend="inline">new canons, canons
					of new types of objects or objects that are ignored… assemblies of odd,
					strange, controversial, nongeneric, or radically new texts stand alongside
					those older sets of privileged works</quote>
				<ptr target="#dekosnik2016" loc="75"/>.</p>
			<p>The <q>break</q> between Chapters Two and Three, called <title rend="quotes"
					>Archive Elves</title> was identified as particularly moving by several
				practicing archivists and students. This break describes the constant,
				unyielding, and academically-unexamined work that goes into maintaining an
				archive. After a few pages of description of the endless, thankless, and
				repetitious tasks undertaken by archivists, De Kosnik points out that users,
				unaware of the amount of work that goes into digital projects, just assume that
				things work like magic: <cit><quote rend="block"> the nature of online
						infrastructuring is such that the infrastructure builders aim to make
						themselves and their work invisible, ghostly, and immaterial. If using
						a networked digital archive feels like using a magic memory machine,
						this is in part because both the server that stores data and serves it
						up on command, and the <term>servers</term> (archivists) who serve the
						archive users (on demand) and maintain the integrity of the archive,
						are concealed from the user’s view</quote>. <ptr
						target="#dekosnik2016" loc="127"/></cit></p>
			<p>As any reader that has undertaken a significant amount of technical work can
				attest, this is true. Infrastructure also includes, I would point out, the text
				you are reading now: the eye-pleasing paragraphs that you are reading were
				worked into the screen via the TEI-encoded ‘magic’ of the editors of this
				journal. This review article is built on top of more than a decade’s worth of
				work by <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> editors, volunteers, and
				archivists.</p>
			<p>By positing a meditation on the nature of archival work between arguments about
				types of archival style and culture, De Kosnik cleverly and subtly reinforces
				her argument, which goes something like this: rogue archival work, which is
				carried out in specific ways by minoritized groups, <emph>is</emph> work, and it
					<emph>is</emph> different because <emph>they</emph> are different and
					<emph>they</emph> are preserving <emph>their</emph> cultures. That these
				meditative breaks when combined with chapters would serve as effective teaching
				modules, speaks to the strength of De Kosnik’s model. The result is a book that
				is an excellent teaching text for a number of disciplines and which may be of
				interest to DH educators.</p>
			<p>The following chapters move away from theory and taxonomies in order to focus on a
				diverse series of case studies. De Kosnik’s examples range from file sharing
				networks to more-traditional (in content) digital archives like the South Asian
				American Digital Archive, FAMA Collection, the Radfem Archive, and others. Most
				important for <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> readers and larger audiences is
				her examination of fan fiction, represented mostly by Archive of Our Own (AO3).
				This chapter documents a long history of internet fan fiction and fan culture,
				from the 1990s to present, which occurs in roughly three different phases:
				centralization (1990s-early 2000s), de-centralization into social media (early
				to mid 2000s), and re-centralization into queer and feminist fan-controlled
				archives (late 2000s to present).</p>
			<p>The establishment of these queer and feminist sites, she convincingly argues in
				her closing chapters, provided homes and sites of discovery for minoritized
				individuals. For a number of reasons, these communities especially embraced
					<quote rend="inline">archontic production</quote>, which is to say, in her
				first (2006) definitional attempt: <cit><quote rend="block">fictional writings
						based on source texts, that is, texts that have been published; the
						writers of archontic literature are readers-turned-authors. Each
						source text is the foundation and core of an archive from which
						reader-authors make withdrawals (elements they wish to use) and into
						which they make deposits (their stories that incorporate those
						appropriated elements), thereby augmenting and enlarging the
						overarching archive.</quote>
					<ptr target="#dekosnik2016" loc="275"/></cit>
				<title rend="italic">Rogue Archives</title> expands this definition to include
					<quote rend="inline">digital derivations</quote>, encompassing <quote
					rend="inline">appropriative writings, soundtracks, still and moving images,
					audiovisual works, games, and codes… constitute[ing] a vast swath of
					digital culture today</quote>
				<ptr target="#dekosnik2016" loc="276"/>.</p>
			<p>By engaging with these materials, minoritized groups <q>perform</q> and
					<q>produce</q> the archive, and the support they receive encourages the
				production of new performances. This chapter showcases De Kosnik’s insightful
				scholarship at its best, justifying the book’s $45.00 hardcover price. <title
					rend="italic">Rogue Archives</title> breaks new ground in its documentation
				of a desperately under-researched topic and provides valuable insight to fields
				as diverse as fan studies, media studies, archiving, sexuality, history,
				archival theory, and internet culture — to mention a few.</p>
			<p>Finally, De Kosnik strikes at the heart of modern and digitally-mediated humanity:
				social media. In De Kosnik’s view, social media — and perhaps even social
				identity — is a performance that can and should be studied. To extend that a
				little bit further, the irony that my livetweeted review of <title rend="italic"
					>Rogue Archives</title> can be (and was) read as a performance is not lost
				on me. Since the beginning of 2019, I have documented a number of book reviews
				that I have read through the lens of Twitter (much of which is available under
				the hashtag #tweetvaluation). The phenomenon of conference livetweeting has been
				examined, but I do not know of any other live-tweeted book reviews [Further
				Reading].</p>
			<p>Part of the purpose behind the ongoing experiment is that I personally engage and
				learn better when in conversation with an audience — even an imagined one.
				Another reason is that it has allowed direct engagement with authors such as in
				this particularly poignant reply from the author herself: <figure>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure01.PNG"/>
					<figDesc>ALT TEXT 1: tweet from [Abigail] @De_Kosnik to @HistoryOfPorn [the
						author’s previous twitter handle]: “you are making my whole year by
						live tweeting the book and I am so sad I have to stop following along
						as my flight is about to take off (I know yours is too) + just want to
						say if I could lift the Tumblr porn ban and give it to you as a thank
						you gift I would.” Reply from author to @De_Kosnik: “😭 [Crying Emoji]
						the sweetest imaginary gift I've ever been offered! (I've decided to
						buy the in flight WiFi so I can keep going, so happy birthday when you
						land!)”</figDesc>
				</figure> Additionally, De Kosnik noted in a private message to the author that
				she enjoyed the experience of being livetweeted, and saw it as “an amazing
				archontic/remix work.” The review triggered other events, including book
				purchases or further authorial replies:</p>
			<figure>
				<graphic url="resources/images/figure02.PNG"/>
				<figDesc>Tweet from @likelyjanlukas “Really great thread. I look forward to
					reading the book!” </figDesc>
			</figure>
			<figure>
				<graphic url="resources/images/figure03.PNG"/>
				<figDesc>Tweet from @JacobOller [Jacob Oller, reporter] to author: “I’m
					FASCINATED yes PLEASE</figDesc>
			</figure>
			<figure>
				<graphic url="resources/images/figure04.PNG"/>
				<figDesc>Tweet from Shannon Devlin to author: “It’s so good! I hope you like it
					as much as I do so far!”</figDesc>
			</figure>
			<p>Most critically, live reviewing digitally recreates the experience of obsolete
				book culture. As historians of the book have noted, the reading of books prior
				to the twentieth century was a social, communal, and cultural experience. For
				example, in <title rend="italic">The Social Life of Books</title> (2017),
				Abigail Williams documents how books were <quote rend="inline">the basis for
					communal entertainment, performance, and discussion</quote>
				<ptr target="#williams2017" loc="58, 64"/>. Even though solitary reading became
				increasingly popular through the century, <cit><quote rend="block">there were
						many reasons why individuals continued to read together. Some of these
						had to do with practical concerns [like lack of oil and candles, but
						also with] control over what was being read, and how…Women’s reading
						became associated with sofas and softness rather than with the
						intellectually rigorous upright reading of men, and young women were
						castigated for this unbecoming lounging.</quote>
					<ptr target="#williams2017" loc="64, 51"/></cit></p>
			<p>To reword this into De Kosnik’s language, live reading is an ‘achronological
				archrontic production.’ This is the final point that I would like to
				demonstrate. One replier to my livethread remarked on the importance of the book
				to her own work: <figure>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
					<figDesc>@julesopolis [Julia de Cook, now assistant professor of Advocacy
						and Social Change in the School of Communication at Loyola University
						Chicago] to author and De Kosnik: “sorry to butt in and interrupt the
						book review: Rogue Archives is a fundamental part of the theoretical
						framing of my dissertation, which looks at extremist groups’ archiving
						practices online as a sustainability practice. Great review btw.
						[Sparkling heart emoji.]” De Kosnik, in reply: “[4 differently colored
						heart emojis] Thank you!!!!!!!!”</figDesc>
				</figure> Indeed, this was taking place two days after the Christchurch Mosque
				Shootings, which demonstrated the result of rogue extremist archives, as I
				noted: <figure>
					<graphic url="resources/images/figure06.PNG"/>
					<figDesc>Two tweets from author’s twitter thread: “I really agree -- there
						are so so many exciting possibilities -- but the internet is a
						double-edged sword and not all good -- there are negative archives.
						f.ex: the digitization, online publication, and archiving of KKK
						material -- or the archives of hate material i know of.” “the effects
						have been demonstrated so strongly &amp; tragically recently -- and it
						is something we are too aware of at @askhistorians and elsewhere (this
						is not to say De Kosnik isn't aware of this, obvs -- she might even
						touch on it later, just my thoughts here!)”</figDesc>
				</figure> The tweets demonstrate in a powerful way the double-edged nature of
				the internet. My only critique of <title rend="italic">Rogue Archives</title> is
				to point out that such double-edgedness is overlooked. De Kosnik is perhaps too
				optimistic about the internet and rogue archives. For example, in discussing
					<quote rend="inline">The Promise of Democratization</quote>, she offers a
				number of <quote rend="inline">exciting political possibilities</quote>:
						<cit><quote rend="block">vast quantities of cultural content [could]
						be preserved and made accessible to a broad public — marking an end
							to…<q>the selective tradition,</q> which always grants priority
						to the culture that supports the narratives and identities of the
						dominant group… The possibility for <q>mass audiences</q> to invert
						the sociocultural hierarchy that places them at the bottom of the
						power structure of media, and to exhibit, en masse, their ability to
						treat the culture industries’ products as the incomplete, often
						impoverished, basic matter from which they construct meaningful texts
						for themselves and their affinity-based communities.</quote>
					<ptr target="#dekosnik2016" loc="9–10"/></cit></p>
			<p>It would be unfair to De Kosnik to criticize her for failing to see the future —
					<title rend="italic">Rogue Archives</title> was written before the election
				of Donald Trump. A contemporary <q>performance</q> of it, though, is haunted by
				a spectre, a perverse Upside Down, where radicalized right-wing archives have
				also gone rogue. Rather than being a flaw, however, its autarchic world, more
				than anything else, is powerful evidence for the contemporaneity and even
				relevance of <title rend="italic">Rogue Archives</title>: the understandings,
				tools, histories, and groundings laid out in this book can be used to understand
				the dark as well as the light. If memory, which is to say the humanities, has
				gone digitally rogue, then we must all beg, borrow, and steal in constructing
				the digital humanities. Rogues, after all, can steal from the rich as well as
				the poor.</p>
			<div type="appendix">

				<head>Further Reading</head>
				<list type="simple">
					<item><bibl>Bombaci, S. P., Farr, C. M., Gallo, H. T., Mangan, A. M.,
							Stinson, L. T., Kaushik, M., et al. <title rend="quotes">Using
								Twitter to communicate conservation science from a
								professional conference: Communicating conservation through
								Twitter</title>. <title rend="italic">Conservation
								Biology</title> 30 (2016), 216–225. doi:<ref
								target="10.1111/cobi.12570"
						>10.1111/cobi.12570</ref>.</bibl></item>
					<item><bibl>Bonnie, S. <title rend="quotes">Academic Twitter and academic
								capital</title>. In L. Deborah, M. Inger, and P. Thomson
							(eds.), <title rend="italic">The Digital Academic</title> (pp.
							63–77). Routledge, 2017. doi:<ref
								target="10.4324/9781315473611-5"
								>10.4324/9781315473611-5</ref>.</bibl></item>
					<item><bibl>Budge, K., Lemon, N., and McPherson, M. <title rend="quotes"
								>Academics who tweet: “Messy” identities in
							academia</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Applied
								Research in Higher Education</title> 8 (2016), 210–221.
								doi:<ref target="10.1108/JARHE-11-2014-0114"
								>10.1108/JARHE-11-2014-0114</ref>.</bibl></item>
					<item><bibl>Chapman, S. J., Mayol, J., and Brady, R. R. <title
								rend="quotes">Twitter can enhance the medical conference
								experience</title>. <title rend="italic">BMJ</title> (2016),
							i3973. doi:<ref target="10.1136/bmj.i3973"
								>10.1136/bmj.i3973</ref>.</bibl></item>
					<item><bibl>Costello, K.L., &amp; Priem, J. <title rend="quotes">Archiving
								scholars’ tweets</title>. In <title rend="italic">Society of
								American Archivists 2011 Research Forum Proceedings</title>.
							Washington, D.C., 12 Aug. 2011. Available at <ref
								target="https://www2.archivists.org/sites/all/files/KCFinal.pdf"
								>https://www2.archivists.org/sites/all/files/KCFinal.pdf</ref>.
						</bibl></item>
					<item><bibl>Ekins, S., and Perlstein, E. O. <title rend="quotes">Ten simple
								rules of live tweeting at scientific conferences</title>.
								<title rend="italic">PLoS Computational Biology</title> 10
							(2014), e1003789. doi:<ref target="10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003789"
								>10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003789</ref>.</bibl></item>
					<item><bibl>Groves, T. <title rend="quotes">Tweeting and rule breaking at
								conferences</title>. <title rend="italic">BMJ</title>
							(2016), i3556. doi:<ref target="10.1136/bmj.i3556"
								>10.1136/bmj.i3556</ref>.</bibl></item>
					<item><bibl>Kimmons, R., and Veletsianos, G. <title rend="quotes">Education
								scholars’ evolving uses of Twitter as a conference
								backchannel and social commentary platform: Twitter
								backchannel use</title>. <title rend="italic">British
								Journal of Educational Technology</title> 47 (2016),
							445–464. doi:<ref target="10.1111/bjet.12428"
								>10.1111/bjet.12428</ref>.</bibl></item>
					<item><bibl>Li, J., and Greenhow, C. <title rend="quotes">Scholars and
								social media: Tweeting in the conference backchannel for
								professional learning</title>. <title rend="italic"
								>Educational Media International</title> 52 (2015), 1–14.
								doi:<ref target="10.1080/09523987.2015.1005426"
								>10.1080/09523987.2015.1005426</ref>.</bibl></item>
					<item><bibl>McGeeney, E. <title rend="quotes">Live tweeting and building
								the digital archive; #NFQLR – who and what is it
								for?</title>
							<title rend="italic">International Journal of Social Research
								Methodology</title> 18 (2015), 307–319. doi:<ref
								target="10.1080/13645579.2015.1017898"
								>10.1080/13645579.2015.1017898</ref>.</bibl></item>
					<item><bibl>Risser, H. S., and Waddell, G. <title rend="quotes">Beyond the
								backchannel: Tweeting patterns after two educational
								conferences</title>. <title rend="italic">Educational Media
								International</title> 55 (2018), 199–212. doi:<ref
								target="10.1080/09523987.2018.1512449"
								>10.1080/09523987.2018.1512449</ref>.</bibl></item>
					<item><bibl>Wilkinson, S. E., Basto, M. Y., Perovic, G., Lawrentschuk, N.,
							and Murphy, D. G. <title rend="quotes">The social media
								revolution is changing the conference experience: Analytics
								and trends from eight international meetings</title>. <title
								rend="italic">BJU International</title> 115 (2015), 839–846.
								doi:<ref target="10.1111/bju.12910"
							>10.1111/bju.12910</ref>.</bibl></item>
				</list>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>


			<listBibl>
				<bibl xml:id="dekosnik2016" label="De Kosnik 2016">De Kosnik, A. <title
						rend="italic">Rogue archives: Digital cultural memory and media
						fandom</title>. MIT Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts (2016).</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="oed2019" label="OED 2019"><title rend="quotes">Rogue</title>, n.
					and adj. <title rend="italic">OED Online</title> (2019), <ref
						target="http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/166894"
						>http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/166894</ref>.</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="williams2017" label="Williams 2017">Williams, A. <title
						rend="italic">The social life of books: Reading together in the
						eighteenth-century home</title>. 1st ed. Yale University Press, New
					Haven (2017).</bibl>
			</listBibl>

		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
