<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Open Data in Cultural Heritage Institutions: Can
                    We Be Better Than Data Brokers?</title>
                <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
                    <dhq:author_name>S.L. <dhq:family>Ziegler</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Louisiana State University Libraries</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>sziegler1@lsu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>S. L. Ziegler is Head of Digital Programs and Services at LSU Libraries
                            in Baton Rouge, Louisiana, where they manage the digitization
                            initiatives, digital preservation operations, and the digital library
                            infrastructure. They build partnerships throughout the state of
                            Louisiana to ensure long-term access to at-risk digital cultural
                            heritage material. Before joining LSU Libraries, Ziegler was the Head of
                            Digital Scholarship and Technology at the American Philosophical Society
                            in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, where they were the founding head of the
                            Center for Digital Scholarship and oversaw all aspects of digital
                            production and outreach.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000462</idno>
                <idno type="volume">014</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2020-06-19">19 June 2020</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
            <change when="2020-05-22" who="murelj">Authorial copyedits made</change>
            <change when="2020-04-23" who="murelj">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>Treating collections in cultural institutions as data encourages novel approaches
                    to the use of historic collections. To reframe collections as data is to focus
                    on how digitized collection material, collection metadata, and transcriptions
                    can be used and reused for various types of computational analysis. Scholars
                    active in the field of digital humanities have long taken advantage of
                    computational data. This paper focuses on the work of cultural heritage
                    institutions, which are increasingly offering collections as data. This paper
                    outlines the collections as data project and examines specific examples of
                    cultural institutions active in this space. The paper then details the practices
                    of data brokers, and explores how the data broker model can frame the use of
                    data in cultural heritage institutions. In closing a number of experiments are
                    described that might help mitigate the harm that data in cultural institutions
                    might cause. As we create and share data, can we be sure we are better than data
                    brokers?</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
                <p>Analyzes the interaction between data brokers and cultural heritage institutions'
                    data collections to explore how to mitigate the harm potentially caused by data
                in cultural institutions</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction: Collections as Data in Cultural Institutions</head>
                <p>Recently, increased attention has been paid to data in cultural
                        institutions.<note>Cultural institutions, for the purpose of this paper, are
                        libraries, archives and museums. These institutions collect, describe, and
                        make available material of cultural significance such as works of art,
                        historical documents, and published material.</note> In both 2016 and 2017,
                    the Library of Congress hosted conferences on the use of library collections as
                    data <ptr target="#loc2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#loc2017"/>. Also in 2016, the Institute of Museums and Library
                    Services (IMLS) funded a two-year project, Always Already Computational (AAC),
                        <quote rend="inline">lead to the creation of a framework to support library
                        collections as data, the identification of methods for making
                        computationally-amenable library collections more discoverable, use cases
                        and user stories for such collections, and guidance for future technical
                        development</quote>
                    <ptr target="#imls2016"/>. In addition to workshops and meetings, the
                        AAC<note>Because the phrase collections as data is used to refer to both the
                        conceptual practice of rethinking the role of collection material and the
                        team active in the IMLS grant, the name AAC will be used for the
                        latter.</note> team compiles information on like-minded projects, and has
                    released <title rend="quotes">The Santa Barbara Statement on Collections as
                        Data</title>, a document of guiding principles for treating collections as
                    data <ptr target="#aac2018b"/>.</p>
                <p>The AAC project has done a great deal of important work in bringing together a
                    wide variety of practitioners and examples and for this reason situating an
                    exploration of data in cultural heritage institutions within the framework of
                    the collections as data conversation is beneficial. As a catalyst within a wider
                    world of data-oriented endeavors in cultural institutions, the AAC project has
                    opened new avenues of investigation and has amplified the need for collaboration
                    among institutions and practitioners. It is becoming increasingly common to see
                    issues related to data in special collections libraries appearing in syllabi,
                    library strategic goals, and position papers <ptr target="#liedlibrary"/>.
                        <quote rend="inline">The growing interest in collections as data,</quote>
                    writes Chela Scott Weber in a recent OCLC Research Position Paper, <quote
                        rend="inline">means we must collaborate with colleagues in scholarly
                        communications, data services, and elsewhere across the library to grapple
                        with what computational access to our collections might look like</quote>
                    <ptr target="#weber2017"/>.</p>
                <p>Collections as data explores an expansive definition of data. “To see collections
                    as data begins with reframing all digital objects as data,” Thomas Padilla
                    writes. <quote rend="inline">Data are defined as ordered information, stored
                        digitally, that are amenable to computation. Wax cylinders, reel to reel
                        tape, vellum manuscripts, websites, masterworks, musical scores, social
                        media, code and software in digital collections are brought onto the same
                        field of consideration</quote>
                    <ptr target="#padilla2017"/>. In addition to digital collections being
                    reconceptualized as data, the metadata — such as titles, descriptions, dates —
                    can also be rethought as data. <quote rend="inline">Data as well as the data
                        that describe those data,</quote> explains the Santa Barbara Statement,
                        <quote rend="inline">are considered in scope. For example, images and the
                        metadata, finding aids, and/or catalogs that describe them are equally in
                        scope. Data resulting from the analysis of those data are also in
                        scope</quote>
                    <ptr target="#aac2018b"/>.</p>
                <p>In many ways treating collections as data eases some barriers to sharing data.
                    However, collections as data is not the same as open data. Open data has few, if
                    any restrictions on use and reuse <ptr target="#oki"/>. <quote rend="inline"
                        >Accessibility and reusability,</quote> write Koster and
                    Woutersen-Windhouwer, <quote rend="inline">do not require collections and
                        objects to be freely available, modifiable and shareable with free
                        tools,</quote> as the open definition requires. <quote rend="inline">Some
                        metadata or objects will be copyright protected, have privacy issues or
                        local law issues</quote>
                    <ptr target="#koster2018"/>. When we rethink collections as data, collections
                    are usually easier to share, however, there are still many reasons that the data
                    might not be open.<note>The author is thankful to Thomas Padilla for reviewing
                        an early draft of this section for accuracy; any remaining errors or
                        misrepresentations are the fault of the author.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In November 2019 the AAC grant project came to an end and was succeeded by a new
                    phase, Collections as Data: Part to Whole (“Part to Whole” n.d.). Collections as
                    Data: Part to Whole fosters <quote rend="inline">the development of broadly
                        viable models that support implementation and use of collections as
                        data</quote> by funding project teams that <quote rend="inline">will develop
                        models that support collections as data implementation and holistic
                        reconceptualization of services and roles that support scholarly use</quote>
                    (“Part to Whole” n.d.). Even beyond the AAC project the number and scale of
                    cultural heritage collections available as data continues to increase. In 2019,
                    the Library of Congress, with funding from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation,
                    launched the Computing Cultural Heritage in the Cloud (CCHC) project, to <quote
                        rend="inline">pilot ways to combine cutting edge technology and the
                        collections of the largest library in the world, to support digital research
                        at scale</quote>
                    <ptr target="#loc2019"/>. Also in 2019, the National Library of Scotland
                    launched the Data Foundry Website to present, <quote rend="inline">collections
                        as data in a machine-readable format, widening the scope for digital
                        research and analysis</quote>
                    <ptr target="#nls2019"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Data in Cultural Heritage Institutions</head>
                <p>The AAC team has compiled a number of Facets, or case studies that draw attention
                    to many ways cultural institutions are creating and using data.<note><quote
                            rend="inline">A facet documents a collections as data implementation. An
                            implementation consists of the people, services, practices,
                            technologies, and infrastructure that aim to encourage computational use
                            of cultural heritage collections.</quote> see <title rend="quotes">A
                            Release and a Call - Collections as Data Facets</title>. Always Already
                        Computational - Collections as Data. Accessed May 17, 2018. <ref
                            target="https://collectionsasdata.github.io/facets/"
                            >https://collectionsasdata.github.io/facets/</ref>.</note> These
                    examples include the use metadata, digital facsimiles, and structured
                    transcriptions. The metadata examples show new forms of access and engagement
                    with collections, <quote rend="inline">allowing people to creatively re-imagine
                        and re-engineer our collection in the digital space</quote>
                    <ptr target="#newbury"/>. The Carnegie Museum of Art, for example, makes
                    available <quote rend="inline">data on approximately 28,269 objects across all
                        departments of the museum[:] fine arts, decorative arts, photography,
                        contemporary art, and the Heinz Architectural Center</quote>
                    <ptr target="#carnegie"/>. Released as part of the 120th anniversary celebration
                    of the museum, the data promotes the central mission of the museum. <quote
                        rend="inline">The case to provide the public increased access to museum data
                        was not a difficult one at the Carnegie Museum of Art,</quote> explain the
                    authors of the data, <quote rend="inline">the museum considers engagement and
                        education to be a core part of its mission, and firmly believes in Open
                        Access as essential to museum practice</quote>
                    <ptr target="#newbury"/>.</p>
                <p>In addition to sharing metadata, many libraries and museums are allowing full
                    access to digital facsimiles. The Getty, for example, <quote rend="inline">makes
                        available, without charge, all available digital images to which the Getty
                        holds the rights or that are in the public domain to be used for any
                        purpose. No permission is required</quote>
                    <ptr target="#getty"/>. As another example, OPenn, at the University of
                    Pennsylvania, <quote rend="inline">contains complete sets of high-resolution
                        archival images of manuscripts … along with machine-readable TEI P5
                        descriptions and technical metadata. All materials on this site are in the
                        public domain or released under Creative Commons licenses as Free Cultural
                        Works</quote>
                    <ptr target="#upenn"/>. </p>
                <p>Beyond metadata and digital facsimiles, collections reformatted as structured
                    data is also a growing trend in cultural institutions. This often involves
                    transcribing text and applying some type of structure. Haverford College
                    Libraries reformatted collections into TEI-encoded text for the projects <title
                        rend="quotes">Beyond Penn’s Treaty</title>
                    <ptr target="#zarafonetis"/> and <title rend="quotes">Ticha: A Digital Text
                        Explorer for Colonial Zapotec</title>
                    <ptr target="#lillehaugen"/>. Reformatting the collections as structured data
                    allows for enhanced linkages between items as well as customized interfaces. The
                    Museum of Modern Art (MOMA) structured exhibition data in a database, and shared
                    as a CSV (Lill n.d.). This project has resulted in a rich history of past MOMA
                    exhibitions.</p>
                <p>A fuller exploration of a particular open data project will help highlight both
                    the process and possible pitfalls of collections as data work in cultural
                    heritage institutions. The American Philosophical Society Library (APS)
                    digitized, reformatted as data, and opened historic prison records. The APS
                    holds three admission books created by the Eastern State Penitentiary.<note>
                        Historically important for many reasons, the Eastern State Penitentiary
                        championed the standardized use of <q>cellular isolation</q> in which each
                        inmate spends all of his or her time in a cell by themselves. For more
                        information, see the APS finding aid: <ref
                            target="https://search.amphilsoc.org/collections/view?docId=ead/Mss.365.P381p-ead.xml"
                            >https://search.amphilsoc.org/collections/view?docId=ead/Mss.365.P381p-ead.xml</ref>,
                        and the website of the Eastern State Historic Site: <ref
                            target="https://www.easternstate.org"
                        >https://www.easternstate.org</ref>.</note> The books, covering the years
                    1830-1850 (with a gap in the 1840s), hold information on each prisoner,
                    including name, age, the crime(s) for which they had been found guilty, the
                    sentence, and often a note on when they were freed (or died). Also included,
                    though less consistently, is gender, race, and religious affiliation.
                    Additionally, notes from the moral instructor appear for each record; similar to
                    contemporary prison parsons, moral instructors were non-denominational religious
                    authorities and they recorded a paragraph-length note on each inmate which
                    details the religious education of the prisoner as well as other biographical
                    elements.</p>
                <p>In 2015, the team<note>The digitization team for this project included Grace
                        DiAgostino and Bayard Miller.</note> digitized the admission books. At this
                    point, the scanned images of the pages of the admission books could be treated
                    as data. As data, they are open to computational analysis. Just as digital
                    representations of paintings allow the application of computer models to extract
                    information and recombine it to find new patterns and propose linkages between
                        pieces,<note>On the uses of digitized art as data, see: <title rend="quotes"
                            >The Next Rembrandt</title>. The Next Rembrandt. Accessed May 29, 2018.
                            <ref target="https://www.nextrembrandt.com"
                            >https://www.nextrembrandt.com</ref>. Hristova, Stefka. <title
                            rend="quotes">Images as Data: Cultural Analytics and Aby Warburg’s
                            Mnemosyne</title>. <title rend="italic">International Journal for
                            Digital Art History</title> 0, no. 2 (October 18, 2016).
                        https://doi.org/10.11588/dah.2016.2.23489.</note> the pages of the prison
                    admission books can be treated as data. For example, by analyzing the pages as
                    data, one could ask if the handwriting changes based on the positive or negative
                    attributes ascribed to the prisoner.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                    </figure>
                
                <p>Taking the process one step further, in 2016 and 2017 the team transcribed the
                    content into spreadsheets.<note>The transcription team consisted of Michelle
                        Ziogas, Bayard Miller, and Kristina Frey</note> The library published the
                    data as CSV files in a variety of outlets, including the APS Github repository
                        <ptr target="#aps-git"/> and the Magazine for Early American Datasets <ptr
                        target="#ziegler2016"/>. The workflow was simple: each transcriber had two
                    computer monitors, one to see the digitized page and the other to type into a
                    spreadsheet. The information on the pages are mostly consistent. For example,
                    the first line of each entry usually includes the prisoner’s name, age, crime
                    for which he or she is incarcerated, race (usually if non-White), and location
                    of birth (if outside of US). The repetition and consistency enabled the
                    information to be captured with few issues. </p>
                <p>However, the process is not always obvious, and choices do matter. For example,
                    the handwriting can often be difficult to read, and conventions about how to
                    depict abbreviations, spelling errors and indecipherable words had to be
                        established.<note>See, for example, the <title rend="quotes">Conventions
                            Used</title> section of the Github Read Me file. <title rend="quotes"
                            >Historic Prison Data</title> American Philosophical Society Github
                        Repository, <ref
                            target="https://github.com/AmericanPhilosophicalSociety/Historic-Prison-Data#conventions-used"
                            >https://github.com/AmericanPhilosophicalSociety/Historic-Prison-Data#conventions-used</ref>
                    </note> Sometimes racial categories are mentioned, such as <term>black</term>,
                    or <term>light black</term>. Sometimes, on the same place on the page, religions
                    are mentioned, such as <term>Catholic</term>. Sometimes the birth location is
                    listed near the same place on the page, such as “Irish”. It is easy to imagine
                    that the categories of race, religion, and birth location were doing
                    interpretive work for both the creator of the records and the intended audience.
                    Jacksonian America was a time of great anxiety of immigration and saw a large
                    number of race riots <ptr target="#feldberg1980"/>. The transcription team
                    needed to make decisions about how to group these pieces of information. Records
                    are not neutral; the process of transcription is not neutral.<note>For concerns
                        about relying on transcriptions, see James H. Merrell, <title rend="quotes"
                                ><q>Exactly as they appear</q>: Another Look at the Notes of a 1766
                            Treason Trial in Poughkeepsie, New York, with Some Musings on the
                            Documentary Foundations of Early American History</title>, <title
                            rend="italic">Early American Studies</title> 12, no. 1 (Winter 2014):
                        202-237. See also Jacqueline Wernimont’s thoughts on the role of tabular
                        data and the loss of understanding: <ref
                            target="https://digital-frontiers.org/conference/2017/texas-digital-library-closing-keynote-address-counting-dead-quantum-media-and-how-we"
                            >https://digital-frontiers.org/conference/2017/texas-digital-library-closing-keynote-address-counting-dead-quantum-media-and-how-we</ref>,
                        as well as Foreman, P. Gabrielle, and Labanya Mookerjee, <title
                            rend="quotes">Computing in the Dark: Spreadsheets, Data Collection and
                            DH’s Racist Inheritance</title> in <title rend="italic">Always Already
                            Computational Position Statements</title>, <ref
                            target="https://collectionsasdata.github.io/resources/"
                            >https://collectionsasdata.github.io/resources/</ref>, accessed
                        5/18/2018</note>
                </p>

                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    </figure>
                
                <p>From the point of view of the APS Library data initiatives team, the CSV files
                    themselves are the finished product. The Open Data Initiative of the APS Library
                    aims to increase access to computational data by identifying material in the
                    collection that <quote rend="inline">is conducive to being reconfigured as
                        datasets</quote>
                    <ptr target="#aps-data"/>. In the case of this project, however, we built
                    example visualization tools as a means of promoting the use of the data. In late
                    2017, the library launched a series of visualization tools grouped together
                    under the title <title rend="quotes">Eastern Apps: Visualizing Historic Prison
                        Data</title>
                    <ptr target="#aps-apps"/>. A suite of three visualization apps, <title
                        rend="quotes">Eastern Apps</title> serves as an example of the use of
                    collections as data for digital humanities projects, and has served to help the
                    APS Digital Scholarship Center promote the use of other datasets to digital
                    humanists <ptr target="#ziegler2019"/>.<note>A growing selection of open data
                        sets can be found on the APS Library Open Data page, <title rend="quotes"
                            >Open Data | APS Digital Library</title>. Accessed June 5, 2018. <ref
                            target="http://diglib.amphilsoc.org/data"
                            >http://diglib.amphilsoc.org/data</ref>. </note>
                </p>
                <p>As the examples in this section highlight, collections as data in cultural
                    institutions can take many forms. Metadata enables the re-imagining of art
                    collections, as in the case with the Carnegie Museum of Art. Digitized objects
                    allow use and reuse for both scholarly and imaginative purposes. Collection
                    content can be transcribed as structured open data allowing for analysis,
                    visualizations, access through innovative interfaces, and new types of research.
                    However, there is always interpretive work that needs to be done when creating
                    datasets from cultural heritage material.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Data Brokers </head>
                <p>In June 2016, HBO’s <hi rend="italic">Last Week Tonight With John Oliver</hi>
                    purchased nearly 15 million dollars of debt for 60 thousand dollars. The
                    purchase was part of an exposé on the debt buying business, what John Oliver
                    called <quote rend="inline">a grimy business.</quote> A large part of the
                    griminess of the business is the ability to buy and sell personal information
                    about individuals. Names, addresses, social security numbers and other
                    information is passed from one buyer to the next, often emailed in spreadsheets.
                    The buyers hope to pressure the named individuals into paying the debts,
                    creating a profit for the debt buyer. While the <title rend="italic">Last Week
                        Tonight</title> exposé focused on debt buying. The business of buying and
                    selling personal information extends much further. </p>
                <p>In March 2014, CBS’ <title rend="italic">60-Minutes</title> aired an episode on
                    data brokers. <quote rend="inline">Every piece of data about us now seems to be
                        worth something to somebody,</quote> said Tim Sparapani during the show.
                        <quote rend="inline">And lots more people are giving up information about
                        people they do business with, from state Departments of Motor Vehicles, to
                        pizza parlors</quote>
                    <ptr target="#cbs2018"/>. The data from different sources are gathered together
                    to form dossiers. <quote rend="inline">The dossiers are about
                        individuals,</quote> one interviewee continued. <quote rend="inline">That's
                        the whole point of these dossiers. It is information that is individually
                        identified to an individual or linked to an individual</quote>
                    <ptr target="#cbs2018"/>. This information can then be used to identify
                    individuals with health issues, significant debt, and individuals who suffer
                    from addictions. This data is then sold to potential employers, other data
                    brokers and increasingly to credit monitoring companies and law enforcement. </p>
                <p>In 2014, the FTC released a report on data brokers that highlighted how little we
                    know about the data being collected, and how much data there is about us.
                    Because most of the data gathered about us do not come directly from us, most
                    people do not fully grasp the amount of information data brokers collect and
                    sell. <quote rend="inline">Some of the information data brokers collect, like
                        bankruptcy information, voting history, consumer purchase data, web browsing
                        activities and warranty registrations</quote> are gathered from other
                    sources <ptr target="#ftc2014"/>. This data is used to put us in categories that
                    make the data easier to market to other companies. <quote rend="inline"
                        >Potentially sensitive categories include those that primarily focus on
                        ethnicity and income-levels, a consumer’s age, or health-related conditions
                        like <q>Expectant Parent,</q>
                        <q>Diabetes Interest,</q> and <q>Cholesterol Focus</q></quote>
                    <ptr target="#ftc2014"/>.</p>
                <p>The practice of data brokerage is secretive, and there is often no way to appeal
                    incorrect information. The profiles these companies assign to us are often
                    incorrect. <quote rend="inline">In the world of data brokers, you have no idea
                        who all has bought, acquired or harvested information about you, what they
                        do with it, who they provide it to, whether it is right or wrong or how much
                        money is being made on your digital identity,</quote> writes Kalev Leetaru,
                    of his efforts to determine who is making money from his information. <quote
                        rend="inline">Nor do you have the right to demand that they delete their
                        profile on you</quote>
                    <ptr target="#leetaru2018"/>. In the case of Leetaru, the companies got many
                    things wrong, including his age. In 2017 writer Caitlyn Renee Miller bought
                    information about herself from a data broker only to find that <quote
                        rend="inline">nearly 50 percent of the data in the report about me was
                        incorrect</quote>
                    <ptr target="#miller2017"/>.</p>
                <p>In 2017, Equifax announced a data breach that allowed the personal information of
                    143 million people to be stolen. In 2018, Facebook announced that the data
                    analysis company Cambridge Analytica used personal data in ways that easily
                    match John Oliver’s definition of grimy. The use of personal data by companies
                    large and small to profit is an important backdrop against which to evaluate
                    open data in cultural institutions. Equifax and Cambridge Analytica are not,
                    technically, data brokers. The former is a credit monitoring company and the
                    latter, before declaring bankruptcy <ptr target="#confessore2018"/>, was a data
                    analysis firm. However, the role of data brokers, companies that buy, combine,
                    and sell personal information to other companies, is instructive for our
                    purposes, and the shades of differences can be grouped together for our
                    purposes. </p>
                <p>Data brokers, along with credit monitoring companies and data analytic companies,
                    benefit from the information of other people. This information often harms
                    individuals through the categories they create. Examples such as <quote
                        rend="inline"><q>single mom struggling in an urban setting</q> or <q>people
                            who did not speak English and felt more comfortable speaking in
                            Spanish</q> or <q>gamblers</q></quote>
                    <ptr target="#naylor2016"/>. Categories such as these, which are created,
                    populated, and shared by data brokers, make life harder for
                        individuals.<note>Quantifying the harm is difficult due to the secretive
                        nature of data transfer and use. The United Kingdom-based non-profit Privacy
                        International is one of many drawing attention to this harm. <title
                            rend="quotes">Video: What Is Data Exploitation?</title> Privacy
                        International. Accessed May 29, 2018. <ref
                            target="http://privacyinternational.org/video/1626/video-what-data-exploitation"
                            >http://privacyinternational.org/video/1626/video-what-data-exploitation</ref>.</note>
                    The data are also used to construct systems that target and harm individuals.
                    Advances in predictive policing, civilian surveillance, and backlashes against
                    activists are all the outcomes of systems built on data shared by and among
                    companies representing us in categories we cannot appeal <ptr
                        target="#winston2018"/>
                    <ptr target="#feldman2018"/>
                    <ptr target="#waldman2018"/>
                    <ptr target="#levin2018"/>.</p>
                <p>Data brokers offer an important example of one way of interacting with data. This
                    is an example against which we should compare ourselves when we release data in
                    cultural institutions and use data for digital humanities. We should always ask
                    ourselves, are we better than data brokers? </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Are We Better Than Data Brokers?</head>
                <p>Data brokers profit from other people’s information. Those described in their
                    datasets often have no way of knowing how they are being represented, and have
                    no way of questioning or correcting this representation. As data becomes more
                    prevalent in cultural institutions, and many of us — through publishing papers
                    and presenting on our work — benefit from data about other people, now is good
                    time to evaluate ourselves in relation to data brokers. This section explores
                    examples of harm done by institutions as they represent individuals and groups. </p>
                <p>Identifying specific cases of harm can be difficult. For this reason, it is
                    common to focus on groups that are historically marginalized, and who have
                    reason to be suspicious of their representation in mainstream culture. Anyone
                    who has ever had a reason to fear categorization by a dominant culture can more
                    easily understand the power of data. Many groups have reason to be suspicious.
                    For the purposes of this paper, however, examples will focus on African American
                    representations. This decision is meant to both draw attention to the unique
                    position of the African American community as a marginalized group and to honor
                    the important work of generations of scholars who struggle to educate the
                    dominant culture about these and related dangers.</p>
                <p>Are people harmed by the data that we have and share? It is not standard practice
                    for cultural institutions to share social security numbers, credit card numbers,
                    or other sensitive personal information in either physical records, digitized
                    facsimiles, or datasets.<note>See, for example, <title rend="quotes">Questions
                            and Answers on Privacy and Confidentiality</title>. <title rend="italic"
                            >Text. Advocacy, Legislation &amp; Issues</title>, May 29, 2007. <ref
                            target="http://www.ala.org/advocacy/privacy/FAQ"
                            >http://www.ala.org/advocacy/privacy/FAQ</ref>. Software for digital
                        preservation systems, such as ePadd for email, are also built with these
                        issues in mind, see <title rend="quotes">EPADD User Guide 5.0</title>.
                        Google Docs, May 2017. <ref
                            target="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1ZMuWU0z-IVsk80_lUEYMfVrwfCsS1bp0sjL28GBGcMU"
                            >https://docs.google.com/document/d/1ZMuWU0z-IVsk80_lUEYMfVrwfCsS1bp0sjL28GBGcMU</ref></note>
                    As such, there is a significant difference between us and the work done by data
                    brokers. Even with standardized practices in place to protect individuals,
                    cultural institutions, historically, have done a form of harm to groups though
                    representation. If we do not take this seriously now, we are likely to compound
                    the problem through our open data. </p>
                <p>Writing about the role of the media in enforcing negative representations of
                    African Americans, and thus the media’s culpability in historic lynchings,
                    Sherrilyn Ifill writes, <title rend="quotes">[t]he failure to report on the
                        <q>ordinariness</q> of the black people's lives … undermined the ability of
                        whites to see their black neighbors, servants, and laborers as human
                        beings</title>
                    <ptr target="#ifill2007" loc="168"/>. She continues: <cit><quote rend="block"
                            source="#ifill2007">Whites could at best ignore the conditions in which
                            most blacks lived and at worst develop a sense that blacks did not lead
                            normal lives in which education, work and family were paramount and
                            central. Instead, blacks could be seen as ‘other,’ ‘different,’ not
                            possessed of the same humanity as whites ... The complicity of ordinary
                            whites, who stood and watched a lynching without interfering, was made
                            possible by the dehumanizing choices the media made in their coverage of
                            blacks.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ifill2007" loc="168"/></cit> And the representations of one
                    group of another, in this case the representation of African Americans by
                    predominantly Caucasian media institutions, continues to affect our society.
                        <quote rend="inline">The lingering remnants of these dehumanizing portrayals
                        of blacks in the media,</quote> writes Ifill, bringing the issue to the
                    present, <quote rend="inline">have modern currency,</quote> including
                    over-incarceration of African American males, hyper policing of black
                    communities, and police brutality <ptr target="#ifill2007" loc="168–9"/>. Many
                    of these issues are often ignored by white communities because of a history of
                    media representation of African Americans. </p>
                <p>The representation of one group by another group can range from obvious fiction
                    to pretense of objective truth. <quote rend="inline">All groups tell
                        stories,</quote> writes David Pilgrim, founding curator of the Jim Crow
                    Museum, <quote rend="inline">but some groups have the power to impose their
                        stories on others, to label others, stigmatize others, paint others as
                        undesirables, and to have these social labels presented as scientific fact,
                        God’s will or wholesome entertainment</quote>
                    <ptr target="#pilgrim2017" loc="8"/>. The types of stories matter. It also
                    matters which type of institution is telling the story. <quote rend="inline"
                        >When we watch movies or read novels,</quote> continues Pilgrim, <quote
                        rend="inline">we know that they are stories; we identify the characters,
                        follow the plot and anticipate the conclusion. But there are other stories
                        that are not so easily identified — sometimes they masquerade as object,
                        race-neutral truth</quote>
                    <ptr target="#pilgrim2017" loc="9"/>. To illustrate this point, Pilgrim
                    investigates the use of pseudo-science to justify racist beliefs and actions.
                    Scientific institutions were used, during slavery and Jim Crow, to promote and
                    legitimize racism. </p>
                <p>In what way are cultural institutions doing the same? The collecting practices of
                    cultural institutions have long been marred by the racial bias of the archivists
                    and curators who build collections. The decisions made about what is collected
                    are colored by the opinions of those doing the collecting and this has tipped
                    the scales on how African Americans are represented in archives. An overt
                    example from the author's own institution is a case in point. In 1945, the LSU
                    Department of Archives and Manuscripts (a pre-curser to the current Special
                    Collections) was offered the opportunity to acquire the collection of African
                    American bibliophile and book collector, Henry P. Slaughter. The quality of the
                    collection was endorsed by archivist Herbert Kellar and book dealer Forest Sweet
                    who wrote, <quote rend="inline">it is no sense a collection to be filed away -
                        it is rather a collection to be worn out with legitimate use for what it can
                        offer as a basis of study of the negro problem</quote>
                    <ptr target="#sweet1945"/>. </p>
                <p>Despite this endorsement, the University eventually passed on the acquisition on
                    the advice of Archivist and History Professor, Edwin Davis:<note>Herbert A.
                        Kellar was the Director of the McCormick Historical Association and a
                        founding member of the Society of American Archivists; Edwin Davis was the
                        first archivist hired to manage the LSU Department of Archives and
                        Manuscripts</note>
                    <quote rend="inline">the collection has been selected with the plan to emphasize
                        the Negro’s point of view of the race problem. If this is true it is my
                        opinion that the collection will have a considerable amount, perhaps an
                        appreciable percentage, of what might be termed weak material. I have
                        however, no evidence for this opinion. It might prove to be a very valuable
                        collection</quote>
                    <ptr target="#davis1946"/>. Davis, based only on his assumption that any
                    collection that centers an African American perspective has minimal value,
                    declined the collection.<note>The collection is currently housed at the Atlanta
                        University Center Robert W. Woodruff Library Archives Research Center.
                            See:<ref
                            target="http://findingaids.auctr.edu/repositories/2/resources/62"
                            >http://findingaids.auctr.edu/repositories/2/resources/62</ref>. The
                    author wishes to thank Jenny Mitchell, Head of Manuscript Processing at LSU Libraries,
                    for this example.</note>
                    Rarely does such documentation, but similar decisions are common throughout
                    collecting institutions. </p>
                <p>Decisions about what material cultural institutions collect have long term
                    repercussions that are felt for generations. In March 2019, Tamara Lanier filed
                    a lawsuit against Harvard University over ownership of a daguerreotype
                    photograph of an enslaved ancestor named Renty and his daughter, Delia. The
                    photographs were commissioned by Professor Louis Agassiz and utilized as
                    evidence of inferiority of the African American race. The photographs were
                    rediscovered in 1976 hidden away in the attic of a campus museum. Since then the
                    University has loaned the photographs to other museums but also limited the use
                    of the images by researchers due to their <quote rend="inline">sensitive</quote>
                    nature <ptr target="#hartocollis2019"/>
                    <ptr target="#schuessler2019"/>. </p>
                <p>What is collected matters, and so does its description. The role of the library
                    catalog in reinforcing dominant points-of-view has been explored many
                        times.<note>See, for example, Berman, Sanford.Prejudices and Antipathies : A
                        Tract on the LC Subject Heads Concerning People. McFarland &amp; Co., 1993.
                        Olson, Hope. <title rend="quotes">Mapping Beyond Dewey’s Boundaries:
                            Constructing Classificatory Space for’ Marginalized Knowledge
                            Domains</title>. <title rend="italic">Library Trends</title> 47, no. 2
                        (Fall 1998): 233–54. Berman, Sanford. <title rend="italic">Prejudices and
                            Antipathies: A Tract on the LC Subject Heads Concerning People</title>.
                        Adler, Melissa. <title rend="quotes">Classification Along the Color Line:
                            Excavating Racism in the Stacks</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of
                            Critical Library and Information Studies</title> 1, no. 1 (January 29,
                        2017). https://doi.org/10.24242/jclis.v1i1.17. <title rend="quotes">View of
                            Engaging an Author in a Critical Reading of Subject Headings</title>.
                        Accessed May 22, 2018. <ref
                            target="http://libraryjuicepress.com/journals/index.php/jclis/article/view/20/12"
                            >http://libraryjuicepress.com/journals/index.php/jclis/article/view/20/12</ref>.</note>
                    Melissa Adler, for example, draws attention to the <quote rend="inline">ways
                        that sections of library classifications were constructed based on ideas
                        about African Americans</quote>
                    <ptr target="#adler2017" loc="5"/>. Adler traces the creation of the library
                    classifications as they map to racist ideas active in the late 19th and early
                    20th centuries. The library catalog freezes these ideas in place, Adler claims,
                    and makes them look natural and obvious, similar to the manner of the
                    pseudo-science Pilgrim describes.</p>
                <p>The business of gathering, combining, and selling data is not new. However, the
                    scope of surveillance and reach of the systems created with the data is
                    unprecedented due to new tools and methods. In the same way, library catalogs
                    have long represented groups of people in problematic ways. What is different is
                    the new tools and methods we are using to promote the use and reuse of these
                    descriptions and collections. The collections as data framework in cultural
                    institutions carries with it the possibility for our descriptions of people to
                    be shared, combined with other data, and used to negatively affect groups. The
                    ability to exert <quote rend="inline">control over group and personal identity
                        and memory,</quote> writes Noble, <quote rend="inline">must become a matter
                        of concern for archivists, librarians, and information workers</quote>
                    <ptr target="#noble2018" loc="172"/>. This is all the more urgent as we look
                    toward a future of increased share-ability and data-oriented services. Now is
                    the time to ask how we can be better than data brokers.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>How Can We Be Better? </head>
                <p>This section posits three possible directions that are still in the early phases
                    of exploration. These possibilities are listed as sincere efforts to investigate
                    possible steps toward a future in which my work with data feels less grimy. As
                    white librarians, we work in a field that has long struggled to be inclusive to
                    historically marginalized communities.<note>See, by way of introduction, Hudson,
                        David James. <title rend="quotes">On Diversity as Anti-Racism in Library and
                            Information Studies: A Critique</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of
                            Critical Library and Information Studies</title> 1, no.1 (2017). DOI:
                        10.24242/jclis.v1i1.6. jesus, nina de. <title rend="quotes">Locating the
                            Library in Institutional Oppression – In the Library with the Lead
                            Pipe</title>. Accessed May 30, 2018.
                        /2014/locating-the-library-in-institutional-oppression/. Galvan, Angela.
                            <title rend="quotes">Soliciting Performance, Hiding Bias: Whiteness and
                            Librarianship – In the Library with the Lead Pipe</title>. Accessed May
                        30, 2018.
                        /2015/soliciting-performance-hiding-bias-whiteness-and-librarianship/.</note>
                    We hope to implement these steps as experiments at our current institution, and
                    to join a community of practitioners exploring these topics in different
                    settings. These experiments are meant to inform the practice of collections as
                    data — as it relates to metadata, digital facsimiles, and structured data — as
                    well as the practice of digital humanities. These approaches are informed by
                    literature on empathy, data science, and critical librarianship. </p>
            <div>
                <head>Empathy and Description</head>
                <p>The grimy business of data brokers is legal.<note>At the time of this writing,
                        the European Union’s General Data Protection Regulations (GDPR) is just
                        coming into effect, and while companies large and small that collect data
                        are adjusting some behaviors the outcome on the core practice of data
                        brokerage in the United States is yet to be determined. Ong, Thuy. <title
                            rend="quotes">Microsoft Expands Data Privacy Tools Ahead of
                        GDPR</title>. The Verge, May 24, 2018. <ref
                            target="https://www.theverge.com/2018/5/24/17388206/microsoft-expand-data-privacy-tools-gdpr-eu"
                            >https://www.theverge.com/2018/5/24/17388206/microsoft-expand-data-privacy-tools-gdpr-eu</ref>.
                        Tiku, Nitasha. <title rend="quotes">How Europe’s New Privacy Law Will Change
                            the Web, and More</title>. WIRED, March 19, 2018. <ref
                            target="https://www.wired.com/story/europes-new-privacy-law-will-change-the-web-and-more/"
                            >https://www.wired.com/story/europes-new-privacy-law-will-change-the-web-and-more/</ref>.</note>
                    While it is important that cultural institutions follow laws when we rethink our
                    collections as data, and when we use this data to build digital humanities
                    projects, this alone will not be enough. For example, the Health Insurance
                    Portability and Accountability Act of 1996 (HIPPA) provides privacy protection
                    for health-related data (Health and Human Services 2015), and, as we saw above,
                    it is established practice in cultural institutions not to share sensitive
                    financial or personal information about people represented in the collection.
                    However this is not enough. A thin legalistic understanding of what should and
                    should not be shared will never be robust enough to ensure we do not harm people
                    we represent. There are no laws, of course, against harmful library subject
                    headers or terminology. </p>
                <p>Arguing for a move away from thin legalistic frameworks, Michelle Caswell and
                    Marika Cifor explore the role of feminist ethics in reconceptualizing the role
                    of archives and the people represented in our collections. This approach is
                    applicable for all cultural institutions, collections as data work, and digital
                    humanities projects that use this data. <quote rend="inline">In a feminist
                        ethics approach,</quote> they write, <quote rend="inline">archivists are
                        seen as caregivers, bound to records creators, subjects, users, and
                        communities through a web of mutual affective responsibility</quote>
                    <ptr target="#caswell2016" loc="23"/>. By caring about the subjects of records —
                    the people represented in the records, who are <quote rend="inline">counted,
                        classified, studied, enslaved, traded as property, and/or murdered</quote>
                    <ptr target="#caswell2016" loc="36"/> — we can make decisions about the records
                    based on our empathy with the people described. Caswell and Cifor write:
                            <cit><quote source="#caswell2016" rend="block">[A] feminist approach
                            guides the archivist to an affective responsibility to empathize with
                            the subjects of the records and, in so doing, to consider their
                            perspectives in making archival decisions. This is in contrast to the
                            dominant West mode of archival practice, in which archivists solely
                            consider the legal rights of records creators … In the feminist
                            approach, the archivist cares about and for and with subjects; she
                            empathizes with them.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#caswell2016" loc="36"/></cit> Even in situations where no laws
                    exist to stop the sharing of information, we can ask ourselves: What would the
                    people described in the records think of this project or representation? If the
                    people described in our data could see our project, would we be as eager to work
                    on this project? </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Asking For Help</head>
                <p>If we would work differently when those represented in our work can see it, how
                    could we ensure that this happens? The particular individuals described in
                    datasets by cultural institutions are likely to be deceased, as is the case for
                    the historic prison records described above. However, we can work with members
                    of affected communities. </p>
                <p>Safiya Noble, writing about the shortcomings of Google and other tech companies,
                    calls for the combination of technology and critical studies. <quote
                        rend="inline">We need people designing technologies for society to have
                        training and an education on the histories of marginalized people, at a
                        minimum,</quote> Nobel writes, <quote rend="inline">and we need them working
                        alongside people with rigorous training and preparation from the social
                        sciences and humanities</quote>
                    <ptr target="#noble2018" loc="70"/>. Applying this idea to the cultural
                    institutions creating and releasing data, and to digital humanist using the
                    data, we could bring in experts in African American Studies, for example, if our
                    data represents the African American community, or Women and Gender Studies, if
                    applicable. The expertise from their subject could be brought to bear within the
                    cultural institution creating the data and within the digital humanities group
                    working with the data. In short, we can ask for help.<note>It’s worth noting
                        here that this can easily go awry. There’s a history of white people asking
                        black people to explain why racism. For example, soon after the 2016
                        presidential election,Slate held a forum for African American writers to
                        reflect on an increased demand of this type.Bouie, Jamelle, Gene Demby,
                        Aisha Harris, Tressie McMillan Cottom, and Chau Tu. <title rend="quotes">I’m
                            Not Your Racial Confessor</title>. <title rend="italic">Slate</title>,
                        December 6, 2016. <ref
                            target="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/politics/2016/12/the_black_person_s_burden_of_managing_white_emotions_in_the_age_of_trump.html"
                            >http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/politics/2016/12/the_black_person_s_burden_of_managing_white_emotions_in_the_age_of_trump.html</ref>.
                        See also: Johnson, Theodore R. <title rend="quotes">How Black Writers Can
                            Help White Readers</title>. <title rend="italic">The New
                            Republic</title>, December 29, 2016. <ref
                            target="https://newrepublic.com/article/139541/black-writers-can-help-white-readers"
                            >https://newrepublic.com/article/139541/black-writers-can-help-white-readers</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Many cultural institutions are unlikely to be able to create new professional
                    positions specifically for individuals trained in the histories of marginalized
                    communities. However, it is critical that we find ways to pay the scholars whose
                    help we seek. In academic libraries and archives this might take the form of
                    graduate assistantships. Digital humanists will likely be similarly restricted.
                    However, including these roles in project plans and grant applications is one
                    way to normalize the process of asking for help. Money is not the only
                    incentive; this could be a valuable means of exposing scholars to possible
                    careers in cultural institutions and digital humanities. However, monetary
                    compensation is an important part of letting scholars know we take their
                    expertise seriously. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Taking Suggestions</head>
                <p>As we have seen, it can be very difficult to know what information data brokers
                    have about us, and to correct what is incorrect.<note>Even attempts at
                        transparency by data brokers often prove to be misleading. See: Insider,
                        Business. <title rend="quotes">The Site That Shows You All The Personal Data
                            Advertisers Have On You Isn’t Entirely Accurate</title>. <title
                            rend="italic">Business Insider</title>. Accessed May 25, 2018. <ref
                            target="http://www.businessinsider.com/acxiom-about-the-data-problems-2013-9"
                            >http://www.businessinsider.com/acxiom-about-the-data-problems-2013-9</ref>.
                        Singer, Natasha. <title rend="quotes">Acxiom Lets Consumers See Data It
                            Collects</title>. <title rend="italic">The New York Times</title>,
                        September 4, 2013, sec. Technology. <ref
                            target="https://www.nytimes.com/2013/09/05/technology/acxiom-lets-consumers-see-data-it-collects.html"
                            >https://www.nytimes.com/2013/09/05/technology/acxiom-lets-consumers-see-data-it-collects.html</ref>.
                        Breen, Bant. <title rend="quotes">AboutTheData: Data Collection Gone
                            Wrong</title>. <title rend="italic">Huffington Post</title> (blog),
                        September 26, 2013. <ref
                            target="https://www.huffingtonpost.com/bant-breen/aboutthedata-data-collect_b_3998252.html"
                            >https://www.huffingtonpost.com/bant-breen/aboutthedata-data-collect_b_3998252.html</ref>.</note>
                    Is there any reason why cultural institutions cannot do better? We could include
                    feedback channels for the systems we create, and we could make our decisions as
                    transparent as possible. We can bring in experts in the history of marginalized
                    communities, as discussed above. We can also take a step further by ensuring
                    that anyone — those we identify as experts and invite into the process, and
                    those we do not — has a chance to ask us about our decisions and suggest
                    alternate practices. We could ensure that every data project includes feedback
                    options for people to ask questions and make suggestions. After all, we will not
                    be able to invite everyone to work with us, but we could try to include everyone
                    who is affected by our representations. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Explaining Ourselves</head>
                <p>We can also include context in downloadable data. For example, the CSV files that
                    constitute the core of the historic prison data project, described above, have
                    the transcriptions of the admission books. No metadata is included in the
                    download, and no context. Instead of simple files containing structured
                    transcriptions, we could use data packets to bundle contextualizing information
                    together with the transcriptions.<note>See, for example, Walsh, Paul, and Rufus
                        Pollock. <title rend="quotes">Data Package</title>. <title rend="italic"
                            >Frictionless Data</title>. Accessed May 29, 2018. <ref
                            target="https://frictionlessdata.io/specs/data-package/"
                            >https://frictionlessdata.io/specs/data-package/</ref>. For a discussion
                        on using data packets in cultural institutions, Averkamp, Shawn. <title
                            rend="quotes">Data Packaging Guide</title>, May 14, 2018. <ref
                            target="https://github.com/saverkamp/beyond-open-data"
                            >https://github.com/saverkamp/beyond-open-data</ref>.</note> As we
                    release collections as data we could standardize the inclusion of context; as we
                    promote data from cultural heritage institutions, we could normalize the process
                    of incorporating the context supplied within data packages. </p>
                <p>Part of the context we could add would be explanations about decisions that we
                    make while creating data. A danger of institutionally-generated collections as
                    data is the perception of objectivity. Devon Mordell, writing about this danger,
                    proposes we frame collections data work in cultural heritage institutions within
                    a new paradigm, a collections-as-data paradigm, that considers both the
                    conceptual and practical concerns related to the use of data in archives <ptr
                        target="#mordell2019"/>. The benefits of framing a paradigm around
                    collections-as-data, Mordell argues, is to <quote rend="inline">ensure that a
                        social justice critique is maintained within</quote> the emerging work
                    related to collections as data <ptr target="#mordell2019" loc="147"/>. In using
                    archival material as data, there is a risk that the archival holdings and
                    descriptions of the holdings will look objective and natural, and the work of
                    archivists and others to show how archival collections are never neutral and
                    natural will be obscured. Mordell argues that <quote rend="inline">active
                        participation and critical discourse</quote> around the tools and practices
                    is needed to ensure that new technologies reinscribe a false since neutrality
                        <ptr target="#mordell2019" loc="156"/>. Following Mordell, we can include
                    context that encourages critical discourse around our data.</p>
                <p>These four directions are presented as a means to begin conversations about
                    practical implementation toward the goal of ensuring that the work we do is
                    better than data brokering. There is still much to learn, and the implementation
                    of any of these proposed solutions will certainly open new possibilities, of
                    both success and failure. Many of the issues we hope to address have taken
                    decades, and sometimes centuries, to create. There will be no quick solution.
                </p>
            </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>The examination of data brokers is meant to offer a warning to those of us
                    working in cultural heritage institutions. However, it is not just one example
                    taken at random. Rather it is a generative lens to view our work because we are
                    always already existing as data in the world of data brokers. The power that
                    data brokers have over us to collect, analyze, describe, and sell our data
                    should bring into sharp focus the power that we have over those with whose data
                    we work.</p>
                <p>Thinking about collections as data framework creates an ideal moment for a
                    reflection on the creation and use of data in cultural institutions and digital
                    humanities. This reconceptionalization enables unprecedented access and
                    interaction with collection material in libraries, archives, and museums,
                        i<quote rend="inline">ncluding but not limited to text mining, data
                        visualization, mapping, image analysis, audio analysis, and network
                        analysis</quote>
                    <ptr target="#aac2018b"/>.</p>
                <p>This is also a moment to consider how we do not want to interact with data.
                    Having a ready example against which to judge our behavior is useful, and data
                    brokers provide a perfect use case. Companies that buy, combine, and resell
                    personal data to the detriment of individuals and groups can be the example we
                    need. Defining ourselves in contrast to data brokers also grants us the
                    opportunity to reflect on the historically problematic aspects of cultural
                    institutions’ descriptive practices. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="adler2017" label="Adler 2017">Adler, Melissa. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Classification Along the Color Line: Excavating Racism in the
                        Stacks</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Critical Library and
                        Information Studies</title> 1, no. 1 (January 29, 2017). <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.24242/jclis.v1i1.17"
                        >https://doi.org/10.24242/jclis.v1i1.17</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="aac2018a" label="AAC 2018a">Always Already Computational - Collections
                    as Data. 2018.<title rend="quotes"> Always Already Computational</title>.
                    Accessed June 5, 2018. <ref target="https://collectionsasdata.github.io/"
                        >https://collectionsasdata.github.io/</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="aac2018b" label="AAC 2018b">Always Already Computational - Collections
                    as Data. 2018. <title rend="quotes">The Santa Barbara Statement on Collections
                        as Data Version 2</title>. Accessed June 5, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://collectionsasdata.github.io/statement/"
                        >https://collectionsasdata.github.io/statement/</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="aps-git" label="APSa n.d.">American Philosophical Society. n.d. <title
                        rend="quotes">Historic Prison Data</title>. <ref
                        target="https://github.com/AmericanPhilosophicalSociety/Historic-Prison-Data"
                        >https://github.com/AmericanPhilosophicalSociety/Historic-Prison-Data</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="aps-data" label="APSb n.d.">American Philosophical Society. n.d.
                        <title rend="quotes">Open Data</title>. Accessed June 5, 2018. <ref
                        target="http://diglib.amphilsoc.org/data"
                        >http://diglib.amphilsoc.org/data</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="aps-apps" label="APSc n.d.">American Philosophical Society. n.d.
                        <title rend="quotes">Eastern Apps: Exploring Historic Prison Data</title>.
                    Accessed June 5, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://diglib.amphilsoc.org/labs/eastern-apps/"
                        >https://diglib.amphilsoc.org/labs/eastern-apps/</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="carnegie" label="Carnegie n.d.">Carnegie Museum of Art. n.d. <title
                        rend="quotes">Carnegie Museum of Art’s Collection Dataset</title>. Accessed
                    June 5, 2018. <ref target="https://github.com/cmoa/collection"
                        >https://github.com/cmoa/collection</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="caswell2016" label="Caswell and Cifor 2016">Caswell, Michelle and
                    Marika Cifor. 2016. <title rend="quotes">From Human Rights to Feminist Ethics:
                        Radical Empathy in the Archives</title>, <title rend="italic">Archival
                        Science</title> 81 (Spring 2016): 23-43. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cbs2018" label="CBS 2018">CBS News. 2018. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Data Brokers: Selling Your Personal Information</title>. Accessed June 5,
                    2018. <ref
                        target="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/the-data-brokers-selling-your-personal-information/"
                        >https://www.cbsnews.com/news/the-data-brokers-selling-your-personal-information/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="confessore2018" label="Confessore and Rosenberg 2018">Confessore,
                    Nicholas, and Matthew Rosenberg. 2018. <title rend="quotes">Cambridge Analytica
                        to File for Bankruptcy After Misuse of Facebook Data</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">The New York Times</title>, May 3, 2018, sec. U.S. <ref
                        target="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/05/02/us/politics/cambridge-analytica-shut-down.html"
                        >https://www.nytimes.com/2018/05/02/us/politics/cambridge-analytica-shut-down.html</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="davis1946" label="Davis 1946">Davis, Edwin. Letter to Guy Lyle. 12
                    January 1946. LSU Department of Archives and Manuscripts records, A1506,
                    University Archives, LSU Libraries Special Collections, Baton Rouge, La.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ftc2014" label="Federal Trade Commission 2014">Federal Trade
                    Commission. 2014. <title rend="quotes">FTC Report Examines Data Brokers</title>.
                    Accessed June 5, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://www.consumer.ftc.gov/blog/2014/05/ftc-report-examines-data-brokers"
                        >https://www.consumer.ftc.gov/blog/2014/05/ftc-report-examines-data-brokers</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="feldberg1980" label="Feldberg 1980">Feldberg, Michael. 1980. <title
                        rend="italic">The Turbulent Era: Riot &amp; Disorder in Jacksonian
                        America</title>. New York: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="feldman2018" label="Feldman 2018">Feldman, Noah. 2018. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Future of Policing Is Being Hashed Out in Secret</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Bloomberg</title>, February 28, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2018-02-28/artificial-intelligence-in-policing-advice-for-new-orleans-and-palantir"
                        >https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2018-02-28/artificial-intelligence-in-policing-advice-for-new-orleans-and-palantir</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hartocollis2019" label="Hartocollis 2019">Hartocollis, Anemona. <title
                        rend="quotes">Taking On Harvard Over Rights to Slave Photos</title>. New
                    York Times, 21 Mar. 2019, p. A1(L). Gale In Context: Biography, <ref
                        target="https://link.gale.com/apps/doc/A579490887/BIC?u=lln_alsu&amp;sid=BIC&amp;xid=c62f7942"
                        >https://link.gale.com/apps/doc/A579490887/BIC?u=lln_alsu&amp;sid=BIC&amp;xid=c62f7942</ref>.
                    Accessed 5 Dec. 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hhs2015" label="HHS 2015">Health and Human Services. 2015. <title
                        rend="quotes">Health Information Privacy</title>. Accessed June 5, 2018.
                        <ref target="https://www.hhs.gov/hipaa/index.html"
                        >https://www.hhs.gov/hipaa/index.html</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ifill2007" label="Ifill 2007">Ifill, Sherrilyn A. 2007. <title
                        rend="italic">On the Courthouse Lawn: Confronting the Legacy of Lynching in
                        the Twenty-First Century</title>. Boston: Beacon Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="imls2016" label="IMLS 2016">Institute of Museum and Library Services.
                    2016. <title rend="quotes">LG-73-16-0096-16</title>. Accessed June 6, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://www.imls.gov/grants/awarded/lg-73-16-0096-16"
                        >https://www.imls.gov/grants/awarded/lg-73-16-0096-16</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="getty" label="Getty Trust n.d.">J. Paul Getty Trust. n.d. <title
                        rend="quotes">Open Content</title>. Accessed June 5, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://www.getty.edu/about/whatwedo/opencontent.html"
                        >https://www.getty.edu/about/whatwedo/opencontent.html</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="leetaru2018" label="Leetaru 2018">Leetaru, Kalev. 2018. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Data Brokers So Powerful Even Facebook Bought Their Data -
                        But They Got Me Wildly Wrong</title>. <title rend="italic">Forbes</title>,
                    April 5, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://www.forbes.com/sites/kalevleetaru/2018/04/05/the-data-brokers-so-powerful-even-facebook-bought-their-data-but-they-got-me-wildly-wrong/#92a30923107a"
                        >https://www.forbes.com/sites/kalevleetaru/2018/04/05/the-data-brokers-so-powerful-even-facebook-bought-their-data-but-they-got-me-wildly-wrong/#92a30923107a</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="levin2018" label="Levin 2018">Levin, Sam. 2018. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Black Activist Jailed for His Facebook Posts Speaks out about Secret FBI
                        Surveillance</title>. <title rend="italic">The Guardian</title>, May 11,
                    2018, sec. World news. <ref
                        target="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/may/11/rakem-balogun-interview-black-identity-extremists-fbi-surveillance"
                        >http://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/may/11/rakem-balogun-interview-black-identity-extremists-fbi-surveillance</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="loc2016" label="Library of Congress 2016">Library of Congress. 2016.
                        <title rend="quotes">Collections as Data 2016</title>. Accessed June 5,
                    2018. <ref target="http://digitalpreservation.gov/meetings/dcs16.html"
                        >http://digitalpreservation.gov/meetings/dcs16.html</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="loc2017" label="Library of Congress 2017">Library of Congress. 2017.
                        <title rend="quotes">Collections as Data IMPACT 2017</title>. Accessed June
                    5, 2018. <ref
                        target="http://digitalpreservation.gov/meetings/asdata/impact.html"
                        >http://digitalpreservation.gov/meetings/asdata/impact.html</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="loc2019" label="Library of Congress 2019">Library of Congress. 2019.
                        <title rend="quotes">Library Receives $1M Mellon Grant to Experiment with
                        Digital Collections as Big Data</title>. Accessed 7 Nov. 2019. <ref
                        target="https://www.loc.gov/item/prn-19-098/library-receives-1m-mellon-grant-to-experiment-with-digital-collections-as-big-data/2019-10-04/"
                        >https://www.loc.gov/item/prn-19-098/library-receives-1m-mellon-grant-to-experiment-with-digital-collections-as-big-data/2019-10-04/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lill" label="Lill n.d.">Lill, Jonathan. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Museum of Modern Art Exhibition Index</title>. Accessed June 5, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://collectionsasdata.github.io/facet12/"
                        >https://collectionsasdata.github.io/facet12/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lillehaugen" label="Lillehaugen and Zarafonetis n.d.">Lillehaugen,
                    Brook and Michael Zarafonetis. <title rend="quotes">Ticha: A Digital Text
                        Explorer for Colonial Zapotec</title>. Accessed June 5, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://collectionsasdata.github.io/facet12/"
                        >https://collectionsasdata.github.io/facet12/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liedlibrary" label="Lied Library">Lied Library. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Collections as Data National Forum 2</title>. Filmed May 7-8 at the
                    University of Nevada Las Vegas. Accessed June 5, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ENaPV2XmO9I"
                        >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ENaPV2XmO9I</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="koster2018" label="Koster 2018">Koster, Lukas and Saskia
                    Woutersen-Windhouwer. <title rend="quotes">FAIR Principles for Library, Archive
                        and Museum Collections: A Proposal for Standards for Reusable
                        Collections</title>. <title rend="italic">The Code4Lib Journal</title>, May
                    7, 2018. <ref target="http://journal.code4lib.org/articles/13427"
                        >http://journal.code4lib.org/articles/13427</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="miller2017" label="Miller 2017">Miller, Caitlyn Renee. 2017. <title
                        rend="quotes">I Bought a Report on Everything That’s Known About Me
                        Online</title>. <title rend="italic">The Atlantic</title>, June 6, 2017.
                        <ref
                        target="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2017/06/online-data-brokers/529281"
                        >https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2017/06/online-data-brokers/529281</ref>/. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mordell2019" label="Mordell 2019">Mordell, Devon. 2019. <title
                        rend="quotes">Critical Questions for Archives as (Big) Data</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Archivaria</title>, vol. 87, no. 0, May 2019, pp.
                    140–61.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nls2019" label="National Library of Scotland 2019">National Library of
                    Scotland. 2019. <title rend="quotes">Launch of Data Foundry Website</title>.
                        <ref target="https://www.nls.uk/news/archive/2019/09/data-foundry"
                        >https://www.nls.uk/news/archive/2019/09/data-foundry</ref>. Accessed 7 Nov.
                    2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="naylor2016" label="Naylor 2016">Naylor, Brian. 2016. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Data Brokers: Selling Your Personal Information</title>.
                    CBS News, July 11, 2016. <ref
                        target="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/the-data-brokers-selling-your-personal-information/"
                        >https://www.cbsnews.com/news/the-data-brokers-selling-your-personal-information/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="newbury" label="Newbury and Fowler n.d.">Newbury, David, and Daniel
                    Fowler. n.d. <title rend="quotes">Carnegie Museum of Art Collection
                    Data</title>. Accessed June 5, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://collectionsasdata.github.io/facet2/"
                        >https://collectionsasdata.github.io/facet2/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="noble2018" label="Noble 2018">Noble, Safiya Umoja. 2018. <title
                        rend="italic">Algorithms of Oppression: How Search Engines Reinforce
                        Racism</title>. New York: New York University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="oki" label="Open Knowledge International n.d.">Open Knowledge
                    International. n.d. <title rend="quotes">The Open Definition - Open Definition -
                        Defining Open in Open Data, Open Content and Open Knowledge</title>.
                    Accessed June 5, 2018. <ref target="https://opendefinition.org/"
                        >https://opendefinition.org/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="padilla2017" label="Padilla 2017">Padilla, Thomas. 2017. <title
                        rend="quotes">On a Collections as Data Imperative</title>. UC Santa Barbara.
                    Retrieved from <ref target="https://escholarship.org/uc/item/9881c8sv"
                        >https://escholarship.org/uc/item/9881c8sv</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pilgrim2017" label="Pilgrim 2017">Pilgrim, David. 2017. <title
                        rend="italic">Watermelons, Nooses, and Straight Razors: Stories from the Jim
                        Crow Museum</title>. Oakland, CA: PM Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schuessler2019" label="Schuessler 2019">Schuessler, Jennifer. <title
                        rend="quotes">Portraits Of Slaves Require Moral Lens</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">New York Times</title>, 23 Mar. 2019, p. C1(L). Gale In
                    Context: Biography, <ref
                        target="https://link.gale.com/apps/doc/A579778374/BIC?u=lln_alsu&amp;sid=BIC&amp;xid=613dc968"
                        >https://link.gale.com/apps/doc/A579778374/BIC?u=lln_alsu&amp;sid=BIC&amp;xid=613dc968</ref>.
                    Accessed 5 Dec. 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sweet1945" label="Sweet 1945">Sweet, Forest. Letter to Edwin Davis. 7
                    January 1945. LSU Department of Archives and Manuscripts Records, #A1506,
                    University Archives, LSU Libraries Special Collections, Baton Rouge, La.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="upenn" label="University of Pennsylvania n.d.">University of
                    Pennsylvania. n.d. <title rend="quotes">OPenn: Read Me</title>. Accessed June 5,
                    2018. <ref target="http://openn.library.upenn.edu/ReadMe.html"
                        >http://openn.library.upenn.edu/ReadMe.html</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="waldman2018" label="Waldman et al. 2018">Waldman, Peter, Lizette
                    Chapman, and Jordan Robertson. 2018. <title rend="quotes">Palantir Knows
                        Everything About You</title>. <title rend="italic">Bloomberg</title>, April
                    19, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://www.bloomberg.com/features/2018-palantir-peter-thiel/"
                        >https://www.bloomberg.com/features/2018-palantir-peter-thiel/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weber2017" label="Weber 2017">Weber, Chela Scott. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Research and Learning Agenda for Archives, Special, and Distinctive
                        Collections and Research Libraries</title>. OCLC Research, 2017. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.25333/c3c34f"
                        >https://doi.org/10.25333/c3c34f</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="winston2018" label="Winston 2018">Winston, Ali. 2018. <title
                        rend="quotes">A Pioneer in Predictive Policing Is Starting a Troubling New
                        Project</title>. <title rend="italic">The Verge</title>, April 26, 2018.
                        <ref
                        target="https://www.theverge.com/2018/4/26/17285058/predictive-policing-predpol-pentagon-ai-racial-bias"
                        >https://www.theverge.com/2018/4/26/17285058/predictive-policing-predpol-pentagon-ai-racial-bias</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zarafonetis" label="Zarafonetis and Horowitz n.d.">Zarafonetis,
                    Michael and Sarah M. Horowitz. <title rend="quotes">Beyond Penn’s
                    Treaty</title>. Accessed May 5, 2018. <ref
                        target="https://collectionsasdata.github.io/facet11/"
                        >https://collectionsasdata.github.io/facet11/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ziegler" label="Ziegler n.d.">Ziegler, Scott. <title rend="quotes"
                        >American Philosophical Society Open Data Projects</title>. Accessed June 5,
                    2018. <ref target="https://collectionsasdata.github.io/facet4/"
                        >https://collectionsasdata.github.io/facet4/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ziegler2019" label="Ziegler and Marti 2019">Ziegler, S. L. and Steve
                    Marti. 2019. <title rend="quotes">A Hidden Gem Become a Fertile Mining Ground:
                        Historic Prison Admission Books and Data-Driven Digital Projects</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">The Pennsylvania Magazine of History and
                        Biography</title>. Vol. 143: 3. Pp. 363-373.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ziegler2016" label="Ziegler and Ziogas 2016">Ziegler, Scott and
                    Michelle Ziogas. 2016. <title rend="quotes">Eastern State Penitentiary Admission
                        Book B</title>, - . 21. Philadelphia, PA: McNeil Center for Early American
                    Studies [distributor], 2016. <ref target="https://repository.upenn.edu"
                        >https://repository.upenn.edu</ref>
                </bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
