<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Naming Slavery in a Digital Public History Project in <name>Mali</name> 
               in the Context of Increased Violence Against Those Who Refuse to Be Called <q>Slaves</q></title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Marie <dhq:family>Rodet</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1129-3203</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>SOAS, University of London</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>mr28@soas.ac.uk</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>A reader in the History of Africa at SOAS, <name>University of London</name>, <name>Marie Rodet</name> has 
                     extensively researched, taught, and published on the history of slavery in <name>Africa</name>. She is passionate 
                     about digital public history: she is the director of the documentary film <title rend="italic">The Diambourou: 
                     Slavery and Emancipation in <name>Kayes</name> – <name>Mali</name></title> (2014) and the web documentary 
                     <title rend="italic"><name>Bouillagui</name>: A Free Village</title> (2020), as well as the scriptwriter of the 
                     animation film <title rend="italic">All Equal!</title>(2024). She has also worked on a mobile game against slavery 
                     called <title rend="italic">USAWA</title> (JIWE studios 2023) based on her research in <name>Western Mali</name>, 
                     and she is currently working on a new game called <title rend="italic">Umoja</title> with UNESCO Kenya on the 
                     history of resistance to slavery along the Swahili coast.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Mamadou Séne <dhq:family>Cissé</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Association Donkosira, Mali</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>pamodicisse@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p><name>Mamadou</name> is general-secretary of Donkosira, a not-for-profit organisation promoting local knowledge in 
                     <name>West Africa</name>. He is working with underrepresented rural communities in <name>West Africa</name>, 
                     helping to highlight and share their traditions, languages, art, and cultural history through the use of 
                     information technology and digital communication, one of the significant challenges of the millennium. He was Co-I 
                     on the UKRI GCRF supported projects <title rend="quotes">Slavery and Forced Migration in Western Mali</title> 
                     (2020-2024) and <title rend="quotes">Equitable Climate Resilience in West Africa</title> (2019-2023), both led by 
                     <name>Marie Rodet</name>.
                  </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000773</idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date><!--include @when with ISO date and also content in the form 23 February 2024--></date>
            <dhq:articleType>case study</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <term corresp="#ethics"/>
               <term corresp="#history"/>
               <term corresp="#race"/>
               <term corresp="#moving_images"/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>descent-based slavery</item>
                  <item>digital public history</item>
                  <item>Mali</item>
                  <item>ethics of care</item>
                  <item>web documentary</item>
                  <item>participatory visual research</item>
                  <item>digital gap</item>
                  <item>co-production</item>
                  <item>shared authority</item>
                  <item>equitable partnership</item>
                  <item>transmedia</item>
                  <item>remediation</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000773/000773.xml">GitHub</ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
           <p>Digital public history has emerged as a powerful tool for addressing difficult pasts with concerned communities in an 
              ethical way. This paper focuses on the ethical issues at stake in co-producing digital historical knowledge about 
              resistance to slavery in a web documentary that involved identifying and naming marginalised populations in 
              <name>Mali</name>, increasingly at risk of violence. The web documentary aims to bridge the gap between endogenous 
              historical resistance to enslaved people and modern anti-slavery activism, while also addressing issues of funding, 
              authority tensions, and asymmetrical relations, in which the digital gap presented specific challenges. In the process, 
              we report on a case of dialogue among researchers, practitioners, and village participants, and we expose the ethical 
              implications of digital research and citizen intervention related to past and present slavery in 
              <name>Africa</name>.
           </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
           <p>How do you create a digital public history project on slavery with concerned communities in <name>Mali</name> who are 
              increasingly at risk of violence because of the very topic of slavery?
           </p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head/>
            <p>Memories of internal slavery and resistance to slavery in <name>Mali</name> tend to disappear because of continuous 
               public shaming of the people considered <quote rend="inline">descendants of enslaved populations</quote> and the 
               disappearance over time of the few indirect witnesses still able to tell the story of their enslaved grandparents 
               <ptr target="#rodet2010"/>. Yet understanding this history is crucial in a context where tensions surrounding 
               descent-based slavery have arisen in <name>Mali</name> since 2018.
            </p>
            <p>Slavery existed in the <name>Sahel</name> before the Transatlantic slave trade and endured beyond its abolitions. 
               In the 19th century, <name>Kayes</name> in western <name>Mali</name> was a major transit zone of slave caravans and 
               experienced an expansion of internal slavery through war and conflict. French authorities abolished the internal slave 
               trade in their West African colonies in 1905 as they searched to recruit liberated enslaved people for forced labour. 
               They soon turned a blind eye on the continuation of what they called <quote rend="inline">domestic slavery</quote>, 
               pretending it had simply transformed into salary contract work thanks to the colonial legislation 
               <ptr target="#camara_etal2021a"/>. Descendant of those enslaved people continued to inherit <quote rend="inline">slave 
               status</quote> and their labour remained controlled by the local historical ruling class with the complicity of the 
               colonial and postcolonial state, a system that allowed historical hierarchies to persist to present day in the form 
               of what is henceforth called <q>descent-based slavery</q>.
            </p>
            <p>Despite the patchy implementation of the 1905 abolition decree on the ground, some formerly enslaved people 
               managed to take their destinies into their own hands, escaping a violent institution to live freely in independent 
               communities such as <name>Bouillagui</name> in western <name>Mali</name>. But this history has remained largely 
               silenced as the colonial and local ideologies prevailing at the time of abolition endured in the postcolonial period 
               which has prevented the stigma of slavery from disappearing. On one hand, although the region experienced successive 
               waves of emancipation in the colonial and postcolonial eras, descent-based slavery continued under disguised forms of 
               kinship, marriage, and adoption/fosterage <ptr target="#rodet2013"/>. On the other hand, the historical ruling class 
               remained largely in power despite abolition and independence and thus continued to exercise control over defining 
               what a society of <q>freemen</q> had to be <ptr target="#rodet2010"/> <ptr target="#rodet2013"/>. In such a context, 
               confining the history of slavery to a <q>public secret</q> well into the postcolonial era was most likely a necessary 
               step in conveying an authoritative national identity. Today, poverty and discrimination continue to exclude Malians 
               with ascribed <q>slave status</q> from social mobility and to restrict their agency about how their history is being 
               told in the public space. Conversely, the elite continues to benefit from their ostracization and exploitation by 
               ruling the moral economy of honour and shame <ptr target="#camara_etal2021b"/> <ptr target="#iliffe2005"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Postcolonial <name>Mali</name> has never criminalized descent-based slavery, despite the numerous advocacy campaigns 
               conducted by Malian human rights and anti-slavery organizations. <name>Mali</name> has certainly signed up to the 
               major international conventions banning slavery (including the UN International Declaration on Human Rights) and 
               passed a law criminalizing international trafficking in 2012. More recently, slavery has been made a criminal offense 
               in the criminal code in <name>Mali</name>, but its definition is still based on the idea of property and thus cannot 
               capture the complexities of descent-based slavery as a web of socio-economic subjugation and control that does not 
               necessarily manifest in overt physical violence. Perpetrators of descent-based slavery can thus still only be 
               prosecuted if physical violence has occurred. The continued amnesia on the history of slavery and fraught political 
               environment in today's <name>Mali</name> contribute to the state's inability or unwillingness to understand 
               descent-based slavery as a contemporary manifestation of slavery <ptr target="#camara_etal2021b"/>.
            </p>
            <p>New technologies have the potential to complement fading oral history transmission, offering new ways to engage, 
               share, and understand collective heritage histories for the longer term. In 2018, we began working on the digital 
               public history research project <title rend="quotes">Visualising Liberté</title>, which was intended to explore the 
               history of the village of <name>Bouillagui</name> in western <name>Mali</name>. <name>Bouillagui</name> has a very 
               specific history: its founders liberated themselves from slavery at the beginning of the twentieth century. Despite 
               the general taboo still surrounding slavery in <name>West Africa</name>, the people of B<name>ouillagui</name> are 
               very proud of their history, and they were particularly keen to share it within the framework of our digital history 
               project recounting the specific histories of the struggle for freedom and resistance and rebellion against slavery.
            </p>
            <p><title rend="quotes">Visualising Liberté</title> was conceived as a transmedia research project: the villagers were 
               given mobile phones and trained to make short video reportages about their village history, which would become the 
               narrative basis for a graphic novel, an animation film, and a web documentary. The web documentary itself was also 
               conceived as a transmedia digital object, in which associated fragments of this history of resistance to slavery were 
               collected over the previous decade of research conducted by <name>Marie Rodet</name> in multiple media (audio, 
               textual documents, video, photographs, etc.) with the new videos made by the villagers themselves. All this was pieced 
               together into a single new digital media platform and made accessible to various audiences, in the form of the 2020 
               web documentary titled <title rend="italic">Bouillagui: A Free Village</title> 
               (<ref target="https://bouillagui.soas.ac.uk/">https://bouillagui.soas.ac.uk/</ref>) <ptr target="#rodet_etal2021b"/>.
            </p>
            <p>In <name>Mali</name>, new technologies are often blamed for the disappearance of the intergenerational oral modes of 
               knowledge transmission. Creating digital media on the history of resistance to slavery was therefore a crucial 
               opportunity to reflect further on how media may be used widely and efficiently to convey a difficult and still traumatic 
               past, which could be capitalised upon to fight against discrimination, exploitation, and modern slavery today.
            </p>
            <p>In the past fifteen years, historians and anthropologists of slavery and post-slavery have paid great attention to 
               retrieving the voices of (formerly) enslaved populations and to analysing oral and written slave narratives 
               <ptr target="#bellagamba_etal2013"/>. However, they have been slow to reflect on the potential ethical implications of 
               such endeavours, including the broad political dimensions of such research and the intricate power relationships enabled 
               by knowledge production about (formerly) enslaved populations <ptr target="#brannelly2018"/>.
            </p>
            <p><title rend="quotes">Visualising Liberté</title> was concerned with <quote rend="inline">listening to the history of 
               those who don't forget</quote> and making these voices — which had often been silenced in a form of continuous 
               epistemological violence — widely heard on their own terms <ptr target="#rodet2013"/>. As with many other public 
               projects dealing with contentious issues, the digital was to be used as a <quote rend="inline">moral 
               technology</quote> to influence and modify thoughts and behaviours regarding slavery in <name>Africa</name> 
               <ptr target="#cameron2008"/>, while also supporting knowledge production by a marginalised community that fits with 
               their own ways of knowing, through visual participatory research with mobile phones 
               <ptr target="#macentee_etal2016"/>. Here, the participatory visual research was used to explore new ways of 
               publicising a neglected history of resistance to slavery, with a commitment to both social justice and an 
               <quote rend="inline">ethics of care</quote> <ptr target="#brannelly2018"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Several events during the project reminded us of the unpredictability of the research process and of several ethical 
               implications. Even as we tried to mitigate ethical issues from the conception of the research project to its end, 
               the COVID-19 pandemic still strongly impacted the co-production dynamic. More importantly, during the project and 
               until today, the violence against people who are ascribed locally with the status of <quote rend="inline">descendants 
               of slaves</quote> and who refuse to be called <quote rend="inline">slaves</quote> increased in their home communities. 
               In 2018, the anti-slavery group Gambana or Ganbanaxuun (which means <quote rend="inline">All Equal</quote> in the 
               Soninke language) was formed by Soninke migrants in <name>Paris</name> to fight systematic discrimination and violence 
               mainly among their ethnic group, which is present in several West African countries, including <name>Mali</name>. 
               Activists denounce the anachronistic and demeaning use of the word <term xml:lang="snk">komo</term> and the worst 
               forms of exploitation this use results in <ptr target="#camara_etal2021a"/><note><term xml:lang="snk">Kome</term> 
               in its plural form means <q>slave</q> in the Soninke language, the equivalent of 
               <term xml:lang="bm">Jon</term></note>. Their protest against descent-based slavery in their community generated a 
               violent backlash: since 2018, more than 3,000 Malians with ascribed <q>slave status</q> have fled slavery-related 
               violence in western <name>Mali</name> <ptr target="#cisse_etal2024"/>. Activists and members of the movement have 
               also been attacked and threatened in several localities of western <name>Mali</name> and beyond, yet the state and 
               global community have remained largely silent <ptr target="#rodet_etal2021a"/>.
            </p>
            <p>This situation changed the ethical stakes of <title rend="quotes">Visualising Liberté</title> and its potential 
               impact: from retrieving the history of people who were proud of having successfully liberated themselves from 
               slavery to rethinking what terms to use and safeguarding measures to add to ensure that exposing people's history 
               would not endanger them. The core question thus became how to conduct a digital public history project that supports 
               social justice, by bridging the gap between endogenous historical resistance to slavery and modern anti-slavery 
               activism, without doing harm to the persons concerned.
            </p>
            <p>In this article, we will focus on the ethical issues at stake in co-producing digital historical knowledge about 
               resistance to slavery in a web documentary that involved identifying and naming marginalised populations in 
               <name>Mali</name>. The other two media produced by <title rend="quotes">Visualising Liberté</title> — the graphic 
               novel and the animation film — have not been officially released yet and are closer to fiction and less documentary 
               in their nature, using fictional names. They thus do not involve the same ethical dimensions, although those related 
               to co-production, shared authority, and equitable partnership could be approached in similar ways. The ethical and 
               safeguarding issues raised by this project will not be resolved exhaustively in the body of this article, especially 
               since unexpected issues may continue to arise due to the fast-changing political and digital landscapes worldwide. 
               Nonetheless, we would like to confront here most of those that have crossed our research paths since the start of our 
               collaboration with the <name>Bouillagui</name> villagers.
            </p>
            <p>Here, we are attempting to uncover some of the blind spots in postcolonial digital historical practices and writings. 
               As the initiator of <title rend="quotes">Visualising Liberté</title>, we built individual careers in recent years 
               based on research material collected in <name>West Africa</name> in collaboration with marginalised populations and 
               with the support of the Malian organisation Donkosira (lit. <q>the road to knowledge</q>, in the Bamanan language), 
               an association working on the dissemination of local community knowledge in <name>West Africa</name> whose founding 
               members are <name>Mamadou Séne Cissé</name>, <name>Moussa Kalapo</name>, and <name>Mariam Coulibaly</name>.
            </p>
            <p>From a decolonial perspective, there is a pressing need to pose rather uncomfortable self-reflecting questions about 
               our own professional practices as historians of <name>Africa</name> and cultural practitioners conducting digital 
               public history together. This is a crucial first step towards confronting the potential (negative) impact of our 
               digital interventions. Indeed, we must question whether a project about decolonising historical knowledge production 
               — through digital media, based on equitable partnership and co-production, and <q>decreed</q> from the outside — is 
               not ultimately doomed to failure. And in the case of research on slavery, is it not at risk of exposing and even doing 
               harm to the marginalised populations involved? To what extent have we succeeded in making the digital and 
               interpretative <q>shared authority</q> and the historical knowledge co-authorship recognised in this project 
               <ptr target="#frisch1990"/>? Have we contributed to the creation of a <quote rend="inline">safe space for unsafe 
               ideas</quote> <ptr target="#gurian1995"/> <ptr target="#anderson2018"/>? How have we been able as a team to work 
               around equitable digital shared authority against a moving political landscape in both <name>Europe</name> and 
               <name>Mali</name>, while the process also entailed naming populations at potential risk? What is the effect of our 
               intervention of digital transmediation or remediation on the voices publicised? How can we position ourselves as 
               researchers and practitioners in such contexts where radical asymmetries in terms of safety increase? How can we 
               ensure that, despite these radical asymmetries, the project works for everyone and guarantees individual safety?
            </p>
            <p>Few researchers and practitioners dare to openly confront these issues of <q>North–South divide</q> and their ethical 
               implications.<note>We reckon that the phrase <q>North-South divide</q>, despite being well established in public 
               discourse and the scholarly literature, is fraught for its simplification and possible misrepresentation of the 
               complex <q>realities</q> of global socio-economic and political power relations. For a more thorough discussion, see 
               <ptr target="#eckl_etal2007"/>.</note> Despite all its promises, the digital poses sepcific challenges in terms of 
               funding, authority tensions, and asymmetrical relations. Without claiming to propose a protocol, we reflect on a case 
               of dialogue among researchers, practitioners, and villagers, and we expose digital research and citizen intervention 
               mechanisms that attributed singular places to each.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>1. <title rend="quotes">Visualing Liberté</title>: The Ethics of Naming Slavery in a Transmedia Collaborative Project 
             in the Face of Public Silence</head>
            <p>As a public history project, <title rend="quotes">Visualising Liberté</title> involved more than using new media — the 
               web documentary — as a dissemination strategy. Since first coined in the <name>United States</name> some fifty years 
               ago, public history works to make history-making largely accessible to large audiences while increasingly using various 
               forms of collaborative, participatory research and communication processes, including digital ones, thereby fostering a 
               more <quote rend="inline">democratic ethos</quote> in historical practices <ptr target="#frisch1990"/> 
               <ptr target="#rosenzweig1998"/> <ptr target="#noiret2022"/> <ptr target="#basaraba_etal2023"/>. This latter aspect of 
               collaborative, participatory history-making was at the heart of <title rend="quotes">Visualising Liberté</title>: using 
               the digital as a powerful tool to accelerate the potential impact of little-known histories of African resistance to 
               slavery.
            </p>
            <p><title rend="quotes">Visualising Liberté</title> emerged after a decade of research focused on the history of slavery 
               and emancipation in the <name>Kayes</name> region (1890–1940) in <name>Mali</name> and following a first experience of 
               public history through a film in which <name>Bouillagui</name>'s history was already partly featured 
               <ptr target="#rodet2020"/>. <name>Rodet</name>'s first interviews in <name>Bouillagui</name> date back to 2009. When we 
               began <title rend="quotes">Visualising Liberté</title> in 2018, the history of internal slavery had long been a taboo 
               subject in <name>West Africa</name>, but there was a demand from local communities in <name>Kayes</name> (western 
               <name>Mali</name>) to know and understand better this difficult past. Populations with ascribed <q>slave status</q> are 
               still discriminated against and stigmatised today, though the younger generations are less aware or understanding of 
               the underlying reasons. Many of the victims of descent-based slavery are also among the most vulnerable to economic 
               uncertainties and thus at continuous risk of being subjected to further exploitation, with new forms of servitude 
               strongly overlapping with the legacies of historical slavery <ptr target="#rodet2016"/> <ptr target="#rodet_etal2021a"/>. 
               The main goals of <title rend="quotes">Visualising Liberté</title> were to capitalise upon historical resistance to 
               slavery in <name>Kayes</name> to produce visual material for the young generations and to raise awareness about slavery 
               and its complex legacies in <name>Mali</name>, while also bridging the gap between historical resistance to slavery and 
               contemporary anti-slavery activism.
            </p>
            <p>With this project the intention was not only to retrieve local narratives and memories of resistance to slavery, but 
               also to bring these histories to a new dimension, in close collaboration with the community, including school children, 
               through the organisation of participatory research activities with strong social impact. It was both a response to 
               specific historiographical questions about African resistance to slavery and a research-action programme raising 
               awareness among younger generations and contributing to the fight against slavery's discriminatory legacies and modern 
               exploitation. As already discussed elsewhere, what is often misunderstood is that descent-based slavery sustains modern 
               slavery, in which descent-based slavery creates a terrain for a continuum of violence. It is the banalization of 
               descent-based slavery and its violence which trivializes next-door exploitation and allows overall social acceptance of 
               modern slavery <ptr target="#camara_etal2021b"/>.
            </p>
            <p>With an <q>ethics of care</q> valuing longer-term, ongoing relationships and the needs and wishes of the community 
               <ptr target="#brannelly2018"/>, this project was the second participatory research project led by <name>Rodet</name> in 
               partnership with <name>Donkosira</name> in which <name>Bouillagui</name> was involved. <name>Bouillagui</name> villagers 
               have since been involved in three other participatory research projects led by <name>Rodet</name> and 
               <name>Donkosira</name>.
            </p>
            <p><name>Bouillagui</name>'s history demonstrates that formerly enslaved populations were not just recipients of colonial 
               abolition of slavery, but rebelled against slavery on their own terms, in some cases violently, and obtained equality 
               through liberating themselves. Similar self-liberation movements would also be followed by other enslaved populations, 
               initiating a series of migratory waves to escape slavery during the twentieth century <ptr target="#rodet2015"/>. 
               This history needed to be named and taught, to help in the fight for human rights and against other forms of modern 
               exploitation. The timing of the project was particularly crucial, as <name>Mali</name> had been encountering at the time 
               deep political, economic, and social crises for almost a decade at the time, a situation that risked increasing further 
               discrimination and exploitation of already marginalised communities. What we did not predict was that the rapidly 
               deteriorating political situation in <name>Mali</name> would effectively prove our hypothesis of increased risk for 
               these populations immediately in the first year of our project (though independently of it). The history of slavery has 
               since been more widely discussed in <name>Mali</name> in the public space, following peaks of violence against these 
               populations since 2018 and for which the victims have regularly been blamed until recently. We will return to the 
               specific impacts of this latter aspect on our project in Section 4 below. For now, we will just add that other 
               research-action interventions within the framework of a follow-on research project (also led by us) on 
               <title rend="quotes">Slavery and Forced Migration in Western Mali</title> (2020–2023) have since contributed to 
               legitimising Malian grassroots anti-slavery activist organisations such as Gambana RMFP and to ending the usual 
               <quote rend="inline">naming and shaming</quote> of victims in the public debate <ptr target="#rodet_etal2021a"/>.
            </p>
            <p>In the <title rend="quotes">Visualising Liberté</title> project, we worked with five <name>Bouillagui</name> villagers: 
               <name>Hawa Cissoko</name>, <name>Salou Diarra</name>, <name>Diangou Diakité</name>, <name>Aboubakar Traoré</name> 
               (deceased in 2023), and <name>Wally Traoré</name>, who had all been designated by their home community as knowledgeable 
               in the history of their village and available for the project. We trained them in a workshop to collect local historical 
               knowledge via mobile phones (provided by the project) and to translate this into non-fiction visual narratives for the 
               broader public, with the help of the <name>Donkosira</name> team. Once the storyboard was conceived, it was shared with 
               the populations of <name>Bouillagui</name>, who gave feedback and further input for the production of the full graphic 
               novel and animation. The school children from <name>Bouillagui</name> also worked with <name>Donkosira</name> on drawings 
               about the history of their village and on collecting family histories. These activities were ultimately integrated into 
               the script of the graphic novel.
            </p>
            <p>By making visible in an accessible way little-known historical resistance against slavery in their own community, the 
               villagers thus co-produced educational material about human rights, citizenship, and social justice. They further 
               contributed to raising awareness among young generations about the importance of fighting against all forms of 
               discrimination and exploitation, including modern slavery, by making the history of resistance to slavery better known 
               and recognised.
            </p>
            <p>Overall, the project had as a key goal to develop a model of equitable partnership with <name>Bouillagui</name> 
               villagers. The project team worked continuously and closely with the villagers to ensure that they remained in control 
               of the narratives about their village and how experiences of slavery were recounted and transmediated. These strategies 
               of inclusion and participation ultimately aimed at reintegrating marginalised historical experiences into the global 
               production of legitimised knowledge, while using the digital media as powerful civic storytelling to spark public 
               dialogue for cognitive justice, democracy, and social struggle <ptr target="#piron_etal2016"/> 
               <ptr target="#hall-budd_etal2017"/> <ptr target="#borum-chatoo2020"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Let us now turn to unpacking the ideas of <q>equitable partnership</q> and <q>co-production</q> of digital data in this 
               project. While these are increasingly stated imperatives of funders to support projects, especially in the 
               <name>United Kingdom</name>, and to decolonise knowledge production on the Global South, surprisingly many historians of 
               <name>Africa</name> are still struggling to confront the asymmetrical relationships of the researcher with 
               <q>their</q> fieldwork (the possessive is extremely revealing) and to recognise the complex positioning of 
               <q>intermediaries</q> in this mechanism, who are often <q>erased</q> <ptr target="#bertho_etal2022"/>. In such contexts, 
               how do we involve villagers in a co-production using different media (graphic novel, animated film, web documentary)? 
               How can we invite them to be actors in their own right, guiding the preservation of local history that is part of a 
               personal, intimate, and political agenda but will also be remediated for dissemination in a digital community? That is, 
               what does it look like to create opportunities for villagers to become public historians through digital media beyond 
               their own community?
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>2. Research as an Ethical Process: The Impact of the COVID-19 Pandemic on the Conditions of Co-Production</head>
            <p>As <name>Jennifer Hart</name>, <name>Victoria Ogoegbunam Okoye</name>, and <name>Joseph Oduro-Frimpong</name> 
               point out, it is important to distinguish between co-writing (exchanging and writing together to produce a text), 
               collaboration (generating knowledge with the participation of diverse social actors and forms of knowledge), and 
               co-production (including research participants as active stakeholders throughout the research production process).
            </p>
            <p>To what extent does working with audio-video digital data — and in this specific case transmediated or remediated 
               historical narratives — change the asymmetric research relationship? Oral and public histories have continuously 
               disrupted the primacy of the written document and the intellectual and interpretive authority of trained academic 
               researchers, while encouraging broader participation and inclusivity in historical debates and producing new historical 
               perspectives from below <ptr target="#frisch1990"/> <ptr target="#dorn2013"/>. The digital permits experimentation with 
               alternative publishing platforms and processes that make research more broadly accessible and allow audio-visual sources 
               to be published directly online.
            </p>
            <p>Interpretive historical authority in the digital age dominated by online mass media often involves remediation. It makes 
               one medium, such as oral historical narratives and memories that have already been refashioned in audio-visual interviews 
               during the research process, <q>remediated</q> on a new online platform <ptr target="#bolter_etal1999"/> — in our case, 
               a web documentary. This immediately invites us to question whether such remediation changes the political meaning of the 
               shared narrative, given that it is no longer intended for an intimate political community agenda but for the wider world. 
               We will explore these questions more carefully in Section 3 of this article.
            </p>
            <p>Digital technology, especially the mobile phone, was used to help strengthen the power of the <name>Bouillagui</name> 
               villagers to narrate their history on their own terms without the immediate intervention of the researcher. Indeed, the 
               wider use of digital technology (phones) was intended to amplify the impact we already attempted to achieve with the 
               free-access version of the 2014 documentary film <title rend="italic">The Diambourou</title> <ptr target="#rodet2020"/>. 
               The first part of the process involved a familiarisation phase — with the project, the various team members, and the 
               mobile phones — so that the villagers could reappropriate the project fully. Participants also drew up their own lists 
               of historical knowledge to be preserved as a priority through their video recordings, such as the song that announced 
               the self-liberation plans and how their ancestors managed to survive the post-liberation famine they experienced. The 
               villagers' video reports and additional research conducted by <name>Marie Rodet</name> and <name>Mamadou Séne 
               Cissé</name> became the basis for the web documentary <title rend="italic">Bouillagui: A Free Village</title>.
            </p>
            <p><name>Bouillagui</name>'s history of resistance to slavery is a complex one to narrate, since people categorised as 
               <q>descendants of slaves</q> are still stigmatised today in <name>Mali</name>. Honour is still associated with the 
               historical ruling class — that is, the so-called nobility <ptr target="#rodet2010"/> <ptr target="#rossi2013"/>. 
               Associating the history of slavery with resistance in the web documentary was to offer a counter-discourse to the public 
               shaming of victims of slavery. The <q>unsafe ideas</q> here go beyond recounting the history of resistance against 
               slavery, which has been <q>whitewashed</q> by national, hegemonic discourses <ptr target="#rodet2010"/> 
               <ptr target="#lloyd_etal2015"/>. By co-producing a <q>safe space</q> for alternative historical voices, the web 
               documentary gives authority to <name>Bouillagui</name> villagers who had been denied the right for their history to be 
               integrated into public, official Malian history.
            </p>
            <p>Naming <name>Bouillagui</name> villagers in the webdocumentary credits as co-producers in a digital public history 
               project that recounts the history of their ancestors' self-liberation was to inevitably identify them publicly as 
               <q>descendants of self-liberated slaves</q>. However, the <name>Bouillagui</name> villagers did not seem to have an issue 
               with this, as what mattered to them and seemed to erase all other aspects was the <q>self-liberated</q> part of the 
               designation. It is their history, a history in which they have cultivated a fierce pride and that they wished to 
               publicise and name in order to defend full and effective equality and citizenship in the longer term in 
               <name>Mali</name>.
            </p>
            <p>The project aim was to further nurture collectively this discourse of pride around the notion of resistance to slavery 
               and the promotion of <term xml:lang="fr">Liberté</term> (the name given to several villages and neighbourhoods founded 
               by freed enslaved people in the region with the support of the colonial authorities), especially within the new 
               generations that did not always know the exact circumstances of a village's creation and its links with the history of 
               slavery. We thus carried out extensive educational work, collecting family histories with <name>Bouillagui</name>'s 
               primary school pupils. This work was integrated into both the web documentary and the script of the graphic novel.
            </p>
            <p>Thus, the digital technologies used in this project were not about showcasing a new fancy digital dissemination 
               strategy; instead, they operated as tools to deeply shape scholarly collaboration, ethical practices, citizen 
               intervention, and communication of research-action results from within the <name>Bouillagui</name> community to a wider 
               audience and academic community <ptr target="#wyatt2012"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Much has been written about the (unintended) consequences of e-research <ptr target="#wyatt2012"/> 
               <ptr target="#christensen_etal2020"/>, participatory visual research <ptr target="#cahill2007"/> 
               <ptr target="#walsh2016"/> <ptr target="#dickens_etal2016"/> <ptr target="#marzi2023"/>, and digital storytelling for 
               the people involved <ptr target="#edmonds_etal2016"/> <ptr target="#gubrium_etal2016"/>. However, the ethical impact of 
               using digital technologies in historical public research has been little studied, although ethical issues in digital 
               history, including concerning slavery, have been of increased scholarly concern in recent years (see for example 
               <ptr target="#lovejoy_etal2022"/>).
            </p>
            <p>Digital technology made available to everyone through a simple smartphone often gives the illusion of a catch-all 
               solution that will level up all communication and technological asymmetries while facilitating democratisation, 
               equitable participatory research, and digital co-production for social change, awareness-raising, and educational 
               purposes — especially through the production of what have been termed <q>cellphilms</q> 
               <ptr target="#macentee_etal2016"/>. However, the notion of <q>co-producing</q> itself remains fraught with a symbolic 
               power relationship that still gives pre-eminence to the researcher, who eventually remains in charge of the budget that 
               also conditions the research process <ptr target="#bertho_etal2022"/>. <quote rend="inline">Radical trust</quote> 
               seems possible only when the participants have at least the same technical savvy as (or even more than) the researchers, 
               which is rarely the case when working with marginalised populations from the Global South — a context in which visual 
               participatory research led by a researcher from the Global North may actually increase hierarchical power relationships 
               <ptr target="#gardner2010"/> <ptr target="#walsh2016"/>.
            </p>
            <p>With <title rend="quotes">Visualising Liberté</title> — despite a carefully thought-through digital data production 
               protocol with the villagers and the crucial building of mutual trust to facilitate the remediation of 
               <name>Bouillagui</name> historical narratives into a digital public history project — the asymmetry was never totally 
               neutralised, since the researcher retained ultimate authority regarding technological decisions that guaranteed, to the 
               funder, achieving production of the project deliverables. This symbolic power was also exacerbated during encounters when 
               we were unable to completely break the domination of the use of French, despite Soninke–French live translation. It 
               especially affected the integration of female villagers, most of whom are non-French speakers. Ultimately, the digital 
               gap was underestimated. It would be naive to think that the digital could have eliminated socio-geographical inequalities 
               once and for all. If a targeted audience is not already widely using a specific medium in their daily life, it can be 
               more difficult to reach them by encouraging them to participate in a medium that they are not familiar with. Despite 
               initial training in cellphilm and historical data collection, the first videos produced were often of poor quality and 
               had to be remade with the support of <name>Mamadou Cissé</name>.
            </p>
            <p>The digital work undertaken was nonetheless facilitated by continuous communication via social media between the 
               researcher and the <name>Donkosira</name> team. At the same time, issues of internet access in such a marginalised 
               community remained one of the major challenges of the project. Aside from the initial training workshop with the 
               villagers conducted in <name>Bamako</name> in December 2018 and the follow-up visit to <name>Bouillagui</name> by the 
               project team, direct communication with the villagers remained the prerogative of the <name>Donkosira</name> team — and, 
               in particular, <name>Mamadou Séne Cissé</name>, who visited <name>Bouillagui</name> every three months on average over 
               almost two years (2019–2020).
            </p>
            <p>The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic and the resulting series of lockdowns exacerbated beyond our expectations the 
               ethical tensions at the heart of co-production. Lockdowns increased, to some extent, what we initially wished to avoid 
               — namely, the risk of delegating the production of research materials and the collection of data to 
               <quote rend="inline">invisible third parties</quote> <ptr target="#bertho_etal2022"/>. <name>Marie Rodet</name> was 
               prevented from travelling again to <name>Mali</name> before the end of the project, which made face-to-face activities 
               crucial to the co-production of the web documentary impossible. Many of the project's other activities were then led by 
               <name>Donkosira</name> — albeit in close collaboration with <name>Marie Rodet</name> via social media — while an effort 
               was made to prevent <name>Donkosira</name>'s members from becoming <quote rend="inline">instrument-bodies</quote> used 
               remotely to access difficult terrain <ptr target="#bisoka2020"/>. This autonomy, reinforced by the constraints of the 
               pandemic, still enabled <name>Donkosira</name> to experiment with research techniques and strengthen their knowledge of 
               local history, both theoretical and practical. Importantly, the designation from the outset of the project of 
               <name>Donkosira</name> as the main partner, with their own allocated budget in a legally binding collaboration agreement 
               with the School of Oriental and African Studies (SOAS) at the <name>University of London</name>, nonetheless greatly 
               mitigated the risk of the <name>Donkosira</name> team's invisibilisation in the process. <name>Mamadou Séne Cissé</name> 
               conducted two workshops in <name>Bouillagui</name> with school children, further supported the villagers in making their 
               video reports about the history of <name>Bouillagui</name>, and conducted additional interviews with elders in the 
               community, while also regularly organising large-screen screenings on the main village square of the historical material 
               produced within the framework of the project. Ultimately, the web documentary was also screened with live translation 
               when necessary in <name>Bouillagui</name> in November 2020. Everyone was able to recognise themselves or their relatives 
               and friends and further discuss the different aspects of <name>Bouillagui</name>'s history.
            </p>
            <p>The web documentary is thus the result of research only partly co-produced with <name>Bouillagui</name> villagers. 
               While the authority was shared in producing the public history narrative at the origin of the web documentary, the 
               project struggled to escape completely the classic mechanisms of practical and symbolic inequality in researcher–villager 
               relations, conditions exacerbated by the consequences of the COVID-19 pandemic. The villagers could not be directly 
               involved in the final stages of the production of the web documentary, which was thus not designed by them but instead 
               was produced online between the <name>United Kingdom</name> and <name>France</name> by <name>Marie Rodet</name> — with 
               the editing support of <name>Cosimo Maximin</name> and the team of the <name>Paris</name>-based creative industry firm 
               Narratives, which specialises in the production of web documentaries. The web documentary remediated and translated 
               historical narratives co-produced by <name>Mamadou Séne Cissé</name> and the villagers, but also older filmed interviews 
               conducted by <name>Marie Rodet</name> for the documentary film <title rend="italic">The Diambourou</title> with 
               <name>Fanny Challier</name> <ptr target="#rodet2020"/>.
            </p>
            <p>If there is no universal recipe for escaping the epistemic violence of knowledge production, the devices — the provision 
               of mobile phones, the attempted insertion into a network of digital family practices, the passage through 
               <name>Donkosira</name> with which the villagers could easily identify — worked to at least nuance and enrich the 
               bilateral relationship between investigator and respondent <ptr target="#bertho_etal2022"/>.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>3. <q>Shared Authority</q> and Co-Production: What Digital Transmedia Production Allows and How it (Re)shapes 
             Research</head>
            <p>Creating a web documentary was not an immediate choice when we started the project in 2018. Our initial main concern 
               was to explore how to engage with different audiences using the digital media and narratives produced with the villagers 
               within the framework of this project. As the media had been co-produced by different authors, we aimed at offering an 
               overarching narrative piecing together polyvocal perspectives while making the material accessible to a large audience. 
               Yet, a specific event made us feel strongly about the pressing need for a rapid alternative publishing platform solution. 
               The <name>Kayes</name> public archives, which we had helped salvage a decade earlier with <name>Mariam Coulibaly</name> 
               (and which had not been digitised), were reduced to ashes at the height of a very restrictive COVID-19 lockdown that 
               fueled widespread discontent and large-scale mob protests in <name>Kayes</name> in the spring of 2020 
               <ptr target="#rodet_etal2021b"/>.
            </p>
            <p>In such a context, and unsure how the rest of the visual participatory research would unfold in the conditions of the 
               COVID-19 pandemic, we decided to make a web documentary with digital storytelling professionals who would produce such 
               output in a timely manner. In addition, the web documentary seemed compatible with the initial idea of writing bottom-up 
               history with the community. Its architecture could easily accommodate transmediation (multiple media use) and remediation 
               (change of media), while acknowledging the intrinsic shared authority of the narratives that had been produced through 
               the active dialogue between historical expertise and experience <ptr target="#frisch1990"/> <ptr target="#frisch2011"/>. 
               Indeed, the web documentary offered a polyvocal transmedia narrative of perspectives often missing from conventional 
               history.
            </p>
            <p>While offering a polyvocal narrative, we did not aim at integrating <emph>all</emph> voices about slavery in this web 
               documentary. Indeed, we did not give space to the memories of former enslavers, as the web documentary aimed at changing 
               the mainstream discourse in <name>Mali</name> — which still mainly featured the negationist voices of the former 
               enslavers at the time <ptr target="#camara_etal2021b"/>. Although objectivity is often argued to be a pre-requisite for 
               the search for historical <q>truth</q>, what is hardly considered under such an imperative is the harm that it can 
               produce by providing <q>equal</q> space to all sides of the story, including the aggressors, while not acknowledging 
               how it can reinforce and reinscribe existing systems of oppression and inequality. People with ascribed <q>slave 
               status</q> continue to face systemic and real violence in present-day <name>Mali</name>, and they should feel safe when 
               co-producing and using digital media in relation to their history. To this end, the recognition of the root causes of 
               harm, past and present, is essential so that digital media used for research do not reinforce or reproduce 
               intergenerational trauma and historical harm. On the contrary, they should be transformative by acknowledging and 
               publicising histories of resilience to slavery. Thus, the project never intended to research conflict narratives or 
               integrate them into the web documentary, unlike what has been done in other transmedia storytelling in digital public 
               history <ptr target="#basaraba_etal2023"/> <ptr target="#mcroberts2016"/>. Instead, it prioritised acknowledging a 
               history of marginalisation, valuing experiential knowledge, and sustaining research praxis review, following key 
               principles of an ethics of care: attentiveness, responsibility, competence, responsiveness, and solidarity 
               <ptr target="#brannelly2018"/>.
            </p>
            <p>The web documentary was certainly based on historical research and ethical standards that required fact-checking. 
               However, it still departed from the usual historical monograph narratives: the artistic and interpretative approaches 
               were defined by the imperatives of using digital storytelling techniques to get the social message across. It included 
               aesthetic choices and necessary simplification of the message to reach a broad audience. The choice of having an 
               aesthetically pleasing layout reinforced the value of telling a marginalised history and aimed at making clear that such 
               a neglected topic deserved as much attention as any other <q>major</q> historical subjects and a dedicated 
               <q>safe space</q> for this purpose.
            </p>
            <p>Digital media change our practice of history but also our relation to the past and the future, as they alter 
               <quote rend="inline">how we value, access, and use pasts and histories</quote> <ptr target="#tanaka2013"/>. For example, 
               a web documentary allows the presentation of multiple temporalities and voices while working around historical memories 
               and consciousness where the past continues to be present in our lives — what <name>Tanaka</name> calls the 
               <quote rend="inline">practical past</quote> <ptr target="#tanaka2013"/>. Nineteenth-century positivism, by approaching 
               the past as a linear, chronological structure and professionalising history as based on objectivity, scientific 
               methodologies, and truth, relegated the <q>practical past</q> to the realm of <q>tradition</q> and colonised societies 
               were perceived as <q>a-historical</q>. The web documentary — by involving <name>Bouillagui</name> villagers as 
               historical knowledge producers — contributed to decolonising such positivist negation of the multiplicity and 
               heterogeneity of pasts. By offering new narratives to link the impact of neglecting such history in recent years in 
               <name>Mali</name> to the renewed violence against people with ascribed <q>slave status</q>, the documentary bridges the 
               gap between endogenous historical resistance to slavery and modern anti-slavery activism.
            </p>
            <p>While historical digital storytelling by <q>non-professional</q> historians is still rarely considered <q>proper history 
               writing</q> in the academic world, historians have nonetheless a responsibility (duty of care) to work as allies with 
               communities to make neglected histories heard and legitimate <ptr target="#rosenzweig1998"/>. They can use their 
               expertise and authority to create with communities digital <q>safe places</q> that speak for all the people involved in 
               the process and that are grounded in an ethics of care with responsibility to produce change. Moving away from their 
               authoritative (narrow) expertise, they become curators of collected material that they help contextualise through 
               increased collaboration with the broader public for a better understanding of human experience and for socio-political 
               change <ptr target="#gardner2010"/> <ptr target="#santana2022"/> <ptr target="#tebeau2022"/>. The web documentary 
               <title rend="italic">Bouillagui: A Free Village</title> is closer to a curated online exhibition with a guided path for 
               the visitor than to a co-produced online primary source repository. The videos have been edited and subtitled in English 
               and French. The navigation follows a specific narrative path, although the visitor can jump from one section to the 
               other, back and forth, without disrupting the understanding of the content.
            </p>
            <p>While historical digital storytelling may be collaborative, including with the creative industry, the risk still remains 
               of blurring the different voices and contributions in general end credits, in similar ways to those in other digital 
               humanities projects that can be explicitly disentangled only in an accompanying academic article, as highlighted by 
               <ptr target="#lovejoy2020"/> and which is attempted in the present article. Indeed, digital humanities projects are the 
               result of multi-layered and multi-partner collaborations, with each partner having their own practices, constraints, and 
               understanding of their role. To turn the conducted historical research about <name>Bouillagui</name> into a narrative 
               for a broad audience, we worked with the <name>Paris</name>-based creative industry firm Narratives, which has 
               longstanding expertise in audio and visual storytelling. It was their first audio-visual project concerned with African 
               history. As they were not involved in the initial research process of co-production, their understanding of the project 
               was primarily centred on the transmediation process and thus about sharing the historian's knowledge and methods (to be 
               narrated in the form of a voice-over by the historian, which they insisted was needed) with the broader public that — 
               we realised too late in the process — they perceived mainly as a Western-based audience. It was <name>Rodet</name>'s 
               first experience with the storytelling creative industry and business-format constraints, which unfortunately allowed 
               little leeway and no trial-and-error process.
            </p>
            <p>In addition, the production took place during the first 2020 COVID-19 lockdown, preventing the direct inclusion of the 
               community in the production process. In these circumstances, we realised only after its production that the web 
               documentary was not usable by the <name>Bouillagui</name> villagers themselves because of its non-accessibility on mobile 
               phones (no app version) and its non-intuitive digital design (for villagers with low literacy). These unacknowledged 
               initial misunderstandings ultimately turned the web documentary into more of a teaching tool for Western universities, 
               with university colleagues acknowledging how the web documentary gave access to voices that otherwise are difficult for 
               teachers to transmit to students <ptr target="#ifph2020"/>. We are currently working on a Bambara and Soninke video 
               version of the web documentary as well as on a mobile app to mitigate accessibility issues for Malian audiences.
            </p>
            <p>One may well wonder whose voices are really to be heard in this web documentary and for what social change. Who owns the 
               past and how is it used? How can we ethically represent others? How do we choose between competing agendas without 
               turning such narratives into history for Western consumption and compromising on the ethics of care 
               <ptr target="#pickering_etal2017"/>? This requires a strong commitment to integrity in the storytelling and editing 
               process <ptr target="#borum-chatoo2020"/>.
            </p>
            <p>The history of <name>Bouillagui</name> here is not just transmediated but has also been remediated. The narrative has 
               been edited and curated by a historian and a professional storyteller, creating post-storytelling that can raise 
               concerns about how testimonies are mediated and presented to audiences <ptr target="#mcroberts2016"/> 
               <ptr target="#pickering_etal2017"/>. As already mentioned, the villagers could not take part in selecting or interpreting 
               the video material for the web documentary, which remained in the hands of the researcher. The historian and the 
               professional storyteller are the two named editors of the web documentary and may thus appear as the primary benefiters 
               professionally of this controlled shared authority, with a risk of appropriation, tokenism, and commodification of 
               research <ptr target="#rose2014"/> <ptr target="#lloyd_etal2015"/> <ptr target="#brannelly2018"/> 
               <ptr target="#macentee2016"/>. Although all contributors to the research project are named in the final credits, such 
               credits are different from acknowledged authorship and copyrights <ptr target="#lovejoy2020"/>.
            </p>
            <p>Despite these significant pitfalls, making a web documentary based on a co-production research project on resistance to 
               slavery is an important ethical step in critically reviewing history practices, making the web documentary more than just 
               an argument about the past <ptr target="#dorn2013"/>. Co-production in public history is about making history come alive, 
               thereby forcing us to actively remember the past rather than existing in a mode of passive consumption, which in turn 
               produces social awareness that could lead to social change, especially with the promises of digital virality. At the same 
               time, socio-political contexts of reception change and electronic data remains ephemeral, even when in the case of a web 
               documentary it cannot be erased or modified by users.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>4. Taking Risks When End-User Environments and Related Ethical Implications Change</head>
            <p>In September 2019, a mobile phone video from a village in western <name>Mali</name> showing a man being beaten and tied 
               up started circulating on social media in <name>Mali</name>.<note>See 
               <ref target="https://observers.france24.com/en/20190924-video-malian-man-tied-public-opposing-traditional-slavery">https://observers.france24.com/en/20190924-video-malian-man-tied-public-opposing-traditional-slavery</ref> 
               (accessed 16 July 2023).</note> The man had been humiliated by a village mob for having dared to oppose descent-based 
               slavery practised in western <name>Mali</name>. Since then, similar scenes have been repeated in villages across the 
               region. The violence culminated in several horrific murders, all taking place in western <name>Mali</name> — in 
               September 2020 in <name>Diandioume</name>, in September 2021 in <name>Bafoulabé</name>, and again in July 2022 in 
               <name>Lany Tounka</name>, where <name>Diogou Sidibé</name>, a 71-year-old grandmother, was hacked to death with a machete 
               on her farmland for having refused to be called a slave. Yet, until the latter murder, the Malian state and global 
               community remained largely silent, despite the important demonstrations organised against slavery in <name>Kayes</name> 
               city <ptr target="#camara_etal2021a"/>. In August 2022, eighteen persons were arrested following 
               <name>Diogou Sidibé</name>'s murder. In February 2023, the Kayes Criminal Court sentenced seven people to the death 
               penalty and one to five years in prison for crimes linked to the practice of descent-based slavery in western 
               <name>Mali</name>, notably those crimes committed in <name>Diandioume</name> in September 2020.<note>See 
               <ref target="https://www.studiotamani.org/129056-esclavage-par-ascendance-7-personnes-condamnees-a-mort-a-kayes">https://www.studiotamani.org/129056-esclavage-par-ascendance-7-personnes-condamnees-a-mort-a-kayes</ref> 
               (accessed 16 July 2023).</note> They were convicted of criminal conspiracy, murder, looting, assault and battery, and 
               ethnic discrimination. Yet, as recently as May 2024, another man fell victim to descent-based slavery: 
               <name>Oumar Konate</name> from <name>Nematoulaye</name> in western <name>Mali</name> died following a violent dispute 
               with the village's enslavers on the grounds that he had refused to accept his ascribed <q>slave status</q>.<note>See 
               <ref target="https://www.dw.com/fr/un-malien-lynche-pour-setre-oppose-a-son-statut-desclave/a-69104750">https://www.dw.com/fr/un-malien-lynche-pour-setre-oppose-a-son-statut-desclave/a-69104750</ref> 
               (accessed 15 July 2024).</note>
            </p>
            <p>Against the backdrop of this unsettling socio-political context of exacerbated violence against populations with 
               ascribed <q>slave status</q>, naming slavery and making this, until recently, <q>invisible</q> history henceforth 
               <q>visible</q> obviously had new political ramifications that needed to be re-evaluated, including the potential risks 
               for the villagers we had involved in our project. As the project's principal investigator and co-investigator, we were 
               indeed accountable for the conditions under which the villagers were to become publicly visible through the research 
               process in general and the web documentary in particular <ptr target="#dickens_etal2016"/>. This changing socio-political 
               situation posed complex ethical dilemmas. Acknowledging this changing context, we were torn between, on the one hand, 
               our responsibilities as researchers and practitioners to make the complex legacies of slavery recognised and the long 
               history of resistance known, and, on the other hand, the need to avoid causing any harm to the villagers — especially 
               as the violence had not stopped at the time the web documentary was being produced (June–November 2020).
            </p>
            <p>The Gambana movement initially began in 2018 among the Mauritanian Soninke diaspora in <name>France</name> in reaction 
               to audio recordings and a video interview, posted on social media, of a Mecca-based Soninke Islamic preacher justifying 
               slavery through the hadith literature.<note>Interview, 21 September 2021, with <name>Gaye Traoré</name>, founder and 
               president of the movement Ganbanaxuun Fedde.</note> The movement, using primarily the social network WhatsApp, soon 
               began to involve many of the West African Soninke diaspora — including the Malian diaspora, as well as a growing number 
               of militants based in <name>West Africa</name> — in exchanging thousands of audio and video recordings a month, with a 
               virality effect never achieved before on such an issue. WhatsApp also facilitated the viral circulation of mobile videos, 
               photographs, and audio recordings of exactions committed against Gambana militants since 2018.
            </p>
            <p>As the saying <q>a picture is worth a thousand words</q> seems to imply, the use of audio-visual media often makes 
               social messages far more effective and appealing, including those concerning historical narratives 
               <ptr target="#salvatori2022"/> <ptr target="#theibault2022"/>. The power of remediation of information into audio-visual 
               narratives such as those in documentary films can sometimes be so effective that viewers tend to forget the medium (due 
               to its <quote rend="inline">transparent immediacy</quote>, per <ptr target="#bolter_etal1999"/>) and fall under the 
               illusion that they directly access and experience unmediated raw information. The (moving) image is usually associated 
               with <q>truth</q>, as the camera has supposedly captured things as they happen, resulting in the illusion for the viewer 
               of almost having witnessed for themselves what has been recorded, even though this presence is no longer there 
               <ptr target="#spence_etal2012"/>. A web documentary allows one to draw attention to the materiality of oral sources, 
               making more transparent the oral history process. Although all representation or remediation is partial transformation 
               <ptr target="#spence_etal2012"/>, the illusion of the <q>authenticity</q> of visual media is probably where lies its 
               greater power, in comparison with writing, in influencing understandings and conceptions about specific topics — 
               and even more so in the digital era when videos can be easily shared on social media. Because the Gambana have been able 
               to widely circulate on social media video evidence of the exactions that their militants experienced, it alerted the 
               international media and increasingly pressured the Malian government to ultimately acknowledge that slavery practices 
               did exist in the country.
            </p>
            <p>It is in such a context of unprecedented <q>abundance</q> of audio-visual material related to slavery in 
               <name>Mali</name> that the production of the web documentary and the related risks must be situated 
               <ptr target="#fickers2012"/> <ptr target="#rose2014"/>. In 2020, the Gambana movement members, who fought for the 
               recognition that slavery still exists in <name>Mali</name>, were paradoxically perceived as being the perpetrators of 
               violence (which they were actually victims of) and of disrupting a purported peaceful social order 
               <ptr target="#camara_etal2021b"/>. Even in <name>Bouillagui</name> and despite their history of resistance to slavery, 
               some villagers were reluctant by then to be associated with the movement.
            </p>
            <p>As highlighted by <ptr target="#cahill2007"/>, one must ask oneself: What is safe to share in this context? Who is at 
               risk of harm? Should we edit out some of the research because the context of reception might not be ripe for it? How can 
               we contextualise our research and make it still relevant for the present when the present changes? In other words, how 
               do we present our research so that it is <q>favourably received</q>, impacts people, and facilitates change, while 
               carefully assessing the risks for the concerned community? How can we name slavery and resistance while preserving our 
               ethical commitment towards the <name>Bouillagui</name> community in (re)presenting their history? What about the risk of 
               the narrative being used or misinterpreted by certain sectors of the public? Once the web documentary has been made 
               public, it is a story that will potentially define <name>Bouillagui</name> villagers for many years to come.
            </p>
            <p>Yet, for the villagers involved it seems that the <quote rend="inline">ethics of recognition</quote> offset the risk of 
               being wrongly perceived by the consumers of the web documentary <ptr target="#dickens_etal2016"/>. They had won their 
               own battle against slavery a long time ago and wanted it to be widely known and publicly acknowledged. The greater risk 
               for <name>Bouillagui</name> so far had been for their history to be continuously invisibilised and their populations to 
               be unrecognised as full citizens. Despite, or, rather, because of <name>Bouillagui</name>'s history of fierce struggle 
               for freedom, the socio-political environment in the region remained hostile to and discriminatory against them, while 
               the slavery ideology continued be upheld in many villages around them. The founders of <name>Bouillagui</name> had 
               already entered the struggle for recognition more than one hundred years ago. In a sense, this digital public history 
               project was just an additional step in a longer history that they had already decided for themselves when they rebelled 
               against their former enslavers in 1914. Here, the risk of naming and public visibility appears necessary and potentially 
               beneficial in the fight for recognition through the gain of increased respect and solidarity in the Malian public sphere 
               and beyond <ptr target="#dickens_etal2016"/>. During the preview screening in <name>Bouillagui</name> in November 2020, 
               <name>Bouillagui</name>'s notables praised the initiative to produce this web documentary, which they believed would 
               teach the younger generations a great deal in terms of citizenship, enable <name>Bouillagui</name>'s children to get to 
               know their village and, above all, the history of its foundation, and make <name>Bouillagui</name> known throughout the 
               world.
            </p>
            <p>Our position as recognised researchers and practitioners has also helped to mitigate the risk of misrecognition, as the 
               shared authority fostered a safe space for and an alliance with the <name>Bouillagui</name> community. We nonetheless 
               attempted a compromise, in that we committed to revisit the documentary as the situation for the Gambana movement in 
               <name>Mali</name> evolves. In one of the videos of the web documentary, <name>Rodet</name>'s voice-over mentions the 
               context of increased violence against people with ascribed <q>slave status</q> and Gambana activists in 
               <name>Mali</name> and how it affected the research. Yet this specific video was not shown at the first official 
               screenings in <name>Mali</name>. This was suggested by <name>Mamadou Séne Cissé</name>, who was in charge of the web 
               documentary screenings in <name>Mali</name> and who assessed that the situation at the time with the Gambana movement 
               in the region was far too tense to run the risk of having its name mentioned at a public screening. All this took place 
               against the backdrop of a very unstable political situation, with increased surveillance and arrest of <q>dissident</q> 
               voices, alongside systematic social media suspensions and the diffusion of fake news to control Malian public opinion. 
               Since then, Gambana's public perception as <q>troublemakers</q> flooding WhatsApp with <q>irresponsible</q>, 
               <q>anti-social</q> discourses has nonetheless changed markedly. They have been recognised by the Malian authorities as 
               a legitimate partner in the fight against slavery. We henceforth play the full version of the web documentary at 
               public screenings.
            </p>
            <p>Such a situation clearly illustrates how research is an ethical process and digital ethics a moving target: 
               conflicting narratives can arise as research unfolds, and the end-user's environment may unpredictably change despite 
               regular risk assessment in the course of the project <ptr target="#ess2012"/>. In the same way, the public for such 
               a web documentary itself can also change. Although we produced this web documentary with specific audiences in mind, 
               as discussed previously, until the web documentary is released it is difficult to predict which audiences will really 
               access and be sensitive to it. Even then, because it is web-based it allows access by a wide range of publics, 
               heterogenous in terms of class and economic status and political commitments — although, as mentioned earlier, the 
               digital gap crucially affects the web documentary's effective accessibility by all publics, most notably in 
               <name>Mali</name>. With digital content, the <q>politics of reception</q> is often unpredictable, with no guarantee 
               that the content will travel well not only within, across, and between cultures, but also over time 
               <ptr target="#macentee2016"/>.
            </p>
            <p>This also raises questions about the future of such digital public history projects. On one side, there is increasing 
               funding pressure for open data — for example, amongst UKRI (UK Research and Innovation)-funded projects in 
               the <name>United Kingdom</name>, since 2023. On the other side, there is only open-access funding for published papers. 
               There is no funding for alternative digital publication platforms or any research website or digital collection beyond 
               the lifetime of the funding project. Funding their continued maintenance often requires applying to craete new research 
               projects that would contribute to enhance parts of the original. We managed to get the web documentary hosted on the 
               SOAS server with the hope that this would secure its future, but as universities increasingly sub-contract their data 
               storage to expensive GAFAM <q>giants</q> (Alphabet, Amazon, Meta, Apple, Microsoft), while experiencing public budget 
               cuts, this becomes an issue of cost-effectiveness, where the university decides which data to maintain, which to store 
               in the cloud, and which to delete — decisions concerning which the researcher is not always consulted.
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore, an online transmedia project such as a web documentary remains fixed in time; it is not meant to be 
               modified, though the end-users might live in different political, cultural, and social environments that are 
               fast-changing. Leaving aside the illusion that the digital will allow us to record and retain everything, we should be 
               mindful as historians that electronic data and the cloud actually require physical storage space and can thus 
               disappear, just as historical evidence and archives themselves regularly do. If a digital public history website becomes 
               no longer fit for purpose, as digital ethics also evolve — while the technology to maintain data can easily become 
               obsolete (our web documentary uses Klynt, an online software to create and publish interactive narratives for the 
               web)<note>See <ref target="https://www.klynt.net/">https://www.klynt.net/</ref>.</note> — we should accept letting it 
               go and take the webpage or website down. We could also consider archiving it with public digital archives, such as with 
               UK data archives.
            </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>With the aim of engaging the past in the present, our digital history project took two main risks at its outset: 
               conducting a public history project on the still-taboo topic of resistance to slavery in <name>Mali</name>; and betting 
               on research co-production and shared authority with <name>Bouillagui</name>'s villagers through participatory visual 
               methods, despite the digital gap. As the socio-political context in <name>Mali</name> and also worldwide rapidly changed 
               over the two years of the project, we did not anticipate all the project's twists and turns. Despite some clear 
               pitfalls, this was an important step in realising that just as research is a process, so too are ethics: digital 
               history and storytelling require responsibility toward co-producers and audiences, not only during the research process 
               but also with the online publication, especially when working with communities who run the risk of sharing their history 
               of resistance to slavery in contexts that have never properly allowed for these voices to be heard. It is through such 
               an ethical process, an ethics of care that relies on long-term engagement and commitment, that the transformative 
               potential of a digital public history project naming slavery can reveal itself. The greater risk for the populations 
               concerned may not actually lie in telling and publicising such history but in allowing the hegemonic discourses to 
               continue to silence them. As highlighted by <name>Gardner</name>, engaging in public history is about taking risks and 
               dealing with unsafe ideas, even in unsafe times, but it is also a risk we should commit to, especially when we have been 
               entrusted by the concerned communities to name slavery and publicise their history of resistance to it 
               <ptr target="#gardner2010"/>.
            </p>
        </div>
      </body>
      <back>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="anderson2018" label="Anderson 2018">Anderson, S. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Episode 31: Are museums 
             <quote rend="inline">safe spaces for unsafe ideas</quote>?</title> [podcast episode], 
             <title rend="italic">Museopunks</title>. American Alliance of Museums. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://www.aam-us.org/2018/11/15/museopunks-episode-31-are-museums-safe-spaces-for-unsafe-ideas/">https://www.aam-us.org/2018/11/15/museopunks-episode-31-are-museums-safe-spaces-for-unsafe-ideas/</ref> 
             (Accessed: 22 July 2023).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="anderson2021" label="Anderson 2021">Anderson, S. (2021) <title rend="quotes"><quote rend="inline">We felt 
             unsafe</quote>. Rethinking risk, harm, and safety in museums</title>, <title rend="italic">Museums &amp; Social 
             Issues</title>, 15(1-2), pp. 4–12. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/15596893.2022.2074639">https://doi.org/10.1080/15596893.2022.2074639</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="basaraba_etal2023" label="Basaraba and Cauvin 2023">Basaraba, N. and Cauvin, T. (2023) 
             <title rend="quotes">Public history and transmedia storytelling for conflicting narratives</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Rethinking History</title>, 27(2), pp. 221-247. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/13642529.2023.2184969">https://doi.org/10.1080/13642529.2023.2184969</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bellagamba_etal2013" label="Bellagamba, Greene, and Klein 2013">Bellagamba, A., Greene, S., and Klein, M. 
             (eds.) (2013) <title rend="italic">African voices on slavery and the slave trade</title>. Cambridge, UK: 
             Cambridge University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bertho_etal2022" label="Bertho et al. 2022">Bertho, E. et al. (2022) <title rend="quotes">L'expérience 
             <quote rend="inline">Donkosira</quote>: Savoirs locaux, coproduction, outils numériques</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Revue d'Histoire Contemporaine de l'Afrique</title>, 28 March. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://oap.unige.ch/journals/rhca/article/view/stcberthocisselupkerodet">https://oap.unige.ch/journals/rhca/article/view/stcberthocisselupkerodet</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bisoka2020" label="Bisoka 2020">Bisoka, A.N. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Disturbing the aesthetics of 
             power: Why COVID-19 is not an <quote rend="inline">event</quote> for fieldwork-based social scientists</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">ITEMS</title>, 28 May. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://items.ssrc.org/covid-19-and-the-social-sciences/social-research-and-insecurity/disturbing-the-aesthetics-of-power-why-covid-19-is-not-an-event-for-fieldwork-based-social-scientists/">https://items.ssrc.org/covid-19-and-the-social-sciences/social-research-and-insecurity/disturbing-the-aesthetics-of-power-why-covid-19-is-not-an-event-for-fieldwork-based-social-scientists/</ref> 
             (Accessed: 22 July 2023).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bolter_etal1999" label="Bolter and Grusin 1999">Bolter, J. and Grusin, R. (1999) 
             <title rend="italic">Remediation: Understanding new media</title>. Boston, MA: The MIT Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="borum-chatoo2020" label="Borum Chatoo 2020">Borum Chatoo, C. (2020) <title rend="italic">Story movements. 
             How documentaries empower people and inspire social change</title>. New York: Oxford University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="brannelly2018" label="Brannelly 2018">Brannelly, T. (2018) <title rend="italic">An ethics of care research 
             manifesto</title>, <title rend="italic">International Journal of Care and Caring</title>, 2(3), pp. 367–378. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1332/239788218X15351944886756">https://doi.org/10.1332/239788218X15351944886756</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cahill2007" label="Cahill 2007">Cahill, C. (2007) <title rend="quotes">Repositioning ethical commitments: 
             Participatory action research as a relational praxis of social change</title>, <title rend="italic">ACME: An 
             International Journal for Critical Geographies</title>, 6(3), pp. 360–373. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://acme-journal.org/index.php/acme/article/view/784">https://acme-journal.org/index.php/acme/article/view/784</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="camara_etal2021a" label="Camara et al. 2021a">Camara, B. et al. (2021a) <title rend="quotes">The fight 
             against descent-based slavery in Mali</title>, <title rend="italic">Africa Is A Country</title>, 3 May. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://africasacountry.com/2021/03/the-fight-against-descent-based-slavery-in-mali">https://africasacountry.com/2021/03/the-fight-against-descent-based-slavery-in-mali</ref> 
             (Accessed: 22 July 2023).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="camara_etal2021b" label="Camara et al. 2021b">Camara, B. et al. (2021b) <title rend="quotes">Under the 
             radar: Descent-based slavery as a form of contemporary slavery</title>, <title rend="italic">The Republic</title>, 
             6 July. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://republic.com.ng/june-july-2021/under-the-radar/">https://republic.com.ng/june-july-2021/under-the-radar/</ref> 
             (Accessed 22 July 2023).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cameron2008" label="Cameron 2008">Cameron, F. (2008) <title rend="quotes">Safe places for unsafe ideas? 
             History and science museums, hot topics and moral predicaments</title>, in Terwey, M. (ed.) 
             <hi rend="italic">Social History in Museums</hi>. London: Social History Curators Group, pp. 5-16.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="christensen_etal2020" label="Christensen and Larsen 2020">Christensen, L.L. and Larsen, M.C. (2020) 
             <title rend="italic">Ethical challenges in digital research: A guide to discuss ethical issues in digital 
             research</title>, 2nd ed., 3 January. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://vbn.aau.dk/en/publications/ethical-challenges-in-digital-research-a-guide-to-discuss-ethical-2">https://vbn.aau.dk/en/publications/ethical-challenges-in-digital-research-a-guide-to-discuss-ethical-2</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cisse_etal2024" label="Cissé, Pelckmans, and Rodet 2024">Cissé, M.S., Pelckmans, L., and Rodet, M. (2024) 
             <title rend="quotes">Rethinking the climate change-migration-conflict nexus in the Sahel: A plea for intersectionality 
             to include descent-based slavery</title>, <title rend="italic">SOAS History Blog</title>, 29 April. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://blogs.soas.ac.uk/soashistoryblog/2024/04/29/rethinking-the-climate-change-migration-conflict-nexus-in-the-sahel-a-plea-for-intersectionality-to-include-descent-based-slavery/">https://blogs.soas.ac.uk/soashistoryblog/2024/04/29/rethinking-the-climate-change-migration-conflict-nexus-in-the-sahel-a-plea-for-intersectionality-to-include-descent-based-slavery/</ref> 
             (Accessed: 1 May 2024).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dickens_etal2016" label="Dickens and Butcher 2016">Dickens, L., and Butcher, M. (2016) 
             <title rend="quotes">Going public? Re-thinking visibility, ethics and recognition through participatory research 
             praxis</title>, <title rend="italic">Transactions of the Institute of British Geographers</title>, 41(4), pp. 528–540. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1111/tran.12136">https://doi.org/10.1111/tran.12136</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dorn2013" label="Dorn 2013">Dorn, S. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Is (digital) history more than an argument 
             about the past?</title>, in Dougherty, J. and Nawrotzki, K. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Writing history in the digital 
             age</title>. Ann Arbor, MI: University of Michigan Press, pp. 21-34.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="eckl_etal2007" label="Eckl and Weber 2007">Eckl, J. and Weber, R. (2007) <title rend="quotes">North: South? 
             Pitfalls of dividing the world by words</title>, <title rend="italic">Third World Quarterly</title>, 28(11), pp. 3–23. 
             Available at: <ref target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/4017790">http://www.jstor.org/stable/4017790</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="edmonds_etal2016" label="Edmonds et al. 2016">Edmonds, F. et al. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Ethical 
             considerations when using visual methods in digital storytelling with Aboriginal young people in Southeast 
             Australia</title>, in Warr, D. et al. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Ethics and visual research methods: Theory, 
             methodology, and practice</title>. Palgrave Macmillan: Springer Science and Business Media, pp. 171-184.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ess2012" label="Ess 2012">Ess, C. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Foreword</title>, in Heider, D. and 
             Massanari, A. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Digital ethics: Research &amp; practice</title> New York: Peter Lang, 
             ix-xix.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fickers2012" label="Fickers 2012">Fickers A. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Towards a new digital 
             historicism? Doing history in the age of abundance</title>, <title rend="italic">VIEW Journal of European Television 
             History and Culture</title>, 1(1), pp. 19-26. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.18146/2213-0969.2012.jethc004">https://doi.org/10.18146/2213-0969.2012.jethc004</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="frisch1990" label="Frisch 1990">Frisch, M. (1990) <title rend="italic">A shared authority: Essays on the 
             craft and meaning of oral and public history</title>. New York: State University of New York Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="frisch2011" label="Frisch 2011">Frisch, M. (2011) <title rend="italic">From a shared authority to the 
             digital kitchen, and back</title>, in Adair, B., Filene, B., and Koloski, L. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Letting go? 
             Sharing historical authority in a user-generated world</title>. Philadelphia, PA: Pew Center for Arts and Heritage, 
             pp. 124-137.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gardner2010" label="Gardner 2010">Gardner, J.B. (2010) <title rend="quotes">Trust, risk and public 
             history: A view from the United States</title>, <title rend="italic">Public History Review</title>, 17, pp. 52–61.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gubrium_etal2016" label="Gubrium, Fiddian-Green, and Hill 2016">Gubrium, A., Fiddian-Green, A., and 
             Hill, A. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Conflicting aims and minimizing harm: Uncovering experiences of trauma in 
             digital storytelling with young women</title>, in Warr, D. et al. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Ethics and visual 
             research methods: Theory, methodology, and practice</title>. Palgrave Macmillan: Springer Science and Business Media, 
             pp. 157-170.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gurian1995" label="Gurian 1995">Gurian, E.H. (1995) <title rend="quotes">Offering safer public 
             spaces</title>, <title rend="italic">The Journal of Museum Education</title>, 20(3), pp. 14–16.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hall-budd_etal2017" label="Hall Budd and Tandon 2017">Hall Budd, L. and Tandon, R. (2017) 
             <title rend="quotes">Decolonization of knowledge, epistemicide, participatory research and higher education</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Research for All</title>, 1(1), pp. 6–19. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.18546/RFA.01.1.02">https://doi.org/10.18546/RFA.01.1.02</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hart_etal2021" label="Hart, Ogoegbunam Okoye, and Oduro-Frimpong 2021">Hart, J., Ogoegbunam Okoye V., and 
             Oduro-Frimpong, J. (2021) <title rend="quotes">On collaboration and communication <quote rend="inline">in the 
             now</quote></title>, <title rend="italic">Africa Today</title>, 67(4), pp. 88–94. 
             <ref target="http://doi.org/10.2979/africatoday.67.4.06">http://doi.org/10.2979/africatoday.67.4.06</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ifph2020" label="IFPH Public History 2020">IFPH Public History (2020) <title rend="italic">Bouillagui: 
             A free village</title> (webinar). Available at: 
             <ref target="https://vimeo.com/478738839">https://vimeo.com/478738839</ref> (Accessed: 12 June 2023).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="iliffe2005" label="Iliffe 2005">Iliffe, J. (2005) <title rend="italic">Honour in African history</title>. 
             Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lloyd_etal2015" label="Lloyd and Moore 2015">Lloyd, S. and Moore, J. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Sedimented 
             histories: Connections, collaborations and co-production in regional history</title>, <title rend="italic">History 
             Workshop Journal</title>, 80, pp. 234–48.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lovejoy2020" label="Lovejoy 2020">Lovejoy, H.B. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Who did what when? 
             Acknowledging collaborative contributions in digital history projects</title>, <title rend="italic">Esclavages &amp; 
             Post-Esclavages</title>, 3, pp. 1–21.
          juhkk</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="macentee2016" label="MacEntee 2016">MacEntee, K. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Facing responses to 
             cellphilm screenings of African girlhood in academic presentations</title>, in MacEntee, K., Burkholder, C., and 
             Schwab-Cartas, J. (eds) <title rend="italic">What's a Cellphilm?</title>. Rotterdam, Netherlands: SensePublishers, 
             pp. 135-152.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="macentee_etal2016" label="MacEntee, Burkholder, and Schwab-Cartas 2016">MacEntee, K., Burkholder, C., and 
             Schwab-Cartas, J. (2016) <title rend="quotes">What's a cellphilm? An introduction</title>, in MacEntee, K., 
             Burkholder, C., and Schwab-Cartas, J. (eds.) <title rend="italic">What's a cellphilm?</title> Rotterdam, Netherlands: 
             SensePublishers, pp. 1-15.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mcroberts2016" label="McRoberts 2016">McRoberts, J. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Negotiating conflict: A 
             discussion of interactive documentary as constructive storytelling in societies emerging from conflict</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Networking Knowledge: Journal of the MeCCSA Postgraduate Network</title>, 9(1). 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.31165/nk.2016.91.414">https://doi.org/10.31165/nk.2016.91.414</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="noiret2022" label="Noiret 2022">Noiret, S. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Sharing authority in online 
             collaborative public history practices</title>, in Noiret, S., Tebeau, M., and Zaagsma, G. (eds.) 
             <title rend="italic">Handbook of Digital Public History</title>. Berlin: De Gruyter Oldenbourg, pp. 49-60.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pickering_etal2017" label="Pickering and Kara 2017">Pickering, L. and Kara, H. (2017) 
             <title rend="quotes">Presenting and representing others: Towards an ethics of engagement</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">International Journal of Social Research Methodology</title>, 20(3), pp. 299-309. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/13645579.2017.1287875">https://doi.org/10.1080/13645579.2017.1287875</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="piron_etal2016" label="Piron, Régulus, and Dibounje Madiba 2016">Piron, F., Régulus, S., and Dibounje 
             Madiba, M.S. (eds.) (2016) <title rend="italic">Justice cognitive, libre accès et savoirs locaux. Pour une science 
             ouverte juste, au service du développement local durable</title>. Québec: Éditions science et bien commun.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rodet2010" label="Rodet 2010">Rodet, M. (2010) <title rend="quotes">Mémoires de l'esclavage dans la région 
             de Kayes, histoire d'une disparition</title>, <hi rend="italic">Cahiers d'études africaines</hi>, 197, pp. 263–291. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.4000/etudesafricaines.15854">https://doi.org/10.4000/etudesafricaines.15854</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rodet2013" label="Rodet 2013">Rodet, M. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Listening to the history of those 
             who don't forget</title>, <title rend="italic">History in Africa</title>, 40(s1), pp. 27-29. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/528345">https://www.muse.jhu.edu/article/528345</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rodet2015" label="Rodet 2015">Rodet, M. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Escaping slavery and building 
             diasporic communities in French Soudan and Senegal, ca. 1880–1940</title>, <title rend="italic">The International 
             Journal of African Historical Studies</title>, 48(2), pp. 363–386. Available at: 
             <ref target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/44723365">http://www.jstor.org/stable/44723365</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rodet2016" label="Rodet 2016">Rodet, M. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Slavery: West Africa</title>, in 
             <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia of Women &amp; Islamic Cultures</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://referenceworks.brill.com/display/db/ewio">https://referenceworks.brill.com/display/db/ewio</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rodet2020" label="Rodet 2020">Rodet, M. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Documenting the history of slavery on 
             film in Kayes, Mali</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Global Slavery</title>, 5(1), pp. 89–104. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1163/2405836X-00501009">https://doi.org/10.1163/2405836X-00501009</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rodet_etal2020" label="Rodet et al. 2020">Rodet, M. et al. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Retours sur 
             l'incendie d'un fonds d'archives à Kayes (Mali): enjeux sociaux, scientifiques et politiques</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Sources: Materials &amp; Fieldwork in African Studies</title>, 2, pp. 239–248. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/SOURCES/halshs-03096910">https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/SOURCES/halshs-03096910</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rodet_etal2021a" label="Rodet et al. 2021">Rodet, M. et al. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Mali fails to face 
             up to the persistence of slavery</title>, <title rend="italic">The Conversation</title>, 15 February. Available at: 
             <ref target="https://theconversation.com/mali-fails-to-face-up-to-the-persistence-of-slavery-147636">https://theconversation.com/mali-fails-to-face-up-to-the-persistence-of-slavery-147636</ref> 
             (Accessed: 22 July 2023).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rodet_etal2021b" label="Rodet and Doquet 2021">Rodet, M. and Doquet, A. (2021) 
             <title rend="quotes">Restituer les mémoires de l'esclavage: une pluralité de supports</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">Esclavages &amp; Post-esclavages</title>, 5. 
             <ref target="https://doi.org/10.4000/slaveries.4693">https://doi.org/10.4000/slaveries.4693</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rose2014" label="Rose 2014">Rose, G. (2014) <title rend="quotes">On the relation between 
             <quote rend="inline">visual research methods</quote> and contemporary visual culture</title>, 
             <title rend="italic">The Sociological Review</title>, 62, pp. 24–46.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rossi2013" label="Rossi 2013">Rossi, B. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Without history? Interrogating 
             <quote rend="inline">slave</quote> memories in Ader (Niger)</title>, in Bellagamba, A., Greene, S., and Klein, M. 
             (eds.) <title rend="italic">African Voices on Slavery and the Slave Trade</title> Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University 
             Press, pp. 536-554.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rosenzweig1998" label="Rosenzweig 1998">Rosenzweig R. (1998) <title rend="quotes">The presence of the 
             past: Roy Rosenzweig afterthoughts: Roy Rosenzweig everyone a historian</title>. Available at: 
             <ref target="http://chnm.gmu.edu/survey/afterroy.html">http://chnm.gmu.edu/survey/afterroy.html</ref> 
             (Accessed: 22 July 2023).
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="santana2022" label="Santana 2022">Santana, D. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Historians as digital 
             storytellers: The digital shift in narrative practices for public historians</title>, in Noiret, S., Tebeau, M., 
             and Zaagsma, G. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Handbook of digital public history</title>. Berlin: De Gruyter 
             Oldenbourg, pp. 485-494.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tanaka2013" label="Tanaka 2013">Tanaka, S. (2013) <title rend="quotes">Pasts in a digital age</title>, 
             in Dougherty, J. and Nawrotzki, K. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Writing history in the digital age</title>. 
             Ann Arbor, MI: University of Michigan Press, pp. 35-46.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tebeau2022" label="Tebeau 2022">Tebeau, M. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Curation: Toward a new ethic of 
             digital public history</title>, in Noiret, S., Tebeau, M., and Zaagsma, G. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Handbook of 
             digital public history</title>. Berlin: De Gruyter Oldenbourg, pp. 277-290.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="walsh2016" label="Walsh 2016">Walsh, S. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Critiquing the politics of 
             participatory video and the dangerous romance of liberalism</title>, <title rend="italic">Area</title>, 48(4), 
             pp. 405-411. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1111/area.12104">https://doi.org/10.1111/area.12104</ref>.
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="wyatt2012" label="Wyatt 2012">Wyatt, S. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Ethics of e-research in social 
             sciences and humanities</title>, in Heider, D. and Massanari, A. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Digital ethics, 
             research and practice</title>. Berlin: Peter Lang, pp. 5-20.
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
