<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Digital Humanities, Postfoundationalism, Postindustrial
                    Culture</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>James <dhq:family>Smithies</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Canterbury</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>james.smithies@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
                    <dhq:bio>

                        <p>James Smithies is Senior Lecturer in Digital Humanities and Associate
                            Director of the UC CEISMIC Canterbury Earthquakes Digital Archive at the
                            University of Canterbury, New Zealand. He has previously worked in the
                            ICT industry as a technical writer and editor, business analyst, and
                            project manager.</p>

                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000172</idno>
                <idno type="volume">008</idno>
                <idno type="issue">1</idno>
                <date when="2014-04-24">24 April 2014</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>defining DH</item>
                        <item>postfoundationalism</item>
                        <item>postindustrialism</item>
                        <item>Theory</item>
                        <item>software studies</item>
                        <item>cultural studies</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2014-02-07" who="DN">Encoded article</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This article articulates a view of the digital humanities that hopes to advance
                    the discipline across broad scholarly and administrative contexts. It will
                    succeed in its aims if it is both comprehensible to newcomers and stimulating
                    for experienced practitioners: a <soCalled>bridging</soCalled> effort, but one
                    undertaken with serious intent. It proceeds by isolating a key debate for
                    examination, describing two concepts that go a significant distance to solving
                    issues raised by that debate (but not far enough), and exploring the theoretical
                    writings of a selection of high profile digital humanists. The goal (a
                    non-trivial undertaking) is to illustrate the utility of postfoundationalism as
                    a conceptual tool, its interdependence with postindustrial culture, and the
                    light it sheds on our understanding of what <q>DH</q> is. If successful the
                    article, rather than making an essentialist claim that <q>Digital Humanities is
                        defined by postfoundational method,</q> will constitute a contribution to
                    the developing digital humanities <soCalled>agenda.</soCalled>
                </p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Postfoundationalism, postindustrialism, and DH</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <note>I would like to thank Alan Liu for reading an early version of this article, and
                Julia Flanders and the anonymous <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> reviewers for
                their extensive and penetrating comments. All failures of interpretation and fact
                are the responsibility of the author. </note>
            <div>
                <head>Preparatory</head>
                <p>This article seeks to explore concepts of significance to the broader Humanities
                    community, and in so doing graft them into the main trunk of Digital Humanities
                    theory and method. This makes a position statement useful. The argument that
                    follows reflects an approach to Digital Humanities (and a view of Digital
                    Humanities) oriented towards the Humanities Computing tradition and what Patrick
                    Svensson would refer to as the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#svensson2010">technology as tool</quote>
                        <ptr target="#svensson2010" loc="24"/>
                    </cit> approach to the field. Because of this, it risks hypostasizing what is
                    only a thesis into a statement of intent, or worse, a totalizing claim that the
                    ground of our discipline is of a particular (rather than multivariate) nature.
                    That would be an unsupportable, and unproductive, approach. That said, it
                        <emph>is</emph> my hope that the article provides additional intellectual
                    justification for a turn to code-craft practices outlined at the Speaking in
                    Code workshop at the University of Virginia’s Scholars’ Lab in 2013 <ptr
                        target="#nowviskie2013"/>, and the adoption of a mindset broadly
                    commensurate with digital artisanship. That topic requires further exploration,
                    and is somewhat peripheral to this present article, but is important to keep in
                    mind: as a scholarly discipline we require conceptual anchors and an openness to
                    theories and methods borrowed from cognate disciplines, but in our daily
                    practice digital humanists are reminded of the importance of craft and the value
                    of tacit knowledge. It is my contention, even accepting my own rudimentary craft
                    skills, that this is where the discipline has the most to offer the broader
                    Humanities community. </p>
                <p>It is counter-productive, however, to ignore the field’s entanglement with
                    postindustrial culture, the rise of technocratic and neoliberal modes of
                    government, and the so-called <soCalled>crisis in the humanities</soCalled> that
                    has seen Humanities disciplines struggle with policy decisions weighted in favor
                    of Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) disciplines <ptr
                        target="#donoghue2008"/>
                    <ptr target="#menand2010"/>. Although a complex soup, this comprises the
                    post-World War Two cultural, intellectual and technological background to the
                    field: it is an important part of our heritage as a community. And while it is
                    perhaps of more interest to intellectual and cultural historians than digital
                    humanists per se, it provides essential context — even, perhaps, an ontological
                    ground — that is important to parse if we are to understand the purpose and
                    potential of the field. This is especially so if it is accepted that the <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#schmidt2013">crisis in the Humanities,</quote>
                    whether real or imagined <ptr target="#schmidt2013"/>, is related to deeper
                    epistemological problems connected to the relative value of scientific and
                    humanistic modes of knowledge creation. This issue touches on issues of
                    fundamental importance for the scholarly community: while there is none of the
                    sense of revolution that accompanied the <soCalled>culture wars</soCalled> of
                    the latter twentieth century, some scholars are questioning the binary
                    opposition of foundationalist and anti-foundationalist modes of knowledge
                    creation, symbolized most starkly in logical positivism on the one hand and
                    postmodern relativism on the other. This paper follows G.B. Madison <ptr
                        target="#madison1991"/>, J. Wentzel Van Huyssteen <ptr
                        target="#vanhuyssteen2000"/>, Paul Healy <ptr target="#healy2005"/>
                    <ptr target="#healy2007"/>, Dimitri Ginev <ptr target="#ginev2001"/>
                    <ptr target="#ginev2007"/>, and Mark Bevir <ptr target="#bevir2011a"/>
                    <ptr target="#bevir2011b"/> in labeling this effort
                        <soCalled>postfoundationalism.</soCalled>
                </p>
                <p>These writers are searching for a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#healy2007">non-defeatist</quote>
                        <ptr target="#healy2007" loc="137"/>
                    </cit> epistemological stance, one that rejects Cartesian foundationalism as
                    unattainable but remains capable of underwriting <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#madison1991">the truth-value of our
                            interpretations</quote>
                        <ptr target="#madison1991" loc="23"/>
                    </cit>. The issue speaks to a broader impulse to seek methods that are <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#madison1991">
                            <emph>neither</emph> foundationalist <emph>nor</emph> relativist</quote>
                        <ptr target="#madison1991" loc="24"/>
                    </cit>, but still capable of advancing knowledge. In his recent book on the use
                    of the R programming language for literary study, digital humanist Matthew
                    Jockers touched on something similar when he noted that methods described in his
                    book reflect a post-Popperian stance somewhere <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#jockers2013">between strict positivism and
                            strict relativism</quote>
                        <ptr target="#jockers2013" loc="viii"/>
                    </cit>. Jocker’s mention of post-positivism represents an important statement
                    given its associations with method in the hard and social sciences, and is
                    deserving of further exploration, but it is outside the scope of this article.
                    Post-positivism does indeed hold significant opportunities for digital humanists
                    working with methods derived from or closely associated to the computer and
                    social sciences, but the argument that follows treads a fine line between
                    researchers like Jockers whose work draws them towards methods prominent in
                    those consciously <soCalled>scientific</soCalled> disciplines, and others who
                    are more focused on cultural theory and critique. Its goal is to explore the
                    possibilities inherent in a <soCalled>bridging</soCalled> concept
                    (postfoundationalism) that might work equally well for all sectors of the
                    community. If successful it will be broadly agreeable to both ends of our
                    disciplinary spectrum; if unsuccessful it may well disappoint all parties. </p>
                <p>Because of its engagement with issues of epistemology and method, there is a need
                    to navigate terrain familiar to historians of ideas: on the one hand the
                    argument must avoid the kind of <quote rend="inline" source="#grafton2006"
                        >unit-ideas</quote> approach, popular with mid-twentieth century historians
                    like A.O. Lovejoy, which enumerates ideas as a record of in-group culture <ptr
                        target="#grafton2006" loc="2–3"/>, and on the other it must not assume to
                    comprehend the <quote rend="inline" source="#burns2006">inside</quote> of
                    actors’ minds <ptr target="#burns2006"/>
                    <ptr target="#olsen1993"/>. These methodological issues are considerable, and
                    the article’s conclusions should certainly be weighed against them, but if
                    comments like Jockers’ reveal a dawning orientation for the field as a whole
                    there are many threads to pull: intellectual, cultural, historical as well as
                    theoretical and methodological. It will be enough if this present article is
                    agreed to be a useful contribution to that process.</p>
                <p>Another problem is, of course, that any analysis of the digital humanities must
                    traverse vast distances. Brett Bobley, CIO and Director of the U.S. National
                    Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) Office of Digital Humanities (ODH), has
                    presented a fabulously broad definition of the field that illustrates this issue
                    well: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#gavin2012">I use <q>digital humanities</q> as
                            an umbrella term for a number of different activities that surround
                            technology and humanities scholarship. Under the digital humanities
                            rubric, I would include topics like open access to materials,
                            intellectual property rights, tool development, digital libraries, data
                            mining, born-digital preservation, multimedia publication,
                            visualization, GIS, digital reconstruction, study of the impact of
                            technology on numerous fields, technology for teaching and learning,
                            sustainability models, media studies, and many others.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#gavin2012" loc="61"/>
                    </cit> This is well and good and, ignoring for the moment people who would
                    strongly disagree with such a broad statement, useful in its Catholicism. But it
                    makes the task of <quote rend="inline" source="#terras2013">defining the digital
                        humanities</quote> difficult <ptr target="#terras2013"/>. Even if there is
                    no great desire to define a <soCalled>discipline</soCalled> in the traditional
                    sense of the term, the field needs to find intellectual levers that can make
                    sense of a very broad definitional continuum, and explain to stakeholders what
                    DH is, how it is connected to the current difficulties encountered by the
                    humanities, how it is connected to broader postindustrial culture, and how
                    technical DH outputs should be assessed. Without answers to these issues the
                    field is unlikely to gain either high levels of student engagement, or a portion
                    of increasingly competitive funding sources. </p>
                <p>Postfoundationalism is one such intellectual lever, but the centrality of it to
                    this article should not suggest it is universally applicable, or unproblematic
                    as a concept and label: it could perhaps sit under <q>P</q> alongside hundreds
                    of other similar concepts in a <title rend="italic">Dictionary of DH
                        Terms</title>, but it is enough to hope that it can serve the purposes of
                    this article and provide entry to the conceptual domain I aim to navigate. It
                    will not be useful for all digital humanists, or be applicable to all DH
                    practices. It certainly shouldn’t be accepted uncritically as a <q>unit-idea</q> in the Lovejoyian
                    sense. It is, however, well-suited to an exploration of the epistemological
                    implications of Svensson’s <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#svensson2010">technology as tool</quote>
                        <ptr target="#svensson2010" loc="24"/>
                    </cit> approach to the digital humanities, which focuses on building digital
                    outputs ahead of engaging in more traditional humanistic pursuits related to
                    interpretation and critique. Because of this the <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#millar2011">technology as tool</quote> approach tends to produce
                    non-traditional scholarly outputs like web archives, ontologies, data models,
                    and suchlike. Indeed, much of what follows is informed by development of the UC
                    CEISMIC Canterbury Earthquakes Digital Archive and the search to find robust
                    arguments to make technical work like this count as <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#millar2011">research</quote>
                    <ptr target="#millar2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#millar2012"/>.</p>
                <p>Justifying non-traditional humanities work to academic administrators can be a
                    challenging task, which isn’t helped by the relative lack of conceptual work
                    across the community. Jan Christoph Meister has suggested that <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#meister2012">the amount of energy that our community
                        invests into theoretical and methodological critique of its practices and
                        their limitations is still disproportionally low,</quote> resulting in a
                    lack of understanding about what a <quote rend="inline" source="#meister2012"
                        >shared methodology</quote> for the field might look like <ptr
                        target="#meister2012"/>. Meister’s comment is perhaps slightly out of date
                    given the recent debates related to <soCalled>defining DH</soCalled> (one of
                    which will be examined in detail later in this paper), and it ignores
                    significant conceptual work undertaken by projects like the United Kingdom’s
                    AHRC funded ICT Methods Network (AHRC 2005 – 2008) and various communities of
                    practice (TEI, manuscript studies, epigraphy, computational linguistics) but his
                    underlying premise remains valid. There is a need to explain in scholarly terms
                    what key concepts carry weight for digital humanists, and how the field and its
                    associated theories, methods, practices, and outputs relate to broader currents
                    in intellectual culture. It is only by positioning the field in the context of
                    broader scholarly discourses and processes driving the contemporary academic
                    knowledge economy — by defining a <soCalled>shared methodology</soCalled> — that
                    a solid claim can be made for long-term institutional investment in it. </p>
                <p>This article therefore articulates a view of the digital humanities that hopes to
                    advance the discipline across broad academic and scholarly contexts. It will
                    succeed in its aims if it is both comprehensible to newcomers and stimulating
                    for experienced practitioners: a <soCalled>bridging</soCalled> effort, but one
                    undertaken with serious intent. It proceeds by isolating a key debate for
                    examination, describing two concepts that go a significant distance to solving
                    issues raised by that debate (but not far enough), and exploring the theoretical
                    writings of a selection of high profile digital humanists. The goal (a
                    non-trivial undertaking) is to illustrate the utility of postfoundationalism as
                    a conceptual tool, its interdependence with postindustrial culture, and the
                    light it sheds on our understanding of what <q>DH</q> is. If successful, the
                    article, rather than making an essentialist claim that <q>Digital Humanities is
                        defined by postfoundational method,</q> will constitute a contribution to
                    the developing digital humanities <soCalled>agenda</soCalled>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#mahoney2004">A field’s agenda consists of what
                            its practitioners agree ought to be done, a consensus concerning the
                            field’s problems, their order of importance, the means of solving them
                            (the tools of the trade), and perhaps most importantly, what constitutes
                            a solution. Becoming a recognized practitioner means learning the agenda
                            and helping to carry it out.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mahoney2004" loc="9"/>
                    </cit>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The DH Moment</head>
                <p>In his introduction to <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities</title>, <title rend="quotes">The Digital Humanities
                        Moment,</title> Matthew Gold notes that the practice has <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#gold2012">arrived amid larger questions
                            concerning the nature and purpose of the university system</quote>
                        <ptr target="#gold2012" loc="ix"/>
                    </cit>. As the discipline develops, these questions of cultural and intellectual
                    context are becoming both more relevant and more contested because, as insiders
                    to DH know, although multivariate the conversation returns to the same basic
                    issue again and again, making it difficult to explain (and therefore justify)
                    the field to university management. Some digital humanists view attempts to
                    divide practitioners into two separate camps as futile, but in practice it’s
                    easier to posit a simple binary opposition: if the field orients itself towards
                    text encoding, computer programming, and producing IT products it is presumed to
                    need to align towards the sciences, engineering, and empirically-oriented
                    humanities and social sciences; if it orients itself towards Theory it is
                    presumed to need to align towards literary and cultural studies. The reality is
                    far more complex than that (text encoding is a classic example, where technical
                    issues are inextricably tied to both theory and knowledge context), but it is a
                    level of complexity that’s difficult to convey to senior scholars and peers in
                    cognate disciplines and service areas, so the dichotomy assumes more
                    significance than it deserves. </p>
                <p>There are some indications that the global community is incapable of pointing the
                    way to a workable compromise. Patrik Svensson has suggested that DH is a <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#svensson2011">twenty-first-century humanities project
                        driven by frustration, dissatisfaction, epistemic tension, everyday
                        practice, technological vision, disciplinary challenges, institutional
                        traction, hope, ideals and strong visions</quote> — hardly a situation
                    conducive to clear articulations of intellectual purpose and antecedent <ptr
                        target="#svensson2011" loc="42"/>. Alan Liu has admitted that he fears: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#liu2011a">the digital humanities are not ready
                            to take up their full responsibility [to reinvigorate the Humanities]
                            because the field does not yet possess an adequate critical awareness of
                            the larger social, economic, and cultural issues at stake.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#liu2011a" loc="11"/>
                    </cit> Liu’s argument is that this unpreparedness stems from a general
                    resistance to theorizing the deeper cultural significance of the discipline
                    across the DH community, in favor of building tools, systems and websites, and
                    programming code <ptr target="#liu2011b"/>. Manfred Thaller probably wouldn’t
                    agree with that sentiment, but appears similarly frustrated about the
                    long-standing tension in the digital humanities over whether the discipline has <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#thaller2012">an intellectual agenda or […]
                            constitute[s] an infrastructure</quote>
                        <ptr target="#thaller2012" loc="20"/>
                    </cit>. In sanguine voice Willard McCarty has pointed out that <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#mccarty2012">…complaints of stagnation and
                        theoretical poverty…</quote> have followed the discipline since at least
                    1962 <ptr target="#mccarty2012" loc="27"/>. It is worth remembering in this
                    context that the older humanities computing tradition was not associated with
                    what could be termed the <soCalled>main currents</soCalled> of late twentieth
                    century intellectual culture. The heated debate surrounding Robert William Fogel
                    and Stanley L. Engerman’s <title rend="italic">Time on the Cross: The Economics
                        of American Negro Slavery</title> (1974) provides one example of how it
                    could become enmeshed in topical debates (in this case around cliometrics, or
                    the use of quantification in economic history), but humanities computing was not
                    known for its engagement with high-profile intellectual trends. Analysis of the
                        <title rend="italic">Humanist</title> email seminar, run by Willard McCarty
                    since 1987, backs this up <ptr target="#rockwellsinclair2012"/>. </p>
                <p>This has changed in recent years as significant numbers of newcomers have joined
                    the community, resulting in sometimes-heated debates between those supporting a
                        <soCalled>traditional</soCalled> humanities computing perspective based on
                        <soCalled>technology as tool,</soCalled> and those supporting the broader
                    definition enabled by the ODH. The recent DH <soCalled>theory debate</soCalled>
                    is a case in point, and the example I have chosen to illustrate the utility of
                    postfoundationalism as a critical tool. While it is only one of several issues
                    that could be explored, it has been chosen here because it exposes a
                    particularly troubling issue. The discussion exposed the fault lines that
                    resulted from the rapid development of the humanities computing tradition into a
                    broader state-sanctioned <q>Digital Humanities</q> field in the United States.
                    While the locus of the debate was centered in the U.S., it resonated around the
                    international community and has particular significance for the field as it
                    expands into new regions of the world. </p>
                <p>The debate’s basic elements are well rehearsed. It took place over the course of
                    two years, and was conducted primarily amongst North American university-based
                    digital humanists. In an influential talk describing digital humanists’ values,
                    given at the CUNY Digital Humanities Initiative in 2010, Tom Scheinfeldt didn’t
                    mention theory, emphasizing coding and Do It Yourself (DIY) instead <ptr
                        target="#scheinfeldt2010"/>. At the time his emphasis seemed unproblematic.
                    At the 2011 MLA conference in Los Angeles, however, Stephen Ramsay put a finer
                    point on the issue by asking: <quote rend="block" source="#ramsay2011c">Do
                        you have to know how to code? I’m a tenured professor of digital humanities
                        and I say <said>yes.</said>
                    </quote> He followed up by opining: <quote rend="block"
                        source="#ramsay2011c">But if you are not making anything, you are not
                        — in my less-than-three-minute opinion — a digital humanist.</quote> Ramsay
                    later softened his position, and has produced his own significant contribution
                    to digital literary theory, but his comment brought a challenging vein of
                    digital humanities discourse into the light of day. Some people were angered,
                    and felt that such a <soCalled>brazen</soCalled> attitude opened up a space for
                    them to air mounting grievances. The assumption was that Ramsay’s comment
                    betrayed a lingering prejudice across the discipline that equated the ability to
                    write computer code with hostility to Theory. This may or may not have been an
                    unjust conflation, but for whatever reason the association of coding with
                    anti-theoretical prejudice had become a touchstone issue. </p>
                <p>It’s easy for people outside the United States to forget that Alan Liu delivered
                    a paper at not only the same MLA conference as Ramsay, but also the same panel
                        <ptr target="#liuetal2011"/>. Titled <title rend="quotes">Where is Cultural
                        Criticism in the Digital Humanities?</title>
                    <ptr target="#liu2011b"/>, it suggested that this cherished focus on <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#liu2011b">more hack, less yack</quote> (focusing on
                    text encoding and computer programming at the expense of theory and cultural
                    criticism) threatened to throw away a crucial opportunity for digital humanists,
                    their students, and the wider tradition. Later in 2011 and the early months of
                    2012 the topic yielded one of the richest intellectual debates outside <title
                        rend="italic">Humanist </title>in the history of the discipline. The debate
                    was prompted by a blog post by a young American scholar, Natalia Cecire, who
                    disagreed with <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#cecire2011a">the zero-sum logic that it [an
                            emphasis on coding] implies</quote>
                        <ptr target="#cecire2011a"/>
                    </cit>. Primed by a year’s worth of discussion resulting from Ramsay and Liu’s
                    comments at the MLA in January, a slew of posts and tweets on the topic
                    dominated digital humanities discourse for several weeks, before petering out
                    with a return to the status quo: hack over yack. Most digital humanists, it
                    seems, agreed with Tom Scheinfeldt, who tweeted that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#scheinfeldt2011">DH arguments are encoded in
                            code. I disagree with the notion that those arguments must be translated
                            / re-encoded in text</quote>
                        <ptr target="#scheinfeldt2011"/>
                    </cit>. </p>
                <p>Perhaps in an acceptance that the time had come to provide a scholarly forum for
                    the debate, the first issue of the partially crowd-sourced <title rend="italic"
                        >Journal of Digital Humanities</title>, produced by George Mason
                    University’s Roy Rosenzweig Centre for History and New Media in late 2011, was
                    devoted to the Theory problem. Natalia Cecire was invited to provide an
                    introduction, where she claimed that the hack versus yack divide had sundered
                    the connection between <quote rend="inline" source="#cecire2011b">saying and
                        doing.</quote> Cecire claimed that <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#cecire2011b">hacking</quote> represented a dominant discourse
                    across the discipline that celebrated tacit knowledge and valued only <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#cecire2011b">embodied, experiential,
                            extradiscursive epistemology” at the expense of deeper philosophical,
                            ethical, and economic issues</quote>
                        <ptr target="#cecire2011b"/>
                    </cit>. Although a far less emotive (and important) topic, it wasn’t unlike the
                    accusations directed at cliometricians like Fogel in the previous century: a
                    claim that positivism, and especially scientism masquerading as post-positivism,
                    becomes anathema to the Humanities when it excludes more traditional methods. In
                    her piece, Jean Bauer openly stated that she was <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#bauer2011">insulted</quote> by these kinds of comments, which she
                    felt betrayed a lack of understanding about the design decisions required for DH
                    products <ptr target="#bauer2011"/>. Several other contributions were similarly
                    forthright in their defense of tacit knowledge. Fred Gibbs came closest to
                    mediating a way forward by simply pointing out that <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#gibbs2011">[p]art of what defines a discipline is the rhetoric
                        and aesthetics of its scholarly discourse</quote> and there are very real
                    practical needs for the development of DH-specific discourse, in order to
                    evaluate scholarly outputs and engage in other normal administrative tasks <ptr
                        target="#gibbs2011"/>. Perhaps the most effective contribution (and
                    certainly the most concise) to that first issue of the <title rend="italic"
                        >Journal of Digital Humanities</title> was offered in <title rend="quotes"
                        >Word and Code</title>, jointly authored by Tom Scheinfeldt and Ryan Shaw.
                    It consisted merely of Scheinfeldt’s tweet and Shaw’s reply: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#scheinfeldtshaw2011">
                            <p>DH arguments are encoded in code. I disagree with the notion that
                                those arguments must be translated / re-encoded in text.</p>
                            <p>
                                <ref target="https://twitter.com/foundhistory"
                                    >@foundhistory</ref> <ref target="https://twitter.com/ncecire"
                                    >@ncecire</ref> If you can't explain to me in words how your
                                code works, you don't really know how it works.</p>
                        </quote>
                        <ptr target="#scheinfeldtshaw2011"/>
                    </cit> The two tweets provided a summation of the hack versus yack debate in 280
                    characters, with a substantial dose of irony. </p>
                <p>What’s missing here, crucially, is that the theory debate prompted by Cecire
                    probably only represented the further development within the U.S. digital
                    humanities movement (itself containing digital history, digital literary studies
                    etc.) of digital cultural studies, an event that had been presaged by the
                    pre-existence of digital media studies <ptr target="#mcpherson2009"/>, and
                    should have been welcomed as a sophisticated addition to the field. The fact
                    that it wasn’t points to one of the fundamental weaknesses in the movement:
                    consistent recourse to a category error that conflates the contributing fields
                    of the digital humanities with the (extra)discipline itself. The problem usually
                    appears with the conflation of DH with digital literary studies, rather than
                    digital cultural studies, to the point where it sometimes seems as if English
                    departments are <soCalled>taking over</soCalled> the field to the detriment of
                    digital history, classics and so on. Mathew G. Kirshenbaum devoted an essay to
                    the issue in 2010. Titled <title rend="quotes">What Is Digital humanities and
                        What’s It Doing in English Departments?,</title> the piece noted that
                    English departments have <quote rend="inline" source="#kirschenbaum2010"
                        >historically been hospitable settings</quote> for scholars interested in
                    humanities computing, because of their natural interest in text analysis and
                    publishing <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2010" loc="5"/>. Kirschenbaum was quite
                    right in noting this can only be a positive thing given the need for
                    institutional support, but DH has also been well supported in History and
                    Classics departments and it would be improper (and perhaps even absurd) for
                    English departments to claim special ownership of the field. If this was to
                    happen there would not only be confusion about what DH is, but digital
                    historians and classists (etc.) might become unwittingly mired in the famously
                    heated debates characteristic of literary studies.</p>
                <p>This was precisely what happened when Stanley Fish <ptr target="#fish2011"/>,
                        <ptr target="#fish2012a"/>, <ptr target="#fish2012b"/> and later Stephen
                    Marche <ptr target="#marche2012"/> wrote essays objecting to the digital
                    humanities in the <title rend="italic">New York Times</title> and <title
                        rend="italic">LA Times</title> respectively. It could be that they were
                    hoping to prompt a campaign of <term xml:lang="la">apologia pro vita sua</term>
                    against DH, as Anthony Daniels has admitted to savoring <ptr
                        target="#daniels2012"/>, but they were ill-served by their sources. Both
                    writers, after presumably cursory research into the digital humanities, assumed
                    that digital humanities equated to digital literary criticism and proceeded to
                    damn the entire subject-area for the (perceived) sins of this one contributing
                    area. Their argument against digital humanities revolved around the lack of
                    benefit in quantitative text analysis rather than the utility of historical GIS,
                    concordances of ancient texts, digital variorums, or transcriptions of
                    philosophical writings. If people involved in digital literary studies were
                    perplexed at the hostility, digital humanists from other fields were left
                    wondering why eminent literary scholars were damning their field without seeming
                    to know their specific area of it even existed. A cursory glance at the book of
                    abstracts for the primary ADHO conference would have alerted Fish et al. to
                    their mistake. In many ways it was an embarrassment for American literary
                    studies, as some of their finest betrayed a tendency to engage in heated
                    polemics in ignorance of elementary facts. The problem continued at the 2013 MLA
                    conference, with one panel discussion, titled <title rend="quotes">The Dark Side
                        of the Digital Humanities</title>
                    <ptr target="#chun2013"/> generating ire for its participants’ conflation of DH
                    with the recent trends towards Massive Open Online Courses, or MOOCS, which
                    digital humanists have been largely uninterested in (the topic is of more
                    interest to people interested in eLearning) <ptr target="#pannapacker2013"/>. </p>
                <p>Category errors like these, perhaps better described through reference to the
                    parable of the blind men and the elephant, do indeed speak to an under-theorized
                    discipline: one that undermines external perceptions and internal cohesion, and
                    suggests that the field doesn’t quite know what it is. Given he has watched
                    digital humanists debating the same issue for several decades it’s telling that
                    Willard McCarty wondered in 2012 whether debates like these indicate <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mccarty2012">…immaturity and lack of outward
                            reach…</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mccarty2012" loc="62"/>
                    </cit> characteristic of the discipline as a whole. To some observers, and
                    despite a large number of blog posts and even a THATCamp unconference devoted to
                    the topic <ptr target="#thatcamp2012"/>, it seems to some observers as if the
                    discipline is stuck in a Becktian moment <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#riederandrohle2012">…where the advocates of
                            computation and interpretation are locked in a dichotomous
                            opposition</quote>
                        <ptr target="#riederandrohle2012" loc="80"/>
                    </cit>. </p>
                <p>And yet Scheinfeldt’s tweet points to a way out of the situation. In distilling
                    decades of debate into 140 characters it presents us with a nicely reductive
                    place to initiate analysis. Contra Cecire’s claim that it amounts to zero-sum
                    logic or a <term xml:lang="la">felix culpa</term>, the implication I draw is
                    that fundamental disciplinary truths must reside <emph>inside</emph> this
                    tautology: <q>DH arguments are encoded in code. I disagree with the notion that
                        those arguments must be translated / re-encoded in text.</q> Wittgenstein
                    might claim Scheinfeldt’s comment simultaneously says nothing and opens up a
                    whole world of interpretation. The key, of course, is finding the right tools to
                    explore this strange new world. Ultimately, of course, this article will argue
                    that postfoundationalism is one of the most satisfactory tools we have at our
                    disposal to understand it, especially when considered in the context of
                    postindustrial culture. In order to understand why, we must explore two slightly
                    less satisfactory concepts first.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Immanence</head>
                <p>It is a fruitless exercise to imply that the digital humanities are incapable of
                    leading us towards intellectual depths as American literary critics like Fish
                    and Marche have, or that the entire field should adopt the theoretical
                    perspectives of one of its contributing disciplines (or, indeed, the theoretical
                    debates of one of its contributing countries). The knowledge domain is too
                    different from anything we’ve encountered before, and study of it too limited,
                    for us to understand what its intellectual potential might be, let alone decide
                    today what its central preoccupations should be for years into the future: it
                    is, and has been for several decades, in development. This paper suggests that,
                    given examples like that outlined above, digital humanists need to continue
                    developing a set of conceptual tools capable of exploring, in the first instance
                    at least, the hackers’ tautological stance towards code. </p>
                <p>It’s easy enough to see why digital humanists have been having the same
                    conversation for decades. Despite the fact that it brings us up against some
                    difficult hermeneutic issues, code is at once our tool, our historical record,
                    and the basis of our theoretical canon. We cannot get away from it. By
                    extension, an understanding of code (the precise level of understanding is yet
                    to be defined) must be, along with knowledge of the humanities themselves, a
                        <term xml:lang="la">sine qua non</term> of entry to the field. Louis Menand
                    would no doubt suggest that we are isolating this aspect of our practice as a
                    means of <quote rend="inline" source="#menand2010">exceeding [our] own
                        history,</quote> as a way of defining borders and laying claim to long-term
                    existence within the academy in the same way that historians, literature
                    professors and lawyers did before us <ptr target="#menand2010" loc="116"/>. The
                    question isn’t so much whether we are going to make such a stand, and what we’re
                    going to make it over, as to whether we have the critical tools to make the
                    stand meaningful to our peers in neighboring disciplines, and administrators
                    requesting justification for continued support. In order to do this we need to
                    start with simple concepts and move outwards: first
                        <soCalled>immanence</soCalled>, then the <soCalled>epistemology of
                        building.</soCalled>
                </p>
                <p>For the <soCalled>hacking</soCalled> branch of the DH community, then, which
                    appears to me to be the obviously (and appropriately) dominant branch of the
                    discipline, computer code is immanent. The Software Studies and Critical Code
                    communities (themselves part of the DH community in the broader definition
                    offered by Brett Bobley) have done considerable work on this subject <ptr
                        target="#manovich2001"/>; <ptr target="#manovich2013"/>; <ptr
                        target="#mackenzie2006"/>; <ptr target="#fuller2008"/>; <ptr
                        target="#montfort2012"/>, but in simple terms it is easy to illustrate what
                    this means. One of the signal DH publications of 2011 used facial recognition to
                        <soCalled>recover</soCalled> the public identities of thousands of
                    nineteenth-century Chinese Australian immigrants previously hidden in a massive
                    archival stack at the National Archives of Australia. Tim Sherratt’s single
                    webpage, titled <title rend="italic">the real face of white Australia</title>
                    <ptr target="#sherratt2011a"/>, is self-explanatory. The real interest for
                    digital humanists was in his accompanying explanatory blog post <ptr
                        target="#sherratt2011b"/>, and the two Python scripts he posted on his
                    public Github account <ptr target="#sherratt2009"/>. </p>

                <dhq:example>
                    <head>Script 1. extract_faces.py</head>
                    <eg>#!/usr/bin/python # Loop through images and feed to facial detection script
                        import os import face_detect #rootdir =
                        "/home/tim/mycode/recordsearch/src/recordsearchtools/files/E752" rootdir =
                        "/home/tim/mycode/recordsearch/src/recordsearchtools/files/ST84-1" #rootdir
                        = "/home/tim/mycode/recordsearch/src/recordsearchtools/files/test" #rootdir
                        =
                        "/home/tim/mycode/recordsearch/src/recordsearchtools/files/ST84-1/1907-391-400-[1731871]"
                        for root, dirs, files in os.walk(rootdir, topdown=True): for file in files:
                        print 'Processing %s' % file face_detect.process_image(os.path.join(root,
                        file))</eg>
                </dhq:example>


                <dhq:example>
                    <head>Script 2. face_detect.py</head>
                    <eg>#!/usr/bin/python # face_detect.py # Face Detection using OpenCV. Based on
                        script at: #
                        http://creatingwithcode.com/howto/face-detection-in-static-images-with-python/
                        # Usage: python face_detect.py [image filename] import sys,os from opencv.cv
                        import * from opencv.highgui import * from PIL import Image, ImageOps
                        CLASSIFIER =
                        '/usr/share/doc/opencv-doc/examples/haarcascades/haarcascade_frontalface_default.xml'
                        CROP_DIR = '/home/tim/mycode/recordsearch/src/recordsearchtools/files/crops'
                        def detect_objects(fn, image): """Detects faces and then crops the image."""
                        #grayscale = cvCreateImage(cvSize(image.width, image.height), 8, 1)
                        #cvCvtColor(image, grayscale, CV_BGR2GRAY) storage = cvCreateMemStorage(0)
                        cvClearMemStorage(storage) #cvEqualizeHist(grayscale, grayscale) cascade =
                        cvLoadHaarClassifierCascade(CLASSIFIER, cvSize(1,1)) faces =
                        cvHaarDetectObjects(image, cascade, storage, 1.3, 3,
                        CV_HAAR_DO_CANNY_PRUNING, cvSize(20,20)) if faces: i = 1 for f in faces:
                        #newfn = fn + ".output.jpg" #os.system("convert %s -stroke red -fill none
                        -draw 'rectangle %d,%d %d,%d' %s" % (fn, f.x, f.y, f.x+f.width,
                        f.y+f.height, newfn)) #os.system("mv %s %s.orig" % (fn, fn)) #os.system("mv
                        %s %s" % (newfn, fn)) #print("[(%d,%d) -&gt; (%d,%d)]" % (f.x, f.y,
                        f.x+f.width, f.y+f.height)) file, ext = os.path.splitext(fn) im =
                        Image.open(fn) # Increase selected area by 50px on each side then crop im =
                        im.crop((f.x-50, f.y-50, f.x+f.width+50, f.y+f.height+50)) # Minor contrast
                        adjustment im = ImageOps.autocontrast(im, cutoff=0.5) im.load() crop =
                        '%s/%s_crop_%s.jpg' % (CROP_DIR, os.path.basename(file), i) im.save(crop,
                        "JPEG") check_crop(crop) i += 1 def check_crop(crop): """Try to reduce false
                        positives by doing a second pass and deleting images that fail.""" image =
                        cvLoadImage(crop); storage = cvCreateMemStorage(0)
                        cvClearMemStorage(storage) cascade = cvLoadHaarClassifierCascade(CLASSIFIER,
                        cvSize(1,1)) faces = cvHaarDetectObjects(image, cascade, storage, 1.3, 3,
                        CV_HAAR_DO_CANNY_PRUNING, cvSize(20,20)) if faces: if faces[0] is None:
                        os.remove(crop) else: os.remove(crop) def process_image(fn): image =
                        cvLoadImage(fn); detect_objects(fn, image) def main(): image =
                        cvLoadImage(sys.argv[1]); detect_objects(sys.argv[1], image) if __name__ ==
                        "__main__": main() </eg>
                </dhq:example>
                <p>For a DH <soCalled>hacker</soCalled> these scripts are rich in humanist detail,
                    from the cultural phenomenon that is Github, to the problems posed by finding
                    and visualizing sources within very large datasets, to the open source code
                    movement that underpins DH and prompted Sherratt to post the code in an online
                    forum, to the referencing of the scripts he used (not only due to licensing
                    requirements but to show his colleagues how <soCalled>easy</soCalled> his task
                    was, using code from <ref target="http://opencv.org/">http://opencv.org/</ref>
                    and adapting it to his purpose). This isn’t to mention the background to the
                    Python scripting language, its suitability for entry-level programming and its
                    widespread adoption and centrality to early 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>
                    century digital products. And like coffee stains in a book margin, we find in
                    the extract_faces.py configuration script references to
                        <code>"/home/tim/mycode</code>, suggesting the work was done not on a
                    proprietary Windows or OSX operating system, but on an open source Linux
                    machine. If the term <q>code</q> is read in even broader terms than this, as a
                    metaphor for a thorough-going understanding of how digital culture is engineered
                    (data architecture and packetization, the nature of databases and networks, the
                    nature of programming languages etc.) it is possible to see even more
                    possibilities, at the point where DH intersects with not only computer science,
                    but the History of Technology, Software Studies, and Science and Technology
                    Studies (STS). In <title rend="italic">10 PRINT CHR$(205.5+RND(1)); : GOTO
                        10</title> Nick Montfort et al. point out that attempts like these, to
                    position <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#montfort2012">the program’s output in a space
                            of symbolic meanings and design principles…</quote>
                        <ptr target="#montfort2012" loc="49"/>
                    </cit> offer rich new interpretative possibilities, but it is equally important
                    to recognize that at some level source code will always remain impenetrable, or <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#chun2011">spectral</quote>
                        <ptr target="#chun2011" loc="24"/>
                    </cit>. Such is the complexity of modern computing that it has become impossible
                    for a single person — even the author (in the event there is a single author) —
                    to grasp what’s going on as functions are called, libraries unpacked, and
                    voltage levels set within logic gates. The reading above ignores these issues
                    and the mechanics of the code itself, but it perhaps indicates some of the
                    mountainous interpretative possibilities inherent in the lines of code being
                    created by digital humanists. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Epistemology of Building</head>
                <p>While the immanence of computer code provides justification to scholars involved
                    in Software Studies, and digital humanists aware that field is either cognate or
                    part of the broader <soCalled>tent</soCalled> depending on their definitional
                    stance, it doesn’t provide a lot of justification for digital humanists seeking
                    evidence that the more technical kinds of digital humanities outputs should be
                    accepted for scholarly assessment. It either relies on techniques of source
                    criticism practiced by a range of humanist disciplines, or merely states the
                    obvious point that people who can write code can also read and interpret it. In
                    order to justify technical outputs as worthy of assessment digital humanists
                    would be more advised to refer to an approach once outlined by Willard McCarty
                    in <title rend="italic">Humanities Computing</title> (2005), augmented by
                    comments in <title rend="italic">Humanist</title> and journal articles <ptr
                        target="#mccarty2008"/>
                    <ptr target="#mccarty2012"/>. </p>
                <p>McCarty’s comments may well represent <soCalled>first use,</soCalled> but my
                    purpose here is not to establish an eponymous origin. My purpose is to suggest
                    that his cognitive stance has become so widespread it represents a
                        <soCalled>habit of mind</soCalled> or, <term xml:lang="fr">mentalité</term>,
                    that reflects the goals and aspirations of a significant portion of the
                    community, including Franco Moretti (2005), Julia Flanders (2009; 2012), Galey
                    and Ruecker (2010), Ramsay and Rockwell (2012) and several others. The
                    implications of the stance are fascinating. In extended commentaries later
                    encapsulated in Scheinfeldt’s epigrammatic tweet, McCarty suggests that theories
                    of computer coding, modeling and design are capable of providing an
                    epistemological basis for the digital humanities; that rather than being mere
                    by-products of the development process, they <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#galeyandruecker2010">contain arguments that
                            advance knowledge about the world</quote>
                        <ptr target="#galeyandruecker2010" loc="406"/>
                    </cit>. The argument proffered is that the need to create models of reality
                    (ontologies, database schemas, algorithms and so on), required to allow
                    computers to mathematically parse problems posed by their human operators,
                    offers a radical new methodological basis for future humanities research. Rather
                    than being merely an indication of computers’ inability to accommodate the
                    complexities of human thought and emotion, and by extension historical reality,
                    the suggestion is that the very inadequacies of the models — their propensity to
                    be radically inadequate, or at best only broadly reliable — suggest a new way of
                    looking at the world that is at once accepting of failure, more in tune with
                    scientific method, and oriented towards <emph>process</emph> instead of Truth: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#mccarty2005">Computational form, which accepts
                            only that which can be told with programmatic explicitness and
                            precision, is thus radically inadequate for representing the full range
                            of knowledge — hence useful for locating what gets lost when we try to
                            specify the unspecifiable.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mccarty2005" loc="25"/>
                    </cit> Ramsay and Rockwell interpret this to mean that we need to develop a
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ramsayandrockwell2012">humanistically
                        informed theory of the <emph>making</emph> of technology,</quote> an
                    epistemology of building that provides scholarly justification for DH outputs in
                    a way that makes sense to our peers in cognate disciplines <ptr
                        target="#ramsayandrockwell2012"/>. </p>
                <p>Although there are notable exceptions, such as McCarty’s modeling of Ovid’s
                        <title rend="italic">Metamorphosis</title>
                    <ptr target="#mccarty2005" loc="55–71"/>, the problem with attempts to define an
                    epistemology of building is that they threaten to float free of the broader
                    humanities tradition. Commentators like Liu and Cecire might argue that, as
                    Allen Tate said of the American Southern Critics, they are locked in the present
                    and cut off from the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#tate1957">benefit of the fund of traditional
                            wisdom</quote>
                        <ptr target="#tate1957" loc="325"/>
                    </cit> that has dealt with similar problems before. Without arguing specifically
                    for more critical or cultural theory, David Berry suggests something similar
                    when he comments that digital humanists need to problematize <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#berry2011">what Lakatos (1980) would have
                            called the <q>hard-core</q> of the humanities, the unspoken assumptions
                            and ontological foundations which support the ‘normal’ research that
                            humanities scholars undertake on an everyday basis.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#berry2011" loc="4"/>
                    </cit> Following this line of argument, which is a powerful one, arguments for
                    more or less critical or cultural theory are simply components of a larger
                    problem. The hack versus yack debate means little in the context of a
                    2000-year-old tradition, after all. This isn’t to criticize the many excellent
                    scholars who have contributed to the discipline over the decades, or to ignore
                    the growing body of work (much of it cited in this article) that suggests growth
                    towards what Lakatos terms the ‘hard-core’ humanities. Any digital humanist who
                    has spent a considerable amount of time staring at code to work out a particular
                    problem will understand why this is easier said than done: the conceptual divide
                    that separates Computer Science and the Humanities is large, and it is natural
                    to only think in one of the two paradigms at any one time. Digital humanists
                    need bridging concepts, or concepts that work just as well for the digital
                    humanities as their analog cousins — levers capable of raising our conceptual
                    understanding to new levels.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Postfoundationalism</head>
                <p>Postfoundationalism holds promise as one of these levers. Although it is only one
                    of several that will be required, it offers our nascent <soCalled>epistemology
                        of building</soCalled> a useful tool. Mark Bevir points out that for
                    historians postfoundationalism has the great benefit of avoiding the simplistic
                    anchoring of explanation in pre-determined <soCalled>facts</soCalled> as with
                    modernist discourse, or the dissolution of fact into fiction characteristic of
                    postmodernism. Postfoundationalism asserts that there is no point asserting
                    either more confidence in our understanding of reality than is justified (as
                    with modernism and logical empiricism) or retreating into a pessimistic view of
                    our ability to grasp any one reality at all (as with postmodernism and
                    postmodern deconstruction) <ptr target="#ginev2001" loc="28"/>. Rather, in a
                    claim that could perhaps be criticized for claiming to have cut the Gordian
                    knot, postfoundationalism <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#bevir2011a">reject[s] the possibility of facts
                            outside theoretical contexts. All knowledge incorporates both facts and
                            theories</quote>
                        <ptr target="#bevir2011a"/>
                    </cit>. It is an intellectual position that balances a distrust of grand
                    narrative with an acceptance that methods honed over centuries and supported by
                    independently verified evidence can lead, if not to Truth itself, then closer to
                    it than we were before. Philosopher of science Dimitri Ginev notes that
                    postfoundationalism offers both a <quote rend="inline" source="#ginev2001"
                        >hermeneutic ontology of existence and a hermeneutic theory of
                        historicity,</quote> and buttresses itself by asserting the validity of both
                    the research process <emph>and</emph> the outputs of that research process <ptr
                        target="#ginev2001" loc="28"/>. Revealingly, Paul Healy suggests that
                    postfoundational rationality aims to develop a <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#healy2007">situated learning</quote> process conducive to the
                    accretion of knowledge, rather than either positivist or relativist <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#healy2007">idealisations</quote>
                        <ptr target="#healy2007" loc="141"/>
                    </cit>. Its devotees hope that it is capable of moving human knowledge and
                    understanding beyond the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#liu2008">just in time, conflicted</quote>
                        <ptr target="#liu2008" loc="2"/>
                    </cit> postmodern historicism described by Alan Liu towards something equally
                    accepting of complexity, but more optimistic and empirically oriented. Healy
                    neatly summarizes the resulting communicative domain in terms of disciplines
                    embracing <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#healy2007">a robust context-transcendent truth
                            standard which, in virtue of preserving the ‘aporetic tension’ inherent
                            in the distinction between what is true and what we hold to be true,
                            suffices to ensure that proffered knowledge claims are held open to
                            critical scrutiny in an indefinitely extended array of situated
                            forums.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#healy2007" loc="143"/>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p>The approach would seem to be well suited to a (trans)discipline like Digital
                    Humanities that runs the gamut from empirically oriented text analysis to the
                    development of database models and cultural critique. It could well be, because
                    it is a field so reliant on a similar hermeneutic, that the digital humanities
                    prove important to the development of postfoundationalism in the coming decades.
                    In straddling the humanities and computer science, and using methods derived
                    from fields as diverse as computational linguistics and sociology, its
                    practitioners are confronted with a need to re-envisage the nature and goals of
                    humanistic enquiry and method, in order to make sense of the radically different
                    questions they’re being confronted with. It makes sense to seek out different
                    new approaches to assist them in that task. Although it is essential that the
                    discipline looks to fields like computer science (and perhaps mathematics and
                    logic) before reinventing the wheel, the basic assumption must surely be that a
                    new problem domain is likely to require new theories as well as new methods. And
                    the parallels between emerging DH theory and postfoundationalism are easy to
                    illustrate. </p>
                <p>Few statements of method could suggest a postfoundational orientation better than
                    McCarty’s comment that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mccarty2005">computational models, however
                            finely perfect, are better understood as <emph>temporary states in a
                                process of coming to know</emph> rather than fixed structures of
                            knowledge</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mccarty2005" loc="27"/>
                    </cit>, or his later point that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#mccarty2008">the word <q>
                                <emph>computing</emph>
                            </q> is a participle — a verbal injunctive that turns things into
                            algorithmic performances</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mccarty2008" loc="254–255"/>
                    </cit>, requiring attention to an ongoing process of iterative modeling rather
                    than final outcomes. By meditating on the procedures involved in the production
                    of electronic texts, from the inscription of bits onto hard-drive platters, to
                    their abstraction in machine code, assembly language and higher level
                    programming languages, to presentation on our screens, Matthew G. Kirschenbaum
                    offers what could be seen as a postfoundationalist argument for critical
                    exegesis focused on process, <quote rend="inline" source="#kirschenbaum2007"
                        >propagation,</quote> and becoming, rather than the fixity of texts, screen,
                    or image: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#kirschenbaum2007">New media cannot be studied
                            apart from individual instances of inscription, object, and code as they
                            propagate on, across, and through storage devices, operating systems,
                            software environments, and network protocols …</quote>
                        <ptr target="#kirschenbaum2007" loc="63"/>
                    </cit> Such an interpretation works equally well for a writer like Stephen
                    Ramsay, who <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ramsay2011b">tries to locate a hermeneutics at
                            the boundary between mechanism and theory</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ramsay2011b" loc="x"/>
                    </cit>, pointing out that <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#ramsay2011b">[T]he stratum that we lodge
                            ourselves upon with algorithmic criticism is one in which both results
                            and the textual generation of results are systematically manipulated and
                            transformed, connected and reconnected with unlike things.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ramsay2011b" loc="63"/>
                    </cit> Peter Lunenfeld et al. suggest that the discipline needs to engage <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#lunefeld2012">with design as a method of
                        thinking-through-practice</quote>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#lunenfeld2012">Digital Humanities is a
                            production-based endeavor in which theoretical issues get tested in the
                            design of implementations, and implementations are loci of theoretical
                            reflection and elaboration.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#lunenfeld2012" loc="13"/>
                    </cit> Franco Moretti offers something similar when he notes that for him <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#moretti2005">[The map itself is not an]
                            explanation, of course: but at least, it offers a model of the narrative
                            universe which rearranges its components in a non-trivial way, and may
                            bring some hidden patterns to the surface.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#moretti2005" loc="53–54"/>
                    </cit> Extending the theme into the materialist world of the hard drive platters
                    and inscribed bits that mediate the manipulation of digitized sources, William
                    Turkel suggests digital humanists would be well-served to think <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#turkel2011">in terms of
                                <emph>transduction</emph>, the conversion of energy from one form to
                            another</quote>
                        <ptr target="#turkel2011" loc="287–296"/>
                    </cit>. In their introduction to the <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital
                        Humanities</title> special issue devoted to topic modeling, Elijah Meeks and
                    Scott Weingart note that: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#meeksandweingart2012">[I]n digital humanities
                            research we use tools, make tools, and theorize tools not because we are
                            all information scientists, but because tools are the formal
                            instantiation of methods.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#meeksandweingart2012" loc="5"/>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p>It would presumably be possible to find more examples, and others that adopt a
                    quite different stance, but in this article it is only my intention to draw
                    attention to a broad habit of mind or <term xml:lang="fr">mentalité</term> —
                    enough to justify further exploration — not to assert that postfoundationalism
                    should represent the definitional <term xml:lang="la">sine qua non </term>for
                    the field. That argument could perhaps be attempted, but it would require a
                    book-length study and even then be difficult to avoid regression into a
                    totalizing discourse. The point is more that the statements above suggest a
                    broadly accepted vision of interpretation as praxis as much as practice,
                    engagement with a process of continuous methodological and, yes, theoretical
                    refinement that produces research outputs as snapshots of an ongoing activity
                    rather than the culmination of <soCalled>completed</soCalled> research.
                    Postfoundationalism offers a way to package these impulses together momentarily,
                    in order to consider their collective implications.</p>
                <p>There is something in postfoundationalism (in its secular articulation at
                        least),<note> Postfoundationalism is also associated with postmodern
                        theology. The general epistemological stance (its approach to the validation
                        of Truth claims) in that <soCalled>strain</soCalled> is very similar to the
                        secular versions discussed in this article, but its ontological orientation
                        places it outside the scope of this article. </note> which resonates with
                    the epistemological stance adopted by a range of digital humanists.
                    Scheinfeldt’s tweet suggesting the immanence of code, Sherratt’s webpage,
                    McCarty’s models, Kirschenbaum’s digital forensics, Ramsay and Rockwell’s
                    epistemology of building, Moretti’s maps, Ramsay’s algorithmic criticism,
                    Turkel’s <soCalled>transduction</soCalled>, Meeks and
                    Weingart’s topic models — these are all examples that sit nicely with the
                    postfoundational stance because they speak to the immanence of knowledge, the
                    significance of its built nature, its coherence not within external facts or
                    contrived narratives but within webs of structure and meaning driven forward by
                    an iterative process, or praxis, of constant becoming. Research methods thus
                    come to include the development of ontologies, schemas, authority control
                    systems, algorithms, scripts, websites, databases and other digital tools that
                    act as grist to an ongoing dialectic between reality, representation, and
                    understanding. Any supporting theoretical corpus would focus on the principles
                    and critical tools that sharpen and refine those methods. </p>
                <p>This approach has significant implications for the broader humanities tradition.
                    By rejecting certain kinds of digital output as being alien to the humanities,
                    or simply not valid research, is to cut short a process that has the ability to
                    provide deep insights into our human world, and to adopt a depressingly
                    short-sighted and pessimistic view of the opportunities provided by digital
                    tools and methods. Opposition to them betrays an essentialist understanding of
                    what kinds of knowledge and meaning-production are valid, in much the same way
                    that scientistic claims function <ptr target="#ginev2007" loc="57"/>. It is this
                    kind of logic which has led the University of Canterbury Library to accept the
                    deposition of the ontology for the UC CEISMIC Digital Archive into its
                    institutional repository.<note> At the time of writing the ontology was being
                        edited in preparation for formal deposit. </note> Although it is by no means
                    a normal output for a humanities research team, it is accepted that it is a both
                    a contribution to knowledge, and one that scholars need to be able to reference
                    and critique. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Postindustrial Culture</head>
                <p>Postfoundationalism appears to be a common epistemological stance amongst digital
                    humanists, and a useful critical tool to help communicate to administrators the
                    scholarly value of technical digital humanities outputs, but it can also help
                    explore and communicate the relationship of the digital humanities to wider
                    postindustrial culture. In doing so it helps explain the <emph>less</emph>
                    technical, more politically and theoretically oriented, instantiations of the
                    field, making it at once a powerful explanatory tool (it can help define both
                    narrow and broad definitions of the field) and a potentially dangerous one (it
                    could be latched upon as <emph>the</emph> rather than <emph>a</emph> way to
                    define the field). </p>
                <p>The political implications of digital humanists’ postfoundational orientation can
                    be seen in the development of the #alt-ac, or <soCalled>alternative academic
                        career</soCalled> movement. #alt-ac began when Brian Croxall, a digital
                    humanist and adjunct faculty member at Emory University, had a colleague deliver
                    a paper for him at the 2009 MLA in absentia because he couldn’t afford to
                    attend. Titled <title rend="quotes">The Absent Presence: Today’s Faculty</title>
                    <ptr target="#croxall2009"/>, the paper outlined the difficult job search
                    process Croxall had been through, and the unfairness implicit in the American
                    university system, which positions adjunct faculty as the <soCalled>waste product</soCalled> of graduate education <ptr
                        target="#bousquet2002"/>. The paper and accompanying blog post generated a
                    storm of interest on Twitter and prompted a conversation about alternative
                    academic careers on that service between Bethany Nowviskie of the University of
                    Virginia’s DH <title rend="quotes">Scholar’s Lab</title> and Jason Rhody from
                    the National Endowment for the Humanities. They proposed the #alt-ac hashtag be
                    used to capture conversations about <soCalled>alternative academic</soCalled>
                    careers, and Nowviskie later established #Alt-Academy, an online collection of
                    essays about the subject. The digital humanities community, though their use of
                    Twitter, had prompted a significant protest against an unfair academic system,
                    and given voice to a large body of disenfranchised but important stakeholders.
                    The #alt-ac community continues to educate and advocate for change in both the
                    orientation of graduate students’ job searches, and the attitude of American
                    universities to adjunct faculty. </p>
                <p>It needs to be remembered that Twitter was by no means an accepted part of
                    academic culture in 2009; indeed, its appearance was met with similar concern
                    about the end of intellectual life as accompanied Wikipedia earlier in the
                    decade. Its use was being spear-headed by digital humanists who, rather than
                    seeing it as a threat to intellectual integrity and the ability of people to
                    read extended passages of prose, chose to view it as merely another useful
                    technology that could be used as part of their broader process: the service was
                    used by digital humanists to offset their geographic dispersal, share ideas and
                    new tools, and build an online community. In 2010, Tom Scheinfeldt went so far
                    as to point out that the use of services like Twitter went beyond the quotidian,
                    and were actually contributing to the development of a radically new mindset: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#scheinfeldt2010">In as much as digital
                            humanities is an Internet-based social network, it should come as no
                            surprise that digital humanities looks a lot like the Internet itself.
                            Digital humanities takes more than tools from the Internet. It works
                            like the Internet. It takes its values from the Internet.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#scheinfeldt2010"/>
                    </cit> Digital Humanities is not only characterized by the <emph>use</emph> of
                    tools like Twitter (along with code, databases, ontologies etc.), it is
                    constituted by them; the discipline assimilates digital tools and methods to the
                    point where they become the thing itself. This is, of course, exactly what we
                    should expect in bringing technology into such a fundamental relationship to
                    scholarly activity. As Heidegger noted in 1949, technology is more than mere
                        <term>techne</term>, or practical art: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#heidegger1949">the manufacture and utilization
                            of equipment, tools, and machines, the manufactured and used things
                            themselves, and the needs and ends that they serve, all belong to what
                            technology is. Technology itself is a contrivance — in Latin, an <term
                                xml:lang="la">instrumentum</term>.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#heidegger1949" loc="288"/>
                    </cit> As Galey and Ruecker noted in their contribution to the DH discussion
                    about the epistemology of building, tools like Twitter ‘contain arguments that
                    advance knowledge about the world’. In assimilating them into fundamental
                    humanistic practice, to the point where understanding of their essential
                    (engineered) nature is a requirement of participation in the debate, digital
                    humanists are engaging in a postfoundational process with far-reaching
                    consequences. A similar argument can be made for the fringe DH activity of
                    contributing to post-disaster cultural heritage archiving and recovery,
                    expressed in projects like the <title rend="italic">September 11 Digital
                        Archive</title>
                    <ptr target="#RRCHNM2002"/>, the <title rend="italic">Hurricane Digital Memory
                        Bank</title>
                    <ptr target="#RRCHNM2011"/>, the <title rend="italic">UC CEISMIC Canterbury
                        Earthquakes Digital Archive</title>
                    <ptr target="#millar2011"/>, and <title rend="italic">Our Marathon: The Boston
                        Bombing Digital Archive</title>
                    <ptr target="#dillon2013"/>. Although not the first thing people would expect
                    humanists to become involved in, it doesn’t take much thought to realize that
                    the interventions of these teams was informed by a range of humanist thinking —
                    about civic responsibility, the importance of cultural memory, public history,
                    engaged scholarship — and that were it not for them significant amounts of
                    valuable cultural heritage content would have been lost. The teams’ scholarly
                    knowledge was put to use via postfoundational methods that resulted in
                    significant contributions to national and international culture. </p>
                <p>As disaster archiving and the development of the #alt-ac community suggests, a
                    growth in postfoundational method has developed coextensively with digital
                    humanities discourse entering the broader public domain. In the American context
                    it might even be reasonable to suggest the growth in postfoundational method has
                        <emph>resulted in</emph> an increase in participation in the public domain.
                        <title rend="italic">Prof Hacker</title>, a blog devoted to trends in higher
                    education and technology started after a THATCamp unconference, was hosted by
                    the <title rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher Education</title> in September of
                    2009. At about the same time articles about both the digital humanities and the
                    general state of graduate education began to appear in trade and IT
                    publications. Articles about the 2011 MLA published in <title rend="italic">The
                        Chronicle of Higher Education</title> on subsequent days heightened
                    interest. William Pannapacker’s <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities
                        Triumphant?</title> described the intense interest in digital humanities
                    sessions at that conference, prompting Fish’s series in the <title rend="italic"
                        >New York Times </title>in response <ptr target="#pannapacker2011"/>.
                    Jennifer Howard focused her attention on the digital humanities and #alt-ac
                    movements, exploring the connections between them <ptr target="#howard2011"/>.
                    At the same conference, Alan Liu announced the publication of <title
                        rend="italic">4Humanities</title>, a web community designed to harness the
                    interest for the benefit of the humanities. <title rend="italic"
                        >4Humanities</title> is overt about its role as critic and conscience of
                    contemporary culture, with a special focus on the effect postindustrial culture
                    is having on the arts and humanities. The connection between DH and advocacy is
                    made explicit on the <title rend="quotes">Mission</title> page: <quote
                        rend="block" source="#howard2011">4Humanities began because the digital
                        humanities community — which specializes in making creative use of digital
                        technology to advance humanities research and teaching as well as to think
                        about the basic nature of the new media and technologies — woke up to its
                        special potential and responsibility to assist humanities advocacy.  The
                        digital humanities are increasingly integrated in the humanities at large. 
                        They catch the eye of administrators and funding agencies who otherwise
                        dismiss the humanities as yesterday’s news.  They connect across disciplines
                        with science and engineering fields.  They have the potential to use new
                        technologies to help the humanities communicate with, and adapt to,
                        contemporary society.</quote> These projects have been added to by <title
                        rend="italic">The Praxis Network</title>,<note> Disclaimer: The author is a
                        member of this project. </note> a group of <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#nowviskie2012">allied but
                            differently-inflected humanities education initiatives… engaged in
                            rethinking pedagogy and campus partnerships in relation to the
                            digital</quote>
                        <ptr target="#nowviskie2012"/>
                    </cit> and ADHO Special Interest Groups like <title rend="italic">Global
                        Outlook: Digital Humanities</title> (ADHO, 2013-), which seeks to assist in
                    the equitable global development of digital humanities as a field. </p>
                <p>
                    <title rend="italic">Transform DH</title>
                    <ptr target="#cong-huyen2012"/> and <title rend="italic">Postcolonial Digital
                        Humanities</title>
                    <ptr target="#kohandrisam2013"/> occupy more overtly theoretical territory,
                    using critical theory to deconstruct the white, middle-class, and straight
                    nature of the Digital Humanities and press for more inclusive attitudes. These
                    projects deploy critical theory in opposition to what they feel is blindness
                    within the discipline to significant inequities across racial, gender, class and
                    sexual boundaries, but pay close attention to the built layers of technologies.
                    Their attitude was summed up at a paper delivered at Digital Humanities 2013,
                    titled <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities: Egalitarian or the New
                        Elite?</title>, where a variety of speakers outlined the work — technical,
                    theoretical, and political — required to ensure the community’s claims of
                    inclusiveness are supported by actions, technical standards and protocols <ptr
                        target="#skallerup2013"/>. </p>
                <p>Just as Software Studies and Critical Code brushed up against my discussion of
                    immanence, so this part of the digital humanities brushes up against projects
                    like the <title rend="italic">Humanities, Arts, Science and Technology Alliance
                        Collaboratory</title>
                    <ptr target="#davidson2002"/> and the <title rend="italic">Fembot
                        Collective</title>
                    <ptr target="#adams2003"/>, and the vast terrain explored in Science and
                    Technology Studies, Cultural Studies and New Media. This isn’t to mention the
                    long-standing connection between the digital humanities and the open access
                    movement, symbolized in projects like <title rend="italic">Open Humanities
                        Press</title>
                    <ptr target="#jöttkandt2007"/> and <title rend="italic">Press Forward</title>
                    <ptr target="#RRCHNM2011"/> but reaching far deeper, into relationships with
                    leading digital presses at M.I.T. and Michigan University, and connections into
                    library science and scholarly communication networks like <title rend="italic"
                        >Media Commons: A Digital Scholarly Network</title>
                    <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2007"/>. It would no doubt be possible to continue
                    surfacing relevant examples, but it is enough to note that over the course of a
                    decade, from around 2001–2011, the digital humanities have moved from an
                    emphasis on technique (represented in the humanities computing tradition) to a
                    blended <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#underwood2011">extra-disciplinary</quote>
                        <ptr target="#underwood2011"/>
                    </cit> praxis involving a continuum that ranges from purely technical work to
                    new media and political advocacy. This process has caused significant and
                    understandable tension; the stakeholder community has struggled to deploy
                    conceptual tools capable of accommodating such a rapidly expanding audience. </p>
                <p>My feeling is that this tension stems from discomfort at the extension of the
                    field towards cognate disciplines that are often deeply critical of the very
                    technologies digital humanists rely on. The critical pressure that has been
                    applied through exposure to these disciplines has resulted in the culturally and
                    critically engaged projects outlined above, which indicate an acceptance of the
                    field’s complex relationship to postindustrial culture. This is unsurprising
                    given the backgrounds of some of the scholars involved in them. Before
                    establishing <title rend="italic">4Humanities</title> Alan Liu explored the
                    relationship between the Humanities and postindustrial culture in <title
                        rend="italic">The Laws of Cool: Knowledge Work and the Culture of
                        Information</title>, arguing that <quote rend="inline" source="#liu2004"
                        >postindustrialism is a technological rationality</quote> that has led to
                    the usurpation of the knowledge economy by corporate interests and threatens <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#liu2004">…the death of knowledge in the
                            information age</quote>
                        <ptr target="#liu2004" loc="39, 69"/>
                    </cit>. He argued that this has shifted the context for the humanities into
                    corporate environments, requiring new analytical techniques, and new research
                    agendas focused on the analysis of corporate culture and power. <title
                        rend="italic">4Humanities</title> reflects a response to this insight,
                    actively countering myths benefitting postindustrial technocrats with evidence
                    from within the Humanities themselves, but anxieties remain. </p>
                <p>At the 2013 MLA Wendy Hui Kyong Chun delivered a talk titled <title rend="quotes"
                        >The Dark Side of the Digital Humanities,</title> which pointed out the
                    paradox of a supposedly booming new discipline producing insecure jobs, lacking
                    scholarly recognition, and requiring a constant search for funding. Chun claimed
                    she wasn’t criticizing the Digital Humanities so much as <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#chun2013">the general euphoria surrounding technology and
                        education</quote> and the <quote rend="inline" source="#chun2013">vapid embrace of
                        the digital</quote> that feeds into the corporatism critiqued by Liu. Her
                    compelling argument was that the heightened interest in the digital humanities
                    (the development of a <soCalled>bandwagon</soCalled>) <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#chun2013">…allows us to believe that the
                            problem facing our students and our profession is a lack of technical
                            savvy rather than an economic system that undermines the future of our
                            students</quote>
                        <ptr target="#chun2013"/>
                    </cit>. Chun’s talk provided a moment of <soCalled>stuplimity,</soCalled> a word
                    coined by Sianne Ngai to refer to those peculiarly modern moments when
                    wonderment gives way to <quote rend="inline" source="#ngai200">an extended duration of
                        consecutive fatigues</quote>: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#ngai2000">As in the case of the repeated
                            pratfalls of the slapstick comedian, stuplimity emerges in the
                            performance of such fatigue-inducing strategies, in which the gradual
                            accumulation of error often leads to the repetition of a refrain: <q>too
                                strong</q>; or <q>something wrong there.</q>
                        </quote>
                        <ptr target="#ngai2000" loc="19"/>
                    </cit> Chun was articulating specific concerns, but they were informed by an
                    awareness of the kind of cultural critique practiced by Liu. She was pointing
                    out that the hype associated with the digital humanities shouldn’t (or shouldn’t
                    be allowed to) hide the fact that the field is as pressured as any other in the
                    arts and humanities by technocratic tendencies and a drift towards corporatism
                    within universities.</p>
                <p>The field’s attitude to this situation — being beset by the same pressures that
                    threaten the broader tradition — could define its future. Rejecting the insights
                    offered by political and cultural theory risks complicity with troubling aspects
                    of the contemporary world <ptr target="#zittrain2008"/>; <ptr
                        target="#golumbia2009"/>; <ptr target="#lanier2010"/>. <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#ross2013">[S]unny prognostications</quote> about a
                    technologically-enabled future of emancipated knowledge workers and efficient
                    markets have been undermined not only by the growth of large multinational
                    technology companies, but unfair labor practices that have all too familiar
                    parallels in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries <ptr target="#ross2013"
                        loc="18"/>. As Foucault pointed out, technical forms of knowledge not only
                    influence the organization of corporate culture, but social life and norms of
                    conduct as well, making cognizance of the issues even more pressing <ptr
                        target="#bevir2011b" loc="93"/>. In another piece of writing Chun goes so
                    far as to suggest we have entered a period where long-standing enlightenment
                    definitions of personal identity and governmentality have been radically altered
                        <ptr target="#chun2011" loc="7"/>. </p>
                <p>Experienced digital humanists are aware of the issues. As Julia Flanders puts it, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#flanders2012">[d]igital humanities projects
                            take place, strikingly, in a universe constrained by a set of technical
                            norms that govern the informational and operational behavior of the
                            digital environment</quote>
                        <ptr target="#flanders2012" loc="67"/>
                    </cit>. Just as a builder needs her tools, then, so she needs access to ethical
                    guidelines and informed design histories to avoid contributing to (or merely
                    providing more reason to resist) the negative social and economic effects of
                    contemporary technology. This brings to mind the work of writers like Chun <ptr
                        target="#chun2006"/>; <ptr target="#chun2011"/> and Anne Balsamo <ptr
                        target="#balsamo1996"/>, who consider the intersection between software,
                    design philosophy, identity, and engineering. These writers offer crucial
                    insights into the digital age, and need to be included within digital humanists’
                    worldview so they can provide input into postfoundational methods. The same can
                    be said for the many authors who have produced books and articles on the history
                    of computing, and historians of technology generally. This is a very well
                    established field, served by an excellent professional body (the Society for the
                    History of Technology, or SHOT, established in 1958). Efforts should be made to
                    understand where synergies between it and DH lie, especially regarding the
                    concept of materiality and the socio-cultural impact of digital technologies,
                    but also in relation to pedagogy and research goals.</p>
                <p>If these insights are grafted onto the turn to <soCalled>code-craft</soCalled>
                    signaled at the NEH funded <title rend="quotes">“Speaking in Code”</title>
                    workshop in November 2013, the field will have a powerful toolkit at its
                    disposal. Although nascent, this <soCalled>craft</soCalled> movement holds great
                    promise as a means of expressing postfoundational methods through a guild or
                    trade-based approach that emphasizes building and experimentation. The stated
                    goal of the workshop can be described as postfoundational in its desire to <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#nowviskie2013">give voice to what is almost
                            always tacitly expressed in our work: expert knowledge about the
                            intellectual and interpretive dimensions of DH code-craft, and unspoken
                            understandings about the relation of that work to ethics, scholarly
                            method, and humanities theory</quote>
                        <ptr target="#nowviskie2013"/>
                    </cit>. The initiative is exciting: the goal appears to be to tease out theory
                    and method from a hermeneutic of practice. This aligns very nicely to what this
                    article describes as postfoundational method.</p>
                <p>The problem, as always, is accommodating and being informed by views ranging from
                    a focus on code-craft to the theoretically informed critique of Chun, Balsamo et
                    al. Some efforts must be made, and ideally some intellectual levers must be
                    found, to help bridge the gap. Andrew Prescott notes that digital humanists are
                    well positioned to understand that <quote rend="inline" source="#prescott2012">knowledge is
                        being turned into a commodity, a data steam disconnected from those who
                        produce it and turned to commercial advantage by monopolistic
                        corporations.</quote> In arguing for the necessity of the field, he suggests
                    that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#prescott2012">…if humanities scholars wish to
                            ensure that their understanding and engagement with human knowledge does
                            not become another Californian commodity, it is essential to engage with
                            the digital world, and not as consumers but as creators</quote>
                        <ptr target="#prescott2012"/>
                    </cit>. Conversely, it seems logical to argue along with Liu that the opposite
                    is also true: that digital humanists involved in building technologies should be
                    aware of the critiques of the cultural, economic and political domains they
                    might seek to retain intellectual freedom from. </p>
                <p>It’s important to acknowledge, though, that rather than rejecting insights
                    produced through cultural critique, many of the projects referred to in this
                    article are designed as active instantiations of them. Put another way, we could
                    note that there might not be significant cause for concern: postfoundational DH
                    method appears to function surprisingly well against issues presented by
                    postindustrial culture. Not all DH projects are politically motivated — and we
                    could perhaps hope that the bulk of focus remains on traditional topics like
                    scholarly editions, concordances and archives, because this is where the
                    discipline’s main service to the tradition lies — but the more politically
                    motivated projects appear to revel in the knowledge that digital humanists’
                    felicity with the manipulation of the postindustrial system’s <soCalled>symbolic
                        architecture</soCalled> (computer code, and the ICT discourses associated
                    with the production and maintenance of not only that, but the system’s broader
                    culture and politics) offers a power that should be mobilized for the common
                    good. Their understanding of the engineered nature of the postindustrial world
                    (their facility with the code that powers its key engines, their ability to
                    build a server rather than be beholden to the dictates of an IT service desk,
                    their ability to do things cost-free) gives them insight into the world of
                        <soCalled>informational capitalism.</soCalled> The targeted success of the
                    projects is due to the realization that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#castells2010">[i]n the new, informational mode
                            of development the source of productivity lies in the technology of
                            knowledge generation, information processing, and symbolic
                            communication</quote>
                        <ptr target="#castells2010" loc="18, 17"/>
                    </cit>. </p>
                <p>This isn’t hack versus yack, it’s hack then act. The projects align extremely
                    well to the goals of more theoretically inclined humanists and evince awareness
                    of the cultural and ideological implications of the technology industry <ptr
                        target="#dyer-witheford1999"/>. Indeed, rather than being anti-theoretical,
                    the projects described above merely suggest a commitment to post (as opposed to
                    anti) foundationalism. They indicate attempts to <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#liu2011b">use the tools, paradigms, and concepts of digital
                        technologies to help rethink the idea of instrumentality</quote> for the
                    Humanities as a whole <ptr target="#liu2011b" loc="501"/>. They aim to use the
                    insights gained from saturation in technical contexts for the greater good of
                    the tradition, politicizing insights gained through postfoundational method and
                    mobilizing them against the aspects of postindustrial capitalism that threaten
                    (and homogenize) the broader arts and humanities community. Historian of
                    technology Rosalind Williams might suggest they have decided that <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#williams2000">when culture is no longer an outer
                        shell of context, but is part of the machine</quote> radically new methods
                    of engagement and scholarly production are required <ptr target="#williams2000"
                        loc="661"/>. Whether production ends with the development of a schema, a
                    data model, a website, a scholarly edition, a journal article or a monograph
                    should matter less than the fact that production has occurred at all.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="adams2003" label="Adams et al. 2003-" key="adams2003"> Adams, Melissa
                    et al. <title rend="italic">Fembot Collective</title>, 2003-, accessed December
                    01, 2013, <ref target="http://fembotcollective.org/"
                        >http://fembotcollective.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ADHO2013"
                    label="Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO) 2013-" key="ADHO2013"
                    >Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO). <title rend="italic"
                        >Global Outlook:DH</title> (GO:DH), 2013 -, accessed December 01, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://www.globaloutlookdh.org/"
                        >http://www.globaloutlookdh.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="balsamo1996" label="Balsamo 2006" key="balsamo1996"> Balsamo, Anne
                    Marie. <title rend="italic">Technologies of the Gendered Body: Reading Cyborg
                        Women</title>. Durham: Duke University Press, 1996.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bauer2011" label="Bauer 2011" key="bauer2011"> Bauer, Jean. <title
                        rend="quotes">Who You Calling Untheoretical?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 1:1 (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="castells2010" label="Castells 2010" key="castells2010"> Castells,
                    Manuel. <title rend="italic">The Rise of the Network Society: The Information
                        Age: Economy, Society, and Culture. </title>1st ed. Hoboken:
                    Wiley-Blackwell, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berry2011" label="Berry 2011" key="berry2011"> Berry, David M. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Computational Turn: Thinking About the Digital
                        Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Culture Machine</title> 12 (2011): 1-22.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dyer-witheford1999" label="Dyer-Witheford 1999"
                    key="dyer-witheford1999"> Dyer-Witheford, Nick. <title rend="italic">Cyber-Marx:
                        Cycles and Circuits of Struggle in High-technology Capitalism</title>.
                    Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bevir2011a" label="Bevir 2011a" key="bevir2011a"> Bevir, Mark. <title
                        rend="quotes">Why Historical Distance Is Not a Problem.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">History and Theory</title> 50:4 (2011): 24–37.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bevir2011b" label="Bevir 2011b" key="bevir2011b"> Bevir, Mark. <title
                        rend="quotes">Political Science after Foucault.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">History of the Human Sciences</title> 24:4 (2011):
                    81–96.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bousquet2002" label="Bousquet 2002" key="bousquet2002"> Bousquet,
                    Marc. <title rend="quotes">The Waste Product of Graduate Education: Toward a
                        Dictatorship of the Flexible.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Social Text</title> 20:1 (2002): 81–104.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burns2006" label="Burns 2006" key="burns2006"> Burns, Robert M. <title
                        rend="quotes">“Collingwood, Bradley and Historical Knowledge.”</title>
                    <title rend="italic">History and Theory</title> 45 (2006): 178–203.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cecire2011a" label="Cecire 2011a" key="cecire2011a"> Cecire, Natalia.
                        <title rend="quotes">When DH Was in Vogue; or, THATCamp Theory.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Works Cited</title>. 2011. Rpt. <title rend="quotes">When
                        Digital Humanities Was in Vogue.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 1:1 (2011a).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cecire2011b" label="Cecire 2011b" key="cecire2011b"> Cecire, Natalia.
                        <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Theory and the Virtues of Digital
                        Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 1:1 (2011b).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chun2006" label="Chun 2006" key="chun2006"> Chun, Wendy Hui Kyong.
                        <title rend="italic">Control and Freedom: Power and Paranoia in the Age of
                        Fiber Optics</title>. Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chun2011" label="Chun 2011" key="chun2011"> Chun, Wendy Hui Kyong.
                        <title rend="italic">Programmed Visions: Software and Memory. Software
                        Studies</title>. Cambridge, Mass: MIT Press, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chun2013" label="Chun 2013" key="chun2013"> Chun, Wendy Hui Kyong.
                        <title rend="quotes">The Dark Side of the Digital Humanities.</title> 4 Jan.
                    2013, accessed December 01 2013, <ref
                        target="http://www.c21uwm.com/2013/01/09/the-dark-side-of-the-digital-humanities-part-1"
                        >http://www.c21uwm.com/2013/01/09/the-dark-side-of-the-digital-humanities-part-1</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chunetal2013" label="Chun et al. 2013" key="chunetal2013"> Chun, Wendy
                    H., Richard A. Grusin, Patrick Jagoda, Rita Raley, <title rend="quotes">The Dark
                        Side of the Digital Humanities,</title> MLA panel discussion, 4 Jan.
                    2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cong-huyen2012" label="Cong-Huyen 2012-" key="cong-huyen2012">
                    Cong-Huyen, Anne et al. <title rend="italic">Transform DH</title> (TransformDH),
                    2012-, accessed December 01, 2013, http://transformdh.org/.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="croxall2009" label="Croxall 2009" key="croxall2009"> Croxall, Brian.
                        <title rend="quotes">The Absent Presence: Today’s Faculty.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Brian Croxall</title>. 28 Dec. 2009, accessed December 01,
                    2013, <ref
                        target="http://www.briancroxall.net/2009/12/28/the-absent-presence-todays-faculty/"
                        >http://www.briancroxall.net/2009/12/28/the-absent-presence-todays-faculty/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="daniels2012" label="Daniels 2012" key="daniels2012"> Daniels, Anthony.
                        <title rend="quotes">The Digital Challenge, I: Loss &amp; Gain, or the Fate
                        of the Book.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The New Criterion.</title> Vol. 31, Nov. 2012, p.4. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="davidson2002" label="Davidson 2012-" key="davidson2002"> Davidson,
                    Cathy N. <title rend="italic">Humanities, Arts, Science and Technology Alliance
                        Collaboratory</title> (HASTAC), 2002-, accessed December 01, 2013,
                    http://hastac.org/.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dillon2013" label="Dillon et al. 2013" key="dillon2013"> Dillon,
                    Elizabeth et al, <title rend="italic">Our Marathon</title>, 2013, accessed
                    December 01, 2013, http://marathon.neu.edu/.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="donoghue2008" label="Donoghue 2008" key="donoghue2008"> Donoghue,
                    Frank. <title rend="italic">The Last Professors: The Corporate University and
                        the Fate of the Humanities</title>. New York: Fordham University Press,
                    2008.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fish2011" label="Fish 2011" key="fish2011"> Fish, Stanley. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Old Order Changeth.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Opinionator</title>. 26 Dec. 2011, accessed December 01,
                    2013, <ref
                        target="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/12/26/the-old-order-changeth/"
                        >http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/12/26/the-old-order-changeth/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fish2012a" label="Fish 2012a" key="fish2012a"> Fish, Stanley. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Digital Humanities and the Transcending of
                        Mortality.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Opinionator.</title> 9 Jan. 2012a, accessed December 01,
                    2013, <ref
                        target="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/01/09/the-digital-humanities-and-the-transcending-of-mortality/?_r=0"
                        >http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/01/09/the-digital-humanities-and-the-transcending-of-mortality/?_r=0</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fish2012b" label="Fish 2012b" key="fish2012b"> Fish, Stanley. <title
                        rend="quotes">Mind Your P’s and B’s: The Digital Humanities and
                        Interpretation.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Opinionator. </title>23 Jan. 2012b, accessed December 01,
                    2013, <ref
                        target="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/01/23/mind-your-ps-and-bs-the-digital-humanities-and-interpretation/"
                        >http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/01/23/mind-your-ps-and-bs-the-digital-humanities-and-interpretation/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fitzpatrick2007" label="Fitzpatrick et al. 2007" key="fitzpatrick2007"
                    > Fitzpatrick, Kathleen et al, <title rend="italic">Media Commons: A Digital
                        Scholarly Network</title>, 2007-, accessed December 01, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/"
                        >http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="flanders2009" label="Flanders 2009" key="flanders2009"> Flanders,
                    Julia. <title rend="quotes">The Productive Unease of 21st-century Digital
                        Scholarship.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 3.3 (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="flanders2012" label="Flanders 2012" key="flanders2012b"> Flanders,
                    Julia. <title rend="quotes">Collaboration and Dissent: Challenges of
                        Collaborative Standards for Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Collaborative Research in the Digital Humanities.</title>
                    Ed. Marilyn Deegan and Willard McCarty. Farnham: Ashgate, 2012: 67-80.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fogelandengerman" label="Fogel and Engerman 1974"
                    key="fogelandengerman1974"> Fogel, Robert William and Stanley L. Engerman.
                        <title rend="italic">Time on the Cross: The Economics of American Negro
                        Slavery</title>. 1st ed. Boston: Little, Brown, 1974.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fuller2008" label="Fuller 2008" key="fuller2008"> Fuller, Matthew,
                        ed. <title rend="italic">Software Studies: A Lexicon</title>. Leonardo.
                    Cambridge, Mass: MIT Press, 2008.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galeyandruecker2010" label="Galey and Ruecker 2010"
                    key="galeyandruecker2010"> Galey, Alan and Stan Ruecker. <title rend="quotes"
                        >How a Prototype Argues.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 25:4 (2010):
                    405–424.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gavin2012" label="Gavin et al. 2012" key="gavin2012"> Gavin, M.,
                    Smith, K.M., &amp; Bobley, B. <title rend="quotes">An interview with Brett
                        Bobley</title> in M.K. Gold ed. <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities</title>, Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2012, pp.
                    61-66.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ginev2001" label="Ginev 2001" key="ginev2001"> Ginev, Dimitri. <title
                        rend="quotes">Searching for a (Post)Foundational Approach to Philosophy of
                        Science: Part I.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal for General Philosophy of Science / Zeitschrift Für
                        Allgemeine Wissenschaftstheorie</title> 32:1 (2001): 27-37.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ginev2007" label="Ginev 2007" key="ginev2007"> Ginev, Dimitri. <title
                        rend="quotes">A (Post)Foundational Approach to the Philosophy of Science:
                        Part II.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal for General Philosophy of Science / <foreign
                            xml:lang="de">Zeitschrift Für Allgemeine Wissenschaftstheorie</foreign>
                    </title> 38:1 (2007): 57–74. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gibbs2011" label="Gibbs 2011" key="gibbs2011"> Gibbs, Fred. <title
                        rend="quotes">Critical Discourse in Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 1.1 (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gold2012" label="Gold 2012" key="gold2012b"> Gold, Matthew K. <title
                        rend="quotes">Introduction: The Digital Humanities Moment.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>. Ed. Matthew K.
                    Gold. Minneapolis: U Minnesota Press, 2012, pp. ix-xvi.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="golumbia2009" label="Golumbia 2009" key="golumbia2009"> Golumbia,
                    David. <title rend="italic">The Cultural Logic of Computation</title>.
                    Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 2009.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="grafton2006" label="Grafton 2006" key="grafton2006"> Grafton, Anthony.
                        <title rend="quotes">The History of Ideas: Precept and Practice, 1950-2000
                        and Beyond.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of the History of Ideas </title>67:1 (2006):
                    2-3.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="healy2005" label="Healy 2005" key="healy2005"> Healy, Paul. <title
                        rend="italic">Rationality, Hermeneutics And Dialogue: Toward A Viable
                        Postfoundationalist Account Of Rationality</title>. Ashgate Publishing,
                    Ltd., 2005.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="healy2007" label="Healy 2007" key="healy2007"> Healy, Paul. <title
                        rend="quotes">Rationality, Dialogue and, and Critical Inquiry: Toward a
                        Viable Postfoundationalist Stance.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Cosmos and History: The Journal of Natural and Social
                        Philosophy</title> 3:1 (2007): 134–158.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="heidegger1949" label="Heidegger 1978" key="heidegger1949"> Heidegger,
                    M. <title rend="quotes">The Question Concerning Technology (1949).</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Basic Writings.</title> London: Routledge and Kegan Paul,
                    1978, pp. 283-317.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="howard2011" label="Howard 2011" key="howard2011"> Howard, Jennifer.
                        <title rend="quotes">Hard Times Sharpen the MLA’s Lens on Labor and the
                        Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education.</title> 9 Jan. 2011,
                    accessed December 01, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://chronicle.com/article/Hard-Times-Sharpen-the-MLAs/125905/"
                        >http://chronicle.com/article/Hard-Times-Sharpen-the-MLAs/125905/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jockers2013" label="Jockers 2013" key="jockers2014"> Jockers, Matthew
                    L. <title rend="italic">Text Analysis With R for Students of Literature</title>.
                    DRAFT. Springer, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jöttkandt2007" label="Jöttkandt et al. 2007-" key="jöttkandt2007">
                    Jöttkandt, Sigi, David Ottina et al. <title rend="italic">Open Humanities
                        Press</title> (OHP), 2007-, accessed December 01, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://openhumanitiespress.org/"
                        >http://openhumanitiespress.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2007" label="Kirschenbaum 2007" key="kirschenbaum2007b">
                    Kirschenbaum, Matthew G. <title rend="italic">Mechanisms: New Media and the
                        Forensic Imagination. </title>Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2007.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2010" label="Kirschenbaum 2010" key="kirschenbaum2010c">
                    Kirschenbaum, Matthew G. <title rend="quotes">What Is Digital Humanities and
                        What’s It Doing in English Departments?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">ADE Bulletin</title> 150 (2010): 1-7.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kohandrisam2013" label="Koh and Risam 2013-" key="kohandrisam2013">
                    Koh, Adeline and Roopika Risam, <title rend="italic">Postcolonial Digital
                        Humanities</title>, 2013-, accessed December 01, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://dhpoco.org/">http://dhpoco.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lakatos1980" label="Lakatos 1980" key="lakatos1980"> Lakatos, I.
                        <title rend="italic">Methodology of Scientific Research Programmes</title>.
                    Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1980.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lanier2010" label="Lanier 2010" key="lanier2010"> Lanier, Jaron.
                        <title rend="italic">You Are Not a Gadget: a Manifesto</title>. New York:
                    Alfred A. Knopf, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2004" label="Liu 2004" key="liu2004"> Liu, Alan. <title
                        rend="italic">The Laws of Cool: Knowledge Work and the Culture of
                        Information</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2004.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2008" label="Liu 2008" key="liu2008"> Liu, Alan. <title
                        rend="italic">Local Transcendence: Essays on Postmodern Historicism and the
                        Database</title>. U Chicago Press, 2008.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2011a" label="Liu 2011a" key="liu2011b"> Liu, Alan. <title
                        rend="quotes">The state of the digital humanities: A report and a
                        critique.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Arts and Humanities in Higher Education</title> 11.1-2
                    (2011a): 8-41.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2011b" label="Liu 2011b" key="liu2011c"> Liu, Alan. <title
                        rend="quotes">Where Is Cultural Criticism in the Digital Humanities?</title>
                    Seminar. University of Nottingham, July 5, 2011b. Rpt. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Where Is Cultural Criticism in the Digital Humanities?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>. Ed. Mathew Gold.
                    Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2012: 490–509.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liuetal2011" label="Liu et al. 2011" key="liuetal2011">Liu, Alan et
                    al, <title rend="quotes">The History and Future of the Digital
                        Humanities,</title> Modern Language Association convention, Los Angeles. 7
                    Jan. 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2013" label="Liu et al. 2013" key="liu2013"> Liu, Alan et al.
                        <title rend="quotes">4Humanities: Mission,</title> accessed December 01,
                    2013, <ref target="http://4humanities.org/mission/"
                        >http://4humanities.org/mission/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lunenfeld2012" label="Lunenfeld et al. 2012" key="lunenfeld2012">
                    Lunenfeld, Peter et al. <title rend="italic">Digital_Humanities</title>.
                    Cambridge MA: MIT Press, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mccarty2005" label="McCarty 2005" key="mccarty2005"> McCarty, Willard.
                        <title rend="italic">Humanities Computing.</title> Houndmills: Palgrave
                    Macmillan, 2005.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mccarty2008" label="McCarty 2008" key="mccarty2008"> McCarty, Willard.
                        <title rend="quotes">What’s Going On?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 23:3 (2008):
                    253–261.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mccarty2012" label="McCarty 2012" key="mccarty2012b"> McCarty,
                    Willard. <title rend="quotes">The Residue of Uniqueness.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Historical Social Research</title> 37:3 (2012):
                    24-45.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2009" label="McPherson 2009" key="mcpherson2009"> McPherson,
                    Tara. <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Media Studies and the Digital
                        Humanities.</title> Cinema Journal 48, no. 2 (January 1, 2009):
                    119–123.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mackenzie2006" label="Mackenzie 2006" key="mackenzie2006"> Mackenzie,
                    Adrian. <title rend="italic">Cutting Code: Software and Sociality</title>. New
                    York: Peter Lang, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="madison1991" label="Madison 1991" key="madison1991"> Madison, Gary
                    Brent. <title rend="quotes">Philosophy Without Foundations.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Reason Papers</title> 16, Fall (1991): 15–44.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mahoney2004" label="Mahoney 2004" key="mahoney2004"> Mahoney, Michael
                    S. <title rend="quotes">Finding a History for Software Engineering.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</title> 26:1
                    (2004): 8-19.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="manovich2001" label="Manovich 2001" key="manovich2001"> Manovich, Lev.
                        <title rend="italic">The Language of New Media</title>. Leonardo. Cambridge,
                    Mass: MIT Press, 2001.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="manovich2013" label="Manovich 2013" key="manovich2013"> Manovich, Lev.
                        <title rend="italic">Software Takes Command: Extending the Language of New
                        Media</title>, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="marche2012" label="Marche 2012" key="marche2012"> Marche, Stephen.
                        <title rend="quotes">Literature Is Not Data: Against Digital
                        Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Los Angeles Review of Books</title>. 28 Oct. 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="meeksandweingart2012" label="Meeks and Weingart 2012"
                    key="meeksandweingart2012"> Meeks, Elijah and Scott Weingart, <title
                        rend="quotes">The Digital Humanities Contribution to Topic Modeling,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 2:1, Winter
                    2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="meister2012" label="Meister 2012" key="meister2012"> Meister, Jan
                    Christoph. <title rend="quotes">DH Is Us or on the Unbearable Lightness of a
                        Shared Methodology.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Historical Social Research</title>. 37:3 (September 2012):
                    77–85.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="menand2010" label="Menand 2010" key="menand2010"> Menand, Louis.
                        <title rend="italic">The Marketplace of Ideas: Reform and Resistance in the
                        American University</title>. New York: W.W. Norton, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="millar2011" label="Millar et al. 2011-" key="millar2011"> Millar, P.,
                    Smithies, J. et al, <title rend="italic">UC CEISMIC Canterbury Earthquakes
                        Digital Archive</title>, 2011-, accessed December 01, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://www.ceismic.org.nz">http://www.ceismic.org.nz</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="millar2012" label="Millar et al. 2012-" key="millar2012"> Millar, P.,
                    Smithies, J., Thomson, C. et al., <title rend="italic">UC QuakeStudies
                        Repository</title>, 2012-, accessed December 01, 2013, <ref
                        target="https://quakestudies.canterbury.ac.nz"
                        >https://quakestudies.canterbury.ac.nz</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="montfort2012" label="Montfort et al. 2012" key="montfort2012">
                    Montfort, Nick et al. <title rend="italic">10 PRINT CHR$(205.5+RND(1)); : GOTO
                        10</title>. Cambridge, Mass.: The MIT Press, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moretti2005" label="Moretti 2005" key="moretti2005"> Moretti, Franco.
                        <title rend="italic">Graphs, Maps, Trees: Abstract Models for a Literary
                        History</title>. London; New York: Verso, 2005.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ngai2000" label="Ngai 2000" key="ngai2000"> Ngai, Sianne. <title
                        rend="quotes">Stuplimity: Shock and Boredom in Twentieth-Century
                        Aesthetics.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Postmodern Culture</title> 10:2 (2000).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nowviskie2011" label="Nowviskie et al. 2011-" key="nowviskie2011c">
                    Nowviskie, Bethany et al. <title rend="italic">#alt-academy</title>, 2011-,
                    accessed December 01, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/alt-ac/"
                        >http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/alt-ac/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nowviskie2012" label="Nowviskie et al. 2012-" key="nowviskie2012a">
                    Nowviskie, Bethany et al. <title rend="italic">The Praxis Network</title>,
                    2012-, <ref target="http://praxis-network.org/"
                    >http://praxis-network.org/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nowviskie2013" label="Nowviskie et al. 2013" key="nowviskie2013">
                    Nowviskie, Bethany et al. <title rend="italic">Speaking in Code
                    Workshop</title>, 2013, <ref target="http://codespeak.scholarslab.org/"
                        >http://codespeak.scholarslab.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="olsen1993" label="Olsen 1993" key="olsen1993"> Olsen, Mark. <title
                        rend="quotes">Motives, Memory and Mind: Collingwood’s Theory of Actions and
                            <q>Histoire Des Mentalités</q>.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Historical Reflections / <foreign xml:lang="fr">Réflexions
                            Historiques</foreign>
                    </title> 19:1 (January 1, 1993): 35–62.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pannapacker2011" label="Pannapacker 2011" key="pannapacker2011">
                    Pannapacker, William. <title rend="quotes">Pannapacker at MLA: Digital
                        Humanities Triumphant?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education</title>. 8 Jan. 2011,
                    accessed December 01, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://chronicle.com/blogs/brainstorm/pannapacker-at-mla-digital-humanities-triumphant"
                        >http://chronicle.com/blogs/brainstorm/pannapacker-at-mla-digital-humanities-triumphant</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pannapacker2013" label="Pannapacker 2013" key="pannapacker2013b">
                    Pannapacker, William. <title rend="quotes">On <title rend="quotes">The Dark Side
                            of the Digital Humanities.</title>
                    </title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education.</title> 5 Jan. 2013,
                    accessed December 01, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://chronicle.com/blogs/conversation/2013/01/05/on-the-dark-side-of-the-digital-humanities/"
                        >http://chronicle.com/blogs/conversation/2013/01/05/on-the-dark-side-of-the-digital-humanities/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="prescott2012" label="Prescott 2012" key="prescott2012"> Prescott,
                    Andrew. <title rend="quotes">An Electric Current of the Imagination: What the
                        Digital Humanities Are and What They Might Become.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title>. 1:2 (2012). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay2011a" label="Ramsay 2011a" key="ramsay2011a"> Ramsay, Stephen.
                        <title rend="quotes">On Building.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Stephen Ramsay</title>. 11 Jan. 2011, accessed December 01,
                    2013, <ref target="http://stephenramsay.us/text/2011/01/11/on-building/"
                        >http://stephenramsay.us/text/2011/01/11/on-building/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay2011b" label="Ramsay 2011b" key="ramsay2011b"> Ramsay, Stephen.
                        <title rend="italic">Reading Machines: Toward an Algorithmic Criticism.
                    </title>Urbana: U. Illinois Press, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay2011c" label="Ramsay 2011c" key="ramsay2011c"> Ramsay, Steven. <title rend="quotes">Who's In and Who's Out?</title> <title rend="italic">MLA</title> Los Angeles, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsayandrockwell2012" label="Ramsay and Rockwell 2012"
                    key="ramsayandrockwell2012"> Ramsay, Stephen and Geoffrey Rockwell. <title
                        rend="quotes">Developing Things: Notes Toward an Epistemology of Building in
                        the Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>. Ed. Matthew
                    Gold. Minneapolis: Michigan University Press, 2012, pp75-84.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="riederandrohle2012" label="Rieder and Rohle 2012"
                    key="rieder-röhle2012"> Rieder, Bernard and Theo Rohle. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Digital Methods: Five Challenges.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Understanding Digital Humanities</title>. Ed. David M.
                    Berry. London: Palgrave Macmillan, 2012, pp.67-84.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rockwellsinclair2012" label="Rockwell and Sinclair 2012"
                    key="rockwellsinclair2012">Rockwell, Geoffrey and Stefan Sinclair, <title
                        rend="quotes">The Swallow Flies Swiftly Through: An Analysis of
                        Humanist,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2012 Conference Abstracts</title>,
                    University of Hamburg Press, 16 – 22 July 2012, pp.339 – 341.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rogers2013" label="Rogers 2013" key="rogers2013a"> Rogers, Katina.
                        <title rend="quotes">Humanities Unbound: Careers &amp; Scholarship Beyond
                        the Tenure Track,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Scholars’ Lab</title>, April 23, 2013, accessed December
                    01, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://www.scholarslab.org/research-and-development/humanities-unbound-careers-scholarship-beyond-the-tenure-track/"
                        >http://www.scholarslab.org/research-and-development/humanities-unbound-careers-scholarship-beyond-the-tenure-track/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ross2013" label="Ross 2013" key="ross2013"> Ross, Andrew. <title
                        rend="quotes">In Search of the Lost Paycheck,</title> in Trebor Scholz, ed.
                        <title rend="italic">Digital Labor: The Internet as Playground and
                        Factory</title>. New York: Routledge, 2013, p.13-32.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="RRCHNM2002" label="RRCHNM 2002" key="RRCHNM2002"> Roy Rosenzweig
                    Center for History and New Media (RRCHNM). <title rend="italic">September 11
                        Digital Archive</title>, 2002, accessed November 29, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://911digitalarchive.org/"
                    >http://911digitalarchive.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="RRCHNM2011" label="RRCHNM 2011-" key="RRCHNM2011"> Roy Rosenzweig
                    Center for History and New Media (RRCHNM). <title rend="italic">Press
                        Forward</title>, 2011–, accessed December 01, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://pressforward.org/">http://pressforward.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="RRCHNM2005" label="RRCHNM and University of New Orleans 2005"
                    key="RRCHNM2005"> Roy Rosenzweig Center for History and New Media (RRCHNM) and
                    University of New Orleans, <title rend="italic">Hurricane Memory Bank</title>,
                    2005, accessed November 29, 2013, <ref target="http://hurricanearchive.org/"
                        >http://hurricanearchive.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="scheinfeldt2010" label="Scheinfeldt 2010" key="scheinfeldt2010a">
                    Scheinfeldt, Tom. <title rend="quotes">Stuff Digital Humanists Like: Defining
                        Digital Humanities by Its Values.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Found History</title>. 2 Dec. 2010, accessed December 01,
                    2013, <ref
                        target="http://www.foundhistory.org/2010/12/02/stuff-digital-humanists-like/"
                        >http://www.foundhistory.org/2010/12/02/stuff-digital-humanists-like/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="scheinfeldt2011" label="Scheinfeldt 2011" key="scheinfeldt2011">
                    Scheinfeldt, Tom. (FoundHistory). <title rend="quotes">DH arguments are encoded
                        in code. I disagree with the notion that those arguments must be translated
                        / re-encoded in text.</title> 11 Nov. 2011 2.42 pm. Tweet. Rpt. <title
                        rend="quotes">Words and Code.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title>, 1.1 (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="scheinfeldtshaw2011" label="Scheinfeldt and Shaw 2011"
                    key="scheinfeldtshaw2011"> Scheinfeldt, Tom and Ryan Shaw. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Words and Code.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</title> 1.1 (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schmidt2013" label="Schmidt 2013" key="schmidt2013"> Schmidt,
                    Benjamin. <title rend="quotes">The Data Shows There’s No Real Crisis in the
                        Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The New York Times</title>, November 4, 2013, accessed
                    December 01, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2013/11/04/the-fate-of-the-humanities/the-data-shows-theres-no-real-crisis-in-the-humanities"
                        >http://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2013/11/04/the-fate-of-the-humanities/the-data-shows-theres-no-real-crisis-in-the-humanities</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sherratt2009" label="Sherratt 2009" key="sherratt2009"> Sherratt, Tim.
                        <title rend="italic">Github/Wragge</title>. 15 Sept. 2009, accessed December
                    01, 2013, <ref target="https://github.com/wragge/"
                        >https://github.com/wragge/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sherratt2011a" label="Sherratt 2011a" key="sherratt2011a"> Sherratt,
                    Tim. <title rend="italic">The Real Face of White Australia.</title> 21 Sept.
                    2011a, accessed December 01, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://invisibleaustralians.org/faces/"
                        >http://invisibleaustralians.org/faces/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sherratt2011b" label="Sherratt 2011b" key="sherratt2011b"> Sherratt,
                    Tim. <title rend="quotes">The Real Face of White Australia.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">discontents</title>. 21 Sept. 2011b, accessed December 01,
                    2013, <ref target="http://discontents.com.au/the-real-face-of-white-australia/"
                        >http://discontents.com.au/the-real-face-of-white-australia/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="short2005" label="Short et al. 2005-2008" key="short2005"> Short,
                    Harold, Marilyn Deegan et al. <title rend="italic">AHRC Methods Network</title>,
                    2005 – 2008, accessed December 01, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://www.methodsnetwork.ac.uk/"
                        >http://www.methodsnetwork.ac.uk/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="skallerup2013" label="Skallerup et al. 2013" key="skallerup2013">
                    Skallerup, Lee et al. <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities: Egalitarian or
                        the New Elite?,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2013 Conference Abstracts</title>,
                    University of Lincoln-Nebraska, 16 – 19 July 2013, pp.406-408.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="svensson2010" label="Svensson 2010" key="svensson2010"> Svensson,
                    Patrik. <title rend="quotes">The Landscape of Digital Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 4:1 (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="svensson2011" label="Svensson 2011" key="svensson2011b"> Svensson,
                    Patrik. <title rend="quotes">The digital humanities as a humanities
                        project.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Arts and Humanities in Higher Education</title> 11.1-2
                    (2011): 42-60. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tate1957" label="Tate 1945" key="tate1957"> Tate, Allen. <title
                        rend="quotes">The New Provincialism: With an Epilogue on the Southern
                        Novel</title> (1945). <title rend="italic">The Man of Letters in the Modern
                        World: Selected Essays, 1928-1955. London: Thames and Hudson,</title> 1957:
                    325.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="terras2013" label="Terras et al. 2013" key="terras2013"> Terras,
                    Melissa, Nyhan, Julianne, Vanhoutte, Edward. <title rend="italic">Defining
                        Digital Humanities: a Reader</title>. Farnham: Ashgate, 2013. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thaller2012" label="Thaller 2012" key="thaller2012"> Thaller, Manfred.
                        <title rend="quotes">Controversies Around the Digital Humanities: An
                        Agenda.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Historical Social Research</title> 37:3 (2012):
                    7-23.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="thatcamp2012" label="THATCamp 2012" key="thatcamp2012"> THATCamp,
                        <title rend="italic">THATCamp (The Humanities and Technology Camp)
                        Theory</title>. Rutgers University. 13-14 Oct. 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="turkel2011" label="Turkel 2011" key="turkel2011"> Turkel, William J.
                        <title rend="quotes">Intervention: Hacking History, from Analogue to Digital
                        and Back Again.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Rethinking History</title> 15:2 (2011): 287-296.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="underwood2011" label="Underwood 2011" key="underwood2011"> Underwood,
                    Ted. <title rend="quotes">Why digital humanities isn’t actually <soCalled>the
                            next thing in literary studies.</soCalled>
                    </title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Stone and the Shell</title>. 27 Nov. 2011, accessed
                    December 01, 2013, <ref
                        target="http://tedunderwood.com/2011/12/27/why-we-dont-actually-want-to-be-the-next-thing-in-literary-studies/"
                        >http://tedunderwood.com/2011/12/27/why-we-dont-actually-want-to-be-the-next-thing-in-literary-studies/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vanhuyssteen2000" label="Van Huyssteen 2000" key="vanhuyssteen2000">
                    Van Huyssteen, J. Wentzel. <title rend="quotes">Postfoundationalism and
                        Interdisciplinarity: A Response to Jerome Stone.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Zygon</title> 35:2 (June 2000): 427–439.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="williams2000" label="Williams 2000" key="williams2000"> Williams,
                    Rosalind. <title rend="quotes">All That Is Solid Melts into Air: Historians of
                        Technology in the Information Revolution.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Technology and Culture</title> 41:4 (2000): 641–668.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zittrain2008" label="Zittrain 2008" key="zittrain2008"> Zittrain,
                    Jonathan L. <title rend="italic">The Future of the Internet — And How to Stop
                        It</title>. New Haven: Yale University Press, 2008.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
