<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Technical Evolution of Vannevar Bush’s Memex </title>
            <author>Belinda Barnet</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Belinda <dhq:family>Barnet</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Swinburne University of Technology, Melbourne</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>belinda.barnet at gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Belinda Barnet is Lecturer in Media and Communications at Swinburne University,
                     Melbourne. Prior to her appointment at Swinburne she worked at Ericsson
                     Australia, where she managed the development of 3G mobile content services and
                     developed an obsession with technical evolution. Belinda did her PhD on the
                     history of hypertext at the University of New South Wales, and has research
                     interests in digital media, digital art, convergent journalism and the mobile
                     internet. She has published widely on new media theory and culture.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000015</idno>
            <idno type="volume">002</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2008-06-21">21 June 2008</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace"
                  rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword
                     taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2008-06-14" who="jf">Added final metadata, bio and abstract, publication
            statement, proofreading corrections. Restored # to targets where it was missing, for
            consistency.</change>
         <change when="2008-04-26" who="Flanders">Encoded document</change>
         <change when="2008-05-24" who="Ashwini"> Added date, id, issue, vol attributes to root
            element, revised encoding of the change element dated 2008-04-26, removed "#" from
            target attribute of ref element, encoded external links as xref in the listBibl, removed
            top xsl declaration </change>
         <change when="2008-06-16" who="Ashwini">Updated revisionDesc format, added details to
            publicationStmt, changed xref to ref for validation with new schema, added some missing
            "#" to target attribute and removed "##".</change>
         <change when="2008-06-20" who="jf">Changed email address, made authorial changes.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>This article describes the evolution of the design of Vannevar Bush's Memex, tracing
               its roots in Bush's earlier work with analog computing machines, and his
               understanding of the technique of associative memory. It argues that Memex was the
               product of a particular engineering culture, and that the machines that preceded
               Memex — the Differential Analyzer and the Selector in particular — helped engender
               this culture, and the discourse of analogue computing itself.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Can we say that technical machines have their own genealogies, their own evolutionary
               dynamic?</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction: Technical Evolution</head>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#eldredge2004">The key difference [between material
                  cultural evolution and biological evolution] is that biological systems
                  predominantly have <q>vertical</q> transmission of genetically ensconced
                  information, meaning parents to offspring… Not so in material cultural systems,
                  where horizontal transfer is rife — and arguably the more important dynamic
                  .</quote>
               <ref target="#eldredge2004">Paleontologist Dr. Niles Eldredge, interview with the
                  author</ref>
            </cit>
            <p>Since the early days of Darwinism, analogies have been drawn between biological
               evolution and the evolution of technical objects and systems. It is obvious that
               technologies change over time; we can see this in the fact that technologies come in
               generations; they adapt and adopt characteristics over time, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#guattari1995">one suppressing the other as it
                     becomes obsolete</quote>
                  <ptr target="#guattari1995" loc="40"/>
               </cit>. The technical artefact constitutes a series of objects, a <q>lineage</q> or a
               line. From the middle of the nineteenth century on, writers have been remarking on
               this basic analogy – and on the alarming rate at which technological change is
               accelerating. But as Eldredge points out, the analogy can only go so far;
               technological systems are not like biological systems in a number of important ways,
               most obviously the fact that they are the products of conscious design. Unlike
               biological organisms, technical objects are <emph>invented</emph>. </p>
            <p>Inventors learn by experience and experiment, and they learn by watching other
               machines work in the form of technical prototypes. They also copy and <q>transfer</q>
               ideas and techniques between machines, co-opting innovations at a whim. Technological
               innovation thus has Lamarckian features, which are forbidden in biology <ptr
                  target="#ziman2003" loc="5"/>. Inventors can borrow ideas from contemporary
               technologies, or even from the past. There is no <q>extinction</q> in technological
               evolution: ideas, designs and innovations can be co-opted and transferred both
               retroactively and laterally. This retroactive and lateral <q>transfer</q> of
               innovations is what distinguishes technical evolution from biological evolution,
               which is characterised by vertical transfer (parents to offspring). As the American
               paleontologist Niles Eldredge observed in an interview with the author,</p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#eldredge2004">Makers copy each other, patents affording
                  only fleeting protection. Thus, instead of the neatly bifurcating trees [you see
                  in biological evolution], you find what is best described as "networks"-consisting
                  of an historical signal of what came before what, obscured often to the point of
                  undetectability by this lateral transfer of subsequent ideas .</quote>
               <ref target="#eldredge2004">Niles Eldredge, interview with the author</ref>
            </cit>
            <p>Can we say that technical machines have their own genealogies, their own evolutionary
               dynamic? It is my contention that we can, and I have argued elsewhere that in order
               to tell the story of a machine, one must trace the path of these transferrals, paying
               particular attention to technical <emph>prototypes</emph> and to also to
                  <emph>techniques</emph>, or ways of doing things. A good working prototype can
               send shockwaves throughout an engineering community, and often inspires a host of new
               machines in quick succession. Similarly, an effective technique (for example, storing
               and retrieving information associatively) can spread between innovations rapidly.</p>
            <p>In this article I will be telling the story of particular technical machine –
               Vannevar Bush’s Memex. Memex was an electro-mechanical device designed in the 1930’s
               to provide easy access to information stored associatively on microfilm. It is often
               hailed as the precursor to hypertext and the web. Linda C. Smith undertook a
               comprehensive citation context analysis of literary and scientific articles produced
               after the 1945 publication of Bush's article on the device, <title rend="quotes">As
                  We May Think</title> in the <title rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</title>. She
               found that there is a conviction, without dissent, that modern hypertext is traceable
               to this article <ptr target="#smith1991" loc="265"/>. In each decade since the Memex
               design was published, commentators have not only lauded it as vision, but also
               asserted that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#smith1991">technology [has] finally caught up with
                     this vision</quote>
                  <ptr target="#smith1991" loc="278"/>
               </cit>. For all the excitement, it is important to remember that Memex was never
               actually built; it exists entirely on paper. Because the design was first published
               in the summer of 1945, at the end of a war effort and with the birth of computers,
               theorists have often associated it with the post-War information boom. In fact, Bush
               had been writing about it since the early 1930s, and the Memex paper went through
               several different versions. </p>
            <p>The social and cultural influence of Bush’s inventions are well known, and his
               political role in the development of the atomic bomb are also well known. What is not
               so well known is the way the Memex came about as a result of both Bush’s earlier work
               with analog computing machines, and his understanding of the <q>mechanism</q> or
               technique of associative memory. I would like to show that Memex was the product of a
               particular engineering culture, and that the machines that preceded Memex — the
               Differential Analyzer and the Selector in particular — helped engender this culture,
               and the discourse of analogue computing, in the first place. The artefacts of
               engineering, particularly in the context of a school such as MIT, are themselves
               productive of new techniques and new engineering paradigms. Prototype technologies
               create cultures of use around themselves; they create new techniques and new methods
               that were unthinkable prior to the technology. This was especially so for the
               Analyzer. </p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#owens1991">In the context of the early 20th-century
                  engineering school, the analyzers were not only tools but paradigms, and they
                  taught mathematics and method and modeled the character of engineering.</quote>
               <ptr target="#owens1991" loc="6"/>
            </cit>
            <p>Bush transferred technologies directly from the Analyzer and also the Selector into
               the design of Memex. I will trace this transfer in the first section. He also
               transferred an electro-mechanical model of human associative memory from the nascent
               science of cybernetics, which he was exposed to at MIT, into Memex. We will explore
               this in the second section. In both cases, we will be paying particular attention to
               the structure and architecture of the technologies concerned.</p>
            <p>The idea that technical artefacts evolve in this way, by the transfer of both
               technical innovations (for example, microfilm) and techniques (for example,
               association as a storage technique), was popularised by French technology historian
               Bertrand Gille. I will be mobilising Gille’s theories here as I trace the evolution
               of the Memex design. We will begin with Bush’s first analogue computer, the
               Differential Analyzer.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Analyzer and the Selector</head>
            <p>The Differential Analyzer was a giant, electromechanical gear and shaft machine which
               was put to work during the war calculating artillery ranging tables and the profiles
               of radar antennas. In the late 1930s and early 1940s, it was <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#owens1991">the most important computer in existence
                     in the US</quote>
                  <ptr target="#owens1991" loc="3"/>
               </cit>. Before this time, the word <q>computer</q> had meant a large group of mostly
               female humans performing equations by hand or on limited mechanical calculators. The
               Analyzer evaluated and solved these equations by mechanical integration. It created a
               small revolution at MIT. Many of the people who worked on the machine (e.g. Harold
               Hazen, Gordon Brown, Claude Shannon) later made contributions to feedback control,
               information theory, and computing <ptr target="#mindell2000"/>. The machine was a
               huge success which brought prestige and a flood of federal money to MIT and Bush. </p>
            <p>However, by the spring of 1950, the Analyzer was gathering dust in a storeroom — the
               project had died. Why did it fail? Why did the world’s most important analogue
               computer end up in a back room within five years? This story will itself be related
               to why Memex was never built; research into analogue computing technology in the
               interwar years, the Analyzer in particular, contributed to the rise of digital
               computing. It demonstrated that <emph>machines could automate the calculus</emph>,
               that machines could automate human cognitive techniques.</p>
            <p>The decade between the Great War and the Depression was a bull market for engineering
                  <ptr target="#owens1991" loc="29"/>. Enrolment in the MIT Electrical Engineering
               Department almost doubled in this period, and the decade witnessed the rapid
               expansion of graduate programs. The interwar years found corporate and philanthropic
               donors more willing to fund research and development within engineering departments,
               and there were serious problems to be worked on generated by communications failures
               during the Great War. In particular, engineers were trying to predict the operating
               characteristics of power-transmission lines, long-distance telephone lines,
               commercial radio and other communications technologies (Beniger calls this the <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#beniger1986">early</quote> period of the Control Revolution
                  <ptr target="#beniger1986" loc="19"/>). MIT’s Engineering Department undertook a
               major assault on the mathematical study of long-distance lines. </p>
            <p>Of particular interest to the engineers was the Carson equation for transmission
               lines. This was a simple equation, but it required intensive mathematical integration
               to solve.</p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#owens1991">Early in 1925 Bush suggested to his Graduate
                  Student Herbert Stewart that he devise a machine to facilitate the recording of
                  the areas needed for the Carson equation … [and a colleague] suggested that
                  Stewart interpret the equation electrically rather than mechanically.</quote>
               <ptr target="#owens1991" loc="7"/>
            </cit>
            <p>So the equation was transferred to an electro-mechanical device: the Product
               Intergraph. Many of the early analogue computers that followed Bush’s machines were
               designed to automate existing mathematical equations. This particular machine
               physically mirrored the equation itself. It incorporated the use of a mechanical
                  <q>integrator</q> to record the areas under the curves (and thus the integrals),
               which was</p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#hartree2000">… in essence a variable-speed gear, and
                  took the form of a rotating horizontal disk on which a small knife-edged wheel
                  rested. The wheel was driven by friction, and the gear ratio was altered by
                  varying the distance of the wheel from the axis of rotation of the disk.</quote>
               <ptr target="#hartree2000"/>
            </cit>
            <p>A second version of this machine incorporated two wheel-and-disc integrators, and it
               was a great success. Bush observed the success of the machine, and particularly the
               later incorporation of the two wheel-and-disc integrators, and decided to make a
               larger one, with more integrators and a more general application than the Carson
               equation. By the fall of 1928, Bush had secured funds from MIT to build a new
               machine. He called it the Differential Analyzer, after an earlier device proposed by
               Lord Kelvin which might externalise the calculus and <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#hartree2000">mechanically integrate</quote> its solution <ptr
                  target="#hartree2000"/>. </p>
            <p>As Bertrand Gille observes, a large part of technical invention occurs by transfer,
               whereby the functioning of a structure is analogically transposed onto another
               structure, or the same structure is generalised outwards <ptr target="#gille1986"
                  loc="40"/>. This is what happened with the Analyzer — Bush saw the outline of such
               a machine in the Product Integraph. The Differential Analyzer was rapidly assembled
               in 1930, and part of the reason it was so quickly done was that it incorporated a
               number of existing engineering developments, particularly a device called a torque
               amplifier, designed by Niemann <ptr target="#shurkin1996" loc="97"/>. But the disk
               integrator, a technology borrowed from the Product Intergraph, was the heart of the
               Analyzer and the means by which it performed its calculations. When combined with the
               torque amplifier, the Analyzer was <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#owens1991">essentially an elegant, dynamical,
                     mechanical model of the differential equation</quote>
                  <ptr target="#owens1991" loc="14"/>
               </cit>. Although Lord Kelvin had suggested such a machine previously, Bush was the
               first to build it on such a large scale, and it happened at a time when there was a
               general and urgent need for such precision. It created a small revolution at MIT.</p>
            <p>In engineering science, there is an emphasis on working prototypes or
                  <q>deliverables</q>. As Professor of Computer Science Andries van Dam put it in an
               interview with the author, when engineers talk about work, they mean <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#vandam1999">work in the sense of machines, software,
                     algorithms, things that are <emph>concrete</emph>
                  </quote>
                  <ptr target="#vandam1999"/>
               </cit>. This emphasis on concrete work was the same in Bush’s time. Bush had
               delivered something which had been previously only been dreamed about; this meant
               that others could come to the laboratory and learn by observing the machine, by
               watching it integrate, by imagining other applications. A working prototype is
               different to a dream or white paper — it actually creates its own milieu, it
                  <emph>teaches those who use it</emph> about the possibilities it contains and its
               material technical limits. Bush himself recognised this, and believed that those who
               used the machine acquired what he called a <soCalled>mechanical calculus</soCalled>,
               an internalised knowledge of the machine. When the army wanted to build their own
               machine at the Aberdeen Proving Ground, he sent them a mechanic who had helped
               construct the Analyzer. The army wanted to pay the man machinist’s wages; Bush
               insisted he be hired as a consultant <ptr target="#owens1991" loc="24"/>. <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#bush1970">I never consciously taught this man any
                     part of the subject of differential equations; but in building that machine,
                     managing it, he learned what differential equations were himself … [it] was
                     interesting to discuss the subject with him because he had learned the calculus
                     in mechanical terms — a strange approach, and yet he understood it. That is, he
                     did not understand it in any formal sense, he understood the fundamentals; he
                     had it under his skin.</quote>
                  <ref target="#bush1970">Bush 1970, 262 cited in Owens 1991, 24</ref>
               </cit>
            </p>
            <p>Watching the Analyzer work did more than just teach people about the calculus. It
               also taught people about what might be possible for mechanical calculation — for
                  <emph>analogue computers</emph>. Several laboratories asked for plans, and
               duplicates were set up at the US Army’s Ballistic Research Laboratory, in Maryland,
               and at the Moore School of Electrical Engineering at the University of Pennsylvania
                  <ptr target="#shurkin1996" loc="99"/>. The machine assembled at the Moore school
               was much larger than the MIT machine, and the engineers had the advantage of being
               able to learn from the mistakes and limits of the MIT machine <ptr loc="102"
                  target="#shurkin1996"/>. Bush also created several more Analyzers, and in 1936 the
               Rockefeller Foundation awarded MIT $85,000 to build the Rockefeller Differential
               Analyzer <ptr target="#owens1991" loc="17"/>. This provided more opportunities for
               graduate research, and brought prestige and a flood of funding to MIT. </p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#owens1991">But what is interesting about the Rockefeller
                  Differential Analyzer is what remained the same. Electrically or not,
                  automatically or not, the newest edition of Bush’s analyzer still interpreted
                  mathematics in terms of mechanical rotations, still depended on expertly machined
                  wheel-and-disc integrators, and still drew its answers as curves.</quote>
               <ptr loc="32" target="#owens1991"/>
            </cit>
            <p>Its technical processes remained the same. It was an analogue device, and it
               literally turned around a central analogy: the rotation of the wheel shall be the
               area under the graph (and thus the integrals). The Analyzer directly mirrored the
               task at hand; there was a mathematical transparency to it which at once held
               observers captive and promoted, in its very workings, the <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#owens1991">language of early 20th-century
                     engineering</quote>
                  <ptr target="#owens1991" loc="32"/>
               </cit>. There were visitors to the lab, and military and corporate representatives
               that would watch the machine turn its motions. It seemed the adumbration of future
               technology. Harold Hazen, the head of the Electrical Engineering Department in 1940
               predicted the Analyzer would <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#hazen1940">mark the start of a new era in mechanized
                     calculus</quote>
                  <ref target="#hazen1940">Hazen 1940, 101 cited in Owens 1991, 4</ref>
               </cit>. Analogue technology held much promise, especially for military computation —
               and the Analyzer had created a new era. The entire direction and culture of the MIT
               lab changed around this machine to woo sponsors <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="39"/>.
               In the late 1930s the department became the Center of Analysis for Calculating
               Machines.</p>
            <p>Many of the Analyzers built in the 1930s were built using military funds. The
               creation of the first Analyzer, and Bush’s <emph>promotion</emph> of it as a
               calculation device for ballistic analysis, had created a link between the military
               and engineering science at MIT which was to endure for over thirty years. Manuel De
               Landa (1994) puts great emphasis in his work on this connection, particularly as it
               was further developed during WWII. As he puts it, Bush created a
                  <soCalled>bridge</soCalled> between the engineers and the military, he <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#delanda1994">connected scientists to the blueprints
                     of generals and admirals</quote>
                  <ptr loc="119" target="#delanda1994"/>
               </cit>, and this relationship would grow infinitely stronger during WWII.
               Institutions that had previously occupied exclusive ground such as physics and
               military intelligence had begun communicating in the late 1930s, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#delanda1994">communities often suspicious of one
                     another: the inventors and the scientists on the one side and the warriors on
                     the other</quote>
                  <ptr target="#delanda1994" loc="36"/>
               </cit>. </p>
            <p>This paper has been arguing that the Analyzer <foreign>qua</foreign> technical
               artefact accomplished something equally important: as a prototype, it demonstrated
               the potential of analogue computing technology for analysis, and engendered an
               engineering culture around itself that took the machine to be a teacher. This is why,
               even after the obsolescence of the Analyzer, it was kept around at MIT for its
               educational value <ptr target="#owens1991" loc="23"/>. It demonstrated that machines
               could automate the calculus, and that machines could mirror human tasks in an elegant
               fashion: something which required proof in steel and brass. The <q>aura</q> generated
               by the Analyzer as prototype was not lost on the military.</p>
            <p>In 1935, the Navy came to Bush for advice on machines to crack coding devices like
               the new Japanese cipher machines <ptr target="#burke1991" loc="147"/>. They wanted a
               long-term project that would give the United States the most technically advanced
               cryptanalytic capabilities in the world, a super-fast machine to count the
               coincidences of letters in two messages or copies of a single message. Bush assembled
               a research team for this project that included Claude Shannon, one of the early
               information theorists and a significant part of the emerging cybernetics community
                  <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="40"/>.</p>
            <p>There were three new technologies emerging at the time which handled information:
               photoelectricity, microfilm and digital electronics. </p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#burke1991">All three were just emerging, but, unlike the
                  fragile magnetic recording his students were exploring, they appeared to be ready
                  to use in calculation machines. Microfilm would provide ultra-fast input and
                  inexpensive mass-memory, photoelectricity would allow high-speed sensing and
                  reproduction, and digital electronics would allow astonishingly fast and
                  inexpensive control and calculation.</quote>
               <ptr target="#burke1991" loc="147"/>
            </cit>
            <p>Bush transferred these three technologies to the new design. This decision was not
               pure genius on his part; they were perfect analogues for a popular conception of how
               the brain worked at the time. The scientific community at MIT were developing a
               pronounced interest in man-machine analogues, and although Claude Shannon had not yet
               published his information theory it was already being formulated, and there was much
               discussion around MIT about how the brain might process information in the manner of
               an analogue machine. Bush thought and designed in terms of analogies between brain
               and machine, electricity and information. This was also the central research agenda
               of Norbert Weiner and Warren McCulloch, both at MIT, who were at the time <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#nyce1991">working on parallels they saw between neural
                  structure and process and computation</quote> (<ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="63"/>;
               see also <ptr target="#hayles1999"/>). To Bush and Shannon, microfilm and
               photoelectricity seemed perfect analogues to the <emph>electrical relay circuits and
                  neural substrates of the human brain </emph>and their capacities for managing
               information. </p>
            <p>Bush called this machine the Comparator — it was to do the hard work of comparing
               text and letters for the humble human mind. Like the analytic machines before it and
               all other technical machines being built at the time, this was an analogue device; it
               directly mirrored the task at hand on a mechanical level. In this case, it directly
               mirrored the operations of <q>searching</q> and <q>associating</q> on a mechanical
               level, and, Bush believed, it mirrored the operations of the human mind and memory.
               Bush began the project in mid-1937, while he was working on the Rockefeller Analyzer,
               and agreed to deliver a code-cracking device based on these technologies by the next
               summer <ptr target="#burke1991" loc="147"/>.</p>
            <p>But immediately, there were problems in its development. Technical objects often
               depart from their fabricating intention; sometimes because they are <emph>used</emph>
               differently to what they were invented for, and sometimes because the
                  <emph>technology itself</emph> breaks down. Microfilm did not behave the way Bush
               wanted it to. As a material it was very fragile, sensitive to light and heat, and
               tore easily; it had too many <q>bugs</q>. It was decided to use paper tape with
               minute holes, although paper was only one-twentieth as effective as microfilm <ptr
                  target="#burke1991" loc="147"/>. There were subsequent problems with this
               technology — paper itself is flimsy, and it refused to work well for long periods
               intact. There were also problems shifting the optical reader between the two message
               tapes. Bush was working on the Analyzer at the time, and didn’t have the resources to
               fix these components effectively. By the time the Comparator was turned over to the
               Navy, it was very unreliable, and didn’t even start up when it was unpacked in
               Washington <ptr target="#burke1991" loc="148"/>. The Comparator prototype ended up
               gathering dust in a Navy storeroom, but much of the architecture was transferred to
               subsequent designs.</p>
            <p>By this time, Bush had also started work on the Memex design. He transferred much of
               the architecture from the Comparator, including photoelectrical components, an
               optical reader and microfilm. In tune with the times, Bush had developed a
               fascination for microfilm in particular as an information storage technology, and
               although it had failed to work properly in the Comparator, he wanted to try it again.
               It would appear as the central technology in the Rapid Selector and also in the Memex
               design.</p>
            <p>In the 1930s, many believed that microfilm would make information universally
               accessible and thus spark an intellectual revolution (<ptr target="#farkas1990"
                  loc="16–22"/>, cited in <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="49"/>). Like many others, he
               had been enthusiastically exploring its potential in his writing <ptr
                  target="#bush1991a"/>, <ptr target="#bush1939"/> as well as the Comparator; the
               Encyclopaedia Britannica <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991c">could be reduced to
                  the volume of a matchbox. A library of a million volumes could be compressed into
                  one end of a desk</quote> he wrote <ptr target="#bush1991c" loc="93"/>. In 1938,
               H.G. Wells even wrote about a <quote rend="inline" source="#wells1938">Permanent
                  World Encyclopaedia</quote> or Planetary Memory that would carry all the world’s
               knowledge. It was based on microfilm. </p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#wells1938 #nyce1991">By means of microfilm, the rarest
                  and most intricate documents and articles can be studied now at first hand,
                  simultaneously in a score of projection rooms. There is no practical obstacle
                  whatever now to the creation of an efficient index to all human knowledge, ideas,
                  achievements, to the creation, that is, of a complete planetary memory for all
                  mankind.</quote>
               <dhq:citRef>
                  <ptr target="#wells1938"/>, cited in <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="50"/>
               </dhq:citRef>
            </cit>

            <p>Microfilm promised <emph>faithful reproduction</emph> as well as miniaturisation. It
               was state-of-the-art technology, and not only did it seem the perfect analogy for
               material stored in the neural substrate of the human brain, it seemed to have a
               certain permanence the brain lacked. Bush put together a proposal for a new microfilm
               selection device, based on the architecture of the Comparator, in 1937. Its stated
               research agenda and intention was</p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#bagg1961">
                  <list>
                     <item>Construction of experimental equipment to test the feasibility of a
                        device which would search reels of coded microfilm at high speed and which
                        would copy selected frames on the fly, for printout and use.</item>
                     <item>Investigation of the practical utility of such equipment by experimental
                        use in a library.</item>
                     <item>Further development aimed at exploration of the possibilities for
                        introducing such equipment into libraries generally.</item>
                  </list>
               </quote>
               <ref target="#bagg1961">Bagg and Stevens 1961, cited in Nyce 1991, 41</ref>
            </cit>
            <p>Corporate funding was secured for the Selector by pitching it as a microfilm machine
               to modernise the library <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="41"/>. Abstracts of documents
               were to be captured by this new technology and reduced in size by a factor of 25. As
               with the Comparator, long rolls of this film were to be spun past a photoelectric
               sensing station. If a match occurred between the code submitted by a researcher and
               the abstract codes attached to this film <ptr target="#burke1991" loc="151"/>, the
               researcher was presented with the article itself and any articles previously
               associated with it. This was to be used in a public library, and unlike his nascent
               idea concerning Memex, he wanted to tailor it to commercial and government
               record-keeping markets. </p>
            <p>Bush considered the Selector as a step towards the mechanised control of scientific
               information, which was of immediate concern to him as a scientist. According to him,
               the fate of the nation depended on the effective management of these ideas lest they
               be lost in a brewing data storm. Progress in information management was not only
               inevitable, it was <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1970">essential if the nation is to be
                     strong</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1970" loc="149"/>
               </cit>. This was his fabricating intention. He had been looking for support for a
               Memex-like device for years, but after the failure of the Comparator, finding funds
               for this <quote rend="inline" source="#burke1991">library of the future</quote> was
               very hard <ptr target="#burke1991" loc="149"/>. Then in 1938, Bush received funding
               from the National Cash Register Company and the Eastman Kodak Company for the
               development of an apparatus for rapid selection, and he began to transfer the
               architecture from the Comparator across to the new design. </p>
            <p>But as Burke writes, the technology of microfilm and the tape-scanners began to
               impose their technical limitations; <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#burke1991">[a]lmost as soon as it was begun, the
                     Selector project drifted away from its original purpose and began to show some
                     telling weaknesses … Bush planned to spin long rolls of 35mm film containing
                     the codes and abstracts past a photoelectric sensing station so fast, at speeds
                     of six feet per second, that 60,000 items could be tested in one minute. This
                     was at least one hundred-fifty times faster than the mechanical
                     tabulator.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#burke1991" loc="150"/>
               </cit>
            </p>
            <p>The Selector’s scanning station was similar to that used in the Comparator. But in
               the Selector, the card containing the code of interest to the researcher would be
               stationary. Bush and others associated with the project <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#burke1991">were so entranced with the speed of
                     microfilm tape that little attention was paid to coding schemes</quote>
                  <ptr target="#burke1991" loc="151"/>
               </cit>, and when Bush handed the project over to three of his researchers, John
               Howard, Lawrence Steinhardt and John Coombs, it was floundering. After three more
               years of intensive research and experimentation with microfilm, Howard had to inform
               the Navy that the machine would not work <ptr target="#burke1991" loc="149"/>.
               Microfilm, claimed Howard, would deform at such speeds and could not be aligned so
               that coincidences could be identified. Microfilm warps under heat, and it cannot take
               great strain or tension without distorting.</p>
            <p>Solutions were suggested (among them slowing down the machine, and checking abstracts
               before they were used) <ptr target="#burke1991" loc="154"/>, but none of these were
               particularly effective, and a working machine wasn’t ready until the fall of 1943. At
               one stage, because of an emergency problem with Japanese codes, it was rushed to
               Washington — but because it was so unreliable, it went straight back into storage. So
               many parts were pulled out that the machine was never again operable <ptr
                  target="#burke1991" loc="158"/>. In 1998, the Selector made Bruce Sterling’s Dead
               Media List, consigned forever to a lineage of failed technologies. Microfilm did not
               behave the way Bush and his team wanted it to. It had its own material limits, and
               these didn’t support speed of access.</p>
            <p>In the evolution of any machine, there will be internal limits generated by the
               behaviour of the technology itself; Gille calls these <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#gille1986">endogenous</quote> limits <ptr target="#gille1986"/>.
               Endogenous limits are encountered only in practice — they effect the actual
                  <emph>implementation</emph> of an idea. In engineering practice, these failures
               can teach inventors about the material potentials of the technology as well. The
               Memex design altered significantly through the 1950s; Bush had learned from the
               technical failures he was encountering. But most noticeable of all, Bush stopped
               talking about microfilm and about hardware.</p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#burke1991">By the 1960’s the project and machine
                  failures associated with the Selector, it seems, made it difficult for Bush to
                  think about Memex in concrete terms.</quote>
               <ptr target="#burke1991" loc="161"/>
            </cit>
            <p>The Analyzer, meanwhile, was being used extensively during WWII for ballistic
               analysis and calculation. Wartime security prevented its public announcement until
               1945, when it was hailed by the press as a great <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#owens1991">electromechanical brain</quote> ready to advance science by
               freeing it from the pick-and-shovel work of mathematics (<ref target="#owens1991">
                  <title rend="italic">Life</title> magazine, cited by Owens 1991, 3</ref>). It had
               created an entire culture around itself. But by the mid-1940s, the enthusiasm had
               died down; the machine seemed to pale beside the new generation of digital machines.
               The war had also released an unprecedented sum of money into MIT and spawned numerous
               other new laboratories. It <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#owens1991">ushered in a variety of new computation
                     tasks, in the field of large-volume data analysis and real-time operation,
                     which were beyond the capacity of the Rockefeller instrument</quote>
                  <ptr target="#owens1991" loc="5"/>
               </cit>. By 1950, the Analyzer had become an antique, conferred to back-room storage. </p>
            <p>What happened? The reasons The Analyzer fell into disuse were quite different to the
               Selector; its limits were <emph>exogenous</emph> to the technical machine itself.
               They were related to a fundamental paradigm shift within computing, from analogue to
               digital. According to Gille, the birth of a new technical system is rapid and
               unforeseeable; new technical systems are born with the limits of the old technical
               systems, and the period of change is brutal, fast and discontinuous. In 1950, Warren
               Weaver and Samuel Caldwell met to discuss the Analyzer and the analogue computing
               program it had inspired at MIT, a large program which had become out of date more
               swiftly than anyone could have imagined. They noted that in 1936, no one could have
               expected that within ten years the whole field of <q>computer science</q> would so
               quickly overtake Bush’s project (<ref target="#weaver1950a">Weaver and
               Caldwell</ref>, cited in <ptr target="#owens1991" loc="4"/>). Bush, and the
               department at MIT which had formed itself around the Analyzer and analogue computing,
               had been left behind.</p>
            <p>I do not have the space here to trace the evolution of digital computing at this time
               in the US and the UK — excellent accounts have already been written by <ptr
                  target="#beniger1986"/>, <ptr target="#shurkin1996"/>, <ptr target="#ceruzzi1998"
               />, <ptr target="#edwards1997"/> and <ptr target="#delanda1994"/> to name a few. All
               we need to realise at this point is that the period between 1945 and 1967, the years
               between the publication of the first and the final versions of the Memex essays
               respectively, had witnessed enormous change. The period saw not only the rise of
               digital computing, beginning with the construction of a few machines in the post-war
               period and developing into widespread mainframe processing for American business, it
               also saw the explosive growth of commercial television <ptr target="#spar2001"
                  loc="194"/>, and the beginnings of satellite broadcasting <ptr target="#spar2001"
                  loc="197"/>. As Beniger sees it, the world had discovered information as a means
               of control <ptr target="#beniger1986" loc="vii"/>.</p>
            <p>It is important to understand, however, that Bush was not a part of this revolution.
               He had not been trained in digital computation or information theory, and knew little
               about the emerging field of digital computing. He was immersed in a different
               technical system: analogue machines interpreted mathematics in terms of mechanical
               rotations, storage and memory as a physical <q>holding</q> of information, and drew
               their answers as curves. They directly mirrored the operations of the calculus.
               Warren Weaver expressed his regret over the passing of analogue machines and the
               Analyzer in a letter to the director of MIT's Center of Analysis: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#owens1991">It seems rather a pity not to have around
                     such a place as MIT a really impressive Analogue computer; for there is a
                     vividness and directness of meaning of the electrical and mechanical processes
                     involved ... which can hardly fail, I would think, to have a very considerable
                     educational value.</quote>
                  <ref target="#owens1991">Weaver, cited in Owens 1991, 5</ref>
               </cit>
            </p>
            <p>The passing away of analogue computing was the passing away of an ethos: machines as
               mirrors of mathematical tasks. But Bush and Memex remained in the analogue era; in
               all versions of the Memex essay, his goal remained the same: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#nyce1991">he sought to develop a machine that
                     mirrored and recorded the patterns of the human brain</quote>
                  <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="123"/>
               </cit>, even when this era of direct reflection and analogy in mechanical workings
               had passed. </p>
            <p>Technological evolution moves faster than our ability to adjust to its changes. More
               precisely, it moves faster than the <emph>techniques</emph> that it engenders and the
               culture it forms around itself. Bush expressed some regret over this speed of passage
               near the end of his life, or, perhaps, sadness over the obsolescence of his own
               engineering techniques. </p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#bush1970">The trend had turned in the direction of
                  digital machines, a whole new generation had taken hold. If I mixed with it, I
                  could not possibly catch up with new techniques, and I did not intend to look
                  foolish.</quote>
               <ptr target="#bush1970" loc="208"/>
            </cit>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Human Associative Memory and Biological-Mechanical Analogues</head>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#bush1991b">There is another revolution under way, and it
                  is far more important and significant than [the industrial revolution]. It might
                  be called the mental revolution.</quote>
               <ptr target="#bush1991b" loc="165"/>
            </cit>
            <p>We now turn to Bush’s fascination with, and exposure to, new models of human
               associative memory gaining current in his time. Bush thought and designed his
               machines in terms of biological-mechanical analogues; he sought a symbiosis between
                  <q>natural</q> human thought and his thinking machines. </p>
            <p>As Nyce and Kahn observe, in all versions of the Memex essay (1939, 1945, 1967), Bush
               begins his thesis by explaining the dire problem we face in confronting the great
               mass of the human record, criticising the way information was then organised <ptr
                  target="#nyce1991" loc="56"/>. He then goes on to explain the reason why this form
               of organisation doesn’t work: it is <emph>artificial</emph>. Information should be
               organised by association — this is how the mind works. If we fashion our information
               systems after this mechanism, they will be truly revolutionary.</p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#bush1939">
                  <p>Our ineptitude at getting at the record is largely caused by the artificiality
                     of systems of indexing. When data of any sort are placed in storage, they are
                     filed alphabetically or numerically, and information is found (when it is) by
                     tracing it down from subclass to subclass. It can only be found in one place,
                     unless duplicates are used; one has to have rules as to which path will locate
                     it, and the rules are cumbersome. Having found one item, moreover, one has to
                     emerge from the system and re-enter on a new path.</p>
                  <p>The human mind does not work that way. It operates by association. With one
                     item in grasp, it snaps instantly to the next that is suggested by the
                     association of thoughts, in accordance with some intricate web of trails
                     carried by the cells of the brain.</p>
               </quote>
               <ref target="#bush1939">Bush 1939, 1945, 1967</ref>
            </cit>
            <p>These paragraphs were important enough that they appeared verbatim in all versions of
               the Memex essay — 1939, 1945 and 1967 <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="57"/>. No other
               block of text remained unchanged over time; the technologies used to implement the
               mechanism changed, Memex grew <q>intelligent</q>, the other machines (the Cyclops
               Camera, the Vocoder) disappeared. These paragraphs, however, remain a constant. Given
               this fact, Nelson’s assertion that the major concern of the essay was to point out
               the artificiality of systems of indexing, and to propose the associative mechanism as
               a solution for this <ptr target="#nelson1991" loc="248"/> seems reasonable. Nelson
               also maintains that these central precepts of the design have been <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#nelson1991">ignored</quote> by commentators <ptr
                  target="#nelson1991" loc="245"/>. I would contend that they have not been
                  <emph>ignored</emph>; fragments of these paragraphs are often cited, particularly
               relating to association. What is ignored is the relationship between these two
               paragraphs — the central <emph>contrast </emph>he makes between conventional methods
               of indexing and the mental associations Memex was to support <ptr target="#nyce1991"
                  loc="57"/>. Association was more <q>natural</q> than other forms of indexing —
               more human. This is why it was revolutionary.</p>
            <p>Which is interesting, because Bush’s model of mental association was itself
               technological; the mind <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1970">snapped</quote>
               between allied items, an unconscious movement directed by the trails themselves,
               trails <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1970">of brain or of machine</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1970" loc="191"/>
               </cit>. Association was a technique that worked independently of its substrate, and
               there was no spirit attached to this machine: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1970">my brain runs rapidly — so rapidly I do
                     not fully recognize that the process is going on</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1970" loc="191"/>
               </cit>. The <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1970">speed of action</quote> in the
               retrieval process from neuron to neuron <ptr target="#bush1970" loc="102"/> resulted
               from a <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1970">mechanical switching</quote> (this
               term was omitted from the <title rend="italic">Life</title> reprint of <title
                  rend="italic">Memex II</title>, <ref target="#bush1970">Bush 1970, 100</ref>), and
               the items that this mechanical process resurrected were also stored in the manner of
               magnetic or drum memory: the brain is like a substrate for <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1970">memories, sheets of data</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1970" loc="191"/>
               </cit>.</p>
            <p>Bush’s model of human associative memory was an electro-mechanical one — a model that
               was being keenly developed by Claude Shannon, Warren McCulloch and Walter Pitts at
               MIT, and would result in the McCulloch-Pitts neuron <ptr target="#hayles1999"
                  loc="65"/>. The MIT model of the human neuronal circuit constructed the human in
               terms of the machine, and later articulated it more thoroughly in terms of computer
               switching. In a 1944 letter to Weeks, for example, Bush argued that <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#nyce1991">a great deal of our brain cell activity is
                  closely parallel to the operation of relay circuits</quote>, and that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#nyce1991">one can explore this parallelism…almost
                     indefinitely</quote>
                  <ref target="#nyce1991 ">November 6, 1944; cited in Nyce and Kahn 1991, 62</ref>
               </cit>. </p>
            <p>In the 1930s and 1940s, the popular scientific conception of mind and memory was a
               mechanical one. An object or experience was perceived, transferred to the
               memory-library's receiving station, and then <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#dennett1993">installed in the memory-library for all
                     future reference</quote>
                  <ptr target="#dennett1993" loc="121"/>
               </cit>. It had been known since the early 1900s that the brain comprised a tangle of
               neuronal groups that were interconnected in the manner of a network, and recent
               research had shown that these communicated and <q>stored</q> information across the
               neural substrate, in some instances creating further connections, via minute
               electrical <q>vibrations</q>. According to Bush, memories that were not accessed
               regularly suffered from this neglect by the conscious mind and were prone to fade.
               The pathways of the brain, its indexing system, needed constant electrical
               stimulation to remain strong. This was the problem with the neural network: <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991c">items are not fully permanent, memory is
                     transitory</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991c" loc="102"/>
               </cit>. The major technical problem with human memory was its tendency toward
               decay.</p>
            <p>According to Manuel De Landa, there was also a widespread faith in
               biological-mechanical analogues at the time as models to boost human functions. The
               military had been attempting to develop technologies which mimicked and subsequently
               replaced human faculties for many years <ptr target="#delanda1994" loc="127"/> and
               this was especially heightened in the years before, during and immediately following
               the war. At MIT in particular, there was a tendency to take <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#hatt1968">the image of the machine as the basis for the understanding of
                  man</quote> and vice versa, writes Harold Hatt in his book on Cybernetics <ptr
                  target="#hatt1968" loc="28"/>. The idea that Man and his environment are
               mechanical systems which can be studied, improved, mimicked and controlled was
               growing, and later gave way to disciplines such as cognitive science and artificial
               intelligence. Wiener and McCulloch <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#nyce1991">looked for and worked from parallels they
                     saw between neural structure and process and computation</quote>
                  <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="63"/>
               </cit>, a model which changed with the onset of digital computing to include on/off
               states. The motor should first of all model itself on man, and eventually augment or
               replace him. </p>
            <p>Bush explicitly worked with such methodologies — in fact, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#nyce1991">he not only thought with and in these
                     terms, he built technological projects with them</quote>
                  <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="62"/>
               </cit>. The first step was understanding the mechanical <q>process</q> or nature of
               thought itself; the second step was transferring this process to a machine. So there
               is a double movement within Bush’s work, the location of a <q>natural</q> human
               process within thought, a process which is already machine-like, and the subsequent
               refinement and modelling of a particular technology on that process. Technology
               should depart from nature, it should depart from an extant human process: this saves
               us so much work. If this is done properly, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1970">[it] should be possible to beat the mind
                     decisively in the permanence and clarity of the items resurrected from
                     storage</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1970" loc="191"/>
               </cit>.</p>
            <p>So Memex was first and foremost an extension of human memory and the associative
               movements that the mind makes through information: a mechanical analogue to an
               already mechanical model of memory. Bush transferred this idea into information
               management; Memex was distinct from traditional forms of indexing not so much in its
               mechanism or content, but in the way it organised information based on association.
               The design did not spring from the ether, however; the first Memex design
               incorporates the technical architecture of the Rapid Selector and the methodology of
               the Analyzer — the machines Bush was assembling at the time.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Design of Memex</head>
            <p>Bush’s autobiography, <title rend="italic">Pieces of the Action</title>, and also his
               essay <title rend="quotes">Memex Revisited</title> tell us that he started work on
               the design in the early 1930s <ptr target="#bush1991d" loc="197"/>; <ptr
                  target="#bush1970" loc="130"/>. Nyce and Kahn also note that he sent a letter to
               Warren Weaver describing a Memex-like device in 1937 <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="43"
               />. The first extensive description of it in print, however, is found in the 1939
               essay <title rend="quotes">Mechanization and the Record</title>
               <ptr target="#bush1939"/>. The description in this essay employs the same
                  <emph>methodology</emph> Bush had used to design the Analyzer: combine existing
               lower-level technologies into a single machine with a higher function that automates
               the <quote rend="inline" source="#owens1991">pick-and-shovel</quote> work of the
               human mind <ptr target="#owens1991" loc="3"/>. </p>
            <p>Nyce and Kahn maintain that Bush took this methodology from the Rapid Selector <ptr
                  target="#nyce1991" loc="54"/>: this paper has argued that it was first deployed in
               the Analyzer. The Analyzer was the first working analogue computer at MIT, and it was
               also the first large-scale engineering project to combine lower-level, extant
               technologies and automate what was previously a human cognitive technique: the
               integral calculus. It incorporated two lower-level analogue technologies to
               accomplish this task: the wheel-and-disk integrator and the torque amplifier, as we
               have explored. Surrounded by computers and personal organisers, the idea of
               automating intellectual processes seems obvious to us now — but in the early 1930s
               the idea of automating what was essentially a <emph>function within thought</emph>
               was radical. Bush needed to convince people that it was worthwhile. In 1939, Bush
               wrote:</p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#bush1939">The future means of implementing thought are …
                  fully as worthy of attention by one who wonders what comes next as are new ways of
                  extracting natural resources, or of killing men.</quote>
               <ptr target="#bush1939"/>
            </cit>
            <p>The idea of creating a machine to aid the mind did not belong to Bush, nor did the
               technique of integral calculus (or association for that matter); he was, however,
               arguably the first person to externalise this technology on a grand scale. Observing
               the success of the Analyzer <foreign>qua</foreign> technical artefact, the method
               proved successful. Design on the first microfilm selection device, the Comparator,
               started in 1935. This, too, was a machine to aid the mind: it was essentially a
               counting machine, to tally the coincidence of letters in two messages or copies of a
               single message. It externalised the <soCalled>drudge</soCalled> work of cryptography,
               and Bush <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#burke1991">rightly saw it as the first electronic
                     data-processing machine</quote>
                  <ptr target="#burke1991" loc="147"/>
               </cit>. The Rapid Selector which followed it incorporated much of the same
               architecture, as we have explored — and this architecture was in turn transferred to
               Memex. </p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#nyce1991">The Memex-like machine proposed in Bush’s 1937
                  memo to Weaver shows just how much [the Selector] and the Memex have in common. In
                  the rapid selector, low-level mechanisms for transporting 35mm film, photo-sensors
                  to detect dot patterns, and precise timing mechanisms combined to support the
                  high-order task of information selection. In Memex, photo-optic selection devices,
                  keyboard controls, and dry photography would be combined … to support the process
                  of the human mind.</quote>
               <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="44"/>
            </cit>
            <p>The difference, of course, was that Bush’s proposed Memex would access information
               stored on microfilm by <emph>association</emph>, not numerical indexing. He had
               incorporated another technique (a technique which was itself quite popular among the
               nascent cybernetics community at MIT, and already articulated mind and machine
               together). By describing an imaginary machine, Bush had <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#nyce1991">selected from the existing technologies of
                     the time and made a case for how they should develop in the future</quote>
                  <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="45"/>
               </cit>. But this forecasting did not come from some genetically inherited genius — it
               was an acquired skill: Bush was close to the machine.</p>
            <p>As Professor of Engineering at MIT (and after 1939, President of the Carnegie
               Institute in Washington), Bush was in a unique position — he had access to a pool of
               ideas, techniques and technologies which the general public, and engineers at other
               smaller schools, did not have access to. Bush had a more <q>global</q> view of the
               combinatory possibilities and the technological lineage. Bush himself admitted this;
               in fact, he believed that engineers and scientists were the only people who could or
                  <emph>should</emph> predict the future of technology — anyone else had no idea. In
                  <title rend="quotes">The Inscrutable Thirties</title>, an essay he published in
               1933, he tells us that politicians and the general public simply can’t understand
               technology, they have <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991a">so little true discrimination</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991a" loc="77"/>
               </cit> and are <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991a">wont to visualize scientific
                  triumphs as <foreign>faits accomplis</foreign>
               </quote> before they are even ready, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991a">even as they are being hatched in the
                     laboratory</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991a" loc="75"/>
               </cit>. Bush believed that the prediction and control of the future of technology
               should be left to engineers; only they can <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#nyce1991">distinguish the <emph>possible</emph> from
                     the virtually <emph>impossible</emph>
                  </quote>
                  <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="49"/>
               </cit>, only they can read the future from technical objects.</p>
            <p>Memex was a future technology. It was originally proposed as a desk at which the user
               could sit, equipped with two <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991c">slanting
                  translucent screens</quote> upon which material would be projected for <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991c">convenient reading</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991c" loc="102"/>
               </cit>. There was a keyboard to the right of these screens, and a <q>set of buttons
                  and levers</q> which the user could depress to search the information using an
               electrically-powered optical recognition system. If the user wished to consult a
               certain piece of information, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991c">he [tapped] its code on the keyboard, and
                     the title page of the book promptly appear[ed]</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991c" loc="103"/>
               </cit>. The images were stored on microfilm inside the desk, <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#bush1991c">and the matter of bulk [was] well taken care of</quote> by
               this technology — <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991c">only a small part of the interior is
                     devoted to storage, the rest to mechanism</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991c" loc="102"/>
               </cit>. It looked like an <q>ordinary</q> desk, except it had screens and a keyboard
               attached to it. To add new information to the microfilm file, a photographic copying
               plate was also provided on the desk, but most of the Memex contents would be <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991c">purchased on microfilm ready for
                     insertion</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991c" loc="102"/>
               </cit>. The user could classify material as it came in front of him using a
               teleautograph stylus, and register links between different pieces of information
               using this stylus. This was a piece of furniture from the future, to live in the home
               of a scientist or an engineer, to be used for research and information
               management.</p>
            <p>The 1945 Memex design also introduced the concept of <q>trails</q>, a concept derived
               from work in neuronal storage-retrieval networks at the time, which was a method of
               connecting information by linking units together in a networked manner, similar to
               hypertext paths. The process of making trails was called <q>trailblazing</q>, and was
               based on a mechanical provision <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991c">whereby any item may be caused at will to
                     select immediately and automatically another</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991c" loc="107"/>
               </cit>, just as though these items were being <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991c">gathered together from widely separated
                     sources and bound together to form a new book</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991c" loc="104"/>
               </cit>. Electro-optical devices borrowed from the Rapid Selector used spinning rolls
               of microfilm, abstract codes and a mechanical selection-head inside the desk to find
               and create these links between documents. <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991c">This is the essential feature of the
                     Memex. The process of tying two items together is the important thing</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991c" loc="103"/>
               </cit>. Bush went so far as to suggest that in the future, there would be
               professional trailblazers who took pleasure in creating useful paths through the
               common record in such a fashion. </p>
            <p>The Memex described in <title rend="italic">As We May Think</title> was to have
               permanent trails, and public encyclopaedias, colleague's trails and other information
               could all be joined and then permanently archived for later use. Unlike the trails of
               memory, they would never fade. In <title rend="italic">Memex Revisited</title>,
               however, an adaptive theme emerged whereby the trails were mutable and open to growth
               and change by Memex itself as it observed the owner's habits of association and
               extended upon these <ptr target="#bush1991d" loc="213"/>. After a period of
               observation, Memex would be given instructions to search and build a new trail of
               thought, which it could do later <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991d">even when the owner was not there</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991d" loc="213"/>
               </cit>. This technique was in turn derived from Claude Shannon’s experiments with
               feedback and machine learning, embodied in the <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#bush1991d">mechanical mouse</quote>; <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#bush1991b">A striking form of self adaptable machine
                     is Shannon’s mechanical mouse. Placed in a maze it runs along, butts its head
                     into a wall, turns and tries again, and eventually muddles its way through.
                     But, placed again at the entrance, it proceeds through without error making all
                     the right turns.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991b" loc="171"/>
               </cit>
            </p>
            <p>In modern terminology, such a machine is called an intelligent <q>agent</q>, a
               concept we shall discuss later in this work. Technology has not yet reached Bush's
               vision for adaptive associative indexing <ptr target="#meyrowitz1991" loc="289"/>,
               although intelligent systems, whose parameters change in accordance with the user's
               experiences, come close. This is called machine learning. Andries van Dam also
               believes this to be the natural future of hypertext and associative retrieval systems
                  <ptr target="#vandam1999"/>.</p>
            <p>In <title rend="italic">Memex II</title>, however, Bush not only proposed that the
               machine might learn from the human via what was effectively a cybernetic feedback
               loop — he proposed that the <emph>human might learn from the machine</emph>. As the
               human mind moulds the machine, so too the machine <q>remolds</q> the human mind, it <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991b">remolds the trails of the user’s brain,
                     as one lives and works in close interconnection with a machine</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991b" loc="178"/>
               </cit>. <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#bush1991b">For the trails of the machine become
                     duplicated in the brain of the user, vaguely as all human memory is vague, but
                     with a concomitant emphasis by repetition, creation and discard … as the cells
                     of the brain become realigned and reconnected, better to utilize the massive
                     explicit memory which is its servant.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991b" loc="178"/>
               </cit>
            </p>
            <p>This was in line with Bush’s conception of technical machines as mechanical teachers
               in their own right. It was a <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#nyce1991">proposal of an active symbiosis between
                     machine and human memory</quote>
                  <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="122"/>
               </cit> which has been surprisingly ignored in contemporary readings of the design.
               Nyce and Kahn pay it a full page of attention, and also Nelson, who has always read
               Bush rather closely <ptr target="#nelson1999"/>. But aside from that, the full
               development of this concept from Bush’s work has been left to Doug Engelbart. </p>
            <p>In our interview, Engelbart claimed it was Bush’s concept of a <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#engelbart1999">co-evolution</quote> between humans and machines, and also
               his conception of our human <quote rend="inline" source="#engelbart1999">augmentation
                  system</quote>, which inspired him <ptr target="#engelbart1999"/>. Both Bush and
               Engelbart believe that our social structures, our discourses and even our language
               can and should <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991d">adapt to mechanization</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991d" loc="210"/>
               </cit>; all of these things are inherited, they are learned. This process is not only
               unavoidable, it is desirable. Bush also believed machines to have their own logic,
               their own <emph>language</emph>, which <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991b">can
                  touch those subtle processes of mind, its logical and rational processes</quote>
               and alter them <ptr target="#bush1991b" loc="177"/>. And the <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#nyce1991">logical and rational processes</quote> which the machine
               connected with were <emph>our own memories</emph> — a prosthesis of the inside. This
               vision of actual human neurons changing to be more like the machine, however, would
               not find its way into the 1967 essay <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="122"/>.</p>
            <p>Paradoxically, Bush also retreats on this close alignment of memory and machine. In
               the later essays, he felt the need to demarcate a purely <q>human</q> realm of
               thought from technics, a realm uncontaminated by technics. One of the major themes in
                  <title rend="italic">Memex II</title> is defining exactly what it is that machines
               can and cannot do. </p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#bush1991b">Two mental processes the machine can do well:
                  first, memory storage and recollection, and this is the primary function of the
                  Memex; and second, logical reasoning, which is the function of the computing and
                  analytical machines.</quote>
               <ptr target="#bush1991b" loc="178"/>
            </cit>
            <p>Machines can remember better than human beings can — their trails do not fade, their
               logic is never flawed. Both of the <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991e">mental
                  processes</quote> Bush locates above take place within human thought, they are
               forms of internal <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991e">repetitive</quote> thought
                  <ptr target="#bush1991e" loc="189"/> — perfectly suited to being externalised and
               improved upon by technics. But exactly what is it that machines <emph>can’t
               </emph>do? Is there anything inside thought which is purely human? Bush demarcates
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991e">creativity</quote> as the realm of
               thought that exists beyond technology. </p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block" source="#bush1991b">How far can the machine accompany and aid its
                  master along this path? Certainly to the point at which the master becomes an
                  artist, reaching into the unknown with beauty and versatility, erecting on the
                  mundane thought processes a thing of beauty … this region will always be barred to
                  the machine.</quote>
               <ptr target="#bush1991b" loc="183"/>
            </cit>
            <p>Bush had always been obsessed with memory and technics, as we have explored. But near
               the end of his career, when <title rend="italic">Memex II</title> and <title
                  rend="italic">Memex Revisited</title> were written, he became obsessed with the
                  <soCalled>boundary</soCalled> between them, between what is personal and belongs
               to the human alone, and what can be or <emph>already is</emph> automated within
               thought.</p>
            <p>In all versions of the Memex essay, the machine was to serve as a personal memory
               support. It was not a <emph>public </emph>database in the sense of the modern
               Internet: it was first and foremost a private device. It provided for each person to
               add their own marginal notes and comments, recording reactions to and trails from
               others' texts, and adding selected information and the trails of others by
                  <soCalled>dropping</soCalled> them into their archive via an electro-optical
               scanning device. In the later adaptive Memex, these trails fade out if not used, and <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1970">if much in use, the trails become
                     emphasized</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1970" loc="191"/>
               </cit> as the web adjusts its shape mechanically to the thoughts of the individual
               who uses it. </p>
            <p>Current hypertext technologies are not quite so private and tend to emphasise <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#oren1991">systems which are public rather than
                     personal in nature and that emphasize the static record over adaptivity</quote>
                  <ptr target="#oren1991" loc="320"/>
               </cit> due to the need for mass production, distribution and compatibility. The idea
               of a <q>personal</q> machine to amplify the mind also flew in the face of the
               emerging paradigm of human–computer interaction that reached its peak in the late
               1950s and early 1960s, which held computers to be rarefied calculating machines used
               only by qualified technicians in white lab coats in air-conditioned rooms at many
               degrees of separation from the <q>user</q>. <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#ceruzzi1998">After the summer of 1946</quote>, writes Ceruzzi, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#ceruzzi1998">computing's path, in theory at least,
                     was clear</quote>
                  <ptr target="#ceruzzi1998" loc="23"/>
               </cit>. Computers were, for the moment, impersonal, institutionally aligned and out
               of the reach of the ignorant masses who did not understand their workings. They lived
               only in university computer labs, wealthy corporations and government departments.
               Memex II was published at a time when the dominant paradigm of human–computer
               interaction was sanctified and imposed by corporations like IBM, and <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#delanda1994">it was so entrenched that the very idea
                     of a free interaction between users and machines as envisioned by Bush was
                     viewed with hostility by the academic community</quote>
                  <ptr target="#delanda1994" loc="219"/>
               </cit>.</p>
            <p>In all versions of the essay, Memex remained profoundly uninfluenced by the paradigm
               of digital computing. As we have explored, Bush transferred the concept of machine
               learning from Shannon — but not information theory. He transferred neural and memory
               models from the cybernetic community — but not digital computation. The analogue
               computing discourse Bush and Memex created never <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#bush1970">mixed</quote> with digital computing <ptr target="#bush1970"
                  loc="208"/>. In 1945, Memex was a direct analogy to Bush’s conception of human
               memory; in 1967, after digital computing had swept engineering departments across the
               country into its paradigm, Memex was still a direct analogy to human memory. It
               mirrored the technique of association in <emph>its mechanical workings</emph>. <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#nyce1991">While the pioneers of digital computing
                     understood that machines would soon accelerate human capabilities by doing
                     massive calculations, Bush continued to be occupied with extending, through
                     replication, human mental experience.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#nyce1991" loc="124"/>
               </cit>
            </p>
            <p>Consequently, the Memex redesigns responded to the advances of the day quite
               differently to how others were responding at the time. By 1967, for example, great
               advances had been made in digital memory techniques. As far back as 1951, the
               Eckert-Mauchly division of Remington Rand had turned over the first <q>digital</q>
               computer with a stored-program architecture, the UNIVAC, to the US Census Bureau <ptr
                  target="#ceruzzi1998" loc="27"/>. <q>Delay Lines</q> stored 1,000 words as
               acoustic pulses in tubes of mercury, and reels of magnetic tapes which stored
               invisible bits were used for bulk memory. This was electronic digital technology, and
               did not mirror or seek to mirror <q>natural</q> processes in any way. It steadily
               replaced the most popular form of electro-mechanical memory from the late 1940s and
               early 1950s: drum memory. This was a large metal cylinder which rotated rapidly
               beneath a mechanical head, where information was written across the surface
               magnetically <ptr target="#ceruzzi1998" loc="38"/>. In 1957, disk memory had been
               produced, for the IBM305 RAMAC, and rapid advances were being made by IBM and DEC
                  <ptr target="#ceruzzi1998" loc="196"/>. </p>
            <p>Bush, however, remained enamoured of physical recording and inscription. His 1959
               essay proposes using organic crystals to record data by means of phase changes in
               molecular alignment. <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991b">[I]n Memex II, when a code on one item
                     points to a second, the first part of the code will pick out a crystal, the
                     next part the level in this, and the remainder the individual item</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991b" loc="169"/>
               </cit>. This was new technology at the time, but certainly not the direction
               commercial computing was taking via DEC or IBM. Bush was fundamentally uncomfortable
               with digital electronics as a means to store material. <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#bush1991e">The brain does not operate by reducing everything to indices
                  and computation</quote>, Bush wrote <ptr target="#bush1991e" loc="190"/>. Bush was
               aware of how out of touch he was with emerging digital computing techniques, and this
               essay bears no trace of engineering details whatsoever, details which were steadily
               disappearing from all his published work. He devoted the latter part of his career to
               frank prophecy, reading from the technologies he saw around him and taking <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991b">a long look ahead</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991b" loc="166"/>
               </cit>. Of particular concern to him was promoting Memex as the technology of the
               future, and encouraging the public that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991b">the time has come to try it again</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991b" loc="166"/>
               </cit>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Memex, Inheritance and Transmission</head>
            <quote rend="block" source="#bush1970">No memex could have been built when that article
               appeared. In the quarter-century since then, the idea has been with me almost
               constantly, and I have watched new developments in electronics, physics, chemistry
               and logic to see how they might help bring it to reality <ptr target="#bush1970"
                  loc="190"/>.</quote>
            <p>Memex became an image of potentiality for Bush near the end of his life. In the later
               essays, he writes in a different tone entirely: Memex was an image he would bequeath
               to the future, a gift to the human race. For most of his professional life, he had
               been concerned with augmenting human memory, and preserving information that might be
               lost to human beings. He had occasionally written about this project as a larger idea
               which would boost <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991c">the entire process by
                  which man profits by his inheritance of acquired knowledge</quote>
               <ptr target="#bush1991c" loc="99"/>. But in <title rend="italic">Memex II</title>,
               this project became grander, more urgent — the idea itself far more important than
               the technical details. He was nearing the end of his life, and Memex was still
               unbuilt. Would someone eventually build this machine? He hoped so, and he urged the
               public that it would soon be possible to do this, or at least, the <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#bush1970">day has come far closer</quote>
               <ptr target="#bush1970" loc="190"/>: <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991b">in the
                  interval since that paper [<title rend="italic">As We May Think</title>] was
                  published, there have been many developments … steps that were merely dreams are
                  coming into the realm of practicality</quote>
               <ptr target="#bush1991b" loc="166"/>. Could this image be externalised now, and live
               beyond him? It would not only carry the wealth of his own knowledge beyond his death,
               it would be like a gift to all mankind. In fact, Memex would be the centrepiece of
               mankind’s <emph>true revolution</emph> — transcending death.</p>
            <quote rend="block" source="#bush1991b">Can a son inherit the memex of his father,
               refined and polished over the years, and go on from there? In this way can we avoid
               some of the loss which comes when oxygen is no longer furnished to the brain of the
               great thinker, when all the patterns of neurons so painstakingly refined become
               merely a mass of protein and nucleic acid? Can the race thus develop leaders, of such
               power and intellect, and such forces of conviction, that the world can be saved from
               its follies? This is an objective of far greater importance than the conquest of
               disease, even than the conquest of mental aberrations <ptr target="#bush1991b"
                  loc="183"/>.</quote>
            <p>Near the end of his life, Bush thought of Memex as more than just an
                  <emph>individual’s</emph> machine; the <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991b">ultimate [machine] is far more subtle
                     than this</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bush1991b" loc="182"/>
               </cit>. Memex would be the centrepiece of a structure of inheritance and
               transmission, a structure that would accumulate with each successive generation. In
                  <title rend="italic">Science Pauses</title>, Bush entitled one of the sections
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991e">Immortality in a machine</quote>
               <ptr target="#bush1991e" loc="189"/>: it contained a description of Memex, but this
               time there was an emphasis on its <quote rend="inline" source="#bush1991e"
                  >longevity</quote> over the individual human mind <ptr target="#bush1991e"
                  loc="190"/>. This is the crux of the matter; the trails in Memex would not grow
               old, they would be a gift from father to son, from one generation to the next. </p>
            <p>Bush died on June 30, 1974. The image of Memex has been passed on beyond his death,
               and it continues to inspire a host of new machines and <soCalled>technical
                  instrumentalities</soCalled>. But Memex itself has never been built; it exists
               only on paper, in technical interpretation and in memory. All we have of Memex are
               the words that Bush assembled around it in his lifetime, the drawings created by the
               artists from <title rend="italic">Life</title>, its erotic simulacrum, its ideals,
               its ideas. Had Bush attempted to assemble this machine in his own lifetime, it would
               undoubtedly have changed in its technical workings; the material limits of microfilm,
               of photoelectric components and later, of crystalline memory storage would have
               imposed their limits; the <q>use function</q> of the machine would itself have
               changed as it demonstrated its own potentials. If Memex had been built, the object
               would have invented itself independently of the outlines Bush cast on paper. This
               never happened — it has entered into the intellectual capital of new media as an
               image of potentiality. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bagg1961" label="Bagg and Stevens 1961" key="bagg1961">
               <author>Bagg, T. C.</author>, and <author>Stevens, M. E.</author>
               <title rend="italic">Information Selection Systems Retrieving Replica Copies: A
                  state-of-the-art report</title>. <title rend="none">National Bureau of Standards
                  Technical note 157</title>. <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>, <date>1961</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="beniger1986" label="Beniger 1986" key="beniger1986">
               <author>Beniger, James R.</author>
               <title rend="italic">The Control Revolution: Technological and Economic Origins of
                  the Information Society</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>, <date>1986</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="burke1991" label="Burke 1991" key="burke1991">
               <author>Burke, Collin</author>. <title rend="quotes">A Practical View of the Memex:
                  The Career of the Rapid Selector</title>. In <ptr target="#nyce1991"/>.</bibl>


            <bibl xml:id="bush1928" label="Bush 1928" key="bush1928">
               <author>Bush, Vannevar</author>. <title rend="quotes">Mechanical Solutions of
                  Engineering Problems</title>, <title rend="italic">Tech Engineering News</title>,
               Vol. 9, <date>1928</date>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bush1939" label="Bush 1939" key="bush1939">
               <author>Bush, Vannevar</author>. <title rend="quotes">Mechanization and the
                  Record</title>, <title rend="italic">Vannevar Bush Papers</title>, Library of
               Congress, Box 138, Speech Article Book File.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bush1991c" label="Bush 1991c" key="bush1991c">
               <author>Bush, Vannevar</author>. <title rend="quotes">As We May Think</title>. In
                  <ptr target="#nyce1991"/>, 85–112. Originally
               published 1945.</bibl>


            <bibl xml:id="bush1991a" label="Bush 1991a" key="bush1991f">
               <author>Bush, Vannevar</author>. <title rend="quotes">The Inscrutable <q>Thirties</q>
               </title>. In <ptr target="#nyce1991"/>, 67–80.
               Originally published 1933.</bibl>


            <bibl xml:id="bush1991b" label="Bush 1991b" key="bush1991a">
               <author>Bush, Vannevar</author>. <title rend="quotes">Memex II</title>. In <ptr
                  target="#nyce1991"/>, 165–184. Originally
               published 1959.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bush1991d" label="Bush 1991d" key="bush1991b">
               <author>Bush, Vannevar</author>. <title rend="quotes">Memex Revisited</title>. In
                  <ptr target="#nyce1991"/>, 197–216. Originally
               published 1967.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bush1991e" label="Bush 1991e" key="bush1991d">
               <author>Bush, Vannevar</author>. <title rend="quotes">Science Pauses</title>. In <ptr
                  target="#nyce1991"/>, 185–196. Originally
               published 1965.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="bush1963" label="Bush 1963" key="bush1963">
               <author>Bush, Vannevar</author>. <title rend="italic">Man’s Thinking
               Machines</title>, Vannevar Bush Papers, MIT Archives, MC78, Box 21.</bibl>


            <bibl xml:id="bush1970" label="Bush 1970" key="bush1970">
               <author>Bush, Vannevar</author>. <title rend="italic">Pieces of the Action</title>.
                  <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>William Morrow</publisher>,
                  <date>1970</date>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="ceruzzi1998" label="Ceruzzi 1998" key="ceruzzi1998">
               <author>Ceruzzi, Paul E.</author>
               <title rend="italic">A History of Modern Computing</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge,
                  MA</pubPlace>: <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>, <date>1998</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="delanda1994" label="De Landa 1994" key="delanda1994">
               <author>De Landa, Manuel</author>. <title rend="italic">War in the Age of Intelligent
                  Machines</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Zone
               Books</publisher>, <date>1994</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dennett1993" label="Dennett 1993" key="dennett1993">
               <author>Dennett, Daniel C.</author>
               <title rend="italic">Consciousness Explained</title>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>Penguin Books</publisher>, <date>1993</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="edwards1997" label="Edwards 1997" key="edwards1997">
               <author>Edwards, Paul N.</author>
               <title rend="italic">The Closed World: Computers and the Politics of Discourse in
                  Cold War America</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>: <publisher>MIT
                  Press</publisher>, <date>1997</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eldredge2004" label="Eldredge 2004" key="[unlisted]">
               <author>Eldredge, Niles.</author>
               <title rend="none">Email interview with Belinda Barnet</title>. <date>March
                  2004</date>. <ref
                  target="http://journal.fibreculture.org/issue3/issue3_barnet.html"
                  >http://journal.fibreculture.org/issue3/issue3_barnet.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="engelbart1999" label="Engelbart 1999" key="[unlisted]">
               <author>Engelbart, Douglas</author>. <title rend="none">Interview with Belinda
                  Barnet</title>. <date>November 10, 1999</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="farkas1990" label="Farkas-Conn 1990" key="farkas1990">
               <author>Farkas-Conn, I. S.</author>
               <title rend="italic">From Documentation to Information Science: The Beginnings and
                  Early Development of the American Documentation Institute — American Society for
                  Information Science</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Greenwood
                  Press</publisher>, <date>1990</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="guattari1995" label="Guattari 1995" key="guattari1995">
               <author>Guattari, Félix</author>. <title rend="italic">Chaosmosis: An
                  Ethico-Aesthetic Paradigm</title>. Tr. <name role="translator">Paul Bains</name>
               and <name role="translator">Julian Pefanis</name>. <pubPlace>Sydney</pubPlace>:
                  <pubPlace>Power Publications</pubPlace>, <date>1995</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gille1986" label="Gille 1986" key="gille1986">
               <author>Gille, Bertrand</author>. <title rend="italic">History of Techniques</title>.
                  <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Gordon and Breach Science
                  Publishers</publisher>, <date>1986</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hartree2000" label="Hartree 2000" key="hartree2000">
               <author>Hartree, Douglas</author>. <title rend="quotes">Differential
               Analyzer</title>, <ref
                  target="http://cs.union.edu/~hemmendd/encyc/articles/difanal/difanal.html"
                  >http://cs.union.edu/~hemmendd/Encyc/Articles/Difanal/difanal.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hatt1968" label="Hatt 1968" key="hatt1968">
               <author>Hatt, Harold</author>. <title rend="italic"> Cybernetics and the Image of
                  Man</title>. <pubPlace>Nashville</pubPlace>: <publisher>Abingdon
               Press</publisher>, <date>1968</date>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hayles1993" label="Hayles 1993" key="hayles1993">
               <author>Hayles, Katherine</author>. <title rend="quotes">Virtual Bodies and
                  Flickering Signifiers</title>, <title rend="italic">October Magazine</title>.
                  No 66 (<date>Fall 1993</date>), 69–91.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hayles1999" label="Hayles 1999" key="hayles1999">
               <author>Hayles, N. Katherine</author>. <title rend="italic">How we Became
                  Posthuman</title>. <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Chicago
                  Press</publisher>, <date>1999</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hazen1940" label="Hazen 1940" key="hazen1940">
               <author>Hazen, Harold</author>. <title rend="none">MIT President's report</title>,
                  <date>1940</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="meyrowitz1991" label="Meyrowitz 1991" key="meyrowitz1991">
               <author>Meyrowitz, Norman</author>. <title rend="quotes">Hypertext: Does it Reduce
                  Cholesterol, Too?</title>. In <ptr target="#nyce1991"/>, 287–318.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mindell2000" label="Mindell 2000" key="mindell2000">
               <author>Mindell, David A.</author>
               <title rend="quotes">MIT Differential Analyzer</title>. <ref
                  target="http://web.mit.edu/mindell/www/analyzer.htm"
                  >http://web.mit.edu/mindell/www/analyzer.htm</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nelson1991" label="Nelson 1991" key="nelson1991">
               <author>Nelson, Theodor H.</author>
               <title rend="quotes">As We Will Think</title>. In <ptr target="#nyce1991"/>,
                  245–260.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nelson1999" label="Nelson 1999" key="[unlisted]">
               <author>Nelson, Theodor H.</author> Interview with the author.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nyce1991" label="Nyce 1991" key="nyce1991">
               <editor>Nyce, James</editor> and <editor>Kahn, Paul</editor>, eds. <title
                  rend="italic">From Memex to Hypertext: Vannevar Bush and the Mind's
                  Machine</title>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Academic
                  Press</publisher>, <date>1991</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oren1991" label="Oren 1991" key="oren1991">Oren, Tim 1991, <title
                  rend="quotes">Memex: Getting Back on the Trail</title>. In <ptr target="#nyce1991"
               />, 319–338.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="owens1991" label="Owens 1991" key="owens1991">
               <author>Owens, Larry</author>. <title rend="quotes">Vannevar Bush and the
                  Differential Analyzer: The Text and Context of an Early Computer</title>. In <ptr
                  target="#nyce1991"/>, 3–38.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shurkin1996" label="Shurkin 1996" key="shurkin1996">
               <author>Shurkin, Joel</author>. <title rend="italic">Engines of the Mind, The
                  Evolution of the Computer from Mainframes to Microprocessors</title>.
                  <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>WW Norton and Company</publisher>,
                  <date>1996</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="smith1991" label="Smith 1991" key="smith1991">
               <author>Smith, Linda C.</author>
               <title rend="quotes">Memex as an Image of Potentiality Revisited</title>. In <ptr
                  target="#nyce1991" loc="261–286"/>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="spar2001" label="Spar 2001" key="spar2001">
               <author>Spar, Debora L.</author>
               <title rend="italic">Ruling the Waves: Cycles of Discovery, Chaos, and Wealth from
                  Compass to the Internet</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>Harcourt</publisher>, <date>2001</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stiegler1998" label="Stiegler 1998" key="stiegler1998">
               <author>Stiegler, Bernard</author>. <title rend="italic">Technics and Time, 1: The
                  Fault of Epimetheus</title>. <pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Stanford
                  University Press</publisher>, <date>1998</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vandam1999" label="Van Dam 1999" key="[unlisted]">
               <author>Van Dam, Andries</author>. Interview with the author.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="weaver1950" label="Weaver 1950" key="[unlisted]">
               <author>Weaver, Warren</author>. <title rend="none">Project diaries</title>.
                  <date>March 17, 1950</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="weaver1950a" label="Weaver 1950a" key="weaver1950a">
               <author>Weaver, Warren</author>. <title rend="none">Letter to Samuel
               Caldwell</title>. Correspondence held in the Rockefeller Archive Center, <idno>RF1.1/224/2/26</idno>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wells1938" label="Wells 1938" key="wells1938">
               <author>Wells, H.G.</author>
               <title>World Brain</title>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Methuen &amp; Co.
                  Limited</publisher>, <date>1938</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ziman2003" label="Ziman 2003" key="ziman2003">
               <author>Ziman, John</author>. <title rend="italic">Technological Innovation as an
                  Evolutionary Process</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Cambridge
                  University Press</publisher>, <date>2003</date>.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
