<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Where’s the ML in DH? And Where’s the DH in ML? The
                    Relationship between Modern Languages and Digital Humanities, and an Argument
                    for a Critical DHML </title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Thea <dhq:family>Pitman</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Leeds</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>t.pitman@leeds.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Thea Pitman is Senior Lecturer in Latin American Studies, in the School
                            of Languages, Cultures and Societies, at the University of Leeds.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Claire <dhq:family>Taylor</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Liverpool</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>c.l.taylor@liv.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Claire Taylor is Professor of Hispanic Studies, in the Department of
                            Modern Languages and Cultures, at the University of Liverpool.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000287</idno>
                <idno type="volume">011</idno>
                <idno type="issue">1</idno>
                <date when="2017-02-07">7 February 2017</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2018-07-09" who="DD">validation check</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This article addresses the relationship of the disciplines of Modern Languages
                    and Digital Humanities in Anglophone academia. It briefly compares and contrasts
                    the nature of these <soCalled>disciplines</soCalled> – most frequently conceived
                    of as either inter- or transdisciplines – before going on to examine in some
                    detail the participation of Modern Linguists in Digital Humanities and that of
                    Digital Humanists in Modern Languages. It argues that, while there is growing
                    evidence of work that crosses <soCalled>disciplinary</soCalled> boundaries
                    between DH and ML in both directions, more work of this sort needs to be done to
                    optimise the potential of both disciplines. It also makes a particular case for
                    Digital Humanities to remain open to critical cultural studies approaches to
                    digital materials as pertaining to the discipline rather than focusing
                    exclusively on more instrumental definitions of Digital Humanities. This
                    argument is consistent with the concerns raised by other scholars with regard to
                    the need for heterogeneity of approach and in particular for increased cultural
                    criticism in Digital Humanities scholarship. Furthermore, we argue that this is
                    where Modern Linguists can make their most decisive contribution to Digital
                    Humanities research, offering what we term a <q>critical DHML</q> approach. We
                    illustrate our arguments with a range of examples from the intersection of ML
                    and DH in the broad field of Hispanic Studies, including the major findings of
                    our own research into digital cultural production in a Latin American context
                    conducted over the last ten years.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Addresses the relationship of Modern Languages and DH in Anglophone academia.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head>The Relationship between Modern Languages and Digital Humanities, and an Argument
                for a Critical DHML</head>
            <epigraph>
                <cit>
                    <quote rend="block" source="#galina2015">A global DH is not one that works
                        towards homogenizing all DH work but rather one that manages to make a
                        heterogeneous landscape enriching for all that participate.</quote>
                    <ptr target="#galina2015"/>
                </cit>
            </epigraph>
            <epigraph>
                <cit>
                    <quote rend="block" source="#liu2011">In the Digital Humanities, cultural
                        criticism – in both its interpretive and advocacy modes – has been
                        noticeably absent by comparison with the mainstream humanities or, even more
                        strikingly, with <title rend="quotes">new media studies</title> (populated
                        as the latter is by net critics, tactical media critics, hacktivists, and so
                        on). We digital humanists develop tools, data, metadata, and archives
                        critically; and we have also developed critical positions on the nature of
                        such resources […]. But rarely do we extend the issues involved into the
                        register of society, economics, politics, or culture…</quote>
                    <ptr target="#liu2011"/>
                </cit>
            </epigraph>
            <epigraph>
                <cit>
                    <quote rend="block" source="#McPherson2012">The lack of intellectual generosity
                        across our fields and departments only reinforces the divide-and-conquer
                        mentality that the most dangerous aspects of modularity underwrite. We must
                        develop common languages that link the study of code and culture.</quote>
                    <ptr target="#McPherson2012" loc="153"/>
                </cit>
            </epigraph>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The decision of <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> to start publishing a series of
                    special issues focusing on Digital Humanities <q>in different languages or regional traditions</q> is a very welcome
                    development. As Hispanists who have worked for the last decade on critical
                    digital culture/new media studies in a Latin American context this is an
                    initiative that we very much wanted to engage with, and we took as our
                    inspiration the special issue dedicated to Digital Humanities work <q>in Spanish</q>. What we address in this
                    article are issues that arose from this initial inspiration but which, however,
                    expand from this to ask questions about what Digital Humanities really is, and
                    what its relationship to Modern Languages (ML) might be; and a converse set of
                    questions about what is happening in Modern Languages and how greater engagement
                    with Digital Humanities is undoubtedly necessary. Our argument is therefore not
                    focused so much on a dialogue with other DH practitioners working in
                    Spanish-language contexts, but on a dialogue with the disciplines – most
                    frequently conceived of as either inter- or transdisciplines – of Digital
                    Humanities and Modern Languages in an Anglophone academic context.</p>
                <p>We are mindful of the fact that scholars working in Anglophone Digital Humanities
                    institutional contexts are currently very open to, and encouraging, of DH
                    initiatives in other languages and contexts and are keen to foster the <quote rend="inline" source="#gallina2015">global DH</quote> that Isabel Galina Russell
                    (cited above) has called for (of this, more later). However, we would like to
                    argue that what scholars working within Modern Languages institutional
                    frameworks in Anglophone academia can contribute are a much more diverse range
                    of projects and materials conducted in languages other than English and that may
                    or may not self-identify as pertaining to <soCalled>Digital
                        Humanities</soCalled>. (Indeed, such materials and the way in which ML
                    scholars approach them are typically more readily embraced by media and
                    communications studies via denominations such as new media studies, internet
                    studies, or digital cultural studies than they are by Digital Humanities.)
                    Related to this expansion of projects and materials, Modern Linguists also tend
                    to approach their materials through the application of the still very useful
                    methodologies of the critical cultural studies scholar. Such methodologies are
                    of course not altogether lacking in DH, but critics such as Liu and McPherson
                    (cited above) have called for a deeper and more sustained cultural criticism to
                    be developed within DH, and this is one way that Modern Linguists can help shape
                    Digital Humanities as it develops.<note> To be clear, Modern Languages is not
                        the only other discipline with which DH should enter into dialogue, nor do
                        we seek to claim that it is, absolutely, <soCalled>the most
                            relevant</soCalled> discipline for DH. Nevertheless, as academics
                        situated within Modern Languages institutional frameworks, we are most
                        interested in exploring areas where we think ML can help expand the
                        objectives of DH and where DH can help ML expand its own disciplinary
                        horizons.</note></p>
                <p>In this article we therefore propose that the heterogeneity that Galina Russell
                    argues should be allowed to flourish in an ideal <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#gallina2015">global DH</quote> also has to extend, as some have already
                    argued, to heterogeneity of approach within Digital Humanities itself, so that
                    cultural criticism of digital products and close textual analysis is accorded a
                    more significant role. Furthermore, we concur with Galina Russell that it is
                    time for all the various and different versions of DH to compare and contrast
                    their situatedness globally, hopefully eschewing the construction of any sense
                    of centre/periphery or <soCalled>one true DH</soCalled> as the exercise unfolds.
                    And moreover, as DH embeds itself within academia across the globe, it is also
                    time to be alert to the dangers of institutionalisation – of
                        <soCalled>Balkanisation</soCalled> – so that this new
                    (inter/trans)discipline does not lose the ability to speak in the vernacular of
                    the humanities, instead keeping alive the <soCalled>common languages</soCalled>
                    that allow it to dialogue with earlier (inter/trans)disciplinary frameworks such
                    as ML.<note> While DH and ML share an epistemological basis in inter- and/or
                        transdisciplinarity, and some of our argument relies on comparisons and
                        suggestions made on this basis, we also seek to move beyond considerations
                        about the nature of disciplinarity and disciplinary change <foreign
                            xml:lang="la">per se</foreign> in order to place the emphasis more
                        firmly on the relationship between DH and ML in its particularity. The study
                        of disciplinarity, even with specific reference to DH, is already extensive
                        and we will refer to this as necessary to advance our arguments. For now, it
                        is worth mentioning that research in DH and ML can be either
                        interdisciplinary or transdisciplinary and we will henceforth use this
                        terminology selectively, depending on the argument being advanced. Where we
                        do not wish to advance an argument based specifically on the distinction
                        between inter- and transdisciplinarity, we will refer to them simply as
                        disciplines. We would also note that quite often terms such as
                        interdisciplinarity and transdisciplinarity are used almost interchangeably
                        in the work of otherwise very accomplished critics, thus complicating any
                        easy definitions.</note> We propose that a name for one such a common
                    language might just be <q>critical DHML</q>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Definitions #1: Digital Humanities</head>
                <p>Digital Humanities has developed rapidly over the past several decades, from
                    supportive <q>humanities computing</q> in the 1980s, through the adoption of the
                    now accepted <q>Digital Humanities</q> label from 2004 onwards <ptr
                        target="#schreibman2004"/>, to the much more self-possessed discipline that
                    it is today, with its own centres, networks, journals and self-identifying
                    Digital Humanists. Part of this latter phase of DH’s development have been the
                    illuminating and ongoing debates about its nature and shape, with debates on DH
                    discussion lists, and recent publications in the field – most notably <title
                        rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>
                    <ptr target="#gold2012"/> and <title rend="italic">Understanding Digital
                        Humanities</title>
                    <ptr target="#berry2012"/><note> We are mindful of the fast pace at which new
                        volumes and/or expanded editions of volumes about DH are being published.
                        While the volumes noted here were some of most significant at the time we
                        started to write this article, we will consider newer volumes and expanded
                        editions of volumes such as Gold’s in due course.</note> – that have sought
                    to reflect critically on the development and consolidation of the discipline,
                    flagging up some of the lacunae and aporias in its theory and praxis. While not
                    wanting to spend too much time going over very familiar ground for a <title
                        rend="italic">DHQ</title> readership, we highlight below some of the key
                    issues and tensions in the definition of DH that help us to identify where ML
                    scholars might best fit in. </p>
                <p>Digital Humanities is most often conceived of as an
                        <soCalled>interdiscipline</soCalled> welding together computing and the
                    traditional humanities. With respect to the complex interdisciplinary nature of
                    DH, Julie Thompson Klein gives a very detailed account of this issue in her
                        <title rend="italic">Interdisciplining Digital Humanities: Boundary Work in
                        an Emerging Field</title>
                    <ptr target="#ThompsonKlein2015"/>. Of particular interest, is her discussion of
                    two different types of interdisciplinarity at work in DH:
                    instrumental/strategic/opportunistic interdisciplinarity which seeks to foster
                    discourse between disciplines to <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#ThompsonKlein2015">create a product</quote> or <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#ThompsonKlein2015">meet a designated pragmatic
                        need</quote>, as opposed to critical or reflexive interdisciplinarity which <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ThompsonKlein2015">interrogates the dominant
                            structure of knowledge and education with the aim of transforming
                            them</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ThompsonKlein2015" loc="18"/>
                    </cit>. Arguably, it is the latter form of interdisciplinarity that we, as ML
                    scholars, see as most clearly aligned with our own objectives.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, we note that DH scholars have deliberately and productively sought
                    to leave the definition of DH as open as possible, with the editorial <title
                        rend="quotes">welcome</title> in the first issue of <title rend="italic"
                        >DHQ</title> not stipulating the boundaries of DH, but rather inviting it to
                    be defined by its contributors <ptr target="#flanders2007" loc="para. 5"/>.
                    Others such as Alvarado have urged, in confessional mode, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#alvarado2012">Let’s be honest — there is no
                            definition of Digital Humanities, if by definition we mean a consistent
                            set of theoretical concerns and research methods that might be aligned
                            with a given discipline, whether one of the established fields or an
                            emerging, transdisciplinary one</quote>
                        <ptr target="#alvarado2012" loc="50"/>
                    </cit>. This gesture towards transdisciplinarity, or disciplinary openness aimed
                    at addressing complex research questions that do not sit neatly within any
                    traditional discipline, is something that we welcome, and that offers rich
                    possibilities for cross-fertilisations with ML, as with a range of other
                    disciplines. Thompson Klein conceives of transdisciplinarity as a framework
                    which evidences similar critical potential to critical/reflexive
                    interdisciplinarity and she makes clear the relationship of a transdisciplinary
                    DH to some of the other fields of critical enquiry that are the basis of much ML
                    research: <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#ThompsonKlein2015"><hi rend="italic"
                                >Transdisciplinarity</hi> in DH is also aligned with
                                <soCalled>transgressive</soCalled> critique and critical imperatives
                            in other interdisciplinary fields of cultural studies, media and
                            communication studies, women’s and gender studies […]</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ThompsonKlein2015" loc="21"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>Yet, despite this disciplinary openness, scholars have at the same time
                    recognised that as DH takes shape, inevitably certain practices emerge and come
                    to be accepted as the norm. Indeed, the same <title rend="italic">DHQ</title>
                    editors noted earlier in their editorial that, <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#flanders2007">Digital Humanities is by its
                            nature a hybrid domain, crossing disciplinary boundaries and also
                            traditional barriers between theory and practice, technological
                            implementation and scholarly reflection. But <emph>over time this field
                                has developed its own orthodoxies, its internal lines of affiliation
                                and collaboration that have become intellectual paths of least
                                resistance</emph>.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#flanders2007" loc="para. 3, our emphasis"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Thus, as has been recognised widely by the DH scholarly community, even if rigid
                    definitions of DH are theoretically avoided, the academic practice that goes on
                    beneath the DH rubric creates a kind of common-law definition that quickly
                    acknowledges <soCalled>orthodoxies</soCalled> and <soCalled>intellectual paths of least resistance</soCalled>. If
                    these orthodoxies are starting to take shape, we now look at DH scholars who
                    have recently outlined the modus operandi of DH to see how ML might contribute
                    to these debates and position itself in fruitful dialogue with DH.</p>
                <p>Kathleen Fitzpatrick’s work has been at the forefront of debates on DH’s shape
                    and its future direction, and her observations provide a particularly useful
                    delineation of the discipline, and, in our view, of where ML can fit.
                    Fitzpatrick argues that DH has two concurrent but quite different modus
                    operandi: one that <quote rend="inline" source="#lopez2015">bring[s] the tools
                        and techniques of digital media to bear on traditional humanistic
                        questions</quote> and another that <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#lopez2015">bring[s] humanistic modes of inquiry to bear on
                        digital media</quote>
                    <ptr target="#lopez2015"/>. She notes elsewhere that such differences of
                    approach <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#fitzpatrick2012">often produce significant
                            tension</quote>
                        <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2012" loc="13–14"/>
                    </cit>, such that, for many <soCalled>hard core</soCalled> and quite pragmatic
                    Digital Humanists the second approach is separated off from DH to form a
                        <soCalled>cousin discipline</soCalled> that goes by the name of critical
                    cybercultural studies, internet studies or new media studies. Nevertheless,
                    Fitzpatrick goes on to make a plea for retaining the plurality of approach that
                    DH theoretically embraces: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#fitzpatrick2012">The particular contribution of
                            the Digital Humanities, however, lies in its exploration of the
                            difference that the digital can make to the kinds of work that we do as
                            well as to the ways that we communicate with one another. These new
                            modes of scholarship and communication will best flourish if they, like
                            the Digital Humanities, are allowed to remain plural.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2012" loc="14"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>It is certainly true that the former of the two ways identified by Fitzpatrick
                    has seen exponential growth in recent years. From the preservation and archiving
                    of manuscripts via digital means to data mining methodologies for large corpora
                    of humanities materials, our broad field of the humanities has seen sweeping
                    changes to its practice, with digital tools enabling humanities research to
                    achieve a breadth and arguably also a depth never before seen. Robust models
                    have been put forward for DH as regards this first path, and new tools and
                    methodologies are constantly under development.</p>
                <p>It is arguably the second of these two paths – the <q>bringing humanistic modes of inquiry to bear on digital
                        media</q> – that has been under-theorised and under-represented in
                    debates on the nature and shape of Digital Humanities. This is not to say that
                    the scholarship is not taking place – a significant amount of work on digital
                    cultural production is taking place across a variety of disciplines –; rather,
                    the issue is that this scholarship, and the debates arising from it, do not
                    always find their way into discussions of DH. There are multiple factors that
                    have led to this, including the pragmatics of a field that is large and
                    unwieldy, and also the fact that scholars of digital cultural production might
                    not necessarily self-identify as Digital Humanists, and their publication
                    outlets, conferences, and arenas for debate may not coincide with those
                    preferred by Digital Humanists.</p>
                <p>If Fitzpatrick set out a neat binary division in the modus operandi of DH, in an
                    alternative but complementary conceptualisation of what DH is, David Berry
                    conceives of it as a series of waves of development, arguing that <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#berry2012">first-wave Digital Humanities
                            involved the building of infrastructure in the studying of humanities
                            texts through digital repositories, text markup and so forth, whereas
                            second-wave Digital Humanities expands the notional limits of the
                            archive to include digital works, and so bring to bear the humanities’
                            own methodological toolkits to look at <q>born-digital</q> materials,
                            such as electronic literature (e-lit), interactive fiction (IF),
                            web-based artefacts and so forth.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#berry2012" loc="4"/>
                    </cit> While these two waves synchronise with Fitzpatrick’s discussion of the
                    different modes of DH scholarship, Berry then goes on to argue that third-wave
                    Digital Humanities would constitute cases where as much attention is paid to
                    what difference the digital makes in the study of digital cultural production as
                    it is to the cultural aspects of the production itself. In other words, this
                    would involve supplementing <q>the humanities’ own
                        methodological toolkits</q> with theoretical insights from software,
                    critical code and platform studies. </p>
                <p>This is a point that is best exemplified in some of Tara McPherson’s work where
                    she argues that we need to understand computer programming in order to perceive
                    the politics embedded in its development, and thus be able to critique the
                    resultant technologies for the ways in which they replicate those political
                    agendas. More specifically, McPherson argues that we need to grasp the way that
                    programming languages have typically been based on modularity and <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#McPherson2012">lenticular logics</quote><note> McPherson
                        describes both the <quote rend="inline" source="#McPherson2012">racial
                            paradigms of the postwar era</quote> and the evolution of programming
                        languages as evincing <quote rend="inline" source="#McPherson2012"
                            >lenticular logics</quote> because, like the <q>3-D</q> images on
                        lenticular (ridged) postcards that you can tilt to see different
                        perspectives, or even completely different images, such that it <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#McPherson2012">makes simultaneously viewing the
                            various images contained on one card nearly impossible</quote>, both the
                        racial paradigms and the programming languages evidence <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#McPherson2012">a way of seeing the world
                                as discrete modules or nodes, a mode that suppresses relation and
                                context. [… that] manages and controls complexity</quote>
                            <ptr target="#McPherson2012" loc="144"/>
                        </cit>. With respect to race in particular, she argues that a society that
                        structures its approach to race through <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#McPherson2012">lentincular logics</quote>
                        <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#McPherson2012">secure[s] our
                                understandings of race in very narrow registers, fixating on
                                sameness or difference while forestalling connection and
                                interrelation</quote>
                            <ptr target="#McPherson2012" loc="144"/>
                        </cit>. She also makes a compelling case for the way in which programming
                        languages have evolved following the same logic in order to manage
                        complexity through rules of modularity, separation, simplicity and so on
                            <ptr target="#McPherson2012" loc="145"/>.</note> which curb
                    relationality and <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#McPherson2012">privilege[…]
                            fragmentation</quote>
                        <ptr target="#McPherson2012" loc="144"/>
                    </cit>, and that those same concepts also underpin the <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#McPherson2012">covert racial logic</quote> of the post-civil rights era in the
                    USA and account for the limitations of 1960s identity politics, such that the
                    architecture of contemporary computing is, from its very base, predestined to
                    best represent a particular, hegemonic worldview. </p>
                <p>Furthermore, Berry also argues that third-wave Digital Humanities researchers
                    should endeavour to challenge unhelpful disciplinary boundaries, as well as
                    problematise <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#berry2012">the <soCalled>hard-core</soCalled>
                            of the humanities, the unspoken assumptions and ontological foundations
                            which support the <soCalled>normal</soCalled> research that humanities
                            scholars undertake on an everyday basis</quote>
                        <ptr target="#berry2012" loc="4"/>
                    </cit>. This endeavour to challenge disciplinary boundaries is one which, as we
                    argue in this article, is pertinent to all of us, ML included. We would also
                    suggest that the particular <soCalled>hard-core</soCalled> of the humanities
                    that might be fruitfully challenged in ML would include national or area studies
                    paradigms that still structure our departments and research projects but that
                    need to be problematised in order to ensure that our research is capable of
                    analysing materials that exist beyond such paradigms, and that our teaching
                    remains relevant in a globalising Higher Education sector. In summary, this
                    third-wave Digital Humanities that is as critical of the digital as it is of the
                    cultural, and which is open to tearing down disciplinary boundaries as well as
                    internal orthodoxies where necessary, is essentially the basis for what Berry
                    and others now term a <q>critical</q> Digital
                        Humanities.<note> For more on Berry’s arguments regarding critical
                        approaches to the digital see <ptr target="#berry2014"/>.</note></p>
                <p>If, as these publications suggest, the time is ripe for some serious critical
                    reflection in this regard, we argue here that engagement with the discipline of
                    Modern Language studies and, in particular, with the work that is done by ML
                    scholars in the field of Digital Humanities understood most broadly, is
                    particularly relevant and can contribute productively to the further development
                    of DH.<note> ML is not the only discipline that has been slow to be embraced by
                        DH but by now it is the most conspicuous in its absence from debates in the
                        field. In Svensson and Goldberg’s <title rend="italic">Between Humanities
                            and the Digital</title>
                        <ptr target="#svensson2015"/>, the editors do much to expand the
                        disciplinary horizons of DH, reaching out to the often overlooked
                        disciplines of religious studies/theology and archaeology, for example. It
                        is also pleasing to see the development of Postcolonial DH over the past
                        several years (cf. the <title rend="italic">Postcolonial Digital
                            Humanities</title> website, <ref target="http://dhpoco.org"
                            >http://dhpoco.org</ref>, edited by Adeline Koh and Roopika Risam).
                        Nonetheless, in both Svensson and Goldberg’s compendious volume, and in Gold
                        and Klein’s 2016 significant update of <title rend="italic">Debates in the
                            Digital Humanities</title>
                        <ptr target="#gold2016"/>, which is also notable for its inclusion of black,
                        and black feminist readings of DH, Modern Languages never features as a
                        discipline at all, with the issue of DH projects that exist in other
                        languages being glossed over as a simple issue of translation.</note> As DH
                    continues to mature and see itself less as providing tools, and more as enabling
                    critical ways of thinking, ML can contribute linguistically- and
                    culturally-specific cultural studies approaches to digital materials, a
                    contestation of assumptions regarding (unstated) Anglophone models of the
                    digital, and a re-thinking of area studies, all of which we set out below.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Definitions #2: Modern Language Studies</head>
                <p>As regards the contributions that Modern Languages can make to the Digital
                    Humanities debates, recent interrogations within our own discipline mean that we
                    find ourselves in a position which encourages us to engage with these questions.
                    For, just as DH has been attempting to define itself, so too, ML has faced the
                    need to examine its own practice. In particular, a challenge for ML has been
                    taking up the gauntlet of the Worton report, which charged it very prominently
                    with the task of promoting a <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#worton2009">clear and compelling identity for
                            Modern Languages as a humanities discipline</quote>
                        <ptr target="#worton2009" loc="37"/>
                    </cit>. </p>
                <p>The need for Modern Languages to articulate its identity <q>as a humanities
                        discipline</q> whilst still negotiating its position as what is essentially
                    a transdisciplinary exercise – and with diverse forms of interdisciplinarity to
                    be found in the work of many individual ML scholars to boot – has been a
                    constant problem. ML has always had to grapple with this tension: on the one
                    hand, the specificity of ML-qua-discipline, and the need to articulate what ML
                    scholars have in common and that makes our research distinctive in comparison
                    with that conducted by scholars working in other disciplinary contexts; and on
                    the other, the fact that ML is, in effect, a multiplicity of disciplines (ML
                    scholars are, variously, historians, literary scholars, film studies scholars,
                    sociolinguists, and so forth). Indeed, indicative of this understanding of ML as
                    constituting a multiplicity of disciplines is the key change in our draft
                    subject benchmark statements in 2015 which moved from identifying the
                        <q>discipline</q> as <q>modern language studies</q> (as it appeared in the
                    previous 2007 statements) to identifying it as <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#qaa">languages, cultures and societies</quote>, precisely in
                    order to clarify the range of humanities disciplines across which we work <ptr
                        target="#qaa"/>. ML has thus been faced with the challenge of what Charles
                    Forsdick has called <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#forsdick2011">prevent[ing] the
                            interdisciplinary from becoming the undisciplined</quote>
                        <ptr target="#forsdick2011" loc="42"/>
                    </cit>. Those of us researching in Modern Languages of necessity start off from
                    this basis of multiplicity and yet (attempted) coherence: negotiations of our
                    identity as ML scholars, <emph>and</emph> being constantly engaged in a trans-
                    and interdisciplinary exercise.<note> It is worth noting that this growing
                        debate about ML as inherently interdisciplinary and as offering
                        transdisciplinary approaches takes place against a backdrop of growing
                        suspicion about disciplinary boundaries; see, for instance, Sandra Harding’s
                        reminder of the constructed, situated nature of all knowledge, and her
                        critique of authoritarian moves to police the boundaries of disciplines
                        and/or suggest that in and of themselves they can offer a <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#harding2015">theory of everything</quote>
                            <ptr target="#harding2015" loc="122"/>
                        </cit>. Her appeal for a <quote rend="inline" source="#harding2015">disunited</quote>
                        and <quote rend="inline" source="#hardin2015">heterogeneous</quote> approach to the
                        construction of forms of knowledge is kith and kin with transdisciplinary
                        dialogue and critical interdisciplinary approaches.</note></p>
                <p>The trans-, as well as inter-, disciplinary nature of Modern Languages is perhaps
                    what makes us so difficult to <soCalled>read</soCalled> from the perspective of
                    other, often more consolidated, humanities disciplines. Indeed, to take this
                    statement quite literally, we may as frequently seek to publish our research in
                    gender or film studies journals as we do in those dedicated specifically to
                    Hispanism or Latin American studies, for example. Equally, particularly before
                    the very recent consolidation of Digital Humanities as a discipline with
                    departments, centres, journals, and so on, the use of digital technologies at
                    all stages of the DH research process often led to the circumvention of the
                    traditional circuits of cultural capital, providing greater flexibility, but a
                    research field that was more diffuse, multiple and ephemeral.<note> Examples of
                        the circumvention of traditional circuits of cultural capital offered by
                        digital technologies include the use of social media platforms for
                        dissemination of research findings, or the use of blogs and wikis as
                        publishing tools instead of traditional editorial outlets.</note> And
                    perhaps because both Modern Languages and Digital Humanities share similar
                    issues with disciplinarity, and therefore with <soCalled>readability</soCalled>
                    – and this despite the general belief that both ML and DH are all about dialogue
                    and translation across (disciplinary and/or linguistic) boundaries –, this
                    should encourage us all in both ML and DH to strive to develop common languages
                    between us, to keep the doors open to dialogue even if we all also need to
                    strive to articulate coherent disciplinary identities for more pragmatic,
                    institutional purposes. Furthermore, this has to be seen as a two-way dialogue:
                    on the one hand, ML can benefit enormously from the insights of DH, which have
                    shown us new ways of working and thinking; on the other, as we argue below, DH
                    can also benefit from ML’s interventions in its debates. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Relationships: Where’s the ML in DH? Where’s the DH in ML?</head>
                <p>With regard to the benefits that Modern Languages has experienced in its
                    engagement with Digital Humanities, digital technologies have, in a variety of
                    ways, changed the way in which we research as ML scholars, across the whole
                    cycle of the research process, from textual preservation, through analysis, to
                    archiving and dissemination. Medieval manuscript scholarship was one of the
                    first areas within ML to embrace DH, with examples such as the University of
                    Wisconsin-Madison <title rend="italic">Dictionary of the Old Spanish
                        Language</title> project that started in the 1970s and developed its own
                    tagging system <ptr target="#nitti1979"/>. Building on this early initiative,
                    the Liverpool <title rend="italic">Cancionero</title> project began in the
                    mid-1980s, using Madison tagging norms, and led to the <title rend="italic"
                        >Electronic Corpus of 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-Century Castilian
                        Cancionero Manuscripts</title>, which included codicological MS
                    descriptions, digitised MS images and digital transcriptions of the corpus.
                    These two projects, pioneering in the field, led the way not only in making use
                    of digital technologies to bring together a dispersed corpus for the first time,
                    but also in developing tagging systems for medieval manuscripts that have
                    changed the way that scholars access such texts.</p>
                <p>If the <title rend="italic">Cancionero</title> project is a prime example of how
                    ML scholarship has integrated DH tools in the analysis of manuscripts, and,
                    essentially, mobilised DH in relation to already existing (pre-digital) sources,
                    other projects have used DH tools and methodologies in the creation of their
                    corpora. Such is the case, for instance, of the HERA-funded collaborative <title
                        rend="italic">Travelling Texts, 1790-1914</title> project which undertakes
                    systematic scrutiny of reception data from large-scale sources (library and
                    booksellers’ catalogues, the periodical press), and thus uses DH approaches in
                    the creation of its data. In a similar vein, Kirsty Hooper’s digital history
                    projects, such as her <title rend="italic">Hispanic Liverpool</title> database
                    of nineteenth-century Liverpool residents who were born in the Hispanic world,
                    or her <title rend="italic">Atlantis Project: Women and Words in Spain,
                        1890-1936</title>, involving a database of bio-bibliographic information
                    about women writers in Spain, make use of databases to explore <q>what the details of forgotten lives can tell us
                        about wider questions in cultural history</q>. In these and other
                    projects, the advent of what are loosely termed <q>big data</q> approaches have
                    had a significant impact on how ML scholarship conceives of itself.<note>
                        Deriving initially from the physical sciences to refer to projects involving
                        very large quantities of data (such as the one petabyte of data per day
                        generated by the Hadron Collider) that exceed our capabilities to deal with
                        it, <q>big data</q> approaches are also being developed within the
                        humanities. Although big data definitions in the humanities are still being
                        agreed upon, we draw on Andrew Prescott’s reflections on big data in the
                        humanities as involving projects when data is on such a scale that the
                            <soCalled>tried and trusted</soCalled> approaches must be re-thought,
                        and meaning a <quote rend="inline" source="#messner2015">shift in the
                            cultural record that we have to deal with</quote> [quoted in <ptr
                            target="#messner2015"/>]. We do not, by this, mean to suggest that big
                        data approaches are necessarily entirely novel, or that they necessitate the
                        overthrowing of all our conventional humanities methodologies. Rather, we
                        take on board Prescott’s reminder that one can argue that big data goes back
                        to classical antiquity [quoted in <ptr target="#messner2015"/>]; and
                        Hitchcock’s exhortations that, in the rush towards big data approaches, we
                        must not forget the <q>small data</q> approaches that have always
                        characterised Humanities methodologies as well as <cit>
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#hitchcock2014">remember the importance of
                                the digital tools that allow us to think small</quote>
                            <ptr target="#hitchcock2014"/>
                        </cit>. </note>
                </p>
                <p>Corpus linguistics is another area within ML that has spearheaded DH approaches,
                    with the Real Academia Española’s <title rend="italic">CORDE</title> (<title
                        rend="italic">Corpus Diacrónico del Español</title>) project – a textual
                    corpus of all time periods and geographical regions in which Spanish has been
                    spoken, up to 1974 – and the <title rend="italic">CREA</title> project (<title
                        rend="italic">Corpus de Referencia del Español Actual</title>) – a corpus of
                    contemporary Spanish, which takes up where CORDE leaves off – being two of the
                    leading and most widely-used resources. These, along with similar projects in
                    other of the Iberian languages – such as the <title rend="italic">CICA</title>
                    corpus of Old Catalán, or the <title rend="italic">Corpus do Português</title> –
                    have had a significant impact on the way in which ML scholars approach corpora.
                    Scholars such as Mark Davies have demonstrated how these large-scale databases
                    provide an <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#davies2010">entirely new perspective on what
                            can be done with historical corpora</quote>
                        <ptr target="#davies2010" loc="142"/>
                    </cit>, allowing for a wide range of queries and the searching of topics in an
                    in-depth way that was not possible previously. </p>
                <p>Yet archiving pre-digital corpora or creating new corpora from disparate
                    pre-digital materials, and the <soCalled>big data</soCalled> approaches that
                    such corpora facilitate, are not the only achievements of Modern Linguists
                    working with Digital Humanities approaches. Digital Humanities approaches in ML
                    also extend to the generation of new analytical methods, as seen, for example,
                    in the work of Hispanist and film studies scholar Catherine Grant who has
                    developed highly innovative video essays on films, both celluloid and digital.
                    These video essays are not just a way for Grant to disseminate her work in
                    public fora – via her <title rend="italic">Film Studies for Free</title> or
                    (co-edited) <title rend="italic">Mediático</title> blogs – but constitute a new
                    form of methodological approach in itself which allows her to view films
                    differently, for example allowing her to analyse excerpts of a film and its
                    remake simultaneously and thus discover things that older, less accurately
                    synchronic methods of comparative analysis arguably could not have revealed. The
                    innovation in Grant’s work, then, is her conception of digital interventions as
                    not purely instrumental tools, but as creative outlets that combine both
                    research and object of study. This innovative methodological development, and
                    others like it, has not yet been fully embraced by DH – Grant’s work, for
                    instance, has not yet been taken up by any DH companion or compendium –, but
                    arguably there is a fruitful conversation to be had about new digital analytical
                    and methodological approaches resulting from it.</p>
                <p>All of these – and many others besides – are examples of how ML has benefitted
                    from DH tools and methodologies, and how ML in its various forms has engaged
                    with DH approaches. The bigger projects for corpora in particular are also
                    indicators of the growing ways in which these and other ML projects have had to
                    conceive of themselves as collaborative, involving computer scientists as much
                    as linguists, and requiring a re-thinking of the <soCalled>lone
                        scholar</soCalled> model. In this regard, DH is one of the drivers within a
                    general paradigm shift that has seen humanities scholarship more broadly move
                    away from this <soCalled>lone scholar</soCalled> model, motivated by a
                    generalised understanding that there is a need for more inter- and
                    transdisciplinarity, as we seek to answer bigger, more complex questions.
                    Digital Humanities tools and methods have, thus, contributed to the growing ways
                    in which we as ML scholars have re-evaluated our practice as researchers, and
                    have enriched our research field.</p>
                <p>In this changing landscape of ML research, which in many cases relates to
                    existing manuscripts, records or corpora and how they may best be mobilised
                    through the digital, an emerging field has also been that of the digital as
                    object of study in ML. Profound and significant changes to our objects of study
                    have been wrought by digital creators and users living in other parts of the
                    globe, and working in a variety of languages. The large and vibrant communities
                    of digital practice in non-Anglophone contexts – from net artists and authors of
                    electronic literature, through to hacktivists and tactical media practitioners –
                    have made, and continue to make, significant contributions to the ways in which
                    we think about and use digital technologies today. Here, ML’s findings as
                    regards digital content creation in various locales and communities around the
                    globe can provide insights that would enrich DH, and contribute to its ongoing
                    shaping of itself as a discipline. </p>
                <p>With regard to the ways in which DH has started to engage with ML, it is
                    important to note the significant efforts that DH associations have made to
                    include the pluricultural and the plurilingual [see <ptr target="#spence2014a"
                        loc="53"/>]. The recent creation of both the Asociación de Humanidades
                    Digitales Hispánicas (HDH) in Spain and the Red de Humanistas Digitales (RedDH)
                    in Mexico are good examples of the growth of a self-identifying Hispanic DH. The
                    Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO) DH2015 conference, which was
                    held in Sydney, Australia, included papers in French, German, Italian and
                    Spanish as well as English, and the next ADHO conference will be held in Mexico
                    City in 2018. At the same time, there has been an active debate on DH discussion
                    lists about how heavily Anglophone a purportedly <soCalled>global</soCalled> DH
                    really is, with Hispanic DH scholars fighting back. Galina Russell’s recent
                    article <ptr target="#galina2014"/> provides an illuminating overview of these
                    debates within the DH community as it grapples with issues of geographical and
                    linguistic diversity, and summarises recent developments that have attempted to
                    create a more global DH community.</p>
                <p>Within these attempts to ensure a greater linguistic and geographical diversity
                    in DH, ML can make important contributions as regards critical analysis of the
                    digital object of study. It is important to note that the first steps in this
                    process have already been taken, with pioneering scholars such as Paul Spence
                    who have aimed to bring digital critical cultural studies into the DH fold. A
                    scholar whose work straddles ML and DH, Spence set down in a recent article as
                    one of his six key proposals the need to <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#spence2014a">crear unas humanidades digitales verdaderamente
                        globales</quote> (to create a truly global digital humanities)<note> All
                        translations from Spanish are our own, unless otherwise indicated.</note>
                    <ptr target="#spence2014a" loc="52"/>, and within the same article, argued for
                    bringing scholars such as comparative literature theorist Laura Borràs – and the
                    critical cultural studies that she represents – into the domain of DH.<note> For
                        further examples of DH projects in Spain see <ptr target="#spence2014b"
                        />.</note> This impetus from Spence is one that we pick up on in this
                    article: we argue that one way of achieving this truly global DH is to bring the
                    critical cultural studies of ML into the DH fold, and we detail here what the
                    advantages of such a manoeuvre might be.</p>
                <p>One particular way in which an ML-inflected approach to DH can be constructive is
                    in the study of (digital) objects. All too frequently, digital technologies,
                    their applications and their analyses have been developed in a predominantly
                    Anglophone environment. Notwithstanding some landmark volumes which have aimed
                    to contest Anglophone models, such as <title rend="italic">Internationalizing
                        Internet Studies</title>
                    <ptr target="#goggin2009"/>, or the multi-authored <title rend="italic">Net
                        Lang: Towards a Multilingual Cyberspace</title>
                    <ptr target="#maaya"/>, it still remains the case that digital culture theory is
                    dominated by the Anglophone. What ML can provide is a pluricultural and
                    plurilingual understanding of digital culture, an attention to cultural and
                    linguistic specificity, and even a questioning of some of the predominantly
                    Anglophone assumptions underpinning many of the purported
                        <soCalled>universal</soCalled> theories of digital technologies.</p>
                <p>As regards the positioning of this research within DH, if, as DH scholars have
                    noted above, attention to digital cultural production remains relatively
                    underdeveloped within DH, but is, nevertheless, a key component of DH’s
                    development, then our work in this area can help to strengthen DH’s profile
                    overall. Furthermore, the cultural and linguistic insights that ML can
                    contribute are key to ensuring that DH’s approach to global digital culture is
                    as well informed and contextualised as possible. As we illustrate below, ML
                    approaches can help develop new insights into how these cultural forms are
                    negotiated by users crossing languages and cultures; we can offer relational and
                    situated approaches; and we can demonstrate how plurilingual and pluricultural
                    understandings of cultural heritage can bring enhanced understandings of these
                    cultural products.</p>
                <p>A DH informed by ML approaches would, for example, look at the digital as object
                    of study, both in terms of the reconceptualisation of existing cultural formats
                    in their meeting with the digital, and in terms of the advent of new platforms
                    that have transformed our understanding of what a <q>text</q> is. It would offer
                    an analysis of new cultural forms being developed at the interface between
                    literary-cultural expression and new media technologies, exploring the
                    transformations in conventional understandings of genres and cultural-artistic
                    codes stimulated by the advent of digital technologies. And most importantly, it
                    would explore how these new digital genres – as varied as hypermedia fiction or
                    game art – do not build exclusively upon an Anglophone heritage, but respond to
                    and continue a rich tradition of cultural, literary and artistic experimentation
                    undertaken by writers, artists and thinkers working in many different languages
                    and countries.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, an ML-inflected Digital Humanities would also allow us to consider
                    how some of the key terms regarding digital technologies might be inflected
                    differently in distinct cultural contexts. It would allow DH to engage more
                    closely with research that explores to what extent these new digital cultural
                    forms foster greater interaction and afford greater agency to the user, and what
                    the implications of this might be when users cross languages and cultures. Here,
                    Puerto Rican scholar Leonardo Flores’s leading work on electronic literature and
                    digital poetics <ptr target="#flores2011"/>, and the work of Colombian
                    scholar-practitioner Jaime Alejandro Rodríguez on hypertext authoring systems
                        <ptr target="#rodríguez2000"/>, would be of particular use in tracing how
                    digital genres mutate and are re-worked by users according to their linguistic
                    and cultural contexts. Similarly, the co-edited work of Chilean poet and
                    theorist Luis Correa-Díaz and Hispanist Scott Weintraub <ptr
                        target="#Correa-Díaz2010"/>
                    <ptr target="#Correa-Díaz2016"/>, and of author and theorist Loss Pequeño
                    Glazier <ptr target="#glazier2002"/> on digital poetics, along with the work of
                    the aforementioned Laura Borràs <ptr target="#borràs2010"/>
                    <ptr target="#borràs2017"/> on electronic literature have been pioneering in
                    analysing how digital cultural forms are inflected and experienced differently
                    in different cultural contexts. Their work has helped move cultural and literary
                    studies forward by exploring how digital technologies make us re-think some of
                    our existing assumptions about genre, whilst at the same time reminding us of
                    the embeddedness of these digital technologies within particular socio-cultural
                    codes.</p>
                <p>Perhaps even more significantly, an ML-inflected DH would allow us to explore the
                    ways in which a deep understanding of cultural and linguistic specificity can
                    help us to understand better – and even problematise – some of the assumptions
                    around the globalising nature of digital technologies. Building on our own
                    experiences as Modern Languages scholars, in which we have had to explore how
                    the implicit nation-state assumptions that conventionally underpin Modern
                    Languages practice need to be re-thought in the light of the opportunities
                    presented by digital technologies for a re-signification of locality, we can
                    offer an enhanced understanding of the digital-as-globalising debates. We can
                    explore how cultural identities that transgress nation-state boundaries may be
                    expressed and enabled through digital technologies, and how non-Anglophone or
                    plurilingual contexts might provide us with models for understanding the
                    processes of de- and re-territorialisation offered by many digital
                    technologies.</p>
                <p>One potential way of opening up these debates between these multiple vectors –
                    between DH and ML on the one hand, and between digital tools and digital objects
                    of study on the other – has been the recent Writing Sprint organised in
                    collaboration with Liverpool University Press’s Modern Languages Open
                        platform.<note> The writing sprint process itself can be seen at the writing
                        sprint blog <title rend="italic">Modlangdigital: The Modern Languages Open
                            Writing Sprint</title>, <ref
                            target="https://modernlangdigital.wordpress.com"
                            >https://modernlangdigital.wordpress.com</ref>, and a summary of the
                        experience has now been published as a more static piece on the Modern
                        Languages Open platform <ptr target="#taylor2017"/>.</note> Focused around
                    the key topic of <q>Modern Languages and the Digital</q>, the writing sprint
                    explored how digital technologies are changing the shape of Modern Languages
                    research and publishing, and asked how the conceptual, methodological and
                    practical bases of Modern Languages research are having to adapt to the
                    challenges of the digital. Key to the Writing Sprint was the bringing together
                    of scholars working both in Modern Languages and in Digital Humanities
                    institutional contexts, and with expertise across the whole range of the
                    research process, thus putting into dialogue digital ethnographers with big data
                    scholars, digital editors with digital critical scholars, and so forth. The
                    Writing Sprint thus aimed to open up these dialogues from tools to objects of
                    study, and one of its main findings was the need for us to be working
                    collaboratively – across institutions, across disciplines, and across languages
                    – and that an in-depth and critical engagement with the digital is central to
                    this collaboration.</p>
                <p>Within this broad context of the contributions that ML scholarship has made to
                    the development of DH, we now move on to some specific examples of our own work
                    in the field of Latin American digital culture studies in order to draw out the
                    connections with the paradigm of <q>critical</q> Digital Humanities, working
                    with a hybrid Modern Languages and Digital Humanities framework that one might
                    like to term a <q>critical DHML</q>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Latin American Digital Cultural Production</head>
                <p>Our first publication, the anthology <title rend="italic">Latin American
                        Cyberculture and Cyberliterature</title>
                    <ptr target="#taylor2007"/>, was intended as no more than a
                        <soCalled>toe-in-the-water</soCalled> collection of essays to explore new
                    forms of literary production, but in retrospect it marked a much more
                    significant change in terms of our disciplinary identities. The shift to look at
                    Latin American engagement with the internet revealed to us the need to move on
                    from an albeit well-contextualised literary studies disciplinary approach – the
                    discipline in which we were both trained – to a cultural studies one, and to
                    others still further removed from our original schooling, in order to embrace
                    the increasing variety of the materials and practices we wanted to study.<note>
                        The shift is evident in the rather awkward title that balances the field of
                            <q>cyberliterature</q>, which is what we had originally set out to write
                        about, with that of <q>cyberculture</q> conceived most broadly.</note> Given
                    that we are scholars of Modern Languages, the (trans/inter)discipline, the
                    concept of shifting from one discipline to another, as well as from one language
                    to another as we move across the dominant languages of the region, sat well with
                    us, and this increasing diversification of disciplines continues in our more
                    recent work.<note> Incipient in the first collection were attempts to move
                        towards a more sociological approach – internet ethnography, as it is most
                        often called – as various scholars sought to explore projects for digital
                        inclusion or examples of digital activism, and this research thread
                        continues to this day in Pitman’s work on self-defining <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#holmes2013">digital indigenous peoples</quote> in Brazil, or
                        particular social media groups based around technofeminist concerns or
                        sexual identities. Our colleague Tori Holmes’s work is also significant for
                        its work in developing internet ethnographic frameworks for working with
                        digital content produced by favela residents in Brazil [see <ptr
                            target="#holmes2013"/>].</note>
                </p>
                <p>Our key findings from the collection were that it was possible to conceive of
                    Latin American cultural producers as often choosing to strategically resist new
                    technologies, albeit while simultaneously using them, and that they had reason
                    to do this because of their non-conformity with the neo-colonialist rhetoric
                    underpinning most Anglophone discourse concerning
                        <soCalled>cyberspace</soCalled> (qua <soCalled>new frontier</soCalled>), and
                    that they even made claims for the need for <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#Martín-Barbero2000">new architectures of
                            language</quote>
                        <ptr target="#Martín-Barbero2000" loc="69"/>
                    </cit> that went as structurally deep as code. As Raúl Trejo Delabre has argued:
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#TrejoDelabre1999">the formats for making and organising
                        websites have been determined by technology and subsequently by the customs
                        of the biggest community of Netusers in the world; i.e. the citizens of the
                        United States</quote>, and thus <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#TrejoDelabre1999">there is no Latin American
                                <emph>language</emph> in which to express our specific content in
                            that global hall of mirrors that is the Internet</quote>
                        <ptr target="#TrejoDelabre1999" loc="330, original emphasis"/>
                    </cit>. </p>
                <p>In a comparable way to the consolidation of European languages in the region such
                    that it is impossible for most to speak in anything but <soCalled>the master’s
                        tongue</soCalled>, it is probably too late for Latin Americans, or indeed
                    any of us, to develop a form of programming that overcomes modularity and
                    lenticularity [see <ptr target="#McPherson2012"/>] – not even open source
                    software can really offer such a radical revision of the paradigms of
                    computational culture, it seems. However, it also became apparent through our
                    work on this collection, how Latin American writers, for example, might attempt
                    to resist, however ironically, the modularity that underpins the functioning of
                    hypertext [see <ptr target="#pitman2007"/>]. In this way our collection sought
                    to offer a postcolonialist critique of the presence and use of the internet and
                    associated technologies in the region and one that tried to dig deeper than a
                    superficial critique of representation on computer screens. Furthermore, if we
                    read <q>Latin Americans</q> as <q>raza</q>,<note> The word <q>raza</q> in
                        Spanish means <q>race</q> but it is also used more broadly to mean a
                            <q>people</q> and when Latin(o) Americans refer to themselves as
                            <q>raza</q> they tend to mean the latter, thus including all different
                        racial groups within Latin American society under this rubric, although
                        sometimes privileging a certain mixed <q>white</q> Spanish-indigenous
                        American racial profile at the same time.</note> or at the very least as a
                    differently situated (and very large) group of people to <q>white</q> US
                    citizens, this collection provides copious examples of academic work in the
                    broad field of Digital Humanities that does not focus on <q>white</q> subjects,
                    and some that explicitly focuses on the role that race, as well as gender and
                    other identitarian vectors, plays in such cultural production. In this way we
                    can be seen as having made an early contribution to the recently emerged fields
                    of critical/postcolonial Digital Humanities.</p>
                <p>In our 2012 book, <title rend="italic">Latin American Identity in Online Cultural
                        Production</title>, we set forth an important confrontation of Latin
                    American cultural studies and digital culture studies, and proposed a
                    theorisation of a post-regional approach to Latin American (digital) cultural
                    studies. Our volume brought into dialogue two disciplinary fields – namely,
                    internet studies and Latin Americanism – and, working in negotiation between
                    these two disciplines, we proposed an innovative theoretical model for
                    understanding how the defining discourses of Latin America are reconfigured
                    online. Our contention in this publication was that Latin American digital
                    culture, and the theoretical and analytical models we proposed for it, engage
                    with some of the central issues that are at the heart of both internet studies
                    and Latin Americanism today. The questioning of the project of area studies, and
                    of Latin American studies as one such area within that, has been widely debated
                    since the 1990s, and represents a potential troubling of the very foundations on
                    which, ostensibly, we Latin Americanists base our research, demanding a
                    re-assessment of what it means to engage in Latin American studies in our
                    contemporary, globalised world. However, we went on to argue that to talk of
                    Latin American online cultural practice is not an outright paradox, but rather
                    emblematic of new forms of rather more deterritorialised Latin Americanism which
                    take into account the problematisation of area studies. Indeed, we argued that
                    it is at the intersection of these two developments – on the one hand, a rise in
                    scholarly debates on Latin American (popular) culture and new media, and, on the
                    other hand, the deconstruction of the term <q>Latin America</q> itself – that
                    the study of Latin American online cultural production lies. This, then, was our
                    contribution to challenging through internet studies a key aspect of <q>the <soCalled>hard-core</soCalled> of the
                        humanities</q> that Berry hoped critical/third-wave Digital Humanities
                    would address.</p>
                <p>In a more recent publication, our research has explored the need to re-think some
                    of the assumptions around globalising digital technologies when looking from a
                    ML perspective. Taylor’s 2013 volume engaged with one of the most topical issues
                    in discussions about the internet in recent years: the extent to which online
                    content can be understood as rooted in a particular place. Taylor’s book
                    explored this issue taking as examples a vibrant community of Latin(o) American
                    artists to investigate how, in their online works, they engage in re-imaginings
                    and representations of offline place. Building on and dialoguing with recent
                    debates on tactical media, as well as upon the rich Latin(o) American-specific
                    heritage of the resistant appropriation of hegemonic tools in a broader sense,
                    the book demonstrated how networked digital media offers the possibilities of
                    rethinking place and territory, and how Latin(o) American net artists make
                    creative use of this possibility. The book’s two overarching questions –
                    firstly, the role that digital technologies play in allowing for the formulation
                    of place-based affiliations, and secondly, how alternative modes of expression
                    and dissemination enabled by digital technologies may be appropriated to give
                    voice to oppositional or resistant discourses – are, we argue, of particular
                    relevance to DH today. The book’s potential contributions to DH therefore
                    include an awareness of the rootedness and of the (cultural, linguistic, ethnic)
                    specificity of how, where, and why digital technologies are used, coupled with
                    an understanding of how these digital technologies are used to express profound
                    social, political and ethical concerns.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>All of these instances discussed above – our own and those of other scholars –
                    demonstrate the potential for the further development of a <soCalled>common
                        language</soCalled> between ML cultural studies and critical DH in which
                    more of us working in these two disciplines ought to seek to achieve fluency.
                    The development of this kind of common language may also prove to be an
                    important factor in helping to avoid disciplinary
                        <soCalled>Balkanisation</soCalled> as DH settles into traditional
                    institutional structures. For as long as scholars of both Digital Humanities and
                    Modern Languages continue to be able to conceive of themselves as promoting a
                        <soCalled>critical</soCalled> or <soCalled>reflexive</soCalled>, rather than
                    instrumental, strategic or opportunistic, kind of interdisciplinarity, and/or a
                    transdisciplinarity that is transgressive, critical and genuinely open to other
                    perspectives, to borrow Thompson Klein’s terms cited earlier, then at an
                    epistemological level, they will be capable of working together and speaking the
                    same language. On a more pragmatic level, they will need both a political
                    climate, within and beyond Higher Education – a climate that, for example, does
                    not seek to manage the dialogue between disciplines as one might a business
                    enterprise –, and the kinds of resources – most importantly, time – that are
                    conducive to creative, speculative engagement with other points of view that
                    may, or may not always, bear fruit. </p>
                <p>Indeed, as Modern Linguists we have seen our own discipline re-think itself over
                    recent years in ways that seem promising with regard to avoiding Balkanisation.
                    In both institutional structures, where individual language departments have
                    been reconfigured into schools or departments of languages (or bigger) – meaning
                    that individual language areas move out of <soCalled>silos</soCalled> to work
                    together – and in intellectual debates about the nature of ML, which have
                    increasingly led us to understand ourselves as being located across disciplines,
                    ML today straddles conventional departmental structures and disciplines in ways
                    that are conducive to reaching out to DH and to the development of a
                        <soCalled>critical DHML</soCalled> language.</p>
                <p>This hybrid <soCalled>critical DHML</soCalled> language is what many more young
                    academics ought to be speaking, and there are already many positive signs that
                    it will, indeed, be the language spoken in our classrooms and conferences, and
                    written in our academic journal and blogs. These signs include the increasing
                    numbers of adverts for lecturing posts (mainly in the USA) that specifically
                    seek academics who work in both Digital Humanities and Latin American/Hispanic
                    studies, and those for postdoctoral or postgraduate study in Hispanic Studies
                    where an interest in DH methodologies is an explicit criterion for appointment
                    or where the research programme is co-supervised between a DH and an ML
                        scholar.<note> For example, a postdoctoral position was advertised at the
                        University of Warwick in 2015, in conjunction with Kirsty Hooper’s AHRC
                        funded project <title rend="quotes">Imperial Entanglements: Transoceanic
                            Basque Networks in British and Spanish Colonialism and their
                            Legacy</title>, for a candidate interested in DH methodologies. King’s
                        College London now offers co-supervised PhDs in <title rend="quotes">Digital
                            Spanish, Portuguese and Latin American Studies</title>, for example,
                        with one supervisor based in the relevant ML department and the other in the
                        Department of Digital Humanities.</note> They may also be discerned in the
                    existence of the growing volume of joint DH and ML conferences and other events
                    within Anglophone academia;<note> One notable example of this was the 2010
                            <title rend="quotes">Exploring the Archive in the Digital Age</title>
                        conference at King’s College London which included contributions by staff
                        from what was then still the Centre for Computing in the Humanities as well
                        as those from across the traditional humanities departments and was
                        organised by the Department of Spanish and Spanish-American Studies.</note>
                    and in the emergence of new or reconfigured research
                        <soCalled>centres</soCalled> such as the recently established Latin American
                    and Latino Digital Humanities initiative at the University of Georgia (UGA) and
                    the recently reconfigured Centre for World Cinemas and Digital Cultures in the
                    School of Languages, Cultures and Societies at the University of Leeds.</p>
                <p>To return to <title rend="italic">DHQ</title>’s initiative to start publishing
                    special issues dedicated to Digital Humanities <q>in different languages or regional traditions</q>, which was the
                    original motivation for this series of reflections on the relationship between
                    DH and ML, perhaps a parallel initiative is what is also necessary: one that
                    does not seek to separate off work written in modern foreign languages and
                    dealing with differently situated materials into discrete entities (special
                    issues) because surely this is also evidence of what McPherson termed the logic
                    of <soCalled>lenticularity</soCalled> or what we discussed
                    above under the rubric of <soCalled>Balkanisation</soCalled>. What we really
                    need, among other things, is a special issue dedicated to <soCalled>critical
                        DHML</soCalled> that probes further the common language that binds us.</p>
                <p>Beyond that, the next steps for achieving such a hybrid language are both
                    pragmatic and intellectual. Following on from our discussion of ways to avoid
                    disciplinary <soCalled>Balkanisation</soCalled>, pragmatic next steps will also
                    include continuing to forge dialogues through shared trans- and
                    interdisciplinary workshops, panels, conferences and public engagement events
                    that bring together our two disciplines, and that ensure that ML is embedded in
                    DH, and vice versa. These developments, coupled with a commitment to equipping
                    the next generation of researchers, through doctoral training and postdoctoral
                    opportunities, as fully-fledged hybrid DHML scholars, are essential in
                    developing our shared language and, eventually, in normalising it. Intellectual
                    next steps include ensuring that both ML and DH are attuned to thematic working.
                    The current shifts in the UK research environment, with the increasing need to
                    work collaboratively, and to address global challenges that cannot be solely
                    answered by any one discipline or methodology, offer fruitful opportunities for
                    the development of our shared language. The continuing development of the
                    synergies between ML and DH, and of thematic working that cuts across
                    disciplines and methods, can help situate both ML and DH at the forefront of
                    approaches to these global challenges. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="alvarado2012" label="Alvarado 2012">Alvarado, R. C. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Digital Humanities Situation.</title> In M. K. Gold (ed.),
                    Debates in the Digital Humanities. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis
                    (2012), pp. 50-55.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berry2012" label="Berry 2012">Berry, D. M. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Introduction: Understanding the Digital Humanities.</title> In D. M. Berry
                    (ed.) Understanding Digital Humanities. Palgrave Macmillan, Basingstoke (2012),
                    pp. 1-20.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berry2014" label="Berry 2014">Berry, D. M. Critical Theory and the
                    Digital. Bloomsbury, New York (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="borràs2017" label="Borràs 2017 (forthcoming)">Borràs, L. En
                    construcció: la literatura en l'era digital. Editorial UIB, Barcelona (2017
                    forthcoming).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="borràs2010" label="Borràs et al. 2010">Borràs, L., Memmot, T., Raley,
                    R., and Stefans, B. K. (eds) Electronic Literature Collection, vol. II,
                    Electronic Literature Organization (2010). <ref
                        target="http://collection.eliterature.org/2/"
                        >http://collection.eliterature.org/2/</ref>. Accessed: 17 January
                    2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Correa-Díaz2010" label="Correa-Díaz and Weintraub 2010">Correa-Díaz,
                    L., and Weintraub, S. (eds) Special Issue: <title rend="quotes">Literatura
                        latinoamericana, española, portuguesa en la era digital (nuevas tecnologías
                        y lo literario)</title>, Arizona Journal of Hispanic Cultural Studies, 14
                    (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Correa-Díaz2016" label="Correa-Díaz and Weintraub 2016">Correa-Díaz,
                    L., and Weintraub, S. (eds) Poesía y poéticas
                    digitales/electrónicas/tecnos/New-Media en América Latina: Definiciones y
                    exploraciones. Universidad Central de Bogotá (2016). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="davies2010" label="Davies 2010">Davies, M. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Creating Useful Historical Corpora: A Comparison of CORDE, the Corpus del
                        Español, and the Corpus do Português.</title> In A. Enrique-Arias (ed.),
                    Diacrónica de las lenguas iberromances: nuevas perspectivas desde la lingüística
                    de corpus. Iberoamericana, Frankfurt (2010), pp. 137-66.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cancionero" label="Cancionero Virtual">An Electronic Corpus of 15<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> Century Castillian <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cancionero</hi> Manuscripts (2008–). <ref
                        target="http://cancionerovirtual.liv.ac.uk/"
                        >http://cancionerovirtual.liv.ac.uk</ref>. Accessed: 17 January 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fitzpatrick2012" label="Fitzpatrick 2012">Fitzpatrick, K. <title
                        rend="quotes">The Humanities, Done Digitally.</title> In M. K. Gold (ed.),
                    Debates in the Digital Humanities. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press,
                    Minneapolis (2012), pp. 12-15.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="flanders2007" label="Flanders et al. 2007">Flanders, J., Piez, W. and
                    Terras, M. <title rend="quotes">Welcome to <title rend="italic">Digital
                            Humanities Quarterly</title></title>, <hi rend="italic">Digital
                        Humanities Quarterly</hi>, 1:1 (2007), <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/1/1/000007/000007.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/1/1/000007/000007.html</ref>.
                    Accessed: 16 October 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="flores2011" label="Flores">Flores, L. (ed.) I ♥ E-Poetry, (2011–).
                        <ref target="http://iloveepoetry.com/">http://iloveepoetry.com/</ref>.
                    Accessed: 12 January 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="forsdick2011" label="Forsdick 2011">Forsdick, C. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Why French Studies Matters: Disciplinary Identity and Public
                        Understanding.</title> In P. Lane and Worton, M. (eds), French Studies in
                    and for the Twenty First Century. Liverpool University Press (2011), pp.
                    37-57.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galina2014" label="Galina Russell 2014">Galina Russell, I. <title
                        rend="quotes">Geographical and Linguistic Diversity in the Digital
                        Humanities</title>, Literary and Linguistic Computing, 1-10 (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="glazier2002" label="Glazier 2002">Glazier, L. P. Digital Poetics: the
                    Making of E-Poetries. University of Alabama Press, Tuscaloosa (2002).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="goggin2009" label="Goggin 2009">Goggin, G., and McLelland, M.
                    Internationalizing Internet Studies: Beyond Anglophone Paradigms. Routledge, New
                    York (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gold2012" label="Gold 2012">Gold, M. K. (ed.) Debates in the Digital
                    Humanities. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gold2016" label="Gold and Klein 2016">Gold, M. K., and Klein, L. F.
                    (eds) Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016. University of Minnesota Press,
                    Minneapolis (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="grant2008" label="Grant 2008">Grant, C. (ed.) Film Studies for Free
                    (2008–). <ref target="http://filmstudiesforfree.blogspot.co.uk/"
                        >http://filmstudiesforfree.blogspot.co.uk/</ref>. Accessed: 17 January 2016. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harding2015" label="Harding 2015">Harding, S. Objectivity and
                    Diversity: Another Logic of Scientific Research. Chicago: University of Chicago
                    Press (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hitchcock2014" label="Hitchcock 2014">Hitchcock, T. <title
                        rend="quotes">Big Data, Small Data, and Meaning</title>, Historyonics
                    (2014). <ref
                        target="http://historyonics.blogspot.co.uk/2014/11/big-data-small-data-and-meaning_9.html"
                        >http://historyonics.blogspot.co.uk/2014/11/big-data-small-data-and-meaning_9.html</ref>.
                    Accessed: 12 January 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="holmes2013" label="Holmes 2013">Holmes, T. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Linking Internet Texts and Practices: Challenges and Opportunities of
                        Interdisciplinarity in an Ethnographically Inspired Study of <q>Local
                            Content</q></title>, Westminster Papers in Communication and Culture,
                    9:3 (2013), 121-42.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hooper2012" label="Hooper 2012">Hooper , K. The Atlantis Project:
                    Women and Words in Spain, 1890-1936 (2012–). <ref
                        target="http://atlantis.kirstyhooper.net/"
                        >http://atlantis.kirstyhooper.net/</ref>. Accessed: 12 January 2016. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hooper2015" label="Hooper 2015">Hooper , K. Hispanic Liverpool
                    (2015–). <ref
                        target="http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/arts/modernlanguages/research/hispanic/hispanicliverpool"
                        >http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/arts/modernlanguages/research/hispanic/hispanicliverpool</ref>.
                    Accessed: 12 January 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu2011" label="Liu 2011">Liu, A. <title rend="quotes">Where Is
                        Cultural Criticism in the Digital Humanities?</title>, original full text of
                    paper presented at the panel on “The History and Future of the Digital
                    Humanities”, Modern Language Association convention, Los Angeles, 7 January
                    2011. <ref
                        target="http://liu.english.ucsb.edu/where-is-cultural-criticism-in-the-digital-humanities/"
                        >http://liu.english.ucsb.edu/where-is-cultural-criticism-in-the-digital-humanities/</ref>.
                    Accessed: 16 October 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lopez2015" label="Lopez et al. 2015">Lopez, A., Roland, F., and
                    Fitzpatrick, K. <title rend="quotes">On Scholarly Communication and the Digital
                        Humanities: An Interview with Kathleen Fitzpatrick</title>, In the Library
                    with the Lead Pipe, 14 January 2015. <ref
                        target="http://www.inthelibrarywiththeleadpipe.org/2015/on-scholarly-communication-and-the-digital-humanities-an-interview-with-kathleen-fitzpatrick/"
                        >http://www.inthelibrarywiththeleadpipe.org/2015/on-scholarly-communication-and-the-digital-humanities-an-interview-with-kathleen-fitzpatrick/</ref>.
                    Accessed: 16 October 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="maaya" label="Maaya Network 2012">Maaya Network Net Lang: Towards the
                    Multilingual Cyberspace. C&amp;F Editions, Caen (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Martín-Barbero2000" label="Martín-Barbero 2000">Martín-Barbero, J.
                        <title rend="quotes">Art/Communication/Technicity at Century’s End.</title>
                    In A. Brooksbank Jones and R. Munck (eds), H. O’Donnell (trans.), Cultural
                    Politics in Latin America. Macmillan, Basingstoke (2000), pp. 56-73.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="McPherson2012" label="McPherson 2012">McPherson, T. <title
                        rend="quotes">Why Are the Digital Humanities So White? or, Thinking the
                        Histories of Race and Computation.</title> In M. K. Gold (ed.), Debates in
                    the Digital Humanities. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2012), pp.
                    139-60.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="messner2015" label="Messner 2015">Messner, D. <title rend="quotes"
                        >CODE 6: Andrew Prescott about Big Data in the Arts and Humanities</title>,
                    Coding History: Podcast Interviews (2015). <ref
                        target="http://codinghistory.com/podcast/code6/"
                        >http://codinghistory.com/podcast/code6/</ref>. Accessed: 12 January
                    2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mld2015" label="Modlangdigital">Modlangdigital: The Modern Languages
                    Open Writing Sprint (2015). <ref
                        target="https://modernlangdigital.wordpress.com/"
                        >https://modernlangdigital.wordpress.com/</ref>. Accessed: 12 January
                    2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nitti1979" label="Nitti 1979">Nitti, J. <title rend="quotes">Computers
                        and the Old Spanish Dictionary</title>, Special Issue: <title rend="quotes"
                        >Medieval Studies and the Computer</title>, Computers and the Humanities,
                    12:1-2 (1979), 43-52. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pitman2007" label="Pitman 2007">Pitman, T. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Hypertext in Context: Space and Time in the Hypertext and Hypermedia
                        Fictions of Blas Valdez and Doménico Chiappe.</title> In C. Taylor and T.
                    Pitman (eds), Latin American Cyberculture and Cyberliterature, Liverpool
                    University Press (2007), pp. 227-43.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dhpoco2013" label="Postcolonial Digital Humanities">Postcolonial
                    Digital Humanities (2013–). <ref target="http://dhpoco.org/"
                        >http://dhpoco.org/</ref>. Accessed: 27 July 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galina2015" label="Galina Russell 2015">Priego, E. <title
                        rend="quotes">Geopolitical Diversity in Digital Humanities: An Interview
                        with Isabel Galina Russell</title>, 4Humanities: Advocating for the
                    Humanities, 6 October 2015. <ref
                        target="http://4humanities.org/2015/10/geopolitical-diversity-in-digital-humanities-an-interview-with-isabel-galina-russell/"
                        >http://4humanities.org/2015/10/geopolitical-diversity-in-digital-humanities-an-interview-with-isabel-galina-russell/</ref>.
                    Accessed: 16 October 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="qaa" label="QAA 2015">Quality Assurance Agency (QAA) Subject Benchmark
                    Statement: Languages, Cultures and Societies, Draft for Consultation (2015).
                        <ref
                        target="http://www.qaa.ac.uk/en/Publications/Documents/SBS-consultation-Languages-Cultures-Societies-15.pdf"
                        >http://www.qaa.ac.uk/en/Publications/Documents/SBS-consultation-Languages-Cultures-Societies-15.pdf</ref>.
                    Accessed: 18 October 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rodríguez2000" label="Rodríguez 2000">Rodríguez, J. A. Hipertexto y
                    literatura: una batalla por el signo en tiempos posmodernos. Pontificia
                    Universidad Javeriana, Bogotá (2000).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schreibman2004" label="Schreibman et al. 2004">Schreibman, S.,
                    Siemens, R. and Unsworth, J. A Companion to the Digital Humanities. Blackwell,
                    Oxford (2004).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="spence2014a" label="Spence 2014">Spence, P. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Centros y fronteras: el panorama internacional de las humanidades
                        digitales</title>, Janus, Anexo 1: S. López Poza y N. Pena Sueiro (eds),
                        <title rend="quotes">Humanidades Digitales: desafíos, logros y perspectivas
                        de futuro</title> (2014), 37-61. <ref
                        target="http://www.janusdigital.es/anexos/contribucion.htm?id=6"
                        >http://www.janusdigital.es/anexos/contribucion.htm?id=6</ref>. Accessed: 1
                    November 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="spence2014b" label="Spence and González-Blanco 2014">Spence, P., and
                    González-Blanco, E. <title rend="quotes">A Historical Perspective on the Digital
                        Humanities in Spain</title>, H-Soz-Kult, Forum: <title rend="quotes">The
                        Status Quo of Digital Humanities in Europe</title>, Oct/Nov 2014. <ref
                        target="http://geschichte-transnational.clio-online.net/forum/type=diskussionen&amp;id=2449"
                        >http://geschichte-transnational.clio-online.net/forum/type=diskussionen&amp;id=2449</ref>.
                    Accessed: 22 November 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="svensson2015" label="Svensson and Goldberg 2015">Svensson, P., and
                    Goldberg, D. T. (eds) Between Humanities and the Digital. Cambridge, MA: MIT
                    Press (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taylor2014" label="Taylor 2014">Taylor, C. Place and Politics in Latin
                    American Digital Cultures: Location and Latin American Net Art. Routledge, New
                    York (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taylor2013" label="Taylor and Pitman 2013">Taylor, C. and Pitman, T.
                    Latin American Identity in Online Cultural Production. Routledge, New York
                    (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taylor2007" label="Taylor and Pitman 2007">Taylor, C. and Pitman, T.
                    (eds) Latin American Cyberculture and Cyberliterature. Liverpool University
                    Press (2007). Also available through Liverpool Scholarship Online, <ref
                        target="http://liverpool.universitypressscholarship.com/view/10.5949/UPO9781846313462/upso-9781846310614?rskey=PMeU3B&amp;result=3"
                        >http://liverpool.universitypressscholarship.com/view/10.5949/UPO9781846313462/upso-9781846310614?rskey=PMeU3B&amp;result=3</ref>.
                    Accessed: 17 January 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taylor2017" label="Taylor and Thornton 2017">Taylor, C. and Thornton
                    N., eds. <title rend="quotes">Modern Languages and the Digital: The Shape of the
                        Discipline</title>, Modern Languages Open, 17 January 2017. <ref
                        target="http://www.modernlanguagesopen.org/articles/10.3828/mlo.v0i0.156/"
                        >http://www.modernlanguagesopen.org/articles/10.3828/mlo.v0i0.156/</ref>.
                    Accessed 3 February 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="terras2013" label="Terras et al. 2013">Terras, M., Nyhan, J. and
                    Vanhoutte, E. (eds) Defining Digital Humanites: A Reader. Ashgate, Farnham
                    (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ThompsonKlein2015" label="Thompson Klein 2015">Thompson Klein, J.
                    Interdisciplining Digital Humanities: Boundary Work in an Emerging Field.
                    University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tierney2014" label="Tierney et al. 2014">Tierney, D., Ramos, J. and
                    Grant, C. (eds) Mediático (2014–). <ref
                        target="http://reframe.sussex.ac.uk/mediatico/"
                        >http://reframe.sussex.ac.uk/mediatico/</ref>. Accessed: 17 January
                    2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="TravellingTexts2014" label="Travelling Texts">Travelling Texts
                    1790-1914: the Transnational Reception of Women’s Writing at the Fringes of
                    Europe (TTT) (2014–). <ref target="http://heranet.info/ttt/index"
                        >http://heranet.info/ttt/index</ref>. Accessed: 17 January 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="TrejoDelabre1999" label="Trejo Delabre 1999">Trejo Delabre, R. <title
                        rend="quotes">La Internet en América Latina.</title> In N. García Canclini
                    and C. J. Moneta (eds), Las industrias culturales en la integración
                    latinoamericana. Grijalbo, Mexico City (1999), pp. 311-56.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="worton2009" label="Worton 2009">Worton, M. Review of Modern Language
                    Provision in Higher Education in England. Higher Education Funding Council for
                    England (HEFCE) (2009). <ref
                        target="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20100202100434/http://hefce.ac.uk/media/hefce1/pubs/hefce/2009/0941/09_41.pdf"
                        >http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20100202100434/http://hefce.ac.uk/media/hefce1/pubs/hefce/2009/0941/09_41.pdf</ref>.
                    Accessed: 17 October 2015.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
