<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">

  <!-- BEGIN TEI HEADER ELEMENTS -->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Audiovisualities out of Annotation: Three Case Studies
          in Teaching Digital Annotation with <emph>Mediate</emph></title>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Joel <dhq:family>Burges</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>University of Rochester</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>joel.burges@rochester.edu</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Joel Burges is Associate Professor of English, Film &amp; Media Studies, and Digital
              Media Studies, Director of the Graduate Program in Visual &amp; Cultural Studies, and
              the Principal Investigator of Mediate at the University of Rochester. At work on a
              book about the figure of the television writer from Carl Reiner to Issa Rae, he is
              author of <title rend="italic">Out of Sync &amp; Out of Work: History and the
                Obsolescence of Labor in Contemporary Culture</title> (Rutgers, 2018) and co-editor
              of <title rend="italic">Time: A Vocabulary of the Present</title> (NYU Press, 2016)
              with Amy J. Elias. More recently, he has co-edited and contributed to special issues
              of <title rend="italic">Post45</title> (<title rend="quotes">Stranger Things and
                Nostalgia Now</title>) and <title rend="italic">InVisible Culture</title> (<title
                rend="quotes">Black Studies Now and the Currency of Hazel Carby</title>).</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Solvegia <dhq:family>Armoskaite</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>University of Rochester</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>solveiga.armoskaite@rochester.edu</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Solvegia Armoskaite is a linguist who enjoys interdisciplinary collaborations on
              anything to do with language. Her current research focuses on emotion in language. The
              need to use digital means to capture emotional nuance drew her to this project.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Tiamat <dhq:family>Fox</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>University of Rochester</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>tfox6@u.rochester.edu</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Tiamat Fox holds a bachelors in Psychology and Language, Media, &amp; Communication,
              and a Minor in Business from the University of Rochester. While at University of
              Rochester, she worked as a research assistant for the Digital Scholarship Lab.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Darren <dhq:family>Mueller</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>University of Rochester</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>dmueller@esm.rochester.edu</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Darren Mueller is assistant professor of musicology at the Eastman School of Music,
              University of Rochester. With a focus in jazz studies, he researches how technologies
              of sound alter musical performance and the construction of racial ideologies in the
              United States. He is also the co-editor of <title rend="italic">Digital Sound
                Studies</title> (Duke University Press, 2018).</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Joshua <dhq:family>Romphf</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>University of Rochester</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>jromphf@library.rochester.edu</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Joshua Romphf is the programmer for the Digital Scholarship Lab at University of
              Rochester’s River Campus Libraries and the lead developer of Mediate. Originally from
              London, Ontario, he holds an MA in Film and Media Preservation from George Eastman
              Museum and The University of Rochester.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Emily <dhq:family>Sherwood</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>University of Rochester</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>esherwood@library.rochester.edu</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Emily Sherwood is the Director of the <ref target="http://dslab.lib.rochester.edu/"
                >Digital Scholarship Lab</ref> at University of Rochester’s River Campus Libraries.
              She is an alum of the Council on Library and Information Resources (CLIR) Postdoctoral
              Fellowship Program and holds a Ph.D. in English from the Graduate Center of the City
              University of New York.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Madeline <dhq:family>Ullrich</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>University of Rochester</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>mullrich@ur.rochester.edu</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Madeline Ullrich is a PhD student in the Graduate Program in Visual and Cultural
              Studies at the University of Rochester and an Andrew W. Mellon Digital Humanities
              Fellow. Her current research focuses on the study of television aesthetics and
              narrative, with an emphasis in feminist and queer theory.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
        <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
        <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000507</idno>
        <idno type="volume">015</idno>
        <idno type="issue">1</idno>
        <date when="2021-03-05">05 March 2021</date>
        <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
        <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
          <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
          <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at<ref
              target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
              >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
          <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2020-09-18" who="Taylor Arnold">Created file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <!-- END TEI HEADER ELEMENTS -->

  <!-- BEGIN TEXT -->
  <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
    <!-- FRONT TEXT -->
    <front>
      <dhq:abstract>
        <p>This article describes <emph>Mediate: An Annotation Tool for Audiovisual Media</emph>,
          developed at the University of Rochester, and emphasizes the platform as a source for the
          understanding of film, television, poetry, pop songs, live performance, music, and
          advertising as shown in three cases studies from film and media studies, music history,
          and linguistics. In each case collaboration amongst students was not only key, but also
          enabled by <emph>Mediate</emph>, which allows students to work in groups to generate large
          amounts of data about audiovisual media. Further, the process of data generation produces
          quantitative and qualitative observation of the mediated interplay of sight and sound. A
          major outcome of these classes for the faculty teaching them has been the concept of
            <emph>audiovisualities</emph>: the physically and culturally interpenetrating modes of
          audiovisual experience and audiovisual inscription where hearing and seeing remediate one
          another for all of us as sensory and social subjects. Throughout the article, we chart how
          audiovisualities have emerged for students and ourselves out of digital annotation in
            <emph>Mediate</emph>.</p>
      </dhq:abstract>
      <dhq:teaser>
        <p>This article describes <emph>Mediate: An Annotation Tool for Audiovisual Media</emph>,
          developed at the University of Rochester, and emphasizes the platform as a source for the
          understanding of film, television, poetry, pop songs, live performance, music, and
          advertising as shown in three cases studies from film and media studies, music history,
          and linguistics.</p>
      </dhq:teaser>
    </front>

    <!-- BODY TEXT -->
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Introduction<note>A 2019 University of Rochester Educational IT Innovation Grant
            supported the teaching described in and the writing of this article.</note></head>
        <p>It has long been a premise in the study of media that multiple senses are in play when we
          view movies, watch television, listen to live or recorded music, read or hear poems read
          aloud, and consume advertising, whether in print or on screens <ptr target="#benjamin1939"/>
          <ptr target="#mcluhan1964"/>
          <ptr target="#hansen2004"/>. Since the late twentieth century, the interplay of seeing and
          hearing has yielded richly variegated writing and thinking about, on the one hand, vision
          and visuality and, on the other, the acoustic, the audible, and the aural. In this essay,
          we pursue this interplay into the digital humanities. More specifically, we advance the
          concept of <emph>audiovisualities</emph> in order to describe that interplay in the
          context of digital annotation of time-based media. In these media, seeing and hearing are
          inseparable and our goal is to understand how processes of digital annotation can help
          scholars and students investigate this entanglement. To do this, we describe a platform we
          have named <emph>Mediate: An Annotation Tool for Audiovisual Media</emph>, which was
          developed with the Digital Scholarship Lab at the University of Rochester and has been
          used in undergraduate courses across the humanities and social sciences there. In these
          settings, <emph>Mediate</emph> has enabled our students and ourselves to see and hear the
          data of our eyes and ears in reflexively collective and recursively interdisciplinary
          ways. This collective process in a variety of classrooms is what has brought us — three
          faculty members (two tenure track, one instructional track), two students (an
          undergraduate and a graduate student), and two staff members from the library (the
          programmer and the Director of the Digital Scholarship Lab) — to the concept of
          audiovisualities we explore in this essay.</p>
        <p>That concept cannot be disaggregated from visual studies and sound studies, two fields
          that have developed alongside their more disciplinary counterparts in art history, film
          studies, musicology, and music theory. Broadly conceived, visual studies offers a means of
          understanding the expansive domain of the visual beyond what disciplines such as art
          history or film studies allow us to see. Wildly diverse in the directions it has taken
          since emerging in the late twentieth century, one of the central legacies of visual
          studies has been the concept of "visuality," or "sight as a social fact," which cannot be
          disaggregated from the act of "vision," or "sight as a physical operation" <ptr
            target="#foster1988"/>. Adapting W. J. T. Mitchell, we can think of visuality as a
          "dialectical concept" in which the study of "visual culture cannot rest content with a
          definition of its object as the social construction of the visual field, but must insist
          on exploring the chiastic reversal of this proposition, <emph>the visual construction of
            the social field</emph>. It is not just that we see the way we do because we are social
          animals, but also that our social arrangements take the forms they do because we are
          seeing animals" <ptr target="#mitchell2002"/>.</p>
        <p>As in visual studies, scholars working in sound studies, which took identifiable shape in
          the early twenty-first century, refuse to be content with a definition of its object as
          solely the social construction of the sonic field, but also account for the sonic
          construction of the social field <ptr target="#bull2013"/>
          <ptr target="#novak2015"/>
          <ptr target="#pinch2012"/>
          <ptr target="#sterne2012"/>. Pushing beyond logocentric and ocularcentric theoretical
          frameworks in various established disciplines, sound studies treats the audible and the
          aural, as Jonathan Sterne has put it, as "an artifact of the messy and political human
          sphere" <ptr target="#sterne2003"/>. Pondering that "artifact," three researchers
          exploring what they call "digital sound studies," including one of the authors of this
          article, have posed a question about the assumed modes in scholarship itself. "How," they
          ask, "can scholars write about sound <emph>in sound</emph>?" <ptr target="#lingold2018"
          />.</p>
        <p>A key effect that sound studies has had on visual studies has been to remind those
          working in the latter that the sights we see often go hand in hand with the sounds we
          hear. While Sterne's work in <emph>The Audible Past</emph> has systematized and
          historicized this sight-sound relation, film theorists such as Michel Chion <ptr
            target="#chion1994"/> and Kaja Silverman <ptr target="#silverman1988"/> and media
          archeologists such as Siegfried Zielinski <ptr target="#zielinski1999"/>
          <ptr target="#zielinski2006"/> and Bernard Stiegler <ptr target="#stiegler2014"/> have
          generatively tracked the dialectic of the visual and the audible in their work. We think
          of this dialectic as producing the audiovisualities — the physically and culturally
          interpenetrating modes of audiovisual experience and audiovisual inscription where hearing
          and seeing remediate one another for all of us as sensory and social subjects — that this
          essay aims to chart in relation to digital annotation in <emph>Mediate</emph>.</p>
        <p>At the University of Rochester, students have used <emph>Mediate</emph> to annotate
          cinematic, televisual, musical, literary, and commercial media in courses housed in the
          Film and Media Studies Program, the Musicology Department, and the Department of
          Linguistics. In these courses, the audiovisual specificities of a given medium become
          radically legible to students in the data they yield by annotating in
          <emph>Mediate</emph>. Further, as we will show in this article, in exploring the
          medium-specific qualities of film or music or advertising in their unique material forms,
          cultural contexts, and social functions, we have unexpectedly ended up in a broader
          concept of audiovisuality that cuts across disciplinary differences. To riff on Mitchell
          one last time, <emph>Mediate</emph> allows us to examine the audiovisual construction of
          the social field as much as the social construction of the audiovisual field. Through the
          annotation it supports, <emph>Mediate</emph> provides a platform in which that field is no
          longer immediately intuited through our senses, but turned into an object of analysis — an
          audible and visible "exteriority" <ptr target="#sterne2003"/> that allows us to grasp the
          interplay of seeing and hearing beyond the often self-contained ways in which we process
          sensory data internally and individually.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head><emph>Mediate</emph> and the Audiovisual State of Digital Annotation</head>
        <p><emph>Mediate</emph> arose out of Joel Burges's desire to have a digital tool that would
          enable the collection of large amounts of data about how time works on television.
          Originally working with Nora Dimmock, Jeff Suszczynski, and Joshua Romphf by experimenting
          with digital humanities projects in the classes "The Poetics of Television," "Film
          History, 1989-Present," and "Clocks and Computers: Visualizing Cultural Time" between 2012
          and 2016, this desire gave way to the still ongoing project of developing a digital
          annotation tool for audiovisual media that would be of more general use. As it did, we
          moved from combining software such as Jubler, DaVinci Resolve, and Adobe Encore to
          building our own platform, primarily through the labor of Romphf <ptr target="#burges2016"
          />. <emph>Mediate</emph> is a web-based platform that allows users to upload audiovisual
          media; produce real-time notes; generate automated and manual annotations (which we also
          call markers) on the basis of customized schema; preserve the annotations as data that can
          be queried; and export the data in CSV and JSON formats for further exploration,
          interpretation, and visualization. The platform is built in Python and JavaScript, and it
          makes use of several open source libraries, including Django, OpenCV, FFMPEG, and React.
          Through websockets tied together by a REST API, <emph>Mediate</emph> supports concurrent
          updates of annotations added by multiple users. <emph>Mediate</emph> provides a real-time
          system for annotating and analyzing myriad genres that yield audiovisualities in which
          sight and sound come into chiastic interplay in medium-specific ways.</p>
        <p>There are other tools like <emph>Mediate</emph>, including ELAN and NVivo, the subjects
          of a recent study of the audiovisual state of digital annotation <ptr target="#melgar2017"
          />. The build of ELAN and NVivo, however, make them technologically and methodologically
          distinct from <emph>Mediate</emph>. NVivo is not open source, while ELAN is — we hope
            <emph>Mediate</emph> will be open source and widely accessible in the future. Both ELAN
          and NVivo are desktop-based programs and have limited collaborative capabilities, whereas
          synchronous and asynchronous collaboration are foregrounded in <emph>Mediate</emph>. ELAN
          projects can only contain one media file whereas NVivo has a more multimodal approach and
          supports a variety of file formats, similar to <emph>Mediate</emph>. ELAN provides tiers
          (like the schema we use in <emph>Mediate</emph>, described below) with controlled
          vocabularies (akin to markers that make up schema in <emph>Mediate</emph>, again described
          below), whereas the categorization in NVivo is done after annotating through a code book
          approach common in the social sciences. Neither tool offers, as <emph>Mediate</emph> does,
          automated shot detection, and the ease of querying and exporting data across projects,
          media, and/or schema. Furthermore, they both feature high learning curves.
            <emph>Mediate</emph> adopts a more streamlined approach to consuming media in the design
          of its interface, which echoes familiar interfaces from our historical moment.</p>
        <p>When a user logs into the <emph>Mediate</emph> website (username: mediate_guest password:
          mediate2019!), they encounter the User Interface that displays their research groups. Each
          group includes the initials of the members along with the media assigned to the group. The
          media thumbnails include a count in the upper right-hand corner for annotations already
          generated.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure01">
          <head>User Interface as seen at login with the research group name, collaborators’
            initials, and available media.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>Selecting, for example, <emph>I Love Lucy</emph>, the user enters the Annotation
          Interface. Here they can watch the media in an interface akin to familiar streaming
          services, but with the addition of a vertical column of time coded annotations that scroll
          as the media plays.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure02">
          <head>Annotation Interface with a sample of markers generated for an episode of <emph>I
              Love Lucy</emph>.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>Clicking on the blue marker button in the upper left-hand corner reveals the Schema Pane.
          Here, users select markers and set short-cuts, which enables the marking process once the
          user returns to the Annotation Interface. This process can take weeks, especially if a
          group is marking across multiple objects. The repetitive work of collaborative marking not
          only helps students comprehend the forms they are analyzing, but also reveals the
          necessary judgments involved in deciding how and when to mark. As a result, it emerges
          that each marker and the concepts it represents become legible as a formal construct
          instead of a natural given.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure03">
          <head>Schema Pane displays available markers for that schema and allows the user to assign
            markers to specific short-cuts for ease of marking.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>At a high level of frequency across seven years and twelve classes, Armoskaite, Burges,
          and Mueller have observed that <emph>Mediate</emph> encourages a process of learning that
          slows down the rapid-fire consumption of everyday media, upending the seemingly intuitive
          and immediate dimensions of the audiovisual field.<note>Enrollments for courses at
            University of Rochester using <emph>Mediate</emph> are as follows: "Poetics of
            Television" (Joel Burges) 2012 (27 students), 2013 (28 students), 2016 (58 students);
            "Film History 1989-Present" (Joel Burges) 2014 (29 students); "Introduction to Media
            Studies" (Joel Burges) 2019 (67 students); "Clocks and Computers" (Joel Burges) 2013 (20
            students), 2015 (8 students); "Recording 20th Century Music" (Darren Mueller) 2018 (8
            students); "Experiments at the Edges of 20th Century Music" (Darren Mueller) 2019 (29
            students); "Language and Advertising" (Solveiga Armoskaite) 2018 (48 students), and 2019
            (35 students); "Signature Hitchcock/Hitchcock's Signature" (James Rosenow) 2020 (24
            students); "Tourist Japan" (Joanne Bernardi) 2020 (4 students); "Unwept: Women and
            Silent film" (Clara Auclair) 2020 (3 students); "Student Teaching Secondary School
            Science" (April Luehmann) 2020 (9 students).</note> Recursive and reflexive, digital
          annotation in <emph>Mediate</emph> has made our students tune into the audiovisualities
          that construct them as seeing and hearing subjects through a range of material forms that
          operate in different cultural contexts and with differing social functions. The digital
          annotation in <emph>Mediate</emph> align with what Liliana Melgar Estrada et al. <ptr
            target="#melgar2017"/> conclude is "the most significant methodological impact" of using
          ELAN and NVivo: "making the analytic procedures more explicit," can generate "more
          self-reflection about scholarly work." The authors suggest that digital annotation's
          greatest strength is its reflexive ability to draw users' attention to various units of
          analysis that they might not otherwise notice. Similarly, <emph>Mediate</emph> allows
          users to slowly comprehend what makes a film or poem or composition what it is as a
          mediated genre unto itself, but also to grasp how this medium-specificity turns on "units
          of analysis" <ptr target="#melgar2017"/> that are subjectively chosen in the first place.
          Just as all data are capta <ptr target="#drucker2011"/>, the unit of analysis by which a
          datum is captured when digitally annotating audiovisual media is itself invented. The
          invented dimension of these units are revealed whenever students discuss and debate marker
          definitions, as we have seen in all of our classes.</p>
        <p>The collaborative process of digital annotation enabled by <emph>Mediate</emph>, starts
          to address one of the concerns raised by Melgar et al. in their analysis of the current
          state of digital annotation: that more "collaborative" and "systematic" efforts might
          allow scholars to transcend "small scale" analyses easily replicated on paper <ptr
            target="#melgar2017"/>. In this, they acknowledge what has long been a both celebrated
          and critiqued feature of the digital humanities: its problematically neoliberal stress on
          teamwork that we hope might be rescued as a project of collective reading and
          collaborative curriculum <ptr target="#burges2016"/>
          <ptr target="#sebok2014"/>. Significant as the debate over the political economy and
          research efficacy of the digital humanities is <ptr target="#allington2016"/>
          <ptr target="#da2019a"/>
          <ptr target="#da2019b"/>, we nonetheless want to stress that in our courses we have found
          that scaling up — collectivizing and collaborating on digital annotation through groups of
          students producing and sharing data with one another about audiovisual media — has allowed
          those students to arrive at analytic findings that go beyond what they are able or willing
          to do otherwise.</p>
        <p>To arrive here, we must not assume that our students are "digital natives" who are
          naturally better at studying and thinking with computational devices than with pen and
          paper. None of us believes this lazy assumption; some of us actively work against it in
          our classes. As we will show, we have nonetheless seen outcomes that are educationally
          remarkable, especially due to the collaborative learning that <emph>Mediate</emph>
          enables, when it comes to how digital annotation in <emph>Mediate</emph> fuels our
          students' grasp of a range of audiovisual media in medium-specific ways. Often such
          medium-specificity is tethered to the discipline-specific approaches that we use in our
          courses, as we chart in the next section. But something interdisciplinary has arisen
          across our courses too: the cross-disciplinary concept of audiovisualities that this essay
          advances.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Three Disciplinary Case Studies in Digital Annotation</head>
        <p>In our courses, we position individual mediums as possessing unique material forms that
          exist in cultural contexts and have some social function, as is reflected in our schemas.
          These schemas emerge from discipline-specific frameworks, with some of us stressing
          material form, cultural context, or social function more when teaching with
            <emph>Mediate</emph>. In this section we provide three case studies. The first draws on
          a number of film and media studies classes where Burges wanted students to understand how
          a range of audiovisual media — television, poetry, and pop songs in the two cases
          discussed here — work formally such that they can be materially differentiated from
          another medium, even if they share certain properties. While Mueller and Armoskaite share
          this concern to varying degrees, their expertise has driven them to underscore questions
          of cultural context and social function more prominently in the study of audiovisual
          media. In his history class for music majors, Mueller asks students to interpret how a
          range of historical contingencies influences the creation and performance of specific
          musical sounds. Here, <emph>Mediate</emph> is a prompt to redirect assumptions about music
          that students already think they "know." Bringing together questions of material form and
          cultural context, Armoskaite uses <emph>Mediate</emph> to spark students to delve into how
          language in advertising itself is audiovisual — or more precisely, how language has a
          social function in commercial media that turns on how it activates the interplay of
          hearing and seeing vis-à-vis linguistic and discursive content meant to induce an action
          in someone.</p>
        <div>
          <head>Case Study 1: Material Form in Film and Media Studies (Burges)</head>
          <p>Questions of material form are central in the film and media studies classes I teach
            for the College of Arts, Sciences, and Engineering at the University of Rochester,
            including the two I discuss here: "The Poetics of Television" and "Introduction to Media
            Studies". In "The Poetics of Television", for example, we spend significant time
            studying the different ways in which the episode is a form of inscription that organizes
            the audiovisual experience of television in narratively open and closed ways. In
            "Introduction to Media Studies," we discuss television not only from this narrative
            perspective, but also from the perspective of television as a historically variable
            technology for transmitting sounds and images onto a screen that was, for many decades,
            primarily part of the TV set. These are both material to the form of television, with
            the latter especially providing the specific audiovisual means by which television
            mediates and materializes narrative, information, and advertising for its viewers. In my
            classes, the question of material form — of how a medium is a matter of form — is not
            reducible to solely inquiring into these means in order to secure that which is, to
            recall Clement Greenberg <ptr target="#greenberg1960"/>, irreducibly exclusive to it. It
            instead involves pursuing lines of inquiry with students in which we explore the
            specificity of a range of media — from television and film to poetry and song — through
            the shifting constellations of qualities constrained and enabled by diverse audiovisual
            means in the first place <ptr target="#doane2007"/>.</p>
          <p>Digital annotation in <emph>Mediate</emph> indelibly contributes to this pursuit,
            especially through the schemas that provide the basis of the highly collaborative — as
            we will show — marking that students do over the course of a semester in classes such as
            "The Poetics of Television" and "Introduction to Media Studies." The schemas we have
            designed so far try to capture the constellations of qualities that make up any medium
            one might annotate in <emph>Mediate</emph>. In "The Poetics of Television," the schemas
            were designed around aural, visual, and narrative qualities in order to show how sound,
            image, and story are respectively constructed on TV.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure04">
            <head>Visual Schema.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
          </figure>
          <figure xml:id="figure05">
            <head>A sample of markers generated using the Visual Schema on a scene from Buffy the
              Vampire Slayer, Season Four.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
          </figure>
          <figure xml:id="figure06">
            <head>Narrative Schema.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
          </figure>
          <figure xml:id="figure07">
            <head>A sample of markers generated using the Narrative Schema on a scene from Game of
              Thrones, Season Three.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
          </figure>
          <p>The schemas for "Introduction to Media Studies," were designed with comparison in mind,
            so one focused on a set of markers for annotating poems read aloud by their authors, the
            other on a set of markers for annotating pop songs by individual singers and bands.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure08">
            <head>Poetry Schema.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
          </figure>
          <figure xml:id="figure09">
            <head> A sample of markers and observations generated using the Poetry Schema on a video
              of Tracy K. Smith reading <title rend="quotes">Wade in the Water.</title></head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
          </figure>
          <figure xml:id="figure10">
            <head>Narrative Schema.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
          </figure>
          <figure xml:id="figure11">
            <head>A sample of markers and observations generated using the Narrative Schema on
              Beyoncé's <title rend="quotes">Partition.</title></head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure11.png"/>
          </figure>
          <p>Over the course of a semester, students in these two classes worked collaboratively in
            groups of four to six people to annotate on the basis of the schema or schemas that
            group was assigned, building toward long papers in which they explored a wide range of
            topics through distant and close readings performed in writing and through
            visualizations. Regardless of the topic, these papers almost universally exhibited a
            deep knowledge of the material form of the audiovisual medium under study; the specific
            interplay of sight and sound embodied by TV, for instance, became "second nature" to one
            student, "so much so that when I watch TV now I automatically mark the episode in the
            back of my mind" <ptr target="#crumrine2016"/>. This is the result of what the students
            characterize as the "immersive" dimension of <emph>Mediate</emph> in which time spent
            marking, however "irritating" and "monotonous" and "tedious" in its slowness over the
            semester, generates a profound concept of the qualities that give material form to their
            audiovisual experience <ptr target="#allen2016"/>. This is most palpable when one looks
            more closely at final projects students completed, in which their collaborative efforts
            yielded a remarkable level of quantitative data and qualitative observation worth
            understanding in greater nuance.<note>We believe it is important not only to include
              these specifics, but also to attribute the papers to the students themselves.
              Moreover, as needed, we obtained permission from various students in the groups cited
              from "The Poetics of Television" and "Introduction to Media Studies" to share their
              work; in the latter, we conducted focus groups where students also signed off on us
              sharing their feedback and ideas. The comments from students in "Experiments at the
              Edges of 20th Century Music" and "Linguistics and Advertising," however, have remained
              anonymous since we had less of this infrastructure in place.</note></p>
          <p>In an essay for "The Poetics of Television" entitled "The Formal Nucleus of Television,
            and Its Subservience to Narrative" <ptr target="#allen2016"/>, the students argued that
            dialogue is a key element of the "formal nucleus" of TV by exploring the nexus of sound
            and story in four historically and generically variable series defined by open narration
              (<emph>Game of Thrones</emph>, <emph>Dark Shadows</emph>, <emph>Guiding Light</emph>,
            and <emph>Robotech</emph>). On the basis of hundreds of markers the students in this
            group annotated, they argue that dialogue is an elementally generative feature of the
            "aural design" of television that "advance[s] the narrative progression of an episode."
            This is due to dialogue allowing "all details pertinent to the comprehension of the
            narrative, in terms of both plot and character, to be enumerated in explicit,
            unequivocal, and economical terms." This group further contends that the television
            camera often obeys the human voice, suggesting that visual design flows from aural
            design, for instance, on the basis of the 54 on-offscreen and off-onscreen shifts of
            sound vis-à-vis the image and diegesis that the group marked in the infamous Red Wedding
            scene of <emph>Game of Thrones</emph> while annotating in the Aural Schema. While both
            the visible and the audible are subservient to narrative in the argument this group's
            paper makes, it nonetheless richly charts the interplay of sight and sound within
            storytelling on TV, revealing how that mediated interplay — that audiovisuality — lets
            narrative take material form on screen.</p>
          <p>"Introduction to Media Studies" similarly attuned students to material form. But rather
            than focusing on one audiovisual medium to achieve this end, as in "The Poetics of
            Television," I used a comparative approach in which I asked students to work in groups
            to annotate poetry and pop songs to which they listened closely and repeatedly in
              <emph>Mediate</emph>. Students were not allowed to pull print versions of the poems
            they were annotating on the basis of oral renditions by their authors, forcing them to
            use their ears to grasp the differences between poems and songs marked using schemas
            developed for each of these genres. What one group observed about those differences will
            sound obvious: while rhythmically structured and lineated language is the medium of
            poetry, pop songs are much more musical in their means, depending on instrumentation,
            chord progression, beat groupings and so on <ptr target="#colberg2019"/>.</p>
          <p>But what is less obvious is how the students in this group came to experience this
            difference because <emph>Mediate</emph> introduced annotation into audition. In
            annotating, they <emph>heard</emph> what was material to the form of poetry and pop
            songs as a fixed and motivated structure of aural notation. The songs went from being an
            internal experience of sound and music to appearing as an externalized — because now
            annotated — form of audiovisual inscription. Thus the long paper this group produced
            focused less on material form in favor of trying to pinpoint what constellation of
            audible qualities inscribe what they call "intensity." For this group, intensity refers
            to how "affective response" and "aesthetic emotion" in a mediated genre of sound turns
            upon medium-specific features, as in their LP record player-inspired visualizations of
            two songs, Troye Sivan's "Wild" and Taylor Swift's "This Love." Audiovisualities in
            their own right, these experimental data visualizations show how distinct kinds of vocal
            stress, chord changes, back-up singing, and instrumentation not only mark the form of
            these songs, but also form the possibility of having a musically "intense" reaction to
            them as well.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure12">
            <head>Experimental Visualization of Formal and Intensity Markings for Troye Sivan’s
              "Wild."</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure12.png"/>
          </figure>
          <figure xml:id="figure13">
            <head>Experimental Visualization of Formal and Intensity Markings for Taylor Swift’s
              "This Love."</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure13.png"/>
          </figure>
          <p>In classes such as "The Poetics of Television" and "Introduction to Media Studies,"
            digital annotation in <emph>Mediate</emph> enables students to work together to see and
            hear the material form of a range of audiovisual media. It is important that they are
            working together, collaborating to annotate such that both within and across their
            groups they are able to explore audiovisuality in a collective way that has both
            quantitative and qualitative effects. On the one hand, the quantitative dimension of
            their collaborative efforts is visible in the plenitude of markers that each group
            generates as a working collective, and in how they draw on the audiovisual data produced
            by other groups marking in the same class to understand the annotation that has occurred
            in a given group. On the other hand, the repeated marking required to yield thousands of
            data points they can share with one another engenders a quality of description and
            interpretation that shows how close they understand the material forms of film,
            television, poetry, and pop songs from multiple audiovisual angles of seeing and
            hearing. As we have more fully argued elsewhere <ptr target="#burges2016"/>, however,
            that "truth" depends upon the discussions that often emerge over how to collectively
            define and collaboratively mark a unit of analysis within and across groups as they
            annotate features of material form; these discussions over how to see and hear, though,
            only further shore up both that no medium is a natural given, and that every audiovisual
            experience is mediated.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Case Study 2: The Cultural Contexts of Music History (Mueller)</head>
          <p>Although connected institutionally, Eastman School of Music (ESM) is quite different
            from the rest of the university in terms of its student population, educational goals,
            and curriculum. All of ESM's approximately 500 undergraduate students are music majors,
            with a primary focus on Western classical music.<note>At the undergraduate level, ESM
              also offers robust degree programs in jazz performance and jazz composition. Graduate
              degree tracks include music leadership, conducting, early music, film composition,
              opera, music theory, ethnomusicology, and musicology.</note> Our students are some of
            the best young musicians in the world, meaning that most view their classroom activities
            through the lens of their future careers in performance, composition, and pedagogy. To
            even gain admittance, they need to have remarkable expertise and years of specialized
            training in a tradition built around individual composers and master performers. So,
            while these students bring a strong passion for music into the classroom, doing academic
            work often forces them to confront viewpoints and approaches that are frequently taken
            as natural rather than culturally constructed.</p>
          <p>Most of the traditions represented at ESM are heavily reliant on musical notation, a
            highly advanced system of written symbols that has, over many centuries, enabled the
            development and circulation of music that originated in Western Europe. In many
            respects, the very presence of notation constitutes the tradition <ptr
              target="#taruskin2005"/>. Musical notation can also be understood as a form of
            audiovisual inscription that communicates specific information about both how to perform
            music and also how an individual piece functions melodically, harmonically,
            rhythmically, and formally <ptr target="#moseley2015"/>
            <ptr target="#rehding2017"/>
            <ptr target="#kittler1999"/>. Reading music, as we would say, is a presumed skill that
            students rely upon as they move through the robust series of classes in music theory and
            history, both of which differently emphasize score-based analysis of internal (within a
            piece) and external (within a tradition) musical features. As a result, students are
            very comfortable working with written music, as well as the specialized language used to
            describe it. Still, the culture surrounding classical music has calcified certain
            perspectives, especially on what it means to do analysis. For many students, music
            analysis is too often conceived of as an action solely in visual terms, rather than an
            act that takes place in a far more expanded audiovisual realm.</p>
          <p>In Fall 2019, I introduced <emph>Mediate</emph> into my "Experiments at the Edges of
            20th Century Music," a required course within the undergraduate music history core. My
            goal was to foreground listening, rather than reading, as the primary means of analysis.
            As exceptional performers already, my students listen with an expertly attuned
            understanding of musical performance. But while they continually analyze music while
            listening, they do not always listen historically — that is, attend to how specific
            musical moments express historically contingent beliefs about culture, society, or the
            many processes of music making. There is no inherent problem with their modality of
            listening. However, it is not always congruous with my major pedagogical goal: to
            examine and interpret how music and its written tradition are both heavily mediated
            creations, dependent on historically situated actors with different investments and
            values. By asking students to pay attention differently, <emph>Mediate</emph> not only
            foregrounds listening but also asks students to translate that listening into specific
            observations represented visually. In effect, this reverses the standard audiovisual
            direction of music making. Rather than move from visual inscription (notation) to aural
            expression (performance), <emph>Mediate</emph> renders what is heard into specific
            visual markings of that performance. Unsettling the assumed relationships between the
            visual and the aural — by putting listening first — encourages alternative viewpoints to
            come into the forefront of the analytical process.</p>
          <p>Inspired by previous uses of <emph>Mediate</emph> in the classroom, I had students
            complete a semester-long collective analysis project. Our work began before I introduced
            the <emph>Mediate</emph> platform by continually asking students during class
            discussions and daily responses to listen through a series of five interrelated
            questions oriented towards cultural contexts:</p>
          <list type="ordered">
            <item><p>Who or what shaped this particular music or performance?</p></item>
            <item><p>What would it be like to perform this music?</p></item>
            <item><p>What are the musical materials used in the creation of this piece?</p></item>
            <item><p>How does this musical material transform?</p></item>
            <item><p>What do you think the creators were trying to say or accomplish with this
                  music?<note>I adapted these questions from composer David Kirkland Garner
                  (University of South Carolina).</note>
              </p></item>
          </list>
          <p>For their <emph>Mediate</emph> project, students organized into groups of two to four.
            Each student within those groups picked one or more of these questions and marked up
            their audio in <emph>Mediate</emph> from those perspectives. I developed specific
            markers for each question to aid in this process, but also encouraged students to
            develop others to meet their specific needs.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure14">
            <head>Categories of Analysis Schema.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure14.png"/>
          </figure>
          <p>As they listened, students would mark everything from the seemingly obvious — what they
            might otherwise notice without thinking — to those details obscured by the rapid
            unfolding of any time-based art. After creating several hundred markers, each group
            began to decipher their efforts and develop a thesis for their written analysis with the
            same five questions again providing a road map. The class went through this process in
            two different iterations. First, all groups analyzed the first movement of William Grant
            Still's Symphony No. 1. Then, each group picked a piece of music or specific performance
            from a given list of artists and composers.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure15">
            <head>A sample of markers and observations generated using the Categories of Analysis
              Schema on Ida Handel performing Part One of the Carmen Fantasy.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure15.png"/>
          </figure>
          <p>Two general observations emerged out of the individual reflections written at the end
            of the semester. First, the slow, sometimes-tedious markup process requires active
            listening. Many students discussed how they came to notice subtle details and
            complexities precisely because the marking up process made "passive" or "casual"
            listening impossible. The intensity involved with repeated listening did not always
            change their initial opinions, but rather increased the precision and specificity of
            their observations. One student remarked with surprise about "how much could happen
            within one tiny second." Second, the processes of collective listening encouraged
            individuals to consider multiple vantage points. Collaboration through group work is not
            always smooth or easy, and it is sometimes unpopular. But by learning from or being
            challenged by their colleagues — perhaps even by becoming a "cultural context" in
            miniature — many students reported that the dialogic experience enabled them to make
            connections that were perhaps not obvious to them before.</p>
          <p>The written work of each group also proved how valuable doing analysis away from the
            score could be. Many groups wrote about meaningful moments that would have otherwise
            remained hidden by only looking at the written notation — the particular use of vibrato,
            the background noise in a recording, a reoccurring timbre, or the use of space or a
            particular texture in the orchestration. Through the analysis of seemingly discrete
            details in relation to the background of the composer or other cultural influences,
            students then found ways to relate what happens musically to what that performance might
            mean more broadly, which is to say historically. As one student commented, the analysis
            provided a way to understand how music functioned as an interconnected web of historical
            events, musical influences, and experiences of "real life people." In comparison with
            previous semesters, the written work of the students in this class was at once more
            precise and bolder in their conclusions.</p>
          <p>The slow and collective process of listening through <emph>Mediate</emph> allows
            students to re-situate their otherwise expert ears towards music as a form of
            audiovisual inscription. Music is a time-based art that exists in performance, yet it
            nevertheless remains heavily dependent on the visual realm. The specialized language
            used in traditional forms of analysis — a Neapolitan sixth chord, for one example —
            describes both what music sounds and looks like. As a digital platform that creates a
            method for analysis, <emph>Mediate</emph> makes the audiovisualities of music clear.
            Musical culture is and has always been an audiovisual culture as well, and new
            possibilities surface for students about this fact when they experience music through
              <emph>Mediate</emph>.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Case Study 3: Social Function in Linguistics (Armoskaite)</head>
          <p>The Department of Linguistics in the College of Arts, Sciences, and Engineering at the
            University of Rochester, while a part of the social sciences, is a hub of
            interdisciplinary research with ties to other departments, including Music (with a focus
            on perception and production of sounds), Brain and Cognitive Science (with a focus on
            meaning and language processing), Anthropology (with focus on culture and language
            intersections), and Psychology (with a focus of child language acquisition). As a field,
            linguistics covers a vast number of topics and methodologies, hence it is impossible to
            provide a general description that would fit the range. For the purposes of this case
            study, it will suffice to state (i) that linguistics focuses on of the makeup of
            grammar, which is a set of sub-systems of sound, form and meaning; (ii) and that these
            subsystems are used for communication, a function that interacts with social conventions
            and societal values, a.o. <ptr target="#fasold2014"/>.</p>
          <p>My course "Language and Advertising," requires students to consider language use in the
            context of audiovisual marketing against the backdrop of current social trends. While
            Linguistics does not have a Business or Marketing track, the course routinely is taken
            by business majors and consistently is a popular elective among other non-Linguistics
            majors. I face a diverse group of students with different backgrounds, skills, and
            assumptions, though united by the three common denominators. First, the ubiquity of
            advertising in their lives gives them a false sense of familiarity and assumed knowledge
            of the medium; second, they want to learn the nuts and bolts of the advertising machine;
            and third, they possess limited knowledge of linguistics. Over the course of the
            semester, they learn that the social function of language in advertising is to
            manipulate, with commercial media, working to apply psychological pressure through a
            mode of audiovisuality that depends on influencing our emotions and circumventing our
            rational mind, a.o. <ptr target="#sedivy2011"/>
            <ptr target="#lewis2013"/>
            <ptr target="#poels2006"/>.</p>
          <p>Situating a familiar medium — advertising — within a likely unfamiliar field —
            linguistics — necessarily slows down the students. They learn to analyze the linguistic
            components that, to call back to the film and media studies case above, "make" the
            medium. The material form that interests a linguist, however, includes not only sounds
            and images of the kind that interest Burges and Mueller in their courses, but also the
            very structure of language as humans speak, read, and hear it. For example, each of the
            following posters can be deciphered in the linguistic terms of sound, form, and meaning,
            which shows that even print advertising functions as an audiovisual medium.</p>
          <p><ref
              target="https://www.redcrossblood.org/content/dam/redcrossblood/campaigns/missing-types/Missing%20Types%20Campaign%20Partner%20Style%20Guide.pdf"
              >The American Red Cross "Missing Types" campaign (2018)</ref> presents a sound-based
            puzzle for the viewer to acoustically fill in, whether in silence or out loud: all the
            missing elements are vowels. The viewer goes in search of those vowels, enjoying a
            language game that depends on visual absence engendering audio presence. And because the
            vowels are associated with types of blood, this audiovisual play becomes a linguistic
            mechanism for soliciting blood donations.</p>
          <p><ref target="https://www.adsoftheworld.com/media/print/snickers_satisfectellent">The
              Snickers "Satisfectellent" (TBWA 2007)</ref> advertisement plays upon another element
            of grammar, namely, derivation of words. In this case, a word that is possible, but does
            not exist, is created. The novelty of the coined word is the striking — and strikingly
            audiovisual — feature of the advertisement: the joy of recognition of the brand of the
            snack is fused with the unexpectedness of the word.</p>
          <p>Finally, the <ref
              target="https://www.adsoftheworld.com/media/print/greenpeace_straws_suck_gull"
              >Greenpeace "Straws Suck: Gull" (Rethink 2018)</ref> advertisement exploits the shades
            of meaning of the verb "to suck." The painful visual is certainly not the first
            association we have about sucking through straws, which we may think about in sonic
            and/or tactile terms primarily. But the unexpected visual connotation is meant to shock
            us into changing our habits of consumption.</p>
          <p>However, language in print advertising engenders audiovisual experience in a far more
            static way than the advertising that flows across our many screens as moving images and
            dynamic sounds. The latter contains hundreds of speech patterns in addition to
            innumerable cues for our ears and eyes. Superimposed on moving images, these patterns
            and cues come at a viewer at a speed that barely allows them to register the component
            parts, let alone perform a thorough analysis. <emph>Mediate</emph> creates a space for
            such analysis external to the ephemerally immediate modes in which we normally consume
            commercial media. In so doing, it makes legible that language plays a constitutive part
            in the interplay of sight and hearing — that all three of these human abilities
            contribute to the social function of manipulation that is the raison d'etre of often
            brilliant acts of commodified audiovisuality that want us to buy or buy into something.
              <emph>Mediate</emph> gets students to treat the audiovisuality of advertising as a
            constellation of elements variously linguistic, optical, and aural — as an object of
            analysis.</p>
          <p>This takes time over the course of the semester. In "Language and Advertising" (Fall
            2018 and Fall 2019), I spent three weeks teaching students the fundamentals of
            linguistics using similar examples to the print advertisements discussed above. Building
            on this print unit, we then turned to the challenge of analyzing commercials using
              <emph>Mediate</emph>. The students began by analyzing an ad without the use of
              <emph>Mediate</emph>. Then I modeled the slow and detailed analysis conducted through
              <emph>Mediate</emph> by providing them with samples of my own marked-up commercial. We
            discussed their observations, along with my own, which gently lets them understand how
            many details they've missed in their own observations. The students were then trained on
            the platform and introduced to the schema over two class sessions. After that initial
            introduction, the students took charge of their own learning with only a light editorial
            supervision.</p>
          <p>Circumventing the top-down didacticism of the traditional lecture, <emph>Mediate</emph>
            allowed the students to immerse themselves into the material on their own. Working in
            groups, they were tasked with selecting and analyzing at least two video ads, splitting
            up the work of marking (what we call "coding" in the field of linguistics) amongst
            themselves. Rather than a traditional linguistic analysis of a video ad that might
            include a transcription of the text divorced from the audio and visual cues,
              <emph>Mediate</emph> facilitated a holistic approach to the interplay and
            interdependencies of the audiovisualities commercial media employ.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure16">
            <head>A sample of markers and observations generated using the Linguistics Schema on
              Cadillac's "The Future is Here" 60 second spot.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/figure16.png"/>
          </figure>
          <p>In slowing down their observations, they are forced to think about each element in the
            totality of the advertisement such that it emerges as a linguistic object of audiovisual
            analysis, with the manipulative properties of this object becoming ever clearer as its
            social function over the time they spend in <emph>Mediate</emph>. As one student noted,
            "there is no escape but to analyze." At the end of the semester, the groups presented
            their analyses of commercial media, with the entire class responding. This collective
            response included debates over how each group defined certain linguistic, audio, and
            visual units of analysis, and about the conclusions about manipulation in commercial
            media that each group reached. These discussions — aided by the carefully coded examples
            in <emph>Mediate</emph> — were paramount in helping students build an applied
            understanding of the social function of advertising from an audiovisual angle grounded
            in linguistics as an interdisciplinary field.</p>
          <p>Despite their engagement and increased capacity with audiovisual analysis through
              <emph>Mediate</emph>, there still is room for greater interdisciplinary collaboration
            in "Language and Advertising", especially in light of the cross-disciplinary sense of
            audiovisuality we are advancing in this article. In my course, I welcome film experts as
            occasional invited speakers. But through my discussions with Burges and Mueller, I have
            realized that more sophisticated ways of tuning into the linguistic, visual, and sonic
            patterns would offer further opportunities to explore the range and means of consumer
            manipulation. For example, thus far, I have left out musical aspects completely as I
            lack relevant training. In the future iterations of this course, I think about the
            potential for more nuanced analysis if I could harness Mueller's expertise in helping
            students define the auditory components, if Burges could work with students to delve
            further into the visual form — that is, if students benefitted not only from their
            collective defining through marking, but also the collective expertise of a more
            intentionally cross-disciplinary approach to teaching and research.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Audiovisualities out of Annotation</head>
        <p>Across our individual classes, we have seen our students more fully enter the study of
          audiovisual media as they are defined by material form, cultural context, and social
          function within our respective disciplinary frameworks. In sharing these experiences with
          one another across our disciplines, we have been reminded that, when it comes to the
          audiovisual field, a film and media studies scholar should sometimes see and hear that
          field <emph>like</emph> a music historian who should sometimes see and hear it
            <emph>like</emph> a linguist. In noticing that we should see and hear like each other
          more, even as we explored medium-specific matters with our students, we have arrived at
          the cross-disciplinary concept of audiovisualities. Pedagogically and intellectually
          segregated from another due to the division of labor that organizes the modern research
          university, this concept allows us to think about the interplay of sight and sound more
          promiscuously and productively, overcoming the binaries that too often divide the audible
          and the visual and the divides that splinter disciplines from one another institutionally.
          In working together the last few years on digital annotation, we have learned to think
          more comprehensively across our respective fields about the (re)mediated sites where the
          physical and cultural operations of audiovisual experience converge. It is these locations
          of convergence that construct not only sensory and social subjectivities grounded in
          seeing and hearing, but also material forms and collective technics that set the
          conditions of possibility to see and hear to begin with — in short, that construct a
          manifold of audiovisualities. Our work on <emph>Mediate</emph> has helped us to estrange,
          even to alienate, the "natural order" that has been imposed on our experience of that
          manifold, or what Michel Chion describes as the "audiovisual contract" <ptr
            target="#chion1994" loc="9"/>.</p>
        <p>As this gesture to Chion telegraphs, we are not the first group of scholars to explore
          such conditions. The cross-disciplinary concept of audiovisualities on which we have
          landed already has a genealogy of thinkers — many of them cited at the outset of this
          essay — associated with visual studies and sound studies, not to mention film and media
          studies, behind it. Indebted to them, we nonetheless think the practice of digital
          annotation that <emph>Mediate</emph> provides contributes a collaborative model of
          learning through collective reading that allows our students to conceptualize
          audiovisualities beyond their individual selves (and our individual disciplines). It may
          do this, as well, for any scholars that take it up, especially, if not only in a
          collective and collaborative form. The collectivity of digital annotation can take that
          which feels intuitive and internal and remake it as unfamiliar and external; the
          collective act of exteriorizing that occurs in <emph>Mediate</emph> brings a new awareness
          to the qualities and characteristics of a given audiovisual medium.</p>
        <p>"History is nothing but exteriorities," writes Jonathan Sterne in <emph>The Audible
            Past,</emph> by which he means that we can only know the "sonic world" of the past
          through its "efforts, expressions, and reactions" <ptr target="#sterne2003"/>.
            <emph>Mediate</emph> embraces this point of view. Digital annotation in
            <emph>Mediate</emph> asks students to exteriorize their reactions to audiovisual media
          not only by slowing down their consumption of them, but also by turning what feels
          subjectively intuitive, immediate, and internal (listening to and even playing music,
          taking in a poem, consuming an advertisement, watching a TV show) into a mediated object
          to be analyzed collaboratively and collectively beyond oneself. Vivid examples of this
          process of exteriorizing abound in our case studies. In "Experiments at the Edges of 20th
          Century Music," students produce digital "notations," so to speak, through their use of
            <emph>Mediate</emph>, thus resituating the ocularcentric primacy of musical notation
          through careful listening and historicizing. Similarly, in "Language and Advertising," the
          interface renders commercials a constellation of elements that act on us linguistically,
          visually, and musically in ways students can tangibly analyze. And the experimental
          visualizations of two pop songs for "Introduction to Media Studies" draw on data produced
          collectively through digital annotation about the aural experience of intensity to
          visually represent the material form of that intensity.</p>
        <p><emph>Mediate</emph> therefore enables a defamiliarized perception of audiovisialities,
          first and foremost, by challenging the consumption of media as an individual and discrete
          act atomized from others. The work of collaborative annotation, which sets
            <emph>Mediate</emph> apart from platforms such as ELAN and NVivo, reveals not only the
          potential for different experiences of the same mediums, but that the criteria through
          which we name and identify media — and indeed, our respective disciplines — can, and
          perhaps should, be subject to the scrutiny made possible by collective re-examination. Our
          respective fields are built upon often now unspoken agreements about what constitutes film
          or poetry or music or television or advertising or language. <emph>Mediate</emph> shows
          how "agreeing to disagree" on a given medium's properties remains a necessary move within
          and across disciplines, especially if we are to take into account critiques of both
          collaboration and computation leveled at the digital humanities. The reverse of the
          earlier claim, in other words, is also true. Our students often debate what a unit
          analysis means when marking, mobilizing the differences amongst themselves in
          collaborating on digital annotation. Similarly, when it comes to the cross-disciplinary
          concept of audiovisualities, a film and media studies scholar should see and hear the
          interplay of sight <emph>unlike</emph> a music historian who should sometimes see and hear
          it <emph>unlike</emph> a linguist as much as we should see and hear it <emph>like</emph>
          each other.</p>
        <p>The case studies recounted in this article reflect this collaborative process of
          disagreement — the self-aware reflection upon "units of analysis" — as a pedagogically
          necessary exercise in understanding the audiovisual world we inhabit in the present.
          However, such a practice is not limited to the undergraduate classroom alone. The
          collaborative nature of digital annotation breaks down a process that scholars, at all
          levels, often take for granted: the terms and tools through which we analyze media,
          especially within our respective fields. By making us be both like and unlike each other,
            <emph>Mediate</emph> has allowed us to take hold of those terms and tools anew,
          discovering audiovisualities out of annotation as a concept that unsettles what we do with
          the interplay of sight and sound inscribed everywhere into experience at present.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <!-- BACK TEXT -->
    <back>
      <listBibl>
        <bibl xml:id="allen2016" label="Allen et al. 2016">Allen, Joseph, Josh Barnes, Arielle Lin,
          Mark Perilli, and Dean Smiros. <title rend="quotes">The Formal Nucleus of Television, and
            Its Subservience to Narrative.</title>Unpublished essay, <title rend="quotes">The
            Poetics of Television,</title>University of Rochester, Fall 2016.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="allington2016" label="Allington et al. 2016">Allington, Daniel, Sarah
          Brouillette, and David Golumbia. <title rend="quotes">Neoliberal Tools (and Archives): A
            Political History of Digital Humanities.</title><title rend="italic">Los Angeles Review
            of Books</title>, May 1, 2016. <ref
            target="https://lareviewofbooks.org/article/neoliberal-tools-archives-political-history-digital-humanities/"
            >https://lareviewofbooks.org/article/neoliberal-tools-archives-political-history-digital-humanities/</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="benjamin1939" label="Benjamin 1939">Benjamin, Walter. <title rend="quotes">The
            Work of Art in the Age of Its Technological Reproducibility.</title>In Benjamin, Walter.
            <title rend="italic">Walter Benjamin: Selected Writings, 4: 1938–1940.</title> Edited by
          Howard Eiland and Michael W. Jennings. Vol. 4. 4 vols. Selected Writings. Cambridge, MA:
          The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 2006.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="bull2013" label="Bull 2013">Bull, Michael, ed. <title rend="italic">Sound
            Studies: Critical Concepts in Media and Cultural Studies</title>. New York: Routledge,
          2013.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="burges2016" label="Burges et al. 2016">Burges, Joel, Nora Dimmock, and Joshua
          Romphf. <title rend="quotes">Collective Reading: Shot Analysis and Data Visualization in
            the Digital Humanities.</title><title rend="italic">DH and Media Studies
            Crossovers</title> 3, no. 3 (2016). <ref
            target="http://www.teachingmedia.org/collective-reading-shot-analysis-and-data-visualization-in-the-digital-humanities/"
            >http://www.teachingmedia.org/collective-reading-shot-analysis-and-data-visualization-in-the-digital-humanities/</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="chion1994" label="Chion 1994">Chion, Michel. <title rend="italic"
            >Audio-Vision: Sound On Screen</title>. Translated by Claudia Gorbman. New York:
          Columbia University Press, 1994.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="colberg2019" label="Colberg et al. 2019">Colberg, Steven, Kayoung Kim, Hannah
          O'Connor, and Rachel Yang. <title rend="quotes">Intensity in Songs: More than a
            Feeling.</title>Unpublished essay, <title rend="quotes">Introduction to Media
            Studies,</title>University of Rochester, Spring 2019.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="crumrine2016" label="Crumrine et al. 2016">Crumrine, Seth, Amber Hudson,
          Simone Johnson, Sarah Kerecman, Anna Llewellyn, and Kyle Smith. <title rend="quotes">'That
            sounds so melodramatic': Theatricality and Realism in the Soap Opera and <title
              rend="italic">Game of Thrones</title>.</title>Unpublished essay, <title rend="quotes"
            >The Poetics of Television,</title>University of Rochester, Fall 2016.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="da2019a" label="Da 2019a">Da, Nan Z. <title rend="quotes">The Digital
            Humanities Debacle.</title>The Chronicle of Higher Education, March 27, 2019. <ref
            target="https://www.chronicle.com/article/The-Digital-Humanities-Debacle/245986"
            >https://www.chronicle.com/article/The-Digital-Humanities-Debacle/245986</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="da2019b" label="Da 2019b">Da, Nan Z. <title rend="quotes">The Computational
            Case against Computational Literary Studies.</title><title rend="italic">Critical
            Inquiry</title> 45, no. 3 (March 2019): 601–39. <ref
            target="https://doi.org/10.1086/702594">https://doi.org/10.1086/702594</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="doane2007" label="Doane 2007">Doane, Mary Ann. <title rend="quotes">The
            Indexical and the Concept of Medium Specificity.</title><title rend="italic"
            >Differences</title> 18, no. 1 (January 1, 2007): 128–52. <ref
            target="https://doi.org/10.1215/10407391-2006-025"
            >https://doi.org/10.1215/10407391-2006-025</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="drucker2011" label="Drucker 2011">Drucker, Johanna. <title rend="quotes"
            >Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display.</title><title rend="italic">Digital
            Humanities Quarterly</title> 5, no. 1 (2011): 1–21.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="melgar2017" label="Melgar et al. 2017">Melgar Estrada, Liliana, Eva Hielscher,
          Marijn Koolen, Christian Gosvig Olesen, Julia Noordegraaf, and Jaap Blom. <title
            rend="quotes">Film Analysis as Annotation: Exploring Current Tools.</title><title
            rend="italic">Moving Image: The Journal of the Association of Moving Image
            Archivists</title> 17, no. 2 (2017): 40–70.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="fasold2014" label="Fasold and Connor-Linton 2014">Fasold, Ralph W., and Jeff
          Connor-Linton, eds. <title rend="italic">An Introduction to Language and
            Linguistics</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2014.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="foster1988" label="Foster 1988">Foster, Hal, ed. <title rend="italic">Vision
            and Visuality</title>. Seattle: Bay Press, 1988.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="greenberg1960" label="Greenberg 1960">Greenberg, Clement. <title rend="quotes"
            >Modernist Painting.</title>In <title rend="italic">The Collected Essays and Criticism,
            Volume 4: Modernism with a Vengeance, 1957-1969</title>, edited by John O'Brian.
          Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1995.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="hansen1992" label="Hansen 1992">Hansen, Miriam. <title rend="quotes">Mass
            Culture as Hieroglyphic Writing: Adorno, Derrida, Kracauer.</title><title rend="italic"
            >New German Critique</title>, no. 56 (1992): 43–73. <ref
            target="https://doi.org/10.2307/488328">https://doi.org/10.2307/488328</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="hansen2004" label="Hansen 2004">Hansen, Miriam Bratu. <title rend="quotes"
            >Room-for-Play: Benjamin's Gamble with Cinema.</title><title rend="italic"
            >October</title> 109 (2004): 3–45.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="kittler1999" label="Kittler 1999">Kittler, Friedrich A. <title rend="italic"
            >Gramophone, Film, Typewriter</title>. Translated and with an introduction by Geoffrey
          Winthrop-Young and Michael Wutz. Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press, 1999.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="lewis2013" label="Lewis 2013">Lewis, David. <title rend="italic">The Brain
            Sell: When Science Meets Shopping: How the New Mind Sciences and the Persuasion Industry
            Are Reading Our Thoughts, Influencing Our Emotions and Stimulating Us to Shop</title>.
          London; Boston: Nicholas Brealey Publishing, 2013.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="lingold2018" label="Lingold et al. 2018">Lingold, Mary Catton, Darren Mueller,
          and Whitney Anne Trettien, eds. <title rend="italic">Digital Sound Studies</title>.
          Durham, NC: Duke University Press, 2018.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="mcluhan1964" label="McLuhan 1964">McLuhan, Marshall. <title rend="italic"
            >Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man</title>. New York: New American Library,
          1964.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="mitchell2002" label="Mitchell 2002">Mitchell, W. J.T. <title rend="quotes"
            >Showing Seeing: A Critique of Visual Culture.</title><title rend="italic">Journal of
            Visual Culture</title> 1, no. 2 (August 2002): 165–81. <ref
            target="https://doi.org/10.1177/147041290200100202"
            >https://doi.org/10.1177/147041290200100202</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="moseley2015" label="Moseley 2015">Moseley, Roger. <title rend="quotes">Digital
            Analogies: The Keyboard as Field of Musical Play.</title> <title rend="italic">Journal
            of the American Musicological Society</title> 68, no. 1 (2015): 151-228.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="novak2015" label="Novak and Sakakeeny 2015">Novak, David, and Matt Sakakeeny,
          eds. <title rend="italic">Keywords in Sound</title>. Durham, NC: Duke University Press,
          2015.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="pinch2012" label="Pinch and Bijsterveld 2012">Trevor Pinch and Karin
          Bijsterveld, eds. <title rend="italic">The Oxford Handbook of Sound Studies</title>. New
          York: Oxford University Press, 2012.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="poels2006" label="Poels and Dewitte 2006">Poels, Karolien, and Siegfried
          Dewitte. <title rend="quotes">How to Capture the Heart? Reviewing 20 Years of Emotion
            Measurement in Advertising.</title><title rend="italic">Journal of Advertising
            Research</title> 46, no. 1 (March 2006): 18–37. <ref
            target="https://doi.org/10.2501/S0021849906060041"
            >https://doi.org/10.2501/S0021849906060041</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="rehding2017" label="Rehding et al. 2017">Rehding, Alexander, Gundula Kreuzer,
          Peter McMurray, Sybille Krämer, and Roger Moseley; <title rend="quotes"
            >Discrete/Continuous: Music and Media Theory after Kittler.</title><title rend="italic"
            >Journal of the American Musicological Society</title> 1 April 2017; 70 (1): 221–256.
          doi: https://doi.org/10.1525/jams.2017.70.1.221</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="sebok2014" label="Sebok 2014">Sebok, Bryan. <title rend="quotes">Collaborative
            Models for Engagement.</title><title rend="italic">Cinema Jounral Teaching
            Dossier</title>, Teaching Film and Media Studies in Liberal Arts Colleges, 2, no. 2
          (Spring 2014). <ref
            target="http://www.teachingmedia.org/teaching-film-media-studies-liberal-arts-colleges-cinema-journal-teaching-dossier-vol-2-2-spring-2014/"
            >http://www.teachingmedia.org/teaching-film-media-studies-liberal-arts-colleges-cinema-journal-teaching-dossier-vol-2-2-spring-2014/</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="sedivy2011" label="Sedivy and Carlson 2011">Sedivy, Julie, and Greg N.
          Carlson. <title rend="italic">Sold on Language: How Advertisers Talk to You and What This
            Says About You</title>. Chichester, West Sussex; Malden, MA: Wiley-Blackwell,
          2011.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="silverman1988" label="Silverman 1988">Silverman, Kaja. <title rend="italic"
            >The Acoustic Mirror: The Female Voice in Psychoanalysis and Cinema</title>.
          Bloomington, IN: Indiana University Press, 1988.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="sterne2003" label="Sterne 2003">Sterne, Jonathan. <title rend="italic">The
            Audible Past: Cultural Origins of Sound Reproduction</title>. Durham: Duke University
          Press, 2003.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="sterne2012" label="Sterne 2012">Sterne, Jonathan, ed. <title rend="italic">The
            Sound Studies Reader.</title> New York: Routledge, 2012.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="stiegler2014" label="Stiegler 2014">Stiegler, Bernard. <title rend="italic"
            >Symbolic Misery, Volume 1: The Hyperindustrial Epoch</title>. Translated by Barnaby
          Norman. Cambridge, UK: Polity Press, 2014.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="taruskin2005" label="Taruskin 2005">Taruskin, Richard.<title rend="italic"
            > The Oxford History of Western Music</title>. New York: Oxford University Press,
          2005.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="zielinski1999" label="Zielinski 1999">Zielinski, Siegfried. <title
            rend="italic">Audiovisions: Cinema and Television as Entr'actes in History</title>.
          Translated by Gloria Custance. Amsterdam: Amsterdam University Press, 1999.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="zielinski2006" label="Zielinski 2006">Zielinski, Siegfried. <title
            rend="italic">Deep Time of the Media: Toward an Archeology of Hearing and Seeing by
            Technical Means</title>. Translated by Gloria Custance. Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press,
          2006.</bibl>
      </listBibl>
    </back>
  </text>
  <!-- END TEXT -->

</TEI>
