<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng"    type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.isosch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"     type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns=      "http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:cc=   "http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq=  "http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:html= "http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
     xmlns:mml=  "http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf=  "http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Genre 2.0? Embedding-Based Cluster Analysis as a
                    Tool for Text Classification in Medieval Hebrew Literature</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Annabelle <dhq:family>Fuchs</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0009-0009-1712-0790</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Haifa</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>fuchs.annabelle@outlook.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Dr. Annabelle Fuchs is a postdoctoral researcher at the University of
                            Haifa and a recipient of the German Research Foundation’s (DFG)
                            prestigious Walter Benjamin Fellowship, supporting a two-year project on
                            the dynamics of Hebrew narrative prose in the Middle Ages. She holds a
                            PhD in Jewish Studies from the Center for Jewish Studies, Heidelberg
                            (Germany), where her dissertation developed a genre-theoretical
                            framework for medieval Hebrew narrative and midrashic literature. Her
                            research combines philological depth with computational methods, and her
                            work has been presented at international conferences such as the AJS,
                            EAJS, and the World Congress of Jewish Studies. In addition to her focus
                            on rabbinic and medieval Hebrew texts, she actively contributes to the
                            development of Digital Humanities approaches in Jewish Studies, with
                            particular attention to manuscript corpora, text classification, and the
                            cultural transmission of texts.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <!-- This information should be added when the file is created -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000806</idno>


                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="volume">019</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2025-09-19">19 September 2025</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/taxonomy.xml">https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/projects.xml">https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/wiki/DHQ-Topic-Keywords; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->

                    <!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new <term> element for each -->
                    <term corresp="#medieval"/>
                    <term corresp="#corpora"/>
                    <term corresp="#data_analytics"/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    
                
                  <term/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>cluster analysis</item>
                        <item>Hebrew</item>
                        <item>stylometry</item>
                        <item>computational literary studies</item>
                        <item>Midrash</item>
                        <item>Jewish studies</item>
                        <item>Jewish literature</item>
                        <item>BEREL 2.0</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Replace "XXXXXX" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
            <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref type="gitHist" target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000806/000806.xml">GitHub</ref>.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>The classification of medieval Hebrew literature has long relied on historically
                    inherited genre labels, often leading to misassignments and blurred textual
                    boundaries. This study applies transformer-based cluster analysis to a corpus of
                    60 texts, using BEREL embeddings and hierarchical clustering to evaluate whether
                    selected computational methods can provide empirically grounded, complementary
                    insights to traditional genre classifications. The analysis identifies several
                    stable clusters, including a distinct <q>Narrative</q> cluster, reinforcing
                    prior research that questions the categorization of certain texts as <q>Aggadic
                        Midrash.</q> While some clusters align with established classifications,
                    others highlight ambiguities that challenge conventional taxonomies. The study
                    demonstrates that computational clustering can systematically capture textual
                    affinities, revealing relationships that may remain obscured in traditional
                    approaches. These findings establish a methodological framework for reassessing
                    genre structures in Hebrew literature, laying the groundwork for future research
                    based on expanded datasets and manuscript evidence.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Can computational methods reclassify medieval Hebrew texts? This study uses transformer-based embeddings and hierarchical clustering to reveal hidden textual affinities and challenge inherited genre labels.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>1. Introduction</head>
                <p>Medieval Hebrew narrative literature has remained largely underrepresented in the
                    study of Hebrew literary history. In contrast, fields such as Hebrew poetry and
                    religious texts have traditionally occupied a more central position in Jewish
                    Studies (cf. <ptr target="#rosen_2004"/>; <ptr target="#yassif_2013"/>. One
                    consequence of this imbalance is the continued reliance on foundational
                    scholarship from the <hi rend="italic">Wissenschaft des Judentums</hi>, the
                    19th- and early 20th-century academic movement that shaped the categorization of
                    Hebrew texts (cf. <ptr target="#fuchs_2024"/>). While these early studies were
                    instrumental in establishing the field, they also introduced classificatory
                    frameworks that remain in use despite their limitations. In particular, medieval
                    Hebrew literary genres lack precise definitions, as their categorization
                    continues to reflect historical terminologies rather than clear formal or
                    stylistic distinctions. As <ptr target="#fuchs_2024"/> has demonstrated, the
                    term <q>Midrash</q> has often been applied indiscriminately to medieval texts
                    that do not align with the genre’s original definition. This overextension of
                    the <q>Midrash</q> label has obscured the distinctiveness of Hebrew narrative
                    texts, relegating them to the margins of literary scholarship and limiting their
                    systematic study.</p>
                <p>Rather than advancing a renewed genre theory, this study takes an empirical
                    approach, asking: Do Hebrew narrative texts, rather than being subsumed under
                    the broad category of <q>Midrash,</q> form a distinct and coherent cluster when
                    analyzed through quantitative methods? If so, this would indicate that
                    computational approaches can detect textual affinities and distinctions that
                    have been overlooked by traditional classifications. To explore this, the study
                    applies embedding-based cluster analysis to a dataset of 60 medieval Hebrew
                    texts, grouping them according to patterns captured by a transformer model
                    rather than relying on predefined genre labels. The aim is to test whether
                    computational methods can reveal textual affinities that align with or challenge
                    existing scholarly categories. The findings lay the groundwork for further
                    research that will refine the dataset and methodology, particularly through the
                    inclusion of manuscript-based texts.</p>
                <p>Transformer models like BEREL 2.0 are deep learning architectures trained on
                    large corpora to recognize contextual patterns in language. Instead of relying
                    on manually defined features, they generate embeddings — dense numerical
                    representations that capture semantic, syntactic, and structural properties of a
                    text. Each text in this study is represented by a vector summarizing its
                    internal linguistic behavior. BEREL 2.0, trained specifically on historical
                    Hebrew, enables the comparison of these vectors, allowing texts to be grouped
                    not by external genre labels but by patterns in how they use language.</p>
                <p>The remainder of this paper proceeds as follows: The next section provides an
                    overview of previous computational approaches to Hebrew text analysis, tracing
                    the development of stylometric methods, clustering techniques, and the more
                    recent use of transformer-based embeddings in Jewish literary studies. This is
                    followed by a description of the dataset and methodology, including text
                    selection, preprocessing, and clustering procedures. The results section
                    presents the key findings, highlighting the emerging clusters and their
                    implications for existing classifications. Finally, the discussion considers
                    both the potential and limitations of computational methods, and the conclusion
                    outlines directions for future research.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. Related Work</head>
                <p>This chapter summarizes key computational approaches in Jewish literary studies,
                    focusing on important predecessors in the fields of stylometry, cluster
                    analysis, and embedding-based methods. <ptr target="#dershowitz_2015"/>
                    introduced a computational approach to source criticism in the Hebrew Bible,
                    using stylistic markers to distinguish between different authorial layers. The
                    foundation for this work was laid already in 2011 and 2013 by Akiva and Koppel
                    et al., who developed unsupervised methods for detecting multiple authorship,
                    demonstrating the effectiveness of computational stylometry for Hebrew texts
                        <ptr target="#koppel_2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#akiva_2013"/>. <ptr target="#bar-asher_2018"/> applied similar
                    techniques to reconstruct lost portions of <hi rend="italic">Mekhilta
                        Deuteronomy</hi>, combining textual pattern recognition with machine
                    learning. While these studies primarily focused on authorship attribution and
                    textual transmission, they demonstrated the viability of computational methods
                    for Hebrew literary analysis, providing a foundation for subsequent work in text
                    classification.</p>
                <p><ptr target="#van-hecke_2018"/> demonstrated the effectiveness of hierarchical
                    clustering for analyzing stylistic relationships in the Dead Sea Scrolls, later
                    refining the methodology with <ptr target="#van-hecke_2021"/>. This approach was
                    extended in 2020 by <ptr target="#van-der-schans_2020"/>, who applied recurrent
                    neural networks (RNNs) to Biblical Hebrew, using clustering techniques to test
                    diachronic models of linguistic variation. Both studies share a conceptual
                    framework with the present research: They employ clustering algorithms to group
                    texts based on stylistic or linguistic features, visualizing these relationships
                    using dendrograms and dimensionality reduction techniques. The key distinction
                    is that these studies relied on manually selected linguistic features or
                    relatively shallow text representations, while the present study advances this
                    methodology by leveraging BERT-based embeddings, automating feature extraction,
                    and enabling deeper stylistic modeling.</p>
                <p>Research in the field over the last years has predominantly applied computational
                    stylometry and cluster analysis to antique texts, such as the Hebrew Bible and
                    the Dead Sea Scrolls. More recent efforts, like those at the Open University of
                    Israel, have shifted focus to modern Hebrew literature (see the project <ref target="https://www.openu.ac.il/en/omilab/pages/stylisticprofiles.aspx"><title rend="quotes">Computational Stylistic Profiles for the Analysis
                            of Modern Hebrew Prose</title></ref>). The only known study examining a
                    medieval Hebrew corpus is that of <ptr target="#tannor_2023"/>, which classified
                    rabbinic texts to identify lost <hi rend="italic">Midrash Tanhuma</hi> material.
                    For the broader history of computational textual analysis of the Hebrew Bible,
                    see <ptr target="#van-peursen_2023"/>.</p>
                <p>A major development in computational Hebrew text analysis has been the
                    introduction of transformer-based language models tailored to historical Hebrew
                    texts. While other models, such as HeBERT <ptr target="#chriqui_2022"/> were
                    trained on modern Hebrew, their application to pre-modern texts is limited. The
                    introduction of BEREL <ptr target="#shmidman_2022"/>, followed by its improved
                    version, BEREL 2.0, marked the first model specifically designed for classical
                    Hebrew (cf. <ref target="https://huggingface.co/dicta-il/BEREL_2.0">BEREL 2.0 on
                        Hugging Face</ref>). <ptr target="#tannor_2023"/> applied BEREL to classify
                    rabbinic and medieval texts, demonstrating that it outperformed alternative
                    models such as AlephBERT <ptr target="#seker_2022"/> in identifying complex
                    language patterns and textual structures. Their findings confirmed that
                    deep-learning-based text representations provide a more robust foundation for
                    Hebrew text classification than earlier feature-based approaches. This study
                    extends their work by applying BEREL embeddings to medieval Hebrew narrative
                    literature, a domain where computational clustering has not yet been
                    explored.</p>
                <p>The present study builds on the methodological foundations established by
                    previous research, adapting them to a new textual corpus and a different
                    literary-historical context. By combining BERT-based embeddings with
                    hierarchical clustering, it explores whether this approach can offer a
                    data-driven complement to traditional genre classification.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3. Data and Methodology</head>
                <div>
                    <head>3.1. Corpus Selection</head>
                    <p>The dataset for this study consists of 60 Hebrew texts from antique,
                        rabbinic, and medieval literary traditions, including a few modern Hebrew
                        translations of earlier works originally preserved in other languages. The
                        majority of these texts were obtained through the Git repository of the
                        Sefaria website (<ref target="https://github.com/Sefaria/Sefaria-Export">Link to GitHub</ref>). <ref target="https://www.sefaria.org/texts">Sefaria</ref>, a widely used online library of Jewish texts,
                        categorizes its collection into the following groups: <q>Tanakh,</q>
                        <q>Mishnah,</q>
                        <q>Talmud,</q>
                        <q>Kabbalah,</q>
                        <q>Liturgy,</q>
                        <q>Jewish Thought,</q>
                        <q>Tosefta,</q>
                        <q>Chasidut,</q>
                        <q>Musar,</q>
                        <q>Responsa,</q> and <q>Second Temple.</q> These categories reflect a
                        conventional classification of Jewish texts and serve as a point of
                        reference in this study, allowing for a systematic comparison between
                        traditional categorizations and the data-driven clusters that emerge through
                        computational analysis.</p>
                    <p>To ensure that the cluster analysis would produce distinct and meaningful
                        clusters, five texts were selected from each of the following categories:
                            <q>Tanakh</q> (= the Hebrew Bible), <q>Talmud,</q>
                        <q>Aggadic Midrash,</q>
                        <q>Halakhic Midrash,</q>
                        <q>Halakha,</q>
                        <q>Liturgy,</q>
                        <q>Jewish Thought,</q>
                        <q>Musar,</q> and <q>Second Temple.</q> The selection was made largely at
                        random, with the only curating criterion being technical constraints, such
                        as a minimum text length of 20,000 characters (though the shortest included
                        text contains approximately 28,000 characters). This process resulted in a
                        core dataset of 45 texts.</p>
                    <p>In addition, 12 further texts from Sefaria’s <q>Aggadic Midrash</q> category
                        were included, each displaying varying degrees of narrative characteristics.
                        These texts have been previously discussed in scholarly debates concerning
                        their classification, making them particularly relevant for assessing how
                        computational methods distinguish between Midrashic and narrative literature
                        (e.g., <ptr target="#borner-klein_2004"/>; <ptr target="#borner-klein_2010"/>; <ptr target="#borner-klein_2016"/>; <ptr target="#nikolsky_2021"/>; <ptr target="#fuchs_2024"/>). Their inclusion allows for a closer examination
                        of whether narrative tendencies influence their clustering and to what
                        extent they align with or diverge from traditionally defined Midrashim.
                        Furthermore, three additional texts were incorporated into the dataset based
                        on previous research indicating their narrative character. Since they are
                        not available on Sefaria — and thus do not fall within its categorization —
                        these texts were obtained from freely accessible online sources such as
                        Wikitext. </p>
                    <p>Two texts from the previously mentioned category <q>Aggadic Midrash</q>, <hi rend="italic">Petirat Moshe</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Petirat
                            Aharon</hi>, were transcribed directly from manuscript witnesses rather
                        than drawn from later printed sources. Most other texts in the dataset are
                        based on later textual traditions, including printed editions, later
                        recensions, and editorially standardized versions. The planned move toward
                        manuscript-based sources is discussed further in section <q>5.2. Limitations
                            &amp; Future Work.</q></p>
                    <p>The 60 texts included in this study were preprocessed before analysis to
                        ensure consistency and eliminate non-textual clues that could interfere with
                        clustering. Special characters, annotations, and <hi rend="italic">nikud</hi> (vowel markings), when present, were systematically removed;
                        in addition, embedded biblical quotations were excluded as part of the
                        preprocessing. Following this, texts exceeding 100,000 characters were
                        truncated to that length, with the selected segment taken from the middle of
                        the text to avoid biases introduced by introductory or concluding
                        sections.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3.2. Text Representation</head>
                    <p>To generate numerical representations of the texts, this study employed BEREL
                        2.0, a transformer model specifically trained on rabbinical Hebrew texts
                            <ptr target="#shmidman_2022"/>. BEREL is based on the BERT
                        (Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers) architecture,
                        which enables it to capture deep contextual and syntactic relationships
                        within texts <ptr target="#devlin_2018"/>. BEREL 2.0 was selected as the
                        sole embedding model for this experiment, as it has been found to be the
                        most suitable for processing medieval Hebrew literature (cf. <ptr target="#tannor_2023"/>). While future research may include comparative
                        evaluations of other transformer models, BEREL 2.0 proved to be effective
                        for the present task.</p>
                    <p>Each text was tokenized into 512-token windows with a stride of 256, ensuring
                        overlapping segments that preserved contextual continuity. The CLS token
                        representation was extracted from each window, as this embedding encodes a
                        summary of the segment’s linguistic characteristics. To obtain a single
                        representation per text, the CLS embeddings from all windows were averaged,
                        creating a 768-dimensional vector that captured the overall semantic,
                        syntactic, and structural properties of the text. This approach ensured that
                        longer texts were not disproportionately influenced by their opening or
                        closing sections, instead providing a balanced representation of the full
                        document.</p>
                    <p>Since BERT-based embeddings are inherently high-dimensional, a two-step
                        dimensionality reduction process was applied to facilitate clustering and
                        visualization. The original 768-dimensional embeddings contain both
                        meaningful linguistic patterns and noise, making direct clustering
                        computationally inefficient. To retain the most relevant features, Principal
                        Component Analysis (PCA) first reduced the embeddings to 50 dimensions,
                        filtering out less informative variance while preserving key structural
                        patterns. To enable clustering, Uniform Manifold Approximation and
                        Projection (UMAP) was applied, reducing the data to two dimensions. UMAP was
                        chosen over alternative methods such as t-SNE due to its ability to maintain
                        both local and global relationships between texts. </p>
                    <p>This study clusters directly in UMAP 2D for computational feasibility and
                        interpretability. Although this necessarily discards some variance, UMAP is
                        designed to preserve meaningful structural relationships even in low
                        dimensions. To mitigate potential instability, UMAP was run 50 times, and
                        the final projection was averaged across runs, preventing random variations
                        from distorting the clusters.</p>
                    <p>Given the effectiveness of this approach, as shown in the <q>4. Results</q>
                        section, there was no immediate need to explore clustering in
                        higher-dimensional spaces for this proof of concept. However, future studies
                        may benefit from testing clustering in higher-dimensional UMAP spaces (e.g.,
                        10D or 20D) to evaluate whether additional variance further refines
                        classification results. For a discussion on the potential limitations of
                        dimensionality reduction, see <q>5.2. Limitations &amp; Future Work.</q></p>
                    <div>
                        <head>3.3. Clustering Approach</head>
                        <p>To identify meaningful textual groupings, this study applied hierarchical
                            clustering to the UMAP-reduced embeddings. Clustering, in this context,
                            refers to the process of grouping texts based on numerical
                            representations that capture internal patterns of language use and
                            structure. The more similar two texts are, the closer their
                            corresponding vectors are in the multidimensional space, which results
                            in them being merged earlier in the hierarchical clustering process.
                            Unlike methods such as K-means, hierarchical clustering does not require
                            specifying the number of clusters in advance, making it well-suited for
                            an exploratory study of textual relationships. Ward’s method was chosen,
                            as it minimizes intra-cluster variance, ensuring that texts within a
                            cluster are as similar to each other as possible. Instead of setting a
                            fixed number of clusters, the threshold for merging clusters was
                            dynamically adjusted to produce a meaningful number of clusters, ranging
                            between eight and ten.</p>
                        <p>To illustrate the clustering process, Figure 1 presents a UMAP projection
                            based on a single clustering iteration. This visualization shows how
                            texts are distributed in the two-dimensional space generated by UMAP,
                            providing a simplified view of their relative positions in the
                            high-dimensional embedding space. The projection offers an intuitive
                            representation of the textual relationships captured in one iteration of
                            the pipeline.</p>
                        <figure>
                            <head>UMAP projection based on one clustering iteration. Each point
                                represents a single text, and colors indicate cluster membership as
                                determined by hierarchical clustering of the UMAP-reduced embeddings
                                in that run. While the projection is simplified to two dimensions,
                                it preserves local relationships between texts and offers an
                                intuitive visualization of the grouping process. In this particular
                                iteration, nine clusters were identified. For clarity and
                                interpretive alignment, the descriptive cluster labels used in Table
                                1 are applied here, even though the exact groupings differ slightly
                                from the final meta-clusters: 1 Blue: <q>Liturgy,</q> 2 Orange:
                                    <q>Pseudo-Bible,</q> 3 Green: <q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible,</q> 4 Red:
                                    <q>Narrative,</q> 5 Purple: <q>Midrash Aggada,</q> 6 Brown:
                                    <q>Midrash–Narrative Mix,</q> 7 Pink: <q>Talmud/Halakha,</q> 8
                                Grey: <q>Halakha–Philosophy Mix,</q> 9 Olive:
                                <q>Philosophy.</q></head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>To ensure the robustness of the clustering results, the entire pipeline,
                            including embedding generation, was repeated 100 times. Since
                            transformer-based models like BEREL 2.0 produce slightly different
                            embeddings in each run, individual cluster assignments showed minor
                            variations across iterations. Rather than relying on a single clustering
                            outcome, a co-occurrence matrix was constructed, tracking how often each
                            text appeared in the same cluster across all 100 runs.</p>
                        <p>A second round of hierarchical clustering was then applied to this
                            matrix, identifying stable groupings that consistently emerged across
                            runs. These stable clusters — referred to in this article as
                            meta-clusters — reflect recurrent textual affinities independent of
                            run-to-run variation. Their distribution is visualized in a
                            co-occurrence heatmap (<ref target="#figure_02">Figure 2</ref>), which highlights the strength of
                            associations between texts across the 100 iterations.</p>
                        <p>In addition to storing cluster memberships, the pipeline also recorded
                            the pairwise distance between each pair of texts in every run. These
                            distance values, derived from the position of each text in the reduced
                            embedding space, represent the degree of dissimilarity between texts:
                            the lower the value, the more similar the texts. By averaging these
                            distances across all runs, a new distance matrix was created that
                            reflects the overall proximity of texts throughout the experiment.</p>
                        <p>A second clustering solution was then derived by applying Ward’s
                            hierarchical clustering directly to the averaged distance matrix. Unlike
                            the meta-clusters, which reflect co-clustering frequency, this second
                            approach sorts texts based on cumulative pairwise dissimilarity. The
                            result is a dendrogram showing hierarchical relationships among all
                            texts, with cluster boundaries generated by an automated distance
                            threshold (<ref target="#figure_03">Figure 3</ref>).</p>
                        <p>Both the meta-clusters derived from co-occurrence patterns and the
                            distance-based clusters obtained from averaged pairwise dissimilarities
                            resulted in ten groupings. While the two structures broadly align,
                            subtle differences highlight texts that occupy boundary positions
                            between clusters — cases that are addressed in section <q>4.
                                Results.</q>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3.4. Evaluation &amp; Validation</head>
                    <p>The co-occurrence matrix confirms that clusters formed consistently,
                        indicating that the results are not random but reflect meaningful textual
                        similarities. The emerging clusters align closely with expected
                        classifications, reinforcing confidence in the method. The heatmap in Figure
                        2 demonstrates that texts with known affinities are repeatedly grouped
                        together across iterations. A complementary clustering structure, derived
                        from the averaged distance measurements between texts, yielded a similar
                        grouping of the corpus, further supporting the robustness of the approach.
                        While factors such as text length and embedding variations were considered
                        potential biases, their influence appears minimal. A more detailed
                        evaluation of methodological limitations follows in section <q>5.
                            Discussion.</q></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4. Results</head>
                <div>
                    <head>4.1. General Overview</head>
                    <p>Both clustering approaches applied in this study — meta-clustering based on
                        co-occurrence patterns and hierarchical clustering of averaged distance
                        measurements — converged on a shared structure of ten distinct clusters. To
                        preserve interpretability and analytical coherence, the number of clusters
                        was constrained to a range between eight and ten; within this range, both
                        methods independently arrived at a division into ten groups. This clustering
                        structure is echoed in both visualizations (<ref target="#figure_02">Figure 2</ref> and <ref target="#figure_03">Figure 3</ref>),
                        highlighting how texts consistently formed meaningful groupings across
                        runs.</p>
                    <p>Notably, these clusters do not always align with Sefaria’s predefined
                        categories. Rather than relying on external (genre) classifications, they
                        are derived from internal textual patterns — semantic, syntactic, and
                        structural — offering a data-driven reflection of textual relationships.
                        These results reinforce the limitations of traditional classification
                        systems, such as those used by the Sefaria website, and confirm the
                        potential of computational methods to produce more reliable textual
                        groupings. The following table presents the ten clusters identified through
                        both meta-clustering and distance-based clustering, allowing for direct
                        comparison between the two methods.</p>
                    <table>
                        <head>The color scheme used in Table 1 mirrors that of Figure 2 and Figure
                            3, providing a consistent visual reference for comparing cluster
                            assignments.</head>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell>Text</cell>
                            <cell>Distance-Based Cluster (Dendrogram)</cell>
                            <cell>Meta-Cluster (Heatmap)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Shemot Rabba </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:blue">1 (<q>Midrash Aggada</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:purple">1 (<q>Midrash Aggada</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Devarim Rabba </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:blue">1 (<q>Midrash Aggada</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:purple">1 (<q>Midrash Aggada</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Bamidbar Rabba </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:blue">1 (<q>Midrash Aggada</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:purple">1 (<q>Midrash Aggada</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Bereshit Rabba </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:blue">1 (<q>Midrash Aggada</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:purple">1 (<q>Midrash Aggada</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Tanhuma Buber </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:blue">1 (<q>Midrash Aggada</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:purple">1 (<q>Midrash Aggada</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Aggadat Bereshit </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:blue">1 (<q>Midrash Aggada</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:purple">1 (<q>Midrash Aggada</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Halakha. Mekhila deRabbi Yishmael </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:red">2 (<q>Midrash/Narrative Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:purple">1 (<q>Midrash Aggada</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Pirke deRabbi Eliezer </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:red">2 (<q>Midrash/Narrative Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:purple">1 (<q>Midrash Aggada</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Petirat Moshe </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:red">2 (<q>Midrash/Narrative Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:green">2 (<q>Midrash/Narrative Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Petirat Aharon </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:red">2 (<q>Midrash/Narrative Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:green">2 (<q>Midrash/Narrative Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Halakha. Sifre Zuta </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:red">2 (<q>Midrash/Narrative Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:green">2 (<q>Midrash/Narrative Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Yalqut on Tora </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:red">2 (<q>Midrash/Narrative Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:green">2 (<q>Midrash/Narrative Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Eldad ha-Dani </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkCyan">3 (<q>Narrative</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:navy">3 (<q>Narrative</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Alphabet of Ben Sira </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkCyan">3 (<q>Narrative</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:navy">3 (<q>Narrative</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Midrash Asseret haDibberot </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkCyan">3 (<q>Narrative</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:navy">3 (<q>Narrative</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Elle Ezkera </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkCyan">3 (<q>Narrative</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:navy">3 (<q>Narrative</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Halakha. Sifre Devarim </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkCyan">3 (<q>Narrative</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:navy">3 (<q>Narrative</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Halakha. Sifra </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkCyan">3 (<q>Narrative</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:navy">3 (<q>Narrative</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>None. Hibbur yafe mehaYehoshua </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DeepPink">4 (<q>Narrative II</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:red">4 (<q>Narrative II</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Maaseh Avraham </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DeepPink">4 (<q>Narrative II</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:red">4 (<q>Narrative II</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>None. Mishle Sendebar </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DeepPink">4 (<q>Narrative II</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:red">4 (<q>Narrative II</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Mussar. Shaar haGmul </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Mussar. Kad haKemah </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Jewish Thought. Ohr haShem </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Jewish Thought. Akeidat Yitzhak </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Mussar. Mivhar haPeninim </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Mussar. Sefer haYashar </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Jewish Thought. Emunot we-Deot </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Jewish Thought. Moreh Nevuchim </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Jewish Thought. Milkhamot haShem </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:brown">5 (<q>Philosophy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> Halakha. Sefer Mitzwot Gadol </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:orange">6 (<q>Halakha/Philosophy Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:orange">6 (<q>Halakha/Philosophy Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Halakha. Kol Bo </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:orange">6 (<q>Halakha/Philosophy Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:orange">6 (<q>Halakha/Philosophy Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Mussar. Sefer haYira </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:orange">6 (<q>Halakha/Philosophy Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:orange">6 (<q>Halakha/Philosophy Mix</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Bible. Josua </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:purple">7 (<q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell>7 (<q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q>)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Bible. Genesis </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:purple">7 (<q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell>7 (<q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q>)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>None. Sefer Jossipon </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:purple">7 (<q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell>7 (<q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q>)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Divre haYamim shel Moshe </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:purple">7 (<q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell>7 (<q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q>)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Bible. Leviticus </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:purple">7 (<q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:grey">8 (<q>Bible</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Bible. Deuteronomy </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:purple">7 (<q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:grey">8 (<q>Bible</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Bible. Isaiah </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:purple">7 (<q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:grey">8 (<q>Bible</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Second Temple. Sefer Makabim I </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:green">8 (<q>Pseudo-Bible</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell>7 (<q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q>)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Aggada. Sefer haYashar </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:green">8 (<q>Pseudo-Bible</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell>7 (<q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q>)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Second Temple. Sefer Makabim II </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:green">8 (<q>Pseudo-Bible</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell>7 (<q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q>)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Liturgy. Siddur Sefard </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkBlue">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkCyan">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Liturgy. Siddur Ashkenaz </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkBlue">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkCyan">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Liturgy. Machsor Yom Kippur Ashkenaz </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkBlue">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkCyan">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Liturgy. Machsor Rosh haShana Ashkenaz </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkBlue">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkCyan">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Liturgy. Siddur Edot haMizrach </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkBlue">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkCyan">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Second Temple. Sefer haYovlim </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkBlue">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkCyan">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Second Temple. Sefer Yehudit </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkBlue">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkCyan">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Second Temple. Tsavaat haShevatim </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkBlue">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DarkCyan">9 (<q>Liturgy</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Halakha. Tur </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:FireBrick">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DeepPink">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Halakha. Sefer Mitzwot Katan </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:FireBrick">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DeepPink">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Midrash Halakha. Midrash Tannaim Dtn </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:FireBrick">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DeepPink">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Talmud. Nezikin. Avoda Zara </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:FireBrick">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DeepPink">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Talmud. Moed. Beitzah </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:FireBrick">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DeepPink">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Talmud. Kodashim. Arakhin </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:FireBrick">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DeepPink">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Talmud. Nashim. Kettubot </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:FireBrick">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DeepPink">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Talmud. Toharot. Nidda </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:FireBrick">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DeepPink">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Halakha. Halakhot Gedolot </cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:FireBrick">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi style="color:DeepPink">10 (<q>Talmud/Halakha</q>)</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>To maintain clarity and transparency throughout this research paper, each
                        text is named according to a consistent convention. The name begins with its
                        traditional classification as listed in Sefaria, followed by a period, and
                        then the individual text title (e.g., <q>Midrash Aggada. Shemot Rabba</q>).
                        This structure ensures that the original genre assignment remains visible,
                        allowing for direct comparison between traditional categorizations and the
                        clusters identified in this study. </p>
                    <p>The cluster names used in this study were assigned post hoc based on the
                        composition of each group, aiming to provide a neutral and descriptive
                        representation of the texts contained within them. Whenever possible, the
                        labels were aligned with traditional literary classifications, ensuring that
                        they reflect recognizable textual traditions rather than imposing new genre
                        definitions.</p>
                    <p>This is particularly relevant when considering the assignment of the term
                            <q>Narrative</q> to one of the clusters, which includes several texts
                        traditionally classified as <q>Aggadic Midrash.</q> In previous research
                            <ptr target="#dan_1974"/>
                        <ptr target="#yassif_2009"/>
                        <ptr target="#fuchs_2024"/>, it has been observed that certain texts labeled
                        as <q>Midrash</q> exhibit a distinctly narrative structure while lacking the
                        formal characteristics of midrashic literature, raising questions about
                        their classification. However, defining clear criteria for distinguishing
                        narrative texts from Midrashim has remained a challenge. </p>
                    <p>The cluster analysis presented here offers an empirical perspective on this
                        issue, as one of the clusters emerged with a distinctive stylistic profile
                        aligning with features typically associated with narrative texts. This
                        grouping was not imposed in advance and only recognized retrospectively
                        based on its clear separation from other clusters and its shared textual
                        characteristics. By relying on measurable textual similarities, rather than
                        preconceived genre definitions, this approach provides a data-driven means
                        of reassessing textual classifications. The naming conventions used
                        throughout this research paper serve as interpretative tools, describing the
                        observed clustering patterns without enforcing rigid genre distinctions.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4.2. Visualization of Results</head>
                    <p>Two visualizations offer insights into the structure and stability of the
                        detected textual groupings: a co-occurrence heatmap (<ref target="#figure_02">Figure 2</ref>) and a
                        dendrogram based on averaged distance measurements (<ref target="#figure_03">Figure 3</ref>). Both
                        visualizations employ Ward’s method for clustering, though they rely on
                        different types of data extracted from the clustering process.</p>
                    <p>The co-occurrence heatmap (<ref target="#figure_02">Figure 2</ref>) presents the frequency with which each
                        pair of texts appeared in the same cluster across 100 full iterations of the
                        pipeline. Each cell in the matrix represents a pairwise relationship, with
                        warmer colors indicating higher co-clustering consistency and cooler colors
                        reflecting weaker associations. This visualization highlights the most
                        stable clusters in the corpus; while, for example, the groups labeled
                            <q>Talmud/Halakha,</q>
                        <q>Liturgy,</q> and <q>Philosophy</q> show strong internal cohesion, other
                        clusters, such as the transitional group <q>Midrash/Narrative Mix,</q>
                        display more fluid boundaries, suggesting stylistic overlap or ambiguity in
                        textual affinities.</p>
                    <p>The heatmap provides an interpretable summary of long-run clustering
                        behavior. Unlike single-run visualizations, it emphasizes robust
                        relationships by averaging over many iterations. Cluster assignments in this
                        visualization form the basis for the meta-cluster structure used in the
                        descriptive table above.</p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure_02">
                        <head>Heatmap of co-occurrence frequencies across 100 clustering iterations.
                            Each cell shows how often a pair of texts was assigned to the same
                            cluster. Warmer colors indicate stronger co-clustering tendencies.
                            Clusters were generated via hierarchical clustering of this
                            co-occurrence matrix using Ward’s method. The color scheme matches the
                            cluster labels in Table 1: Red: <q>Narrative II,</q> Blue: <q>Midrash
                                Aggada,</q> Green: <q>Midrash–Narrative Mix,</q> Purple: <q>Midrash
                                Aggada,</q> Orange: <q>Halakha–Philosophy Mix,</q> Brown:
                                <q>Philosophy,</q> Pink: <q>Talmud/Halakha,</q> Teal:
                                <q>Liturgy,</q> Grey: <q>Bible,</q> Black:
                                <q>Pseudo-Bible/Bible.</q></head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In contrast to the heatmap, which is based on co-occurrence patterns, the
                        dendrogram (<ref target="#figure_03">Figure 3</ref>) visualizes the average pairwise distances between
                        texts across the 100 clustering runs. These distances reflect how similar or
                        dissimilar each text is to every other text, based on their relative
                        positions in the embedding space. The dendrogram arranges the texts
                        hierarchically, grouping the most similar pairs first, and successively
                        merging them into larger clusters.</p>
                    <p>The horizontal axis in the dendrogram represents distance: the further to the
                        right the merging point, the more similar the texts. Cluster divisions were
                        produced by applying a threshold of 0.26 to the tree structure, resulting in
                        a division into ten groups. However, the dendrogram also allows for a more
                        nuanced reading: even when texts fall into different clusters, their
                        proximity in the tree reveals how closely related they remain. </p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure_03">
                        <head>Dendrogram showing hierarchical clustering of averaged pairwise
                            distances between texts (across 100 runs). Ward’s method was used for
                            clustering. A threshold of 0.26 was applied to determine ten clusters.
                            The horizontal axis represents dissimilarity; shorter branches indicate
                            greater similarity. The color scheme corresponds to Table 1: Blue:
                                <q>Midrash Aggada,</q> Red: <q>Midrash/Narrative Mix,</q> Teal:
                                <q>Narrative,</q> Pink: <q>Narrative II,</q> Brown:
                                <q>Philosophy,</q> Orange: <q>Halakha–Philosophy Mix,</q> Purple:
                                <q>Pseudo-Bible/Bible,</q> Green: <q>Pseudo-Bible,</q> Blue II:
                                <q>Liturgy,</q> Red II: <q>Talmud/Halakha.</q></head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4.3. Key Findings</head>
                    <p>The clustering results reveal stable and meaningful groupings, though these
                        do not always align with Sefaria’s predefined categories. Rather than
                        replicating traditional genre classifications, the clusters reflect patterns
                        in textual structure, language use, and composition, allowing texts to be
                        grouped based on internal features rather than external labels. This
                        highlights how embedding-based similarities can transcend historical or
                        thematic classifications, resulting in clusters that are broader and more
                        flexible than conventional genre categories.</p>
                    <p>The following discussion of cluster contents proceeds in the order of
                        appearance in Table 1, which lists both the meta-cluster and distance-based
                        cluster assignments. </p>
                    <p>The first cluster may be described using the label <q>Midrash Aggada.</q> In
                        the distance-based clustering, this group is relatively cohesive, comprising
                        six core texts: <title rend="italic">Bereshit Rabba</title>, <title rend="italic">Shemot Rabba</title>, <title rend="italic">Bamidbar
                            Rabba</title>, <title rend="italic">Devarim Rabba</title>, <title rend="italic">Tanhuma Buber</title>, and <title rend="italic">Aggadat
                            Bereshit</title>. The meta-clustering approach includes two additional
                        works: <title rend="italic">Pirke deRabbi Eliezer</title> and <title rend="italic">Mekhilta deRabbi Yishmael</title>. The latter, however,
                        already belongs to a more mixed grouping of midrashic and narrative works in
                        the distance-based clustering.</p>
                    <p>Despite these minor differences in cluster boundaries, both approaches
                        confirm the internal stylistic coherence of the core aggadic midrashim.
                        Their textual similarities outweigh distinctions in historical context or
                        thematic content, supporting the conclusion that their classification as
                            <q>Aggadic Midrashim</q> is not merely conventional but grounded in
                        measurable linguistic and structural features. Notably, the included texts
                        span from approximately the 4th to the 12th centuries, yet they are
                        consistently grouped together by the model. This suggests that the features
                        captured by BEREL, such as lexical choice, syntactic structure, and
                        discursive patterns, reflect a unique stylistic cluster profile that
                        persists across centuries, and therefore includes both earlier and later
                        Midrashim alike.</p>
                    <p>The next group can be described as <q>Midrash/Narrative Mix.</q> It appears
                        in both clustering outcomes, albeit with slight differences in text
                        allocation, as previously discussed. In both cases, the works in this
                        cluster are positioned between the <q>Midrash Aggada</q> and the
                            <q>Narrative</q> groups, suggesting that they share features with both.
                        Most of the included texts are traditionally classified as <q>Midrash
                            Aggada,</q> though <title rend="italic">Sifre Zuta</title> stands out as
                        an exception, having been traditionally identified as a halakhic midrash.
                        The cluster analysis indicates that all of these works exhibit at least
                        partial narrative characteristics, positioning them stylistically between
                        the more homogeneous <q>Midrash Aggada</q> and <q>Narrative</q> clusters. </p>
                    <p>The third group, described as the <q>Narrative</q> cluster, is identical in
                        both clustering approaches. It consists of six works and is closely related
                        to a fourth cluster that also contains texts with predominantly narrative
                        character. The separation of these two groups results from the threshold
                        applied during the clustering process: Had the cutoff been set slightly
                        higher, they would have merged into a single, broader cluster.</p>
                    <p>The emergence of this distinct Narrative cluster is a central finding of the
                        study. This grouping includes texts that are traditionally labeled as
                            <q>Aggadic Midrashim,</q> not only in Sefaria’s classification but also
                        in broader scholarly discourse. Some even bear the word <quote rend="inline">Midrash</quote> in their titles, such as <title rend="italic">Midrash
                            Aseret ha-Dibberot</title> (<title rend="quotes">The Midrash of the Ten
                            Commandments</title>). Despite these labels, the clustering consistently
                        identified their stronger affinity with other works characterized by
                        narrative structure, suggesting that their stylistic and linguistic features
                        align more closely with narrative compositions than with midrashic works
                        from the <q>Midrash Aggada</q> group. The clustering process, grounded in
                        internal textual features rather than inherited genre designations,
                        highlights these affinities and challenges the conventional classification
                        schemes that have long shaped the field.</p>
                    <p>The next cluster, broadly labeled <q>Philosophy,</q> appears identically in
                        both clustering outcomes. It brings together texts that Sefaria
                        distinguishes as either <q>Musar</q> or <q>Jewish Thought,</q> but which the
                        clustering process grouped into a single coherent category. From a
                        computational perspective, this suggests that the boundary between these two
                        designations may be less rigid than traditionally assumed.</p>
                    <p>A related cluster contains just three texts, <title rend="italic">Sefer
                            Mitzvot Gadol</title>, <hi rend="italic">Kol Bo</hi>, and <title rend="italic">Sefer haYira</title>, and also appears identically in both
                        clustering outcomes. Conventionally, these works are classified as either
                        halakhic (<title rend="italic">Sefer Mitzvot Gadol</title>, <title rend="italic">Kol Bo</title>) or ethical (<title rend="italic">Sefer
                            haYira</title>). In the meta-clustering, they show partial overlap with
                        both the <q>Talmud/Halakha</q> and <q>Philosophy</q> clusters, while in the
                        distance-based clustering, they are positioned closer to the broader
                            <q>Philosophy</q> group. Nonetheless, these three works demonstrate a
                        consistent stylistic affinity with one another that sets them apart from
                        their neighboring clusters. Their internal cohesion was strong enough for
                        both clustering methods to isolate them as a distinct group. For the
                        purposes of this study, this cluster is labeled <q>Halakha–Philosophy
                            Mix,</q> reflecting the dual influence of legal and
                        ethical-philosophical traditions within these texts.</p>
                    <p>A group of works broadly categorized as <q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q> appears in
                        both clustering outcomes, though with minor internal differences. The
                        overall cluster consists of ten texts that are either part of the biblical
                        canon or imitate its style. Both clustering methods separate the group into
                        two smaller subclusters but do so in different ways.</p>
                    <p>In the distance-based clustering, three works, <hi rend="italic">Sefer
                            Makkabim I</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Sefer Makkabim II</hi>, and the
                        midrashic <hi rend="italic">Sefer haYashar</hi>, are set apart as a
                        stylistically coherent subgroup. These texts of different backgrounds
                        imitate the language and structure of the biblical narrative, marking them
                        as <q>pseudo-biblical</q> compositions. In contrast, the meta-clustering
                        approach isolates three canonical books, <hi rend="italic">Leviticus</hi>,
                            <hi rend="italic">Deuteronomy</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Isaiah</hi>,
                        as a separate cluster, while grouping <hi rend="italic">Genesis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Joshua</hi> together with pseudo-biblical texts. </p>
                    <p>Both clustering approaches yield results that are interpretable: Either the
                        canonical books (with the exception of <hi rend="italic">Genesis</hi> and
                            <hi rend="italic">Joshua</hi>) form a separate group, or the
                        pseudo-biblical works of later origin cluster together. The placement of <hi rend="italic">Genesis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Joshua</hi> alongside
                        biblical imitations reflects their influence as stylistic models, while the
                        grouping of later pseudo-biblical compositions underscores their shared
                        narrative form. Although it is difficult to determine exactly which features
                        led to the separation in each case, the resulting groupings align well with
                        known patterns and raise no unexpected contradictions.</p>
                    <p>The <q>Liturgy</q> cluster is likewise identical in both clustering outcomes
                        and forms a cohesive group overall. Within the cluster, however, the
                        visualizations reveal two internally distinct subgroups. One consists of the
                        prayer books — texts labeled as <hi rend="italic">Siddur</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Machzor</hi> — while the other includes works
                        traditionally classified as <q>Second Temple.</q> Although these two
                        subgroups originate from different historical contexts and were composed for
                        different purposes, their proximity in the embedding space suggests a level
                        of formal or discursive similarity. The transformer-based model recognizes
                        consistent textual features across both types — perhaps in terms of
                        formulaic structure, elevated diction, or liturgical framing — which brings
                        them into alignment despite their thematic and functional differences. The
                        clustering thus reflects both their shared stylistic core and their internal
                        differentiation.</p>
                    <p>The final cluster, labeled <q>Halakha,</q> is the most internally unified
                        group in the dataset and appears identically in both clustering outcomes.
                        The distinctive linguistic and structural features characteristic of
                        talmudic-halakhic discourse set them apart from all other works included in
                        the study. Their strong affiliation, detected across both the co-occurrence
                        and distance-based analyses, reflects and reinforces traditional genre
                        attributions. The halakhic texts form a vector-space signature, further
                        validating the clustering approach used in this study.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4.4. Notable Observations and Interpretive Implications</head>
                    <p>Atypical placements within the clustering process can offer valuable entry
                        points for deeper textual analysis. Whether through unexpected affinities or
                        hybrid textual profiles, such results highlight irregularities that may hold
                        particular relevance for scholars working on the individual texts. More
                        broadly, the analysis demonstrates that computational clustering can uncover
                        patterns of literary behavior that transcend conventional genre categories,
                        inviting both methodological reflection and new avenues of literary
                        interpretation.</p>
                    <p>One such case is the placement of <hi rend="italic">Midrash Tannaim</hi>.
                        While this work consistently aligns with halakhic texts in the
                        distance-based clustering, the meta-clustering reveals an interesting
                        pattern: across several iterations, <hi rend="italic">Midrash Tannaim</hi>
                        also clustered with liturgical texts. This positioning suggests the presence
                        of stylistic features that link it not only to halakhic discourse but also
                        to formal or structural traits found in liturgical compositions. Given that
                        parts of this work are later reconstructions, the observed behavior may
                        reflect influences from the sources used in this process, offering valuable
                        clues for scholars investigating the text’s editorial history and
                        compositional layers.</p>
                    <p>Another example of interpretive interest is the work <hi rend="italic">Mishle
                            Sendebar</hi>. As a Hebrew version of a widely circulated medieval
                        frame-tale narrative, it exists in multiple cultural and linguistic
                        traditions. <hi rend="italic">Mishle Sendebar</hi> clusters consistently
                        with the <q>Narrative</q> group in both clustering outcomes. The
                        co-occurrence heatmap, however, reveals a weaker secondary affinity with the
                            <q>Philosophy</q> cluster. This outcome reflects a certain stylistic
                        hybridity, likely connected to the text’s Arabic <hi rend="italic">Vorlage</hi>.</p>
                    <p>A third case that invites closer attention is the clustering of <hi rend="italic">Petirat Moshe</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Petirat
                            Aharon</hi>. The analysis shows that these texts do not clearly align
                        with the <q>Midrash Aggada</q> cluster, as one might expect based on
                        traditional classification. This outcome reflects recent scholarship that
                        places them in a more narrative framework <ptr target="#fuchs_2024"/>.
                        Rather than forcing a definitive categorization, the embedding-based
                        analysis identifies stylistic affinities with both narrative and midrashic
                        texts. This dual positioning offers a compelling, data-driven starting point
                        for integrating traditional genre assignments with more recent interpretive
                        developments, demonstrating the method’s potential to mediate between
                        competing classifications.</p>
                    <p>The scattering of texts traditionally grouped under <q>Midrash Halakha</q>
                        across several clusters further underscores the model’s sensitivity to
                        internal textual variation. While some of these texts align with the
                            <q>Halakha</q> group, others are distributed across the <q>Narrative</q>
                        and <q>Midrash/Narrative Mix</q> clusters. This dispersion may be partly
                        influenced by technical factors such as text truncation (see <q>5.2.
                            Limitations &amp; Future Work</q>), but in many cases, only detailed
                        case studies will uncover the textual or structural features that shaped
                        these results. Their varied placement should be seen not as anomalies, but
                        as productive starting points for future research.</p>
                    <p>A last pattern to be pointed out is the clustering of texts composed in a
                        pseudo-biblical style from different historical periods. It supports the
                        idea that biblical imitation functions as a stylistic marker independent of
                        historical or canonical context. This reinforces the view that so-called
                            <q>Rewritten Bible</q> traditions can be empirically identified through
                        computational analysis, and that <q>rewriting</q> is best understood as an
                        ongoing literary method rather than a discrete genre category (cf. <ptr target="#zsengeller_2014"/>).</p>
                    <p>This article does not aim to offer a comprehensive interpretation of each
                        individual observation derived from the presented clustering results.
                        Rather, it serves as a proof of concept for embedding-based cluster analysis
                        in the study of Hebrew literature. The findings presented here demonstrate
                        that the method can reveal meaningful textual relationships and
                        genre-blurring tendencies — details that merit closer examination in future
                        research.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5. Discussion</head>
                <div>
                    <head>5.1. Implications</head>
                    <p>One of the challenges in applying embedding-based methods to literary
                        classification is the opacity of machine-generated clusters. Unlike
                        traditional literary categories, which are explicitly defined based on
                        historical, thematic, or formal criteria, computational clusters emerge from
                        statistical patterns in textual features — patterns that remain largely
                        uninterpretable from a data science perspective. Coherent and meaningful
                        clusters emerge, but the model’s rationale for linking specific texts cannot
                        always be fully explained, as it draws on intricate and largely opaque
                        similarity structures in the embedding space.</p>
                    <p>From a humanistic perspective, this ambiguity does not diminish the value of
                        the results but instead offers two distinct paths for further research.
                        First, scholars can attempt to interpret the clusters post hoc, identifying
                        the underlying stylistic, rhetorical, or structural features that justify
                        their formation. For example, what linguistic elements unify <q>Rewritten
                            Bible</q> texts across different historical periods? Second, these
                        clusters can serve as a starting point for broader literary and cultural
                        inquiries. Scholars might, e.g., compare how specific themes, such as the
                        Death of Moses, manifest in texts within the <q>Narrative</q> cluster versus
                        those in the <q>Midrash Aggada</q> cluster. By grounding such studies in
                        empirically derived groupings rather than inherited genre labels, we
                        increase the likelihood of identifying meaningful textual relationships.</p>
                    <p>The results of this study demonstrate that embedding-based cluster analysis
                        is not merely a means of validating existing classifications; it actively
                        challenges and refines them. The clusters identified here do not simply
                        replicate conventional genre labels but instead reveal measurable textual
                        affinities, highlighting both expected relationships and areas where
                        traditional classifications obscure significant textual connections.</p>
                    <p>One of the most striking findings is the emergence of a distinct cluster
                        that, based on its composition, has been retrospectively labeled
                            <q>Narrative.</q> The cluster itself formed automatically; its label was
                        only assigned post-analysis, reinforcing the argument that certain texts
                        traditionally classified as <q>Aggadic Midrash</q> are, in fact, better
                        understood as independent narrative compositions. </p>
                    <p>It should be mentioned that this does not mean narrativity is confined to
                        this cluster. Many texts outside of it, such as those categorized as
                            <q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible,</q>
                        <q>Talmud/Halakha,</q> and <q>Midrash Aggada,</q> contain strong narrative
                        elements yet do not cluster with the <q>Narrative</q> group. The texts in
                        the <q>Narrative</q> cluster are so stylistically dominated by narrative
                        structure that they form a computationally detectable unit, separate from
                        texts that incorporate narrative elements within a broader literary
                        framework. </p>
                    <p>By analyzing texts based on measurable intrinsic similarities rather than
                        inherited classifications, this study reveals new relationships between
                        works that may have been overlooked due to historical misclassifications.
                        Traditional taxonomies have often grouped texts together based on
                        assumptions about their function, theme, or historical context, whereas
                        embedding-based clustering highlights affinities rooted in linguistic form,
                        structural organization, and deeper representational patterns. As a result,
                        certain connections have remained obscured, while other groupings may have
                        been artificially imposed. The findings here demonstrate how computational
                        methods can help correct and refine these historical classifications,
                        allowing us to identify clusters that more accurately reflect textual
                        composition.</p>
                    <p>Importantly, embedding-based clustering does not replace traditional literary
                        scholarship — rather, it enhances it by providing a systematic and empirical
                        basis for text classification. The results confirm that computational
                        methods can reliably distinguish well-defined textual traditions, while also
                        highlighting ambiguous cases that demand further literary and philological
                        analysis. By extending these methods, future research can explore broader
                        questions of intertextuality, manuscript transmission, and literary
                        influence within Hebrew literature.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>5.2. Limitations &amp; Future Work</head>
                    <p>The results of this study provide meaningful insights into the classification
                        of medieval Hebrew texts, although several limitations must be considered
                        when interpreting the findings.</p>
                    <p>First, the textual sources used in this analysis present certain constraints.
                        The corpus consists of online-available versions, which often reflect later
                        textual traditions rather than manuscript-based readings. Manuscript sources
                        are generally preferable, as they preserve earlier textual layers and
                        minimize the influence of editorial reshaping found in printed editions.
                        Future research should aim to work directly with manuscript evidence, which
                        would allow for a more precise understanding of textual features without the
                        influence of later edited text versions. New transcriptions of handwritten
                        Hebrew sources are expected to become available soon through the ERC-funded
                        project MiDRASH (<ref target="https://doi.org/10.3030/101071829">https://doi.org/10.3030/101071829</ref>). Comparative experience with
                        other medieval corpora may also offer useful points of reference (cf. <ptr target="#gueville_2024"/>). The fact that two texts, <hi rend="italic">Petirat Moshe</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Petirat Aharon</hi>, were
                        transcribed from manuscript sources rather than from later recensions had no
                        known impact on the presented results. An additional constraint lies in the
                        fact that, although all texts were cleaned and standardized, the corpus as a
                        whole was not manually checked for editorial inconsistencies.</p>
                    <p>Second, the size of the corpus imposes certain limitations. While 60 texts
                        provide a preliminary overview, they do not allow for fine-grained
                        distinctions between subcategories. This limitation becomes evident in cases
                        such as <hi rend="italic">Tanhuma Buber</hi>, which clustered with
                            <q>Midrash Aggada</q> due to the absence of other texts from the <hi rend="italic">Tanhuma-Yelammedenu</hi> genre in the dataset (cf. <ptr target="#bregman_2003"/>; <ptr target="#nikolsky_2021"/>). Likely, a
                        more extensive dataset would enable clearer distinctions between only
                        loosely related texts or cases like the <q>Halakha/Philosophy Mix</q>
                        micro-cluster. Furthermore, corpus selection was constrained by
                        availability. Texts were chosen not only based on scholarly relevance but
                        also on accessibility, meaning that some works were omitted simply due to a
                        lack of reliable online versions.</p>
                    <p>In addition, the corpus contains a relative imbalance, as the Midrash
                        category is more strongly represented than others. This reflects the central
                        role of the Midrash–narrative distinction in the present study. The results
                        indicate that this imbalance did not distort the clustering: Smaller but
                        more distinct categories, such as <q>Talmud,</q>
                        <q>Liturgy,</q> and <q>Philosophy,</q> still formed stable groups, while the
                            <q>Midrashic–narrative</q> spectrum displayed internal differentiations
                        that align with philological expectations. This suggests that the embeddings
                        captured genuine textual similarities rather than simply reproducing prior
                        group sizes. As a proof of concept, the present study provides a foundation
                        for further research, and its results strongly encourage follow-up studies
                        including broader and more balanced corpora.</p>
                    <p>A further limitation concerns text truncation. To ensure uniformity, all
                        texts were analyzed as 100,000-character samples, always taken from the
                        middle section of each text. On the one hand, this approach provides a
                        consistent basis for comparison; on the other hand, it may have affected the
                        classification of longer texts. For example, the work <hi rend="italic">Sifra</hi> was assigned to the <q>Narrative</q> cluster. It is possible
                        that selecting a different text segment would have resulted in stronger
                        alignment with the <q>Talmud/Halakha</q> group. This suggests that
                        truncation may have influenced the clustering results in some cases. Future
                        studies should explore the impact of different segmentation strategies.</p>
                    <p>Additionally, the dataset includes texts of varying lengths, ranging from
                        28,000 to 100,000 characters. No strong correlation between text length and
                        clustering behavior was observed, but the possibility of length-based biases
                        cannot be entirely ruled out. A more controlled dataset — where text length
                        is systematically balanced — could help determine whether this factor has
                        any impact on clustering results.</p>
                    <p>When interpreting the findings of this study, the potential effect of
                        dimensionality reduction on clustering accuracy must also be taken into
                        account. While the two-step reduction (PCA to 50D, UMAP to 2D) effectively
                        structured the data for insightful preliminary observations, clustering
                        directly in 2D may have discarded some variance. This choice prioritized
                        interpretability and computational feasibility. The results demonstrate that
                        stable, meaningful clusters emerged despite this reduction. Future studies,
                        however, may explore clustering in higher-dimensional spaces (e.g., 10D or
                        20D) to assess whether additional variance improves classification
                        accuracy.</p>
                    <p>Another consideration is the choice of BEREL embeddings. No alternative
                        models were tested for comparison. The decision to use BEREL 2.0 was based
                        on prior research indicating its effectiveness for handling pre-modern
                        Hebrew texts, and the results of this study confirm that it produced
                        meaningful and expected clusters. Future research could still explore
                        whether other transformer-based models, potentially fine-tuned on medieval
                        Hebrew corpora, yield similar or even improved results. Testing multiple
                        embeddings could help determine whether stylistic clustering outcomes are
                        model-dependent or if they remain stable across different representations of
                        textual features.</p>
                    <p>A further methodological limitation concerns the interpretability of
                        embedding-based clustering. Since transformer models encode texts as dense
                        vectors without an explicit decoder, the rationale for grouping particular
                        texts cannot be directly recovered. In this respect, the method applied here
                        produces clusters whose internal logic must be analyzed post hoc through
                        philological and literary analysis, which provides a humanistic framework
                        for interpretation rather than an explanation of the encoding process
                        itself. Future research may seek to complement this approach with more
                        fine-grained examinations on the digital side, for instance, by combining
                        embedding-based clustering with selected stylometric features, or by
                        experimenting with segment-level representations rather than aggregated text
                        embeddings. Such strategies will not render the embedding process
                        transparent, but they may provide additional interpretive traction and help
                        clarify whether the observed affinities hold consistently across different
                        portions of a text.</p>
                    <p>Despite the outlined limitations, the overall clustering patterns align well
                        with expected textual relationships, confirming the robustness of the
                        presented method. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>6. Conclusion</head>
                <p>This study has demonstrated that embedding-based clustering is an effective tool
                    for identifying textual affinities in Hebrew literature. The results confirm
                    that computational methods can both validate traditional classifications and
                    highlight areas where inherited taxonomies require refinement. The emergence of
                    a distinct <q>Narrative</q> cluster supports the argument to reconsider some
                    historically inherited genre labels in medieval Hebrew literature, suggesting
                    that certain texts traditionally categorized as <q>Aggadic Midrash</q> may be
                    more accurately described as independent narrative compositions under
                    contemporary classification frameworks. At the same time, clusters such as
                        <q>Liturgy,</q>
                    <q>Talmud/Halakha,</q> or <q>Bible/Pseudo-Bible</q> proved to be highly stable,
                    reinforcing established textual groupings. Other clusters, such as
                        <q>Midrash/Narrative Mix,</q> exhibit a more fluid internal structure, which
                    provides valuable insights into texts that occupy intermediate positions between
                    literary traditions.</p>
                <p>Beyond its immediate findings, this study demonstrates that computational
                    approaches provide a powerful, data-driven means of identifying textual
                    relationships. Categorization remains an essential scholarly tool — allowing for
                    meaningful comparisons, distinctions, and analyses of parallel developments.
                    Without classification, it would be impossible to trace literary dependencies,
                    influences, and thematic connections across texts. However, within the study of
                    medieval Jewish literature, existing classifications have often lacked
                    precision, relying on overly broad terminology that has not proven analytically
                    useful. Instead of simply redefining literary genres, this study argues that a
                    parallel approach is now possible — one that, in addition to traditional
                    reasoning, empirically derives textual relationships from semantic, structural,
                    and rhetorical patterns. This is a methodological enhancement that has only
                    recently become feasible, as advances in computational analysis allow for
                    objective, data-driven classification systems. </p>
                <p>A valuable outcome of this study is that the clustering methodology and
                    computational pipeline developed here can be easily reapplied to larger and more
                    refined corpora. As more manuscript-based texts become available, the same code
                    and algorithm can be used to test whether the same stable clusters emerge in a
                    more comprehensive dataset. This ensures that the approach remains scalable and
                    adaptable, allowing for continued refinement of textual classifications without
                    requiring significant modifications to the underlying methodology.</p>
                <p>Although these findings are preliminary, they provide a solid foundation for
                    further research. Future studies should expand the dataset, incorporate
                    manuscript-based texts, and refine clustering methodologies. Furthermore, the
                    effectiveness of BEREL 2.0 embeddings in this experiment suggests that additional
                    comparative tests with other models could further enhance the reliability of
                    transformer-based classifications. While immediate follow-up research will
                    likely focus on refining the computational approach, the present study has
                    already yielded meaningful results on the level of literary analysis. The
                    observed cluster structures not only validate the method but also point to
                    interpretive insights that merit deeper engagement within Jewish literary
                    studies. A more detailed investigation into medieval Hebrew narrative literature
                    is already planned as part of the upcoming Digital Humanities postdoctoral
                    project <title rend="quotes">Dynamics in the Polysystem: A Study of Hebrew
                        Narrative Prose and its Changing Status within the Jewish Literary Canon of
                        the Middle Ages,</title> which will be conducted at the University of Haifa
                    from November 2025 onward, funded as a Walter Benjamin Fellowship by the DFG
                    (German Research Association).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="akiva_2013" label="Akiva and Koppel 2013">Akiva, N. and Koppel, M.
                    (2013) <title rend="quotes">A generic unsupervised method for decomposing
                        multi‐author documents</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of the American
                        Society for Information Science and Technology</title>, 64(11), pp.
                    2256-2264. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.22924">https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.22924</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bar-asher_2018" label="Bar-Asher Siegal and Shmidman 2018" sortKey="Barasher">Bar-Asher Siegal, M. and Shmidman, A. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Reconstruction of the Mekhilta Deuteronomy using philological
                        and computational tools</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Ancient
                        Judaism</title>, 9(1), pp. 2-25. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.30965/21967954-00901002">https://doi.org/10.30965/21967954-00901002</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="borner-klein_2004" label="Börner-Klein 2004" sortKey="Bornerkleina">Börner-Klein, D. (2004) <title rend="italic">Pirke de-Rabbi Elieser: Nach der
                        Edition Venedig 1544 unter Berücksichtigung der Edition Warschau
                        1852</title>. Berlin: Walter de Gruyter.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="borner-klein_2010" label="Börner-Klein 2010" sortKey="Bornerkleinb">Börner-Klein, D. (2010) <title rend="quotes">Tell me who I am: reading the
                        Alphabet of Ben Sira</title>, in H. Liss and M. Oeming (eds.) <title rend="italic">Literary Construction of Identity in the Ancient
                    World</title>. Winona Lake, IN, pp. 135-144. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5325/j.ctv1bxh3w5.11">https://doi.org/10.5325/j.ctv1bxh3w5.11</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="borner-klein_2016" label="Börner-Klein 2016" sortKey="Bornerkleinc">Börner-Klein, D. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Yalkut Shimoni Numbers on
                        Proselytes</title>, in C. Cordoni and G. Langer (eds.) <title rend="italic">Let the Wise Listen and Add to Their Learning (Prov 1:5). Festschrift for
                        Günter Stemberger on the Occasion for his 75th Birthday</title>. Berlin,
                    Boston: De Gruyter, pp. 431-444. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110435283-024">https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110435283-024</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bregman_2003" label="Bregman 2003">Bregman, M. (2003) <title rend="italic">The Tanhuma-Yelammedenu Literature: Studies in the Evolution
                        of the Versions</title>. Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chriqui_2022" label="Chriqui and Yahav 2022">Chriqui, A. and Yahav, I.
                    (2022) <title rend="quotes">HeBERT and HebEMO: a Hebrew BERT model and a tool
                        for polarity analysis and emotion recognition</title>, <title rend="italic">INFORMS Journal on Data Science</title>, 1(1), pp. 81-95. Available at:
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1287/ijds.2022.0016">https://doi.org/10.1287/ijds.2022.0016</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dan_1974" label="Dan 1974">Dan, J. (1974) <title rend="italic">Hebrew
                        Story in the Middle Ages [Hebrew]</title>. Jerusalem: Keter.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dershowitz_2015" label="Dershowitz et al. 2015">Dershowitz, I., et al.
                    (2015) <title rend="quotes">Computerized source criticism of biblical
                        texts</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Biblical Literature</title>,
                    134(2), pp. 253-271. Available at: <ref target="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/582808">https://muse.jhu.edu/article/582808</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="devlin_2018" label="Devlin et al. 2018">Devlin, J., et al. (2018)
                        <title rend="quotes">BERT: Pre-training of deep bidirectional transformers
                        for language understanding</title>, <title rend="italic">arXiv
                        preprint</title>, arXiv:1810.04805. Available at: <ref target="https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.04805">https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.04805</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fuchs_2024" label="Fuchs 2024">Fuchs, A. (2024) <title rend="italic">Neither <q>Minor</q> nor <q>Midrash</q> – <q>Medieval Hebrew Bibletales</q> as an alternative to the concept of the <q>Minor Medieval Midrashim</q> [German]</title>. University
                    Library Heidelberg. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.11588/heidok.00035472">https://doi.org/10.11588/heidok.00035472</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gueville_2024" label="Guéville and Wrisley 2024" sortKey="Gueville">Guéville, E. and Wrisley, D.J. (2024) <title rend="quotes">Transcribing
                        medieval manuscripts for machine learning</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Data Mining &amp; Digital Humanities</title>, Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2207.07726">https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2207.07726</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="koppel_2011" label="Koppel et al. 2011">Koppel, M., et al. (2011)
                        <title rend="quotes">Unsupervised decomposition of a document into authorial
                        components</title>, in D. Lin, Y. Matsumoto and R. Mihalcea (eds.) <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 49th Annual Meeting of the Association for
                        Computational Linguistics: Human Language Technologies</title>. Portland,
                    OR: Association for Computational Linguistics, pp. 1356-1364. Available at: <ref target="https://aclanthology.org/P11-1136/">https://aclanthology.org/P11-1136/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nikolsky_2021" label="Nikolsky and Atzman 2021">Nikolsky, R. and
                    Atzmon, A. (2021) <title rend="italic">Studies in the Tanhuma-Yelammedenu
                        Literature</title>. Leiden: Brill.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rosen_2004" label="Rosen and Yassif 2004">Rosen, T. and Yassif, E.
                    (2004) <title rend="quotes">The study of Hebrew literature of the Middle Ages:
                        major trends and goals</title>, in M. Goodman (ed.) <title rend="italic">The
                        Oxford Handbook of Jewish Studies</title>. Oxford: Oxford University Press,
                    pp. 241-294. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199280322.013.0011">https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199280322.013.0011</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="seker_2022" label="Seker et al. 2022">Seker, A., et al. (2022) <title rend="quotes">AlephBERT: language model pre-training and evaluation from
                        sub-word to sentence level</title>, in S. Muresan, P. Nakov and A.
                    Villavicencio (eds.) <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 60th Annual Meeting
                        of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long
                        Papers)</title>. Dublin: Association for Computational Linguistics, pp.
                    46-56. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2022.acl-long.4">https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2022.acl-long.4</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shmidman_2022" label="Shmidman et al. 2022">Shmidman, A., et al.(2022)
                        <title rend="quotes">Introducing BEREL: BERT embeddings for rabbinic-encoded
                        language</title>, <title rend="italic">arXiv preprint</title>,
                    (arXiv:2208.01875). Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2208.01875">https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2208.01875</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tannor_2023" label="Tannor et al. 2023">Tannor, S., et al. (2023)
                        <title rend="quotes">Style classification of rabbinic literature for
                        detection of lost midrash tanhuma material</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Data Mining &amp; Digital Humanities</title>, Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.46298/jdmdh.11375">https://doi.org/10.46298/jdmdh.11375</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="van-der-schans_2020" label="Van der Schans et al. 2020" sortKey="Vandershans">van der Schans, Y., et al. (2020) <title rend="quotes">Clustering biblical texts using re-current neural networks</title>, <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Network Institute Academy Assistants
                        Program 2018/2019</title>. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4003508">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4003508</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="van-hecke_2018" label="Van Hecke 2018" sortKey="Vanheckea">van Hecke,
                    P. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Computational stylometric approach to the Dead
                        Sea Scrolls: towards a new research agenda</title>, <title rend="italic">Dead Sea Discoveries</title>, 25(1), pp. 57-82.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="van-hecke_2021" label="Van Heck and Joode 2021" sortKey="Vanheckeb">Van Hecke, P. and Joode, J.D. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Promises and
                        challenges in designing stylometric analyses for classical Hebrew</title>, in
                    S. Fassberg (ed.) <title rend="italic">Hebrew Texts and Language of the Second
                        Temple Period: Proceedings of an Eighth Symposium on the Hebrew of the Dead
                        Sea Scrolls and Ben Sira</title>. Leiden, Boston: Brill, pp. 349-374.
                    Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1163/9789004447981_021">https://doi.org/10.1163/9789004447981_021</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="van-peursen_2023" label="van Peursen 2023" sortKey="Vanpeursen">van
                    Peursen, W. (2023) <title rend="quotes">Computational Linguistic Analysis of the
                        Biblical Text</title>, in W. A. Ross and E. Robar (eds.) <title rend="italic">Linguistic Theory and the Biblical Text: Semitic Languages and Cultures,
                        Vol. 20</title>. Cambridge: Open Book Publishers, pp. 223-272. Available at:
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.11647/obp.0358.05">https://doi.org/10.11647/obp.0358.05</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="yassif_2009" label="Yassif 2009">Yassif, E. (2009) <title rend="italic">The Hebrew folktale: history, genre, meaning</title>.
                    Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="yassif_2013" label="Yassif 2013">Yassif, E. (2013) <title rend="quotes">The Hebrew story in the Middle Ages: an introduction</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">Jewish Studies Quarterly</title>, 20(1), pp.
                    3-8.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zsengeller_2014" label="Zsengellér 2014" sortKey="Zsengeller">Zsengellér, J. (2014) <title rend="italic">Rewritten Bible after fifty years:
                        texts, terms, or techniques. A last dialogue with Géza Vermès</title>.
                    Leiden, Boston: Brill.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>