<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">The App-Maker Model: An Embodied Expansion of Mobile
                    Cyberinfrastructure</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Brett <dhq:family>Oppegaard</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Hawaii</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>brett.oppegaard@hawaii.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Brett Oppegaard, PhD, an assistant professor at University of Hawaii,
                            studies ubiquitous computing and mobile media. He was the individual
                            recipient of the regional and national 2012 George and Helen Hartzog
                            Award for his research into mobile app development and media delivery
                            systems within the National Park Service as well as the national 2013
                            John Wesley Powell Prize winner for outstanding achievement in the field
                            of historical displays.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Michael <dhq:family>Rabby</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Washington State University Vancouver</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>michael.rabby@wsu.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Dr. Michael Rabby began researching how people talked to each other over
                            e-mail in 1995, and has continued investigating various facets of
                            internet relationships ever since. He was one of the first researchers
                            to study the actual content of e-mail messages, the subject of his
                            Master’s thesis, and to use the Internet as a tool to collect survey
                            data for his PhD. This research path has led him through areas such as
                            mobile apps, online and offline romantic relationships, online
                            relationship maintenance, online impression management and
                            self-presentation, the use of social media by deployed troops, and
                            adoption of tablets for journalism. He currently works in the Creative
                            Media and Culture program at Washington State University Vancouver.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000267</idno>
                <idno type="volume">010</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2016-08-17">17 August 2016</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2018-07-09" who="DD">validation check</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p> With the Maker Movement promoting a refreshing DIY ethic in regard to creation
                    and epistemology, the time might be ripe for scholars to adopt such techniques
                    into their own research, particularly in the subfield of mobile communication
                    studies. One can now relatively easily participate in the building and
                    implementation of a variety of digital products, such as mobile apps, that can
                    then be used to study user experiences through interactions with rhetorical
                    forms, including a variety of types of informatics. Our experiences in several
                    projects that use both large- and small-scale mobile apps offer a critique and
                    lessons learned directly from engaging in this type of field experimentation,
                    including reflections on observations, survey responses, and other types of data
                    collection made possible through this model. Four larger issues are addressed
                    here, about conducting research through making apps, providing potential
                    research paths, opportunities and challenges to consider. Perhaps most
                    importantly, this research approach offers the ability to tailor an instrument
                    specific to research needs and then test that instrument in a natural setting,
                    affording a true sense of how people interact with their environments in real
                    situations and real settings.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>A discusssion of action research approaches in DH.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head>The App-Maker Model: An Embodied Expansion of Mobile Cyberinfrastructure</head>
            <p>Just as a scholar studying music might benefit in various ways from having composed
                and played at least a few tunes, digital humanists might gain broader and deeper
                knowledge about mobile media through the process of building and testing more mobile
                apps. These integrated processes could lead to richer understandings of the
                technical backend of the media ecosystem as well as heightened awareness of
                practical communication issues related to real-world performance and audiences.
                Imagine a photography class taught by a person who has never taken a picture. Or
                think about a painting class led by a person who has never mixed and applied
                different types of pigments to canvas. Or, even more poignantly, ponder a writing
                teacher who might read a lot but has never written. </p>
            <p>Illustrated in those examples, a certain level of expertise clearly seems gained
                through direct perfomative experiences with media communication technologies,
                whether those are expressing audio, visual, or textual messages. If such experiences
                also are valued in scholarly work, mobile media researchers are poised right now to
                transform knowledge about this field. These digital humanists could create new
                research methods through the integration of their everyday practical experiences
                with smartphones, tablet computers, smart watches, etc., and the development of new
                mobile apps that reflect their research interests (not necessarily a third-party
                company’s profit orientation), guided by their robust training in methodologies and
                theoretics as well as their academic ethics. </p>
            <p>Normative rhetoric, observations, surveys, counting users, dollars, interactions,
                etc., has helped to build the field to where it is today. But what’s the next step
                in developing our understandings about mobile media? Could direct participation in
                the development processes open up the scope of what we know as scholars? If we
                hypothesize that digital humanists could benefit from participating more in the
                mobile medium in various ways, through alternative research approaches, several
                critical questions come trailing close behind, such as: What are those ways? What
                are the appropriate participatory roles for scholars? And, what systematic
                methodological standards could be employed in this pursuit? The following piece –
                part critique, part reflections on lessons learned, part argument for more active
                research approaches – intends to prompt such discussions and delve into related
                issues.</p>
            <p>To complicate these associated matters even more, such active research approaches are
                not easy. Digital humanists who single-handedly can write code, mark up data,
                construct databases, design interfaces, write grants, manage projects, and provide
                expert content as well as teach, publish, and serve on numerous university
                committees are rare <ptr target="#reed2014"/>. Consequently, much of the core
                content and future of computing will be multidisciplinary, collaborative, and
                understood through mixed methods <ptr target="#rosenbloom2012"/>. In such a complex
                and fluid research environment, Porsdam <ptr target="#porsdam2013"/> argued, the
                    <quote rend="inline" source="#porsdam2013">read-only</quote> ethos of
                traditional humanities needs to be replaced with a <quote rend="inline"
                    source="#porsdam2013">read/write/rewrite</quote> approach, rooted in making
                and integrating processes of design, which could be framed by a broad Action
                Research ethic. </p>
            <p>Action Research, as a process, typically features a researcher (or research team) who
                works with a group to define a problem, to collect data to determine whether or not
                this is indeed the problem, and then to experiment with potential solutions to the
                problem, creating new knowledge <ptr target="#hughes2008"/>. This insider
                positionality blends <quote rend="inline" source="#burdick2012">the experiential,
                    the social, and the communal,</quote> as described by Burdick, Drucker,
                Lunefeld, Presner, and Schnapp <ptr target="#burdick2012" loc="83"/>. In turn, they
                contended, we are leaving the era of scholarship based upon the individual author’s
                generation of the <quote rend="inline" source="#burdick2012">great book</quote>
                and entering the era of collaborative authoring of the <quote rend="inline"
                    source="#burdick2012">great project.</quote> These projects today often either
                involve mobile technologies in some way or are conceptualized and created through
                the mobile medium, giving this piece its particular arena, as a way to focus our
                exploration in an area. But we also hope this work transcends any particular fields
                or subfields and speaks broadly to the concept of limitations on a researcher’s
                mindset. As part of the increasingly mobile-oriented environment – again, as an
                example – digital humanities scholars can choose to build the cyberinfrastructure
                they want or be inherently constrained by the ideas, policies, tools, and services
                bequeathed to them by non-humanist domains. That is the foundation of the social
                constructivist perspective of this article. That is the position from which we
                launch. That is the ground we all stand upon and share.</p>
            <div>
                <head>Participating allows for more control of the research environment</head>
                <p>This piece argues that by creating our own instrument designs, for our own
                    purposes, and building our research tools specifically for the research we want
                    to do, we can control our scholarly inquiries more efficiently and therefore
                    create more effective studies than otherwise possible through outsider,
                    uninvolved viewpoints. By plunging deeply inside these processes that we are
                    studying (and that inherently shape our studies), we, as researchers, can gain
                    deeper understandings of the phenomena we are investigating. We also can
                    discover new questions that need to be asked in similarly engaged ways. Without
                    an Action Research approach, many of the facets of a situation would be cloaked
                    and inaccessible, in a practical manner, to the outsider, who wouldn’t be able
                    to see them or even perceive they are present. The advantages of outsider
                    research, from our perspective, are many, but they also create distinct
                    constraints and limits on our knowledge. Sometimes, some people need to go past
                    those boundaries and explore new territory in unconventional ways. We can miss a
                    lot of the richness of our processes by not directly participating in them. So
                    we tried Action Research approaches, and we benefitted as researchers. We argue
                    that you, too, could benefit from such research strategies and tactics, if you
                    incorporate those into your studies of the digital humanities in pursuit of
                    methodologically appropriate questions.</p>
                <p>For example, with new technological affordances emerging regularly throughout our
                    modern lives and interactions with various technologies continually increasing,
                    prototyping as a form of inquiry has gained traction in many scholarly contexts.
                    That point especially gains importance when the dizzying speed of information
                    communication technology development rapidly outpaces the academic publishing
                    system. Such hands-on efforts include reexamining the past, such as through
                    Jentery Sayers’ <ptr target="#sayers2015"/> remaking of communication
                    technologies that no longer exist. They include exploring the possibilities of
                    the future, such as through Bolter, Engberg, and MacIntyre’s <ptr
                        target="#bolter2013"/> experimentations with augmented reality. And they
                    include epistemological examinations and critiques of research methodologies,
                    such as Henze, Pielot, Poppinga, Schinke, and Boll’s <ptr target="#henze2011"/>
                    argument that the creation of their mobile app <emph>is</emph> the experiment.
                    Along those lines, this article aims to synthesize the fully engaged ethic of
                    those types of studies and bring them together through a holistic paradigm that
                    values the acts and artistry of <soCalled>making something.</soCalled> We
                    anticipate this approach will become an integral part of the future of research
                    in the digital humanities. From this perspective, we contend, if digital
                    humanists more fully appreciate and value the process of this kind of research
                    approach sooner rather than later, we in turn will more fully understand the
                    products of our research and the ramifications of our scholarship, creating
                    better academic work as well as a platform from which we can explain that value
                    to people with more external resonance.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Acknowledging obstacles, then moving onward</head>
                <p>Lynch <ptr target="#lynch2014"/> identified a variety of the reasons why such
                    work needs to be done and why essential framework-building efforts, like this,
                    have been uncommon in mobile-based digital humanities, including a paucity of
                    readily available resources, expertise, and rewards. For such projects, digital
                    humanists typically need to collaborate across disciplines and with industry
                    practitioners. They also usually need to raise significant external funds.
                    Recognition within current academic systems for collaboration and community
                    engagement can be diffused or even disregarded, particularly when related to
                    tenure and promotion <ptr target="#bartanen2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#cavanagh2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#cheverie2009"/>
                    <ptr target="#harley2007"/>. Most schools grant tenure based in some combination
                    of the <soCalled>Big Three,</soCalled> consisting of research, teaching, and
                    service. Time spent building and maintaining websites, mobile apps, social media
                    channels, databases, and similar artifacts generally does not fit within those
                    goals. </p>
                <p>Takats <ptr target="#takats2013"/>, for example, described the amorphous and
                    shifting opinions of his digital humanities work by senior faculty and
                    administrators throughout his tenure process. The college-level committee
                    decreed that the project management, prototype development, design and coding he
                    conducted for such major public projects as the research tool Zotero, and for
                    activities funded by The National Endowment for the Humanities, Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services, and The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation should be
                    classified as the typically least-valuable of the Big Three, service (a notion
                    later overridden by his dean). In such cases, Lynch <ptr target="#lynch2014"/>
                    argued, digital humanists must persevere, overcome the policy and political
                    issues, and lead this type of cyberinfrastructure development, because they
                    alone can judge the usefulness of technologies in the field and guide their
                    related scholarly innovations.</p>
                <p>Scholars with such a mindset might ponder how so many outside of the academy have
                    realized and reaped rewards in recent years because of the mass societal
                    integration of ubiquitous mobile technologies. That list includes: Corporations,
                    doctors, spy agencies, artists, teenagers, media companies, personal trainers,
                    criminals, lawyers, farmers, game makers, and many others. These rewards range
                    from capitalizing on the novel mobilities that the devices enable to the
                    intimate analytics that they track. Scholars also might question why they aren’t
                    allowed (practically speaking) to join this Maker crowd to experiment with these
                    tools and see what they can do for public good, by creating and implementing new
                    mobile ideas into authentic settings, without lumping that exploration in with
                    other traditional research practices and getting academic credit for only a
                    portion of the work, if any. </p>
                <p><q>Authentic,</q> as a term, has been chosen and will be used in the descriptions
                    in this piece due to its extensive development in the social sciences as a label
                    used to classify perceptions of human experiences. Wang <ptr target="#wang1999"
                    /> traced that term back to verification procedures in museum usage, via
                    Trilling <ptr target="#trilling1972"/>, and MacCannell <ptr
                        target="#maccannell1973"/> began integrating the label into sociological
                    work in tourist settings. Many other scholars have followed that path, including
                    Cohen <ptr target="#cohen1988"/>, Bruner <ptr target="#bruner1989"/>, Hughes
                        <ptr target="#hughes1995"/>, Wang <ptr target="#wang1999"/>, and Gilmore and
                    Pine <ptr target="#gilmore2007"/>. From the social constructivist strain of this
                    perspective, an authentic setting is one within which the participants align
                    their self-reflection with the experience they are having, and consider if it
                    matches their expectations of a sense of realness. They meanwhile feel that they
                    have a self-determined freedom to do what they want, as they would do it, in the
                    situation, while the researcher has been allowed to observe such
                        <soCalled>authentic</soCalled> conduct and record data about it. </p>
                <p>In seeking the <soCalled>real,</soCalled> and conducting research in authentic
                    situations, we wanted to open this approach up for deeper discussion. This
                    article, reflecting upon such sentiments and contexts, therefore describes a
                    sample of our recent project-based experiences in mobile app development for the
                    digital humanities, infusing ideas from the Maker Movement, and driven by an
                    Action Research ethic. Such reflection, as a core cycle of Action Research,
                    intends to illuminate, from an insider’s perspective, some of the key issues
                    that arise during these kinds of participatory scholarly projects. This piece
                    also identifies affordances and constraints, in terms of related opportunities
                    and obstacles, of the app-maker approach, in an effort to move these ideas past
                    the inertia phase and to propel them into a problem-solving phase beneficial to
                    other researchers encountering the same, or similar, difficulties. </p>
                <p>In this vein, a critique of the situation, through our perspective, is intended
                    to initiate these important conversations. The lessons-learned portion of this
                    piece, though, also is intended to connect the criticism to real-world examples
                    and help to carry scholarship over the pervasive gap separating practice and
                    research, a daunting leap but one that is seemingly surmountable. Therefore,
                    after exploring the potential of Action Research as well as the possibilities of
                    research in the wild, we will share some of the experiences we have had in
                    conducting a systematic program of inquiry that involved building several mobile
                    apps for research purposes. Four important concerns and challenges merited
                    consideration here: 1) App building requires broad expertise and extensive
                    resources, infrastructure needs not to be taken lightly, 2) Audience
                    authenticity creates some issues but solves others, 3) Action Research is not a
                    scholarly magic bullet, and entails a certain amount of risk, from a variety of
                    fronts, and 4) New ways of data collection could help to evolve the type of data
                    researchers can collect, as part of an expansive approach to research fusing
                    technological advances and the ideals of the Maker Movement.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Making as a research approach</head>
                <p>The larger Maker Movement encompasses the cultural and technological factors that
                    have aligned to entice people into active participation and manipulation of the
                    objects of the world, both physical and digital. A smattering of researchers
                    have adopted this do-it-yourself ethic in mobile contexts, too, as some of these
                    scholars have experimented extensively with what could be considered Maker
                    methodologies, such as Action Research, demonstrating promising and novel
                    results that deserve more documentation and further consideration.</p>
                <p>With the introduction of <title rend="italic">Make</title> magazine in 2005, the
                    Maker Faire concept in 2006, and the opening of the Apple App Store in 2008, the
                    Maker Movement not only broadly made connections – from John Dewey’s
                    progressivism to Seymour Papert’s constructionism, as Resnick and Rosenbaum <ptr
                        target="#resnick2013"/> noted – but also brought together all of the
                    learning-by-doing advocates in-between. The Maker Movement spread deep into the
                    computing industry’s cultural foundations, reminiscent of when old-school
                    hackers experimented with the possibilities of new media forms through the
                    process of building them and playing around with them, just to see what was
                    possible. Through the creation and improvement of those formative methodologies
                    over multiple iterations, makers showed the development of new knowledge through
                    the created objects, shared via public demonstrations. They also created
                    knowledge through the discussions about their exploratory activities, as acts of
                    both learning and teaching in a world yearning for new ways to account for – and
                    adapt to – the perpetual uncertainty and rapid change happening across
                    industries, cultures, and societies <ptr target="#hayes2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#dougherty2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#resnick2013"/>.</p>
                <p>In mobile media and communication research, from the late 1970s through the
                    1980s, many early ideas were born out of abstractions, through theorizing in
                    environment-independent settings. Those initial studies included a mass of
                    normative writings about conceptual frameworks. Mobile telephony in the early
                    1990s, when cell phones became more accessible and widespread, then generated
                    another wave of interest and methodologies. That period included the rise of the
                    highly controlled laboratory experiments, which tested specific stimuli and
                    behaviors in artificial settings. Many still employ this laboratory approach
                    (e.g., <ptr target="#kjeldskov2012"/> and <ptr target="#jones2013"/>). </p>
                <p>Yet as mobile research grew and expanded, particularly in the smartphone era, it
                    began to raise other kinds of questions. New paths of inquiry have appeared,
                    diverging, and spreading fast, with many of those related to the wide social
                    implications of mobilities and ubiquitous computing (e.g., <ptr
                        target="#desouza2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#frith2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#jones2013"/>). As different questions have emerged, scholars have
                    begun to also examine the possibilities that mobile technologies might afford
                    for distinct, efficient, and efficacious digital humanities methodologies (<ptr
                        target="#büscher2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#dandrea2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#fincham2010"/>
                    <ptr target="#merriman2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#sheller2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#svensson2015"/>.</p>
                <p>Of particular interest has been the potential for mobile technologies to connect
                    to the holy grail of methodological pursuits, to develop a reliable measure of
                    the events occurring in the stream of consciousness over time <ptr
                        target="#csikszentmihalyi1978"/>
                    <ptr target="#csikszentmihalyi1988"/>
                    <ptr target="#hektner2007" loc="6"/>
                    <ptr target="#karnowski2013"/>. Much research still relies on survey measures,
                    rather than direct, in-situ observation and accounting of a rich spectrum of
                    related activities. In the realm of user-experience studies, for example,
                    research so far heavily relies upon survey questionnaires. Yet with the sensors
                    and relatively unobtrusive data collection abilities of smartphones and other
                    types of high-tech trackers, users now also can be observed – in a triangulated
                    manner – having their behaviors documented in great detail across time and
                    space, and even be surveyed while in the moment, as experiences shift, rather
                    than in summary, at the end of a multifaceted activity <ptr
                        target="#bouwman2013"/>. In turn, sampling data from mobile experiences,
                    within the <soCalled>earthy</soCalled> environment in which they happen, allows
                    researchers to avoid the inherent limitations of methodologies that rely solely
                    on memory performance or reconstructions of respondent behavior, through
                    reflective thoughts and attempts at recollection <ptr target="#karnowski2013"/>.
                    So why aren’t more researchers instinctively jumping into this Maker fray to
                    find out what they can do in it?</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Into <soCalled>the wild</soCalled></head>
                <p>As a quick historical summary of the issues involved, Kjeldskov and Graham <ptr
                        target="#kjeldskov2003"/> decided – well before the iPhone, and the mass
                    rise of smartphones in society – that mobile human-computer interaction needed
                    to have a methodological snapshot taken of it. This would help identify
                    shortcomings and to propose opportunities for future research. Inspired by
                    similar work in Information Systems, they analyzed more than 100 human-computer
                    interaction (HCI) publications. Among the methodological trends noted were
                    infrequent study in natural settings, including Action Research, case studies,
                    and field studies, which was perceived at the time as a lack of attention to
                    both the design and the use of the mobile systems. </p>
                <p>Mobile interaction design in the early 2000s, in turn, was dominated by
                    trial-and-error evaluations in laboratories. These studies usually segregated
                    into two distinct camps: those who studied people, and those who studied
                    systems. In retrospect, Kjeldskov and Graham warned of three prevalent
                    assumptions of the field at that time: 1) We already know what to build, 2)
                    Context is not important, and 3) Methodology matters very little. Having
                    assumptions, such as already knowing the problem to solve, made it difficult to
                    put those ideas aside and identify more fundamental challenges at play. A lack
                    of a focus on methodology influenced the results subsequently produced <ptr
                        target="#kjeldskov2012"/>. That issue led to a diffusive research agenda
                    shared in some streams by relatively small factions but generally without broad
                    consensus on approaches to addressing the major issues of the field <ptr
                        target="#büscher2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#dandrea2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#fincham2010"/>
                    <ptr target="#merriman2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#sheller2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#svensson2015"/>.</p>
                <p>The evolution of HCI methodologies then was compared longitudinally – over a
                    seven-year span – by Kjeldskov and Paay <ptr target="#kjeldskov2012"/>, who
                    found much more collaboration existing between the original group of
                    researchers, primarily in engineering and computer science, and the next wave,
                    which included the social sciences, the humanities, and the arts. The first
                    group, in general, had created the technological possibilities with mobile. The
                    next wave brought with it new ideas about the problem space, the importance and
                    role of context, and the impact and critical nature of methodology. The nearly
                    complete absence of Action Research in the field in the early 2000s, they
                    argued, pointed to both the lack of an established body of knowledge within the
                    discipline and the wariness of failure, in an era when experimentation was
                    expensive and time consuming.</p>
                <p>As Kuutti and Bannon <ptr target="#kuutti2014"/> described, HCI has expanded its
                    scope and eclecticism in recent years. As part of that growth, it has developed
                    a <soCalled>practice</soCalled> paradigm to accompany its more traditional
                        <soCalled>interaction</soCalled> paradigm. When focused on interaction,
                    researchers tend to study the human-machine dyadic relationship in ahistorical
                    situations, often within a highly controlled lab setting and involving
                    predetermined experimental tasks. The practice paradigm has a more long-term
                    perspective, examining both historical processes and performances, and studying
                    actions over the full length of their temporal trajectory. These studies are
                    situated in specific time and space, and they are dependent on their
                    surroundings and cultural context. </p>
                <p>In short, the practice paradigm considers practices as the origin of the social
                    (rather than in the mind, in discourses, or in interactions). Those practices
                    consist of routines that interweave any number of interconnected and inseparable
                    elements, both physical and mental, affected by the material environment,
                    artifacts and their uses, contexts, human capabilities, affinities and
                    motivations. From the practice paradigm, practices are the minimal units of
                    analysis, at the nexus of essential and interesting social issues, accessible
                    for study in natural and authentic ways. So while the interaction paradigm has
                    been helpful in numerous cases, for many years, it also has created blind spots
                    in the field that the practice paradigm – as developed through approaches like
                    the app-maker model – could help to reveal in new and valuable ways.</p>
                <p>Because so many of our technologies have been embedded in our everyday lives,
                    Crabtree, Chamberlain, et al. <ptr target="#crabtree2013"/> contended that
                    researchers should seek to understand and shape new interventions <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#crabtree2013">in the wild.</quote> Those include
                    the novel technologies developed to augment people, places, and settings without
                    designing them for specific user needs but also new technological possibilities
                    that could change or even disrupt behaviors. As the costs of mobile app
                    experimentations, though, have diminished in recent years, and while the body of
                    knowledge in the field and interest about in-situ experimentation appears to
                    have grown, the amount of mobile-related Action Research projects has not
                    suddenly increased. As Crabtree, Chamberlain, et al. <ptr target="#crabtree2013"
                    /> document, scholarly literature has emerged that shows in-situ user
                    experiences reporting different findings than what was predicted for them in
                    laboratory settings. In other words, what participants tend to do in controlled
                    settings, under instruction and regiment, can be dramatically different from
                    what they might do, under their own volition, in an authentic situation. A
                    growing realization of such disconnect suggests that researchers need to develop
                    more paths that are reflexive and focused upon experiences as well as creative –
                    and often serendipitous – inquiries <ptr target="#adams2013"/>. Action Research,
                    in its various forms, has been developing as an approach for decades and
                    provides opportunities to study practices in authentic settings, which could
                    guide researchers to venture into <soCalled>the wild.</soCalled></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Action Research as a base</head>
                <p>Unlike in the early days of mobile research, scholars in the field today no
                    longer have to lock themselves into the stereotype of wearing white lab coats,
                    carrying around clipboards and staring at people through one-way glass. They do
                    not necessarily have to remain pure spectators, completely detached from their
                    surroundings, and seeking <soCalled>Truth,</soCalled> as an isolated Baconesque
                    figure. Instead, through Action Research methodologies, they can bridge the gap
                    between scholars/science and industry/practice in more directly involved ways
                        <ptr target="#herr2005"/>. Action Research can be known by many other
                    labels, including participatory action research, practitioner research, action
                    science, collaborative action research, cooperative inquiry, educative research,
                    appreciative inquiry, emancipatory praxis, teacher research, design science,
                    design research, design experiments, design studies, development research,
                    developmental research, and formative research <ptr target="#dbrc2003"/>
                    <ptr target="#herr2005"/>. But the basic idea is the same: get inside the
                    system, and study it from that viewpoint.</p>
                <p>According to Archer <ptr target="#archer1995" loc="11"/>, such an inquiry simply
                    for <quote rend="inline" source="#archer1995">the purposes of,</quote> and
                    having underpinned a particular practitioner activity, should not necessarily
                    earn the label <q>research.</q> He stated that the cases that legitimately
                    warrant the <q>research</q> designation generally come from research activity
                    carried out through the <quote rend="inline" source="#archer1995">medium of
                        practitioner,</quote> in which the best way to shed light on <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#archer1995">a proposition, a principle, a material,
                        a process, or a function is to attempt to construct something, or to enact
                        something, calculated to explore, embody or test it</quote> and generate
                    communicable knowledge. These tests tend to generate spirals of action, starting
                    with planning and implementation, followed by observations of the effects and
                    then a reflection as a basis for more planning, action, observation and so on,
                    in a succession of cycles <ptr target="#kemmis1982"/>. This article, as an
                    illustration of the approach, is part of a reflection stage of our recent Action
                    Research efforts, which will then lead us to further planning, action, and more
                    observation. As part of the Action Research methodological framework, these
                    techniques for inquiry are practical, cyclical, and problem-solving by nature,
                    meant to generate change and improvement at the local level <ptr
                        target="#taylor2006"/>. </p>
                <p>Also embedded within this type of research is the idea that the builders of a
                    system gain knowledge in ways that an observer cannot, as our earlier examples
                    of musicians, painters, and writers illustrated. The relationship between
                    knowledge and practice is complex and nonlinear, and the knowledge needed to
                    clarify practice relates to context and situation <ptr target="#campbell2007"/>.
                    The app-maker approach, posited here – often generating interrelated qualitative
                    and quantitative data – provides a depth-seeking philosophy to gaining
                    understanding about complicated issues that otherwise could be inaccessible to
                    system outsiders. From this perspective, romanticized non-participatory
                        <soCalled>objectivity</soCalled> and personal subjectivity are not
                    polarities but rhetorical constructs, and participation in the research process
                    inherently integrates the researcher <ptr target="#daston2007"/>
                    <ptr target="#douglas2004"/>
                    <ptr target="#kusch2011"/>. </p>
                <p>A key question that emerges in this epistemological process, then, is how openly
                    the researcher’s values are described and debated <ptr target="#douglas2004"/>.
                    An alternative scale of consideration with this type of methodology could be
                    conceptualized as the positionality of the researcher, either as an insider or
                    an outsider. The interpretive perspective, from which Action Research generates,
                    transparently acknowledges the researcher as an insider, as a part of the fabric
                    of the inquiry, and an indivisible element of the environment, within which
                    people, including the researcher, are interacting <ptr target="#mcniff2006"/>. </p>
                <p>Research objectives, of course, should dictate the methodology of a study, and
                    not all research questions warrant the use of Action Research. Various practical
                    challenges also exist with the methodology, and those comprise substantial
                    barriers to even attempting the approach. Action Research, for example, can be
                    relatively more time consuming than some other approaches, and the objectivity
                    of the research perspective can be difficult to maintain when immersed in the
                    environment as a participant and engaged in the project as a stakeholder <ptr
                        target="#kjeldskov2003"/>. Yet interest in Action Research continues to
                    develop in HCI as well as in other fields that could be of interest to digital
                    humanists, as scholars seek to conduct democratic, collaborative, and
                    Maker-oriented research within – not just about – their communities <ptr
                        target="#hayes2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#hayes2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#hayes2014"/>. This piece attempts to transform principles of the
                    Maker Movement, and similar exploratory scientific practices, into a coherent
                    research paradigm, based on the founding idea that first-hand prototyping serves
                    a critical role in the research process in the field of mobile media and should
                    be valued as a legitimate method of scholarly inquiry on its own, without having
                    to employ a Trojan horse of a more traditional methodology, just to gain entry
                    into academic castles.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>A longitudinal look at mobile methodologies</head>
                <p>When Kjeldskov and Paay <ptr target="#kjeldskov2012"/> examined a snapshot of
                    mobile methodologies again, the second literature review – in the same 10
                    outlets – showed a more than quadrupling of the number of publications on the
                    topic. While lab experiments still dominated at 49 percent, field studies grew
                    dramatically, to 35 percent. The purpose of both approaches, most often, was for
                    evaluation. Field studies meanwhile developed into three distinct subcategories
                    of <emph>field ethnography</emph>, <emph>field experiment</emph>, and
                        <emph>field survey</emph>. Normative writings, in turn, nearly disappeared
                    from the field (2 percent). Case studies (6 percent) and Action Research (less
                    than 1 percent) gained little traction. While the expansion of field studies
                    encouraged Kjeldskov and Paay, the often-incomplete images that they created
                    could be misleading without the triangulation of the more comprehensive accounts
                    that case studies and Action Research could provide. </p>
                <p>Around 2010, mobile researchers began to explore the app stores as potential
                    delivery systems for the distribution of research instruments, in the guise of
                    mobile apps, which could be used to conduct large-scale and relatively
                    unobtrusive human subjects studies <ptr target="#henze2012"/>. Just as in
                    traditional studies, researchers develop an apparatus for their study. However,
                    the apparatus in these cases gets embedded into an app, which then is published
                    to the public mobile application market <ptr target="#henze2013"/>. In
                        <soCalled>the wild,</soCalled> researchers can gain insights about how
                    people might fit new systems into their existing practices and contexts of use
                    as well as how people might change their contexts and practices to accommodate
                    or take advantage of new systems <ptr target="#mcmillan2010"/>. As part of a
                    user’s real-life context, such studies ensure a high external validity and allow
                    for findings otherwise impossible to obtain <ptr target="#henze2012"/>.</p>
                <p>Projects by Henze, Pielot, Poppinga, Schinke, and Boll <ptr target="#henze2011"/>
                    are examples of such an app-building approach, in which scholars can relatively
                    easily create and distribute research instruments to the masses through Apple’s
                    App Store and Google’s Android Play market. In their case, the research team
                    produced and distributed five differing mobile apps with various research
                    objectives to observe what would happen. These apps were downloaded more than
                    30,000 times. Some of the apps were successful in gathering many participants
                    and unobtrusively compiling research data quickly and in large quantities. The
                    app Tap It, for example, a simple game of touching rectangles – devised as a way
                    to assess touch performance of users in relation to screen locations and target
                    sizes – gathered 7,000 users, contributing 7 million data points, in just two
                    months. Some of these efforts also definitely did not reach their goals,
                    including one app – called SINLA, an augmented reality viewer of nearby points
                    of interest – that only collected eight samples over the course of a year, a
                    sample the researchers deemed worthless. Therefore, merely creating a research
                    app – even if the same talented people work on it, with the same amount of
                    resources, with the same objectives – does not guarantee the return of a large
                    data set. </p>
                <p>In another public app project, using the App-Maker Model, Henze <ptr
                        target="#henze2012"/> created a simple screen-touching game that allowed him
                    to not only collect basic device details – such as handset type, time zone, and
                    screen resolution – but also to log each touch event, in relation to the
                    position and size of the targets, as a way to determine error rates. In the
                    process, which garnered more than 400,000 downloads, the data also documented a
                    systematic skew to the touch position that could be corrected with additional
                    device calibration. So many factors dictate the app adoption and use, including
                    the marketing of the project, the perceived production value of the app, and the
                    realistic nature of the related activities. </p>
                <p>On the negative side of this approach, Lew, Nguyen, Messing, and Westwood <ptr
                        target="#lew2011"/> contended that the authenticity of the experience
                    significantly affects internal and external validity. If a mobile experiment,
                    for example, lacks ecological realism in any of four dimensions – appearance,
                    content, task, and setting – the study can be compromised, and test subjects
                    could be inadvertently responding to the treatment rather than the controlled
                    research condition. Other significant issues with data collection included the
                    difficulty of complementary observations, in an ethnographic sense, because the
                    use of the devices is tough to monitor, as the movement of the users, and the
                    intimate relationship of the device to the user, makes viewing the screens and
                    interactivity generally impractical <ptr target="#mcmillan2010"/>. Apps also get
                    used in unpredictable ways, such as getting turned on and inadvertently left on,
                    when the user leaves the device behind (giving the false appearance of long
                    use), creating the potential for noise in the data that needs to be filtered
                        <ptr target="#henze2011"/>. With an insider’s positionality, and systematic
                    and thorough accounting of the procedures and data collected, the researchers
                    can have access to more material, in more direct ways, often allowing them to
                    make more informed interpretations of the data generated in the study. The
                    App-Maker Approach might not be a perfect one, and it does include
                    disadvantages. But, it also has advantages as well that should not be
                    discounted.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Our experiences in the field</head>
                <p>After conducting several traditional user studies, through observations and
                    surveys, and building a few functional app prototypes in 2010 at the Fort
                    Vancouver National Historic Site, a National Park Service hub near Portland, OR,
                    we started to build and release to the public early versions of a location-based
                    history-learning smartphone app in the spring of 2011. Eventually, after dozens
                    of iterations, the beta version of the app was released in June 2012 <ptr
                        target="#oppegaard2013"/>. As of this writing, significant work continues on
                    the project, with development of the app planned for as long as resources for it
                    can be gathered and maintained, as well as for an offshoot tablet app. In the
                    meantime, we also created and used in studies several separate mobile apps
                    designed specifically to answer particular research questions. These were mobile
                    apps built for one-time use, at public events, and designed to gather precise
                    data from users, in-situ, about their responses to mobile media within the
                    authentic environment of intended use. For the larger projects, we gathered data
                    from the devices of the users, through the app, but for the one-time apps, to
                    save time, we brought our own devices. The users then simply used the research
                    instrument apps as is, with a consistent experience.</p>
                <p>The first prototype of this one-time model tested social facilitation and user
                    engagement at a community festival in 2012 by providing unique historical
                    background on the festival. This app enabled the delivery of video and audio
                    files as well as easy sharing of that information to users not present at the
                    time of use. The second prototype, in 2013, expanded upon the idea even further
                    by gathering data about user satisfaction. Both prototypes encased all of the
                    research procedures within the app, including the consent letter, the survey,
                    and the acknowledgements, along with the various shared media forms. Later
                    prototypes, employed in 2014 and beyond, generally were modeled after the second
                    version. </p>
                <p>Our hope was that this iterative process would create ever-improving models of
                    mobile apps that could be quickly tailored and deployed to address any research
                    question we had about mobile app use, in context, including investigating issues
                    related to interface design, physical-digital interaction and media-form choice,
                    within the mobile medium. The mobile apps generated a highly detailed log of
                    user behaviors during the tests. Users were given various media forms in
                    randomized scenarios, with randomized ordering of questions. They interacted
                    with the device within the situation, and all of this logged information was
                    stored locally on the device, avoiding complications related to Internet
                    connections and data transfers, or third-party interference (something we
                    learned after the first round of data collection, as we discuss later).
                    Exporting the logs into a data analysis system not only was streamlined and
                    easy, because we designed the app with that transfer in mind, but the
                    information was rich, precise, and responded directly to our predetermined
                    research questions.</p>
                <p>The following remarks therefore primarily relate to the formative experiences we
                    have had during these processes, either in summative composite, or to specific
                    incidents that are identified as such. These reflective comments – as part of a
                    Maker cycle intended to prompt further Action Research – are intended to
                    corroborate, strengthen, and add detailed particulars to the theoretical
                    assertions being made. They also provide an insider’s perspective and could
                    prompt discussions about some of the most significant methodological issues
                    encountered during these Action Research efforts:</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Lessons Learned</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Issue 1: App building requires broad expertise and extensive
                        resources</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Opportunities:</head>
                        <p>Unlike the apocryphal tales of teenagers developing million-dollar apps
                            in an evening hack-a-thon, the thought of building your first mobile app
                            research tool should seem like a daunting task, because it is. Such a
                            project can overwhelm you and your team, as it has ours at times,
                            especially if not managed within the scope of your expertise and
                            resources. The larger projects we mentioned earlier involved multi-year
                            endeavors with dozens of professionals, more than 100 volunteers, and
                            more than $100,000 in grant monies to produce. That said, we also did
                            not need to build such enormous programs to test many of the ideas that
                            we eventually started focusing upon, including most of our recent
                            studies. The bigger projects had numerous and varied goals, including
                            civic engagement, service learning, and even some exploratory
                            meandering. </p>
                        <p>For the most recent studies, though, we simply built spare formulaic apps
                            that had the functions we wanted, without any aesthetic flourishes. We
                            then installed those apps onto a set of identical tablet computers
                            dedicated to this research. That refined approach avoided the
                            complications we have had with the development and installations of the
                            other apps, and various problems with compatibilities to the many
                            different handsets that could be using the apps. The smaller and
                            more-focused apps took roughly a day for a professional coder to
                            complete, and even less in cases in which existing code could be reused
                            in similar ways. So the hack-a-thon approach can be fruitful, as such,
                            if focused. </p>
                        <p>Yet that does not mean these more-limited efforts were cost-free. A full
                            day of paid mid-level programming typically costs about $1,000, and that
                            does not include the pre-planning, post-analysis, or fixing the errors
                            that become apparent during the design process. If the app design is
                            simple enough, and if the scholar has some programming experience, an
                            app of this nature probably could be made in a week or so by hobbyists
                            familiar and comfortable with basic HTML5, CSS 3, and JavaScript. The
                            initial design work of the throw-away app – including how it would
                            function, and precisely what media would be delivered when – was roughly
                            the same amount of work as any other equivalent research design. Instead
                            of printing and handing out surveys, for example, that same data was
                            gathered and delivered digitally through the app. In the past 15 years,
                            collecting survey data online has become the norm, and this merely
                            represents, from our perspective, the next iteration of taking digital
                            data collection into the field. </p>
                        <p>Publishing apps to the App Store or Google Play market requires another
                            level of expertise and more time, but Android APK files (the program
                            installed on the devices) can bypass the markets altogether and be
                            shared directly via email. As an open system, making, testing and
                            distributing via Android can be relatively easy (although it creates
                            different sets of issues related to the multitude of devices that
                            operate on Android OS). Apple has some work-arounds at this point, too,
                            such as <ref target="http://hockeyapp.net/features/">HockeyApp</ref>,
                            which allows non-store distribution. If the goal is to conduct research
                            on specific devices that you can reach via email, rather than a mass
                            market reached through the app markets, then a lot of the hassle of
                            publishing and sharing apps can be avoided simply by focusing on Android
                            development or working through services such as HockeyApp.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Challenges:</head>
                        <p>As digital-media delivery systems become more and more accessible and
                            open to the general public, mobile app development is an example of an
                            activity within a ubiquitous system that many scholars could navigate
                            within and directly participate. While reachable, the bar still remains.
                            Scholars without adequate coding skills and/or resources to hire a
                            programmer could tailor the content of readily available third-party
                            software and test through that system, but then the researcher would
                            have limited access to the data collected and to the controls of the
                            overall app environment, which we consider significant trade-offs.
                            Large-scale public projects, such as Fort Vancouver Mobile (<ref
                                target="http://www.fortvancouvermobile.net"
                                >www.fortvancouvermobile.net</ref>), create several research paths,
                            but they also have significant drawbacks as well, including the exertion
                            of enormous amounts of energy, often without the equivalent academic
                            credit in many institutions, and with continual maintenance concerns.
                            Starting small, with a focused research tool, and taking that mobile app
                            all of the way through the implementation process, before raising
                            ambitions and the stakes in sustainable increments, is the path we
                            recommend as a lesson learned. Building a mobile app also means becoming
                            aware of the many possibilities that mobile technologies offer. Scope
                            creep and feature creep are ever-present. Focus is difficult to
                            maintain, with so many available options, and easily reachable
                            enticements, along the lines of, <q>We can do that, too,</q> which
                            easily can derail original intent or distract from the research purpose
                            and drain resources, of which the needs already are many.</p>
                        <p>This broader challenge was one we could have anticipated, of course.
                            Trial and error remains a common element of research and development
                            procedures, as well as of collecting data in new ways through emerging
                            protocols. But the details of these difficulties were revealed in the
                            discovery process, not in the abstract conversations about what could go
                            wrong. For example, we initially used both mobile phones and tablet
                            computers for our field tests. After finding no significant differences
                            between them in regards to how people reacted to our research app (data
                            from our first collection confirmed this), we used tablet computers
                            exclusively in ensuing field work. The bigger devices were easier for us
                            to track in the field, provided a larger interface for the participants,
                            were not as likely to be pocketed and stolen, and also importantly, were
                            easily accessible to us in terms of equipment with which we had access
                            and were familiar. We encountered a few minor issues regarding the
                            alteration of survey items as we planned the study; rather than having
                            the ability to directly change the items, for example, working through a
                            developer bogged the process a bit. Working with trusted development
                            partners, though, cannot be overstated. We hired and worked with a few
                            different developers before and during this project. The ones who did
                            not deliver sapped our resources – including time, money, and enthusiasm
                            – but the highly valuable people who did seemed to be able to nearly
                            perfectly translate our ideas to the technologies and in the process
                            generate new forms of research instruments.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Issue 2: Audience authenticity exacerbates control issues</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Opportunities:</head>
                        <p>Mobile technologies can gather deep data about a person, doing real
                            tasks, in real situations, in real settings, but that data – even if it
                            is considered <soCalled>authentic</soCalled> – is not complete, and it
                            is not highly controlled. Mobile apps can acquire extremely detailed
                            data from people unobtrusively, in the flow of life, and in situ. With
                            our apps, for example, we have tracked from the exact moment a user
                            opens a program until the user closes it, and everything in-between.
                            These acts included the precise time and location of the person when any
                            sensor, such as a touch of the screen, is triggered. That geospatial
                            context – directly connected to specific interactions and users, in
                            particular places at exact times – offers unprecedented potential for
                            the granularity of data collection and data-point triangulation.</p>
                        <p>That insight is arguably the most meaningful addition to our
                            understandings of the research topic, but problems arise when
                            researchers, including us, begin to parse that data, or combinations of
                            that data, into usable units, in terms of determining exactly what
                            variables are affecting what behaviors. In short, one cannot possibly
                            control for all of the variables in <soCalled>the wild.</soCalled>
                            Action Research with mobile devices, though, can create fascinating
                            forms of self-contained triangulation. The devices gather detailed
                            analytics of use, and then they also can push users into traditional
                            research instruments, with more methodological certainty, such as
                            Likert-like scale surveys, which are geolocated and taken in the context
                            of the other data points. If a researcher observes the test subject
                            performing the tasks with the app and taking the survey, another
                            perspective dynamically is added to the rich mix of app-collected data. </p>
                        <p>We also have found that people generally enjoy participating in research
                            that does not feel like research. We typically have kept our
                            hypermediate interventions, such as pushing a survey to the user, to a
                            minimal time (ideally 5 to 7 minutes). As such, we tend to ask just a
                            few questions at a time, which has reduced the traditional data
                            collection results, in exchange for the instrumental transparency of
                            in-flow data of ordinary use. The trade-off comes in the form of a
                            high-quality sample composed not of a homogeneous group (e.g., students,
                            members of an organization), but of a wide-swath of the surrounding
                            community. Too often, in our opinion, validity gets sacrificed for
                            statistical <soCalled>purity.</soCalled> This App-Maker Model approach
                            allows for both, though the breadth of some statistics is lost in the
                            pursuit of a more-representative sample.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Challenges:</head>
                        <p>An authentic real-world data sample is one drawn from the complexities of
                            humanity in action in authentic settings. Laboratory scientists,
                            reductionists, and those who favor highly controlled experiments, of
                            course, might be troubled by the inherent messiness of this style of
                            data gathering (and have told us so in various formal and informal
                            settings). The App-Maker Model approach means looser levels of control
                            compared to traditional laboratory experiments. In a lab, we can put
                            people into evenly divided groups, in the same environment, and examine
                            their behaviors within a consistent experience. In the field, conditions
                            are harder to manipulate (though our randomized app conditions, more or
                            less, address this), environmental factors such as sunlight, noise, and
                            temperature can impact the results, and the wider swath of humanity
                            studied requires more adept communication skills and responsiveness to
                            the situation than, for example, interactions with homogeneous crowds of
                            college students in a lecture hall. </p>
                        <p>In addition, the mass of data collected by mobile devices could be
                            misleading, or could be misinterpreted, without other methodologies to
                            triangulate and fully comprehend the results. People might not naturally
                            cooperate in pursuing the goals of the research agenda. They might not
                            stay on task. They might act in ways unaccountable to the device, and
                            irrational, such as leaving an app turned on and running, so it appears
                            to be in use, while instead the person has placed the smartphone into a
                            pocket and forgotten about the app. <q>Constant use</q> could be
                            mistaken for neglect. </p>
                        <p>We can anticipate some of these issues, but they also often come in forms
                            we do not expect and don’t discover until in the midst of the situation.
                            To us, those experiences just deepen our understandings of mobile media.
                            For the most part, as an example, we have had pleasant weather during
                            our tests, and everything has proceeded according to plan. On days we
                            didn’t (during a couple of early prototype testing periods), rainy days
                            turned highly organized and resource-intensive testing environments into
                            wastelands of resources. From those failures, we learned to constantly
                            check the weather reports. We also learned how environmental conditions
                            (such as nearly unavoidable screen glare caused by the sun at high noon)
                            significantly could affect use. In another testing situation, we had a
                            train park next to a collection site less than an hour into the event.
                            It proceeded to backfire at irregular intervals for the duration of the
                            data collection. Many people had trouble hearing the multimedia portions
                            of the app (and rated their experiences accordingly). The noise held
                            constant across conditions, and although the raw numbers experienced
                            some differences, the distinctions between groups we investigated likely
                            did not. During another collection, the cold weather impacted people’s
                            abilities to effectively utilize the touch screen (apparently cold
                            fingers do not register on a touch screen well), a problem that
                            potentially could have been mitigated with a stylus, if we had thought
                            to bring one. Ultimately, these observances constitute a real view of
                            the environmental factors that people face in the wild and help remind
                            us to take these things into account in the design process. </p>
                        <p>The last and perhaps most important issue we faced involved connectivity,
                            as most outdoor spaces do not have accessible Wi-Fi. Our field
                            experiments at Yellowstone National Park, for example, have been
                            severely constrained by connectivity issues. During our initial data
                            collection with the one-time-use app, for example, we relied on a cell
                            phone data plan, which became erratic. For ensuing studies, everything
                            was stored on the device, allowing the media to load quickly, and data
                            remained on the local device until we downloaded it to a common file. In
                            studies such as ours (working in a park with less connectivity), this
                            higher level of control allowed for a consistent and expedient
                            experience. Apple has improved its ability to host local apps with the
                            HockeyApp application, but we found the Android APK to have more robust
                            features and less glitches. So we would recommend staying in an Android
                            development environment for initial pilot explorations, at least at this
                            point in history. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Issue 3: Action Research through mobile technologies is not a scholarly
                        magic bullet and entails significant risks</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Opportunities:</head>
                        <p>Conducting Action Research within mobile environments offers solid
                            methodological choices for many situations. The App-Maker Model can
                            uncover and build knowledge that other approaches simply cannot reach.
                            It has been potent, in particular, for our studies of the medium, media
                            forms, interaction design, remediation, and mobile learning. We have
                            used mobile technologies to track behaviors in traditional HCI contexts,
                            such as measuring time on task, in design contexts, such as A/B
                            comparisons of interface features, in learning contexts, such as with
                            error rates, and in broader medium and media studies, such as comparing
                            knowledge transfer from a brochure versus a mobile app, and response to
                            information in video form versus audio-only. Further, we have made new
                            media forms, such as location-oriented videos, and studied how audiences
                            reacted to them. We have explored prompts and triggers for audience
                            interaction, particularly those in which users might be compelled to
                            make and share media. All of those different approaches have been
                            enabled by the opportunities afforded when researchers build their own
                            mobile app instruments, which, in turn, creates some forms of
                            experimental controls.</p>
                        <p>By pioneering in this realm of mobile technologies, and actively
                            participating in its construction, through building in it and seeking
                            out new areas to explore, a researcher can break ground and set the
                            foundation for a field or subfield. Such unexplored territory has
                            significant value, and the findings can feel thrillingly fresh. When we
                            have built mobile apps, and have seen what they can do, we often have
                            small moments in which we truly think we might be the first people on
                            the planet to have encountered a particular scholarly research
                            situation. New mobile affordances and applications emerge continually. </p>
                        <p>Digital humanists have to ask digital-humanist questions in these cases,
                            because no one else is going to do that for us. Generating an original
                            thought about that sort of situation can be an exciting moment, and it
                            happens relatively frequently through this kind of formative research.
                            Those moments, in turn, can open new research paths of all shapes and
                            sizes. As a research engine, this approach can reveal many otherwise
                            obscured issues. Ideas for next steps appear everywhere. Those recurring
                            moments empower and energize, and research feels less like incremental
                            boulder rolling and more like an adventure.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Challenges:</head>
                        <p>Action Research through mobile technologies also can be ineffective and
                            inefficient for some research pursuits. This App-Maker Model approach,
                            by nature, is time consuming and involves laborious cycles of planning,
                            action, reflection, and so on. Combine that pace of research with the
                            tedious nature of app development (and publishing), and some researchers
                            simply might not have the patience or perseverance, or the interest, to
                            see what eventually might come from such long-term efforts. </p>
                        <p>Many other kinds of research methodologies have been developed over
                            decades and proven themselves in specific niches for answering certain
                            kinds of questions about particular kinds of things. They also have
                            developed a methodological certainty that comforts many researchers,
                            administrators, and publishers. Frankly, they are less trouble to use.
                            Action Research, by nature, might be more exploratory and also more
                            unpredictable than other types of methodologies. The App-Maker Model
                            approach also integrates the researcher directly into the research,
                            rather than keeping operations at arm’s length and safe from direct
                            influence by stakeholders’ desires, even subconscious ones. Sometimes,
                            such observational distance helps provide clarity. Likewise, such
                            detachment reveals flaws that otherwise could be missed, especially by
                            researchers invested in the production process.</p>
                        <p>Risks also can lead to failures, sometimes in grand fashion. The research
                            community generally wants new ideas and research paths to emerge.
                            Contradictorily, it often has a difficult time dealing with new
                            paradigms and findings that challenge the status quo, or scholarly
                            traditions, in terms of fitting those into pre-existing conventions and
                            forms. Action Research, for example, has been a widely discussed and
                            supported scholarly approach for decades, yet its messiness and
                            methodological uncertainties keep it on the fringe of the academic
                            publishing world. Work with this approach can be widely unappreciated,
                            or underappreciated, and confusion about its standards and techniques
                            contribute to its outlier status. When people in power do not understand
                            this approach, or dismiss it as unscientific, there are ramifications
                            beyond just social capital. By not following the specific leads of
                            others, down well-trodden methodological paths, action researchers can
                            be ostracized or even punished, especially when issues of promotion and
                            tenure are raised, especially by non-digital-humanists. </p>
                        <p>In our experiences, for example, we have had research grants from the
                            National Endowment for the Humanities indiscriminately classified as
                                <q>service</q> work because they funded these sorts of Action
                            Research initiatives. Besides the various issues related to credit for
                            the work, formative studies in any new field, like this, can get lost in
                            search of landmarks, because of the novelty of the technologies and the
                            inexperience of the test subjects (and researchers) with those
                            technologies. That should not be a surprise or be set up for
                            organizational punishment. This is part of the wayfinding, as getting
                            lost can sometimes lead to interesting, otherwise unknown places. In the
                            meantime, working with technologies that change and rapidly update
                            creates a churning of effort and resources needed just to maintain a
                            place within the research realm. When operating systems are updated,
                            when hardware innovations appear, when societal use patterns
                            dramatically shift as the newness of an idea wears off, action
                            researchers need to remain nimble and ready to adapt. Otherwise, they
                            quickly get left behind, and their work could become irrelevant. Those
                            recurring moments of shifting and reconfiguration can be draining and
                            exhausting.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Issue 4: New ways of data collection help evolve the types of data
                        researchers can collect</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Opportunities:</head>
                        <p>Mobile technologies allow data to be collected in novel ways. During our
                            recent research, we have combined traditional ideas with new mobile
                            techniques, such as inserting survey questions into an app, so that they
                            are interspersed throughout the experience, rather than solely being
                            collected at the end. While the survey itself is standard (e.g., asking
                            for basic demographic information, using Likert-like scaled questions to
                            better understand responses to the mobile intervention), the process is
                            fundamentally changed by the technology’s affordances. For example, the
                            questions can be automatically randomized. This gives each user the
                            items in a different order, helping to eliminate any fatigue effects
                            that the ordering might cause. The data is entered directly into the
                            app, limiting data entry mistakes to the ones created by users, and the
                            app exports the data into a common database form. The surveys also can
                            keep the user from advancing through the app until all of the questions
                            are answered, eliminating missed questions, and preventing users from
                            skipping parts, keeping the survey data complete. In turn, the data can
                            be collected in ways that simply have not been readily available to
                            researchers in the past. For example, as soon as the research app has
                            been opened, if the privacy permissions have been allowed, the test
                            subject will create a complete record of all interactions with the
                            mobile device when using that app, including a GPS trail of where those
                            interactions took place, and a time and date stamp. The richness of such
                            available deep field data is unprecedented.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Challenges:</head>
                        <p>Yet the more data collected from a test subject, the more choices that
                            have to be made about how that data is collected, how that collection
                            process affects the data, and what the data inherently means. In short,
                            the potential of what we can do now dramatically increases the
                            possibilities and therefore exponentially expands the complexity of what
                            can and could be done. We do not know yet, for example, how survey data
                            collected in a mobile fashion, within an app, and as part of a mobile
                            experience, affects the ways in which test subjects answer the questions
                            and approach those surveys. What would the results be if a paper survey
                            was included in the same experience, in place of the mobile survey, and
                            given at the same time? Other data collection techniques are more
                            complicated and need more consideration, whether they are extensions of
                            traditional methods or some sort of new methodology emerging from the
                            primordial technological ooze. In turn, this data resembles discovering
                            a new species of information. We think we know something about it, but
                            we do not know enough to make many assumptions without carefully
                            measuring and tempering our leaps. In the process, we also encounter the
                            risk of becoming too reliant on the data and the machinery and losing
                            mindfulness about what we study and what the data reveals.</p>
                        <p>This freshness of perspective was the most predictable benefit, in our
                            experience. The different types of data allow for new ways to
                            triangulate findings, and provide ways to validate the data analytically
                            beyond statistical <hi rend="italic">p</hi> values. The biggest drawback
                            here goes back to Issue 3; collecting data in a new way does entail risk
                            and doesn’t fit into the prescribed patterns most people are trained to
                            recognize and evaluate in graduate school. Combining a humanistic
                            approach with qualitative and/or quantitative data is historically rare,
                            but scholars are beginning to integrate these approaches more frequently
                                <ptr target="#kinshuk2013"/>
                            <ptr target="#lynch2014"/>
                            <ptr target="#spiro2014"/>. A journal editor, in turn, could face
                            significant challenges finding appropriate reviewers to which such an
                            article can be sent for feedback, and junior faculty, eager to build
                            publishing credentials, hardly can afford additional obstacles in an
                            often highly challenging and ultra-competitive peer-review
                            environment.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Discussion</head>
                <p>Cognition <soCalled>in the wild</soCalled> has been a significant topic for
                    anthropologists since the late 1980s <ptr target="#crabtree2013"/>. Lave and
                    Wenger <ptr target="#lave1991"/> furthermore detailed how new members are
                    brought into knowledge communities, and how those communities both transform and
                    reproduce themselves. That process starts through peripheral participation by
                    the new members, but gradually their involvement usually increases in engagement
                    and complexity the longer they are a part of the community <ptr
                        target="#adams2010"/>. The Maker Movement shares such heritage, as a call
                    for people, including scholars, to return to learning by doing. </p>
                <p>Calls for action at various academic conferences we have attended in recent years
                    regularly have challenged researchers to actively pursue innovative
                    methodologies that reflect the distinct affordances of the mobile systems
                    studied, along with an integrated view of the users of those systems <ptr
                        target="#lew2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#kjeldskov2012b"/>
                    <ptr target="#kjeldskov2012"/>. Action Research approaches, in turn, could be
                    worth more exploration, as long as the opportunities are weighed with the
                    inherent challenges. Instead of waiting for someone else to invent research
                    tools, the way to get started, in summary, is to get started, to try and fail
                    and try again.</p>
                <p>One area not addressed in much depth in the academic literature of this topic,
                    and a primary motivational factor for us to develop our own programs, is the
                    stark reality that digital humanist researchers, whether studying mobile or not,
                    are constrained and contorted by third-party data and third-party systems,
                    created for other purposes (e.g., making profits). Invariably, that subservient
                    dynamic leads to projects getting restricted by the whims, agendas, and
                    benevolence/malfeasance of the developers. Instead of having independent agency
                    and basic control of the core systematic procedures, like through other
                    applications of the scientific method, many digital humanist researchers today
                    have to settle for what they can get in terms of mobile data and trying to make
                    something useful out of it. Sometimes, even under such heavy constraints,
                    significant insights emerge. </p>
                <p>We think there are clear benefits for researchers in the digital humanities to
                    have broader procedural control of their projects, especially in terms of direct
                    involvement in the design, delivery, and data-output decisions. The only way to
                    assure such oversight and jurisdiction in the future, though, is for digital
                    humanists to build these data collection systems and sets of data, under the
                    designs of academic researchers. Instead of data created by for-profit ventures,
                    or even non-profit organizations with alternative goals, the information
                    accumulated in these cases can be exactly what the researchers planned for and
                    needed, governed by established research protocols, and exported into
                    easy-to-process forms, for analysis and interpretation.</p>
                <p>Natural settings, typified by field studies, also have been shown to offer
                    significant potential, but mobile researchers have tended to not do as much work
                        <soCalled>in the wild.</soCalled> Concerns about control issues and
                    methodological certainty hold some people back. The App-Maker Model approach
                    offers an acknowledgment of insider’s positionality and full transparency about
                    the techniques incorporated, including the option to share the specific
                    mobile-app code used to allow for easy replication of studies in different
                    settings. Mobile technologies offer researchers many other new possibilities,
                    too, for better research procedures. Many other professions already are
                    embracing such potential, within their respective fields. In our experience,
                    using mobile devices for research provides a substantial level of control,
                    without the artificiality of a lab experiment. Whether the App-Maker Model
                    approach becomes a primary strategy for the field, or remains as a secondary or
                    tertiary option, some mobile researchers will continue to benefit while others
                    remain on the sidelines, missing their chance to play and explore in this field
                    as it forms.</p>
                <p>From our Action Research paradigm, participating through this App-Maker Model
                    approach was an extremely helpful way for us to transform our understandings of
                    mobile technologies and mobile media from an outsider’s perspective to an
                    insider’s perspective, where we began to understand more completely why people
                    acted in particular ways with their smartphones and tablet computers, often for
                    practical reasons. We did not take this approach as a step toward becoming app
                    developers or to transition into industry profiteers. We did not take this
                    approach as a way to circumvent scholarly traditions and work outside the
                    boundaries of rigorously established and highly valued conventions. We did not
                    take this approach as a way to reap academic rewards. Instead, we thought that
                    we understood mobile technologies and mobile media to a certain extent from
                    observing it but that we might be able to learn more about it by participating
                    in it. We just had no idea how much existed below the surface, until we were
                    under there. </p>
                <p>If such a perspective seems like a common-sense approach – like the sculptor, who
                    works with the clay rather than only looking at the creations of others – then
                    we circle back to the fundamental and underlying question, related to mobile
                    technologies or not: Why aren’t more scholars, especially in the digital
                    humanities, experimenting with these kinds of action-research approaches?
                    Academics working in the digital humanities will never be able to – and
                    shouldn’t aim to – replicate the approaches and perspectives taken by natural
                    scientists studying non-human behavior. Action Research, such as through the
                    App-Maker Model approach, offers legitimate alternatives. But we will only know
                    how valuable and effective these approaches can be (and become) through applying
                    them to a variety of situations and environments and writing about those
                    experiences and responding to the discourse circulating about those efforts.
                    Mobile media and communication research, as illustrated here, might be an ideal
                    field for such innovative approaches, as long as researchers can adequately
                    address and overcome biases and control systems and various other pragmatic
                    obstacles limiting this type of approach and experimentation. Also, they have to
                    be willing to take chances and give it a try.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Appendix</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Screenshots from the mobile apps mentioned in this paper:</head>
                    <p><figure xml:id="figure01">
                            <head>The mobile app on the tablet computer first gathered basic
                                demographics.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                        </figure></p>
                    <p><figure xml:id="figure02">
                            <head>After the audio or video file played, users were offered a photo
                                option.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                        </figure></p>
                    <p/>
                    <p><figure xml:id="figure03">
                            <head>After the photo option was offered, users were asked specific
                                survey questions about their experiences.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                        </figure></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Images showing the research context (Photos courtesy of Michael
                        Rabby)</head>
                    <p><figure xml:id="figure04">
                            <head>A researcher (in the tan vest) talks with test subjects in front
                                of the Old Apple Tree during the initial test in 2012.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpeg"/>
                        </figure></p>
                    <p/>
                    <p><figure xml:id="figure05">
                            <head>The equivalent research context two years later (in 2014), with a
                                research assistant, in khaki shorts and holding one of the tablet
                                computers, standing near a newly erected fence around the
                                tree.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpeg"/>
                        </figure></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="adams2010" label="Adams, Davies, Collins, and Rogers 2010">Adams, A.,
                    Davies, S., Collins, T., and Rogers, Y. (2010). Out there and in here: design
                    for blended scientific inquiry learning. In: <title rend="italic">17th
                        Association for Learning Technology Conference ALT-C 2010</title>, 07–09 Sep
                    2010, Nottingham, UK.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="adams2013" label="Adams, Fitzgerald, and Priestnall 2013">Adams, A.,
                    Fitzgerald, E., and Priestnall, G. (2013) Of catwalk technologies and boundary
                    creatures. ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI), 20,
                    (3).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="archer1995" label="Archer 1995">Archer, B. (1995). The Nature of
                    Research. <title rend="italic">Co-Design Journal, 2</title>(11), 6-13.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bartanen2014" label="Bartanen 2014">Bartanen, K. (2014). Digital
                    Scholarship and the Tenure and Promotion Process. <title rend="italic">The
                        Academic Commons.</title>  Retrieved from<ref
                        target="http://www.academiccommons.org/2014/07/24/digital-scholarship-and-the-tenure-and-promotion-process/"
                        >
                        http://www.academiccommons.org/2014/07/24/digital-scholarship-and-the-tenure-and-promotion-process/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bolter2013" label="Bolter, Engberg, and MacIntyre 2013">Bolter, J. D.,
                    Engberg, M., &amp; MacIntyre, B. (2013). Media studies, mobile augmented
                    reality, and interaction design. <title rend="italic">interactions,
                    20</title>(1), 36-45.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bouwman2013" label="Bouwman, de Reuver, Heerschap, and Verkasalo 2013"
                    >Bouwman, H., de Reuver, M., Heerschap, N., and Verkasalo, H. (2013).
                    Opportunities and problems with automated data collection via smartphones.
                        <title rend="italic">Mobile Media and Communication, 1</title>(1),
                    63-68.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bruner1989" label="Bruner 1989">Bruner, E. M. (1989). Tourism,
                    Creativity, and Authenticity. <title rend="italic">Studies in Symbolic
                        Interaction</title>, 10, 109–114.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burdick2012" label="Burdick et al. 2012">Burdick, A., Drucker, J.,
                    Lunefeld, P., Presner, T., and Schnapp, J.  (2012) <title rend="italic">Digital
                        Humanities</title>. Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="büscher2011" label="Büscher, Urry, and Witchger 2011">Büscher, M.,
                    Urry, J., &amp; Witchger, K. (2011). Introduction: Mobile methods. In M.
                    Büscher, J. Urry, &amp; K. Witchger (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Mobile
                        Methods</title>. New York, NY: Routledge.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="campbell2007" label="Campbell and Groundwater-Smith 2007">Campbell, A.
                    and Groundwater-Smith, S. (2007). <title rend="italic">An ethical approach to
                        practitioner research: Dealing with issues and dilemmas in action
                        research</title>. New York: Routledge.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cavanagh2013" label="Cavanagh 2013">Cavanagh, S. (2013). Living in a
                    Digital World: Rethinking Peer Review, Collaboration, and Open Access. <title
                        rend="italic">ABO: Interactive Journal for Women in the Arts, 1640-1830,
                        2</title>(1), 15. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cheverie2009" label="Cheverie, Boettcher, and Buschman 2009">Cheverie,
                    J. F., Boettcher, J., &amp; Buschman, J. (2009). Digital Scholarship in the
                    University Tenure and Promotion Process: A Report on the Sixth Scholarly
                    Communication Symposium at Georgetown University Library 1. <title rend="italic"
                        >Journal of Scholarly Publishing, 40</title>(3), 219-230.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cohen1988" label="Cohen 1988">Cohen, E. (1988). Authenticity and
                    Commoditization in Tourism. <title rend="italic">Annals of Tourism
                        Research</title>, 15: 371–386.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="crabtree2013" label="Crabtree et al. 2013">Crabtree, A., Chamberlain,
                    A., Grinter, R., Jones, M., Rodden, T. and Rogers, Y. (eds.) (2013) Special
                    issue on <title rend="quotes">The Turn to the Wild</title> with authored
                    introduction, ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction - ToCHI 20(3),
                    13:1-13:4.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="csikszentmihalyi1978" label="Csikszentmihalyi 1978">Csikszentmihalyi,
                    M. (1978). Attention and the holistic approach to behavior. In K. S. Pope and J.
                    L. Singer (Eds.), <title rend="italic">The stream of consciousness</title> (pp.
                    335-358). New York: Plenum.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="csikszentmihalyi1988"
                    label="Csikszentmihalyi and Csikszentmihalyi 1988">Csikszentmihalyi, M., and
                    Csikszentmihalyi, I. (1988). <title rend="italic">Optimal experience:
                        psychological studies of flow in consciousness</title>. Cambridge, England:
                    Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dandrea2011" label="D'Andrea, Ciolfi, and Gray 2011">D'Andrea, A.,
                    Ciolfi, L., &amp; Gray, B. (2011). Methodological challenges and innovations in
                    mobilities research. <title rend="italic">Mobilities, 6</title>(2), 149-160. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="daston2007" label="Daston and Galison 2007">Daston, L., &amp; Galison,
                    P. (2007). <title rend="italic">Objectivity</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="desouza2013" label="de Souza e Silva 2013">de Souza e Silva, A.
                    (2013). Location-aware mobile technologies: Historical, social and spatial
                    approaches. <title rend="italic">Mobile Media and Communication, 1</title>(1),
                    116-121.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dbrc2003" label="Design-Based Research Collective 2003">Design-Based
                    Research Collective (2003). Design-based research: An emerging paradigm for
                    educational inquiry. <title rend="italic">Educational Researcher</title>, 32(1),
                    5-8.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dougherty2012" label="Dougherty 2012">Dougherty, D. (2012). The maker
                    movement. <title rend="italic">Innovations, 7</title>(3), 11-14.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="douglas2004" label="Douglas 2004">Douglas, H. (2004). The irreducible
                    complexity of objectivity. <title rend="italic">Synthese, 138</title>(3), 453 -
                    473. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fincham2010" label="Fincham, McGuiness, and Murray 2010">Fincham, B.,
                    McGuiness, M., &amp; Murray, L. (2010). <title rend="italic">Mobile
                        methodologies</title>. Basingstoke, England: Palgrave Macmillan.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="frith2015" label="Frith 2015">Frith, J. (2015). <title rend="italic"
                        >Smartphones as locative media</title>. Cambridge: Polity Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gilmore2007" label="Gilmore and Pine 2007">Gilmore, J. H., &amp; Pine,
                    B. J. (2007). <title rend="italic">Authenticity: What consumers really
                        want</title>. Boston, MA: Harvard Business Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harley2007" label="Harley et al. 2007">Harley, D., Earl-Novell, S.,
                    Arter, J., Lawrence, S., &amp; King, C. J. (2007). The Influence of Academic
                    Values on Scholarly Publication and Communication Practices. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Journal of Electronic Publishing, 10</hi>(2). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hayes2011" label="Hayes 2011">Hayes, G. R. (2011). The relationship of
                    action research to human-computer interaction. <title rend="italic">ACM
                        Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI), 18</title>(3),
                    15.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hayes2012" label="Hayes 2012">Hayes, G. R. (2012). Taking action in
                    your research. <title rend="italic">interactions, 19</title>(4), 50-53.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hayes2014" label="Hayes 2014">Hayes, G. R. (2014). Knowing by Doing:
                    Action Research as an Approach to HCI. <title rend="italic">Ways of Knowing in
                        HCI</title> (pp. 49-68): Springer.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hektner2007" label="Hektner, Schmidt, and Csikszentmihalyi 2007"
                    >Hektner, J. M., Schmidt, J. A., and Csikszentmihalyi, M. (2007). <title
                        rend="italic">Experience sampling method: Measuring the quality of everyday
                        life</title>. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage Publications.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="henze2012" label="Henze 2012">Henze, N. (2012, May 5-12). <title
                        rend="italic">Hit it!: An apparatus for upscaling mobile HCI
                        studies.</title> Paper presented at the CHI 2012, Austin, TX.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="henze2013" label="Henze and Pielot 2013">Henze, N., and Pielot, M.
                    (2013). App stores: external validity for mobile HCI. <title rend="italic"
                        >interactions, 20</title>(2), 33-38.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="henze2011" label="Henze et al. 2011">Henze, N., Pielot, M., Poppinga,
                    B., Schinke, T., and Boll, S. (2011). My app is an experiment: Experience from
                    user studies in mobile app stores. <title rend="italic">International Journal of
                        Mobile Human Computer Interaction, 3</title>(4), 71-91.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="herr2005" label="Herr and Anderson 2005">Herr, K., and Anderson, G. L.
                    (2005). <title rend="italic">The action research dissertation: A guide for
                        students and faculty</title>. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage Publications,
                    Inc.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hughes1995" label="Hughes 1995">Hughes, G. (1995). Authenticity in
                    Tourism. <title rend="italic">Annals of Tourism Research</title>, 22:
                    181–803.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hughes2008" label="Hughes and Hayhoe 2008">Hughes, M., and Hayhoe, G.
                    (2008). <title rend="italic">A research primer for technical communication:
                        methods, exemplars, and analyses</title>. New York: Lawrence Erlbaum.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jones2013" label="Jones, Karnowski, Ling, and von Pape 2013">Jones,
                    S., Karnowski, V., Ling, R., and von Pape, T. (2013). Welcome to Mobile Media
                    and Communication. <title rend="italic">Mobile Media and Communication,
                        1</title>(1), 3-7.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="karnowski2013" label="Karnowski 2013">Karnowski, V. (2013). Befragung
                    in situ: Die Mobile Experience Sampling Method (MESM) <title rend="italic"
                        >Handbuch standardisierte Erhebungsverfahren in der
                        Kommunikationswissenschaft</title> (pp. 235-247): Springer.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kemmis1982" label="Kemmis 1982">Kemmis, S. (Ed.). (1982). <title
                        rend="italic">The action research planner</title>. Geelong, Victoria,
                    Australia: Deakin University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kinshuk2013" label="Kinshuk, Sampson, and Chen 2013">Kinshuk, H.W. H.,
                    Sampson, D., &amp; Chen, N.S. (2013). Trends in educational technology through
                    the lens of the highly cited articles published in the Journal of Educational
                    Technology and Society. Educational Technology &amp; Society, 16(2),
                    3-20.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kjeldskov2012b" label="Kjeldskov et al. 2012">Kjeldskov, J., Cheverst,
                    K., de Sá, M., Jones, M., and Murray-Smith, R. (2012, Sept. 21-24). Research
                    methods in mobile HCI: Trends and opportunities. Paper presented at the Mobile
                    HCI 2012, San Francisco, CA.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kjeldskov2003" label="Kjeldskov and Graham 2003">Kjeldskov, J., and
                    Graham, C. (2003). A review of mobile HCI research methods. <title rend="italic"
                        >Human-computer interaction with mobile devices and services</title> (pp.
                    317-335). Heidelberg: Springer Berlin.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kjeldskov2012" label="Kjeldskov and Paay 2012">Kjeldskov, J., and
                    Paay, J. (2012, Sept. 21-24). <title rend="italic">A longitudinal review of
                        mobile HCI research methods.</title> Paper presented at the Mobile HCI 2012,
                    San Francisco, CA.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kusch2011" label="Kusch 2011">Kusch, M. (2011). Knowledge and
                    Certainties in the Epistemic State of Nature. <title rend="italic">Episteme,
                        8</title>(1), 6-23. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kuutti2014" label="Kuutti and Bannon 2014">Kuutti, K., and Bannon, L.
                    J. (2014, April 26 - May 1, 2014). <title rend="italic">The turn to practice in
                        HCI: towards a research agenda.</title> Paper presented at the Proceedings
                    of the 32nd annual ACM conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems,
                    Toronto, Canada.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lave1991" label="Lave and Wenger 1991">Lave, J. and Wenger, E. (1991)
                        <title rend="italic">Situated learning. Legitimate peripheral
                        participation</title>, Cambridge: University of Cambridge Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lew2011" label="Lew, Nguyen, Messing, and Westwood 2011">Lew, L.,
                    Nguyen, T., Messing, S., and Westwood, S. (2011, May 7-12). <title rend="italic"
                        >Of course I wouldn't do that in real life: Advancing the arguments for
                        increasing realism in HCI experiments.</title> Paper presented at the CHI
                    2011, Vancouver, BC.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lynch2014" label="Lynch 2014">Lynch, T. J. (2014). Social Networks and
                    Archival Context Project: A Case Study of Emerging Cyberinfrastructure. <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly, 8</title>(3).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="maccannell1973" label="MacCannell 1973">MacCannell, D. (1973). Staged
                    Authenticity: Arrangements of Social Space in Tourist Settings. <title
                        rend="italic">American Journal of Sociology</title> 79, 589–603.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcniff2006" label="McNiff and Whitehead 2006">McNiff, J., and
                    Whitehead, J. (2006). <title rend="italic">All you need to know about action
                        research</title>. Thousand Oaks, CA: SAGE Publications Ltd.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcmillan2010" label="McMillan et al. 2010">McMillan, D., Morrison, A.,
                    Brown, O., Hall, M., and Chalmers, M. (2010). Further into the wild: Running
                    worldwide trials of mobile systems <title rend="italic">Pervasive
                        Computing</title> (pp. 210-227). Heidelberg: Springer Berlin.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="merriman2014" label="Merriman 2014">Merriman, P. (2014). Rethinking
                    mobile methods. <title rend="italic">Mobilities, 9</title>(2), 167-187. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="oppegaard2013" label="Oppegaard and Adeopse 2013">Oppegaard, B., &amp;
                    Adeopse, O. (2013). Mobilizing the past for the present and the future:
                    Design-based research of a model for interactive, informal history lessons.
                        <title rend="italic">Journal of Teaching and Learning with
                        Technology</title> 2(2): 90–113.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="porsdam2013" label="Porsdam 2013">Porsdam, H. (2013). Digital
                    Humanities: On Finding the Proper Balance between Qualitative and Quantitative
                    Ways of Doing Research in the Humanities. <title rend="italic">Digital
                        Humanities Quarterly, 7</title>(3).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="reed2014" label="Reed 2014">Reed, A. (2014). Managing an Established
                    Digital Humanities Project: Principles and Practices from the Twentieth Year of
                    the William Blake Archive. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly,
                        8</title>(1).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="resnick2013" label="Resnick and Rosenbaum 2013">Resnick, M., and
                    Rosenbaum, E. (2013). Designing for tinkerability. In Honey, M., and Kanter, D.
                    (eds.), <title rend="italic">Design, Make, Play: Growing the Next Generation of
                        STEM Innovators</title>, pp. 163-181. Routledge: London.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rosenbloom2012" label="Rosenbloom 2012">Rosenbloom, P. S. (2012).
                    Towards a conceptual framework for the digital humanities. <title rend="italic"
                        >Digital Humanities Quarterly, 6</title>(2).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sayers2015" label="Sayers 2015">Sayers, J. (2015). Prototyping the
                    Past. <title rend="italic">Visual Language, 49</title>(3), Retrieved from <ref
                        target="http://visiblelanguagejournal.com/issue/172/article/1232."
                        >http://visiblelanguagejournal.com/issue/172/article/1232.</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sheller2015" label="Sheller 2015">Sheller, M. (2015). 8 Vital
                    Methodologies. In P. Vannini (Ed.), <title rend="italic">Non-Representational
                        Methodologies: Re-Envisioning Research</title> (pp. 130). New York, NY:
                    Routledge.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="spiro2014" label="Spiro 2014">Spiro, L. <title rend="quotes">Defining
                        Digital Social Sciences</title> (2014) <ref
                        target="http://acrl.ala.org/dh/2014/04/09/defining-digital-social-sciences/"
                        >http://acrl.ala.org/dh/2014/04/09/defining-digital-social-sciences/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="svensson2015" label="Svensson and Goldberg 2015">Svensson, P., &amp;
                    Goldberg, D. T. (2015). <title rend="italic">Between Humanities and the
                        Digital</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="takats2013" label="Takats 2013">Takats, S. (2013). A Digital
                    Humanities Tenure Case, Part 2: Letters and Committees. <ref
                        target="http://quintessenceofham.org/2013/02/07/a-digital-humanities-tenure-case-part-2-letters-and-committees/"
                        >http://quintessenceofham.org/2013/02/07/a-digital-humanities-tenure-case-part-2-letters-and-committees/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taylor2006" label="Taylor, Wilkie, and Baser 2006">Taylor, C., Wilkie,
                    M., and Baser, J. (2006). <title rend="italic">Doing action research: a guide
                        for school support staff</title>. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage Publications
                    Ltd.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="trilling1972" label="Trilling 1972">Trilling, L. (1972). <title
                        rend="italic">Sincerity and Authenticity</title>. London: Oxford University
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wang1999" label="Wang 1999">Wang, N. (1999). Rethinking authenticity
                    in tourism experience. <title rend="italic">Annals of tourism research,
                        26</title>(2), 349-370.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
