<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Investing in Project
               Maintenance: Auditing the Digital Transgender Archive</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Eamon <dhq:family>Schlotterback</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>Northeastern University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>schlotterback.e@northeastern.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Eamon Schlotterback is a doctoral candidate in literature at Northeastern University. She studies life writing, queer and trans literature, and transgender theory. Schlotterback's dissertation project interrogates practices of self-creation in transgender memoir. She is lab coordinator at the Digital Transgender Archive and her writing has appeared in <title rend="italic">Insurrect: Radical Thinking in Early American Studies</title>.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Cailin Flannery <dhq:family>Roles</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>Northeastern University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>roles.c@northeastern.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Cailin Flannery Roles is a doctoral student in the English department at Northeastern university. Their fields of study include global animation and comics, cultural studies, and queer theory. They also conduct research on special projects for the Digital Transgender Archive, and they are Project Coordinator of the Homosaurus. In 2019, they received their MA in English with an emphasis in cultural studies at Kansas State University. Their writing has been published in <title rend="italic">Texas Studies in Literature and Language</title>.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>K.J. <dhq:family>Rawson</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>Northeastern University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>k.rawson@northeastern.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>K.J. Rawson works at the intersections of the Digital Humanities and Rhetoric, LGBTQ+, and Feminist Studies. Focusing on archives as key sites of cultural power, he studies the rhetorical work of queer and transgender archival collections in both brick-and-mortar and digital spaces. He has co-edited special issues of <title rend="italic">Peitho</title> and <title rend="italic">TSQ</title> and co-edited <title rend="italic">Rhetorica in Motion: Feminist Rhetorical Methods and Methodologies</title> (University of Pittsburgh Press, 2010). Rawson’s scholarship has appeared in Archivaria, Enculturation, Peitho, Present Tense, QED, RSQ, TSQ, and several edited collections.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000611</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->1</idno>
            <date when="2022-02-23">23 February 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2022-08-03" who="BRG">added teaser</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>In this case study of the Digital Transgender Archive, <ref
                  target="www.digitaltransgenderarchive.net/"
               >www.digitaltransgenderarchive.net</ref>, the authors discuss the results of a
               yearlong audit of the project. While scholarship in the field has focused on both the
               startup and sustainability stages of DH project lifecycles, far less attention has
               been paid to fostering healthy project growth and self-evaluation during the
               maintenance stage. After discussing the motivations for our audit and the methods we
               employ, this article offers five key observations and summarizes our responses to
               them. Our hope is that other DH project teams will find that some of these
               observations are applicable to their work and will then benefit from the responses we
               developed.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>Discussing motivations for the audit of the Digital Transgender Archive and the methods employed.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            
         <head></head>
         <p>Archival materials related to the experiences of transgender and gender-nonconforming
            people are often difficult to locate due to the relative scarcity of these materials and
            the access barriers presented by brick-and-mortar archives (e.g., geographic, financial,
            environmental, intellectual) <ptr target="#page2017"/> <ptr target="#rawson2009"/>. The global pandemic exacerbated
            such barriers, causing in-person research to be temporarily suspended and, as of this
            writing, continually disrupted. Digital access is therefore more important now than
            ever. </p>
         <p>The Digital Transgender Archive (DTA) is a free online collection of trans-related
            primary source historical materials and information on undigitized archival collections
            held throughout the world. The goal of the project is to leverage an open-access digital
            archive to mitigate barriers to research on transgender and gender-nonconforming
            people. When the DTA moved institutions in mid-2020, we chose this natural lull to
            conduct the project’s first audit. Our aim was to thoroughly examine every aspect of the
            project to identify our strengths and areas for growth while charting a course for
            continued development and vibrancy into the future. In preparation for this audit, we
            searched for published models, examples, or theorizations of auditing a digital project,
            but we found little scholarship to guide our work. To contribute to this area, this
            article presents a project report that shares the findings of our yearlong audit of the
            DTA. We begin with an introduction to the DTA alongside a discussion of existing
            scholarship on Digital Humanities project lifecycles and evaluative procedures. We then
            highlight five key observations that the audit revealed and how we addressed (or plan to
            address) those observations. In using this observation/response structure, we offer
            readers the distilled results of our audit in a format that we hope will be easy to
            apply to other Digital Humanities (DH) projects. </p>
         <p>DH projects generally move through fairly predictable cycles, often including startup,
            dissemination, maintenance, and sustainability (or abandonment) stages. Given that
            cultural and institutional pressures guide digital humanities scholars towards
            innovation <ptr target="#maron2014"/>, it is unsurprising that there is an abundance of
            scholarship, resources, and workshops designed to aid digital humanists at the planning
            and inception stages of a project’s life, leading some to suggest that DH scholars
            <quote rend="inline">specialize in imagining and launching digital projects</quote> <ptr target="#rockwell2014"/>. On the
            opposite end of the project lifecycle are well-known concerns about the problem of
            orphaned projects left to wither on the vine <ptr target="#meneses2019"/> <ptr target="#miller2020"/> <ptr target="#smithies2019"/>. Projects have met more successful ends
            when transitioned into being preserved as digital archives <ptr target="#carlin2018"/>. Of course
            maintaining an ongoing project exists as an alternative to ending or abandoning
            projects. As an archive recording trans histories which remain ongoing and often inaccessible except through the DTA’s interventions, we are committed to maintaining and developing the DTA.</p>
         <p>Like many DH projects, the startup phase of the DTA, from approximately 2013 to 2018,
            was a period of feverish growth. Following a model that will be familiar to readers, the
            DTA is a collaborative online aggregator of historical materials that are contributed by
            a range of cultural heritage institutions. Boosted by the support of a Digital
            Innovation grant from the American Council of Learned Societies, the DTA initially
            launched in January of 2016 while Rawson was a faculty member at the College of the Holy
            Cross. For the next several years, Rawson worked to build the collection with a dynamic
            team of undergraduate students and, when funding allowed, Digital Archivist Nicole
            Tantum. Software developer Steven Anderson, an external consultant funded through small
            internal grants, has also been key to our success as he is responsible for both the
            preliminary development and continued maintenance of the site. During this initial
            growth stage, we focused on deepening our collaborative networks and implementing a
            functional database that would have sufficient resources to attract researchers.</p>
         <p>As we invested more time and resources into the project, our collaborative network
            expanded and the size of our collections grew. As of January 2022, we have 70
            contributors from eight countries (Brazil, Canada, England, Ireland, Norway, Spain,
            South Africa, United States). These collaborators represent a range of cultural
            institutions––from grassroots archives and historical societies to university and public
            libraries––and most are primarily brick-and-mortar organizations. We currently have
            approximately 8,800 items available on our site, a small percentage of which were
            directly donated to the project and are not available for researchers to access in
            physical archives. The project’s primary purpose is to increase the accessibility of trans history. We accomplish this through our centralized database of primary source materials and our efforts to identify and include a wide range of materials fitting under a capacious banner of pre-2000, non-normative gender practices. In other words,
            our collections are not only focused on individuals who identify as transgender;
            instead, we include documentations of any experiences relating to transgressions of
            gender norms (in relation to particular cultural and historical contexts).</p>
         <p>With our expanding collaborations and content, we became increasingly aware of the
            responsibilities involved in maintaining this important resource. We attuned ourselves
            to conversations in DH about orphaned projects and project sustainability, though we
            noted the lack of consensus among digital humanists as to what sustainability means
            exactly <ptr target="#fenlon2020"/>. Within the unique challenges of the digital ecosystem,
            sustainability may involve <quote rend="inline">continuity of funding, data preservation (including choice
            of standards and longevity of data) and the need for flexibility in order to change
            business models,</quote> particularly as digital platforms transform or become obsolete
            <ptr target="#zorich2003"/>. Thus, building a sustainable project can mean maintaining an
            organization or institution with evolving goals beyond the initial project, preserving
            data and metadata internally for continued access and (inter)operability, or
            transferring the project to the community so it can be adapted to stakeholders’ evolving
            needs <ptr target="#edmond2020"/>. Yet, according to <ptr target="#edmond2020"/>,
            sustainable DH projects are often expected to be accessible to users long-term “without
            further requirement of investment or resources from the original funder of the work.”
            This model of sustainability centers around ongoing access without considering growth
            and responsiveness to shifting contexts. As a result, recommendations for stagnating
            long-term projects typically include renewed dissemination efforts and interdepartmental
            collaboration to increase visibility <ptr target="#maron2014"/>.</p>
         <p>While we found these discussions of the startup and sustainability stages of DH project
            lifecycles to be quite helpful, we also observed that the maintenance stage has received
            considerably less attention, perhaps because it is the least glamorous part of any DH
            project. As Ashley Reed notes, there remain many opportunities to discuss how to
            maintain a DH project and keep it healthy and thriving <ptr target="#reed2014"/>. In order to prevent
            project decay, a robust approach to the management and continuation of projects can
            helpfully supplement attention to the startup and sustainability stages. However,
            long-term collaborative projects may not always document or publish the critical
            maintenance work they undertake after the first stage of dissemination. Therefore, we
            find ourselves in agreement with Edin Tabak that DH must better attend to issues of
            project management and, moreover, develop models and principles specifically suited
            toward our field <ptr target="#tabak2017"/>. Attending to these issues is particularly important because DH
            approaches change not only the ways scholars disseminate information, but also the ways
            <quote rend="inline">they work, the tools they build, the disciplines they connect to</quote> <ptr target="#edmond2020"/>.</p>
         <p>With respect to the DTA, as we focused on developing and launching the platform and
            meeting grant deliverables, we had little time to evaluate the project as it emerged.
            Many of the DTA’s features, policies, and internal documents had not been reviewed since
            the first few years of our startup phase. In some cases, policies that had become
            integral to the project over the years had never been formally recorded. The majority of
            the DTA’s materials have been processed by revolving teams of undergraduate students,
            making it difficult to maintain consistent practices. These issues were exacerbated by
            the DTA’s move to Northeastern in fall 2020 and the complexities of working remotely
            during the COVID-19 pandemic, as our previous model for workflow depended on a physical
            lab space in which new team members were trained by veteran ones. Because crucial
            process-based work went undocumented, it also could not be critiqued or modeled by
            community stakeholders or fellow DH practitioners, which is a noted problem in the field
            <ptr target="#edmond2020"/>. Similarly, the movement from a physical lab space to a
            digital environment made processing materials a less collaborative and efficient
            experience, resulting in metadata that required additional review before it could be
            made public and demonstrating why project workflow must be sustainable across changes in
            platform <ptr target="#sheffield2020"/>.</p>
         <p>When Rawson began a new position at Northeastern University (NU) in the fall of 2020,
            the move presented an ideal opportunity to hit pause on expanding the project and
            instead conduct a robust audit in order to adapt to a new institutional environment. The
            audit was also well-timed from a project development standpoint because the DTA had
            settled into collections development without conducting a thorough evaluation of our
            site, our holdings, or our planned growth. In order to move toward future grants and new
            collaborations with purpose and intention, it was important to fully and candidly
            consider where we stand now.</p>
         <p>We understand audits as comprehensive and evaluative analyses of data collected on a
            given project to gauge efficacy. Audits are common across many realms, and can be
            particularly useful for digital humanists seeking to appraise a project’s success and
            plan for future development. In auditing the DTA, we evaluated the site’s goals and the
            degree to which it accomplishes those goals while also developing concrete strategies
            for growth. Most importantly, we sought to ensure the DTA was adequately serving its
            mission of making trans history accessible and identified ways to better serve that
            mission. To conduct the audit, Rawson was able to enlist two NU Ph.D.
            students––co-authors Eamon Schlotterback and Cailin Roles ––who led the audit as part of
            their 10-hour-per-week graduate research assistant positions. In order to
            comprehensively audit the project, we decided to spend the full year on this work (with
            some of our time still focused on small-scale processing and supporting a 3-member team
            of volunteers)<note> As a project executed during a pandemic, our audit of the DTA was a
               completely digital process (in fact, the three of us have still never met together in
               person). Since we were unable even to consider whether it was desirable to establish
               a dedicated lab on the Northeastern campus, we instead built a “digital lab,” both to
               facilitate work and to foster stronger team relationships and communication. We
               worked entirely over digital platforms, including Zoom, Slack, Google Workspace, and
               the DTA website itself.</note>. Our goal was to assess every aspect of the project,
            paying particular attention to scope, accessibility, usability (for researchers inside
            and outside the academy), and outreach (especially social media presence). Because Eamon
            and Cailin were still gaining familiarity with the DTA and were thus uniquely positioned
            to respond to the project from the perspective of a new user, our approach was broadly
            structured to move from the outside in. Therefore, we pursued our audit through the
            following steps: (1) we began with our outward facing presence, including social media,
            static pages on our site, and reviews of the project; (2) we examined other projects and
            targeted areas for feature development; (3) we focused on the database and collection
            scope by evaluating the status of our collaborations, researching new materials from
            existing collaborators, and identifying gaps in our holdings; (4) we closely reviewed
            our metadata and addressed areas of concern; and (5) we concluded by evaluating our
            options for project workflow and lab space on campus.</p>
         <p>Throughout each step of the audit, we also employed a series of checks to ensure that
            the DTA site content and features aligned as much as possible with widely accepted
            standards for accessibility. Specifically, we compared our practices to those
            recommended in the <ref target="https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG21/">Web Content Accessibility
               Guidelines (WCAG) 2.1</ref> and ran the site through accessibility evaluation tools
            such as <ref
               target="https://fae.disability.illinois.edu/anonymous/?Anonymous%20Report=/"
               >Functional Accessibility Evaluator 2.2</ref> and <ref
               target="https://wave.webaim.org/">WAVE Web Accessibility Evaluation Tool</ref>. We
            also reviewed blogs and forums written by and for screen reader users and downloaded an
            open-access screen reader, <ref target="https://www.nvaccess.org/">NV Access</ref>, to
            test the site. We plan to continue running these checks routinely to ensure the DTA site
            is as accessible to as many users as possible, and we encourage others to adopt similar
            practices.</p>
         <p>In publishing our account of the audit and its results, our purpose is twofold: first,
            we want to share specific insights into the state of our project and the results of this
            maintenance audit; and second, we want to offer a model for DH practitioners who are
            performing their own evaluations of their projects or who may want to extrapolate some
            of our results to improve other DH projects. </p></div>
         <div>
         <head> Observation #1: Assessment of Scope</head>
         <p>Since the DTA initially launched in 2016, there have been significant developments in
            the understanding of trans history and the language used to describe gender-nonconforming (GNC) people and practices. With renewed scholarly and public interest in
            trans identities, there has also been an increasing push to digitize more trans-related
            historical materials, in part due to dissatisfaction with the oversaturation of
            materials relating to white trans women. Within this context, we spent a significant
            amount of time during the audit evaluating the DTA’s scope to better adapt to the
            shifting landscape of trans history.</p>
         <p>We were interested in interrogating scope on a number of levels, including: genre of
            materials; dates covered; race and ethnicities represented; trans identities
            represented; and types of experiences documented. Among the elements of scope we
            considered, race and ethnicity were particularly important to us. As VanHaitsma and
            others have observed in reviewing the project, and as Rawson has discussed in interviews
            and his own publications, the DTA’s holdings skew toward white U.S. and Canadian
            subjects <ptr target="#vanhaitsma2019"/> <ptr target="#bergen2016"/> <ptr target="#rawson2018"/>. This trend reflects a larger
            concern regarding the lack of diversity in the digital humanities writ large. Per
            <ptr target="#risam2015"/>, many of the most developed digital humanities projects preserve
            the writings and histories of well-known white men, individuals unlikely to be otherwise
            forgotten. While our materials disrupt that trend by focusing on individuals whose lives
            have been largely relegated to the margins of history, it is also true that white U.S.
            and Canadian trans histories have been better preserved than any others, resulting in
            concerning racial inequities in archival representation.</p>
         <p>As one of extraordinarily few archives focused on trans experiences, it is critical that
            we attend to these issues of impact and access. Researchers interested in trans history
            have had to negotiate a number of systematic challenges — including lack of
            communication across archival institutions and the recent emergence and cultural
            specificity of the term <term>transgender</term> — that make it difficult to
            determine where trans materials are held and what those materials are. Furthermore,
            historical materials depicting people of color who transgress gender norms are even less
            likely to have been preserved or archived. Unless we pay careful attention to these
            issues, it is all too easy for projects like the DTA to unwittingly reproduce a
            narrative of trans history focused on the experiences of white North Americans and
            Europeans.</p>
            <p><ptr target="#vanhaitsma2019"/> further suggests that the DTA's holdings skew toward
            transfeminine-related materials with a proportionally smaller number of transmasculine
            materials. Such inequities in our holdings reveal the complexities of representation in
            a project guided by trans-affirming ethics. As we expand our collection of
            transmasculine objects, we recognize that the differential representations of
            transfeminine and transmasculine subjects is due in part to a visual regime that renders
            trans men <quote rend="inline">invisibilized and ignored</quote> and trans women <quote rend="inline">glamourized and vilified</quote> <ptr target="#green2020"/>.
               More images of transfeminine people can be archived and published in part because
            of how transfeminine people have been spectacularized by a transmisogynist social
            context <ptr target="#green2020"/> <ptr target="#kochrein2020"/> <ptr target="#rodriguez2015"/>. This is also complicated
            by the fact that certain forms of trans visibility often further marginalize trans
            people and lead to transphobic violence, which disproportionately targets trans people
            of color <ptr target="#stanley2017"/> <ptr target="#griffingracy2017"/>. Although part of our audit was to
            identify and fill gaps in our collections, simply adding items to fill a quota was
            insufficient to our aims. The complex histories of racism and transphobia demanded we
            reevaluate the quality of the items we host.</p>
         <p>Before we began working to increase the number of people with marginalized identities
            represented in the DTA, it was necessary to closely examine how and why we choose to
            represent people’s identities overall. Our audit began at the tail end of the summer of
            2020, when the United States was reckoning with its continued history of anti-Blackness
            following the murders of George Floyd and Breonna Taylor, which deeply informed our
            work. The audit became an opportunity to renew our approach to archiving objects
            depicting BIPOC, to learn from Black and anti-racist archival practices, and reconsider
            how we frame historically significant objects depicting racism <ptr target="#antracoli2019"/> <ptr target="#blackwomenssuffrage"/> <ptr target="#brathwaiteshirley2020"/>.
            Over the course of the audit,
            we identified a number of gaps in the content we make available on our site, as well as
            issues with the DTA’s current representation practices, particularly regarding
            marginalized groups we (three white settler academics) are not a part of. For instance,
            the complexities of Two-Spirit identities and their inclusion on the DTA was a recurring
            concern, one we realized could only be addressed through deeper collaborations with
            Two-Spirit groups. Our work to address scope therefore became inseparable from our
            ethical commitments to and work with BIPOC communities.</p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Response: Extending Our Collaborations, Building Our Collections, and Planning for the
            Future</head>
         <p>A central project completed over the course of our audit was our search for potential
            additions to our holdings, both to diversify the scope of the project going forward and
            to ensure that we provide broad access to as many trans-related historical materials as
            possible. We approached this search for materials with two objectives in mind: 1) to
            identify new materials at institutions we have existing relationships with; and 2) to
            locate new institutions and collections for future collaborations.</p>
         <p>Among our partnered institutions’ collections, we found over 300 items that were already
            digitized and could be made available on the DTA, ranging from nineteenth-century
            medical literature to 1960s glamour shots. Of these, we prioritized certain materials
            for immediate processing based on gaps in our current holdings. For instance, materials
            related to incarceration and GNC children became higher priorities, whereas drag show
            programs were less pressing since we already have a preponderance of those items. As we
            filled some of the gaps in our collection, we sought opportunities to not simply add
            items <emph>depicting</emph> marginalized individuals, but to prioritize
            materials in which these subjects speak for themselves. These materials include items
            such as oral histories with trans men and people of color, manifestos written by trans
            women of color, and a collection of web resources related to Two-Spirit communities.</p>
         <p>Our search for new partners was fruitful beyond our aims. At the start of our audit, we
            had 64 contributing partners, but we have since added five more to the DTA site and
            identified an additional 15 that we plan to reach out to in order to form
            collaborations.These new institutions include organizations with significant holdings
            related to transmasculine individuals, Indigenous peoples of New Zealand, and Asian
            Americans. Our goal in collaborating with more archives, especially community- and
            trans- and BIPOC-led archives, is not only to make more items related to trans history
            available online, but also to build mutually beneficial relationships with our partners.
            Another result of these efforts is that we are currently pursuing funding for a
            large-scale project that will allow us to work with our partners to digitize thousands
            of pages of materials related to trans people of color, as well as improve our
            anti-racist description practices through a BIPOC-led steering committee.</p>
         <p> Even six years since it went live, the DTA remains one of extraordinarily few archives
            devoted to trans experiences, and many of our materials are only accessible to the
            public through the DTA. Our position as one of the few freely available archival
            resources on trans people necessitates that we expand our holdings to better represent
            the full spectrum of trans experience and to continually strengthen our commitments to
            ethical representation. Like many long-term DH projects, our work over the years has
            often focused on expanding the quantity of materials rather than quality of
            representation. This is not uncommon — as <ptr target="#risam2018"/> discusses, DH projects
            often <quote rend="inline">[equate] decolonization with the need for diversity in the field,</quote> as if <quote rend="inline">the
            mere addition of ‘diverse’ bodies will transform the practices of digital humanities</quote>
            and the traces of colonialism therein. Instead, as we evaluated the scope of the DTA, we
            also worked to strengthen and extend our relationships with BIPOC-focused initiatives,
            pursue funding for projects to enhance access to trans BIPOC histories, develop
            antiracist description policies, and enact more informed mechanisms of
            representation.</p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Observation #2: Metadata Concerns in Relation to Privacy and Description Policies</head>
         <p>Assessing the DTA’s scope led us to larger questions about the ways we describe
            materials hosted on the site. Since the project’s start, we have attempted to maintain
            consistent descriptive practices by implementing a metadata application profile (MAP), a
            detailed document that outlines requirements and best practices for each metadata
            element (e.g., Title, Subject Coverage, Description). However, over the course of the
            DTA’s history, a number of different people from different backgrounds and levels of
            archival experience have participated in processing materials, which has resulted in
            discrepancies in the metadata for different objects.</p>
         <p>Although DTA materials are discoverable through metadata and the terms used within the
            materials, there were numerous inconsistencies regarding the usage of certain elements
            and descriptive practices for trans identities and practices. For example, the most
            commonly used term in subject coverage was <q>crossdressers,</q> though in many instances the
            materials predated the term and it was unlikely the subjects represented would identify
            with it. This practice was in contrast to our policy, which cautions against assuming
            individuals’ identities without self-acknowledgement. At the same time, this policy was
            more consistently applied in regards to race and ethnicity, which meant that materials
            focused on people of color were too often unmarked in the metadata. As a result, race
            often became hidden or obscured while gender identity was frequently overdetermined.
            Additionally, we noticed that in some cases, our metadata reproduced harmful language
            practices from other institutions and that some items were published with little
            description because team members were unsure how to interpret their content and account
            for their complexity.</p>
            <p>Our <ref target="https://www.digitaltransgenderarchive.net/about/policies">policies</ref> regarding privacy, explicit content, and descriptive practices have always
            been publicly available on the project site, and the DTA has been widely praised for its
            collaborative nature and continued accountability to the community <ptr target="#patterson2019"/> <ptr target="#shepard2020"/> <ptr target="#sabharwal2021"/>.
            In recognizing this strength and the benefits it has
            offered to others, we saw an opportunity to further develop this dimension of the
            project. Simultaneously, as the project has grown and we have received feedback, our
            implementation of our policies has become more complex––for example, determining whether
            exploitative or private materials should be public or how to address harmful
            language––and we wanted to find a way to convey that complexity. In other words, we
            needed to evaluate whether there were any gaps between our stated policies and our
            everyday practices and to consider how we could make our internal processes even more
            transparent for users.</p></div>
         <div>
         <head> Response: Revision of MAP and Policies</head>
         <p>To get a better sense of what MAP and policy changes might be in order, we began by
            evaluating our collections and compiling a list of metadata-related concerns and best
            practices. Aware of our limitations as a U.S.-based team that is predominantly white, we
            researched the policies of a number of BIPOC-led digital archives, DH projects, and
            social justice organizations. In addition, we found Antracoli et al.’s <title rend="italic">Archives for
               Black Lives in Philadelphia: Anti-Racist Description Resources</title> to be a
            particularly helpful resource <ptr target="#antracoli2019"/>.</p>
         <p>In some cases, addressing metadata issues on the DTA required simply correcting typos.
            Other issues necessitated case-by-case analysis and editorial flexibility. For example,
            we reached out to an individual represented in our materials who changed his name to ask
            how we should refer to him when processing materials he created before the name change.
            His answer — that we could either update his name or maintain both names — reflects his personal choice rather than archival best practices..<note> Although name authority records
               often list variations of individuals’ names that they may have been known by or used
               throughout their life, these variations are controlled under a single uniform name
               and only the authorized name is displayed in a record. This subject’s preference to
               maintain both names in a single record defies the logic of a name authority and shows
               how, for some trans people, prior names not should be treated as <q>dead names.</q> </note>
            This example shows why it is important to consider not only whether data practices are
            consistent and (inter)operable but whether they are ethical and what impact they have on
            people. When possible, it is ideal to reach out to individuals represented in the
            collections so that they can determine how they should be described in the metadata.</p>
         <p>We also expanded our project-wide policies to clarify our processes for describing
            gender, race, ethnicity, and other identity markers. Though our metadata typically
            adopts language already used in the materials and language known to be used by the
            individuals represented, we often process items that cannot be neatly categorized, such
            as photographs with no extant context. The decisions we make in describing these items
            may not be immediately clear to visitors of the site, which could make them difficult to
            locate or result in misunderstanding of historical terminology. Therefore, as we
            evaluate ways to best represent individuals’ identities, we also turn a critical eye
            toward harmful language practices in the archival field. We have sought to disrupt
            racist and transphobic materials or descriptions by questioning whether to make
            available compelling but ethically questionable items, adding critical framing to
            descriptions of complicated items, and removing harmful descriptions and metadata
            inherited from contributing institutions. To support our team members in describing
            complex items, we began writing short reference documents that include language and
            framing suggestions as well as contextual information to guide them through the
            difficult and thorny process of respectfully and accurately representing trans and GNC
            subjects. We have also developed content warnings within the Description field for items
            with potentially harmful language and imagery.</p>
         <p>As we resolved specific metadata issues and revised our policies and processing
            workflow, we also began to write a new edition of the DTA MAP that better reflects our
            current descriptive practices. This work includes clarifying how fields like Spatial
            Coverage become searchable so team members can apply it more effectively and updating
            Subject Coverage examples to match the newest version of <ref target="https://homosaurus.org/">Homosaurus</ref>, the LGBTQ+ linked
            data vocabulary we use to supplement the Library of Congress Subject Headings. While in
            the past the MAP has only been available to team members and contributors, we have
            chosen to make the <ref target="https://docs.google.com/document/d/11LNJ0YEsdi-g7EsoVDIdSWeWTJ_Y1vEtILc_mHqCRBo/edit">DTA MAP 3.0</ref> publicly accessible on the project website, both to
            encourage feedback from our stakeholders and to provide a model for other DH projects
            writing or revising their own MAPs.</p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Observation #3: Incomplete Tracking of Project Use and Reception</head>
         <p>In the six years since the DTA went live, the project and items from its collections
            have been taken up by academic researchers, pop culture journalists, intrigued readers,
            documentary filmmakers, and teachers of all kinds. We have taken great joy in seeing how
            the DTA has been utilized and engaged, often posting to our social media channels items
            that refer to the DTA and circulating these items among students working on the project.
            At no point, however, did we formally track such qualitative usage, even though
            measurable evidence of a project’s impact is critical for grant writing efforts.
            Additionally, while the DTA’s mission is to make trans history more accessible to a wide
            public audience, we had no dedicated methods for evaluating users’ experiences in
            accessing our materials.</p>
         <p>Throughout the life of the project, we have relied on Google Analytics to track site
            usage and Google Alerts to keep up-to-date with mentions of the DTA online.<note> Google
               Analytics is often recommended to library, museum, and archives decision makers as a
               tool for measuring and improving users’ experiences <ptr target="#fang2007"/> <ptr target="#breeding2008"/> <ptr target="#turner2010"/>. 
               However, as <ptr target="#galbraith2016"/> has discussed, the fact that
               Google Analytics data <quote rend="inline">belongs to Google and is housed on U.S. servers, where data
               may be subject to the legislation of that country,</quote> raises serious concerns about
               user privacy, particularly for a trans-focused project. As the DTA and its user base
               grows, we find ourselves reevaluating whether Google Analytics fits into our project
               values.</note> While analytics seem reliable, alerts have proven to be quite fallible
            and we often became aware of invaluable references to the DTA long after the fact. Our
            sense of this engagement was impressionistic, favoring the more memorable coverage, and
            we could not report with confidence on trends and patterns in the data. Without a means
            of consistently tracking project use and reception, it became difficult to measure the
            impact of the DTA for funding applications or to prioritize our users’ needs when
            forming new collaborations.</p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Response: Systematic Collection and Summary of Reviews and Usages of the DTA</head>
         <p>We initially considered conducting a typical usability test to better understand the
            project’s uptake and user interactions; however, we quickly recognized that soliciting
            test users during the pandemic would be difficult and potentially unsafe. Tabling the
            usability test for the time being, we decided instead to systematically evaluate usage
            of the project through reviews, discussions, and mentions of the DTA across academic
            databases, institutions’ websites, public forums, and social media platforms. In
            addition to bibliographic information, we tracked articles, chapters, theses and
            dissertations, resource lists, articles on pop culture outlets and non-academic
            websites, and social media posts. We noted what items people were using or responding
            to, paying particular attention to the DTA’s accessibility for young readers and
            individuals unfamiliar with digital archives. We also recorded feedback from formal
            reviews of the DTA, particularly reviewers’ observations regarding ways to expand the
            project’s scope and functionality and the need to clarify some site features.</p>
            <p>Reviews of the DTA and articles highlighting its usage in classrooms by <ptr target="#chatterjee2020"/>, <ptr target="#shepard2020"/>,
               <ptr target="#watson2019"/>, and others allowed us to gain a better
            understanding of the site’s perceived functionality by new users. For example, Nikita
            Shepard’s 2020 write-up on the DTA for <title rend="italic">Reviews in Digital
               Humanities</title> indicated that the function of the Map search tool was unclear, which
            we have attempted to resolve by providing explanatory copy above the tool. Similarly,
            several researchers have reported being unsure why certain <q>outdated</q> terms are used on
            the site or how to effectively search using those terms. Recognizing that the creation
            of metadata is a highly subjective and political act and that trans-related terminology
            is both personal and contextual, we describe individuals’ identities and practices using
            terms provided within the materials, terms known to be used by individuals represented
            in the materials, and, when we have no other information, terms contemporaneous to the
            period or culture. Since this practice influences search results in ways that may not be
            immediately apparent, we developed a front-facing <ref
               target="https://www.digitaltransgenderarchive.net/learn/searchterms">Search Tips
               &amp; Terms page</ref> that explains how we use search terms and suggests terms for
            researchers to consider based on their interests.</p>
         <p>Along with identifying areas for improvement, we learned a great deal about how the DTA
            has been used in academic research. While scholars such as <ptr target="#adler2016"/>, <ptr target="#powell2018"/>, and <ptr target="#alilunas2018"/> 
            analyze our practices to advocate for restorative
            archival projects, others use the DTA’s materials to examine public reception of trans
            historical figures <ptr target="#jackson2020"/> and consider the ways digital platforms permit the
            recirculation of early trans activism <ptr target="#steinbock2019"/>. Through library guides,
            resource lists, and teaching modules, we have also discovered that the DTA is widely
            recommended by teachers at colleges and universities across the United States. To better
            connect with our community members and share the critical resources they have compiled,
            we are now considering ways of highlighting research and teaching tools on our
            website.</p>
         <p>In reviewing uptakes and usages of the DTA, it became clear that the project inspires a
            wealth of valuable engagement that is often overlooked by Google Alerts and other
            automated searches. Bearing this discovery in mind, we now dedicate lab hours at the end
            of each month to actively locate and record engagement to improve our understanding of
            users’ experiences and remain accountable to our communities’ needs. </p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Observation #4: Social Media Underutilized</head>
         <p>Social media offers a useful tool for better connecting with potential users of the DTA,
            particularly those outside of academia. As <ptr target="#ross2012"/> discusses, when adequately
            utilized, social media platforms for DH projects can become spaces for
            <quote rend="inline">self-representation, expression or reflection and more organized forms of collaboration
            and knowledge building.</quote> The DTA maintains three social media accounts––Facebook,
            Twitter, and Instagram. Early in the audit, we determined that our social media posts
            had a few shortcomings: they were inconsistently published, their contents were not
            standardized, they varied in the amount of information provided, and they were not
            always fully accessible. Further, our engagement with our followers was minimal, often
            occurring only through responses to comments rather than proactive communication. It was
            unclear who our audience was or what they sought from the DTA on social media, which
            made it difficult to foster a sense of community on these platforms.</p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Response: Development of Social Media Workflow and Style Guide</head>
         <p>In response to these concerns, we developed a
            <ref target="https://www.digitaltransgenderarchive.net/about/policies">Social Media
               Style Guide</ref> to foster more consistent and effective use of our social media
            presence across all three platforms (Facebook, Twitter, and Instagram). To create this
            guide, we evaluated platform-specific analytics to identify our audience’s demographics
            and track trends in post engagement. Next, we reviewed each platform’s accessibility
            guidelines and discussed ways to ethically present materials addressing discrimination
            and trauma. These data points allowed us to begin posting more accessible content (e.g.,
            providing alternate text to describe images, using CamelCase for hashtags) that was
            better tailored to the interests of our social media communities. We also shifted the
            timing of our posts to our followers’ peak activity hours and developed a list of
            important annual dates to ensure that we commemorate events important to our work.
            Because some of our materials discuss violence and discrimination, the Social Media
            Style Guide includes best practices for content warnings.</p>
         <p> Additionally, as a collaborative archive that relies upon the labor of countless
            individuals and organizations, we wanted to make sure we were consistently crediting our
            partnering institutions on social media posts, directing traffic to their websites and
            social media presences as well as our own, and calling attention to exciting new
            projects. Therefore, we created policies for citing the sources of our content and began
            sharing more posts about the archives and websites that inspire us.</p>
         <p>Given that physical archives can be uniquely inaccessible to trans people, we have found
            that social media is one additional way we can ensure that we are reaching the people
            whose histories are the focus of our work. Already, we are seeing positive responses to
            these changes, including higher rates of post engagement, increased site traffic
            originating from social media, and more consistent responses from our communities. Our
            Social Media Style Guide functions as a living document that we continually revise as we
            receive feedback and track usage. By formalizing social media policies while retaining
            space for further experimentation, we are now better able to create informative outreach
            content that is consistent with our goals and ethical commitments.</p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Observation #5: Static Pages Neglected</head>
         <p>Since the driving mission behind the DTA is making trans-related history more
            accessible, we have a strong commitment to ensuring that our website content is
            welcoming and functional for as many of our visitors as possible, irrespective of their
            academic background or level of experience with archival research. While the majority of
            our day-to-day work is focused on developing and expanding the database itself, there
            are a series of static pages on the site that serve as important features of the
            project. These include “About” pages explaining the history of the project, our team and
            board, and our policies, as well as “Learn” pages that offer a starter’s guide to the
            DTA, a race and ethnicity research guide, a glossary, and a list of global terms. Many
            of these pages were created in the early stages of the project and have not been
            consistently updated.</p>
         <p>As new team members, Roles and Schlotterback brought fresh perspectives on the project,
            and they conducted a comprehensive reading and analysis of our website copy and images.
            They were specifically focused on consistency, accuracy, intellectual accessibility, and
            user experience. Their review ultimately determined that while we were generally
            successful at presenting our content in an easy-to-navigate format with a style and tone
            that was appropriate for a generalist audience, there were significant inconsistencies
            across our static pages, including some content that was concerningly outdated.</p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Response: Creation of a Static Page Style Guide and Revision of Copy</head>
         <p>Identifying the areas of our static pages that needed further development led to a
            number of changes. Some of the edits were quite simple, such as fixing typos and broken
            links. Yet even such minor changes pointed to the need to clarify our editorial
            practices. To eliminate inconsistencies in grammar and terminology, we devised and
            implemented a 
            <ref target="https://www.digitaltransgenderarchive.net/about/policies">Style Guide</ref>
            for the DTA’s copy. Though we decided to defer to the AP Style Book for many stylistic
            decisions, we collectively established best practices for the specificities of writing
            about sex and gender, topics often neglected by mainstream style guides.</p>
         <p>To better facilitate user engagement with the various functions on the DTA site, we
            developed explanatory and instructional copy for certain features, such as the Map tool.
            Among the front-facing pages of the DTA, we identified a number of areas that required
            more sustained care, such as the 
            <ref target="https://www.digitaltransgenderarchive.net/learn/glossary">Glossary</ref> and 
            <ref target="https://www.digitaltransgenderarchive.net/learn/terms">Global Terms</ref>
            pages. Rather than attempting a short-term, superficial revision during the first phase
            of the audit, the Glossary was significantly expanded by Roles and Schlotterback during
            the spring 2021 semester. In addition to revising existing definitions to better
            represent the complexities of trans experiences, Roles and Schlotterback identified a
            number of new terms to define, including the most commonly used words in DTA materials’
            subject coverage, as well as historical terms like <q>female impersonators</q> and
            <q>masquerading</q> that are less familiar to present-day readers. As we highlight in the
            introduction of the revised Glossary, our goal in defining these terms is not to
            prescribe a single, correct definition, but to clarify how the DTA understands and uses
            terms throughout the project. We view this page as a living document that will be
            revised and expanded upon as needed, and we encourage DTA visitors to offer suggestions
            for terms to add or clarify. As of this writing, revision of the Global Terms page is
            ongoing.</p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Conclusion</head>
         <p> The five observations and responses discussed above capture the key results of our
            year-long audit of the Digital Transgender Archive. The results of our audit have
            already proven to be tremendously insightful. In brief, we accomplished the following:
            our project scope has been critically analyzed and we have identified areas for
            intentional growth moving forward; more of our project documentation is written and
            publicly available; our project values have been articulated and shared; many of our
            static pages have been significantly revised; our social media presence is now more
            consistent and purposeful; we have more qualitative and quantitative user data to
            include in our grants; and we directly responded to reviews and feedback on the
            project.</p>
         <p>We have shared these results in the hopes that our observations resonate with other
            project teams and their work. Irrespective of the specific outcomes, we found the
            process of auditing the DTA to be a highly effective time investment for a project that
            had passed through the startup phase and was just beginning to settle into ongoing
            maintenance. While there is always some pressure to innovate and expand, spending most
            of our year auditing our work allowed us the space for genuine self-evaluation so that
            we can now move forward with clearer intention and purpose.</p>
         </div>
         
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="adler2016" label="Adler 2016"> Adler, M. 2016. <title rend="quotes">The Case for Taxonomic Reparations</title>, <title rend="italic"
               >Knowledge Organization</title>, 43.8 (2016): 630-640.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="alilunas2018" label="Alilunas and Erdman 2018"> Alilunas P. and Erdman D. <title rend="quotes">The Adult Film History Project</title>,
               <title rend="italic">JCMS: Journal of Cinema and Media Studies</title>, 58.1 (2018):
               152-157.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="antracoli2019" label="Antracoli et al. 2019"> Antracoli, A. A., Berdini, A., Bolding, K., Charlton, F., and
               Ferrara, A. <title rend="italic">Archives for Black Lives in Philadelphia Anti-Racist
                  Description Resources</title>. Archives for Black Lives in Philadelphia (2019).
               <ref target="https://archivesforblacklives.files.wordpress.com/2019/10/ardr_final.pdf"
                  >https://archivesforblacklives.files.wordpress.com/2019/10/ardr_final.pdf</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bergen2016" label="Bergen 2016"> Bergen, S. <title rend="quotes">Trans-ing History on the Web: The Digital Transgender
               Archive</title>, <title rend="italic">Perspectives on History</title> (2016). 
               <ref
                  target="https://www.historians.org/publications-and-directories/perspectives-on-history/summer-2016/trans-ing-history-on-the-web-the-digital-transgender-archive"
                  >https://www.historians.org/publications-and-directories/perspectives-on-history/summer-2016/trans-ing-history-on-the-web-the-digital-transgender-archive</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="blackwomenssuffrage" label="Black Women’s Suffrage n.d."> Black Women’s Suffrage. <title rend="quotes">Harmful Language Statement</title> (n.d.).
               <ref target="https://blackwomenssuffrage.dp.la/harmful-language-statement"
                  >https://blackwomenssuffrage.dp.la/harmful-language-statement</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brathwaiteshirley2020" label="Brathwaite-Shirley 2020"> Brathwaite-Shirley, D. <title rend="italic">Black Trans
               Archive</title> (2020).
               <ref target="https://blacktransarchive.com/">https://blacktransarchive.com/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="breeding2008" label="Breeding 2008"> Breeding, M. <title rend="quotes">Content, Community and Visibility: A Winning Combination</title>,
               <title rend="italic">Computers in Libraries, </title>28.4 (2008): 26-28.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="carlin2018" label="Carlin 2018"> Carlin, Claire. <title rend="quotes">Endings: Concluding, Archiving, and Preserving Digital
               Projects for Long-Term Usability</title> , <title rend="italic">KULA: Knowledge Creation,
                  Dissemination, and Preservation StudiesI, </title>2 (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chatterjee2020" label="Chatterjee 2020"> Chatterjee, S. <title rend="quotes">Listening to the Archive: Reimagining Global Trans
               History</title>, <title rend="italic">University of Pittsburgh Humanities Engage</title> (2020).
               <ref
                  target="https://www.humanitiescareers.pitt.edu/blog/listening-archive-reimagining-global-trans-history"
                  >https://www.humanitiescareers.pitt.edu/blog/listening-archive-reimagining-global-trans-history</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="edmond2020" label="Edmond and Morselli 2020"> Edmond, J., and Morselli, F. <title rend="quotes">Sustainability of Digital
               Humanities Projects as a Publication and Documentation Challenge</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Journal of Documentation</title>, 76.5 (2020).
               <ref
                  target="https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/JD-12-2019-0232/full/html"
                  >https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/JD-12-2019-0232/full/html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fang2007" label="Fang 2007"> Fang, W. <title rend="quotes">Using Google Analytics for Improving Library Website Content and
               Design: A Case Study</title>, <title rend="italic">Library Philosophy and Practice, </title>9.2
               (2007).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fenlon2020" label="Fenlon 2020"> Fenlon, K. <title rend="quotes">Sustaining Digital Humanities Collections: Challenges and
               Community-Centered Strategies</title>, <title rend="italic">International Journal of Digital
                  Curation</title>, 15.1 (2020).
               <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.2218/ijdc.v15i1.725"
                  >http://dx.doi.org/10.2218/ijdc.v15i1.725</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="galbraith2016" label="Galbraith 2016"> Galbraith, S. <title rend="quotes">Piwik: Breaking Away from Google Analytics</title>, <title
               rend="italic">Open Shelf</title> (2016). <ref
                  target="http://open-shelf.ca/160215-piwik/">http://open-shelf.ca/160215-piwik/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="green2020" label="Green 2020"> Green, J. <title rend="italic">Becoming a Visible Man</title>. Vanderbilt
               University Press, Nashville (2020).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="griffingracy2017" label="Griffin-Gracy et al. 2017"> Griffin-Gracy, McDonald, and Torinek. <title rend="quotes">Cautious Living:
               Black Trans Women and the Politics of Documentation.</title> In <title rend="italic">Trap Door:
                  Trans Cultural Production and the Politics of Visibility</title>, MIT Press, Cambridge
               (2017): 23-38.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jackson2020" label="Jackson 2020"> Jackson, N. C. <title rend="quotes">‘There is No Question About This and There Never Has Been
               for Eight Years’: The Public Reception of Christine Jorgensen</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Peitho: Journal of the Coalition of Feminist Scholars in the History of Rhetoric and
                  Composition</title>, 22.4 (2020).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kochrein2020" label="Koch-Rein et al. 2020"> Koch-Rein, Yekani, and Verlinden. <title rend="quotes">Representing trans:
               visibility and its discontents</title>, <title rend="italic">The European Journal of English
                  Studies</title>, 24:1 (2020): 1-12.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="maron2014" label="Maron and Pickle 2014"> Maron, N. L., and Pickle, S. <title rend="quotes">Sustaining the Digital Humanities:
               Host Institution Support Beyond the Start-Up Phase</title>, <title rend="italic">Ithaka S+R</title> (2014).
               <ref target="https://doi.org/10.18665/sr.22548">https://doi.org/10.18665/sr.22548</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="meneses2019" label="Meneses and Furuta 2019"> Meneses, L., and Furuta, R. <title rend="quotes">Shelf life: Identifying the
               Abandonment of Online Digital Humanities Projects</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital
                  Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 34.1 (2019): i129-i134.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="miller2020" label="Miller and Taylor-Poleskey 2020"> Miller, A., and Taylor-Poleskey, M. <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities
               Preservation: A Conversation for Developing Sustainable Digital Projects.</title> In M. M.
               Balkun and M. M. Deyrup (eds), <title rend="italic">Transformative Digital Humanities</title>,
               Routledge, New York (2020): 103-119.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="page2017" label="Page 2017"> Page, Morgan M. <title rend="quotes"><title rend="italic">One from the Vaults: </title>Gossip, Access,
               and Trans History-Telling</title>, In <title rend="italic">Trap Door: Trans Cultural Production
                  and the Politics of Visibility</title>, MIT Press, Cambridge (2017): 135-146.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="patterson2019" label="Patterson 2019"> Patterson, N. <title rend="quotes">ETHICS in Data: Exploring a Model of Collaborative
               Curation</title>, <title rend="italic">FSU Digital Scholars</title> (2019).
               <ref target="https://digitalscholars.wordpress.com/2019/03/03/1882/"
                  >https://digitalscholars.wordpress.com/2019/03/03/1882/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="powell2018" label="Powell 2018"> Powell, K. <title rend="quotes">Hidden Archives: Revealing Untold Stories</title>, <title rend="italic"
               >Journal of American Studies</title>, 52.1 (2018): 26-44.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rawson2009" label="Rawson 2009"> Rawson, K. J. <title rend="quotes">Accessing Transgender // Desiring Queer(er?) Archival
               Logics.</title> <title rend="italic">Archivaria</title>, 68 (Fall 2009): 123-140. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rawson2018" label="Rawson 2018"> Rawson, K. J. <title rend="quotes">The Rhetorical Power of Archival Description: Classifying
               Images of Gender Transgression</title>, <title rend="italic">Rhetoric Society Quarterly</title>, 48.4
               (2018): 327-351.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="reed2014" label="Reed 2014"> Reed, A. <title rend="quotes">Managing an Established Digital Humanities Project: Principles and
               Practices from the Twentieth Year of the William Blake Archive</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 8.1 (2014). 
               <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/1/000174/000174.html%3E"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/1/000174/000174.html%3E</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="risam2015" label="Risam 2015"> Risam, R. <title rend="quotes">Beyond the Margins: Intersectionality and the Digital
               Humanities</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 9.2 (2015). 
               <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/2/000208/000208.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/2/000208/000208.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="risam2018" label="Risam 2018"> Risam, R. <title rend="quotes">Decolonizing the Digital Humanities in Theory.</title> In J. Sayers
               (ed), <title rend="italic">The Routledge Companion to Media Studies and Digital
                  Humanities</title>, Routledge, New York (2018): 78-86.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rockwell2014" label="Rockwell et al., 2014"> Rockwell, G., Day, S., Yu, J., and Engel, M. <title rend="quotes">Burying Dead
               Projects: Depositing the Globalization Compendium</title>, <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                  Quarterly</title>, 8.2 (2014). 
               <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/2/000179/000179.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/2/000179/000179.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rodriguez2015" label="Rodriguez 2015"> Rodriguez, H. <title rend="quotes">We can't let increased transgender visibility lead to
               more vulnerability</title>, <title rend="italic">The Guardian</title> (21 August 2015). 
               <ref
                  target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/aug/21/transgender-visibility-vulnerability"
                  >https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/aug/21/transgender-visibility-vulnerability</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ross2012" label="Ross 2012"> Ross, C. <title rend="quotes">Social Media for Digital Humanities and Community Engagement.</title> In
               C. Warwick, M. Terras, and J. Nyhan (eds), <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities in
                  Practice</title>, Facet Publishing, Cambridge (2012): 23-45.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sabharwal2021" label="Sabharwal 2021"> Sabharwal, A. <title rend="quotes">Functional Frameworks for Socialized Digital Curation:
               Curatorial Interventions and Curation Spaces in Archives and Libraries</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Library Trends</title>, 69.3 (2021): 672-695.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sheffield2020" label="Sheffield 2020"> Sheffield, R. <title rend="quotes">Archival Optimism, or How to Sustain a Community
               Archives.</title> In <title rend="italic">Community Archives, Community Spaces: Heritage, Memory
                  and Identity</title>, Facet Publishing, London (2020): 3-20.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shepard2020" label="Shepard 2020"> Shepard, N. <title rend="quotes">Review: Digital Transgender Archive</title>, <title rend="italic"
               >Reviews in Digital Humanities</title>, 1.10 (2020). 
               <ref target="https://doi.org/10.21428/3e88f64f.7bede3fd"
                  >https://doi.org/10.21428/3e88f64f.7bede3fd</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="smithies2019" label="Smithies et al. 2019"> Smithies, Westling, Sichani, Mellen, and Ciula. <title rend="quotes">Managing 100
               Digital Humanities Projects: Digital Scholarship &amp; Archiving in King’s Digital Lab</title>,
               <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 13.1 (2019). 
               <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/1/000411/000411.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/1/000411/000411.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stanley2017" label="Stanley 2017"> Stanley, E. <title rend="quotes">Anti-Trans Optics: Recognition, Opacity, and the Image of
               Force</title>, <title rend="italic">South Atlantic Quarterly</title>, 116.3 (2017): 612-620.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="steinbock2019" label="Steinbock 2019"> Steinbock, E. <title rend="quotes">The Early 1990s and Its Afterlives: Transgender Nation
               Sociality in Digital Activism</title>, <title rend="italic">Social Media + Society</title> (2019):
               1-12.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tabak2017" label="Tabak 2017"> Tabak, E. <title rend="quotes">A Hybrid Model for Managing DH Projects</title>, <title rend="italic"
               >Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 11.1 (2017).
               <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/1/000284/000284.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/1/000284/000284.html</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="turner2010" label="Turner 2010"> Turner, S. J. <title rend="quotes">Website Statistics 2.0: Using Google Analytics to Measure
               Library Website Effectiveness</title>, <title rend="italic">Technical Services Quarterly,
               </title>27.3 (2010).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vanhaitsma2019" label="VanHaitsma 2019"> VanHaitsma, P. <title rend="quotes">Digital LGBTQ Archives as Sites of Public Memory and
               Pedagogy</title>, <title rend="italic">Rhetoric and Public Affairs</title>, 22.2 (2019): 253-280.
               <ref
                  target="https://reviews.americanarchivist.org/2019/06/18/homosaurus-and-digital-transgender-archive/"
                  >https://reviews.americanarchivist.org/2019/06/18/homosaurus-and-digital-transgender-archive/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="watson2019" label="Watson 2019"> Watson, B. <title rend="quotes">Homosaurus and the Digital Transgender Archive</title>, <title
               rend="italic">The American Archivist Reviews Portal</title> (2019).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zorich2003" label="Zorich 2003"> Zorich, D. M. <title rend="italic">A Survey of Digital Cultural Heritage
               Initiatives and Their Sustainability Concerns</title>. Council on Library and
               Information Resources, Washington, D.C. (2003). 
               <ref target="https://www.clir.org/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/pub118.pdf"
                  >https://www.clir.org/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/pub118.pdf</ref>
            </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
