<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Towards Hermeneutic Visualization in Digital
                    Literary Studies</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Rabea <dhq:family>Kleymann</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Leibniz Center for Literary and Cultural
                        Research</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>kleymann@zfl-berlin.org</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Rabea Kleymann is a postdoctoral digital humanities researcher at the
                            Leibniz Centre for Literary and Cultural Research in Berlin. Her
                            research interests lie in the areas of philosophy of science, new
                            materialism and critical infrastructure studies. She is co-convenor of
                            the German working group <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities
                                Theory</title> and co-chair of the working group <title
                                rend="quotes">Diversity &amp; Inclusion</title> of the Postdoc
                            Network of the Leibniz Association.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Jan-Erik <dhq:family>Stange</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Freie Universität Berlin</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>jan-erik.stange@fu-berlin.de </email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Jan-Erik Stange is a research associate at the cluster EXC 2020 <title
                                rend="quotes">Temporal Communities</title> at Freie Universität
                            Berlin. His research interests lie in critical data visualization and
                            interface design in the digital humanities. As a designer by profession
                            he has brought a design perspective to numerous digital humanities
                            projects.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000547</idno>
                <idno type="volume">015</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2021-06-15">15 June 2021</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
        	<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target=
        		"https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000547/000547.xml">GitHub
        	</ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>In this article, we present our reflections on hermeneutic data visualizations
                    for digital literary studies. Hermeneutic approaches in the digital humanities
                    have been rather agnostic about the epistemological premises of hermeneutic
                    theory. These can be summarized as (1) differentiation author/text, (2)
                    hermeneutic circle and (3) dependency text/recipient. In this article, we
                    present the concept of hermeneutic visualization as a means of bridging the gap
                    between <soCalled>classic</soCalled> literary hermeneutics and the emerging
                    practice of digital literary hermeneutics. Since data visualization is based on
                    epistemological premises stemming from the natural or social sciences, it is not
                    well-equipped to meet hermeneutic demands. In this article, we argue that the
                    digital humanities can meet hermeneutic demands through a critical interface and
                    visualization concept. We discuss four postulates that can be used as guidelines
                    and help transform <soCalled>more traditional</soCalled> data visualization into
                    hermeneutic visualization, while respecting the epistemological foundations of
                    hermeneutic theory. We demonstrate the usefulness of the postulates with an
                    interactive prototype <title rend="italic">Stereoscope</title> designed to
                    support them.<note>In our article, we refer to the discussions and results of
                        the three-year research project <title rend="italic">Three-Dimensional
                            Dynamic Data Visualisation and Exploration for Digital Humanities
                            Research</title> (3DH) at the University of Hamburg (04/2016–12/2018).
                        The considerations on hermeneutic visualizations presented here are
                        therefore the result of a very productive collaboration. Therefore we cannot
                        claim the presented ideas as our own.</note></p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>This article discusses hermeneutic data visualizations within the field of
                    digital literary studies.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>1. Introduction</head>
                <p>Data visualization has become a prolific method in digital literary studies to
                    represent the results of a research process. While it is most commonly used to
                    communicate these results to a scholarly audience, there is an increasing number
                    of cases that exhibit an analytical use of the method in order to gain a better
                    understanding of the textual data under investigation (cf. <ptr
                        target="#jessop2008" loc="283"/>; <ptr target="#sinclair2013"/>). A common
                    definition of data visualization is: <quote rend="inline">The use of
                        computer-supported, interactive, visual representations of abstract data to
                        amplify cognition</quote>
                    <ptr target="#card1999"/>. Although literary text can be transformed into
                    abstract data with the help of statistical or computational methods like natural
                    language processing, this is not the kind of data that literary scholars
                    practicing an hermeneutic approach are concerned with. Here, scholars are
                    dealing with subjective and ambiguous data, usually in the form of text
                    annotations, for which conventional data visualization is not adequate (cf. <ptr
                        target="#drucker2018"/>). Precisely this discrepancy between conventional
                    data visualizations used and the interpretative data and processes to be
                    visualized is the starting point of our considerations for a more reflective
                    interface and visualization concept for literary analysis and interpretation
                    processes.</p>
                <p>As Meister et al. point out: <quote rend="inline">Most current DH visualizations
                        are thus epistemological one-way avenues toward knowledge, from data via
                        rendering algorithm to visual display</quote>
                    <ptr target="#meister2017"/>. But the process of understanding texts and other
                    cultural artifacts in the humanities is a continuous, dynamic interplay of
                    modeling as well as reasoning operations. These operations repeatedly affect a
                    dynamic data model in form of enrichment and reconfiguration (cf. <ptr
                        target="#gius2017" loc="115"/>). The hermeneutic approach is a specific form
                    of the process of understanding, which has significance especially for literary
                    and cultural studies. In the humanities, the term <term>hermeneutic</term>
                        (<foreign>hermeneuein</foreign> in Greek means <quote rend="inline">to say,
                        to explain, to translate</quote>
                    <ptr target="#palmers1969" loc="13"/>) generally stands <quote rend="inline">for
                        the practice of exegesis (i. e. interpretation) that leads to understanding,
                        [...] [as well as] for the theory of interpretation as a reflection on the
                        conditions and norms of understanding and linguistic utterance in
                        general</quote>
                    <ptr target="#mittelstrab2008" loc="364"/><note>Original German text passages
                        quoted or paraphrased above are translated by the authors of this
                        paper.</note>. Already developed as a practice in ancient times,
                    hermeneutics took different forms over the 19th century, especially in
                    Schleiermacher’s and Herder’s approach, then around 1900 in Dilthey’s conception
                    and finally in the 20th century in the thinking of Heidegger, Gadamer and the
                        <title rend="quotes">Konstanzer Schule</title>. As a result, the following
                    distinction has become established in the humanities. On the one hand,
                    hermeneutic refers to a literary-philological art theory of the interpretation
                    of texts (and other cultural artefacts). We speak of <term>literary
                        hermeneutics</term>. On the other hand, hermeneutic is a philosophical
                    discipline with an universalistic claim that is concerned with the conditions of
                    humanistic understanding per se (cf. <ptr target="#nunning2008" loc="281"/>;
                        <ptr target="#stiening2016" loc="54"/>). In this context, we are talking of
                        <emph>hermeneutic philosophy</emph>. However, both meanings of the term are
                    strongly interdependent and partly overlap in different theories of the
                    humanities.</p>
                <p>In digital humanities research, there has been some discussion on how the digital
                    humanities might live up to expectations and methodological requirements
                    associated with a digitally supported hermeneutic practice (cf. <ptr
                        target="#zundert2016"/>; <ptr target="#rockwellandsinclair2016"/>). Often a
                    very broad notion of hermeneutics as a theory of understanding (as opposed to
                    explaining) is applied. We can observe results that have arisen from these
                    discussions in a number of software tools (e.g. <title rend="italic"
                        >Catma</title>, <title rend="italic">Voyant</title>). These tools are, for
                    example, replicating traditional scholarly activities that are considered a part
                    of the interpretation process. Unsworth <ptr target="#unsworth2000"/> gives a
                    systematic account of <soCalled>scholarly primitives</soCalled>, as he calls
                    these activities, some of which are applied by scholars during the
                    interpretative process. Among these are annotation, comparison and
                    representation. As for annotation, this is often the starting point of
                    hermeneutic practice: highlighting parts of a document and writing down comments
                    in the margins are two of the oldest scholarly techniques.</p>
                <p>While the integration of these primary activities into digital tools certainly is
                    a step towards hermeneutics in the digital realm (or <term>digital literary
                        hermeneutics</term>), most of these efforts have been rather agnostic about
                    the epistemological premises of hermeneutic theory. We argue that visualization
                    could serve as the missing link between fundamental hermeneutic premises and
                    digital (literary) hermeneutics. We claim that visualizations not only have to
                    fulfill certain conditions to adequately support literary analysis and
                    interpretation. Rather, we assert that, in referring to the traditional theory
                    of hermeneutics, these qualities can be distinctively described and designed
                    for. We define <term>hermeneutic visualization</term> as: <quote rend="block"
                        >The use of computer-supported, interactive, visual representations of text
                        annotations to manipulate, reconfigure and explore them in order to create
                        visual interpretations that can be used as arguments and allow a critical
                        reflection of the hermeneutic process in light of a research
                        question.</quote> By clarifying the premises and postulates for hermeneutic
                    visualization, we address two research desiderata. First, a systematic
                    elaboration of the implicit premises of hermeneutic text interpretations is
                    still missing. What premises of hermeneutics do we have to consider when we want
                    to use visualizations as tools for the interpretation process? We propose four
                    premises for hermeneutic visualizations. These can be summarized as (1)
                    differentiation author/text, (2) hermeneutic circle and (3) dependency
                    text/recipient.</p>
                <p>Second, data visualizations within the DH scholarship are often limited to a
                    representational usage. The current data visualization paradigm in the digital
                    humanities foregrounds operations and transformations of input data at the
                    expense of the human user whose agency as producer and interpreter of
                    visualizations is largely ignored. This has triggered a conceptual and technical
                    reification of visualization that invites its misinterpretation as an objective
                    representation. At worst, visualizations are taken as quasi-objects that appear
                    to exist on the same ontological level as the objects whose properties they
                    claim to faithfully represent. But especially in digital literary studies, we
                    are dealing with data that rather refer to an interpretation process.
                    Polyvalence is a characteristic of this data generated by interpretation.
                    Because of the assumed objective nature of the data, polyvalence is not
                    accounted for in the visual representation of the visual variables, which raises
                    a range of questions: What demands must be made on a critical interface and
                    visualization concept for hermeneutic text interpretations? What do hermeneutic
                    visualizations look like? How do we create them? In order to tackle these
                    questions we propose four postulates for hermeneutic visualizations: <title
                        rend="italic">Two Way Screen, Quality, Parallax</title> and <title
                        rend="italic">Discourse</title> [cf. <ptr target="#meister2017"/>; <ptr
                        target="#drucker2018"/>]. These four postulates serve as guidelines for
                    creating hermeneutic visualizations and embedding them in user interfaces. To
                    get our postulates on a concrete footing, we will demonstrate their usefulness
                    with the help of the interactive visualization prototype <title rend="quotes"
                        >Stereoscope</title>.</p>
                <p>In our paper, we want to raise awareness for the extent to which research in
                    digital humanities always contributes to the <quote rend="inline">epistemic
                        self-enlightenment</quote>
                    <ptr target="#albrecht2015" loc="10"/> of one’s own discipline. This article
                    aims to show how digital humanities research is based on a thorough and
                    continuous reflection of the epistemological principles at work. Our article
                    represents an attempt to think visualization in terms of literary hermeneutics.
                    Contrary to current narratives of an <quote rend="inline">end of theory</quote>
                    (cf. <ptr target="#anderson2008"/>) or a post-theoretical era (cf. <ptr
                        target="#scheinfeldt2012"/>) in the DH, we argue for a productive discussion
                    of theories, in our case literary theories. Against this background, we believe
                    that the question of hermeneutic visualizations gains an exemplary status. We
                    are not only interested in demonstrating possibilities of operationalization for
                    the singular case of hermeneutic visualizations. Rather, we believe that our
                    case of hermeneutic visualization can be regarded as a prototypical procedure
                    with respect to the question of methodology in digital humanities research in
                    general. The issue of <soCalled>hermeneutic visualization</soCalled> is, we
                    argue, both a demonstration object and a medium of reflection.</p>
                <p>Here is the structure of our argument: In section 2, we will begin with a short
                    synopsis of the development of classic hermeneutics and an exposition and
                    explanation of the three epistemological premises. Against this backdrop, we
                    will discuss how visualizations are well-suited to represent these activities,
                    but are also lacking qualities in order to meet the epistemological premises.
                    Section 3 will address these lacking qualities by discussing four postulates. In
                    section 4 we will then demonstrate how these postulates have been addressed in a
                    software prototype. In closing, we reflect on the results and discuss directions
                    for future research.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. From the Hermeneutic Foundation to Digital Hermeneutic
                    Visualizations</head>
                <p>This section is initially dedicated elaborating implicit premises in hermeneutic
                    literary theory. These premises are then the lens through which we discuss
                    current hermeneutical approaches in digital humanities, especially with regard
                    to the role of visualizations.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>2.1 Interpretation, Theory, Method, and Argument in Literary
                        Studies</head>
                    <p>Among the main activities of researchers working in the field of literary
                        studies one can count the following: interpretation, development and
                        application of literary theory and of methods, argumentation. These core
                        activities form part of the wider literary studies framework and therefore
                        warrant closer inspection. In order to investigate hermeneutic
                        visualizations we think that work on our terminology is required.</p>
                    <p>Interpretation is considered one of the main activities of literary studies
                        (cf. <ptr target="#albrecht2015" loc="1"/>).<note>We acknowledge that the
                            chosen terms overlap with terms for example like <term>heuristic,
                                technique, practice</term>.</note> The term
                            <term>interpretation</term>, a derivation from the Latin word <quote
                            rend="inline">interpretatio: understand, explain, translate</quote>, is
                        defined as <quote rend="inline">the methodically induced result of
                            understanding texts in their totality</quote>
                        <ptr target="#spree2000" loc="168f"/> as well as <quote rend="inline">the
                            formulation of hypotheses about aspects of meaning in literary
                            texts</quote>
                        <ptr target="#gius2017" loc="236"/>. Following Winko <ptr
                            target="#winko2003" loc="597"/> the synthesizing interpretation can, on
                        the one hand, presuppose the results of a rather descriptive and analytical
                        text analysis. Analysis and interpretation are thus considered in a
                        procedural relationship. On the other hand, text analysis and interpretation
                        can be determined as synonyms, since both terms are based on the same rules
                        of meaning-making treatment of the text. Despite the idea of a reasoning
                        process that does not require any principles or the claim of some literary
                        scholars <quote rend="inline">that literary texts are ambiguous or
                                <q>polyvalent</q> by nature</quote>, as Gius &amp; Jacke <ptr
                            target="#giusjacke2017" loc="234"/> point out, a literary interpretation
                        is based on rules [cf. <ptr target="#jannidis2003" loc="6"/>]. These rules,
                        which are applied in a reasoning process, can be provided by different
                        theoretical approaches (cf. <ptr target="#spree2000" loc="169"/>).</p>
                    <p>A <emph>literary theory</emph> can be defined as an <quote rend="block"
                            >explicit, elaborated, logical structured system of categories in order
                            to describe, explore or explain certain issues [of texts]</quote>
                        <ptr target="#nunning2010" loc="6"/>. Literary theories provide not only
                        specific epistemological implications regarding, for example, the concept of
                        authorship or the relevance of contexts, but also contain an implicit idea
                        of meaning. During decades of theoretical debates and throughout different
                        turns, the parameters indicating or representing meaning have shifted (cf.
                            <ptr target="#jannidis2003" loc="7"/>). Besides the epistemological
                        implications, this also changed the definition of what actually constitutes
                        a research object as such.<note>Krämer <ptr target="#kramer2015" loc="163"/>
                            points out that in the practice of text interpretation different
                            theoretical approaches are often mixed up.</note> Methods, however,
                        differ from theories. A literary method is a procedure for accomplishing
                        knowledge in a research inquiry. Methods can be characterized as purposeful
                        and rule-based (cf. <ptr target="#nunning2010" loc="8"/>; <ptr
                            target="#winko2003" loc="581"/>). A theory could not only encompass one
                        or a set of several methods, but also demand the application of methods with
                        varying degrees of specification (for example, deductive or dialectical
                        methods compared to the more general operations such as reading or
                        generating hypotheses).</p>
                    <p>Argumentation is described as the <quote rend="inline">unfolding of given
                            proofs</quote> by Cicero in De partitione Oratoria (cf. <ptr
                            target="#radle2000" loc="130"/>). In literary studies, argumentation
                        plays an important role for the process of generating and validating
                        interpretations (cf. <ptr target="#albrecht2015" loc="12"/>). Argumentation
                        can be described as a formal or logical organization of single observations,
                        that serve as arguments <quote rend="inline">to provide evidence in favor of
                            some point of view</quote>
                        <ptr target="#groarke2017"/>. Krämer <ptr target="#kramer2015" loc="163"/>
                        speaks of <quote rend="inline">practices of arguing</quote>, that means
                            <quote rend="inline">patterns of links, in which certain types of text
                            data can be associated with certain ways of attributing meaning.</quote>
                        An argumentation explicates the interpretative process in a textual or
                        visual form by structuring, connecting, and subsuming single observations
                        (cf. <ptr target="#eemeren2009" loc="5"/>). Von Savigny, on the one hand,
                        distinguishes eight types of literary arguments, for example <quote
                            rend="inline">arguments of understanding</quote> or <quote rend="inline"
                            >poetic arguments</quote>
                        <ptr target="#savigny1976" loc="102"/>. Kindt and Schmidt <ptr
                            target="#kindt1976" loc="9"/>, on the other hand, mention three
                        attributes for the evaluation of an argumentation: rigor, intersubjectivity,
                        validation. One issue, for example, is the idea of <quote rend="inline"
                            >evidentiary transparency</quote>
                        <ptr target="#piper2020" loc="6"/>. How can we verify a literary hypothesis?
                        Is it acceptable for a hypothesis to merely resist falsification, or does it
                        need to be positively confirmed via case studies? (cf. <ptr
                            target="#albrecht2015" loc="13"/>).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.2 Foundations of Literary Hermeneutics</head>
                    <p>The next point to be addressed concerns the foundations of the type of
                        hermeneutics practiced in the field of literary studies. Thus, the first
                        sentence of Szondi’s <title rend="italic">Introduction to Literary
                            Hermeneutics</title>
                        <ptr target="#szondi1995" loc="1"/> reads: <quote rend="inline">Literary
                            hermeneutics is the study of the interpretation [...] of literary
                            works.</quote> Köppe &amp; Winko <ptr target="#winko2003" loc="19"/>
                        point out that the hermeneutic approach is a <soCalled>precursor</soCalled>
                        theory, which is not practiced anymore. But according to introductions into
                        literary studies, hermeneutic theory is not only still widespread, it is
                        often also mentioned before all other theories (cf. <ptr
                            target="#jessing2007" loc="276"/>; <ptr target="#nunning2010" loc="29"
                        />; <ptr target="#jahraus2002" loc="36"/>). While Stiegler notes a kind of
                            <quote rend="inline">hermeneutics bashing</quote>
                        <ptr target="#stiegler2015" loc="26"/> conducted by other theoretical
                        approaches, hermeneutic theory and its methodological tradition constitute
                        an essential approach to text interpretation.</p>
                    <p>Essential for hermeneutic theory is the idea of an understanding, which aims
                        to reach a deeper meaning or hidden reason of a text. Consequently, it is
                        assumed that (literary) texts have a meaning, which can be exposed under
                        certain conditions. This meaning does not have an objective, but rather an
                        observer-dependent and contextual status. In that regard, the hermeneutic
                        approach differs widely, for example, from Derrida’s deconstruction (cf.
                            <ptr target="#derrida1967"/>). In his work <title rend="italic"
                            >Hermeneutik und Kritik mit besonderer Beziehung auf das Neue
                            Testament</title> (1838) Friedrich Schleiermacher (1768–1834) stresses
                        two important epistemological premises of the hermeneutic understanding of
                        meaning. First, Schleiermacher differentiates between the intentions of the
                        author and the expressions in the text. Schleiermacher’s distinction leads
                        to the idea of an autonomous intention of the text, which is not necessarily
                        congruent with the intention of the author. Therefore, the text is regarded
                        as an artificial and aesthetic work of art with a specific meaning (cf. <ptr
                            target="#selbmann2002" loc="38"/>). Second, Schleiermacher argues that a
                        profound understanding of the text corresponds with the holistic dependency
                        of parts and the whole. He proposes the <quote rend="inline">Grundsatz der
                            Ganzheit</quote> : <quote rend="inline">[T]he same way that the whole
                            is, of course, understood in reference to the individual, so too, the
                            individual can only be understood in reference to the whole</quote> (cf.
                            <ptr target="#schleiermacher1838"/>, <ptr target="#mantzavinos2016"
                        />).</p>
                    <p>Moreover, the philologist Friedrich Ast (1778–1841) and later Schleiermacher
                        emphasize the circular procedure of interpretation, i.e., the hermeneutic
                        circle. In literary studies, the hermeneutic circle or spiral is regarded as
                        an instrument for the formulation of a hypothesis connecting a meaningful
                        whole and its elements [cf. <ptr target="#otoole2018"/>]. In Gadamer’s
                        conception of hermeneutic experience, understanding is also determined as a
                        circular movement that arises precisely through the examination of the text.
                        The circular structure of understanding thereby aims to change the view of
                        the world in a way that reveals something new or revises old experiences and
                        prejudices (cf. <ptr target="#rese2010" loc="176"/>). The negation of
                        certain experiences through the reading and analysis of a text leads to the
                        transformation of the horizon of understanding (cf. <ptr
                            target="#gadamer1990"/>). <soCalled>Textual understanding</soCalled>, as
                        Gius &amp; Jacke <ptr target="#gius2017" loc="236"/> describe it, <quote
                            rend="inline">is attained in the interplay between (contextual)
                            assumptions about the text on the one hand, and textual data on the
                            other hand […].</quote> Thus, the act of interpretation constitutes a
                        specific practice of a <quote rend="inline">reading and questioning […],
                            back and forth, shifting the focus of one’s attention and revising
                            interim interpretations and judgements along the way</quote>
                        <ptr target="#chamber2006" loc="35"/>.<note>Problems and critics of the
                            hermeneutic circle cf. Danneberg (1995).</note></p>
                    <p>Another premise of the hermeneutic method – besides the differentiation
                        between author and text intention and the holistic premise – is the highly
                        valued co-dependency between the text and the recipient. The co-dependency
                        is linked to the issue of context and subjective or social perceptions and
                        views. According to Gadamer’s <emph>fusion of horizons</emph>, a recipient,
                        who engages with the text in a productive way, generates partial and
                        subjective knowledge. This generated knowledge in the form of meaning <quote
                            rend="inline">can neither be deduced theoretically, nor be fully
                            articulated, but rests on a kind of tact or sensitivity that is only
                            exhibited in the form of exemplary judgments and interpretations</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ramberg2005"/>. Gius &amp; Jacke <ptr target="#giusjacke2017"
                            loc="234"/> explain: <quote rend="inline">Because these reasoning
                            processes are non-deductive, i.e., they are not strictly based on rules
                            of deductive logic, they may result in more than one account of
                            meaning.</quote></p>
                    <p>In summary, we define literary hermeneutics as a specific approach to produce
                        meaning through an iterative, non-deterministic, and subjective procedure.
                        Essential for this approach are three premises, as explicated in the
                        previous paragraphs: <list type="ordered">
                            <item>The differentiation between intentions of author and text</item>
                            <item>The holistic premise (hermeneutic circle)</item>
                            <item>The dependency between text and recipient</item>
                        </list> The hermeneutic approach is one possibility to tackle the complexity
                        of text comprehension. Further research could investigate visualization in
                        other literary interpretative processes based on Derrida’s idea of
                        deconstruction or Foucauldian parameters of discourse, for example.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.3 Conceptions of Digital Literary Hermeneutics</head>
                    <p>So far, hermeneutics, as understood in traditional literary studies and based
                        on these three premises, has not played a prominent role in digital
                        humanities. As van Zundert <ptr target="#zundert2016" loc="335"/> states:
                            <quote rend="block">The dialogue surrounding hermeneutics seems not to
                            have developed fully yet in digital humanities – references to
                            hermeneutics are scant and often at a concrete level of the practice of
                            text interpretation, such as when Katherine Hayles (2012) uses the
                            phrase <q>hermeneutic close reading</q>. Yet from several paragraphs and
                            sections in the literature the emergence of a debate seems
                            traceable.</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Literary scholars participating in this debate on hermeneutics in digital
                        humanities or <emph>digital hermeneutics</emph>, as it is often called, have
                        different views on how (the use) of digital technology might shape literary
                        hermeneutics and what digital literary hermeneutics should encompass.
                        Generally speaking, the debate is dominated by attempts to digitally
                        replicate interpretative processes known from the analog world. However, a
                        systematic effort to reflect on how the hermeneutic premises might be
                        answered by digital technology is still missing.</p>
                    <p>Commonly, approaches toward a digital literary hermeneutics, or more
                        generally toward interpretation, share the notion that it involves a process
                        of <quote rend="inline">reconfiguration, reorganization or
                            restructuring</quote>
                        <ptr target="#armaselu2017"/>, or as Samuels &amp; McGann <ptr
                            target="#samuels1999"/> describe it, <quote rend="inline"
                            >deformance</quote>. Rockwell <ptr target="#rockwell2003" loc="213"/>
                        calls the results of algorithmic analysis of texts <quote rend="inline"
                            >hybrid texts</quote> that operate as <quote rend="inline">interpretive
                            aids</quote>: <quote rend="inline">[T]hey are generated by processes of
                            taking information apart and putting it back together into new
                            configurations for the purposes of discovery and reflection.</quote>
                        This reconfiguration can be carried out automatically by an algorithm, as is
                        the case, for example, in concordances, or by manual annotations and
                        comments of text passages by scholars [cf. <ptr target="#rapp2017"/>; <ptr
                            target="#jacke2018"/>]. While the former is idiosyncratic to the digital
                        realm, the latter has been practiced in literary hermeneutics for a long
                        time. In terms of possibilities to reconfigure and restructure, however, the
                        digital world grants considerably more freedom than analog annotations.
                        Bradley <ptr target="#bradley2008" loc="266"/> describes a research software
                        prototype called <title rend="italic">Pliny</title> that is guided by
                        scholarly practice of interpretation in the analog world: <quote
                            rend="block">Notetaking, and this kind of juggling of notes to discover
                            previously unrecognised patterns and relationships and to stimulate new
                            ideas is one of the long established methods of scholarship.</quote></p>
                    <p><title rend="italic">Pliny</title> allows scholars to annotate texts, images
                        and other media by creating digital notes that can be arranged to one’s
                        likings on a plane. Relationships between notes can be conveyed by placing
                        them in spatial proximity or by nesting notes to account for hierarchical
                        relationships. In contrast to analog environments, notes can be reused in
                        different structures and contexts as they are references, not actual
                        objects. References between all the notes can be visualized in a special
                        graph view.</p>
                    <p>Boot (2009) takes up Bradley’s tripartition of the scholarly process into
                            <title rend="quotes">Reading and Annotation (Resource)</title>, <title
                            rend="quotes">Developing Interpretation</title> and <title rend="quotes"
                            >Presentation of Interpretation (Article/Argument)</title> and describes
                        the structure of annotations as <soCalled>mesotext</soCalled> that is made
                        out of <soCalled>mesodata</soCalled> (individual annotations). <title
                            rend="italic">Mesotext</title> acts as a connector between the primary
                        text (which it references) and <soCalled>secondary texts</soCalled> or
                            <soCalled>narratives</soCalled> (the article a scholar is working on),
                        for which it provides arguments. Similar to <title rend="italic"
                            >Pliny</title>, allowing scholars to adjust the <emph>mesotext</emph>
                        structure, when new insights have been gained, the concept comes close to
                        the traditional analog annotation process.</p>
                    <p>As a clear differentiation from the scientific method and a way of
                        strengthening the literary hermeneutic approach, some scholars argue for
                        exploration or a <quote rend="inline">hermeneutic of play</quote>
                        <ptr target="#rockwell2003" loc="214"/>. van Zundert <ptr
                            target="#zundert2016" loc="335"/> calls for a usage of data not so much
                        as evidence in the scientific sense, but rather as a resource to <quote
                            rend="inline">provoke new questions and explorations</quote> that can be
                        utilized in a <quote rend="inline">playful iterative approach</quote>.
                        Ramsay <ptr target="#ramsay2007"/> even speaks of a
                            <soCalled>Screwmeneutical Imperative</soCalled> that scholars should
                        follow, an obligation to be playful and try out things.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.4 Towards Hermeneutic Visualizations</head>
                    <p>In addition to the still pending consideration of hermeneutic premises in
                        digital literary studies, we now take a look at approaches from data
                        visualization. How are visualizations used in digital literary studies so
                        far? Why does an <soCalled>uncritical</soCalled> use of data visualizations
                        possibly interfere with an interpretation process? For this purpose, we
                        discuss two ways of incorporating visualization into digital humanities
                        research: humanizing visualizations and visual text analysis.</p>
                    <p>Firstly, research approaches can be brought together that ask about the
                        critical potential of data visualizations in the humanities. The starting
                        point is often the criticism of the purely instrumental function of
                        visualizations. Visualizations serve, following Card et al. <ptr
                            target="#card1999" loc="5"/>, as <soCalled>external aids</soCalled>.
                        Hinrichs et al. <ptr target="#hinrichs2019"/> critically conclude that
                        visualizations have been considered only as tools <quote rend="inline">to
                            facilitate quantitative and qualitative analysis processes, potentially
                            within any research discipline or practice.</quote> Further the authors
                        explain that <quote rend="inline">this pragmatic approach risks overlooking
                            the research value of visualization and relegating computer science and
                            design to service-based roles.</quote> Moreover, Correll <ptr
                            target="#correll2019"/> even argues <quote rend="inline">that
                            visualization is a bad neighbor to the digital humanities: it
                            exacerbates the worst tendencies of DH scholarship and promotes
                            parasitic, technocratic collaborations.</quote> In this context, he
                        pleas not only for new alliances between the humanities and visualization
                        research. Rather, he points out, that <quote rend="inline">[w]e need to
                            humanize visualization before we visualize the humanities.</quote>
                        Traditionally, visualizations have been developed and used in scientific
                        contexts. Drucker <ptr target="#drucker2011"/> explains that <quote
                            rend="inline">realist models of knowledge</quote> have been instrumental
                        in forming these representations and that <quote rend="inline">we need to
                            take on the challenge of developing graphical expressions rooted in and
                            appropriate to interpretative activity.</quote></p>
                    <p>In order to re-explore new alliances, visualizations are on the one hand
                        reconsidered by means of concepts or function in a humanities context.
                        Seifert et al. speak of visualization as <quote rend="inline">an effective
                            enabler for exploratory analysis, making it a powerful tool for gaining
                            insight into unexplored data sets.</quote><ptr target="#seifert2014"
                            loc="190"/> Dörk et al. <ptr target="#dork2013"/> go one step further
                        and show a critical approach to information visualization. Disclosure,
                        plurality, contingency, and empowerment are presented as the main
                        characteristics of critical information visualization. In the context of
                        trans-disciplinary research in the digital humanities, Hinrichs et al.
                        advocate for the concept of <soCalled>sandcastles</soCalled>, which they
                        describe as <quote rend="inline">tailored, unique, often stunning yet also
                            transient and unstable interactive visualizations.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hinrichs2019"/> With this, the authors oppose the reification
                        of data and refer to an iterative process of understanding. In contrast to a
                        conception of visualization as tools, they <quote rend="inline">elicit
                            critical insights, interpretation, speculation and discussions within
                            and beyond scholarly audiences.</quote></p>
                    <p>While Galey &amp; Ruecker <ptr target="#galey2010"/> do not refer to
                        visualizations in particular (although they use visualizations as case
                        studies), they argue for the use of digital artifacts as arguments: <quote
                            rend="block">The digital humanities must not lose sight of the design of
                            artifacts as a critical act, one that may reflect insights into
                            materials and advance an argument about an artifact’s role in the world.
                            Our purpose here is to follow the implications of a hermeneutical
                            approach to design for digital humanities projects that entail the
                            strategic prototyping of digital artifacts.</quote></p>
                    <p>However, as Ramsay &amp; Rockwell <ptr target="#ramsay2012"/> convincingly
                        point out, Galey &amp; Ruecker’s concept of argument refers rather to the
                        interface of the digital artifact than to the contents of the text which is
                        supposed to be analyzed with the digital tool. Relating to our earlier
                        comment on argumentation in the context of literary studies as a formal or
                        logical organization of single observations that serve as arguments <quote
                            rend="inline">to provide evidence in favor of some point of view</quote>
                        <ptr target="#groarke2017"/>, visualizations could serve as another
                        non-linear form of argument that complements textual explications in an
                        argumentation (cf. <ptr target="#meirelles2019" loc="169"/>). In a similar
                        vein, Ramsay &amp; Rockwell also sees visualization tools behaving <quote
                            rend="inline">like hermeneutical theories</quote>
                        <ptr target="#ramsay2012"/> that offer new perspectives on the research
                        object. Kath et al. <ptr target="#kath2015"/> have already brought to
                        attention the need for a second order hermeneutics, termed <title
                            rend="italic">New Visual Hermeneutics</title>, which can guide the
                        interpretation of such visualizations.</p>
                    <p>A second research field that plays a role in our demand for hermeneutic
                        visualizations are the approaches from visual text analysis. Although there
                        is a large selection of mainly generic visualization tools scholars can
                        choose from (The TAPoR website<note><ref target="http://tapor.ca"
                                >http://tapor.ca</ref></note> with its large collection gives a good
                        overview), some tools have gained significant popularity for certain use
                        cases and can almost be considered the de facto standard. Stylometry, for
                        example, is usually conducted with the <title rend="italic"
                                >Stylo</title><note><ref
                                target="https://github.com/computationalstylistics/stylo"
                                >https://github.com/computationalstylistics/stylo</ref></note>
                        package of the statistical language <title rend="italic">R</title>, <title
                            rend="italic">Gephi</title><note><ref target="https://gephi.org/"
                                >https://gephi.org/</ref></note> is very popular for visualizing
                        character networks (cf. <ptr target="#barbot2019"/>). These visualization
                        tools and techniques offer quite complex user interfaces to control the
                        appearance of a visualization. However, a direct manipulation of the
                        resulting visualization is often not possible and so the process is split
                        into two parts: Manipulation of the interface followed by the generation of
                        a static visualization image as an end result. The image does not contain
                        any information on how the scholar got there and what other possible visual
                        configurations might have been possible by changing the parameters and the
                        data used.</p>
                    <p>Static visualization images produced by visualization tools are decoupled
                        from the raw text and the modeled text data (produced by the scholar and/or
                        an algorithm), neither allowing a direct manipulation of the data, nor a
                        back-and-forth between data and text.</p>
                    <p>Other software applications for example <title rend="italic">Voyant
                            Tools</title><note><ref target="https://voyant-tools.org/"
                                >https://voyant-tools.org/</ref></note> offer a coexistence of text
                        and data in one user interface, thereby creating the general possibility for
                        hermeneutic process. A constant movement between text and data is a
                        prerequisite formulated by the holistic premise and as a representation of
                        the data the visualization should be tightly linked to the text and allow to
                        view text and visualization side-by-side or at least enable quick changes
                        between these two views. In order to enable that we need to take into
                        account not only the visualization but the user interface surrounding
                            it.<note>These insufficiencies which many tools have in common do not
                            prevent hermeneutic practice with them entirely. Literary scholars
                            practicing an hermeneutic approach have found workarounds to enable a
                            critical handling of these visualization tools despite their
                            shortcomings.</note> Most of these tools need to be bent to comply with
                        hermeneutic practice. Especially the third premise, the dependency between
                        recipient and text and how it could be represented, has only started to
                        become an object of special attention in the digital humanities (cf. <ptr
                            target="#drucker2018"/>, <ptr target="#binder2014"/>, <ptr
                            target="#theron2018"/>, <ptr target="#piotrowski2019"/>).</p>
                    <p>A special use case of visual text analysis is annotation visualization. As
                        Jannidis et al. <ptr target="#jannidis2017" loc="256"/> explain: <quote
                            rend="inline">The creation of annotation categories, the discovery of
                            corresponding phenomena and the enrichment with appropriate annotations
                            is part of the hermeneutical analysis process.</quote> Meister <ptr
                            target="#meister2020"/> even claims, that we need to understand
                        annotation as <quote rend="inline">a <q>methodological mediator</q> that can
                            prove the connectivity of digital methods also and especially for
                            traditionally hermeneutically oriented literary scholars.</quote>
                        Baumann et al. <ptr target="#baumann2020" loc="276"/> give a differentiated
                        overview of current approaches to annotation visualization. But what we
                        think has not yet been sufficiently considered in visualization approaches
                        is the hermeneutic profit of annotation following Gius &amp; Jacke <ptr
                            target="#giusjacke2017" loc="236"/>. The authors refer to Piez’s <ptr
                            target="#piez2010"/> conception of a hermeneutic markup: <quote
                            rend="block">By <q>hermeneutic markup</q> I mean markup that is
                            deliberately interpretive. It is not limited to describing aspects or
                            features of a text that can be formally defined and objectively
                            verified. Instead, it is devoted to recording a scholar’s or analyst’s
                            observations and conjectures in an open-ended way.</quote></p>
                    <p>According to Gius &amp; Jacke, what constitutes Piez’s approach to
                        hermeneutical markup is that it is precisely the polyvalence and context
                        sensitivity of literary texts that are taken into account. In order for
                        visualizations to meet hermeneutical requirements, they need to be linked to
                        annotations as interpretative endeavors [cf. <ptr target="#zirker2017"/>,
                            <ptr target="#nantke2020"/>]. Polyvalence in particular is not only the
                        decisive feature of interpretative data. Rather, the acknowledgement of
                        polyvalence is one of the conceptual requirements that need to be taken into
                        account in the sense of our hermeneutical premises when using
                        visualizations. This is also linked to the distinction of data and capta, as
                        emphasized by Drucker. In other words, in order to serve this purpose of
                        polyvalence, hermeneutic visualizations must value the performative and
                        theoretical aspect of an interpretative endeavor (modelling, theorizing,
                        critique and discourse) higher than the declarative visual output (results,
                        experimental validation, applicability).</p>
                    <p>We have now discussed approaches of digital hermeneutics and data
                        visualization against the background of our premises. Based on our research
                        approach, the question now arises which requirements visualizations have to
                        fulfill in order to support hermeneutic interpretation processes. For this,
                        we will propose the four postulates that help creating and embedding such
                        visualizations into a user interface.<note>In our understanding hermeneutic
                            visualizations have to be developed with respect to the user interface
                            that is holding these visualizations. To be able to reconfigure, explore
                            and form arguments with hermeneutic visualizations there has to be a
                            user interface surrounding these visualizations that is oriented towards
                            the hermeneutic process as a whole and allows the manipulation of the
                            visualizations as well as the arrangement of them.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3. Hermeneutic Visualization: Four Postulates</head>
                <p>As we have seen, one issue of the current approaches to digital hermeneutics is
                    the disregard of the epistemological premises of hermeneutics, i.e., the
                    differentiation between intention of author and text, the holistic idea of the
                    understanding of the whole and its parts (circularity of the interpretation
                    process), as well as the dependency between the text and the recipient
                    (subjective and context-dependent reasoning process). Second, the visualizations
                    used in the DH seem to contradict the hermeneutical premises. We see a
                    distortion of the hermeneutic interpretation process, for example, in the use of
                    visualizations that do not take into account the polyvalence of interpretative
                    data. However, in order for visualizations to be used as the missing link in the
                    process of <soCalled>becoming hermeneutical</soCalled> in the digital
                    humanities, we need a concept of visualizations that meets the following four
                    postulates as guidelines: <title rend="italic">Two Way Screen, Quality, Parallax
                        and Discourse</title>. We understand these postulates as transformers of and
                    mediators between the theoretical hermeneutic model and the concrete visual
                    arrangement.</p>
                <p> The postulate of the <title rend="italic">Two Way Screen</title> refers to the
                    interface, which should not be restricted to rendering, but allow manipulation
                    as well. More precisely, a commitment to the <title rend="italic">Two Way
                        Screen</title> implies that the screen serves as an interactive and visual
                    environment in which interpretation (ranging from low-level annotation and
                    structuring to high-level theorizing activity) takes place, not only gets
                    displayed [cf. <ptr target="#drucker2018" loc="252"/>].</p>
                <p>The structure of the interface does not serve as a mere representation space for
                    an interpretative result. Rather, the interface provides incentives to engage
                    and to change bidirectionally between the representation of text data and the
                    modelling of text data. This means that actions taken by changing any graphical
                    feature as an act of interpretation are registered as new data and/or as changes
                    in the data model on the fly. The underlying principle is to get away from the
                    flat screen as a space of display by acknowledging the additional dimension of
                    interpretative activity [cf. <ptr target="#drucker2016"/>]. The postulate of the
                        <title rend="italic">Two Way Screen</title> is based on the holistic
                    premise, as it allows a continuous shift between exploring the visualization to
                    learn something about the text (the whole) and applying that new knowledge to
                    change text data (the part), in consequence, creating new representations. Here,
                    as well as in the postulate of <title rend="italic">Quality</title>, the
                    constructedness of the data becomes apparent and we can grasp it <quote
                        rend="inline">as capta, taken and constructed</quote>
                    <ptr target="#drucker2011"/>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Drucker <ptr target="#drucker2016"/>: Conception of the Two-Way-Screen
                        (draft originated in the 3DH project)</head>
                    <figDesc>A hand-drawn representation of a 3DH project showing the relationship
                        between data and the display.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>While the postulate of the <title rend="italic">Two Way Screen</title> formulates
                    the necessity of providing means for changing and constructing interpretative
                    data through the visualization, it does not specify how the data might be
                    visually represented. To this end, the postulate of <title rend="italic"
                        >Quality</title> demands the incorporation of the epistemological qualities
                    of hermeneutic practice into the visualization. Responding to the hermeneutic
                    premise of the dependency between text and recipient, <title rend="italic"
                        >Quality</title> takes into account the subjective and contextual quality of
                    the data by showing the annotated text data as <emph>capta</emph>. We suggest an
                    extension of the use of Bertin’s visual variables (position, color, tone, size,
                    shape etc.) [cf. <ptr target="#bertin1983"/>; <ptr target="#meirelles2019"
                        loc="175"/>] to the encoding of <emph>capta</emph>, allowing literary
                    scholars to express interpretative dimensions like salience or relatedness [cf.
                        <ptr target="#drucker2018" loc="249"/>].</p>
                <p>The third postulate of <title rend="italic">Parallax</title> stresses the
                    importance of providing multiple views on the object of hermeneutic inquiry [cf.
                        <ptr target="#drucker2018" loc="260"/>]. The term
                        <foreign>parallax</foreign>
                    <quote rend="inline">(Greek παράλλαξις (parallaxis)), meaning
                        <q>alternation</q></quote> [cf. <ref
                        target="https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/parallax">Oxford
                        English Dictionary</ref>] is a metaphorized <foreign>terminus
                        technicus</foreign> of optics. We understand Parallax as visual
                    multiperspectivity or multiple points of view that reveal the ambiguity of a
                    text. Coles <ptr target="#mccurdy2016"/> stresses the aesthetic importance of
                    the <quote rend="inline">ambiguity of meaning</quote> in contrast to scientific
                    replicability. Ambiguity, as Berndt <ptr target="#berndt2009" loc="122"/> points
                    out, <quote rend="inline">denotes a fundamental ‘equivocalness’ that engenders
                            <q>uncertainty</q> and <q>doubt</q>.</quote> The visualization in its
                    parallax function, hence, provokes an ambiguity of a maybe
                        <soCalled>assumed</soCalled> certainty or evidence. This provocation
                    generated by the visualization relates to the premise of dependency between text
                    and recipient once more and puts the situatedness and partialness of the
                    hermeneutic reasoning process into effect. Moreover, the ambiguity evokes a
                        <quote rend="inline">questionability whose astonishment gives cause to
                        further research</quote>
                    <ptr target="#mersch2009" loc="111"/>. Instead of limiting the points of view,
                    the postulate of <title rend="italic">Parallax</title> increases the possibility
                    for productive contradiction in the reasoning process.</p>
                <p>The last postulate <title rend="italic">Discourse</title> defines the role of the
                    visualization in the argumentation. Following Latour <ptr target="#latour1986"
                    />, who claims that <quote rend="inline">the ways in which we represent our
                        arguments changes the way in which we argue</quote> (cf. <ptr
                        target="#hinrichs2017"/>), we think that a hermeneutic visualization fosters
                    the critical reflection of the hermeneutic process itself. An argumentation
                    comprised of text as well as visualizations as single observations differs from
                    the mere textual form. The connection between visualization, annotations (the
                    object of study) and textual arguments enables a complex, non-linear movement
                    between these entities that does not restrict scholars to one possible reading,
                    but allows a multitude of readings. Furthermore, the direct connection between
                    annotations and visualizations creates a transparency of individual arguments
                    that invites the author as well as the audience to critically reflect the
                    argumentation. In this way, it lives up to the evaluation criteria rigor,
                    intersubjectivity and validation mentioned in 2.1 and leads to an iterative
                    refinement of the argumentation and an oscillation between part and whole,
                    addressing the holistic premise in that way.</p>
                <p>The postulates describe four interrelated aspects, under which visualizations can
                    be beneficial for the hermeneutic process in the digital realm and act as
                    hermeneutic visualizations. In the next part, we would like to underpin their
                    validity by presenting their exemplary application in an interface concept and
                    its prototypical implementation.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4. The Four Postulates Used as Guidelines for Prototypical
                    Implementation</head>
                <p>Referring to Boot’s <ptr target="#boot2009"/> model of <emph>mesotext</emph> as a
                    particular configuration of annotations (<emph>mesodata</emph>) that relates to
                    the primary text, as well as to the secondary text (an article for example), we
                    incorporated a tripartite user interface in our concept. There is a text area on
                    the left side holding the primary text a scholar is studying, a canvas in the
                    middle that can represent different configurations of annotations of the text
                    with different visualizations and a views area on the right side that allows a
                    scholar to build arguments by saving different views of canvasses with tags and
                    comments assigned to them (Fig. 2). All these parts are connected with each
                    other, so that interacting with one part of the interface, such as a mouse hover
                    over an annotation in the text area, leads to a highlight of that annotation in
                    the canvas area (or highlight of the visually represented annotation,
                    respectively).</p>
                <p>Our concept will be illustrated by screenshots of our prototype <title
                        rend="italic">Stereoscope</title> that implements the most important
                    features of the concept. Stereoscope is a web-based software prototype for
                    visualizing two core processes of literary studies: hermeneutic exploration of
                    textual meaning and construction of arguments about texts. In Stereoscope
                    scholars can represent their manually created digital annotations with multiple
                    visualizations to record and convey qualitative statements.<note><ref
                            target="http://stereoscope.threedh.net/"
                            >http://stereoscope.threedh.net/</ref></note> In this article, we use a
                    German-based text, but Stereoscope can be applied to texts in other languages,
                    too.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>User interface of the Stereoscope prototype with
                            <soCalled>overlays</soCalled> layout selected</head>
                    <figDesc>A screenshot of a Stereoscope scatter plot of various colored circles
                        in clusters.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                </figure>
                <div>
                    <head>Text</head>
                    <p>The area on the left side shows the primary text a scholar is working on and
                        the parts of the text that have already been annotated. Hovering over
                        annotations produces a pop-up that informs about the categories of the
                        annotations for the respective text passage. Annotations can be saved to a
                        selection by clicking them. A toggle switch at the top of the text area
                        allows scholars to switch between the linear text view and a view of the
                        selected annotations.</p>
                    <p>The prototype allows to upload a text file together with an annotation file
                        created by the software <title rend="italic">CATMA</title>. For practical
                        purposes the prototype was developed to work with the CATMA format, however,
                        a compatibility with other formats would be desirable.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Canvas</head>
                    <p>The canvas is the larger area in the middle of the interface that serves as a
                        plane for creating configurations expressed through visualizations. Each
                        visualization contains circles of different sizes that represent
                        annotations. We call these circles <emph>glyphs</emph>. Their size informs
                        the length of individual annotations. While the circles themselves are
                        immutable, the position of glyphs on the canvas can change depending on the
                        visualization layout scholars have selected. Furthermore, different types of
                        relationships between annotations can be expressed with connecting lines
                        between glyphs. Currently, there is only one type of relationship that
                        depicts the degree of textual proximity of text passages in the
                            <emph>overlaps</emph> layout.</p>
                    <p>When hovering over a glyph a little pop-up reveals the type of annotation
                        category. The category is also expressed by the color of the circle.
                        Clicking on a glyph causes the text area to scroll to the corresponding
                        annotated text passage. Analogous to the text area, alt-clicking on glyphs
                        allows scholars to collect annotated text passages that can be viewed in the
                        text area in the selected <emph>annotations</emph> mode (Fig. 3).</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Selected annotations mode: Collected annotations shown on the left and
                            corresponding glyphs highlighted on the canvas</head>
                        <figDesc>Screenshot of a scatter plot with various colored circles depicting
                            glyphs.</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Using the scroll wheel of the mouse or a pinch gesture on the track pad
                        visualizations can be zoomed in and out of and parts of the visualization
                        can be moved into focus.</p>
                    <p>Above the canvas area different controls allow scholars to change the layout,
                        show and hide panels and labels and export the current view as an image. We
                        call the current state of the visualization on the canvas a
                            <soCalled>view</soCalled>.</p>
                    <p>There are three selectable panels for filtering by annotation category,
                        adding comments to a canvas view, and adjusting settings for individual
                        visualizations. When activated, these overlay the canvas in the bottom half
                        (Fig. 4). Scholars can currently select from three different types of
                        visualizations: grid, scatterplot, and overlaps (network diagram). These
                        visualizations are integrated into the prototype as template files and the
                        list can be extended to incorporate further visualization techniques.
                        Scholars are encouraged to add new visualizations that are suited to their
                        individual research questions and needs.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Panels filter, comment and layout shown with three categories selected
                            in the filter panel (Annotated text not falling under these categories
                            is grayed out in the text area)</head>
                        <figDesc>A screenshot of a scatter plot with various colored
                            circles.</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Views</head>
                    <p>The narrow column on the right side offers space for saving different views
                        of the canvas as small thumbnails. Each view in this area consists of a
                        miniature static image of the selected layout for the view, a title, the
                        name of the layout, tags, and a button to assign tags. If a comment has been
                        written for a particular canvas, it is shown here as well. The currently
                        selected view is marked by an orange border. All manipulations of the
                        canvas, like selected filters or glyphs, adjusted settings or a change in
                        zoom state are saved automatically for each view and are re-established,
                        when scholars click on other canvasses to switch to them.</p>
                    <p>Clicking the plus sign at the top opens a dialog window for adding a new
                        view. Here, title, layout, and comment can be filled in. All the comments
                        assigned to the views can be searched with a search field at the top. Typing
                        something in there filters the list of views, fading out views that do not
                        contain comments that match the search term. If tags have been assigned to
                        views, clicking on one of them filters the list with the respective tag. In
                        that way, either ad-hoc search strings or tags can be used to create
                        temporary subselections of the list. Individual views can also be exported
                        as images.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Using the four postulates as guidelines for implementation</head>
                    <p>In this section, we will elaborate on the concrete development of a prototype
                        using the four postulates. Naturally, this prototypical implementation is
                        exemplary and not exhaustive. There are alternative ways of adhering to the
                        postulates when developing a user interface.</p>
                    <p>As described in the previous part, understanding annotations as
                            <emph>capta</emph> rather than data, we accounted for this in the
                        interface of the prototype with the possibility of assigning different
                        attribute values to selected annotations (or glyphs, respectively). This is
                        exemplified with two attributes scholars can add: certainty and importance.
                        Both attributes take values on a scale from 1 to 5. Setting these values
                        changes the appearance of the glyphs and saves the changes in the underlying
                        JSON format (see Fig. 5). The altered JSON file can be downloaded for each
                        individual view (by clicking on the respective icon on the thumbnail image
                        in the views area). This functionality provides an example of the postulate
                        of the <title rend="italic">Two Way Screen</title>, that could be extended
                        to further functionality, like assigning other attributes or the change of
                        categories, for example. Generally, when thinking about applying our concept
                        to a full-fledged software tool, it would be desirable to integrate full
                        annotation functionality into the system, while allowing the manipulation of
                        annotation metadata via text as well as visualization.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Changing certainty and importance values changes the appearance of the
                            glyphs and writes these changes to the JSON file</head>
                        <figDesc>A screenshot of a scatterplot showing one annotation.</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>When assigning certainty or importance values scholars create a qualitative
                        statement about the epistemic status of annotations, in that way addressing
                        the <title rend="italic">Quality</title> postulate. Qualitative statements
                        are not restricted to the individual annotation. Adding comments and tags to
                        views offers a way of making qualitative assessments about a particular
                        configuration of annotations or collection of configurations, respectively
                        (Fig. 6).</p>
                    <p>In the prototype, visualizations are always based on an automatic structuring
                        algorithm, be it the two scales of the scatterplot or the forces operating
                        in the network layout. In addition to it, the interface concept also
                        includes a functionality that allows scholars to define the spatial
                        structures themselves, for example, by positioning glyphs freely on the
                        canvas or allowing to group them by encircling them with lines drawn on the
                        canvas. Interacting with the glyphs on the canvas in such a way could also
                        be a way to offer meta annotations.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Canvas with assigned comment and tags (Tags visible in the views area
                            on the right side)</head>
                        <figDesc>A screenshot of a visualization showing a network with various
                            colored circles connected by lines.</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In the most basic way, the postulate of <title rend="italic">Parallax</title>
                        is accomplished by presenting annotations in the context of the surrounding
                        text in a linear fashion side by side with the different non-linear
                        configurations represented by the visualization layouts. Furthermore, with
                        the views area on the right side of the prototype it becomes possible to
                        compare different configurations with each other by switching between them.
                        On another level, the ambiguity mentioned in the postulate is exemplified by
                        the certainty attribute values assigned to glyphs. When looking at a
                        particular visualization on the canvas, the filter and settings panel allow
                        scholars to change the foundation for the representation, for example, by
                        showing only certain categories of annotations in the visualization or to
                        change parameters regarding the visualization layout (Fig. 7).</p>
                    <p>The views column on the right side of the interface responds to the <title
                            rend="italic">Discourse</title> postulate. Here, scholars are encouraged
                        to build an argumentation out of visualizations (views) and texts (comments)
                        as single observations.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head><soCalled>Enclosed</soCalled> lines deselected in the settings panel
                            (bottom right) for the overlaps layout</head>
                        <figDesc>A screenshot of a visualization of overlaps of various colored
                            circles.</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Tags assigned to views provide a structuring mechanism that can be used to
                        form different argumentations out of the same views, thus presenting
                        different possible readings to compare with each other.</p>
                    <p>Scholars can jump between views and, by clicking on them, in that manner read
                        the argumentation in a non-linear way. By investigating individual views
                        they can follow the argument down to the specific annotations in the text
                        that constitute the foundation for the argument. This possibility to drill
                        down creates a transparency in the argumentation that allows critical
                        reflections on the rigor, intersubjectivity, and validation of the
                        argumentation. Figure 8 shows the usage of several views for different
                        argumentations (Fig. 8).</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>A scholar scrolls through views belonging to two different
                            argumentations (three leftmost images). In the right image the tag
                                <title rend="quotes">Häufungen und Lücken</title> representing one
                            of the two argumentations has been selected.</head>
                        <figDesc>A screenshot showing varies views of the interface.</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5. Conclusions</head>
                <p>In this article, we suggested four postulates as guidelines for developing
                    hermeneutic visualizations. The resulting visualizations are designed to promote
                    the connection of digital literary hermeneutics with digital approaches, since
                    they address the epistemological premises of hermeneutics, as we have shown in
                    our exemplary prototypical implementation guided by the postulates.</p>
                <p>Looking at the hermeneutic visualizations in the prototype, one might notice that
                    they have an appearance similar to traditional visualizations. This leads us
                    back to the question formulated in the introduction: What do hermeneutic
                    visualizations look like? In other words: Are we able to name distinctive
                    qualities of hermeneutic visualizations?</p>
                <p>The answer to this is to be found in the nature of hermeneutic theory expressed
                    by the three premises and operationalized by the four postulates. While
                    certainty and importance are typical examples of partial, contextual, and
                    subjective knowledge and are expressed with the help of visual variables in the
                    prototype, the central holistic premise demands an iterative, circular process
                    of generating meaning and forming arguments that becomes visible in the
                    structure of the user interface, but not primarily in individual
                    visualizations.</p>
                <p>Future implementations might put a stronger focus on the premise of the
                    dependency between text and recipient (represented by the <title rend="italic"
                        >Qualitative</title> and <title rend="italic">Parallax</title> postulate),
                    which might result in more examples of visual variables depicting partial,
                    contextual and subjective knowledge or even completely new visualizations.
                    Newness for its own sake, however, has not been our concern here.</p>
                <p>Although the presented prototype has been iteratively developed and reviewed by
                    the researchers within our team based on a real-world hermeneutic scenario
                    (Interpretation of Franz Kafka’s <title rend="italic">In der
                        Strafkolonie</title>), we are interested to learn more about other scholars’
                    experience with the prototype in order to further study the appropriateness of
                    the postulates and the idea of hermeneutic visualization. To this end, the
                    prototype has been launched on a website for other scholars to use.<note><ref
                            target="http://threedh.janerikstange.com/"
                            >http://threedh.janerikstange.com/</ref> (temporary domain)</note> In
                    addition, the source code has been published on BitBucket<note><ref
                            target="https://github.com/janerikst/stereoscope"
                            >https://github.com/janerikst/stereoscope</ref></note> in order to give
                    interested scholars the opportunity to contribute to the development. Being
                    aware that our prototype cannot address all eventualities of hermeneutic
                    activity, we deemed it important to enable scholars to extend the repertoire of
                    hermeneutic visualizations that can be used as arguments. The source code
                    provides a visualization template that can be used to develop other
                    visualizations. Following Hinrichs et al. <ptr target="#hinrichs2019"/>, we
                    encourage scholars to come up with new visualizations and adjust existing
                    hermeneutic practices, in that way building <soCalled>sandcastles</soCalled> and
                    experimenting with hermeneutic visualizations. The prototype itself necessarily
                    has to be a generic tool, that is capable of supporting a diverse range of
                    hermeneutic scenarios.</p>
                <p>Finally, we hope that our research might inspire other researchers to investigate
                    what premises need to be considered in order for visualization to benefit other
                    interpretative approaches. Since some attributes like ambiguity are not specific
                    to hermeneutics, but common to all theories of interpretation, this research
                    might serve as a starting point for the development of respective approaches in
                    other areas.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>6. Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>The research and the software prototype Stereoscope was developed as part of the
                    3DH project <title rend="italic">Three-Dimensional Dynamic Data Visualisation
                        and Exploration for digital humanities Research</title> at the University of
                    Hamburg (04/2016–12/2018).<note><ref target="http://threedh.net/"
                            >http://threedh.net/</ref></note> The project is conducted by Jan
                    Christoph Meister. Associated members are Marian Dörk (University of Applied
                    Sciences Potsdam), Johanna Drucker (University of California), Evelyn Gius (TU
                    Darmstadt), Geoffrey Rockwell (University of Alberta), Florian Windhager (Danube
                    University Krems).</p>
                <p>Furthermore, we would like to thank Jan Christoph Meister, Jan Horstmann and
                    Marian Dörk for comments and suggestions on this paper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>7. Links</head>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Article <title rend="quotes">Parallax</title> in <title rend="italic"
                            >Oxford English Dictionary</title>. Available at: <ref
                            target="https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/parallax"
                            >https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/parallax</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="https://voyant-tools.org/"
                        >https://voyant-tools.org/</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="https://github.com/computationalstylistics/stylo"
                            >https://github.com/computationalstylistics/stylo</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="https://gephi.org/">https://gephi.org/</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="http://tapor.ca">http://tapor.ca</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="http://threedh.net/">http://threedh.net/</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="http://catma.de/">http://catma.de/</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="https://github.com/janerikst/stereoscope"
                            >https://github.com/janerikst/stereoscope</ref></item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="albrecht2015" label="Albrecht et al. 2015">Albrecht, A., Danneberg,
                    L., Krämer, O., Spoerhase, C., (eds.) (2015). <title rend="italic">Theorien,
                        Methode und Praktiken des Interpretierens</title>. Berlin: de
                    Gruyter.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="anderson2008" label="Anderson 2008">Anderson, C. (2008). <title
                        rend="quotes">The End of Theory: The Data Deluge Makes the Scientific Method
                        Obsolete</title>, in <title rend="italic">Wired</title>, 23/06/2008.
                    Available at: <ref target="https://www.wired.com/2008/06/pb-theory/"
                        >https://www.wired.com/2008/06/pb-theory/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="armaselu2017" label="Armaselu et al. 2017">Armaselu, F., van den
                    Heuvel, C., (2017). <title rend="quotes">Metaphors in Digital Hermeneutics:
                        Zooming through Literary, Didactic and Historical Representations of
                        Imaginary and Existing Cities</title>, in <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital
                        Humanities Quarterly</title>, 11(3). Available at: <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/3/000337/000337.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/3/000337/000337.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barbot2019" label="Barbot et al. 2019">Barbot L., Fischer, F.,
                    Moranville, Y., Pozdniakov I. (2019). <title rend="quotes">Which DH Tools are
                        actually used in Research?</title>, in weltliteratur.net, A Black Market for
                    the digital humanities, Available at: <ref
                        target="https://weltliteratur.net/dh-tools-used-in-research/"
                        >https://weltliteratur.net/dh-tools-used-in-research/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="baumann2020" label="Baumann et al. 2020">Baumann, M., Koch, S., John,
                    M., Ertl, T. (2020). <title rend="quotes">Interactive Visualization for
                        Reflected Text Analytics</title>, in Reiter, N., Pichler, A., Kuhn, J.
                    (eds.) <title rend="italic">Reflektierte algorithmische Textanalyse.
                        Interdisziplinäre(s) Arbeiten in der CRETA-Werkstatt</title>, Berlin: de
                    Gruyter, pp. 269-296.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="berndt2009" label="Berndt 2009">Berndt, F. (2009). <title
                        rend="quotes">In the Twilight Zone. Ambiguity and Aesthetics in
                        Baumgarten</title>, in Berndt, F., Kammer, S. (eds.) <title rend="italic"
                        >Amphibolie, Ambiguität, Ambivalenz</title>. Würzburg: Königshausen &amp;
                    Neumann, pp. 121-137.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bertin1983" label="Bertin 1983">Bertin, J. (1983). <title
                        rend="italic">Semiology of Graphics: Diagrams, Networks, Maps</title>.
                    Madison: University of Wisconsin Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="binder2014" label="Binder et al. 2014">Binder, F., Entrup, B.,
                    Schiller, I., Lobin, H. (2014). <title rend="quotes">Uncertain about
                        Uncertainty: Different ways of processing fuzziness in digital humanities
                        data</title>, in <title rend="italic">Conference Abstracts</title>, DH2014,
                    pp. 95-98. Available at: <ref target="https://d-nb.info/1164023926/34"
                        >https://d-nb.info/1164023926/34</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="boot2009" label="Boot 2009">Boot, P. (2009). <title rend="italic"
                        >Mesotext: digitised emblems, modelled annotations and humanities
                        scholarship</title>. Amsterdam: Amsterdam University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bradley2008" label="Bradley 2008">Bradley, J. (2008). <title
                        rend="quotes">Thinking about interpretation: Pliny and scholarship in the
                        humanities</title>, in <title rend="italic">Literary and linguistic
                        computing</title>, 23(3), pp. 263-279.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="card1999" label="Card et al. 1999">Card, S., Mackinlay, J.,
                    Shneiderman, B. (1999). <title rend="italic">Readings in information
                        visualization: Using vision to think</title>. San Francisco:
                    Kaufmann.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chamber2006" label="Chamber, Gregory 2006">Chambers, E., Marshall G.
                    (2006). <title rend="italic">Teaching &amp; Learning English Literature</title>.
                    Thousand Oaks: SAGE Publications.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="correll2019" label="Correll 2019">Correll, M. (2019). <title
                        rend="italic">Counting, Collaborating, and Coexisting: Visualization and the
                        digital humanities</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://mcorrell.medium.com/counting-collaborating-and-coexisting-visualization-and-the-digital-humanities-1bf157400d8"
                        >https://mcorrell.medium.com/counting-collaborating-and-coexisting-visualization-and-the-digital-humanities-1bf157400d8</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="danneberg1995" label="Danneberg 1995">Danneberg, L. (1995). <title
                        rend="quotes">Die Historiographie des hermeneutischen Zirkels: Fake und
                        fiction eines Behauptungsdiskurses</title>, in <title rend="italic"
                        >Zeitschrift für Germanistik</title>, 5(3), pp. 611-624.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="derrida1967" label="Derrida 1967">Derrida, J. (1967). <title
                        rend="italic">De la grammatologie</title> [dt. Grammatologie 1974, 2004].
                    Paris: Editions de Minuit, Frankfurt: Suhrkamp.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dork2013" label="Dörk et al. 2013">Dörk, M., Feng P., Collins, C.,
                    Sheelagh C. (2013). <title rend="italic">Critical InfoVis: Exploring the
                        Politics of Visualization</title>, in <title rend="italic">alt.chi
                        2013</title>: Extended Abstracts of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors
                    in Computing Systems, ACM, pp. 2189-2198.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2011" label="Drucker 2011">Drucker, J. (2011). <title
                        rend="quotes">Humanities approaches to graphical display</title>, in <title
                        rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 5(1). Available at:
                        <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2016" label="Drucker 2016">Drucker, J. (2016). <title
                        rend="italic">3DH Visualizations: Three dimensional / digital
                        humanities</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://pages.gseis.ucla.edu/faculty/drucker/3DH_Gallery/Text_3DH_Gallery.html"
                        >https://pages.gseis.ucla.edu/faculty/drucker/3DH_Gallery/Text_3DH_Gallery.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2018" label="Drucker 2018">Drucker, J. (2018). <title
                        rend="quotes">Non-representational approaches to modeling interpretation in
                        a graphical environment</title>, in <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship
                        in the Humanities</title>, 33(2), pp. 248-263.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eemeren2009" label="Eemeren et al. 2009">Eemeren, F., Grootendorst,
                    R., Snoeck Henkemans, A. F. (1996, 2009). <title rend="italic">Fundamentals of
                        argumentation theory : a handbook of historical backgrounds and contemporary
                        developments</title>. New York, London: Routledge [Erlbaum].</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gadamer1990" label="Gadamer 1990">Gadamer, H.-G. (1960, 1990). <title
                        rend="italic">Hermeneutik I. Wahrheit und Methode. Grundzüge einer
                        philosophischen Hermeneutik</title>. Tübingen: Mohr.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galey2010" label="Galey, Ruecker 2010">Galey, A., Ruecker, S. (2010).
                        <title rend="quotes">How a prototype argues</title>, in <title rend="italic"
                        >Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 25(4), pp. 405-424.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gibson2014" label="Gibson 2014">Gibson, J. (2014). <title
                        rend="italic">The ecological approach to visual perception</title>. London:
                    Psychology Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="giusjacke2017" label="Gius and Jacke 2017">Gius, E., Jacke, J. (2017).
                        <title rend="quotes">The hermeneutic profit of annotation: on preventing and
                        fostering disagreement in literary analysis</title>, in <title rend="italic"
                        >International Journal of Humanities and Arts Computing</title>, 11(2), pp.
                    233-254.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gius2017" label="Gius et al. 2017">Gius, E., Kleymann, R., Meister
                    J.C., Petris M. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Datenvisualisierung als
                        Aisthesis</title>, in <title rend="italic">Conference Abstracts</title>, DHd
                    2017, pp. 115-120. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4646123"
                        >http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4646123</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="glinka2017" label="Glinka et al. 2017">Glinka, K., Pietsch, C., Dörk,
                    M. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Past Visions and Reconciling Views: Visualizing
                        Time, Texture and Themes in Cultural Collections</title>, in <title
                        rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 11(2). Available
                    at: <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/2/000290/000290.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/2/000290/000290.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="groarke2017" label="Groarke 2017">Groarke, L. (2017). <title
                        rend="quotes">Informal Logic</title>, in Zalta, E. (ed.) <title
                        rend="italic">The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</title>. Available at:
                        <ref
                        target="https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/spr2017/entries/logic-informal/"
                        >https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/spr2017/entries/logic-informal/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hinrichs2017" label="Hinrichs, Forlini 2017">Hinrichs, U., Forlini, S.
                    (2017). <title rend="quotes">In defense of sandcastles: research thinking
                        through visualization in DH</title>, in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                        the conference on Digital Humanities</title>. International Alliance of
                    Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO). Available at: <ref
                        target="https://dh2017.adho.org/abstracts/133/133.pdf"
                        >https://dh2017.adho.org/abstracts/133/133.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hinrichs2019" label="Hinrichs et al. 2019">Hinrichs, U., Forlini, S.,
                    Moynihan, B. (2019). <title rend="quotes">In defense of sandcastles: Research
                        thinking through visualization in digital humanities</title> in <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 34(1), pp.
                    180-199. DOI: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqy051"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqy051</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jacke2018" label="Jacke 2018">Jacke, J. (2018). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Manuelle Annotation</title>, in <title rend="italic">forTEXT. Literatur
                        digital erforschen</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://fortext.net/routinen/methoden/manuelle-annotation"
                        >http://fortext.net/routinen/methoden/manuelle-annotation</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jahraus2002" label="Jahraus, Neuhaus 2002">Jahraus, O., Neuhaus, S.
                    (eds.) (2002). <title rend="italic">Kafkas <q>Urteil</q> und die
                        Literaturtheorie. Zehn Modellanalysen</title>. Stuttgart: Reclam.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jannidis2003" label="Jannidis et al. 2003">Jannidis, F., Lauer, G.,
                    Martínez, M., Winko, S. (eds.) (2003). <title rend="quotes">Der
                        Bedeutungsbegriff in der Literaturwissenschaft. Eine historische und
                        systematische Skizze</title>, in <title rend="italic">Regeln der Bedeutung.
                        Zur Theorie der Bedeutung literarischer Texte</title>. Berlin: de Gruyter,
                    pp. 3-32.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jannidis2017" label="Jannidis et al. 2017">Jannidis, F., Kohle, H.,
                    Rehbein, M. (eds.) (2017). <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities. Eine
                        Einführung</title>, Stuttgart: Metzler.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jessop2008" label="Jessop 2008">Jessop, M. (2008). <title
                        rend="quotes">Digital Visualization as a scholarly activity</title>, in
                        <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 23(3), pp.
                    281-293.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jessing2007" label="Jeßing, Köhnen 2007">Jeßing, B., Köhnen, R.
                    (2007). <title rend="italic">Einführung in Die Neuere Deutsche
                        Literaturwissenschaft</title>. Stuttgart [u.a.]: Metzler.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kath2015" label="Kath et al. 2015">Kath, R., Schaal, G., Dumm, S.
                    (2015). <title rend="quotes">New Visual Hermeneutics</title>, in <title
                        rend="italic">Zeitschrift für germanistische Linguistik</title>, 43(1), pp.
                    27-51.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kindt1976" label="Kindt, Schmidt 1976">Kindt, W., Schmidt, S. (1976).
                        <title rend="italic">Interpretationsanalysen: Argumentationsstrukturen in
                        Literaturwissenschaftlichen Interpretationen</title>. München: Fink.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kramer2015" label="Krämer 2015">Krämer, O. (2015). <title
                        rend="quotes">Goethes Wahlverwandtschaften in Interpretationen von der
                        Geistesgeschichte bis zum Poststrukturalismus</title>, in Albrecht, A.,
                    Danneberg, L., Krämer, O., Spoerhase, C., (eds.) (2015) <title rend="italic"
                        >Theorien, Methode und Praktiken des Interpretierens</title>. Berlin: de
                    Gruyter, pp. 159-203.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="koppe2013" label="Köppe, Winko 2013">Köppe, T., Winko, S. (2013).
                        <title rend="italic">Neuere Literaturtheorien. Eine Einführung</title>.
                    Stuttgart: Metzler.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="latour1986" label="Latour 1986">Latour, B. (1986). <title
                        rend="quotes">Visualization and Cognition: Drawing Things Together</title>,
                    in <title rend="italic">Knowledge and Society: Studies in the Sociology of
                        Culture Past and Present</title>, 6, pp. 1-40.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="maceachren2012" label="MacEachren et al. 2012 ">MacEachren, A. M.,
                    Roth, R. E., O'Brien, J., Li, B., Swingley, D., Gahegan, M. (2012). <title
                        rend="quotes">Visual semiotics &amp; uncertainty visualization: An empirical
                        study</title>, in <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Visualization
                        and Computer Graphics</title>, 18(12), pp. 2496-2505.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mantzavinos2016" label="Mantzavinos 2016">Mantzavinos, C. (2016).
                        <title rend="quotes">Hermeneutics,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</title> (Fall 2020
                    Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.). <ref
                        target="https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2020/entries/hermeneutics/"
                        >https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2020/entries/hermeneutics/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mccurdy2016" label="McCurdy et al. 2016">McCurdy, N., Lein, J., Coles,
                    K., Meyer, M. (2016). <title rend="quotes">Poemage: Visualizing the Sonic
                        Topology of a Poem</title>, in <title rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on
                        Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>, 22(1), pp. 439–448. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1109/TVCG.2015.2467811"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1109/TVCG.2015.2467811</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mersch2009" label="Mersch 2009">Mersch, D. (2009). <title
                        rend="quotes">The Chiasmus of Language - Six Theses of Language and
                        Alterity</title>, in Berndt, F., Kammer, S. (eds.) <title rend="italic"
                        >Amphibolie, Ambiguität, Ambivalenz</title>. Würzburg: Königshausen &amp;
                    Neumann, pp. 107-120.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="meirelles2019" label="Meirelles 2019">Meirelles, I. (2019). <title
                        rend="quotes">Visualizing information</title>, in Flanders, J., Jannidis, F.
                    (eds.) <title rend="italic">The Shape of Data in the Digital Humanities.
                        Modeling Texts and Text-based Resources</title>. London, New York:
                    Routhledge, pp. S. 167-177.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="meister2017" label="Meister et al. 2017">Meister, J.C., Drucker, J.,
                    Rockwell, G. (2017). <title rend="quotes">Modeling Interpretation in 3DH: New
                        dimensions of visualization</title> in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of
                        the conference on Digital Humanities</title>. International Alliance of
                    Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO). Available at: <ref
                        target="https://dh2017.adho.org/abstracts/058/058.pdf"
                        >https://dh2017.adho.org/abstracts/058/058.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="meister2020" label="Meister 2020">Meister. J.C., (2020). <title
                        rend="quotes">Annotation als Mark-Up avant la lettre</title>, in Jannidis
                    F., Winko, S., Rapp, A., Meister J.C., Stäcker T. (eds.) <title rend="italic"
                        >Digitale Literaturwissenschaft</title>. DFG-Symposium Villa Vigoni, 2017.
                    Berlin, Boston: de Gruyter (to appear).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mittelstrab2008" label="Mittelstraß 2008">Mittelstraß, J. (ed.)
                    (2008). <title rend="italic">Enzyklopädie Philosophie und
                        Wissenschaftstheorie</title>. Vol. 3. Stuttgart: Metzler.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nantke2020" label="Nantke, Schlupkothen 2020">Nantke, J.,
                    Schlupkothen, F. (eds.) (2020). <title rend="italic">Annotations in Scholarly
                        Editions and Research. Functions, Differentiation, Systematization</title>,
                    Berlin, Boston: de Gruyter.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nunning2008" label="Nünning 2008">Nünning, A. (2008). <title
                        rend="italic">Metzler Lexikon Literatur- und Kulturtheorie: Ansätze –
                        Personen – Grundbegriffe</title>. Stuttgart: Metzler.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nunning2010" label="Nünning and Nünning 2010">Nünning, V., Nünning, A.
                    (2010). <title rend="italic">Methoden der literatur- und
                        kulturwissenschaftlichen Textanalyse. Ansätze – Grundlagen –
                        Modellanalysen</title>. Stuttgart: Metzler.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="otoole2018" label="O'Toole 2018">O'Toole, M. (2018). <title
                        rend="italic">The Hermeneutic Spiral and Interpretation in Literature and
                        the Visual Arts</title>. New York: Routledge.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="palmers1969" label="Palmers 1969">Palmers, R. E. (1969). <title
                        rend="italic">Hermeneutics. Interpretation Theory in Schleiermachers,
                        Dilthey, Heidegger, and Gadamer</title>. Evanston: Northwestern University
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piez2010" label="Piez 2010">Piez, W., (2010). <title rend="italic"
                        >Towards Hermeneutic Markup: An architectural outline</title>. Available at:
                        <ref
                        target="http://dh2010.cch.kcl.ac.uk/academic-programme/abstracts/papers/pdf/ab-743.pdf"
                        >http://dh2010.cch.kcl.ac.uk/academic-programme/abstracts/papers/pdf/ab-743.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piotrowski2019" label="Piotrowski 2019">Piotrowski, M. (2019). <title
                        rend="quotes">Accepting and Modeling Uncertainty</title>, in Kuczera, A.,
                    Wübbena, T., Kollatz, T. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Die Modellierung des
                        Zweifels – Schlüsselideen und -konzepte zur graphbasierten Modellierung von
                        Unsicherheiten</title>. Zeitschrift für digitale Geisteswissenschaften.
                    Wolfenbüttel. <ref target="https://zfdg.de/sb004_006">DOI:
                        10.17175/sb004_006a</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piper2020" label="Piper 2020">Piper, A. (2020). <title rend="italic"
                        >Can We Be Wrong? The Problem of Textual Evidence in a Time of Data</title>.
                    Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="radle2000" label="Rädle 2000">Rädle, F. (2000). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Argumentum</title>, in Fricke, H. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Reallexikon
                        der deutschen Literaturwissenschaft</title>. Vol. 1. Berlin: de Gruyter, pp.
                    130-132.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rapp2017" label="Rapp 2017">Rapp, A. (2017). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Manuelle und automatische Annotation</title>, in Jannidis, F., Kohle, H.,
                    Rehbein, M. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities. Eine
                        Einführung</title>. Stuttgart: Metzler, pp. 253-267.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay2007" label="Ramsay 2007">Ramsay, S. (2007). <title
                        rend="quotes">Algorithmic criticism</title>, in Siemens, R., Schreibmann, S.
                    (eds.) <title rend="italic">A Companion to Digital Literary Studies</title>.
                    Oxford: Blackwell. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion/view?docId=blackwell/9781405148641/9781405148641.xml&amp;chunk.id=ss1-6-7&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;toc.id=ss1-6-7&amp;brand=9781405148641_brand"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion/view?docId=blackwell/9781405148641/9781405148641.xml&amp;chunk.id=ss1-6-7&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;toc.id=ss1-6-7&amp;brand=9781405148641_brand</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay2012" label="Ramsay and Rockwell 2012">Ramsay, S., Rockwell, G.,
                    (2012). <title rend="quotes">Developing Things: Notes toward an Epistemology of
                        Building in the Digital Humanities</title>, in Gold, M. (ed.) <title
                        rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/11"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/11</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramberg2005" label="Ramberg, Gjesdal 2005">Ramberg, B., Gjesdal, K.
                    (2005). <title rend="quotes">Hermeneutics</title>, in Zalta, E. (ed.) <title
                        rend="italic">The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</title>. Available at:
                        <ref
                        target="https://stanford.library.sydney.edu.au/archives/sum2010/entries/hermeneutics/"
                        >
                        https://stanford.library.sydney.edu.au/archives/sum2010/entries/hermeneutics/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rese2010" label="Rese 2010">Rese, F. (2010). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Hans-Georg Gadamer</title>, in Martínez, M., Scheffel, M. (eds.). <title
                        rend="italic">Klassiker der modernen Literaturtheorie</title>. München:
                    Beck, pp. 168-190.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rockwell2003" label="Rockwell 2003">Rockwell, G. (2003). <title
                        rend="quotes">What is text analysis, really?</title>, in <title
                        rend="italic">Literary and linguistic computing</title>, 18(2), pp.
                    209-219.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rockwellandsinclair2016" label="Rockwell and Sinclair 2016">Rockwell,
                    G., Sinclair, S. (2016). <title rend="italic">Hermeneutica: Computer-assisted
                        interpretation in the humanities</title>. Cambridge, Massachusetts, London,
                    England: The MIT Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="samuels1999" label="Samuels and McGann 1999">Samuels, L., McGann, J.
                    (1999). <title rend="quotes">Deformance and interpretation</title>, in <title
                        rend="italic">New Literary History</title>, 30(1), pp. 25-56.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="savigny1976" label="Savigny 1976">von Savigny, E. (1976). <title
                        rend="italic">Argumentation in der Literaturwissenschaft</title>. München:
                    Beck.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="scheinfeldt2012" label="Scheinfeldt 2012">Scheinfeldt, T. (2012).
                        <title rend="quotes">Where’s the Beef? Does Digital Humanities Have to
                        Answer Questions?</title>, in Gold, M. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Debates in
                        Digital Humanities</title>. Minnesota: University of Minnesota Press.
                    Available at: <ref target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/18"
                        >http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/18</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schleiermacher1838" label="Schleiermacher 1838">Schleiermacher, F.
                    (1838). <title rend="italic">Hermeneutik und Kritik</title>. Deutsches
                    Textarchiv. Available at: <ref
                        target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/schleiermacher_hermeneutik_1838/8"
                        >http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/schleiermacher_hermeneutik_1838/8</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schwan2019" label="Schwan et al. 2019">Schwan, H., Jacke, J.,
                    Kleymann, R., Stange, J. E., Dörk, M. (2019). <title rend="quotes">Narrelations
                        – Visualizing Narrative Levels and their Correlations with Temporal
                        Phenomena</title>, in <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</title>, 13(3). Available at: <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/3/000414/000414.html"
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/13/3/000414/000414.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="selbmann2002" label="Selbmann 2002">Selbmann, R. (2002). <title
                        rend="quotes">Kafka als Hermeneutiker. Das Urteil im Zirkel der
                        Interpretation</title>, in Jahraus, O., Neuhaus, S. (eds.) <title
                        rend="italic">Kafkas <q>Urteil</q> und die Literaturtheorie. Zehn
                        Modellanalysen</title>. Stuttgart: Reclam, pp. 36-58.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="seifert2014" label="Seifert et al. 2014">Seifert, C., Sabol, V.,
                    Kienreich, W., Lex, E., Granitzer, M. (2014). <title rend="quotes">Visual
                        analysis and knowledge discovery for text</title>, in <title rend="italic"
                        >Large-Scale Data Analytics</title>. New York: Springer, pp. 189-218.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sinclair2013" label="Sinclair et al. 2013">Sinclair, S., Ruecker, S.,
                    Radzikowska, M. (2013). <title rend="quotes">Information Visualization for
                        Humanities Scholars</title>, in Price, K. M., Siemens, R. (eds.). <title
                        rend="italic">Literary studies in the digital age: An evolving anthology.
                        New York: Modern Language Association</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/273450219_Information_Visualization_for_Humanities_Scholars"
                        >DOI: 10.1632/lsda.2013.6</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="spree2000" label="Spree 2000">Spree, A. (2000). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Interpretation</title>, in Fricke, H. (ed.): <title rend="italic"
                        >Reallexikon der deutschen Literaturwissenschaft</title>. Vol. 2. Berlin,
                    New York: de Gruyter, pp. 168-172.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stiegler2015" label="Stiegler 2015 ">Stiegler, B. (2015). <title
                        rend="italic">Theorien der Literatur- und Kulturwissenschaften</title>.
                    Paderborn: Schöningh.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="stiening2016" label="Stiening 2016">Stiening, G. (2016). <title
                        rend="quotes">Hermeneutik. Über die Grenzen des Verstehens und die Gefahren
                        ihrer Missachtung</title>, in Jahraus, O. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Zugänge
                        zur Literaturtheorie</title>. Stuttgart: Reclam, pp. 54-70.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="szondi1995" label="Szondi 1995">Szondi, P. (1995). <title
                        rend="italic">Introduction to literary hermeneutics</title>. Trans. by
                    Martha Woodmansee. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="theron2018" label="Therón et al. 2018">Therón, R., Losada, A. G.,
                    Benito, A., Santamaría, R. (2018). <title rend="quotes">Toward supporting
                        decision-making under uncertainty in digital humanities with progressive
                        visualization</title>, in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Sixth
                        International Conference on Technological Ecosystems for Enhancing
                        Multiculturality</title>, pp. 826-832.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="unsworth2000" label="Unsworth 2000">Unsworth, J. (2000). <title
                        rend="quotes">Scholarly primitives: What methods do humanities researchers
                        have in common, and how might our tools reflect this</title>, in <title
                        rend="italic">Symposium on Humanities Computing: Formal Methods,
                        Experimental Practice</title>. King’s College, London, 3.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="weimar2000" label="Weimar 2000 ">Weimar, K. (2000). <title
                        rend="quotes">Hermeneutik</title>, in Fricke, H. (ed.): <title rend="italic"
                        >Reallexikon der deutschen Literaturwissenschaft</title>. Vol. 2. Berlin,
                    New York: de Gruyter, pp. 25-29.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="winko2003" label="Winko 2003">Winko, S. (2003). <title rend="quotes"
                        >Textanalyse</title>, in Fricke, H. (ed.): <title rend="italic">Reallexikon
                        der deutschen Literaturwissenschaft</title>. Vol. 2. Berlin, New York: de
                    Gruyter, pp. 597-601.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zirker2017" label="Zirker, Bauer 2017">Zirker, A., Bauer, M. (2017).
                        <title rend="quotes">Explanatory Annotation in the Context of the Digital
                        Humanities: Introduction</title>, in <title rend="italic">International
                        Journal of Humanities and Arts Computing - A Journal of Digital
                        Humanities</title>, 11 (2017), pp. 145-152.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zundert2016" label="van Zundert 2016">van Zundert, J. (2016). <title
                        rend="quotes">Screwmeneutics and hermenumericals: the computationality of
                        hermeneutics</title>, in Schreibmann S., Siemens, R., Unsworth J. (eds.)
                        <title rend="italic">A New Companion to Digital Humanities</title>. Oxford:
                    Wiley Blackwell, pp. 331-347.</bibl>

            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
