<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Explicit!: Coding Carceral Censorship and Social
                    Biases in United States Prisons</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Kim <dhq:family>Bobier</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3745-0609</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Pratt Institute and Smithsonian American Art
                        Museum</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>kbobie15@pratt.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Kim Bobier is an Adjunct Assistant Professor in the History of Art and
                            Design Department at Pratt Institute, Lenapehoking/Brooklyn. Her art
                            history work takes a social justice lens, emphasizing critical race
                            studies, Black studies, transnational feminism, surveillance studies,
                            and archives. As a 2025 Pratt Center for Teaching &amp; Learning Faculty
                            Fellow and a 2025-26 Smithsonian Institute Postdoctoral Fellow at the
                            Smithsonian American Art Museum, she is currently at work on forthcoming
                            projects, including her book <title rend="italic">Capturing the Body:
                                Embodying Racializing Surveillance in Contemporary Art</title>.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Sue <dhq:family>Jeong Ka</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>New York University's Asian Pacific American
                        Institute</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>suejeongka@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Sue Jeong Ka is a Lenapehoking/New York-based visual artist whose
                            research-driven practice investigates censorship, surveillance, and
                            systemic erasure. Centering Asian and queer bodies, her work
                            interrogates institutional power while advancing embodied, collective
                            strategies of resistance. Ka is currently developing <title
                                rend="italic">Mapping Carceral Censorship</title> in collaboration
                            with the San Francisco Public Library, UCLA, NYC Books Through Bars, and
                                <title rend="italic">Bad Boundaries</title>, a forthcoming
                            curatorial exhibition at Apex Art that reframes feminist refusal as a
                            critical methodology of survival.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <!-- This information should be added when the file is created -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000803</idno>


                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="volume">019</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2025-09-01">September 1, 2025</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl xml:id="" label="">DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl xml:id="" label="">Keywords supplied by author; no controlled
                        vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
                    <bibl xml:id="" label="">DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/wiki/DHQ-Topic-Keywords; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->

                    <!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new <term> element for each -->
                    <term corresp="#dh"/>
                    <term corresp="#social_justice"/>
                    <term corresp="#databases"/>


                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>socially engaged art</item>
                        <item>censorship</item>
                        <item>prison industrial complex</item>
                        <item>sexual speech</item>
                        <item>art</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Replace "XXXXXX" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
            <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
                    target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000803/000803.xml"
                    >GitHub </ref></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>Social practice artist Sue Jeong Ka’s ongoing digital database, <title
                        rend="italic">Coding Carceral Censorship</title> (CCC) (2019-), charts the
                    United States carceral system’s publication censorship. Ka made data categories
                    to track the knowledge production that US prison book bans target and why.
                    Concentrating on the most common justification for this censorship, sexual
                    explicitness, her initial data analysis reveals restrictive penal trends that
                    devalue women’s and East Asian sexual speech via romance/ erotica literature and
                    manga bans, respectively. These patterns reflect how national white
                    cis-hetero-patriarchal values play an outsized role in determining which types
                    of expression the government protects and prioritizes. Our article argues that
                    through its capacity to identify such under-examined censorship patterns, CCC
                    underscores Digital Humanities’ (DH’s) potential to intervene in and interpret
                    the prison industrial complex’s social biases. CCC’s data indicate that US
                    prison bans enact these biases through excessively barring content by and about
                    marginalized groups, thereby impeding incarcerated people’s access to socially
                    marginalized perspectives and authors. In framing CCC as both critically made DH
                    and part of Ka’s socially engaged art, we further suggest that her database
                    illuminates how DH and socially engaged art practices can be mutually
                    enriching.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Prison staff policing pleasure? The database Coding Carceral Censorship turns dry
                    DOC paperwork into blazing receipts of gender- and race-skewed publication bans
                    on sexual speech. </p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head/>
            <div>
                <head/>
                <p><quote rend="block">The alphabet is an abolitionist. If you would keep a people
                        enslaved, refuse to teach them to read… The despotic spirit which
                        instinctively disliked free schools also sought to exclude books and
                        newspapers except for aristocracy…It struck at the tongue. It abhorred free
                        speech. It knew that knowledge is power, and it trembled (Harper’s Weekly,
                        1867, pp. 706–707).</quote>
                </p>
                <p>What is the relationship between the right to read and abolition? In the
                    aftermath of the United States Civil War, abolitionists argued that institutions
                    continued to disenfranchise formerly enslaved people by limiting their access to
                    reading and education. Correspondingly, throughout US history, censors have used
                    book bans to cut off marginalized groups (e.g., women, people of color, and
                    queer and poor people) from the potential power of knowledge. To be clear,
                    sources of knowledge, such as reading, are not by themselves automatically
                    liberatory. On the one hand, both reading as a way of knowing and particular
                    content read can reinforce ideologies that undermine marginalized peoples’
                    points of view.<note> For instance, critical pedagogy writers Paulo Freire,
                        Donaldo Mercado, and Henry A. Giroux lament the ways in which formal
                        colonial education uses literacy not as tool of liberation or democracy, but
                        instead as one for training students “to reproduce efficiently and
                        unquestioningly the dominant ideology” (Eldred and Mortensen, 1992, pp.
                        516). </note> On the other hand, by reading against the grain, marginalized
                    readers can use even dominant cultural texts to serve their own interests
                    (Ryden, 2005). In short, although reading does not guarantee empowerment,
                    inhibiting it among any population hinders that population’s access to learning,
                    debate, and alternative perspectives. Therefore, prohibiting select groups’
                    reading is a mechanism for minimizing their paths to power. The legacy of
                    restricting marginalized people’s right to read thrives in prisons, where
                    publication censorship practices in the nation are most extreme and opaque
                    (Hall, 2023). In this sense, the shackles of epistemic unfreedom connect
                    historical abolitionist objections to slavery and contemporary abolitionist
                    objections to the prison industrial complex. </p>
                <p>Book banning in the US carceral system is full of inconsistencies but, overall,
                    it consistently favors those with the most power in society while disadvantaging
                    those with the least. This system prohibits publications that its
                    decision-makers deem a threat to orderly conduct (Thornburgh v. Abbott, 1989)
                    (PEN America, 2019).<note> Federal Bureau of Prisons regulations allow for the
                        censorship of books found “to be detrimental to the security, good order,
                        rehabilitation or discipline of the institution.” (Thornburgh v. Abbott,
                        1989, pp. 404-405).</note> Yet criteria for these bans are anything but
                    straightforward. From individual states and prison facilities to prison
                    officials and mailroom staff, there are multiple levels of decision-making that
                    can determine whether a single publication’s content is permissible. At each
                    level, the judgment calls are prone to haphazard logic. Banned prison book lists
                    vary state by state and censorship guidelines vary from one correctional
                    facility to the next within the same region. Moreover, the appeals process is
                    arduous for incarcerated people to navigate while the courts defer to prison
                    administrators. As a result, prison personnel can usually deny books in hasty
                    and unreasonable ways without challenge (PEN America, 2019). This faulty
                    censorship system entails little recourse for incarcerated readers while
                    limiting their resources for knowledge and self-knowledge. Marginalized groups
                    disproportionately comprise the US prison population with the high incarceration
                    rates of people of color, queer people, and poor people’s being well
                        documented.<note> The Sentencing Project, a research and advocacy center
                        with in-depth and relatively up-to-date data analysis on the US prison
                        population, articulates these social disparities through statistics. For
                        instance, a recent Sentencing Project study found “Black men are six times
                        as likely to be incarcerated as white men and Latinx men are 2.5 times as
                        likely” (Nellis, 2023) while another reported that “LGBTQ+ adults are
                        incarcerated at three times the rate of the total adult population”
                        (Ghandnoosh and Stammen, 2022). Such studies often discuss how impoverished
                        conditions predispose people to incarceration. Indeed, the Council of State
                        Governments Justice Center’s work makes clear that a significant majority of
                        incarcerated Americans are financially under-resourced: “two-thirds of
                        people detained in jail report annual incomes under $12,000 prior to arrest”
                        (McLean and Thompson, 2007).</note> Marginalized groups in prison are also
                    hard hit by publication banning biases that hinder their access to
                    self-understanding. In recent years, PEN America and Thurgood Marshall Civil
                    Rights Center have cataloged numerous instances of US prisons targeting material
                    that addresses racial justice, LGBTQAI+ perspectives, and civil and human
                    rights, including content related to the prison industrial complex (2019)
                    (2021). </p>
                <p>The digital database, <title rend="italic">Coding Carceral Censorship</title>
                    (CCC), charts such censorship trends. Since 2019, social practice artist Sue
                    Jeong Ka has been creating this repository of state-wide prison publication bans
                    to visualize and analyze the data. As a work in progress, CCC’s web interface
                    now freely provides visitors structured and synthesized data about prohibited
                    prison publications. Its database records this hard-to-find information with a
                    broader array of publication types and more detail about each publication than
                    any other database that we can locate.<note> Kate Cauley stressed the unmet need
                        for a digital repository with structured data on banned prison books
                        throughout the United States (2020). More recently, the non-profit news
                        organization, The Marshall Project, launched a searchable database on US
                        banned prison books by state. Although useful, this database has far fewer
                        data categories than CCC and does not code authors’ gender or race while it
                        mostly neglects publications that are not books, such as comics, magazines,
                        and journals (The Marshall Project, 2023). </note> Through its breadth and
                    depth, CCC grapples with US prison censorship patterns that reflect national
                    white cis-hetero-patriarchal hierarchies by reframing data from government
                        records.<note> White cis-hetero-patriarchy refers to a system of dominance
                        that simultaneously privileges racial whiteness, cis identity (wherein one
                        self-identifies with the sex one was assigned at birth) heterosexuality
                        (i.e., straight sexuality), and patriarchy (systemic sexism). The hyphenated
                        term emphasizes how these types of dominance intersect with and reinforce
                        one another (Muncaster, 2022, pp. 87). White cis-hetero-patriarchal forces
                        are forces that advantage white, cisgender, heterosexual men and/or that
                        advantage white, cisgender, heterosexual, and patriarchal
                        perspectives.</note> Ka’s project demonstrates how databases can make social
                    biases explicit. </p>
                <p>This article argues that, in so doing, CCC underscores Digital Humanities’
                    potential to intervene in and interpret the prison industrial complex’s white
                    cis-hetero-patriarchal biases. CCC’s preliminary data indicate that US prison
                    bans enact these biases through disproportionately barring content by and about
                    marginalized groups, thereby impeding incarcerated people’s access to
                    marginalized social perspectives. In other words, prisons’ excessive regulation
                    of publications with content centering marginalized groups and by authors from
                    these groups hampers incarcerated readers’ opportunities to engage with views
                    and voices beyond white cis-hetero-patriarchy. Ka’s data categories make such
                    discriminatory censorship policies and practices legible. As later discussed in
                    more depth, these data categories include the censored publications’ titles
                    (from Department of Corrections (DOC) documentation), types, genres, and
                    subgenres (based on American Library Association’s Cataloging and Classification
                    guidelines) (American Library Association, 2024). The categories also cover the
                    social identities of censored publications’ authors (based on the CCC team’s own
                    research into their gender, racial, and ethnic identities), and publication
                    censorship by state and individual correctional facilities as well as the cited
                    reasons for publications’ censored status (based on state legal codes and DOC
                    documentation). CCC’s interactive web displays expressively picture many of
                    these results by visualizing them on different scales and through design
                    elements that connote governmental and carceral data gathering. </p>
                <p>CCC suggests a role for socially engaged art in what the #transformDH collective
                    calls a necessary “shift in focus of digital humanities from technical processes
                    to political ones,” via work that “center[s] on the intersection of digital
                    production and social transformation through research, pedagogy, and activism”
                    (Bailey et al., 2016, pp.71). Socially engaged art (also known as social
                    practice art or art as social practice) refers to process-driven and
                    participatory work that uses the tools of art (sometimes in obvious ways and
                    sometimes in more invisible theoretical or methodological ones) to bring about
                    social change (burrough and Walgren, 2022, pp. 4–5). Definitions vary, but they
                    often attribute collaboration, dialogue, and critical, contextual understanding
                    to this artistic mode (Helguera, 2011, pp.1–8) (Kester, 2005).<note> For
                        instance, Minerva Cuevas’ socially engaged artwork <title rend="italic"
                            >Mejor Vida Corp. </title>(in English <title rend="italic">Better Life
                            Corporation</title>) (1998–) stems from her earlier public interventions
                        in Mexico City. It is a web-based nonprofit corporation that provides a
                        variety of public goods and services. Through this interface, Cuevas has
                        shared “pre-validated subway tickets, pre-paid envelopes for domestic and
                        international mailing, student ID cards that allow users to receive
                        discounted rates, and barcode stickers that reduce the price of food in
                        supermarkets.” <title rend="italic">Mejor Vida Corp. </title>parodies codes
                        of the capitalist market to critique its exploitative tactics while offering
                        a small-scale, free alternative as well as grassroots inspiration to
                        participants who act as the work’s donors, recipients, and/or observers
                        (Thompson, 2012).</note> Accordingly, Ka’s web project operates to
                    precipitate social change by educating its users, in her case, about prison
                    censorship and about the marginalized content producers and consumers it
                    affects. CCC serves as a vehicle for Ka’s wide-ranging work on banned prison
                    publications, extending to art installations and exhibitions, a collective zine
                    series, scholarship (such as this essay), as well as behind-the-scenes and
                    public-facing exchanges with knowledge workers, activists, and artists.<note> Ka
                        began investigating prison censorship for the installation, <title
                            rend="italic">Book Repair Lab: The Jefferson Market Library and the
                            Women's House of Detention </title>(2019-ongoing). Through it, she set
                        up a workstation in The New School’s Kellen Gallery for fixing damaged New
                        York Public Library (NYPL) books on the wish lists of Rikers Correctional
                        Center’s incarcerated residents before redirecting the books to NYPL’s Rose
                        M. Singer Center jail library there. <title rend="italic">Book Repair
                            Lab</title> also traced relationships between the New School, NYPL, and
                        NYC correctional services. This work inspired Ka to continue amassing,
                        aggregating, and analyzing banned publication lists. As shown on her artist
                        website, these activities inform many of Ka’s projects since 2019 (Ka,
                        2025).</note> Ka’s framing of her database clarifies ways that Digital
                    Humanities (DH) and socially engaged art can enhance one another. As a DH
                    project, CCC presents research findings stemming from her socially engaged art
                    in a data-based and accessible manner while, as a socially engaged artist, Ka’s
                    creative handling of her database makes its social justice concerns enticing to
                    explore.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Sue Jeong Ka, <title rend="italic">Book Repair Lab: The Jefferson Market
                            Library and the Women's House of Detention, </title>2019, site-specific
                        installation with book chart, table, second-hand books, and artist’s book,
                        The New School’s Anna-Maria and Stephen Kellen Gallery, New York, New
                        York.</head>
                    <figDesc>In a gallery room, the artist sits at a desk while repairing a used
                        book from the book cart that stands beside her. </figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Direct experiences activating CCC and related undertakings shape our appraisal of
                    it. Ka’s project exemplifies critical making because it departs from the model
                    of an isolated work devised mainly for technical or aesthetic appreciation
                    (Jentery, 2017). Far from self-enclosed, her database is a dynamic platform for
                    artistic production, exchange, study, and activism. To borrow Critical Making
                    Lab Director Matt Ratto’s phrase, through Ka, CCC conducts “ongoing critical
                    analysis” of its own constitutive parts and networks (2011, pp.253).</p>
                <p>Relevant literature underscores DH’s role in enhancing incarcerated people’s
                    access to self-expressive, educational, and entertainment resources.<note> DH
                        projects that engage the prison industrial complex must, however, be
                        vigilant to avoid exposing sensitive personal information of the parties
                        involved and exacerbating incarcerated people’s exploitation. Many
                        technology reporters and librarians recognize this complex’s stakeholders’
                        penchant for weaponizing data and digital tools in such predatory ways
                        (Logic, 2020) (PLSN, 202) (Cahn, 2022) (Kaun and Stiernstedt, 2023).</note>
                    Like CCC, many DH projects about the prison industrial complex harness alluring
                    digital interfaces to raise public awareness about the systems and systematic
                    barriers that diminish incarcerated people’s humanity (Cauley, 2020). For
                    example, the web-based American Prison Writing Archive (APWA) is the US’s
                    largest collection of non-fiction essays by currently incarcerated Americans
                    about their experiences behind bars. The platform grants incarcerated people
                    authorial and editorial power (Larson, 2021). A handful of other digital
                    archives, DH mapping projects, and online pedagogical networks also foreground
                    interactive and data-based storytelling to critique the penal system. Along with
                    APWA, some notable archives include: JSTOR’s American Prison Newspapers: Voices
                    from Inside the Prison; After Violence Archive; The Washington State Prison
                    History Project; and Inside Books Project Archive.<note> Antoni Muntadas’s
                            <title rend="italic">The File Room</title> (1994) does not focus on the
                        carceral context, but as an artistically staged database of censorship
                        cases, the work is a relevant digital archive precedent to CCC. First
                        installed at the Chicago Cultural Center, <title rend="italic">The File
                            Room</title> consisted of a file-cabinet-filled room at the center of
                        which was a computer terminal with an online, open-source database. Through
                        it, users could browse hundreds of accounts of censorship and upload their
                        own (Petito, 2016). <title rend="italic">The File Room</title> now remains
                        and continues to grow as a website.</note> In addition to building on
                    existing projects’ work with state departments’ records to generate CCC’s
                    database, CCC’s Geographical Information System presentation of correctional
                    facilities (explained later) bears similarity with DH projects, such as Million
                    Dollar Hoods and Torn Apart/ Separados, which center carceral geographies to
                    expose their infrastructures. Other DH projects emphasize education, such as
                    Duke University’s Carceral Studies Network website of curricular resources.
                    Together, critical prison industrial complex DH projects span different focal
                    points and strategies but often serve at least one common purpose: to inform the
                    public about this complex’s hidden inner-workings and unjust power dynamics. CCC
                    shares this purpose, while distinguishing itself by charting biases in US prison
                    publication censorship patterns. </p>
                <p>This article describes CCC’s capacity for exposing these under-examined patterns
                    and their underpinning biases. To this end, we concentrate on two findings from
                    the CCC dataset: many states’ prisons restrict romance/erotica and manga
                    publications by labeling them sexually explicit. In what follows, we first
                    introduce these case studies by explaining Ka’s critical making strategies for
                    building a database that renders the information about such bans visible. Our
                    discussion then performs the kind of critical inquiry CCC can facilitate about
                    neglected prison censorship dynamics and social biases therein. This application
                    points to the penal system’s discriminatory tendencies toward publications that
                    are not associated with white, Euro-American, and/or cis-hetero-patriarchal
                    cultural production. Our layered analysis of CCC resonates with its
                    multi-pronged challenge to US prisons’ discriminatory approaches through
                    socially engaged and critically made database design.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>1. CCC as Critical Making</head>
                <p>The CCC database evolved as part of Ka’s artistic reckoning with structural
                    barriers that drastically limit incarcerated people’s access to reading
                    material. Her ongoing examination of this topic shapeshifts in response to each
                    iteration’s analytical focal points, participants, and spaces (physical,
                    virtual, and/or discursive). CCC stems from Ka’s open-ended critical making
                    approach to prison censorship and carceral exchange. In particular, CCC’s
                    information architecture showcases her creative and critical methods for
                    adopting digital formats. It breaks with default web templates to aesthetically
                    convey her database’s conceptual and contextual specificities. As we will
                    detail, CCC presents data in evocative yet orderly geometric compositions,
                    including a matrix presentation that nods to the history of computing via the
                    punch card matrix. </p>
                <div>
                    <head>1.1. CCC’s Information Architecture </head>
                    <p>CCC aims to raise awareness about US carceral information exchange and
                        censorship. This project leans into a data-driven format more than Ka’s
                        previous ones on the same topic, while still maintaining the expressive
                        concerns of her social art practice. She conceived CCC not only as a
                        methodical user-friendly representation of copious data about US prisons’
                        banned publications, but also as a critical entry point into this topic. </p>
                    <p>CCC’s visuals refer to governmental and computational systems of
                        meaning-making. The database uses arrangements of rectangles where each
                        rectangle serves as a data point and signifies a single banned prison
                        publication. Together, the rectangles map US prison bans according to
                        different geographic scopes. For example, Ka’s national display pictures
                        individual publications together through a matrix of rectangles. </p>

                    <figure>
                        <head>View of publications banned in prisons throughout the US<title
                                rend="italic">. </title>Combines Ka’s data on all the states’ prison
                            banned publications spanning 2010 to 2024.<note> Of the 50 states in the
                                US only 26 have prison banned publication lists (i.e., relatively
                                consistent documentation of banned publications in prisons
                                throughout the state). Consequently, CCC data represents only these
                                states. These include Arizona, California, Colorado, Connecticut,
                                Florida, Georgia, Illinois, Iowa, Kansas, Michigan, Minnesota,
                                Mississippi, Missouri, New Hampshire, New Jersey, North Carolina,
                                Oregon, Pennsylvania, South Dakota, Tennessee, Texas, Utah,
                                Virginia, Washington, Wisconsin.</note> Sue Jeong Ka, <title
                                rend="italic">Level 1: The U.S.</title> from<title rend="italic">
                                Banned Books: Coding Carceral Censorship</title>, 2019-, website
                            screenshot. </head>
                        <figDesc>A webpage with a grayscale matrix of rectangles. A cursor hovers
                            over one rectangle that is accompanied by a black pop-up box with
                            publication information indicating that this rectangle represents the
                            prison banned magazine <title rend="italic">Aerospace &amp; Defense
                                Technology.</title></figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>As we will discuss further, Ka uses state legal codes and DOC banned book
                        lists to generate data about which publications prisons in different states
                        censor and why. </p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>iew of publications banned in prisons by state<title rend="italic">.
                            </title>Sue Jeong Ka, <title rend="italic">Level 2: Individual States
                                </title>from<title rend="italic"> Coding Carceral
                            Censorship</title>, 2019-, website screenshot. </head>
                        <figDesc>A webpage showing rectangles that represent Arizona and Colorado
                            prison censored publications organized in columns by state and in rows
                            by the publication’s first letter. </figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        <figure>
                            <head>View of correctional facilities<title rend="italic">. </title>Sue
                                Jeong Ka, <title rend="italic">Level 3: Facilities
                                    </title>from<title rend="italic"> Coding Carceral
                                    Censorship</title>, 2019-, website screenshot. </head>
                            <figDesc>A webpage with a grayscale aerial map showing two Kansas
                                facilities and the number of publications they each ban: Topeka
                                Correctional Facility (23) and Lansing Correctional Facility
                                (82).</figDesc>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                    <p>The database employs a rectangular visualization system to represent banned
                        publications. Clicking on a rectangle reveals a black pop-up box containing
                        the publication’s title, and, if available, author/s, and year. The national
                        view differentiates rectangles by width to signify three primary reasons for
                        banning based on DOC documentation: </p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>View of publications banned in prisons throughout the US with a legend
                            explaining how to read the matrix’s rectangles. Sue Jeong Ka, <title
                                rend="italic">Level 1: The U.S.</title> from<title rend="italic">
                                Coding Carceral Censorship</title>, 2019-, website screenshot. </head>
                        <figDesc>A webpage with a grayscale matrix of rectangles along with a legend
                            of rectangles with three different widths, each of which indicates one
                            of the primary justifications for prison publication censorship: no
                            reason given, mail censorship, and sexually explicit. </figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                    </figure>

                    <p>At the state level, users can apply filters to explore DOC’s additional
                        content-based censorship reasons.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>View of publications banned in prisons by state and censorship reason
                            drop-down menu<title rend="italic">. </title>Sue Jeong Ka, <title
                                rend="italic">Level 2: Individual States </title>from<title
                                rend="italic"> Coding Carceral Censorship</title>, 2019-, website
                            screenshot. </head>
                        <figDesc>The same image as Figure 3, a webpage showing rectangles that
                            represent Arizona and Colorado prison censored publications organized in
                            columns by state and alphabetically, along with a drop-down menu of
                            three different censorship reason types for filtering the view of banned
                            publications. </figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>CCC’s entirely grayscale color palette suggests the governmental paperwork
                        behind its own data collection. Moreover, the database’s matrix composition
                        draws inspiration from the rectangular matrix of punch cards used for
                        proto-computing data processing. Ka thought of Herman Hollerith’s punch
                        card, devised for the eleventh US census of 1890. One such machine-readable
                        punch card represented one US resident’s data. Each hole punch mark within
                        the columns and rows on the card stood for a data point relating to that
                        resident’s characteristics, such as their sex, race, employment, marital
                        status, etc. (Franklin, 2015). </p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Hollerith punch card from the 1890 US Census of Population. Wikimedia.
                            Creative Commons.</head>
                        <figDesc>A paper punch card with columns divided into data fields and some
                            punched data points.</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The 1890 census was the first to rely on mechanical punch cards. In the years
                        leading up to this census, an upsurge in immigration and anxieties about
                        racial mixing following the emancipation of Americans of African descent
                        motivated the US government to adopt a more systematic process for gathering
                        data on its changing population (Hodes 2006, pp.250). The characteristic
                        represented by each punch mark helped normalize reductive concepts of
                        identity. Moreover, as Martha Hodes writes, this card design gave the
                        government data to further exclude those identified with marginalized
                        characteristics from “participation in the full privileges of national
                        citizenship” (Franklin, 2015) (Hodes, 2006, pp. 250).</p>
                    <p>By alluding to Hollerith’s punch card data matrix, CCC recalls techniques of
                        governmental control, discrimination, and disenfranchisement embedded within
                        computation’s legacy — including its prehistory. After inventing his punch
                        card-based tabulation machine for the census, Hollerith founded Tabulating
                        Machine Company, which in 1924 became International Business Machines (IBM)
                        (Franklin, 2015). This corporation continues to have an immense impact on
                        computing technologies today.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>1.2. Navigating Social Identity Categories with CCC</head>
                    <p>Ka’s integration of visual traces from this punch-card-to-IBM trajectory
                        evokes computational methods’ socio-political ramifications. In keeping with
                        these methods, her datasets also rely on social identity categories of race
                        and ethnicity as well as gender. She uses these categories to shed light on
                        racist and sexist censorship practices corresponding to authors’ identities.
                        Nevertheless, like the social categories of the 1890 census, Ka’s are based
                        on hegemonic constructs and do not represent the vast range of ways people
                        self-identify their race, ethnicity, and gender. A lack of preexisting
                        structured data on publication authors self-identification in relation to
                        these attributes is one of the many challenges Ka negotiates when creating
                        her database. Here, as Catherine D'Ignazio and Lauren F. Klein’s remark
                        “[t]he absence of data,” in this case, on authors’ social identities,
                        “becomes an important takeaway, as meaningful as the data themselves” (2020,
                        pp. 113). In the face of this absence, CCC’s team collects their own data on
                        authors’ race, ethnicity, and gender via online research. The team codes
                        each author in the database according to the latest 2020 US census
                        categories of these properties of social identity. This coding method draws
                        on pronouns, names, and other indicators or representations of authors that
                        appear in the authors’ publications and basic online searches. By using such
                        signifiers, the CCC team loosely approximates how prison officials, who are
                        non-expert evaluators of the publications that they decide to censor or not,
                        perceive authors’ race, ethnicity, and gender. Ka’s method for approximating
                        prison officials’ impressions about these properties of identity follows
                        sociological resume studies as well as theories of the perception of both
                        gender and racial categorization (Bertand and Mullainathan, 2004) (Ridgeway,
                        2011, pp.78-79). </p>
                    <p>CCC directly applies the 2020 US census categories of race and ethnicity to
                        its author data but takes more liberties with this census’s binary “sex”
                        categories of male and female. Ka revises them as “gender” categories of men
                        (which includes transmen), women (which includes transwomen), uncertain (for
                        authors whose gender the CCC team cannot determine), non-binary, and
                        publisher (when authorship is not attributed to people but instead the
                        publisher). Whereas sex refers to how people identify biologically, Ka’s
                        shift to gender departs from reductive biologically determined definitions
                        of identity in favor of more inclusive and complex understandings of it.
                        Gender refers to culturally constructed notions of femininity and
                        masculinity that reflect an interplay between a person’s self-presentation
                        and others’ perception of it (Butler, 1990). With the non-binary category,
                        CCC makes space for studying the prison censorship of authors who present as
                        outside the gender binary of man or woman. CCC’s categories still, however,
                        simplify the nuances of gender. The database fails to capture how an
                        author’s gender might change, how people live gender on a spectrum (rather
                        than on static terms), and the great diversity of identifications for gender
                        beyond the binary. Even so, CCC’s five less than ideal gender categories
                        along with its US census racial and ethnicity categories (that likewise
                        overgeneralize group identities) allow the database to highlight gendered
                        and racialized disparities in prison censorship publication practices.</p>
                    <p>Ka also developed a website mechanism for illustrating how race, ethnicity,
                        and gender intersect with censorship practices. To explore banned
                        publication authors by social identity, users can select categories of
                        gender as well as race and ethnicity. These categories each overlay texture
                        visualizations onto the existing data. Additionally, the database includes
                        categories that present DOC designated reasons for each publication’s
                        censorship with another kind of texture.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Close-up view of part of Level 1, showing US prisons banned
                            publications filtered by the Black author category. Sue Jeong Ka, <title
                                rend="italic">Level 1: The U.S.</title> from<title rend="italic">
                                Coding Carceral Censorship</title>, 2019-, website
                            screenshot.</head>
                        <figDesc>A close-up view of a webpage with a grayscale matrix of rectangles,
                            representing individual US prison banned publications, some of which are
                            filled in with a crisscross pattern. Above this matrix, the race and
                            ethnicity menu’s selected Black category indicates that the rectangles
                            filled in with this crisscross pattern are publications by Black
                            authors.</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Close-up view of part of Level 1, showing US prison banned
                            publications filtered by the woman author category. Sue Jeong Ka, <title
                                rend="italic">Level 1: The U.S.</title> from<title rend="italic">
                                Coding Carceral Censorship</title>, 2019-, website
                            screenshot.</head>
                        <figDesc>A close-up view of a webpage with a grayscale matrix of rectangles,
                            representing individual US prison banned publications, some of which are
                            filled in with a striated weave pattern. Above this matrix, the gender
                            menu’s selected woman category indicates that the rectangles filled in
                            with this striated weave pattern are publications by women authors. </figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Combining more than two types of categories (e.g., race &amp; ethnicity,
                        gender, or censorship reasons) will generate a new composite texture. These
                        composite textures visually represent the intersectionality of censorship. </p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Close-up view of part of Level 1, showing US prison banned
                            publications filtered to show those banned for sexually explicitness by
                            Black women authors. Sue Jeong Ka, <title rend="italic">Level 1: The
                                U.S.</title> from<title rend="italic"> Coding Carceral
                                Censorship</title>, 2019-, website screenshot.</head>
                        <figDesc>A close-up view of a webpage with a grayscale matrix of rectangles,
                            representing individual US prison banned publications, some of which are
                            filled in with a horizontal textile-like pattern. Above this matrix, the
                            banned reasons’ selected sexually explicit category, the race and
                            ethnicity menu’s selected Black category and the gender menu’s selected
                            woman category together indicate that the rectangles filled in with this
                            horizontal textile-like pattern are publications banned for sexual
                            explicitness by Black women authors. </figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Ka adopts and adapts governmental categories of identity to hold such social
                        disparities as well as their intersections up for scrutiny. Presently, CCC’s
                        “Design Statement” page articulates the project’s goal of proposing “a new
                        system for aggregating, structuring, and visualizing carceral censorship
                        data that empowers free and incarcerated people along with banned
                        publications’ authors to challenge prison administration overreach, social
                        discrimination, and civil rights violations.” This statement establishes
                        CCC’s intent to provide data in service of marginalized populations. It also
                        marks CCC’s difference from the 1890 census punch card, which served to
                        codify the exclusion of select US demographics. In contrast, by indexing
                        censorship imposed on the nation’s incarcerated readers, Ka’s project calls
                        attention to an excluded US demographic and the governmentally sanctioned
                        biases that condition incarcerated people’s access to knowledge. </p>
                    <p>Ka’s bespoke conceptual website construction undermines the fallacy that DH
                        work either takes up theory or method, critical thinking or technical
                            making.<note> Rather than relying on popular DH Content Management
                            Systems such as Omeka or WordPress, Ka turned to the web platform
                            Angular. Angular provides many kinds of visual languages for programmers
                            to choose from while its coding language of TypeScript allows for
                            intricate web design. Ka used the web interface application Figma to
                            wireframe CCC.</note> CCC’s information architecture intertwines these
                        modes of production with references to the bureaucratic backdrop of its own
                        data and computing’s social legacy. Moreover, this database prompts critical
                        social examination of prison publication bans. CCC’s intersectional
                        visualization capacities not only mark how US carceral censorship affects
                        different identity groups of authors but also invite users to interrogate
                        the power dynamics and biases driving DOC censorship decisions. Ka’s own
                        preliminary CCC data analysis revealed that of all the censorship reasons,
                        DOC across the nation most frequently apply the sexually explicit
                        designation. She found this justification is largely applied to
                        romance/erotica literature (whose censorship mostly impacts women authors)
                        and manga (whose censorship mostly impacts East Asian authors). </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. Censoring Romance/ Erotica and Manga’s Sexual Speech in and beyond US
                    Prisons </head>
                <p>According to our research, these under-examined censorship patterns indicate that
                    standards differentiating between acceptable and unacceptable sexual content are
                    rarely as neutral as they might first appear. Even when the guidelines for
                    banning sexually explicit or obscene content seem unbiased, US authorities’
                    application of them often devalues socially marginalized people and
                    perspectives. The heightened prison censorship of women’s and East Asians’
                    sexual speech via romance/erotica literature and manga we see in Ka’s initial
                    findings offer two telling examples. As previously noted, CCC data derive from a
                    synthesis of sources: DOC materials (such as their banned book lists, their
                    censorship codes, and publication censorship reports) that provide censorship
                    reasons, the CCC team’s research on authors’ identities, and the American
                    Library Association designations for different kinds of publications (such as
                    manga as a type of publication and romance and erotica as genres). CCC’s
                    database provides all the data for the categories and analyses discussed as well
                    as visualized in this article, but CCC’s website does not currently represent
                    all these categories and analyses. </p>
                <p>A close look at CCC’s three most-detailed state datasets reflect broader US
                    prison ban trends. These trends align with those signaled by CCC’s aggregated
                    (if less up-to-date) national data from all states as well as other evidence
                    discussed later in this article, such as DOC censorship guidelines from various
                    states, case studies of specific prison publication bans, and content analysis
                    of such publications.<note> The prison censorship data for the 26 states that
                        CCC represents are not yet all updated through 2024 nor are all the states’
                        datasets as clean as they could be. We feature waffle charts informed by the
                        most accurate data possible based on Ka’s up-to-date and cleaned state
                        datasets — those for California, Oregon, and Virginia. Ka prioritized
                        Oregon’s dataset because its DOC currently bans the most publications of any
                        state in the nation and provides the most detailed censorship documentation.
                        She finalized California’s and Virginia’s datasets in preparation for
                        CCC-related site-specific artwork commissioned for exhibitions in these
                        states. </note> In correctional facilities across Virginia (2,634 banned
                    publications), California (1,695 banned publications), and Oregon (5,936 banned
                    publications, the CCC shows significant DOC censorship of romance and erotica
                    for sexual explicitness, particularly regarding works in these genres authored
                    by women. In general, most romance and erotica authors are women, so it is not
                    surprising that the majority of these states’ prison-censored publications
                    associated with these genres are by women.<note> According to a 2015
                        sociological study, 99 percent of romance authors are “female” (Lois and
                        Gregson, 2015, pp. 464). A more recent report by the non-commercial,
                        international and research data and analytics group WordsRated found that 83
                        percent of romance and erotica books were written by women (Talbot, 2023).
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Prominent censorship patterns related to banned romance/erotica
                            publications in Virginia, California, and Oregon DOC.</head>
                        <figDesc>Waffle charts organized in three rows by state. Every state’s row
                            includes a waffle chart that visualizes each of the censorship
                            percentages described in the below table’s corresponding state
                            row.</figDesc>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure11.png"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <table>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell>State DOC</cell>
                            <cell>Percentage of banned publications that are romance &amp;
                                erotica</cell>
                            <cell>Percentage of banned publications in these genres authored by
                                women</cell>
                            <cell> Percentage of banned woman-authored romance &amp; erotica
                                publications censored for sexual explicitness </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell>
                                <p>Virginia</p>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>38%</cell>
                            <cell>71%</cell>
                            <cell>98%</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell>California</cell>
                            <cell>11%</cell>
                            <cell>52%</cell>
                            <cell> California DOC does not provide censorship reasons </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell>Oregon</cell>
                            <cell>28%</cell>
                            <cell>65%</cell>
                            <cell> 98% </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <p>Likewise, these three same states’ correctional facilities often target manga, a
                    publication type primarily by East Asian authors.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Prominent censorship patterns related to banned manga publications in
                        Virginia, California, and Oregon DOC.</head>
                    <figDesc>Waffle charts organized in three rows by state. Every state’s row
                        includes a waffle chart that visualizes the percent of that state’s DOC
                        banned publications that are manga and the percent of those banned manga by
                        East Asian authors. These percentages correspond to those in the below
                        table.</figDesc>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure12.png"/>
                </figure>

                <table>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell>State DOC</cell>
                        <cell>Percentage of banned publications that are manga</cell>
                        <cell>Percentage of banned manga publications in these genres authored by
                            East Asians</cell>
                        <cell> Percentage of banned East Asian-authored manga publications censored
                            for sexual explicitness </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell>
                            <p>Virginia</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>5%</cell>
                        <cell>100%</cell>
                        <cell>81%</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell>California</cell>
                        <cell>12%</cell>
                        <cell>100%</cell>
                        <cell> California DOC does not provide censorship reasons </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell>Oregon</cell>
                        <cell>22%</cell>
                        <cell>98%</cell>
                        <cell> 100% </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In short, California, Oregon, and Virginia prisons most often cite sexual
                    explicitness to justify their bans on romance/erotica and manga. These bans
                    result in DOC censorship of mostly women authors and East Asian authors
                    respectively.</p>
                <p>These prison censorship patterns are novel CCC-powered findings, but biased US
                    censorship practices in the US are nothing new. Hegemonic identity-group
                    concerns steered early US censorship policies of sexually explicit content. The
                    US Constitution’s First Amendment protects free speech and prohibits the
                    government from favoring any religions. Nevertheless, throughout the nation’s
                    history, many courts have suppressed sexually suggestive material to uphold
                    Christian morality. During the turn of the nineteenth century, Evangelicals of
                    the Second Great Awakening introduced bans of such material beyond the pale,
                    calling it obscenity. They attempted to use the state’s power to curb what they
                    perceived as sin (Stone, 2017). Christian anti-vice activist Anthony Comstock’s
                    crusade fortified earlier regulations with the 1873 Comstock laws, “ma[king] it
                    a crime to knowingly mail obscene materials or advertisements and information
                    about obscene materials, abortion, or contraception” (Steele, 2020). Comstock
                    and other enforcers of such legislation did not differentiate between content
                    for sex education and sexual arousal (Semonche, 2017, pp.16). Courts’ objections
                    to sexually explicit material are now pitched in more secular terms, but
                    obscenity rulings’ religious heritage and related cis-hetero-patriarchal legacy
                    still reinforce discriminatory censorship.<note> After the Supreme Court first
                        directly ruled on obscene expression and upheldthe government’s power to ban
                        it, legal scholar Louis Henkin criticized such censorship as
                        anunconstitutional “relic… of [Americans’] religious heritage.” He lamented
                        that “obscenity, at bottom, is not crime. Obscenity is sin” (Stone, 2017,
                        pp. 278) (Henkin, 1963, pp. 402, 395). </note>
                </p>
                <p>The US Supreme Court’s current guidelines for censoring obscene material
                    constitute one of these secular and seemingly neutral mandates. Established in
                    1973, these guidelines are known as the Miller test. Through the test, states
                    can designate content obscene and therefore unprotected by the First Amendment.
                    To be judged obscene, content must fit not just one or two, but all three of the
                    following characterizations </p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>“the average person, applying contemporary community standards, would find
                        that the work, taken as a whole, appeals to the prurient interest” </item>
                    <item> “the work depicts or describes, in a patently offensive way, sexual
                        conduct or excretory functions specifically defined by applicable state
                        law”</item>
                    <item> “the work, taken as a whole, lacks serious literary, artistic, political,
                        or scientific value” (<title rend="italic">Miller v. California</title>,
                        1973).</item>
                </list>
                <p>Again, the First Amendment protects sexual speech, i.e., any form of
                    communication about sexual matters, which passes the Miller test. </p>
                <p>Yet in and beyond prison, censors frequently ban sexual speech in romance/erotica
                    and manga even when it passes the Miller test. We propose that such double
                    standards stem from censors’ discriminatory appraisals of the sexual speech that
                    these publications engage. To be clear, we do not assume all the enforcers of
                    prison censorship mean to push an ideologically suppressive or anti-woke agenda.
                    Some may, but plenty are just responding to the bureaucratic pressures of
                    maintaining a semblance of order and efficiency in the carceral system
                    (Tewksbury and DeMichele, 2005, pp. 36). Many of these censors are working
                    without much accountability, clear guidance, or literary or legal expertise, so
                    they likely make snap judgements about what to ban informed by unconscious
                    biases (PEN America, 2019). CCC provides a data-driven mechanism for
                    interrupting such unconscious national biases in US prison censorship by making
                    them conscious.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>2.1 US Censorship and Romance and Erotica</head>
                    <p>Contemporary communities who, as referenced in the Miller test, set norms for
                        what kind of sexual content is socially acceptable have largely embraced
                        romance and erotica literature. E.L. James’ risqué romance <title
                            rend="italic">Fifty Shades</title> trilogy accounted for the US’s three
                        top-grossing books between 2019 and 2021 while selling 165 million copies as
                        of 2021 (Aviles, 2019) (Alter, 2021). Although the first book in the
                        trilogy, Fifty Shades of Grey (2011), is now one of the bestselling romance
                        novels worldwide, it is commonly censored in prisons throughout the US.
                        According to CCC’s data, of the 26 states with available banned prison
                        publication data, 15 states’ prisons (i.e., 58 percent of these states’
                        prisons) ban one or more books within the Fifty Shades trilogy and its
                        extended series.<note> The states with available banned prison publication
                            data and that censor Fifty Shades of Grey include: Arizona, California,
                            Florida, Illinois, Michigan, Minnesota, Missouri, New Hampshire, New
                            Jersey, North Carolina, Oregon, Texas, Virginia, Washington, and
                            Wisconsin.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Outside of the carceral context, the First Amendment protects sexually
                        explicit material if it is not obscene by the Miller test’s standards. Then
                        again, correctional facilities can go beyond the Miller test to deny such
                        material if content threatens to adversely affect the prison environment.
                        The non-profit legal resource and educational provider, The Americans for
                        Effective Law Enforcement, Inc. (AELE) reports that “courts have usually
                        upheld bans on sexually explicit materials in prisons that cite legitimate
                        reasons, such as safety and security, prevention of crime, rehabilitation,
                        prevention of sexual harassment and assault, discipline, recidivism and
                        treatment, or institutional order” (AELE, 2010). </p>
                    <p>Yet, in practice, DOC use of this First Amendment exception for prohibiting
                        sexually explicit material seems less than sound. According to Ka’s team’s
                        research, states’ DOC documented rationales for banning romance/erotica
                        publications as sexually explicit vary from state to state while failing to
                        clearly explain why these publications’ flagged content might compromise
                        penal subjects’ safety and wellbeing. Whereas some DOC such as Florida’s and
                        Pennsylvania’s specifically permit the first three books of Fifty Shades,
                        others such as the Connecticut, Kansas, and Washington DOC ban the entire
                        trilogy. Washington DOC records provide the most in-depth account of the
                        reasoning for banning the trilogy that we can find. For instance, Washington
                        DOC notes justifying its rejection of the first book <title rend="italic"
                            >Fifty Shades of Grey</title>, read: “Publication contained sexually
                        explicit depictions of sex acts including but limited to; genital- genital,
                        oral-genital, anal-genital contact/penetration. The [p]ublication also
                        describes, in great detail, a masochistic/sadistic relationship and includes
                        bondage on pages 105-106, 113-122, 135- 142, 166-167, 170-175, 193-196,
                        231-232, 263-268, 274-275, 323-328, 349-350, 363-363, 365-366,429-430,
                        437-438” (Washington Department of Corrections, 2019). Admittedly, this
                        romance series, centering BDSM (bondage, discipline, sadomasochism) dynamics
                        in which a virginal woman protagonist willingly roleplays the sexual servant
                        to a billionaire man, is not, for us, an exemplar of progressive
                        twenty-first-century sexual politics. As <title rend="italic">The New York
                            Review of Books</title> writer Emily Eakins observes, “Despite the
                        risqué trappings, the books hew to the conventions of the nineteenth-century
                        marriage plot” (2012). Yet various states’ DOC reasons for censoring it,
                        like those provided by the Washington DOC, seem to reject E. L. James’ books
                        not out of concern for their sexual politics, but instead their vivid
                        description of sexual acts and transgressive turn-ons. In contrast,
                        feminists critique her series for glorifying asymmetrical power between a
                        cis-heterosexual woman and man. For instance, they lament that <title
                            rend="italic">Fifty Shades</title> feeds into some women’s fantasies of
                        sexual submission (Roiphe, 2012). At the same time, many feminists defend or
                        even champion the series for unapologetically exploring a woman
                        protagonist’s sexual proclivities and the ways that old gender dynamics seep
                        into modern heterosexual relationships (Rodale, 2015, pp.14) (Chemaly,
                        2014). Our purpose here is not to judge whether <title rend="italic">Fifty
                            Shades </title>empowers women. Instead, we raise this romance series
                        example (about which there is more discourse and writing than most) to
                        underscore 1) how empowering women does not stand out as a variable in DOC
                        documented reasoning for the censorship of sexually explicit content and 2)
                        the inconsistent and questionable censorship logic among state DOC that
                        deems graphic romance/ erotica a threat to order in prison.</p>
                    <p>Prohibiting graphic romance and erotica is not neutral or without
                        consequence. Some such literature can be a vehicle for marginalized points
                        of views and when prisons ban such publications, they further undermine the
                        neglected perspectives this kind of romance/erotica represents. Like E.L.
                        James, Zane is another contemporary <title rend="italic">New York
                            Times</title> bestselling author of these genres whose books many DOC
                        reject. At the time of this writing, her Simon &amp; Schuster publisher page
                        advertises Zane’s 38 romance books (Simon &amp; Schuster). Among her
                        followers, Zane has a reputation as a Black woman writer who operates within
                        the tradition of urban erotica/urban fiction and who discusses desire and
                        sex acts in unvarnished terms (Stallings, 2015, pp.82). California,
                        Connecticut, Iowa, Oregon, Texas, Virginia, and Wisconsin prisons all ban
                        multiple titles by Zane for sexual explicitness. The most detailed prison
                        records that we can obtain regarding the censorship of Zane’s books due to
                        sexual explicitness hail from Oregon and Virginia DOC explanations of these
                        states’ prison bans of Zane’s <title rend="italic">Vengeance: A
                            Novel</title>. It is about a pop star, Wicket, struggling against the
                        temptation to get back at the people who traumatized her as a youth to
                        instead overcome her long-held pain and suffering. The Oregon DOC cites
                            <title rend="italic">Vengeance</title>’s pages 110-112 and 168-169 as
                        those which merit prison censorship, on the grounds of the following
                        codes:</p>
                    <p>1.01: Portrayal of actual or simulated sexual acts or behaviors between human
                        beings</p>
                    <p>1:02: Portrayal of actual or simulated penetration of the vagina or anus, or
                        contact between the mouth and the breast, genitals, or anus.</p>
                    <p>1:03: Portrayal of actual or stimulated stimulation of the breast genitals,
                        or anus (Oregon Department of Corrections, 2020) (Oregon Laws, 2021).</p>
                    <p>Indeed, both sets of cited pages describe instances of oral sex, contact
                        with intimate body parts, and masturbation that correspond with these codes.
                        The Virginia DOC, however, does not cite these pages as grounds for
                        censoring <title rend="italic">Vengeance</title>, but instead identifies two
                        other pages, 51 and 64, for violations A.1 and A.2 under criterion A,
                        “Material that emphasizes explicit or graphic depictions or descriptions of
                        sexual acts.” On page 51, the protagonist contemplates using the heel of a
                        shoe as a tool of self-penetration, which counts as violation A.1, “Actual
                        sexual intercourse (vaginal, anal, or oral) including inanimate object
                        penetration.” Both pages 51 and 64 describe characters, secreting bodily
                        fluids as the result of sexual excitement, which counts as violation A.2,
                        “Secretion or excretion of bodily fluids or substances in the context of
                        sexual activity or arousal” (Virginia Department of Corrections, 2024,
                        pp.10)</p>
                    <p>As in the case of DOC stated reasons for disapproving <title rend="italic"
                            >Fifty Shades</title>, various DOC stated reasons for disapproving
                            <title rend="italic">Vengeance</title> do not seem to reflect feminist
                        concerns. Justifications for banning both publications target text about
                        sexual acts rather than the sentiments behind them, such as what these acts
                        imply relative to characters’ story arc, social power dynamics, etc. In the
                            <title rend="italic">Vengeance</title> pages that Oregon and Virginia
                        DOC deem violations, the protagonist narrates consensual sexual encounters,
                        where she takes charge. For example, on pages 64 and 110-112, Wicket seduces
                        a man, declines penetrative intercourse with him, and, in response, he
                        happily follows her lead on to other sexual activity. Also told from her
                        point of view, pages 51 and 168-169 cast Wicket as the dom in a
                        sadomasochistic exchange with two other eager participants.</p>
                    <p>Occasionally, DOC guidelines for prison officials stipulate that they
                        consider material’s merit when determining whether to ban it. This
                        censorship factor is especially notable when it comes to the romance and
                        erotica genres, given that their worth is often subject to public and
                        literary debate as well as social biases. For instance, the Virginia DOC
                        guidelines state an exception for its sexual explicitness censorship
                        category: “No publication generally recognized as having literary value
                        should be excluded under this criterion” (2024, pp.10). By banning <title
                            rend="italic">Vengeance</title>, the Virginia DOC therefore determined
                        it lacks literary merit. Yet discussion around the worth of Zane’s books
                        demonstrates that questions of literary or social value can favor dominant
                        group views at the expense of marginalized ones. Critics often dismiss
                        Zane’s books for their rough and direct writing, which contrasts with the
                        kind of romance/erotica novel that plays up florid language, metaphors or
                        poetic prose (Stallings, 2015, pp.79-82). Writerly craft and figurative
                        writing can elevate sexually explicit romance in the eyes of literary
                        tastemakers and potential porn censors who accept risqué content if it has
                        redeeming social value (Wyngaard, 2015, pp. 983, 989-990). According to
                        these standards of articulation, Zane’s straightforward tone and lack of
                        literary devices make her books crass and without social value. Yet L.H.
                        Stallings argues that Zane’s blunt narration of sexual subject matter is an
                        expression of “epistemic self-defense” and “erotic sovereignty” for Black
                        women whose sexuality is heavily exploited and policed by both white and
                        patriarchal forces (2015, pp. 62). In Stallings’ view, Zane’s text validates
                        the oft-discounted communication style and vantage points of the many Black
                        women who compose its primary readership: “Zane writes about the repressed
                        in the language of the repressed. Likewise, her audience is composed of
                        those who speak and read in a similar manner” (2015, pp.83). By reclaiming
                        modes of expression and sexual longing that resonate with numerous Black
                        women and perhaps other demographics, Zane’s directness could enhance its
                        social value. Yet prison censorship guidelines do not encourage censors to
                        weigh such marginalized views of value when deciding what kind of sexual
                        expression is safe for the prison environment. </p>
                    <p>On the contrary, DOC rejections of Zane’s books and <title rend="italic"
                            >Fifty Shades</title> appear to reflect discriminatory value judgements.
                        More specifically, we propose these publications’ prison censorship is
                        symptomatic of the US patriarchal censorship of women’s sexual speech and
                        portrayals of their sexual desire — both in and beyond prison. The history
                        of US censorship bears out this enduring pattern and CCC’s data on romance/
                        erotica sheds light on this pattern’s contemporary impact in prison.</p>
                    <p>Censors’ anxieties about women’s corruptibility played an outsized role in
                        early US obscenity legislation. In 1821, the first recorded US obscenity
                        trial outlawed John Cleland's<title rend="italic"> Memoirs of a Woman of
                            Pleasure, </title>popularly known as <title rend="italic">Fanny
                            Hill</title>, the name of its protagonist. As intimated by its title,
                        the novel chronicled a young woman’s sexual awakening and observations
                        (Semonche, 2007, pp.13). In the tradition of the modern romance novel,
                            <title rend="italic">Fanny Hill</title> foregrounds a love story and
                        rewards its heroine’s erotic adventures with a happy ending (Ivanski, et al.
                        2022, pp.3). This is not only a case of the government regulating a sexually
                        provocative account. <title rend="italic">Fanny Hill’</title>s ban until
                        1966 and continued challenges thereafter also exemplify US morality
                        crusaders’ long-standing opposition to narratives in which women’s sexual
                        pleasure goes unpunished (Semonche, 2007, pp.41) (Rodale, 2013). The
                        patriarchal impulse took literal form when, in 1923, father and New York
                        Supreme Court Judge John Ford led the Clean Books legislative charge after
                        finding his 16-year-old daughter with a library copy of D.H. Lawrence’s
                        sexually explicit <title rend="italic">Women in Love</title>. Had it
                        succeeded, the Clean Books Bill would have extended the definition of
                        obscenity to criminalize a book even if it contained an isolated passage
                        deemed “filthy” or “disgusting,” regardless of whether that passage was
                        sexually stimulating (Semonche, 2007, pp.10) (New York Times, 1923).</p>
                    <p>Along with curbing representations that affirm women’s sexual curiosity, US
                        censorship campaigns against sexual content often thwart women’s sexual
                        self-representation and expression. Although women’s bodies are among the
                        most frequently censored subject matter, through the mid-twentieth century,
                        there were few well-known sexually explicit publications by women. This
                        started to change with Boston Women’s Health Collective’s handbook first
                        published in 1969 as “Women and Their Bodies” and then in subsequent
                        editions with the more famous title <title rend="italic">Our Bodies,
                            Ourselves</title> (Our Bodies Ourselves). Its women authors sought to
                        provide other women with a resource for understanding their sexuality and
                        reproductive health, not shying away from then taboo topics such as
                        masturbation, premarital sex, and lesbianism (Semonche, 2007, pp. 44)
                        (Wells, 2008). As the publication gained popularity, political conservatives
                        and evangelists fought to ban it (Semonche, 2007, pp. 44). This instance
                        also speaks to US right-wing moralists’ historical use of censorship as a
                        tool for maintaining their power and values through policy initiatives. Over
                        the past couple of centuries, they have attempted to prohibit the
                        publication, production, and circulation of sexual content. To this end,
                        such moralists turned to postal censorship acts, tariff laws,
                        “anti-pornography” ordinances, etc. (Semonche, 2007) (Blanchard, 1992).</p>
                    <p>Anti-pornography measures have especially bolstered the censorship of romance
                        and erotica, and by extension, literature about women’s sexuality. In the
                        1980s, Christian fundamentalists, political conservatives, and
                        pro-censorship feminists set out to ban pornography. The Supreme Court
                        struck down resulting anti-pornography ordinances, ruling that they violated
                        the First Amendment’s guarantee of free speech in accordance with the Miller
                        test (Blanchard, 1992). Even so, the political controversy exacerbated the
                        national public stigma surrounding sexual speech. Attempts to restrict it
                        through anti-pornography ordinances pivot around descriptions and depictions
                        of women’s bodies.<note> For instance, an Indianapolis anti-pornography
                            ordinance described pornography as “the graphic sexually explicit
                            subordination of women, whether in pictures or in words,” declaring such
                            content a civil rights violation against women (Indianapolis Code, 1984,
                            § 16(q)).</note> Consequently, those pushing patriarchal agendas often
                        leverage anti-pornography rhetoric to control representations of women,
                        including women’s representations of other women and themselves. Late
                        twentieth-century feminists for and against porn censorship both feared that
                        such agendas would co-opt anti-porn regulations (Strauss, 1990, pp. 1142).
                            <note> Anti-porn feminists claimed that banning such pornography would
                            support women's pathways to gender equity, by reducing men’s tendency to
                            regard women as sexual objects (Stone, 2010). Pro-porn feminists,
                            however, cautioned that this censorship would suppress sexually explicit
                            feminist representation of women as well as queer expression (Rogerson
                            and Semple, 1990).</note> In contrast to religious and political
                        anti-porn conservatives, feminists Andrea Dworkin and Katherine MacKinnon,
                        who co-authored the anti-porn Indianapolis ordinance (1984), intended to
                        limit this censorship to expression that harms women (Blinoff, 2021, pp.
                        100-110). They defined pornography not as general erotica (that represents
                        or arouses sexual love or desire), but as nine specific types of sexual
                        pictures and/or words that they argue degrade and dehumanize women.<note>
                            Dworkin and MacKinnon write: “<title rend="italic">Pornography</title>
                            is the graphic sexually explicit subordination of women through pictures
                            and/or words that also includes one or more of the following: (i) women
                            are presented dehumanized as sexual objects, things, or commodities; or
                            (ii) women are presented as sexual objects who enjoy pain or
                            humiliation; or (iii) women are presented as sexual objects who
                            experience sexual pleasure in being raped; or (iv) women are presented
                            as sexual objects tied up or cut up or mutilated or bruised or
                            physically hurt; or (v) women are presented in postures or positions of
                            sexual submission, servility, or display; or (vi) women's body
                            parts-including but not limited to vaginas, breasts, or buttocks- are
                            exhibited such that women are reduced to those parts; or (vii) women are
                            presented as whores by nature; or (viii) women are presented being
                            penetrated by objects or animals; or (ix) women are presented in
                            scenarios of degradation, injury, torture, shown as filthy or inferior,
                            bleeding, bruised, or hurt in a context that makes these conditions
                            sexual” (1988, pp.101).</note> Yet the ordinance’s anti-degradation
                        definition noticeably differs from the more general, colloquial
                        understanding of pornography, which means “material (such as books or a
                        photograph) that depicts erotic behavior and is intended to cause
                        excitement” (Merriam Webster Dictionary). It is then not surprising that
                        under the guise of banishing pornography, many censors attack romance and
                        erotica publications, regardless of whether these novels fit Dworkin and
                        MacKinnon’s definition. Managing Director Jonathan Friedman at PEN America
                        laments this phenomenon in the contemporary climate: “[a]ctivists and
                        politicians are inflating the notion of what constitutes ‘pornography’
                        beyond all recognition… They are going after romance books, books about
                        puberty or sex education and books that just have LGBTQ characters” (Sargent
                        and Walden, 2023). One recent example entails various bans on Nora Roberts’
                        romance novels in red states such as Florida. To discredit her books,
                        right-wing activists vilified them as porn. Yet these books focus on friends
                        pursuing love and contain accounts of only consensual sex premised on
                        respect via “language vague enough that a child would have little idea what
                        was happening” (Sargent and Walden, 2023). Whether or not one agrees with
                        feminist porn censorship, we mean to establish that there is an ongoing
                        track record of US special interest groups mobilizing charged
                        anti-pornography language to minimize who can exercise and access sexual
                        speech. This context likely contributes to prison bans of romance and
                        erotica and by extension women’s sexual speech since this literature is
                        mostly by women authors.</p>
                    <p>The policing of porn and women’s sexual speech raises questions about what
                        constitutes appropriate expressions of desire. Even when content aligns with
                        Dworkin and MacKinnon’s definition of porn, parties that stigmatize and/or
                        censor it among adults risk dictating these standards. In this sense,
                        anti-porn arbiters proceed as if they know what is best for a vast diversity
                        of audiences and how these audiences experience content. Feminist porn
                        movement advocates argue that such anti-porn tendencies are not only
                        presumptuous, but exclusionary because they privilege “normative and
                        constricted sexualities,” such as “sexual acts and identities” that promote
                        “heterosexuality, marriage, monogamy, and reproduction,” while dismissing
                        sexual expression that does not as perverse (Rubin, 1984, pp. 280).
                        Furthermore, when content exceeds normative and constricted sexualities and
                        even when it stays within these bounds, audiences do not perceive
                        expressions of desire in literal or homogenous ways. For instance, feminist
                        porn scholars “explor[e] sexual ideas and acts that may be fraught,
                        confounding, and deeply disturbing to some, and liberating and empowering to
                        others” (Penley et al., 2013, pp.15). Likewise, scholar Janice Radway finds
                        that readers’ interpretations of content about desire is complex and
                        contingent. She conducted a reception-based ethnography of a midwestern
                        community of women who consumed romance upholding traditional
                        cis-hetero-patriarchal values. These romance books might appear to demean
                        women’s agency, but Radway concludes they granted their readers emotional
                        and psychological support (1991, pp. 96). Plot points associated with
                        regressive gender politics, such as “heroines in relative positions of
                        weakness” and violent men, resonated with the readers not because the women
                        took pleasure in these obstacles, but rather because they got to accompany
                        the heroine as she resolved these obstacles en route to happily ever after.
                        This process helped the readers understand and cop with the
                        cis-hetero-patriarchal limitations that conditioned their own lives (Radway,
                        1991, pp. 75, 14). Radway’s study and feminist porn scholarship, along with
                        the previously mentioned cases of <title rend="italic">Fifty Shades</title>
                        and Zane’s books are telling. They establish that the nuanced social
                        functions of romance and erotica should not be taken for granted. </p>
                    <p>To summarize, we believe at least three factors underlie why US prisons’
                        frequent censorship of romance and erotica publications most impacts women’s
                        sexual speech. First, these contemporary genres are dominated by women
                        authors. Banning publications in these genres means banning largely
                        women-authored publications. This correlation bears out in Ka’s most
                        accurate datasets of state DOC censorship (figure 12). Second, romance and
                        erotica cater to the historically suppressed themes of women’s sexual desire
                        and sexual liberation. Objections to these themes motivated important early
                        US obscenity debates and more recent anti-pornography censorship efforts,
                        including those aimed at romance and erotica. Third, the well-documented US
                        history of patriarchal campaigns against these genres helps explain the
                        understudied yet prominent phenomenon of US prison bans on them. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.2 US Censorship and Manga</head>
                    <p>In addition to revealing that numerous prison bans on romance and erotica
                        detract from incarcerated people’s access to women’s sexual speech, Ka’s
                        preliminary data analysis shows that prisons throughout the nation often
                        reject manga. In so doing, these prisons reject a great deal of publications
                        by people of East Asian descent who make up the majority of the banned
                        manga’s authors. Just as restrictions on romance and erotica outside the
                        carceral system relate to those inside it, prisons’ penchant for prohibiting
                        manga reflects this publication type’s commonly censored status within US
                        society at large.</p>
                    <p>To some degree, manga’s comic book format accounts for these restrictions.
                        Comics are highly susceptible to obscenity charges due to the misguided
                        notion that they are categorically children’s entertainment (Blanchard,
                        1992) (CBLDFa) (Sergi, 2015, pp.220-224). This perception undermines their
                        serious literary, artistic, political, or scientific value, which the Miller
                        test requires censors to consider. Moreover, the presumption that comics
                        target the youngest members of society rather than its adult members means
                        that courts are more likely to apply harsher community standards to this
                        material. The Miller test justifies harsher standards for children’s
                        content. At the same time, censors cite anti-pornography legislation that
                        prohibits sexualized representation of minors for both children’s and adult
                        content to rationalize their strict appraisals of manga. Even so, as we will
                        discuss, Americans’ tendency to misconstrue manga’s target audience and
                        subjects often prevent US censors from applying these standards to the
                        publication type fairly. </p>
                    <p>Manga bans also demonstrate how US censorship policies can contain the
                        diversification of cultural content. At the turn of the twentieth century,
                        overall US community standards around sexual expression broadened as
                        developments in mass media and eventually the Internet circulated suggestive
                        and even brazenly risqué content, such as pornography (Stone, 2017).
                        Meanwhile, the rise of the Internet and global markets helped spread
                        Japanese popular culture. Manga is a kind of comic stemming from this
                        culture with long story lines and complex graphics (Johnson-Woods, 2010, pp.
                        25, 1). These publications came to dominate the East Asian comic book
                        market. In 2007, manga started making US best-seller lists (Johnson-Woods,
                        2010, pp.1). Manga encompasses an enormous range of genres and only select
                        subsets of them portray young-looking characters in sexual ways. Yet as
                        national attitudes around sexual content relaxed in the aughts, US
                        prosecutors, customs agents, and other law enforcement increasingly charged
                        those in possession of manga publications with obscenity regardless of
                        whether the publications belonged to these subsets (Stone, 2017)
                        (CBLDFb).</p>
                    <p>We believe the forces behind this uptick in manga censorship are multifold.
                        At least three probable factors include:</p>
                    <p>1) The 2003 anti-child pornography PROTECT Act and the flawed application of
                        its obscene child pornography component <note> The PROTECT of the PROTECT
                            act stands for Prosecutorial Remedies and Other Tools to End the
                            Exploitation of Children Today (CBLDFb).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Comic Book Legal Defense Fund (CBLDF) explains that this act strengthened
                        law enforcement’s ability to prevent and respond to child sex offenses. At
                        the same time, it instituted the category of “obscene child pornography,”
                        which criminalizes a non-photographic visualization of any kind that depicts
                        “a minor engaging in sexually explicit conduct and is obscene” (CBLDFb)
                        (PROTECT Act, 2003). Although some adult manga entails sexual
                        representations of characters who appear youthful, US governmental actors
                        mistakenly equate manga in general with youth and sexual deviancy (CBLDFb). </p>
                    <p>2) Different cultural perceptions of both taboo sexual expression and
                        manga</p>
                    <p>When it comes to sexual content, in Japan, nudity, certain expressions of
                        sensual intimacy (such as those between humans and non-human creatures), and
                        escapist fantasy in adult cultural products are more socially sanctioned
                        than in the US. Such distinctions can lead non-East Asian viewers who are
                        unfamiliar with a sexual trope in manga to view it as perverse. In contrast,
                        East Asian audiences who recognize the same trope as a well-established part
                        of their culture’s artistic and popular production might regard it as tame
                        (Briel, 2010, pp. 201–203). </p>
                    <p>Oregon DOC’s censorship of the hit manga <title rend="italic">A Centaur’s
                            Life</title> underscores how, when presented with culturally unfamiliar
                        scenarios that involve nudity or light sexual content, US censors are quick
                        to reject it, even when these scenarios represent socially acceptable
                        approaches to sexual issues in Japan. The series <title rend="italic">A
                            Centaur’s Life</title> (2011 — ) by Kei Murayama, is <title
                            rend="italic">shōjo </title>manga (manga primarily targeted at
                        pre-adolescent girls and young women). It is set at a high school in a world
                        that resembles contemporary Japan but is inhabited only by mythological
                        creatures. The protagonist is a high school-aged centaur girl (Lee, 2016,
                        pp.56-60). Japanese writers and artists have long embraced human-animal
                        hybrids from the Greek tradition and others. <title rend="italic"
                            >Jingai</title> (non-human humanoid) characters in general and centaur
                        characters in particular have enjoyed increased prominence in Japanese manga
                        since 2010 (Lee, 2016, pp. 58) (Escande, 2022, pp. 33). According to
                        comparative literature scholar Jessy Escande, by centering characters that
                        are visibly proximate to but other than human, recent manga with <title
                            rend="italic">jingai</title> often give manga creators and audiences an
                        inviting way to grapple with the challenging “relationship between the self
                        and the Other in a society [Japan] that still values homogeneity and
                        conformism” (2022, pp. 31). <title rend="italic">A Centaur’s Life</title>
                        focuses on the centaur protagonist’s “otherness-related problems that are
                        typical of a human adolescent,” such as teenage puberty, dating anxieties,
                        and queer crushes (Escande, 2022, pp. 33, 36). On these matters, as Escande
                        sees it, <title rend="italic">A Centaur’s Life</title> provides sexual
                        education through socially palatable narratives of <title rend="italic"
                            >jinga </title>with horns, halos, and tails<title rend="italic">,
                        </title>thereby responding to Japanese students’ disappointment in their
                        wanting high school sexual education in the human world (2022, pp. 33, 36).
                            <title rend="italic">A Centaur’s Life </title>volume 9 directly explores
                        teen dilemmas such as romantic feelings between friends and queer desire
                        perceived to go against the norm. A satyr girl Nadeshiko confesses to her
                        friend: “If only you were a boy, Akira-chan. I’m sure I’d be asking you to
                        kiss me” (Murayama, 2016). They never kiss or touch each other in a sexual
                        manner, but Nadeshiko encounters her crush Akira, a tomboyish part-satyr,
                        part-imp girl, in a somewhat provocative way when picking Akira up for
                        school. Nadeshiko finds Akira still dozing off in her sleeping gown. It is
                        scrunched up over her neck, partially exposing Akira’s not-yet-developed
                        breasts in one panel and an undifferentiated bump between her bare legs
                        (hinting at but not depicting her vulva) in another. Acknowledging the
                        impropriety of the situation, the Nadeshiko exclaims: “That’s no way for a
                        lady to sleep, by the way.” Akira shrugs the comment off: “It’s hot in here.
                        Besides, we’re all girls here, so what’s the problem?” Nadeshiko lets it go
                        and helps Akira get ready. This scene shows the two <title rend="italic"
                            >jingai </title>girls on the cusp of adulthood navigating both increased
                        societal expectations of modesty and new feelings of sexual tension prompted
                        by partial nudity. Whereas this material takes on an educational tenor for
                        adolescents in Japan, US censors are more prone to object to it as an
                        inappropriately sexual representation of youth. Indeed, Oregon DOC prohibits
                        this volume 9 for “portraying sexual acts of a minor” (Oregon Department of
                        Corrections, 2020) (Oregon Laws, 2021).</p>
                    <p>Oregon DOC bans volume 10 of the series for this same offense as well as
                        “simulated or threatened [sex/ual] acts” (Oregon Department of Corrections,
                        2020) (Oregon Laws, 2021). Although this DOC report does not cite specific
                        pages for these acts, it likely refers to the part of volume 10 where
                        characters’ sexual curiosity is most visibly on display: when the <title
                            rend="italic">jinga</title> girls relax in hot springs together. No sex
                        acts unfold there. The characters, however, are unclothed and, as girls
                        undergoing puberty, they jokingly compare breasts. One even touches
                        another’s. When the centaur girl Hime helps her friend, an imp-girl Nozomi
                        out of the tub, Nozomi accidentally knocks into Hime’s chest. For US
                        censors, the tub setting might instantly imply an erotic context that
                        heightens the sensuality of this comedic run-in and the youth’s
                        light-hearted consideration of their maturing bodies to the level of
                        censorship. In contrast, Japanese traditions of public baths linked to
                        ritual and religious purification (associated with Shinto and Buddhist
                        practices) reduce communal bathing’s sexual connotations. History books, TV
                        shows, and movies about the Edo period as well as celebrated national works
                        from that era, such as Hokusai Manga’s <title rend="italic">Public
                            Bath</title> (1815-1849) woodblock print, visualize these settings as
                        routine rather than risqué environments. Communal bathing in hot springs
                        remains a popular Japanese approach to cleansing the body and easing the
                        mind (Clark, 1994, pp.5, 30, 88). </p>
                    <p>Reductive US perceptions of manga overall also encourage censors’
                        overgeneralized views of its sexual extremeness. Manga is a massive industry
                        in Japan and elsewhere for all manner of narrative — news, education,
                        sports, science fiction, romance, etc. — geared toward different audiences
                        (Johnson-Wood, 2010). This publication type cannot be reduced to one
                        sensibility or age group. Jason Thompson’s encyclopedic manga guidebook
                        identifies over a thousand genres (2007). There is a vast array of manga
                        publications, some feature sexual content and many do not. </p>
                    <p>DOC bans on commercially successful, sexually tame manga geared at youth such
                        as <title rend="italic">Life of a Centaur</title>, highlight dubious prison
                        censorship practices around manga publications. We do not deny that sexually
                        explicit manga with devastating gender politics, pornographic
                        representations of minors, and/or sexually degrading depictions exist. They
                        do. Some of the best-known examples can be found in <title rend="italic"
                            >hentai</title> manga, which is an intentionally pornographic type, and
                        hardcore <title rend="italic">lolicon</title> manga, which sexualize
                        prepubescent girls. Revenge porn-centered narratives with violence against
                        women, such as <title rend="italic">Prison Experiment</title> (2016) and
                            <title rend="italic">Redo of Healer </title>(2017 — ), express striking
                        forms of misogyny that some manga contain (Ellecosta, 2023, pp.78, 111, 78,
                        119-121). </p>
                    <p>Moreover, feminist critiques of erotic and non-erotic manga abound because,
                        like countless other artistic and entertainment formats the world over,
                        manga often marks sexist double standards. For instance, manga artists’
                        tendency to portray girls and women characters with enormous breasts, wide
                        hips, tiny waistlines, and long legs risks sexually objectifying them and
                        perpetuating unattainable feminine beauty standards (Ellecosta, 2023)
                        (Orbaugh, 2003). Yet, in recent decades manga creators increasingly either
                        incorporate these double standards to undermine them or depart from them,
                        offering alternative progressive views of gender (Hemmann, 2020). </p>
                    <p>As with romance and erotica publications, numerous manga publications include
                        risqué elements and/or reinforce patriarchal stereotypes while also
                        unsettling confining gendered expectations. On the one hand, the extent to
                        which these kinds of manga publications promote views of gender equality is
                        up for debate. On the other hand, the US prison bans on a lot of these
                        publications for sexual explicitness are suspect. Many such manga with a
                        combination of progressive and regressive gender politics, in our eyes,
                        readily meet the requirements of the Miller test without evidentially
                        undermining prison order and safety.<note> One such example is the sci-fi
                            manga <title rend="italic">Ghost in the Shell</title> (1989-1990) by
                            Masamune Shirow, censored by Oregon DOC for sexual explicitness (Oregon
                            Department of Corrections, 2024). This manga’s gender politics can be
                            understood as regressive for fetishizing its protagonist cyborg police
                            officer Major Motoko Kusanagi’s stereotypically idealized slim, yet
                            voluptuous feminine physique (Orbaugh, 2003). At the same time, some
                            hail <title rend="italic">Ghost in the Shell</title>’s exploration of
                            hi-tech gender and identity fluidity for its progressive gender politics
                            (Gerdne, 2021). Oregon DOC materials do not clearly specify what <title
                                rend="italic">Ghost in the Shell</title> content is unacceptably
                            sexual, but it seems the DOC objects to the manga’s slightly sensual yet
                            relatively sanitized portrayal of Major Kusanagi’s bare cyborg body.
                            Even so, we doubt this portrayal threatens to ignite disorder in the
                            prison environment.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>3) Lack of consideration for publications’ societal value (cultural,
                        artistic, literary, etc.)</p>
                    <p>
                        <title rend="italic">Berserk </title>(1989-), a manga series censored in
                        nine states’ prisons, explores matters of substance with highly skilled
                            storytelling.<note> These nine states include California, Colorado,
                            Connecticut, North Carolina, Oregon, Texas, Virginia, Washington,
                            Wisconsin.</note> In Japan and manga circles, people recognize it as an
                        artistic masterwork. They compare the dark fantastical beauty in <title
                            rend="italic">Berserk’s</title> pages to Dante’s <title rend="italic"
                            >Inferno</title> illustrations and the Dutch Renaissance paintings by
                        Hieronymus Bosch. As these artworks, <title rend="italic">Berserk
                        </title>tackles serious subject matter about the human condition that
                        extends to eye-catching sexual content: group sex, sexual assault, and rape
                        (Traub, 2021). <title rend="italic">Berserk</title> condemns the sexual
                        violence it illustrates and attends to characters’ emotional trauma from it.
                        While noting that original creator Kentaro Miura depicts sexual violence
                        with more sensitivity than most of his contemporaries, some fans lament that
                            <title rend="italic">Berserk</title> still glamorizes it by drawing
                        attention to the beauty of women victims’ bodies in such scenes
                        (o-blessed-king-of-longing, 2014). Virginia’s DOC is among those which ban
                            <title rend="italic">Berserk</title> for sexual explicitness. The
                        state’s DOC overtly instructs prison censors to weigh works’ overall merits,
                        stipulating that “[n]o publication generally recognized as having literary
                        value” should be rejected for sexual explicitness (2024, pp.10). Virginia
                        DOC prohibits all of <title rend="italic">Berserk</title>’s now 42 volumes
                        anyway. This is implicitly a dismissal of the series acclaimed cultural,
                        craft, and storytelling qualities. Virginia DOC and other states’ DOC
                        failure to wholistically evaluate a work’s societal worth when making
                        censorship decisions is noteworthy. This negligence reflects the narrow
                        cultural thinking that informs prison censorship around sexual material. </p>
                    <p>To sum up, we believe that the PROTECT Act, cultural differences between the
                        US and Japan (including overgeneralized US perceptions of manga as a sexual
                        entertainment format), and US prison censorship protocols’ lack of
                        consideration for publications societal value variously promote xenophobic
                        US prison censorship of manga. Xenophobia refers to fear of or dislike for
                        the foreign or culturally unfamiliar. Time and time again, US censors’
                        ignorance about manga (whether willed or not) has led them to misinterpret a
                        manga’s sexual character. They then excessively deem manga publications as
                        harmful, as worthy of fear. The xenophobic trends of sexually-explicit-based
                        prison bans are also bound up with white supremacist ones, given that white
                        supremacy fuels orientializing stereotypes of East Asians as
                            hypersexual.<note> Cultural critic and theorist Edward Saïd, famously
                            explained orientalizing stereotypes as a function of Orientalism, a
                            European colonial perspective that casts non-white Eastern people and
                            their cultures as lascivious, strange, and irrational (Said,
                            1994).</note> The xenophobic and racist dimensions of manga prison
                        censorship are in keeping with broader discrimination that protects US white
                        cis- hetero-patriarchal hierarchies in the carceral context (Alexander,
                        2010) (Davis and Shaylor, 2001) (Mogul, Ritchie, and Whitlock, 2011).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion </head>
                <p>Among DH projects about the prison industrial complex, CCC is distinct for its
                    critical artistic construction led by inquiry into social bias. CCC partakes in
                    Ka’s socially engaged art practice, experiments with information architecture,
                    and tracks the US prison censorship of numerous publication types for further
                    inspection. Its unique web design promotes not only an interactive
                    user-experience, but also an evocative one, as its visuals reference the
                    governmental and computational contexts of its own data. Moreover, CCC invites
                    users to explore perspectives that prison publication bans target and why. As
                    the website partially now shows, the database and its categories reveal
                    relationships between prison officials’ censorship justifications, censored
                    publications and their types, and censored authors’ social identities at the
                    local institutional, state, and national level within the US. Concentrating on
                    the sexually explicit justification for censorship, CCC’s initial findings
                    uncover widespread banning habits that devalue views associated with women’s and
                    East Asians’ sexual speech (through the prison censorship of romance/erotica
                    literature and manga). CCC’s ability to make these two overlooked prison
                    censorship patterns detectable illustrates how Ka’s database, and by extension
                    DH more broadly, can galvanize efforts to articulate and agitate against
                    discrimination within the prison industrial complex. </p>
                <p>By animating the database’s inquiry into social biases through her artistic
                    treatment of it, Ka illuminates how DH and socially engaged art practices can be
                    mutually enriching. The former offers data-driven methods for strengthening the
                    analytical aspects and reach of the latter beyond the art field. In turn,
                    socially engaged art’s creative means of reckoning with social justice issues
                    can invigorate DH strategies.</p>

            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="aele_2010" label="AELE 2010">AELE. (2010) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Prisoners and Sexually Explicit Material</title>, <title rend="italic">AELE
                        Monthly Law Journal</title> 2 (February), pp. 301–309. Available at <ref
                        target="https://www.aele.org/law/2010all02/2010-02MLJ301.pdf"
                        >https://www.aele.org/law/2010all02/2010-02MLJ301.pdf</ref> (Accessed: 29
                    August 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="afterviolence_n.d." label="After Violence Archive n.d.">
                    <title rend="italic">After Violence Archive</title>. Available at <ref
                        target="https://www.afterviolencearchive.org"
                        >https://www.afterviolencearchive.org</ref> (Accessed 19 September
                    2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="alexander_2010" label="Alexander 2010"> Alexander, E. (2010) <title
                        rend="italic">The New Jim Crow: Mass Incarceration in the Age of
                        Colorblindness</title>. New Press: New York. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="alter_2021" label="Alter 2021"> Alter, A. (May 29, 2021) <title
                        rend="quotes">The <title rend="italic">Fifty Shades of Grey</title> author
                        finishes what she started (and restarted)</title>, <title rend="italic">New
                        York Times</title>, (Updated 8 June 2021) Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/05/29/books/el-james-freed-fifty-shades-of-grey.htm"
                        >https://www.nytimes.com/2021/05/29/books/el-james-freed-fifty-shades-of-grey.htm</ref>
                    (Accessed: 18 August 2023). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ala_2024" label="American Library Association 2024"> American Library
                    Association. (2024) <title rend="italic">Cataloging and Classification - ALA
                        Groups and Guidelines</title>. Available at <ref
                        target="https://www.ala.org/tools/atoz/catalogandclassification/cataloging_and_classification"
                        >https://www.ala.org/tools/atoz/catalogandclassification/cataloging_and_classification</ref>
                    (Accessed 26 April 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="aviles_2019" label="Aviles 2019"> Aviles, G. (2019) <title
                        rend="quotes"><title rend="italic">Fifty Shades of Grey</title> was the
                        best-selling book of the decade,</title> NBC News, Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.nbcnews.com/pop-culture/books/fifty-shades-grey-was-best-selling-book-decade-n1105731"
                        >https://www.nbcnews.com/pop-culture/books/fifty-shades-grey-was-best-selling-book-decade-n1105731</ref>
                    (Accessed: 18 August 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bailey_2016" label="Bailey et al. 2016"> Bailey et al. (2016) <title
                        rend="quotes">Reflections on a movement: #transformDH, growing up</title> in
                    Gold, M.K. and Klein, Lauren F. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Debates in the
                        Digital Humanities</title>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press <ref
                        target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled/section/9cf90340-7aae-4eae-bdda-45b8b4540b6b"
                        >https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled/section/9cf90340-7aae-4eae-bdda-45b8b4540b6b</ref>
                    (Accessed: 01 April 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bertand_2004" label="Bertand and Mullainathan 2004"> Bertand, M. and
                    Mullainathan, S. (2004) <title rend="quotes">Are Emily and Greg more employable
                        than Lakisha and Jamal? A field experiment on labor market
                        discrimination</title>, <title rend="italic">American Economic
                        Review</title> 94(4), pp. 991—1013. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1257/0002828042002561 "
                        >https://doi.org/10.1257/0002828042002561</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blanchard_1992" label="Blanchard 1992"> Blanchard, M.A. (1992) <title
                        rend="quotes">The American urge to censor: Freedom of expression versus the
                        desire to sanitize society - From Anthony Comstock to 2 Live
                        Crew</title>,<title rend="italic">William &amp; Mary Law Review </title>
                    33(3), pp. 741—848. Available at <ref
                        target="https://scholarship.law.wm.edu/wmlr/vol33/iss3/4"
                        >https://scholarship.law.wm.edu/wmlr/vol33/iss3/4</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blinoff_2021" label="Blinoff 2021"> Blinoff, Jacqueline. (2021) <title
                        rend="quotes">Revisiting Dworkin-MacKinnon approach for the censorship of
                        pornography in 2021: Why a pro-censorship stance on pornography remains
                        beneficial for women</title>, <title rend="italic">Amherst College Law
                        Review</title> (6), pp. 98-124. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.middlebury.edu/college/sites/default/files/2022-03/Blinoff%20ACLR.pdf"
                        >https://www.middlebury.edu/college/sites/default/files/2022-03/Blinoff%20ACLR.pdf</ref>
                    (Accessed: 30 May 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burrough_2022" label="burrough and Walgren 2022" sortKey="Burrough">
                    borrough, x. and Walgren, J. (2022) <title rend="italic">Art as Social Practice:
                        Technologies for Change</title>. New York: Routledge.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="butler_1990" label="Butler 1990"> Butler, J. (1990) <title
                        rend="italic">Gender Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of
                        Identity</title>. New York: Routledge. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="briel_2010" label="Briel 2010"> Briel, H. (2010) <title rend="quotes"
                        >The roving eye meets traveling pictures: The field of vision and the global
                        rise of adult Manga</title> in Berninger, M., Ecke, Jo. and Haberkorn, G.
                    (eds.) <title rend="italic">Comics as a Nexus of Cultures: Essays on the
                        Interplay of Media, Disciplines, and International
                    Perspectives</title>.Jefferson, NC: McFarland &amp; Company, Inc. Publishers,
                    pp. 187—210.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cahn_2020" label="Cahn 2020"> Cahn, A.F. Esq. (2020) <title
                        rend="quotes">Listening beyond the bars: New York’s artificial intelligence
                        surveillance of prisoners and their loved ones</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >Stop: Surveillance Technology Oversight Project</title>. <ref
                        target="https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5c1bfc7eee175995a4ceb638/t/5f5ff0bd5b99c619be085e91/1600123069848/2020-9-15+Listening+Beyond+The+Bars.pdf"
                        >https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5c1bfc7eee175995a4ceb638/t/5f5ff0bd5b99c619be085e91/1600123069848/2020-9-15+Listening+Beyond+The+Bars.pdf</ref>
                    (Accessed: 03, July 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="carceral-studies-network_n.d." label="Carceral Studies Network  n.d."
                        ><title rend="italic">Carceral Studies Network</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://digitalhumanities.duke.edu/carceral-studies-network"
                        >https://digitalhumanities.duke.edu/carceral-studies-network</ref> (Accessed
                    19 September 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cauley_2020" label="Cauley 2020"> Cauley, K. (2020). <title
                        rend="quotes">Banned books behind bars: Prototyping a data repository to
                        combat arbitrary censorship practices in U.S. prisons</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Humanities</title> 9(4),  <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.3390/h9040131"
                        >https://doi.org/10.3390/h9040131</ref> (Accessed: 01 April 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cbdlf_a_n.d." label="CBLDF(a) n.d."> CBLDF(a). (n.d.) <title
                        rend="quotes">History of comics censorship part 1</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">CBLDF</title>. Available at <ref
                        target="https://cbldf.org/resources/titlestory-of-comics-censorship/titlestory-of-comics-censorship-part-1/"
                        >https://cbldf.org/resources/titlestory-of-comics-censorship/titlestory-of-comics-censorship-part-1/</ref>
                    (Accessed: 30 May 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cbdlf_b_n.d." label="CBLDF(b) n.d."> CBLDF(b). <title rend="quotes"
                        >History of comics censorship part 6</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >CBLDF</title>. Available at <ref
                        target="https://cbldf.org/resources/titlestory-of-comics-censorship/titlestory-of-comics-censorship-part-6/"
                        >https://cbldf.org/resources/titlestory-of-comics-censorship/titlestory-of-comics-censorship-part-6/</ref>
                    (Accessed: 30 May 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chemaly_2014" label="Chemaly 2014"> Chemaly, S. (April 2, 2014) <title
                        rend="quotes">Virgins, bondage, and a shameful media fail</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Huffington Post</title>. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/50-shades-of-grey_b_1441008"
                        >https://www.huffpost.com/entry/50-shades-of-grey_b_1441008</ref> (Accessed
                    12 June 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="clark_1994" label="Clark 1994"> Clark, S. (1994) <title rend="italic"
                        >Japan, a View from the Bath</title>. Honolulu: University of Hawaii Press. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="davis_2001" label="Davis and Shaylor 2001"> Davis, A.Y., and Shaylor,
                    C. (2001) <title rend="quotes">Race, gender, and the prison industrial complex:
                        California and beyond</title>, <title rend="italic">Meridians</title> 2(1),
                    pp. 1–25. Available at: <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/40338793"
                        >https://www.jstor.org/stable/40338793</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dignazio_2020" label="D’Ignazio and Klein 2020" sortKey="Dignazio">
                    D’Ignazio, C. and Klein L.F. (2020) <title rend="italic">Data Feminism</title>.
                    Cambridge, MA: MIT Press. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dworkin_1988" label="Dworkin and MacKinnon 1988">Dworkin, A. and
                    MacKinnon, C.A. (1988) <title rend="italic">Pornography and Civil Rights: A New
                        Day for Women's Equalit</title>y. Minneapolis: Organizing against
                    Pornography.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eakins_2012" label="Eakins 2012"> Eakins, Emily. (2012) <title
                        rend="quotes">Grey area: How <q>Fifty Shades</q> dominated the
                        market</title>, <title rend="italic">The New York Review of Books</title> 27
                    July Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.nybooks.com/online/2012/07/27/seduction-and-betrayal-twilight-fifty-shades/"
                        >https://www.nybooks.com/online/2012/07/27/seduction-and-betrayal-twilight-fifty-shades/</ref>
                    (Accessed 12 June 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="edelstein_2017" label="Edelstein et al. 2017"> Edelstein et al. (2017)
                        <title rend="quotes">Historical research digital age: Reflections from the
                        Mapping the Republic of Letters Project</title>, <title rend="italic">The
                        American Historical Review</title> 122(2), pp. 400—424. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="eldred_1992" label="Eldred and Mortensen 1992">Eldred, J.C, and Peter
                    M. (1992) <title rend="quotes">Reading literacy narratives</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">College English </title>54 (5), pp. 512—539. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.2307/378153"
                    >https://doi.org/10.2307/378153</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ellecosta_2023" label="Ellecosta 2023">Ellecosta, N. (2023) ‘Gender
                    and Body Representations in Japanese Comics’, Master’s thesis. Padua: University
                    of Padua.Available at: <ref
                        target="https://thesis.unipd.it/retrieve/dd1bcc4d-4e26-4901-8049-36da842774a4/Ellecosta_Nicol.pdf"
                        >https://thesis.unipd.it/retrieve/dd1bcc4d-4e26-4901-8049-36da842774a4/Ellecosta_Nicol.pdf</ref>
                    (Accessed: 10 June 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="escande_2022" label="Escande 2022">Escande, J. (2022) <title
                        rend="quotes">Jingai characters in Japanese popular culture and their
                        function as proxies for Representing and questioning otherness</title>, in
                        <title rend="italic">Proceedings of International Seminar 2021: Coping with
                        the “New Normal” and the Promotion of International Exchange</title>. Osaka:
                    University Knowledge Archive, pp.31-39. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.18910/89120"
                    >https://doi.org/10.18910/89120</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="the-file-room_n.d." label="The File Room"><title rend="italic">The
                        File Room</title>. (n.d.) Available at <ref
                        target="http://www.thefileroom.org">http://www.thefileroom.org</ref>
                    (Accessed 19 March 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="franklin_2015" label="Franklin 2015">Franklin, S. (2015) <title
                        rend="italic">Control: Digitality as Cultural Logic</title>. Cambridge, MA:
                    MIT Press. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gerdne_2021" label="Gerdne 2021">Gerden, Jacqueline. (2021) <title
                        rend="quotes">The intersection of identity, gender, and “goolness” in <title
                            rend="italic">Ghost in the Shell</title></title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >Medium</title>, 24 August. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://medium.com/@Jacquelinegerdne/the-intersection-of-identity-gender-and-coolness-in-ghost-in-the-shell-5ba338fe846d"
                        >https://medium.com/@Jacquelinegerdne/the-intersection-of-identity-gender-and-coolness-in-ghost-in-the-shell-5ba338fe846d</ref>
                    (Accessed: 10 June 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ghandnoosh_2022" label="Ghandnoosh and Stammen 2022">Ghandnoosh, N.
                    and Stammen, E. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Incarcerated LGBTQ+ adults and
                        youth</title>, <title rend="italic">The Sentencing Project</title>, 9 June.
                    Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.sentencingproject.org/policy-brief/incarcerated-lgbtq-adults-and-youth/"
                        >https://www.sentencingproject.org/policy-brief/incarcerated-lgbtq-adults-and-youth/</ref>
                    (Accessed 27 August 2022). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hall_2023" label="Hall 2023">Hall, T.D. (May 3, 2023) <title
                        rend="quotes">Compulsory (il) literacies: intersecting race, information
                        redlining, and limitations on the right to read</title> in <title
                        rend="italic">Henry Cohen Lecture Series</title> [YouTube]. The New School,
                    New York. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DHdStRjLnX0&amp;t=1633s"
                        >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DHdStRjLnX0&amp;t=1633s</ref> (Accessed
                    July 10, 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harpers_1867" label="Harper’s Weekly 1867">Harper’s Weekly. (November
                    9, 1867) <title rend="quotes">Education in the southern states</title>, <title
                        rend="italic">Harper’s Weekly</title>, pp. 706–707. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://americanexperience.si.edu/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/Education-in-the-Southern-States-Harpers-Weekly-Nov-9-1867.pdf"
                        >https://americanexperience.si.edu/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/Education-in-the-Southern-States-Harpers-Weekly-Nov-9-1867.pdf</ref>
                    (Accessed September 15, 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="helguera_20111" label="Helguera 2011">Helguera, P. (2011) <title
                        rend="italic">Education for Socially Engaged Art: A Materials and Techniques
                        Handbook</title>. New York: Jorge Pinto Books. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hemmann_2020" label="Hemmann 2020">Kathryn H. (2020) <title
                        rend="italic">Manga Cultures and the Female Gaze</title>. Cham, Switzerland:
                    Palgrave Macmillan.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="henken_1963" label="Henkin 1963">Henkin, L. (1963) <title
                        rend="quotes">Morals and the Constitution: The sin of obscenity</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">Columbia Law Review</title>, 63(2) pp.391 — 414.
                    
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hades_2006" label="Hodes 2006">Hodes, M. (2006) <title rend="quotes">Fractions and fictions in
                    the United States Census of 1890</title> in Laura Stoler, A. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Haunted by Empire:
                    Geographies of Intimacy in North American History</title>. Durham: Duke University
                    Press, pp. 240-270.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="indiana_1984" label="Indianapolis Code 1984">
                    <title rend="italic">Indianapolis Code</title> § 16-3(q). (1984).Available at:
                        <ref
                        target="https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/appellate-courts/F2/771/323/379919/"
                        >https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/appellate-courts/F2/771/323/379919/</ref>
                    Accessed: 11 June 2025).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="inside_n.d." label="Inside Books Project Archive">Inside Books Project Archive.
                    Available at <ref target="https://insidebooksproject.org/">https://insidebooksproject.org/</ref> (Accessed 8 June 2025).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ivanski_2022" label="Ivanksi et al. 2022">Ivanski, C. et al. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Do We
                    Judge Fiction by the Author’s Gender?</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of Media
                        Psychology</title>, <!-- PLACEHOLDER FIX THIS --> pp.—14.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sayers_2017" label="Jentery 2017">Sayers, J. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Introduction: I don’t
                    know all the circuitry</title> in Sayers, J. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Making
                        Things and Drawing Boundaries: Experiments in the Digital
                    Humanities</title>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, pp.1-17.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jstor_nd" label="JSTOR n.d." sortKey="Jstor">JSTOR. <title rend="italic">American Prison
                        Newspapers, 1800s-present: Voices from Inside the Prison.</title> Available
                    at: <ref
                        target="https://www.jstor.org/site/reveal-digital/american-prison-newspapers/?searchkey=1695174278346"
                        >https://www.jstor.org/site/reveal-digital/american-prison-newspapers/?searchkey=1695174278346</ref>
                    (Accessed 19 September 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ka_2025" label="Ka 2025">Ka, S.J. (2025) <title rend="italic">Sue Jeong
                        Ka</title>. Available at <ref target="https://www.suejeongka.com/"
                        >https://www.suejeongka.com/</ref> (Accessed 26 May 2025).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Ka 2019">Ka, Sue Jeong. (2019-)<title rend="italic">. Coding
                        Carceral Censorship: The United States of America.</title> Available at
                    https://codingcarceralcensorship.com/(Accessed 8 June 2025).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ka_2021" label="Ka 2021">Ka, S.J. (2021) <title rend="italic">Dear
                        Readers Beyond Bars</title>. Available at <ref
                        target="https://dearreadersbeyondbars.org/"
                        >https://dearreadersbeyondbars.org/</ref> (Accessed 13 October 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kester_2005" label="Kester 2005">Kester, G. (2005) <title rend="quotes">Conversation pieces: The
                    role of dialogue in socially engaged art </title>in Kocur, Z. and Leung, S. (eds.)
                        <title rend="italic">Theory in Contemporary Art Since 1985</title>. Malden,
                    MA: Blackwell Publishing, pp. 76—100.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="larson_2021" label="Larson 2021">Larson, D. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Prison writer as witness:
                    Can DH read for social justice?</title>, <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</title> 15(3). Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/3/000571/000571.html"
                        >https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/3/000571/000571.html</ref>
                    (Accessed 30 May)</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lois_2015" label="Lois and Gregson 2015">Lois, J. and Gregson, J.
                    (2015) <title rend="quotes">Sneers and leers: Romance writers and gendered sexual stigma</title>, <title
                        rend="italic"> Gender &amp; Society </title> 29(4), pp.459–483. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0891243215584603"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1177/0891243215584603</ref> (Accessed: 18 August
                    2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="marshall-project_2023" label="The Marshall Project 2023">The Marshall Project. (2023) <title rend="quotes">The
                    Books banned in your state’s prisons</title>, Available at <ref
                        target="https://www.themarshallproject.org/2022/12/21/prison-banned-books-list-find-your-state"
                        >https://www.themarshallproject.org/2022/12/21/prison-banned-books-list-find-your-state</ref>
                    (Accessed 18 August 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mclean_2007" label="McLean and Thompson 2007" sortKey="Mclean">McLean, R.L. and Thompson, M.D.
                    (2007) <title rend="italic">Repaying Debts</title>. New York: Council of State
                    Governments Justice Center. Available at
                    <ref target="https://www.ojp.gov/ncjrs/virtual-library/abstracts/repaying-debts">https://www.ojp.gov/ncjrs/virtual-library/abstracts/repaying-debts</ref> (Accessed 18
                    August 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="merriam-webster_n.d." label="Merriam-Webster n.d.">Merriam-Webster. <title rend="italic"
                        >Pornography</title>. Available at <ref
                        target="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/pornography"
                        >https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/pornography</ref> (Accessed 16
                    June 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="miller-vs-california_1973" label="Miller v. California 1973"> Miller v.
                        California, 1973 <title rend="italic">Miller v. California</title>
                    (1973) 413 U.S. 15</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="million-dollar-hoods_n.d." label="Million Dollar Hoods n.d."> Million Dollar Hoods. Available
                    at <ref target="https://milliondollarhoods.pre.ss.ucla.edu"
                        >https://milliondollarhoods.pre.ss.ucla.edu</ref> (Accessed 19 September
                    2023). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mogul_2011" label="Mogul et al. 2011"> Mogul, J.L. et al. (2011) <title rend="italic">Queer (In)Justice: The
                        Criminalization of LGBT People in the United States</title>. Boston: Beacon
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="muncaster_2022" label="Muncaster 2022">Muncaster, K. (2022)
                    <title rend="quotes">Cisheteropatriarchy</title> in Strunk, Kamden R. and Shelton, S.A. (eds.)
                        <title rend="italic">Encyclopedia of Queer Studies in Education</title>.
                    Leiden: Brill.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="​​Nellis 2023">Nellis, Ashley. (2023) ‘Mass Incarceration
                    Trends’, The Sentencing Project, 25 January. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.sentencingproject.org/reports/mass-incarceration-trends/"
                        >https://www.sentencingproject.org/reports/mass-incarceration-trends/</ref>
                    (Accessed 18 August 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="New York Times 1923">New York Times. (1923) ‘Author Berates
                    Justice John Ford’, 11 February, <title rend="italic">New York Times</title>,
                    18. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1923/02/11/105902435.html?pageNumber=18"
                        >https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1923/02/11/105902435.html?pageNumber=18</ref>
                    (Accessed 29 August 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="o-blessed-king-of-longing 2014" sortKey="Oblessed"
                    >o-blessed-king-of-longing. (2014) all a dream [tumblr], 27 September. Available
                    at: <ref
                        target="https://o-blessed-king-of-longing.tumblr.com/post/98559212464/i-understand-and-agree-with-the-criticism-that"
                        >https://o-blessed-king-of-longing.tumblr.com/post/98559212464/i-understand-and-agree-with-the-criticism-that</ref>
                    (Accessed: 10 June 2024). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Orbaugh 2003">Orbaugh, Sharalyn. (2003) ‘“Busty Battlin”
                    Babes: The Evolution of the Shōjo in 1990s Visual Culture,’ in Mostow, Joshua
                    S., Bryson, Norman and Graybill, Maribeth (eds.) <title rend="italic">Gender and
                        Power in the Japanese Visual Field</title>. Honolulu: University of Hawaii
                    Press, pp. 201—228. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Oregon Department of Corrections 2024">Oregon Department of
                    Corrections. (2024) ‘Banned Book Report’.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Oregon Department of Corrections 2020">Oregon Department of
                    Corrections. (2020) ‘Banned Book Report’.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Oregon Laws 2021">Oregon Laws. (2021) ‘OAR 291-131-0035
                    Prohibited Mail’. Available
                    https://oregon.public.law/rules/oar_291-131-0035#google_vignette (Accessed: 10
                    July 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="">Our Bodies, Ourselves Today Our Bodies, Ourselves Today.
                    The History of Our Bodies Ourselves. Available at <ref
                        target="https://www.ourbodiesourselves.org/about-us/our-history/"
                        >https://www.ourbodiesourselves.org/about-us/our-history/</ref> (Accessed 30
                    August 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="PEN America 2019">PEN America. (2019) ‘Literature Locked Up:
                    How Prison Book Restriction Policies Constitute the Nation’s Largest Book Ban’,
                    PENAmerica, September. Available at </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="">
                    <ref target="https://pen.org/literature-locked-up-prison-book-bans-report/"
                        >https://pen.org/literature-locked-up-prison-book-bans-report/#</ref>
                    (Accessed 1 April 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Penley et al. 2013">Penley, Constance et al. (2013)
                    ‘Introduction: The Politics of Producing Pleasure’ in Penley, Constance, et al.
                    (eds.) <title rend="italic">The Feminist Porn Book: The Politics of Producing
                        Pleasure. </title>New York: The Feminist Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Petito 2017">Petito, Dillon. (2016) ‘The File Room: An
                    Open-Source Library of Censorship’, <title rend="italic">Rhizome</title>, 17
                    November. Available at <ref
                        target="https://rhizome.org/editorial/2016/nov/17/antoni-muntadas-the-file-room/"
                        >https://rhizome.org/editorial/2016/nov/17/antoni-muntadas-the-file-room/</ref>
                    (Accessed 19 March 2024). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="PLSN 2021">Prison Library Support Network. (2021)
                    ‘Surveillance Is Censorship: 5 Thoughts on Technology’s Reach in the PIC’, in
                    Ka, Sue Jeong (organizer) ‘Carceral Information Exchange,’ Dear Readers Beyond
                    Bars (0). Available at: <ref
                        target="https://dearreadersbeyondbars.org/Surveillance-IS-Censorship"
                        >https://dearreadersbeyondbars.org/Surveillance-IS-Censorship</ref>
                    (Accessed 1 April 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="PROTECT Act 2023">PROTECT Act. (2003) S.151. Available at
                        <ref target="https://www.congress.gov/bill/108th-congress/senate-bill/151"
                        >https://www.congress.gov/bill/108th-congress/senate-bill/151</ref>
                    (Accessed 13 October 2023). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Kaun and Stiernstedt 2023">Kaun, A. and Stiernstedt, F.
                    (2023) Prison Media: Incarceration and the Infrastructure of Work and
                    Technology. Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Logic 2020">Logic. (2020) ‘Community Defense: Sarah T. Hamid
                    on Abolishing Carceral Technologies’, Logic, 31 August Available at: <ref
                        target="https://logicmag.io/care/community-defense-sarah-t-hamid-on-abolishing-carceral-technologies/"
                        >https://logicmag.io/care/community-defense-sarah-t-hamid-on-abolishing-carceral-technologies/</ref>
                    (Accessed 2 June 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Radway 1991">Radway, Janice A. (1991) <title rend="italic"
                        >Reading the Romance: Women, Patriarchy, and Popular Literature</title>.
                    Chapel Hill and London: University of North Carolina Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Ratto 2011">Ratto, Michael. (2011) ‘Critical Making:
                    Conceptual and Material Studies in Technology and Social Life’, <title
                        rend="italic">The Information Society</title> 27 (4), pp. 252–260. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Ridgeway 2011">Ridgeway, Cecilia. (2011) <title rend="italic"
                        >Framed by Gender: How Gender Inequality Persists in the Modern
                        World</title>. New York: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Rodale 2015">Rodale, Maya. (2015) <title rend="italic"
                        >Dangerous Books for Girls: The Bad Reputation of Romance. Novels
                        Explained.</title> New York: Maya Rodale. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Rodale 2013">Rodale, Maya. (2013) ‘Banned Romance: What’s So
                    Bad About Happily Ever After?’ NPR 22 September. Available at <ref
                        target="https://www.npr.org/2013/09/22/223174127/banned-romance-whats-so-bad-about-happily-ever-after"
                        >https://www.npr.org/2013/09/22/223174127/banned-romance-whats-so-bad-about-happily-ever-after</ref>
                    (Accessed: 29 August 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Rogerson and Semple 1990">Rogerson, Gillian and Semple,
                    Linda. (1990) ‘Who Watches the Watchwomen? : Feminists against Censorship’,
                        <title rend="italic">Feminist Review</title> Autumn, pp. 19-24.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Roiphe 2012">Roiphe, Katie. (2012) ‘Working Women’s
                    Fantasies’, <title rend="italic">Newsweek, </title>16 April.Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.newsweek.com/working-womens-fantasies-63915"
                        >https://www.newsweek.com/working-womens-fantasies-63915</ref> (Accessed 12
                    June 2024).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Rubin 1984"> Rubin, Gayle. (1984) ‘Thinking Sex: Notes for a
                    Radical Theory of the Politics of Sexuality’ in Vance, Carole S. (ed.) <title
                        rend="italic">Pleasure and Danger: Exploring Female Sexuality</title>.
                    Boston and London: Routledge and Kegan Paul.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Ryden 2005">Ryden, Wendy. (2005) ‘Conflicted Literacy:
                    Frederick Douglass’s Critical Model’, <title rend="italic">Journal of Basic
                        Writing</title> 24 (1), pp. 4-23.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Said 1994">Said, Edward W. (1994) <title rend="italic"
                        >Orientalism</title>. Vintage Books: New York. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="">Sargent and Walden 2023 Sargent, Greg and Walden, Paul.
                    (2023) ‘Florida’s Book Ban-Frenzy Targets Nora Roberts, and She’s Not Happy’,
                        <title rend="italic">The Washington Post</title>, 28 April. Available at:
                        <ref
                        target="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2023/04/28/ron-desantis-book-ban-nora-roberts-florida/"
                        >https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2023/04/28/ron-desantis-book-ban-nora-roberts-florida/</ref>
                    (Accessed: 29 August 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Sauer 2009">Theresa Sauer. (2009) <title rend="italic"
                        >Notations 21</title>. New York: Mark Batty Publisher.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Semonche 2007">Semonche, John E. (2007) <title rend="italic"
                        >Censoring Sex: A Historical Journey Through American Media</title>. Lanham:
                    Rowman &amp; Littlefield. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Sergi 2015">Sergi, Joe. (2015) <title rend="italic">The Law
                        for Comic Book Creators.</title> Jefferson, NC: McFarland &amp; Company
                    Inc., Publishers. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Silvio, 1999">Silvio, Carl. (1999) ‘Refiguring the Radical
                    Cyborg in Mamoru Oshii’s Ghost in the Shell’, Science Fiction Studies 26, pp.
                    54-72.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Simon &amp; Schuster">Simon &amp; Schuster. <title
                        rend="italic">Zane</title>. Available at:
                    https://www.simonandschuster.com/authors/Zane/269527 (Accessed 8 June 2025). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Stalings 2015">Stallings L.H. (2015). <title rend="italic"
                        >Funk the Erotic: Transaesthetics and the Black Sexual Cultures</title>.
                    Urbana, IL: University of Illinois Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Steele 2020">Steele Jennifer. (2020) ‘A History of Censorship
                    in the United States’, <title rend="italic">Journal of Intellectual Privacy
                    </title>5(1) Available at: <ref
                        target="https://journals.ala.org/index.php/jifp/article/view/7208"
                        >https://journals.ala.org/index.php/jifp/article/view/7208</ref> (Accessed:
                    1 April 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Stone 2017">Stone, Geoffrey R. (2017) <title rend="italic"
                        >Sex and the Constitution: Sex, Religion, and Law from America’s Origins to
                        the Twenty-First Century.</title> New York: Liveright Publishing
                    Corporation.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Stone 2010 ">Stone, Geoffrey R. (2010) ‘American Booksellers
                    Association v. Hudnut: The Government Must Leave to the People the Evaluation of
                    Ideas’, <title rend="italic">University of Chicago Law Review</title> 77, pp.
                    1219-1238.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Strossen 1993">Strossen, Nadine (1993). ‘A Feminist Critique
                    of the" Feminist Critique of Pornography"’,<title rend="italic"> Virginia Law
                        Review </title>79 (5), pp. 1099-1190. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Suter 2012">Suter, Rebecca. (2012) ‘Orientalism,
                    Self-Orientalism, Occidentialism in the Visual-Verbal Medium of Japanese Girls’
                    Comics’, <title rend="italic">Literature &amp; Aesthetics</title> 22 (2), pp.
                    230-247. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Talbot 2023">Talbot, Dean. (2023). <title rend="italic"
                        >Author Demographics Statistics</title>, 8 February. Available at <ref
                        target="https://wordsrated.com/author-demographics-statistics/#:~:text=83%25%20of%20Romance%20genre%20books%20were%20written%20by%20women"
                        >https://wordsrated.com/author-demographics-statistics/#:~:text=83%25%20of%20Romance%20genre%20books%20were%20written%20by%20women</ref>
                    (Accessed: 10 September 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Tewksbury and DeMichele 2005">Matthew Tewksbury, Richard and
                    DeMichele, Matthew. (2005) ‘Porn in Prison: How Does It Get In? Who Receives
                    It?’, <title rend="italic">Journal of Offender Rehabilitation </title>42 (2),
                    pp. 35-48.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Thompson 2012">Thompson, Nato. (2012) <title rend="italic"
                        >Living as Form: Socially Engaged Art from 1991-2011</title>. Cambridge, MA:
                    MIT Press. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Thornburgh v. Abbott 1989"><title rend="italic">Thornburgh v.
                        Abbott.</title> (1989) 490 U.S. 401 </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Thurgood Marshall Civil Rights Center 2021">Thurgood Marshall
                    Civil Rights Center (2021) ‘Banning the Caged Bird: Prison Censorship across
                    America’, Howard University School Law Available at:
                    https://thurgoodmarshallcenter.howard.edu/sites/tmcrc.howard.edu/files/2021-10/HU8108%20%28Prison%20Censorship%20Report%20Update%29v1-revised.pdf
                    (1 April 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Johnson-Woods 2010">Johnson-Woods, T. (2010) ‘Introduction’
                    in Johnson-Woods, Toni (ed.) <title rend="italic">Manga: An Anthology of Global
                        and Cultural Perspectives</title>. New York: Continuum, pp. 1-14.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="">Torn Apart/ Separados Torn Apart/ Separados. Available at
                        <ref target="https://xpmethod.columbia.edu/torn-apart/volume/2/"
                        >https://xpmethod.columbia.edu/torn-apart/volume/2/</ref> (Accessed 19
                    September 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="">Traub 2021 Traub, Alex. (2021) ‘Kentaro Miura, Creator of
                    Epic Manga 'Berserk,' Dies at 54’, <title rend="italic">International New York
                        Times</title>, 27 May. Available at:
                    https://www.nytimes.com/2021/05/25/arts/kentaro-miura-dead.html (Accessed 8 June
                    2025).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Virginia Department of Corrections 2024">Virginia Department
                    of Corrections. (2024) ‘Operating Procedure 803.2’, pp. 1-14. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="">Virginia Department of Corrections 2023 Virginia Department
                    of Corrections. (2023) ‘Approved /Disapproved Publication List’, December
                    2013-December 2023.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="Washington Department of Corrections 2019">Washington
                    Department of Corrections. (2019) ‘Banned Book List’.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="" label="">The Washington State Prison History Project <title
                        rend="italic">The Washington State Prison History Project.</title>Available
                    at <ref target="https://waprisonhistory.org">https://waprisonhistory.org</ref>
                    (Accessed 19 September 2023).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wells_2008" label="Wells 2008">Wells, S. (2008) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Our bodies, ourselves: Reading the written body</title>, <title
                        rend="italic"> Signs: Journal of Women and Culture </title>33 (3), pp.
                    697—723. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1086/523710"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1086/523710</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wilkinson_2009" label="Wilkinson and Friendly 2009">Wilkinson, L. and
                    Friendly, M. (2009) <title rend="quotes">The history of the cluster heat
                        map</title>, <title rend="italic">The American Statistician</title>63(2),
                    pp. 179-184. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1198/tas.2009.0033"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1198/tas.2009.0033</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wyngaard_2015" label="Wyngaard 2015 ">Wyngaard, A.S. (2015) <title
                        rend="quotes">The end of Ppornography: The story of <q>Story of
                        O</q></title>. <title rend="italic">MLN</title>, 130 (4), pp. 980—997. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1353/mln.2015.0060"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1353/mln.2015.0060</ref></bibl>

            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
